<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-04-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="166" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State.</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-04-05"><hi rend="italic">April 5,
                                1906</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 426.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the legation’s dispatches
                            Nos. 363, of January 2, and 373, of January 19, on the subject of the
                            organization and the opening of the residency-general and residencies in
                            Korea, I have the honor to transmit herewith a translation of the bill
                            relating to the judicature in Korea, which was passed by the Japanese
                            Diet at its last session.</p>
                        <p>This law prescribes in a general way the procedure in the courts of the
                            residency-general and residencies, and provides for cooperation between
                            them and the courts of Japan and Formosa in such matters, for instance,
                            as the issuance of letters regatory.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington
                            Wilson.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">bill for the judicature in korea</hi>.</head>
                            <p rend="center">[Introduced into the House of Peers by the
                                Government.]</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>I.</label>
                                <item>The residency shall conduct the preliminary examinations of
                                    lawsuits and perform duties connected with noncontentious
                                    procedure within its jurisdiction.</item>
                                <label>II.</label>
                                <item>The resident-general may transfer the judicial business of one
                                    residency to another.</item>
                                <label>III.</label>
                                <item>In the residency the resident of the vice-resident alone shall
                                    examine and pronounce judgment.</item>
                                <label>IV.</label>
                                <item>The court of the residency-general shall examine appeals
                                    concerning decisions of the residents and give final
                                    judgment.</item>
                                <label>V.</label>
                                <item>The court of the residency-general shall be composed of three
                                    judges, of whom the highest in rank shall be presiding
                                    judge.</item>
                                <label>VI.</label>
                                <item>Only those who have been judges, prosecuting attorneys,
                                    professors of law in the Imperial University, residents,
                                    vice-residents, or attorneys at law for at least five years may
                                    be judges or prosecuting attorneys of the court of the
                                    residency-general.</item>
                                <label>VII.</label>
                                <item>The resident shall cause the officials of the residency to act
                                    as prosecuting attorneys of the residency.</item>
                                <pb facs="1194" n="1036" xml:id="pg_1036"/>
                                <label>VIII.</label>
                                <item>The prosecuting business of the court of the residency-general
                                    shall be dealt with by the prosecuting attorney.</item>
                                <label>IX.</label>
                                <item>The provisions for legal cooperation in the judiciary law for
                                    courts (in Japan) and the Formosan court shall be applied
                                    respectively to the legal cooperation between the residencies
                                    and the residency general court on the one hand and the court
                                    (in Japan) on the other, and between the residences and the
                                    residency-general court on the one hand and the Formosan court
                                    on the other. The provisions for legal cooperation by request of
                                    foreign law courts shall be applied to legal assistance to be
                                    rendered in the residencies and the residency-general.</item>
                                <label>X.</label>
                                <item>Concerning the laws to be applied to Korea with respect to
                                    judicial matters not provided for in this law, imperial
                                    ordinances may be issued.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>