<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Chargé Wilson to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d186</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">186</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1906-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1906-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="186"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d186">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State.</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-02-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 1, 1906</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 384.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the legation’s dispatch No. 372, of
                    the 18th ultimo, I have the honor to forward herewith a copy of the minister for
                    foreign affairs’ note of the 23d, informing me of an ordinance issued the 21st
                    by the governor-general of the Kwantung, under the terms of which foreigners may
                    proceed to Port Arthur and Dalny to examine their properties temporarily
                    abandoned there. A translation of the regulations as they appeared in full in
                    the Official Gazette of January 23 is likewise inclosed. Besides prescribing the
                    obligations of foreigners after their arrival within the jurisdiction of the
                    Kwantung government office, the regulations provide that each application on the
                    part of a foreigner for a permit to visit Port Arthur or Dalny shall be made
                    through the diplomatic representative of his Government at Tokyo, and shall be
                    accompanied by a detailed list of the properties he wishes to investigate.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to inclose also a copy of my note of January 24, renewing the
                    request for permits for Messrs. Friede, Nielsen, and Toritch to visit the
                    Kwantung, and adding the name of Mr. Dunn, of the American Trading Company. The
                    required data in regard to the properties to be investigated by these gentlemen
                    had long since been furnished by the legation, with the exception of a list of
                    the property of Mr. Friede, a proportion of whose interest consisted in
                    important business papers, and in whose case a list was not available.</p>
                <p>On the 25th ultimo the legation made further inquiries at the foreign office; and
                    on the following day the minister for foreign affairs wrote to state that, in
                    order to save time, the War Department would issue telegraphic instructions to
                    the Kwantung authorities simultaneously with the issuance of the permits,
                    whereby the applicants would be admitted pending their receipt of the permits by
                    mail. A copy of Mr. Kato’s communication is inclosed. On the same day informal
                    inquiries as to when the permits might be expected were made at the war
                    office.</p>
                <p>Major Yoshida telephoned to me on the 29th to say that the permits had been
                    issued and would reach the legation through the foreign office that day. I
                    thereupon telegraphically informed the applicants, through our consul-general at
                    Shanghai, that they might <pb facs="1238" n="1080" xml:id="pg_1080"/> proceed at
                    once to Port Arthur and Dalny. Late in the afternoon I received from the
                    minister for foreign affairs three permits, with a letter, as inclosed, to the
                    effect that Mr. Friede’s could not be issued because no itemized statement of
                    property had been submitted with his application. It was then evident that there
                    had been a mistake in the above-mentioned message telephoned to the legation,
                    and the matter was thus left in a very awkward position, since Mr. Friede had
                    already been notified that he might set out for Port Arthur.</p>
                <p>It was extremely disappointing that an imperfection in his application to the
                    legation should render fruitless in the case of Mr. Friede, the efforts of many
                    months; so that evening at a dinner at the Chinese legation I took the
                    opportunity to speak to his excellency, Mr. Kato, on the subject, and also to
                    the chief of the political bureau, under whose charge these vexed matters have
                    been. I was sorry to find discouragement in that quarter. The minister for war
                    being present, I then stated Mr. Friede’s case fully to his excellency, and
                    General Terauchi was kind enough to interest himself and to promise to see what
                    could be done.</p>
                <p>On the 31st of January I visited the war office, and was later informed by
                    telephone that the military authorities had overcome the technical difficulty
                    and had issued Mr. Friede’s permit, which reached this legation to-day, with a
                    note from Mr. Kato, as inclosed. The notification given Mr. Friede on the 29th
                    thus becomes effective, and since that date all the Americans now desiring to
                    visit the Kwantung are at liberty to go there.</p>
                <p>Telegrams from the American merchants concerned have continued to show anxiety in
                    regard to their interests, and I have had the honor to report this matter very
                    exhaustively, as it may interest you to know what efforts have been required to
                    obtain permission for them to revisit the ports of the Liaotung Peninsula even
                    at the present very late date, in view of the bearing of the subject upon
                    foreign commercial interests in Manchuria and upon the attitude which the
                    Japanese are disposed to assume toward them.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington Wilson.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs</gloss> to Chargé <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-01-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 23, 1906</hi>.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In compliance with the request of the
                        minister of war, I have the honor to inform you that, while the sailing of
                        foreigners to Port Arthur, Tairen, and other places within the jurisdiction
                        of the governor-general of Kwantung has hitherto been prohibited, in
                        consequence of military necessity of the imperial forces during the war, the
                        governor-general of Kwantung issued an ordinance under date of the 21st
                        instant (vide to-day’s Official Gazette), stating that such foreigners as
                        left behind their private property when they withdrew from those places, or
                        their agents, who will sail there, shall be permitted to examine, dispose
                        of, or take away such property. Therefore, the minister of war will grant
                        permits to sail to those places to owners of such property, or their agents,
                        if application is made through the diplomatic representative resident in
                        this country, under the following conditions: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>No persons other than the owners of the private property left
                                behind in the various places under the jurisdiction of the
                                governor-general of Kwan-rung <pb facs="1239" n="1081"
                                    xml:id="pg_1081"/> at the time of their withdrawal from those
                                places, or their agents, who will sail with the object of examining,
                                disposing of, or taking away such property, shall be permitted to
                                sail.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The applicants shall send in at the time of application a paper
                                stating in full the dates of withdrawal from the various places and
                                the locations, names, quantities, and values of the property left
                                behind.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Only one agent shall be permitted for each owner of said property;
                                in case any such property is owned in common by several persons, one
                                of such persons shall be permitted to sail.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The person who is permitted to sail may take three employees with
                                him.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The person who is permitted to sail shall be required, during
                                their stay in any places under the jurisdiction of the
                                governor-general of Kwantung, to comply with the regulations and
                                orders issued by the military authorities having
                                jurisdiction.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kato Takaaki</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">regulations for controlling travelers going to dalny,
                            port arthur, etc., for the purpose of examining properties left in those
                            places</hi>.</head>
                    <p rend="center">[Issued by the governor-general of Kwantung, January 21,
                        1906.]</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>I.</label>
                        <item>If the owners of private properties left by them at the time of
                            withdrawal in the Province of Kwantung or within the jurisdiction of the
                            governor-general of Kwantung, or the representatives of those property
                            owners, proceed to Dalny or Port Arthur, bearing the permits issued by
                            the war department, they may examine, settle, or carry away their
                            properties in accordance with these regulations.</item>
                        <label>II.</label>
                        <item>The travelers to those places who formerly left their properties at
                            Port Arthur and other places shall respectively report in writing to the
                            branch office of the civil governor at Port Arthur and to the civil
                            governor’s office at Dalny. In the said report the travelers and their
                            companions shall state their nationality, names, ages, occupations, home
                            addresses, present addresses, and the reasons for coming thither. A copy
                            each of their permits issued by the war department shall be attached to
                            the report.</item>
                        <label>III.</label>
                        <item>The travelers shall stay in the city of Dalny or Port Arthur. In case
                            of necessity for going out of the city limit for the purpose of
                            examining their properties, they shall apply for permission to the civil
                            governor’s office or the branch office of the same.</item>
                        <label>IV.</label>
                        <item>Those private properties which are left in those places without any
                            trustees appointed and are in the custody of the military authorities
                            shall be returned to the owners on application by the owners or their
                            representatives for the recovery of their properties only within eight
                            months from the date of the promulgation of these regulations.</item>
                        <label>V.</label>
                        <item>In the application referred to in the previous article shall be stated
                            in Japanese the names, nature, number, quantity, and value, as well as
                            the place and time of leaving properties.</item>
                        <label>VI.</label>
                        <item>Concerning the examination, settlement, and carrying away of
                            properties left in the places mentioned in these regulations, the
                            directions and orders of the military authorities shall be observed and
                            obeyed.</item>
                        <label>VII.</label>
                        <item>The period of sojourn for the purpose of examining, settling, and
                            carrying away the properties referred to in these regulations shall not
                            be longer than a month.</item>
                        <label/>
                        <item>The civil governor may, however, shorten or prolong the period
                            according to expediency.</item>
                        <label>VIII.</label>
                        <item>Besides all these regulations, the travelers shall observe and obey
                            the regulations and orders in force within the jurisdiction of the
                            governor-general of Kwantung.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">(Official Gazette, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1906-01-23">January 23, 1906</date>.)</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="1240" n="1082" xml:id="pg_1082"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Chargé <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Minister for Foreign Affairs</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-01-24">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 24, 1906</hi>.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 208.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Monsieur le Ministre</hi>: In reiterating the request
                        contained in this legation’s note No. 204, of the 13th instant, that permits
                        to visit Port Arthur and Dalny be issued to Mr. C. Neilsen, representing the
                        American firm of Clarkson &amp; Co., and to Messrs. S. Friede and W.
                        Toritch, with the minimum possible delay, I have the honor to add the
                        request that such a permit be similarly issued to Mr. W. E. Dunn,
                        representing the American Trading Company.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency’s note No. 6, of yesterday, the receipt of which I now have
                        the honor to acknowledge, mentions certain data required by the war
                        department as a preliminary to the issuance of such permits. With regard to
                        these particulars I have the honor to refer your excellency to this
                        legation’s notes Nos. 116, of February 21, 1905; 122, of March 3, 1905; 160,
                        161, 162, and 163, of August 3, 1905; and to a memorandum of the
                        last-mentioned date, with which were transmitted lists of properties
                        belonging to Messrs. Clarkson &amp; Co., the American Trading Company, and
                        Mr. Toritch.</p>
                    <p>In the case of Mr. Friede, his property left at Port Arthur consists in large
                        measure of valuable documents and private papers, a detailed list of which
                        is not available.</p>
                    <p>I seize this opportunity, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington Wilson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs</gloss> to Chargé <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-01-26">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 26, 1906</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Concerning the regulations issued on the 21st
                        instant by the governor-general of Kwantung for controlling travelers
                        proceeding to Port Arthur and other places for the purpose of examining,
                        carrying away, etc., their properties, I beg leave to refer you to Article I
                        of the same, which reads, “Those who proceed to Dalny or Port Arthur bearing
                        the permits issued by the war department,” as a special arrangement has been
                        made by this department with the military authorities for the sake of those
                        who are now in distant places outside of Japan. In case any of those
                        travelers should desire to proceed direct to Dalny or Port Arthur, without
                        coming to Japan, on account of his staying in a distant place outside of
                        Japan, the war department shall notify the civil governor of Kwantung by
                        telegram as soon as a permit is issued for the applicant. For the sake of
                        convenience the military authorities at Dalny or Port Arthur are to permit
                        his landing on the strength of the telegraphic notification referred to. As
                        to the copy of the permit required in connection with the application
                        mentioned in Article II of these regulations, it shall be presented to the
                        military authorities by the applicant upon its receipt. The above
                        arrangement has been agreed upon by the war department and the
                        governor-general of Kwantung, and I hereby have the honor to inform you of
                        the result of consultations between the authorities concerned.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kato</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs</gloss> to Chargé <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-01-29">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 29, 1906</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your note
                        No. 208, dated January 24, relating to the application for permitting Mr. C.
                        Nielsen, representative of Clarkson &amp; Co., and three other gentlemen to
                        go to Port Arthur. The minister of war, to whom the matter was referred, has
                        issued three permits for Messrs. C. Nielsen, E. Dunn, and W. Toritch, and I
                        have the honor herewith to forward them to you. I also beg to inform you
                        that Mr. Friede’s application can not be granted unless he sends in an
                        itemized statement for application, concerning <pb facs="1241" n="1083"
                            xml:id="pg_1083"/> which I beg to refer you to my note No. 6, dated
                        January 24, as he states that he intends merely to go to Port Arthur for the
                        purpose of searching some important documents. As to Mr. Friee’s case, I
                        wish to say that I am repeating the statement of the authorities
                        concerned.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kato</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>P. S.—The authorities concerned have sent a telegram to the civil
                            governor’s office at Dalny concerning the permission granted to the
                            three gentlemen whose names are mentioned in the body of this note. It
                            is therefore to be understood that there will be no trouble now for them
                            to proceed to the places they wish to go to.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 6.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs</gloss> to Chargé <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-01-31">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 31, 1906</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In reply to your communication concerning the
                        application for permitting Mr. W. S. Friede, a citizen of your country, to
                        go to Port Arthur and Dalny, I addressed you an informal note dated the 29th
                        instant. I have, however, received a permit for him from the war department,
                        and I have the honor herewith to forward it to you. The minister of war
                        states that in issuing the permit a special arrangement has been made for
                        the present case, as you said that the documents for the application would
                        be presented in accordance with the regulations. As to the documents in
                        question, I wish to request you to present them as soon as possible, for the
                        forms of which I beg to refer you to my note No. 6, dated January 23. The
                        minister of war also states that the arrangement made by the authorities in
                        dealing with the present case is due to a special favor, and it is to be
                        understood that it shall not be regarded as a precedent for cases of similar
                        nature.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kato</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister for Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
