<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ambassador Leishman to the Secretary of State..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1906p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d492</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">492</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1906-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1906-11-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-11-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="492"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d492">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName type="from">Leishman</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-11-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 2, 1906</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 80.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your instruction No. 53<note n="a" xml:id="d492fna">Not printed.</note> of the
                    18th ultimo with reference to the petition of George Kanavuts to be relieved
                    from personal taxation in the Ottoman Empire, and to inform you that I am
                    transmitting a copy of the same to the Sublime Porte. I beg leave to state,
                    however, that the Porte prefers that similar petitions be handed to the Turkish
                    minister <pb facs="1562" n="1404" xml:id="pg_1404"/> at Washington, a copy only
                    being forwarded to the embassy for transmission to the minister of foreign
                    affairs.</p>
                <p>For the department’s further information I must state that such petitions in
                    recent years have almost invariably been pigeonholed at the Porte without
                    further action being taken. The personal tax in question is what is known as the
                    military exemption tax, which is cheerfully paid by all non-Moslem inhabitants
                    of the Empire, as it is in lieu of service in the army. This tax, which amounts
                    to about $1.70 a year, represents the quota owed by those who do not serve in
                    the ranks as their share toward the yearly maintenance of a soldier. The Turkish
                    authorities as a rule do not collect this directly from individuals, but from
                    communities. A Christian village, for instance, is held responsible for a
                    certain amount each year, the same being based on the size of its population.
                    But if anyone should emigrate from such village, the tax would none, the less
                    remain the same, the village elders when necessary collecting the amount due by
                    the emigrant from his nearest of kin. Petitions to escape taxations are
                    therefore made with a view of avoiding this. The Turkish Government, however,
                    hardly ever takes action in such cases, for by so doing they are not only
                    obliged to strike the names released from off the list of taxation, but it would
                    be also admitting the right of an Ottoman subject to change his allegiance
                    without permission from his Government, which has not been the case since the
                    treaty of 1869.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John G. A. Leishman.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
