<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-07-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-07-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="546" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d546">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Russell</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-07-22"><hi rend="italic">July 22,
                                1906</hi>.</date></dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 95.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that on the
                            16th instant General Castro named a new cabinet, as follows: <list>
                                <item>Interior—Dr. Julio Torres-Cardenas.</item>
                                <item>Foreign affairs—Dr. José de J. Paúl.</item>
                                <item>Finance—Dr. Eduardo Celis.</item>
                                <item>War and marine—Gen. Manuel Salvador Araujo.</item>
                                <item>Fomento—Jesus M. Herrera Irigoyen.</item>
                                <item>Public works—Juan Casanova.</item>
                                <item>Public Instruction—Dr. Laureno Villanueva.</item>
                                <item>Governor of the Federal District—Dr. Luis Mata Illas.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The new minister of interior, Doctor Torres-Cardenas, has been
                            secretary-general to the President ever since the latter came to power
                            and is one of his most trusted advisers.</p>
                        <p>The new minister for foreign affairs, Dr. José de J. Paúl, holds over
                            from the last cabinet. The new minister for finance, Doctor <pb facs="1606" n="1448" xml:id="pg_1448"/> Celis, was formerly
                            collector of the port at La Guaira, and is said to be a very capable
                            man.</p>
                        <p>The new minister of war, General Araujo, was one of Castro’s fighters in
                            the last revolution and has lately been commandant of arms of the
                            Federal District.</p>
                        <p>The new minister of fomento, Mr. Herrera Irigoyen, is the owner and
                            editor of El Cojo, a Caracas illustrated monthly magazine.</p>
                        <p>The new minister of public works, Mr. Casanova, is a rich planter, and a
                            member of one of the prominent families of Caracas.</p>
                        <p>The new minister of public instruction, Doctor Villanueva, was rector of
                            the university before he was called to the cabinet.</p>
                        <p>The new governor of the Federal District, Dr. Luis Mata, was minister of
                            public works in the old cabinet.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William W.
                            Russell.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>