<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1906-03-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1906-03-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="7" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d7">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Furniss</persName> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Port au
                                        Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-03-02"><hi rend="italic">March 2,
                                1906</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 26.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In further reference to my No. 11 of
                            February 16, 1906, relative to the Government of Haiti withdrawing the
                            exequatur of our vice-consul at Cape Haitien, I beg leave to inclose for
                            the information of the department the correspondence between this
                            legation and Consul Livingston.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">H. W. Furniss.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Minister <persName type="from">Furniss</persName> to Consul <persName type="to">Livingston</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Port au
                                            Prince, Haiti</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-02-17"><hi rend="italic">February 17, 1906</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose herewith copies of the
                                correspondence between this legation and the Haitian Government
                                relative to Mr. Behrmann, your vice-consul.</p>
                            <p>For the information of this legation I would thank you to make a
                                thorough investigation of the charges made against Mr. Behrmann, and
                                ascertain if it is true that he was warned that his actions were
                                objectionable to the Llaitian Government.</p>
                            <p>In view of the fact that the Haitian Government has withdrawn Mr.
                                Behrmann’s exequatur as vice-consul, you have no alternative but to
                                nominate another in his stead.</p>
                            <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">H. W.
                                Furniss.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Consul <persName type="from">Livingston</persName> to Minister <persName type="to">Furniss</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cape Haitien, Haiti</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-02-27"><hi rend="italic">February 27, 1906</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Replying to your letter of the 17th
                                instant, inclosing copy and translation of a communication from the
                                minister of foreign relations of Haiti, making charges of political
                                activity on the part of Mr. Th. Behrmann, American vice-consul here,
                                against the present Haitian Government and withdrawing his exequatur
                                as vice-counsul, I have the honor to inclose herewith copy of a
                                letter from this consulate to Mr. Behrmann and his reply, making a
                                sweeping general denial of all charges. Although the sympathies of
                                Mr. Behrmann are generally supposed to be in favor of the opposition
                                to the Government, I have not been able to verify any specific overt
                                act of interference on his part.</p>
                            <p>It is proper for me to add that, inasmuch as the consular regulations
                                require that the appointment of his successor be approved by the
                                department and that the reasons for a change be stated, I have asked
                                the Department of State for instructions as to whether the
                                withdrawal of an exequatur on general charges of political activity
                                may be considered as sufficient cause for making the change.</p>
                            <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lemuel W.
                                Livingston.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Consul <persName type="from">Livingston</persName> to Vice-Consul <persName type="to">Behrmann</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cape Haitien, Haiti</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-02-21"><hi rend="italic">February 21, 1906</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It becomes my duty to call your
                                attention to the inclosed copy and translation of a communication
                                from the minister of foreign relations of Haiti to the American
                                minister at Port au Prince and referred to this consulate by <pb facs="1033" n="875" xml:id="pg_875"/> the American minister,
                                making charges of political activity on your part against the
                                present Haitian Government and withdrawing your exequatur.</p>
                            <p>You are requested to make reply to these charges without delay and
                                forward the same to this consulate.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully, yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lemuel W.
                                Livingston.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Vice-Consul <persName type="from">Behrmann</persName> to Consul <persName type="to">Livingston</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Cape Haitien, Haiti</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1906-02-21"><hi rend="italic">February 21, 1906</hi>.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                                reception of your letter of to-day, inclosing copy and translation
                                of a communication from the minister of foreign relations of Haiti
                                to the American minister, making charges of political activity on my
                                part against the present Haitian Government, and withdrawing my
                                exequatur as vice-consul at the residence of Cape Haitien.</p>
                            <p>Having carefully gone over this communication, I emphatically and
                                earnestly deny said charges against me. Since the thirty years that
                                I have lived in Haiti, I have always conformed myself to its laws
                                and have never meddled in political affairs. The actual President,
                                Gen. Nord Alexis, can personally give the best information of it.
                                During the number of years while his excellency was délegué in this
                                department, he never had any cause to complain against me and while
                                in active service, representing the United States of America, from
                                1889 to 1893 in Port de Paix and from 1895 to 1898 in Cape Haitien,
                                there were the most cordial relations between the délegué and
                                myself, in charge of the consulate.</p>
                            <p>I positively deny the possibility of bringing any tangible proof
                                against me to sustain said complaint and declare it a villainous
                                conspiracy of some unknown enemy of mine.</p>
                            <p>I sincerely hope that the Government of the United States of America
                                will demand from the Haitian Government the proofs of the facts
                                advanced against me before admitting the withdrawal of my exequatur
                                as vice-consul.</p>
                            <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Th.
                                Behrmann.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>