<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-09-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                        <head>146. Memorandum From the Executive Secretary of the Department of
                            State (<persName corresp="#p_TPR_1">Tarnoff</persName>) to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d146fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> Material,
                                Country File, Box 27, Hungary: 1–12/77. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-09-22">September 22, 1977</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Returning the Crown of St. Stephen</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Your memorandum of August 4 requested that we ascertain Hungarian wishes
                            concerning return and display of the Crown, without making any
                            commitment to return it.<note n="2" xml:id="d146fn2">See <ref target="#d144fn5">footnote 5, Document 144</ref>. Carter’s
                                decision was transmitted in telegram 194954 to Budapest, August 17.
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, P840070–0724)</note> In response to such a
                            query, the Hungarian Government informed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaiser</persName> last month that: 1) it would be
                            happy to work out the details of the transfer once our decision had been
                            made and we had indicated how we intended to return it; and 2) it would
                            place the Crown on public display in an appropriate edifice in Budapest,
                            without restriction on foreigners or Hungarians who wish to see it (Tab
                                1).<note n="3" xml:id="d146fn3">Tab 1 is telegram 2916 from
                                Budapest, August 26, which reported that Nagy assured <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaiser</persName> that if the United States
                                returned the Crown, the Hungarian Government would “receive it with
                                the dignity and honor appropriate to this unique national and
                                cultural treasure.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                P850050–2281)</note> We believe this latter statement constitutes
                            acceptable assurances about the Crown’s “continuing display” as set
                            forth in Presidential Directive/<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>–21<note n="4" xml:id="d146fn4">See <ref target="#d16">Document 16</ref>.</note> as a precondition for us to indicate
                            to the Hungarians our willingness to return the Crown.</p>
                        <pb facs="0496" n="451" xml:id="pg_451"/>
                        <p>Deputy Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_AG_1">Aczel</persName>
                            reiterated to Dr. Billy Graham that Hungary wants to put the Crown on
                            public display and added that, if the United States decided to return
                            the Crown, the Hungarians would receive it in whatever way would fit the
                            President’s requirements.<note n="5" xml:id="d146fn5">This conversation
                                was reported in telegram 3097 from Budapest, September 9. (National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D770327–0356) Telegram 3099 from Budapest, September
                                10, judged Graham’s visit to have “exceeded his expectations,” and
                                to be a “highly valuable event in bilateral relations.” (National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D770328–1231)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>We believe that we should inform the Hungarian Government before the
                            Belgrade <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> Conference gets under
                            way of our willingness to return the Crown under appropriate
                            circumstances. Telling the Hungarians that we are taking this important
                            step both because of improved bilateral relations and Hungary’s positive
                            attitude toward <gloss target="#t_CSCE_1">CSCE</gloss> implementation
                            should favorably affect Hungary’s attitude at Belgrade and after. The
                            President’s decision can be conveyed in one of the following
                            manners:</p>
                        <list type="simple">
                            <item>—By the President in a bilateral meeting with the Hungarian
                                Foreign Minister at <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss>;</item>
                            <item>—By a Presidential oral message to the Hungarian President,
                                delivered by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaiser</persName>;</item>
                            <item>—By the Secretary to the Hungarian Foreign Minister during their
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss> bilateral.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>A Presidential bilateral with the Hungarians would be so unusual as to
                            provoke undesirable press speculation about the substance of the
                            meeting—and might lead to disclosure of our plans before an acceptable
                            scenario of transfer has been arranged. A Presidential oral message
                            delivered by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaiser</persName>
                            could be used to convey our intention right now. Since there is no
                            pressing reason to inform the Hungarians immediately, we prefer using
                            the Secretary’s bilateral with the Hungarian Foreign Minister
                            (tentatively scheduled for October 1).</p>
                        <p>In New York the Secretary will also note that the Hungarian Government
                            has already stated its intention to us to place the Crown on public
                            display in an appropriate place. He will add that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaiser</persName> has been asked to work out with
                            the Foreign Minister an appropriate scenario of transfer that would
                            permit the Crown’s return by the end of 1977.</p>
                        <p>At that point we would send Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaiser</persName> guidance, along the lines of the Secretary’s July
                            28 memorandum to the President for his scenario talks with the
                            Hungarians. (Tab 2)<note n="6" xml:id="d146fn6">Attached but not
                                printed. See <ref target="#d144fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                144</ref>.</note> Once we have Hungarian agreement to a suitable
                            scenario, we would consult with key Congressional leaders and inform the
                            Vatican.</p>
                        <pb facs="0497" n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/>
                        <p>In working out the scenario of transfer with the Hungarian Government, it
                            will be important to indicate to the Hungarians at an early date whom
                            the President will appoint as head of the US delegation and to suggest
                            exact dates for the ceremony of return that would be convenient to that
                            individual. The Secretary’s memorandum to the President of July 28
                            suggested that the Vice President or Governor <persName corresp="#p_HA_1">Harriman</persName> would be appropriate.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_TPR_1"><hi rend="strong">Peter
                                    Tarnoff</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>