<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-10-17T05:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-10-17T05:35:00-05:00" n="185" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                        <head>185. Telegram From the Embassy in Romania to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d185fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D770380–1259. Confidential. Also sent to
                                Budapest.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Bucharest</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-10-17T10:35:00+00:00">October 17, 1977, 1035Z</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>7631. Subj: <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss>’s Campaign for
                            Multi-Year <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss>. Ref: Bucharest
                                6891.<note n="2" xml:id="d185fn2">In telegram 6891 from Bucharest,
                                September 19, the Embassy reported on a September 14 conversation
                                between <persName corresp="#p_BHGJ_1">Barnes</persName> and Patan.
                                Despite understanding the challenges multi-year <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> for Romania would have to
                                overcome, Patan made clear “<gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss>
                                will persist in discussing here and in D.C. the desirability of
                                multi-year review and continue to explore modalities, direct and
                                indirect, for attaining their objective.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770340–0145)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>1. Summary: During Counselor <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName>’s visit in Romania, he met with three high-level
                                <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> officials who, each in his
                            fashion, issued a clear signal that the Romanians intend to launch a
                            full-blown campaign for the eventual achievement of multi-year Most
                            Favored Nation treatment. President <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> has clearly put this issue at the head of his
                            list of priorities in terms of US–<gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss>
                            economic relations. The point man in this campaign will be Deputy Prime
                            Minister Patan who is scheduled to visit Washington, October 27–November
                            3. The culmination of this phase of the campaign would logically occur
                            with the <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> visit.
                            Meanwhile we need to think out how best to achieve our own interests.
                            End of summary.</p>
                        <p>2. The Government of Romania’s serious intent to attempt to achieve the
                            extension of Most Favored Nation treatment for longer than one year at a
                            time was clearly and repeatedly expressed in conversations held with
                            Counselor <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName> in the course of
                            his visit to Romania, October 10–12. Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName> said that it was politically
                            important to avoid an annual debate in Congress which tends to be
                            treated as an open invitation for a debate focusing on any topic whether
                            or not it has any direct bearing on US–<gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> economic relations. He said that if it appears now to
                            be politically impractical or unwise to attempt to separate out the
                            Romanian case from the 1974 Trade Act, some provision should be found
                            which would permit that the congressional review take place only every
                            three years. Noting that the Foreign Minister was even more familiar
                            with the <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> issue than he was, the
                            Counselor pointed out that emigration performance was bound to be
                            important, especially in coming months, as we assess it on a bi-annual
                            basis. Anything <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> could do to make
                            this performance <pb facs="0598" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/> attractive,
                            especially with regard to emigration to Israel, would be helpful.<note n="3" xml:id="d185fn3">In telegram 7677 from Bucharest, October 18,
                                the Embassy reported on <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName>’s discussions of bilateral issues with Gliga
                                and <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName>, including the
                                proposed <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> visit to
                                Washington, other high-level exchanges, arms control, and scientific
                                and cultural exchanges. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770382–0169)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. RCP CC Secretary for International Affairs <persName corresp="#p_AS_1">Stefan Andrei</persName> noted October 10 that <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> was surely aware both of Rom desire
                            for more ample relations and of President <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>’s desire to get away from the annual review of
                            the <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> clause; the President’s
                            argument that we need a more stable basis for the whole relationship
                            strengthened this desire, <persName corresp="#p_AS_1">Andrei</persName>
                            said. Counselor replied that it is difficult to be optimistic about
                            short-term prospects. Multi-year review would be a serious matter in the
                            Congress, as most recent annual extension had not been, and it would be
                            necessary to lay the groundwork very carefully. Acceleration of the
                            process of good relations between the two countries and a demonstration
                            to our public that progress on human rights is possible here would be
                            the kinds of developments needed. It is important to continue to consult
                            on these matters.<note n="4" xml:id="d185fn4">In telegram 7726 from
                                Bucharest, October 19, the Embassy reported that <persName corresp="#p_AS_1">Andrei</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName> that Communist parties in
                                the West are in the process of establishing an independent line,
                                with the strongest parties having a special role. (National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D770385–0502)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>4. In <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName>’s meeting with Deputy
                            Prime Minister Patan on October 11, Patan stressed the peculiarity of
                            the Romanian fate, pointing out that it was the single country which had
                            concluded an arrangement under the provisions of the Trade Act of 1974
                            for Most Favored Nation treatment. By doing so, Romania had set a sort
                            of example for those states which were and remain highly skeptical that
                            any satisfactory accommodation on this issue can be reached with the
                            United States. Patan stressed that the example set by the <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> should be a more positive model. There
                            are diplomatic representatives in Bucharest, who, having advised against
                            the <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> entering into the agreement
                            with the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> concerning <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss>, are now saying, quote, I told you so,
                            end quote.</p>
                        <p>5. In October 12 meeting, FornMin <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName> was somewhat less elliptical in comments on
                            annual review process.<note n="5" xml:id="d185fn5">
                                <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName> also discussed
                                international issues with <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName> during their meeting. In telegram 7602
                                from Bucharest, October 14, the Embassy reported <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName>’s assertion to <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName> that the joint <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Soviet declaration preoccupied
                                Romania, and that Bucharest was wary of any agreements between the
                                superpowers which might infringe on its sovereignty. (National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D770378–0592) In telegram 7655 from Bucharest, the
                                Embassy reported <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName>’s
                                summary to <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName> of the
                                Romanian position on the Middle East and his conversations with
                                Israeli Foreign Minister Dayan. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770380–1259)</note> As Foreign Minister he wished to give the
                            political viewpoint, he said: It is important from all points of view to
                            avoid the kinds of things that happen during the <pb facs="0599" n="554" xml:id="pg_554"/> annual renewal. If discussion were normal, on the
                            substance of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Romanian economic
                            relations, this would be fine, but what is actually discussed is neither
                            to Romania’s advantage nor to that of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Romania is not afraid to confront serious issues but
                            needs to know what it is doing so far. On Transylvania, quote, we know
                            whom we should discuss it with, end quote, and have all sorts of
                            arguments at our disposal, but the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                            Congress is not the place to talk about rights or non-rights in
                            Transylvania. Both the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and Romania
                            can live without such discussion and, after all, we entered into the
                            trade agreement from other motives.<note n="6" xml:id="d185fn6">In his
                                September 29 meeting with <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> in New York at the <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss>, reported to Bucharest in telegram 238769, October
                                4, <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName> had made a
                                similar pitch. The Romanian Foreign Minister pressed for de-coupling
                                issues such as human rights and emigration from the review of “a
                                trade agreement.” <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>
                                suggested that multi-year review could be discussed, but that too
                                would require legislation. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D770362–1086)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>6. Counselor responded that <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> citizens
                            are free to raise any topic which interests them in such congressional
                            hearings, but that what <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName>
                            had called the Transylvanian problem is not a problem for us; it is a
                            Romanian domestic affair. Like Mexican-Americans and other Americans of
                            foreign descent, Americans of Hungarian descent sometimes like to
                            consider the cultural affairs of their country of origin their own, but
                            we do not consider that this has political significance. During the last
                            renewal period there were not many questions on the topic in the
                            Congress. From time to time members of Congress are given papers and
                            speeches to read, but these should not be overrated; at times we have
                            the impression that only the <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> reads
                            them. Cultural diversity in the sense defined by the Helsinki Final Act
                            is a valid topic of discourse, but this is a very general proposition.
                            Using the example of putting Spanish on the ballot and in the schools of
                            New York City, Counselor noted that Americans are used to discussing
                            these issues and expressed view that Hungarian-American thinking should
                            not be considered at any other level.</p>
                        <p>7. <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName> concluded discussion
                            by noting that Romania has a public opinion, too, and while it may not
                            be as “tough” as ours, <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> officials
                            can still be asked uncomfortable questions—such as what possible link
                            there is between Transylvania and a trade agreement—in Parliament.
                            Transylvania is not a problem for Romania, but it may be a problem in
                            bilateral relations; it would be wrong to ignore issues which seem small
                            today but which may be important tomorrow, “in both directions.”</p>
                        <p>8. Counselor indicated in his conversations that these issues would
                            continue to be studied in Washington, and <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> interlocutors expressed <pb facs="0600" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> appreciation for his willingness to listen and for
                            frank responses, showing that he was thinking seriously about the
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>9. Comment: Romanians clearly saw Counselor’s visit as Bucharest opener
                            for process leading up to <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>’s visit in the spring, and Patan’s upcoming
                            trip will be opener in <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> just as
                            clearly, multi-year <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> review will be
                            the repeat the central issue in preparing successful Presidential visit.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Macovescu</persName>’s frank references
                            to Transylvania also suggest political context in which Romanians see
                            these matters, and Department may wish to consider next steps in <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Hungarian relations in this context as
                            well as broader Soviet-<gloss target="#t_EE_1">EE</gloss> framework.</p>
                        <p>10. As Ambassador discussed with Counselor, we feel it important to keep
                            bearing in mind our own interests—both political and commercial—in
                            achieving a more solid long term relationship with Romania. Patan’s
                            visit should be used to further the process of helping <gloss target="#t_GOR_1">GOR</gloss> to understand the context in which
                            multi-year <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> might become possible.
                            In fact the pre-<persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> visit
                            period needs to be thought of in terms of how we can best make use of
                            the Romanian push for a revised <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss>
                            status.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_BHGJ_1"><hi rend="strong">Barnes</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>