<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-04-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="196" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d196">
                        <head>196. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                            European Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_VGS_1">Vest</persName>), the
                            Assistant Secretary of State for Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_DPM_1">Derian</persName>), and the Director
                            of the Policy Planning Staff (<persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Lake</persName>) to the Deputy Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d196fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Office of the Secretariat Staff, Official
                                Working Papers, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> Director
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LWA_1">Anthony Lake</persName>, 1977–Jan
                                1981, Lot 82D298, Box 3, <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>-Lake
                                Papers—4/1–15/78. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_AN_1">Andrews</persName>, Sillins, <persName corresp="#p_BC_2">Brody</persName>, and Kaplan; cleared by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LWH_1">Luers</persName>, Fuerth, and Wolf.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LWH_1">Luers</persName> initialed the
                                memorandum for <persName corresp="#p_VGS_1">Vest</persName>;
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BC_2">Brody</persName> initialed for
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DPM_1">Derian</persName>. The undated
                                memorandum was sent under a covering memorandum through <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName> on April 5. In his
                                memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName>
                                recommended that <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> raise
                                the Hungarian minority issue with <persName corresp="#p_AS_1">Andrei</persName>, that there was no need to raise the IFI
                                issue, and that the Rauta case not be brought up during the
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> visit.
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Office of
                                the Secretariat Staff, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Matthew
                                    Nimetz</persName>, Counselor of the Department of State, Under
                                Secretary of State for Security Assistance, Science and Technology,
                                January 1977 thru December 1980, Lot 81D85, Box 1, MN
                                Chron—Official, January–June 1978) <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName> forwarded <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>’s decisions to <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> under an April 10 covering
                                memorandum. (Ibid.)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-04-05">April 5, 1978</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> Visit—Human
                                Rights Issues</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">ISSUES FOR DECISION</p>
                        <p>How three humanitarian issues should be taken up during President
                                <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>’s visit. Decisions
                            are needed well before <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>’s arrival on April 11.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">BACKGROUND</p>
                        <p>We agree that the President should raise the subject of human rights with
                                <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>, making reference
                            to obligations in the Helsinki Final Act assumed by all signatory states
                            to respect human rights and discuss such matters with one another. The
                            President should urge <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>
                            directly to take favorable and prompt action on present and future
                            emigration and marriage requests including emigration to Israel,
                            particularly if Romania wishes the Administration to seek Romanian
                                <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss> status from Congress on a
                            multi-annual basis. Since human rights problems are already an important
                            item on our bilateral agenda, there is disagreement within the
                            Department over the degree to which and whether the following three
                            additional and sensitive human rights issues should be raised with the
                            Romanians during this visit.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">THE THREE ISSUES</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">A. </hi>Hungarian Minority</p>
                        <p>The Romanian Government is periodically accused of officially sanctioned
                            discrimination against the approximately 1.7 million ethnic <pb facs="0641" n="596" xml:id="pg_596"/> Hungarians in Romania, such as
                            restrictions on schooling in the Hungarian language, employment
                            discrimination, and strong efforts to assimilate Hungarians into the
                            Romanian culture. American-Hungarian organizations are sensitive to this
                            issue. Sixty-six Members of Congress wrote to President <persName corresp="#p_CJ_2">Carter</persName> on March 22 stating their
                            concern and specifically asking that he raise the matter with <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Recent media attention has focused on detailed written criticism of the
                            official Romanian policy towards ethnic Hungarians. The author was
                            Karoly Kiraly, an ethnic Hungarian still in Romania who formerly held a
                            high position in the Romanian Communist Party.</p>
                        <p>For Romania, the Hungarian minority issue raises sensitive territorial
                            questions. Most ethnic Hungarians live in Transylvania which was not
                            incorporated into modern Romania until after World War I. Romanian
                            authorities fear that the real motivation behind the recent public
                            debate in Hungary over this issue is an irredentist attempt. They are
                            also concerned that the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> may be
                            stirring it up to pressure Romania because of its independent foreign
                            policy. It has assumed increasing importance in Romanian-Hungarian
                            relations since <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> and
                            Kadar referred to it publicly for the first time in June 1977. It
                            continues to be discussed at high levels between the two governments. In
                            a speech March 16, <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>
                            criticized shortcomings and deficiencies in Romanian policy toward the
                            Hungarian and German minorities and put forward specific remedial
                            actions.</p>
                        <p>Department officials (<persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName> et
                            al) have raised the issue with visiting Romanian officials, most
                            recently with Deputy Foreign Minister Gliga on March 17.<note n="2" xml:id="d196fn2">In telegram 74362 to Bucharest, March 22, the
                                Department informed the Embassy of the <persName corresp="#p_NM_1">Nimetz</persName>-Gliga conversation on the treatment of the
                                Hungarian minority in Romania. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D780127–0309)</note> We put the issue in the context of our global
                            support for minority rights, reiterated our firm support for Romanian
                            territorial integrity, and made clear that we are not proposing specific
                            solutions but felt we had to raise the matter because of Administration,
                            public and Congressional interest in humanitarian matters set down in
                            the Helsinki Final Act.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> may well preempt the
                            issue by raising it with the President and explaining the situation as
                            he sees it. If so, it would be an opportunity for the President to
                            express his satisfaction that the issue has come up and to explain the
                            concern which exists in the United States in this regard.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">OPTIONS</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">1.</hi> The President Raises Issue with <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>Should <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> not raise the
                            issue, the President on his own would raise it to make clear at the
                            highest level the seriousness with which the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> views this aspect of human rights.</p>
                        <pb facs="0642" n="597" xml:id="pg_597"/>
                        <p>In doing so he could note that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                            seeks a continuing official dialogue on such questions rather than any
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> involvement in Romania’s
                            internal affairs. He could emphasize that if <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> public debate on this issue is erroneous or
                            ill-informed, such debate is still a legitimate consequence of the
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> democratic process. The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Government, however, would be better
                            informed as to allegations of discrimination if there were a better
                            bilateral discussion of the matter. (HA supports.)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">2.</hi> The Secretary Raises Issue with the Foreign
                            Minister</p>
                        <p>If the President has not raised the issue during his general discussion
                            of human rights and emigration issues with <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>, he could note his concern about certain
                            delicate human rights problems and indicate his wish that those be
                            discussed at the Foreign Minister level.</p>
                        <p>If the issue is left for the Secretary, we would try to have the
                            Romanians raise it. In response to their presentation, the Secretary
                            would explain the interest which exists in the Administration, Congress
                            and the public domain for a fair and just solution to existing
                            problems.</p>
                        <p>If the Romanians do not raise it, the Secretary could ask the Foreign
                            Minister to comment on the Hungarian minority issue as one of the human
                            rights issues embodied in the Helsinki Final Act. In either case, he
                            could stress that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> strongly
                            supports Romanian territorial integrity, opposes irredentism, and has no
                            wish to see this issue troubling the relations among the United States,
                            Romania and Hungary.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary’s approach would serve to bring strong <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> interest in this matter to <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>’s attention. It would not
                            fully address the concerns of the Congressmen that the President raise
                            the matter. (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> support, as does HA if the President
                            does not raise it.)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">3.</hi> Issue is not Raised by the President or
                            Secretary</p>
                        <p>Choosing this option signifies recognition that the Romanians and
                            Hungarians have this issue on their agenda at a high level; that
                                <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> recently made
                            recommendations to correct Romanian policy toward minority problems; and
                            that the United States has little or nothing to gain from involving
                            itself directly in an issue between two Communist governments.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendations:</p>
                        <p>1. That the President raise the issue with <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>. (HA supports.)</p>
                        <p>2. That the Secretary raise the issue with the Foreign Minister. (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> support, as does HA if the President does not raise
                                it.)<note n="3" xml:id="d196fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> approved Option
                                2 on April 8, and wrote in the margin: “Suggest that President state
                                that he has asked <gloss target="#t_Secy_1">Secy</gloss> of State to
                                raise certain human rights matters. <gloss target="#t_WC_1">WC</gloss>.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. That the issue not be raised by the President or Secretary.</p>
                        <pb facs="0643" n="598" xml:id="pg_598"/>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">B.</hi> Loans to Romania from International Financial
                            Institutions</p>
                        <p>Recently, and in accordance with current legislative requirements, we
                            have advised Romanian officials of our obligation to take human rights
                            considerations into account in determining our position on loan
                            applications to international financial institutions (IFIs) like the
                            World Bank. However, we have not advised the Romanians that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> is contemplating specific negative
                            action against them in the IFIs. It is widely understood that <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> maintains a tightly
                            controlled internal political system. There is lack of consensus in the
                            Department on the degree to which there is a pattern of violations of
                            human rights in Romania serious enough to warrant such action.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> encouraged Romania to join the
                            World Bank and the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>, in keeping with
                            our interest in lessening Romania’s economic and political dependence on
                            the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and Communist economic
                            organizations. This stems from Administration policy (in accordance with
                            PD–21) to make legitimate efforts to accord Romania favored treatment
                            in, among other things, economic matters. We are required by the Harkin
                            Amendment (1977)<note n="4" xml:id="d196fn4">The Harkin Amendment to the
                                Fair Trade Act prohibited the United States from offering economic
                                assistance to countries that grossly violated human rights.</note>
                            and PD–30<note n="5" xml:id="d196fn5">PD–30, signed by Carter on
                                February 17, 1978, established that promoting the observance of
                                human rights would be a major objective of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> foreign policy.</note> to consider Romania’s human
                            rights policies in the IFI context.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">OPTIONS</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">1.</hi> The President Raises Issue with <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>This would signal the most serious intent to reflect upon the human
                            rights situation in Romania and our need to consider this in decisions
                            for positive votes, abstaining or voting against Romanian loan
                            applications in the IFIs. The President could raise this issue in a calm
                            fashion without suggesting that the United States is on the verge of
                            abstaining or of a negative vote in the IFI and could make clear he has
                            an open rather than closed mind on the subject. (HA supports.)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">2.</hi> Secretary Raises Issue with the Foreign
                            Minister</p>
                        <p>This could be taken up as one of the “delicate problems” mentioned by the
                            President (see above). The Secretary could explain the requirements of
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> law and stress our wish to
                            continue supporting Romanian IFI loan applications. (<gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> supports, as does HA if the President
                            does not raise it.)</p>
                        <pb facs="0644" n="599" xml:id="pg_599"/>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">3.</hi> Issue is not Raised by President or
                            Secretary</p>
                        <p>This course would avoid difficulties in our relations and maintain
                            consistency with PL–21. The Romanians have already been informed at a
                            high level of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> legislative
                            requirements. The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> has other levers
                            (for example, the MFN/emigration hearings) with which to exert pressure
                            on human rights issues. (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>
                            supports.)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendations:</p>
                        <p>1. That the President briefly raise the issue with <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>. (HA supports.)</p>
                        <p>2. That the Secretary raise the issue with the Foreign Minister. (<gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> and HA support.)<note n="6" xml:id="d196fn6">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> approved Option
                                2 on April 8.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. That the issue not be raised during the visit. (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss> supports.)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">C.</hi> The Rauta Case</p>
                        <p>Constantin Rauta was a Romanian official with intelligence
                            responsibilities who defected just before <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>’s official visit to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> in December 1973. Rauta is now an
                            engineer at the Goddard Space Flight Center. He was traveling as a
                            diplomatic courier and asked <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                            officials to help him trade his classified pouch for Romanian permission
                            for his wife and young son to join him in the United States. We
                            convinced him of the impracticality of such an exchange given the
                            imminent arrival of the Romanian President and the pouch was returned
                            unopened to the Romanians.</p>
                        <p>The principal Romanian objection to allowing Mrs. Rauta and the child to
                            emigrate is that the family’s reunification would be seen as a reward to
                            a traitor and would encourage similar defections. <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> is reportedly familiar with
                            all the above aspects of the case, apparently regards Rauta’s defection
                            as a personal affront and is the only person who can decide the fate of
                            Rauta’s wife and child.</p>
                        <p>Our representation on humanitarian grounds have been stubbornly rebuffed
                            by Romanian officials who insist that because Rauta is a traitor, this
                            is not a human rights matter. They may maintain that our raising it in
                            this context only confuses matters. We do not accept that view but are
                            prepared to resolve this issue on any practical basis. Prospects are not
                            bright in the near future but we intend to persist.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">OPTIONS</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">1.</hi> The President Raises the Issue with <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>
                        </p>
                        <p>This would signal the strongest interest in resolving this longstanding
                            case and our understanding that only <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> holds the key to <pb facs="0645" n="600" xml:id="pg_600"/> unlocking this case. Raising the issue with
                                <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> could make him
                            uncomfortable and may not immediately secure the release of Rauta’s
                            family.</p>
                        <p>This would give the Romanian President an understanding of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> view that, three years after the
                            granting of <gloss target="#t_MFN_1">MFN</gloss>, there should be
                            progress in even the most difficult of the divided family cases with
                            Romania. A number of longstanding cases will have been resolved in the
                            weeks before <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>’s arrival
                            here, clearly as a result of a Romanian attempt to put its best face
                            forward. Indications are that there is little high-level Romanian
                            receptivity to bargaining for the Rauta family’s release. A high-level
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> reaffirmation to <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> that the Rauta matter is a
                            humanitarian issue which can be resolved will maintain the momentum we
                            have generated in pressing the case with Romanian authorities. There has
                            been no confirmation to us that the Romanian President is even aware of
                            our heightened concern for the Rauta wife and child. (HA supports.)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">2.</hi> Secretary Raises the Issue with the Foreign
                            Minister</p>
                        <p>This course would also make clear very strong <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> interest in resolving this case, without producing a
                            confrontation during the <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName> visit. It could be taken up as one of the
                            “delicate problems” referred to by the President. (<gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> support this option, as does HA, if the
                            issue is not raised by the President.)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                            <hi rend="roman">3.</hi> Issue is not Raised by the President or
                            Secretary</p>
                        <p>We have already raised this issue at high levels this year. Our
                            Ambassador raised it with Deputy Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_PC_1">Pacoste</persName> in January and delivered a
                            note. We raised it with Presidential Counselor Pungan in Washington.
                            Just recently, on March 30, our Ambassador made a strong pitch to Pungan
                            to find some solution and Congressman Vanik made an equally strong pitch
                            to the Foreign Minister on April 1 at our prodding. (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss> supports.)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendations:</p>
                        <p>1. That the President confirm <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                            interest in the Rauta affair as humanitarian and seek <persName corresp="#p_CN_1">Ceausescu</persName>’s agreement to allow the wife
                            and child to join Mr. Rauta here. (HA supports.)</p>
                        <p>2. That the Secretary raise the issue with <persName corresp="#p_AS_1">Andrei</persName>. (<gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss> supports,
                            as does HA, if the President does not raise.)<note n="7" xml:id="d196fn7">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName> approved Option
                                2 on April 8.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. That the issue not be raised. (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>
                            supports.)</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>