<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-05-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="263" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d263">
                        <head>263. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_HR_2">Robert
                                Hunter</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RJ_1">Jim
                                Rentschler</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d263fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> Material,
                                Country File, Box 86, Yugoslavia: 1–12/79. Confidential. Sent for
                                action. Sent through <persName corresp="#p_AM_1">Madeleine
                                    Albright</persName>. Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MJT_1">Mathews</persName>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-05-08">May 8, 1979</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Aid to Yugoslavia (U)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>As you know, Senator Kennedy has introduced legislation<note n="2" xml:id="d263fn2">Senator Edward Kennedy (D–Massachusetts) drafted an
                                amendment to the <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 80–81
                                Development Assistance Authorization Bill, but did not introduce it
                                on the Senate floor. See <ref target="#d264fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                    264</ref>. The text of the amendment, reported by the Department
                                in telegram 109909 to Belgrade, May 1, called for a $20 million
                                appropriation to be used by the President for relief and
                                reconstruction assistance to Yugoslavia. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D790198–0941)</note> calling for $20 million in aid to Yugoslavia
                            after its devastating earthquake<note n="3" xml:id="d263fn3">On April
                                15, 1979, at 7:30 a.m. local time, an earthquake measuring 7.0 on
                                the Richter Scale struck 15 km from the Montenegro coast causing
                                extensive damage.</note>
                            <pb facs="0913" n="868" xml:id="pg_868"/> (damage in Montenegro, for
                            example, was equal to a year’s gross product). In the absence of
                            Administration support—or even comment—the <gloss target="#t_SFRC_1">SFRC</gloss> did not approve it, though Kennedy’s office believes
                            the <gloss target="#t_SFRC_1">SFRC</gloss> would respond to the
                            Administration, and Kennedy will go to the floor in any event, where he
                            believes he will get support. It would not be surprising if our
                            non-response were made an issue on the Senate floor—a position we should
                            seek to avoid on a humanitarian matter. (C)</p>
                        <p>At State, <persName corresp="#p_VGS_1">Vest</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NDD_1">Newsom</persName> believe we should support this
                            expenditure; <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> does not,
                            simply on budgetary grounds: i.e. the President’s desire not to raise
                            the budget. There is also a question about a supplemental which
                                <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry Owen</persName> flags: at what
                            point does the Congress start whittling away at other things in the aid
                            field? (C)</p>
                        <p>Our belief—which <persName corresp="#p_VGS_1">Vest</persName> shares—is
                            1) that the Congress will judge whether or not to set this aid off
                            against other aid appropriations independently of the position the
                            Administration takes on this item; and 2) the Yugoslavs will never
                            understand why we refused to support it. Even a “no comment” will not be
                            understood. Belovski has been calling around town in support. (C)</p>
                        <p>In view of the genuine humanitarian purposes—plus the importance of the
                            Yugoslav relationship—we believe that State’s decision should be
                            reconsidered. As a result, we recommend that you talk with <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Cy Vance</persName>, and urge him to give a
                            positive response. (C)</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">RECOMMENDATION:<note n="4" xml:id="d263fn4">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> neither approved
                                nor disapproved the recommendation.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>That you call <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Cy Vance</persName> along the
                            above lines. (U)</p>
                        <p>Yes No </p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>