<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-01-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-01-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="377" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d377">
                        <head>377. Letter From the Counselor of the Embassy in Iran (<persName corresp="#p_SE2" type="from">Stevens</persName>) to the Officer in
                            Charge of Iranian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HNB1" type="to">Hannah</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d377fn1">Source: Department of State, GTI Files: Lot 60 D 533, Iran,
                                Official Informal Letters from Tehran, 1957. Secret;
                                Official–Informal.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-01-14"><hi rend="italic">January 14,
                                1957</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Norm</hi>: Enclosed is a summary of a
                            conversation which [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text
                                not declassified</hi>] had with HIM on January 5.</p>
                        <p>I understand that in the past summaries of this kind have not been
                            provided either to the Embassy or to the Department. We have now agreed
                            that in the future the Embassy will receive such summaries and [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                            pass copies of the original report to the Department. If this system
                            does not operate satisfactorily please let me know and we will provide
                            you copies from here.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Francis</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0909" n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">[Enclosure]</note>
                            <note n="2" xml:id="d377fn2">Secret.</note>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>In a 2 hour session with the Shah on January 5 the following
                                    political-economic information was obtained: <list>
                                        <label>A.</label>
                                        <item><persName>Ahmad Mehbod</persName>, designated by the
                                            Prime Minister as “Co-negotiator”, with NIOC Chief, for
                                            foreign contracts to develop offshore oil, has “no
                                            authority to sign anything.” U.S. oil firms should deal
                                            with NIOC. However, the only deal acceptable to Iran is
                                            (and “soon will be written into law”): <list>
                                                <label>(1)</label>
                                                <item>NIOC must have 50% stock in any operating
                                                  company.</item>
                                                <label>(2)</label>
                                                <item>Foreign company will be required to advance
                                                  all costs of exploration.</item>
                                                <label>(3)</label>
                                                <item>NIOC will pay for 50% ownership from its half
                                                  of profits after production begins.</item>
                                                <label>(4)</label>
                                                <item>Foreign company must pay Iranian income tax on
                                                  its 50% of profits.</item>
                                            </list></item>
                                        <label>B.</label>
                                        <item>Qum oil “must remain in Iranian hands.” U.S. technical
                                            and financial help is needed to develop the field,
                                            construct a pipeline to Alexandretta, Turkey, and
                                            install port facilities cost estimated by the Shah at
                                            “450–500 million.”</item>
                                        <label>C.</label>
                                        <item>Iran has “no air force,” and “although we have long,
                                            vulnerable coast line to control, we have only two
                                            gunboats.” Vehemently: “We must have a navy. We hope to
                                            obtain it from the U.S. but if it is not available there
                                            we must have it from whatever source available.”</item>
                                        <label>D.</label>
                                        <item>In answer to the recent Iranian invitation to a
                                            proposed Mid-East conference, <persName corresp="#p_NNNGA1">Nasr</persName> declined saying
                                            he could not confer with a nation which occupied “an
                                            Arab island”; <persName corresp="#p_SAA1">Saud</persName> did not “formally” decline but
                                            passed word it would not appear proper for him to meet
                                            with leaders of armed forces which expelled his troops
                                            from El Arabi Island.<note n="3" xml:id="d377fn3">Reference is to the dispute between Saudi Arabia
                                                and Iran over Arabi and Farsi Islands in the Persian
                                                Gulf. The Saudis landed troops on Arabi island in
                                                October 1956 shortly after Iranian occupation of
                                                Farsi in September of the same year. In November,
                                                Iranian forces dislodged the Saudis from Arabi and
                                                took control of the island. (Despatch 613 from
                                                Tehran, January 24; Department of State, Central
                                                Files, 788.022/1–2457)</note></item>
                                        <label>E.</label>
                                        <item>In transiting Iran enroute to Washington, <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName> sent the Shah only
                                            Christmas greeting (“apparently he doesn’t know I am
                                            Moslem”).</item>
                                        <label>F.</label>
                                        <item>During his Moscow visit the Shah never promised the
                                            Soviets that “no foreign military bases will be built in
                                            Iran.” Although he was aware of the West’s “lack of
                                            interest” in such bases, he always responded to Russian
                                            urging with only the following words: “Iran will not be
                                            used as a spring board for launching aggression against
                                            the Soviet Union.”</item>
                                        <pb facs="0910" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/>
                                        <label>G.</label>
                                        <item>The Shah still feels that Iran is “not ready” for the
                                            establishment of formal political parties. He is aware
                                            that several small groups are convening “but they are
                                            unimportant.”</item>
                                        <label>H.</label>
                                        <item>The Shah is irritated by rumors that the U.S. is
                                            sympathetic to, and in touch with, NRM leaders. He is
                                            constantly striving to “broaden political base,” and all
                                            useful, loyal former followers of <persName corresp="#p_MM2">Mossadeq</persName> have been taken
                                            into the government (specifically Iran party members in
                                            the Plan Organization) but he is highly critical of
                                                <persName>Allayer Saleh</persName>, “who wears
                                                <persName corresp="#p_MM2">Mossadeq</persName>
                                            likeness on his label.”</item>
                                        <label>I.</label>
                                        <item>Re “<persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName>
                                                Report”<note n="3" target="d377fn3">Reference is to
                                                recommendations by Dr. <persName>Philip
                                                  Taylor</persName> on ways Iran might increase its
                                                revenues by changing taxes on cultivated land and
                                                real estate from an income to capital value basis.
                                                (Toica <gloss target="#t_A1">A</gloss>–337 from
                                                Tehran, August 17, 1956; Washington National Records
                                                Center, <gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss> Files:
                                                FRC 58 A 403, Box 18, Tehran)</note>—the Shah is
                                            obviously cool; stated that “committee is studying this,
                                            and I think the Minister of Finance favors it slightly.”
                                            However, the Shah continued by saying it was his
                                            understanding that only a few “highly organized nations
                                            such as America, England and Scandinavia collected any
                                            such tax. How do you expect us to? Anyway it will take
                                            four or five years to make the required land surveys.”
                                            From this, the Shah launched into a revealing discourse
                                            on “unfairness” of penalizing the present generation and
                                            allowing the future ones to realize all blessings from
                                            “vast” oil income. He indicated that he is giving
                                            serious thought to widespread borrowing now to finance
                                            development and meet budgetary needs, with future
                                            generations repaying from expected rising oil
                                            revenues.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The Shah repeated his old pledge that he is fully committed to
                                    the West and “can never change.”</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>In the discussion of <persName>Mehbod</persName>, [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not
                                        declassified</hi>] pointed out (at Embassy request) that
                                    U.S. firms are puzzled as to <persName>Mehbod</persName> status;
                                    viewed him as “ignorant of oil business, irresponsible,
                                    opportunist and corrupt to extent he is openly asking for bribes
                                    to be passed on to higher levels.” The Shah said that
                                        <persName>Mehbod</persName> had denied these allegations
                                    and, in the absence of proof, the Shah is reluctant to take any
                                    action, but U.S. firms should be assured that they need pay
                                    nobody anything. He said he felt <persName>Mehbod</persName>
                                    “useful” because of his “energy, industry, imagination and
                                    commercial contacts.”</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>During the conversation, the Shah expressed optimism (probably
                                    reflected from <persName>Mehbod</persName>) that several U.S.
                                    firms would accept proposal outlined in Para 1 A above. He added
                                    that an Italian firm already had accepted, ([<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                                    note: Embassy Economic Counselor subsequently revealed that the
                                    Italians turned the proposal down; Americans highly unlikely to
                                    consider. He added that he felt the Shah was not getting the
                                    true picture through <persName>Mehbod</persName>.)</item>
                                <pb facs="0911" n="871" xml:id="pg_871"/>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>At the conclusion of the meeting, the Shah [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source text not declassified</hi>]
                                    urged: “Please keep me advised on any oil developments. This is
                                    most important to us.” (The Ambassador and the Economic
                                    Counselor, told of this—as well as other subjects
                                    reported—approved [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line of source
                                        text not declassified</hi>] acting as channel to the Shah to
                                    expose false claims he is apparently receiving about progress
                                    toward anticipated “deals” for new oil areas.)</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>