<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-02-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="389" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d389">
                        <head>389. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                            Eastern, South Asian, and African Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWM1" type="from">Rountree</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary
                                of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d389fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, S/S-<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files:
                                Lot 63 D 351, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5703 Series. Top
                                Secret. Drafted by <persName>Hannah</persName> and concurred in by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BRG1">Barnes</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_KTV1">Kalijarvi</persName>, who added as a comment a
                                copy of his memorandum to the Secretary, <ref target="#d388"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>. According to a covering note
                                from <persName corresp="#p_HF1">Fisher Howe</persName> to
                                    <persName>Dulles</persName>, February 6, <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> approved this paper and read
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KTV1">Kalijarvi</persName>’s comment.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> did not, to use
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HF1">Howe</persName>’s words, “feel that
                                any disagreement on policy is involved, but has suggested to Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KTV1">Kalijarvi</persName> that he attend
                                the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> briefing in order to present
                                E’s views.”</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-02-06"><hi rend="italic">February 6,
                                1957</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5703—Draft Policy Toward
                                Iran</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>There will be a Departmental briefing on this paper February 6 at 11:00
                                a.m.<note n="2" xml:id="d389fn2">See <hi rend="italic">infra.</hi></note></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi></p>
                        <p>The attached draft (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5703), which is
                            scheduled for consideration by the Council on February 7, points out
                            that Iran has made significant progress in recent years; under the
                            Shah’s personal leadership the Government has strengthened internal
                            security, begun a development program financed out of rising oil
                            revenues and aligned the country with the West. The paper also notes the
                            effects of the Shah’s personal weaknesses and the failure to make
                            budgetary and administrative reforms or to meet rising popular
                            expectations of a better living standard.</p>
                        <p>Internationally, as the paper explains, Iran is becoming a positive Free
                            World asset, as evidenced by its adherence to the Baghdad Pact and its
                            support of the United States on major Middle East issues. But, in view
                            of its exposed position and relative weakness Iran continues to need
                            U.S. political, military and economic support. This draft paper takes
                            the position that it is in the U.S. interest to support Iran within
                            reasonable limits in order to bolster its confidence in its new
                            international posture. This is particularly important at a time when the
                            U.S. is trying to obtain Middle East support for the President’s January
                            5 proposals.</p>
                        <p>Politically, the President’s proposals have strengthened the Iranian
                            Government’s confidence in itself, in the U.S. and in the future of
                            Middle East defense. The proposals will ease the pressure for a U.S.
                            guarantee of Iranian territorial integrity but will encourage the Shah
                            to hope for more military aid.</p>
                        <pb facs="0931" n="891" xml:id="pg_891"/>
                        <p>Militarily, the paper proposes a somewhat stepped-up aid program designed
                            to give the armed forces some defensive delaying capability within a
                            framework of <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>-approved goals (which
                            the Shah has agreed to) and of Iranian limited military and economic
                            capacities. Besides the usual end-items, the plan includes a large
                            military construction program to relocate Iranian units in better
                            defensive positions.</p>
                        <p>Economically, the paper recommends a declining scale of aid after <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1958. Since the Government of Iran has
                            adequate resources to meet its normal budgetary requirements, provided
                            reforms are made, it is planned to avoid direct budgetary aid unless
                            required by unusual circumstances to protect U.S. interests in the
                            area.</p>
                        <p>While the sources of many of Iran’s weaknesses are internal, the ability
                            of the U.S. to encourage difficult reforms depends on preserving
                            confidence in the U.S. The recommended aid programs are calculated to
                            maintain the U.S. ability to influence Iran while simultaneously tending
                            to reduce the present Iranian over-reliance on the U.S. to compensate
                            for internal weaknesses.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi></p>
                        <p>That you recommend <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> approval of the
                            proposed new policy.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>