<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-10-29T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-10-29T04:00:00-05:00" n="74" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d74">
                        <head>74. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Iraq</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d74fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 780.5/10–2955. Secret; Priority. Repeated to London, Ankara,
                                Tehran, Karachi, and Paris.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Baghdad</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-10-29T12:00:00+03:00"><hi rend="italic">October 29,
                                        1955—noon</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>409. I gave <persName>Nuri</persName> substance of Department circular
                            283, October 27<note n="2" xml:id="d74fn2"><ref target="#d72">Document
                                    72</ref>.</note> at his home this morning. He was genuinely
                            pleased. “You have come a long way” he said with obvious relief and
                            satisfaction. He would pass the good word on to the King immediately and
                            after talks <pb facs="0220" n="180" xml:id="pg_180"/> with Foreign
                            Minister, Under Secretary Foreign Affairs and Chief of Staff he would
                            have some observations to make on nature of liaison and timing of
                            publicity.</p>
                        <p><persName>Nuri</persName> told me agreement has now been reached among
                            all signatories to hold first meeting of Council on November 20 in
                            Baghdad. British, Turks and Pakistanis have given their assent to
                            establishing permanent seat of Council in Baghdad. Iranians have not yet
                            replied on this point but he anticipates their concurrence too.</p>
                        <p><persName>Nuri</persName>’s present thinking is to have first meeting
                            establishing Council on government level and then between meetings on
                            that level to carry on the work through the Ambassadors of member
                            countries accredited in Baghdad.</p>
                        <p><persName>Nuri</persName> is meeting later today with Chief of Staff to
                            discuss various items that he would like to see put on agenda for first
                            meeting. In 2 or 3 days he said he would be able to give me his full
                            views on agenda.</p>
                        <p>We are formulating our views on nature of liaison that we think should be
                            established and will telegraph them within next few days.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_GWJ1"><hi rend="strong">Gallman</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>