<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Hay to Mr. Porter..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1902</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">367</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1902-03-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1902-03-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1902-03-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1902-03-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="367"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d367">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hay</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Porter</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-03-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 27, 1902</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1000.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose herewith an autograph letter from the
                    President to President Loubet, with an office copy thereof, tendering an
                    invitation to the Government and people of France to unite with the Government
                    and people of the United States in a tit and appropriate dedication of the
                    monument of Marshal de Rochambeau to be unveiled in the city of Washington on
                    May 24, 1902.</p>
                <p>I inclose also, with copies for your tiles, letters addressed to Comte Rene de
                    Rochambeau and Mr. Gaston de Sahune de Lafayette, through whom, as prominent
                    representatives of the Rochambeau and Lafayette families, a like invitation is
                    extended to those families.</p>
                <p>These invitations are extended in pursuance of a joint resolution of Congress of
                    March 21, 1902, copies of which I transmit herewith.</p>
                <p>You will deliver the President’s letter to the President of the French Republic,
                    and will ask for an audience for that purpose. In communicating the invitations
                    to the President of France and to the Rochambeau and Lafayette families, you
                    will appropriately express the grateful feelings which prompted this action, and
                    will express the President’s hope that the invitations will be accepted.</p>
                <p>The visitors who may represent the French Republic on the occasion referred to,
                    as well as the members of the Rochambeau and Lafayette families who may come as
                    private citizens, will be entertained as the guests of the American Government
                    and people.</p>
                <p>If the invitations be accepted, I shall be pleased to have you telegraph the fact
                    and date of acceptance.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">President of the United
                                States</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">President of France</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Great and Good Friend</hi>: I have the honor to inform
                        you that the Congress of the United States has adopted a joint resolution
                        authorizing and requesting me to extend to the Government and people of
                        France a cordial invitation to unite with the Government and people of the
                        United States in a fit and appropriate dedication of the monument of Marshal
                        de Rochambeau, to be unveiled in the city of Washington on the 24th day of
                        May, 1902. It becomes, therefore, my agreeable duty to tender, in the name
                        of the Government and people of the United States, this invitation to the
                        Government and people of France.</p>
                    <p>I trust that Your Excellency will see in this action another proof of the
                        lasting gratitude of the American Government and people for the inestimable
                        services rendered by France during the war of our revolution, and that the
                        occasion will serve to join together still more firmly the ties which since
                        that time have united the two countries.</p>
                    <p>I avail myself of this opportunity to assure Your Excellency of my fervent
                        desire for the prosperity and happiness of yourself and of the Government
                        and people of France.</p>
                    <p>Written at Washington this 27th day of March, 1902.</p>
                    <p>Your good friend,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Theodore Roosevelt.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>By the President:<lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0490" n="410" xml:id="pg_410"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hay to Mr. de
                                Lafayette</persName>, and, with appropriate changes, to Count
                                <persName type="to">de Rochambeau</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-03-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 27, 1902</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Animated by a sense of profound gratitude for
                        the inestimable services rendered to the United States during their war of
                        revolution by your renowned ancestor, the Congress of the United States, by
                        a joint resolutiou of March 21, 1902, authorized and requested the President
                        to extend to the family of the Marquis de Lafayette a cordial invitation to
                        unite with the Government and people of the United States in a fit and
                        appropriate dedication of the monument of Marshal de Rochambeau to be
                        unveiled in the city of Washington on May 24, 1902.</p>
                    <p>It is with more than ordinary pleasure that I fulfill the duty of
                        transmitting this invitation to you and through you to the family of the
                        Marquis de Lafayette.</p>
                    <p>I have instructed the ambassador of the United States at Paris to convey this
                        to you in a fitting manner, and to say that the members of this illustrious
                        family who may do us the honor to visit the United States upon this occasion
                        will be welcomed as guests of the nation.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">(Inclosure 3.—Public Resolution—No.
                        11.)</note>
                    <p rend="flushleft">JOINT RESOLUTION authorizing and requesting the President to
                        extend to the Government and people of France and to the families of Marshal
                        de Rochambeau and Marquis de Lafayette an invitation to join the Government
                        and people of the United States in the dedication of the monument of Marshal
                        de Rochambeau to be unveiled in the city of Washington.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Resolved by the Senate and House of Representatives of the
                            United States of America in Congress assembled</hi>, That the President
                        be, and is hereby, authorized and requested to extend to the Government and
                        people of France and the family of Marshal de Rochambeau, commander in chief
                        of the French forces in America during the war of independence, and to the
                        family of Marquis de Lafayette, a cordial invitation to unite with the
                        Government and people of the United States in a fit and appropriate
                        dedication of the monument of Marshal de Rochambeau to be unveiled in the
                        city of Washington on the twenty-fourth day of May, nineteen hundred and
                        two; and for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this resolution
                        the sum of ten thousand dollars is hereby appropriated, out of any money in
                        the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, the same, or so much thereof as may
                        be necessary, to be expended under the direction of the Secretary of
                        State.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Approved, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1902-03-21">March 21, 1902</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
