<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1902-02-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1902-02-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="429" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d429">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">White</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Bay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy
                                        of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-02-07"><hi rend="italic">February 7,
                                1902</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1844.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that on the
                            28th ultimo the embassy intervened in behalf of one Peter Mikolainis, to
                            the end that he might be permitted to remain in Prussia until March 15
                            next, and that a note has to-day been received from the imperial foreign
                            office in which it is stated that, to its regret, the Royal Prussian
                            Government is not in a position to allow him to do so.</p>
                        <p>Kikolainis was born in Russia, in 1868, and emigrated to the United
                            States in 1896. He was naturalized as a citizen in Luzerne County, Pa.,
                            on October 7, 1901, and he holds a passport issued to him by the
                            Department of State last October. According to his own story, he left
                            the United States in November and went to Tilsit, Prussia, near the
                            Russian frontier, where he at once proceeded to establish himself in the
                            bookselling business, his stock consisting of religious and scientific
                            books printed in the Lithuanian language, imported from the United
                            States. In January he was arrested, his books attached, and his premises
                            searched, and an order served upon him to leave Prussian territory
                            within forty-eight hours.</p>
                        <p>In its note the foreign office states that Mikolainis had lived in Tilsit
                            from 1893 to 1896, and that during that time he was employed in a
                            publishing house, and was engaged in the secret importation of forbidden
                            books into Russia; that upon the nature of his business and his
                            connection with certain agitators becoming known, he left Tilsit for the
                            purpose of evading observation; that upon his return from America he
                            engaged an apartment under an assumed name, resumed his <pb facs="0531" n="451" xml:id="pg_451"/> relations with the agitators in question,
                            and began again to act as he had done before; and, further, that the
                            books found in his possession were by no means of a “harmless”
                            character. Under the circumstances the Prussian Government has every
                            reason to consider him an objectionable foreigner.</p>
                        <p>It is evident that Mikolainis, who remained in the United States merely
                            long enough to become naturalized as a citizen, and who then at once
                            returned to the scene of his former activity, has merely sought to make
                            a convenience of his American nationality.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">And. D. White.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>