<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. White to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1902</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d448</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">448</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1902-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1902-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1902-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1902-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="448"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d448">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">White</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-06-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 30, 1902</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1987.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the embassy’s dispatch No. 1814 of
                    December 31, 1901, I have the honor to append hereto a memorandum report of
                    certain military cases, more particularly mentioned below, which have not been
                    the subject of previous correspondence or which have been settled during the
                    quarter ending to-day. There were no military cases to report for the quarter
                    ending March 30 last.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">And. D. White.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Military case report.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>At the instance of his attorney, Mr. Theo. Steeg, of Buffalo, N. Y., the
                        embassy addressed a note (F. O., No. 1130) to the imperial foreign office on
                        March 21, 1902, <pb facs="0541" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/> in support of the
                        petition to be allowed to visit his former home, which had been sent to the
                        Imperial Statthalter at Strasburg by one Rene (Renatus) Huttler, an American
                        citizen of Alsatian origin. Under date of April 9 the foreign office replied
                        that the desired permission had been granted as a result of the embassy’s
                        intervention.</p>
                    <p>On March 8, 1902, the embassy learned through the United States consulate at
                        Kiel, Baden, that Eugene Herr, an American citizen born in Wurttemberg, had
                        been arrested on crossing the frontier at Deutsch-Avricourt and had been
                        transferred to a prison at Lörchingen, in Lorraine, on account of his
                        evasion of military service, and intervention (F. O., No. 1123) was at once
                        made in his behalf. A few days later, March 11, the embassy was informed
                        that Herr had been released after depositing 400 marks as security for the
                        payment of a military fine, and it at once renewed its intervention (F. O.,
                        No. 1124) in his behalf. So far as the embassy is aware, Herr was not
                        molested again, and under date of April 28 the foreign office intimated to
                        the embassy that the Wurttemberg authorities were ready to return the money
                        in question upon Herr’s submitting an authenticated copy of the certificate
                        of his American naturalization, and stated that the local district attorney
                        had been directed to communicate with the United States consul at Stuttgart
                        in order to bring this about.</p>
                    <p>At his own request the embassy addressed a note (F. O., No. 1153) to the
                        foreign office on April 21, 1902, in support of a petition sent in by Meyer
                        Schwartz, an American citizen of Alsatian origin, for permission to visit
                        his father at Strasburg, and under date of June 9 it was informed by the
                        foreign office that in view of this action the permission had been granted
                        as desired.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J. B. J.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
