<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Choate to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1902</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d518</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">518</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1902-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1902-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1902-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1902-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="518"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d518">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Choate</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-02-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 12, 1902</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 781.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that at an interview
                    yesterday with His Majesty’s secretary of state for foreign affairs he gave me a
                    copy of the new defensive treaty of alliance between Great Britain and Japan. I
                    now inclose the copy that he gave me.</p>
                <p>It seems to me greatly to fortify the policy of the “open door,” and goes far to
                    secure the independence and integrity of the Chinese and Korean empires. Perhaps
                    also it explains the decision of His Majesty’s Government, announced in
                    Parliament the day before, not to proceed further with the fortification of
                    Weihaiwei as a naval base. I inclose a clipping from the London Times of
                    yesterday’s date, containing the debate on this interesting subject, in which,
                    however, I see no allusion to the provision in the lease to Great Britain of
                    Weihaiwei that it was to be for so long a period as the Russian occupation of
                    Port Arthur should last.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph H. Choate</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Marquis of Lansdowne</gloss> to Sir
                                <persName type="to">C. MacDonald</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-01-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 30, 1902</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dispatch to His Majesty’s minister at Tokyo forwarding
                            agreement between Great Britain and Japan of January</hi> 30, 1902.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have signed to-day, with the Japanese
                        minister, an agreement between (Treat Britain and Japan, of which a copy is
                        inclosed in this dispatch.</p>
                    <p>This agreement may be regarded as the outcome of the events which have taken
                        place during the last two years in the Far East, and of the part taken by
                        Great Britain and Japan in dealing with them.</p>
                    <p>Throughout the troubles and complications which arose in China consequent
                        upon the Boxer outbreak and the attack upon the Pekin legations, the two
                        powers have been in close and uninterrupted communication, and have been
                        actuated by similar views.</p>
                    <p>We have each of us desired that the integrity and independence of the Chinese
                        Empire should be preserved, that there should be no disturbance of the
                        territorial status quo either in China or in the adjoining regions, that all
                        nations should, within those regions, as well as within the limits of the
                        Chinese Empire, be afforded equal opportunities for the development of their
                        commerce and industry, and that peace should not only be restored, but
                        should, for the future, be maintained.</p>
                    <p>From the frequent exchanges of views which have taken place between the two
                        Governments, and from the discovery that their Far Eastern policy was
                        identical, it has resulted that each side has expressed the desire that
                        their common policy should find expression in an international contract of
                        binding validity.</p>
                    <p>We have thought it desirable to record in the preamble of that instrument the
                        main objects of our common policy in the Far East to which I have already
                        referred, and in the first article we join in entirely disclaiming any
                        aggressive tendencies either in China or Korea. We have, however, thought it
                        necessary also to place on record the view entertained by both the high
                        contracting parties, that should their interests, as above described, be
                        endangered, it will be admissible for either of them to take such measures
                        as may be indispensable in order to safeguard those interests, and words
                        have been added which will render it clear that such precautionary measures
                        might become necessary and might be legitimately taken, not only in the case
                        of aggressive <pb facs="0594" n="514" xml:id="pg_514"/> action or of an
                        actual attack by some other power, but in the event of disturbances arising
                        of a character to necessitate the intervention of either of the high
                        contracting parties for the protection of the lives and property of its
                        subjects.</p>
                    <p>The principal obligations undertaken mutually by the high contracting parties
                        are those of maintaining a strict neutrality in the event of either of them
                        becoming involved in war, and of coming to one another’s assistance in the
                        event of either of them being confronted by the opposition of more than one
                        hostile power. Under the remaining provisions of the agreement, the high
                        contracting parties undertake that neither of them will, without
                        consultation with the other, enter into separate arrangements with another
                        power to the prejudice of the interests described in the; agreement, and
                        that whenever those interests are in jeopardy they will communicate with one
                        another fully and frankly.</p>
                    <p>The concluding article has reference to the duration of the agreement which,
                        after five years, is terminable by either of the high contracting parties at
                        one year’s notice.</p>
                    <p>His Majesty’s Government have been largely influenced in their decision to
                        enter into this important contract by the conviction that it contains no
                        provisions which can be regarded as an indication of aggressive or
                        self-seeking tendencies in the regions to which it applies. It has been
                        concluded purely as a measure of precaution, to be invoked, should occasion
                        arise, in the defense of important British interests. It in no way threatens
                        the present position or the legitimate interests of other powers. On the
                        contrary, that part of it which renders either of the high contracting
                        parties liable to be called upon by the other for assistance can operate
                        only when one of the allies has found himself obliged to go to war in
                        defense of interests which are common to both, when the circumstances in
                        which he has taken this step are such as to establish that the quarrel has
                        not been of his own seeking, and when, being engaged in his own defense, he
                        finds himself threatened, not by a single power, but by a hostile
                        coalition.</p>
                    <p>His Majesty’s Government trust that the agreement may be found of mutual
                        advantage to the two countries, that it will make for the preservation of
                        peace, and that, should peace unfortunately be broken, it will have the
                        effect of restricting the area of hostilities.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lansdowne</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Agreement between Great Britain and Japan, signed at
                            London, January 30, 1902.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The Governments of Great Britain and Japan, actuated solely by a desire to
                        maintain the status quo and general peace in the extreme East, being
                        moreover specially interested in maintaining the independence and
                        territorial integrity of the Empire of China and the Empire of Korea, and in
                        securing equal opportunities in those countries for the commerce and
                        industry of all nations, hereby agree as follows:</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The high contracting parties having mutually recognized the independence of
                        China and of Korea, declare themselves to be entirely uninfluenced by any
                        aggressive tendencies in either country. Having in view, however, their
                        special interests, of which those of Great Britain relate principally to
                        China, while Japan, in addition to the interests which she possesses in
                        China, is interested in a peculiar degree politically, as well as
                        commercially and industrially, in Korea, the high contracting parties
                        recognize that it will be admissible for either of them to take such
                        measures as may be indispensable in order to safeguard those interests if
                        threatened either by the aggressive action of any other power, or by
                        disturbances arising in China or Korea, and necessitating the intervention
                        of either of the high contracting parties for the protection of the lives
                        and property of its subjects.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>If either Great Britain or Japan, in the defense of their respective
                        interests as above described, should become involved in war with another
                        power, the other high contracting party will maintain a strict neutrality,
                        and use its efforts to prevent other powers from joining in hostilities
                        against its ally.</p>
                    <pb facs="0595" n="515" xml:id="pg_515"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article III.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>If in the above event any other power or powers should join in hostilities
                        against that ally, the other high contracting party will come to its
                        assistance and will conduct the war in common, and make peace in mutual
                        agreement with it.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The high contracting parties agree that neither of them will, without
                        consulting the other, enter into separate arrangements with another power to
                        the prejudice of the interests above described.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article V.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Whenever, in the opinion of either Great Britain or Japan, the
                        above-mentioned interests are in jeopardy, the two Governments will
                        communicate with one another fully and frankly.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article VI.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The present agreement shall come into effect immediately after the date of
                        its signature, and remain in force for five years from that date.</p>
                    <p>In case neither of the high contracting parties should have notified twelve
                        months before the expiration of the said five years the intention of
                        terminating it, it shall remain binding until the expiration of one year
                        from the day on which either of the high contracting parties shall have
                        denounced it. But if, when the date fixed for its expiration arrives, either
                        ally is actually engaged in war, the alliance shall, ipso facto, continue
                        until peace is concluded.</p>
                    <p>In faith whereof the undersigned, duly authorized by their respective
                        Governments, have signed this agreement, and have affixed thereto their
                        seals.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Done in duplicate at
                                <placeName>London</placeName> the <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1902-01-30">30th January, 1902</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s.</hi>] <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lansdowne</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">His Britannic Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State
                                for Foreign Affairs.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>.] <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hayashi</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of
                                His Majesty the Emperor of Japan at the Court of St. James.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Weihaiwei</hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">[The Times, Tuesday, <date
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1902-02-11">February 11,
                            1902</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Earl Spencer asked the undersecretary of state for the colonies what were the
                        intentions of His Majesty’s Government with regard to Weihaiwei.</p>
                    <p>The Earl of Onslow: My lords, I do not think I need trouble you with the
                        early history of Weihaiwei, because it is probably well known to you. But I
                        may say that the Government have held a careful inquiry into the advantages
                        of the place as a military and naval station, and they have decided that the
                        idea which was at one time entertained of fortifying it and keeping there a
                        large garrison has been abandoned. There is at present there a Chinese
                        regiment. That regiment will be gradually disbanded or withdrawn, and in
                        future the administration of the colony will be undertaken by the police,
                        which will be raised by the administrator of the colony itself. The position
                        has been found to be one which could only be fortified at very great
                        expense; but it is an extremely useful place for small-arms practice and for
                        gunnery practice for the navy, as the bay is large and the water is shallow.
                        It is also an extremely healthy station, and it is believed that in the
                        course of a very short time a number of persons will utilize it as a
                        sanitarium for Hongkong and Shanghai and other places on the coast of China.
                        It will also be used as a sanitarium for our military and naval forces. It
                        has been taken over by the colonial office from January 1, and the new
                        administrator will be Mr. Lockhart, who has had many years official
                        experience at Hongkong. It is hoped that in his hands the place will be made
                        to yield a much larger revenue than that at present, which is something like
                        £2,000 a year. The inhabitants are mostly fishermen and agriculturists who
                        are not rich nor very prosperous; but there are capabilities about the
                        colony which lead us to hope that before very long it will yield a much
                        greater revenue than at present. Your <pb facs="0596" n="516"
                            xml:id="pg_516"/> lordships will recollect that Hongkong was in very
                        much the same position as Wei-haiwei is today. It has no custom duties, no
                        railway communication with the interior, and yet it has proved to be a very
                        important commercial port, and Weihaiwei has the advantage of being on the
                        highway from the Gulf of Pechili to northern China. It has an excellent
                        harbor, labor is cheap, and there is therefore every reason to believe that
                        it will continue to be a useful and valuable possession. At any rate, the
                        rumor that there is an intention on the part of His Majesty’s Government to
                        give it up, either returning it to China orhanding it over to another power,
                        is entirely without foundation. His Majesty’s Government have no intention
                        of abandoning the place, which they believe to be a very valuable
                        possession. [Hear! hear!] The Earl of Rosebery said their lordships must
                        have listened to the statement just made with mixed feelings. He had been in
                        no way prepared for the explanation just made by the undersecretary for the
                        colonies, for otherwise he would have endeavored to refresh his memory by
                        some reference to the statements which were made at the time when Weihaiwei
                        was first occupied. He recollected that the acquisition of the place had
                        been announced with a flourish of trumpets, and now apparently all that was
                        thought of it was that it was an important watering place. Was he to
                        understand that the inquiry as to its naval and military value was held
                        subsequently to its occupation by the Government? If so, some of the
                        statements which were made at the time of its acquisition would appear to
                        have been put forward with more rashness than was becoming in the case of a
                        Government taking over an important post in an empire like China.</p>
                    <p>The Earl of Onslow: The inquiries were made subsequently to the lease.</p>
                    <p>The Earl of Rosebery said that Weihaiwei was no longer a naval base. It was
                        no longer a place of arms; no longer a protection for our commerce or our
                        fleets. It had become a sort of second-rate watering place. [Hear! hear! and
                        laughter.] It was hoped that its salubrious climate would induce people to
                        come and spend what was known as the unhealthy season there. He had no doubt
                        that, if their lordships consulted the original authorities, they would find
                        that the statements made by the Government compared somewhat strangely with
                        the very piano announcement they had just listened to from the
                        undersecretary of the colonies.</p>
                    <p>Viscount Goschen said that, as one who had held a responsible position at the
                        admiralty when Weihaiwei was acquired, he had listened with a certain amount
                        of surprise to some of the statements of the undersecretary of the colonies.
                        He could assure their lordships that not long ago most exhaustive inquiries
                        had been made into the capacities of Weihaiwei in various aspects. The
                        question of the number of guns requisite for its fortification was carefully
                        examined, and the subject of a breakwater was likewise considered. In fact a
                        dredger was sent out to deepen the water. The number of battle ships which
                        could find anchorage within the bay was also fully examined into. There was
                        no lack of information originally, but he was disposed to think that on
                        review His Majesty’s Government had come to the conclusion on fresh
                        information acquired that the first opinions as to the value of Weihaiwei as
                        a naval and military base could not be sustained. There could be no doubt at
                        the same time that Weihaiwei occupied a most important position in the Gulf
                        of Pechili, and any power holding it possessed a strategical advantage. He
                        hoped the Government, in deciding that it should not be a fortified place,
                        would state whether this decision was based on financial or strategical
                        considerations. He was glad at the same time to hear that if Weihaiwei was
                        not to be fortified there was no intention of handing it over to another
                        power or of returning it to China. [Hear! hear!] He felt that their
                        lordships had not sufficient information before them to enable them
                        adequately to debate the change of policy on the part of the Government. As
                        to the proposed disbandment of the Chinese regiment, he understood that it
                        had been a very successful experiment. But if there were any international
                        reasons against making a fuller statement he should be perfectly satisfied
                        with the explanation of the Government.</p>
                    <p>The Earl of Portsmouth was of opinion that if Weihaiwei was not to be
                        fortified and no money spent upon it, then the place would not be a
                        strength, but a menace to us, and that therefore if we were not to take the
                        necessary precautions to strengthen our position there we had much better
                        retire. He could not help being impressed by a sense of the extraordinarily
                        flippant and careless way in which the matter had been dealt with on the
                        part of the Government.</p>
                    <p>The Earl of Selborne: I shall be prepared to go into this question at length
                        on any occasion in which any one of your lordships brings it again before
                        the notice of the House, and I think perhaps later on we shall be in a
                        better position to discuss it in the fullest detail. But I have now, and at
                        once, to say that the decision of this question has not been financial. It
                        has been purely strategical, and that strategy was purely naval. Lord
                        Rosebery spoke of Weihaiwei as the protection to British <pb facs="0597"
                            n="517" xml:id="pg_517"/> commerce. I think on reflection the noble earl
                        would not repeat that. The only protection to British commerce in Chinese
                        seas is the navy, and the value and importance of Weihaiwei is purely
                        relative to the navy. Naval opinion as to the proper method of utilizing
                        Weihaiwei has differed, and does differ; but speaking as one who has closely
                        studied this question for more than a year, perhaps I may say that there is
                        an extraordinary concurrence of naval opinion in favor of the course which
                        the Government has adopted. There are, roughly speaking, two alternatives.
                        One is to make Weihaiwei a fortress like Hongkong, the other is to use it as
                        a peace base, and not to commit ourselves to the custody of the fortress.
                        The naval opinion has been pronounced, and I venture strongly to concur with
                        it, in favor of the latter course as against the former. While that decision
                        has been taken and while naval opinion has pronounced itself in the degree I
                        have mentioned in favor of this course, naval opinion is also equally strong
                        as to the value, the great value, of this base to the navy, of value to the
                        efficiency of the navy and of value to the health of the navy; and while I
                        should oppose personally any attempt to turn Weihaiwei into a fortress like
                        Hongkong I should also oppose any idea of surrendering it.</p>
                    <p>Earl Spencer asked the Government whether they would present full papers on
                        the subject.</p>
                    <p>The Earl of Selborne, in reply, stated that many of the reports were
                        confidential, but the Government would carefully consider the
                        suggestion.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
