<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1902-05-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1902-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="524" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d524">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hay</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Choate</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-05-09"><hi rend="italic">May 9,
                                1902</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 911.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In its No. 743, of October 14 last, the
                            Department instructed Mr. White to “express the great pleasure with
                            which this Government recognizes the valuable aid courteously extended
                            by His Majesty’s agency at Sofia, in the absence of direct
                            representation of the United States in Bulgaria which has now been
                            supplied, and to ask that our grateful thanks be communicated to the
                            agent.”</p>
                        <p>At the time of writing that instruction the Department did not anticipate
                            that there would be any delay in the recognition by the Bulgarian
                            Government of Mr. Dickinson, who had been appointed to <pb facs="0602" n="522" xml:id="pg_522"/> the dual capacity of agent to Bulgaria and
                            consul-general at Constantinople.</p>
                        <p>It now appears that the Bulgarian Government is disinclined to receive
                            Mr. Dickinson unless the agency to Bulgaria be separated from the
                            consulate-general at Constantinople. This, of course, can be done only
                            by Congress. Meanwhile the United States has no representative in
                            Bulgaria.</p>
                        <p>I should be pleased to have you explain the situation to Lord Lansdowne,
                            and to formally request him to instruct Mr. Elliot to take charge of
                            United States interests in Bulgaria, as before, until other arrangements
                            are made for our direct representation.</p>
                        <p>If it should be the pleasure of His Majesty’s Government to comply with
                            this request, it is the hope of this Department that Mr. Eliot will
                            communicate freely with it and with the United States minister at
                            Constantinople on all matters on which he may require to do so.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>