<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Leishman to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1902</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d926</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">926</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-09-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-09-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-09-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-09-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="926"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d926">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Leishman</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-09-24">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 24, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 79.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the abduction of Miss Ellen M. Stone
                    by brigands, you will observe from copy of correspondence inclosed herewith that
                    the scene of operations appears to have shifted from Turkish to Bulgarian
                    territory, and judging from the best information obtainable the miscreants who
                    committed the outrage were Bulgarians, or possibly Macedonians, living close to
                    the frontier, instigated by the central Bulgarian committee. I am not disposed,
                    however, to accept the opinion of a number of the missionaries, which seems to
                    be partly snared by Mr. McGregor, acting British agent at Sofia (who up to the
                    present time has been looking after American interests, as Mr. Dickinson has not
                    presented his credentials, although, as I advised privately, all objections have
                    been removed), that the outrage was committed for political reasons under the
                    direction of the central Bulgarian Macedonian committee with the hope of
                    stirring up foreign intervention. I consider that it is quite within the range
                    of probabilities that the central committee may have had a hand in the matter,
                    but in all probability the principal motive was money; and the only way lean
                    explain the long delay in sending a demand for ransom is that the Turkish
                    Government not only acted very promptly, but with unusual activity, keeping the
                    brigands on the move and thus preventing them from feeling secure enough to
                    warrant opening up negotiations; but now that they have succeeded in recrossing
                    the frontier, notwithstanding the assurance given me by Mr. Guechoff, the
                    Bulgarian agent, that his government was guarding the frontier so closely that
                    it would be impossible for the brigands to enter Bulgaria, it is reasonable to
                    expect that negotiations may be commenced that will lead to the prompt and safe
                    return of Miss Stone, especially if Mr. Dickinson can induce the Bulgarian
                    authorities to act with the same energy that the Turkish officials have
                    displayed, the latter having acted with so much energy that the consul-general
                    and several of the leading officers of the missionary board have been to see me,
                    advising against such great activity, fearing that if too closely pressed the
                    brigands might harm Miss Stone rather than permit her to be rescued.</p>
                <p>* * * I feel quite satisfied that it is only a question of money <pb facs="1081"
                        n="1001" xml:id="pg_1001"/> and that the brigands will take the best care
                    possible of Miss Stone and return her unharmed to her friends as soon as the
                    question of ransom is settled.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John G. A. Leishman.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">McGregor</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Leishman</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">His Britannic Majesty’s Agency and
                                    Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sofia</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-09-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 16, 1902</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my telegram of yesterday
                        morning, which I presume was duly communicated to you by His Majesty’s
                        ambassador, I have the honor to report that, immediately on learning that
                        the American citizen, Miss Stone, and her companion had been captured by
                        brigands within a short distance of the Bulgarian frontier, I wrote to Mr.
                        Daneff, the Bulgarian minister of foreign affairs, requesting that the
                        necessary vigilance should be exercised by the frontier guards, and was
                        informed the same day by Mr. Daneff that measures in that sense had, from
                        the first moment, been taken by His Excellency’s Government.</p>
                    <p>Since then the local newspapers, and among them a journal said to be inspired
                        by Mr. Daneff, have announced that the outrage is supposed to have been
                        perpetrated by Turkish deserters, an announcement which has been taken
                        advantage of by the Reforme, the organ of the Macedonian central committee,
                        to publish a diatribe against the evils of Ottoman administration in
                        Macedonia.</p>
                    <p>On the evening of the 14th instant, however, I received from the Rev. Robert
                        Thomson, a British subject in the employ of the American mission at
                        Samakoff, a letter, of which I have the honor to inclose a copy, putting
                        quite a different and, in my opinion, a much more serious complexion on the
                        whole matter.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Thomson, whom I believe to be a cautious and trustworthy man, quotes
                        facts pointing unmistakably to the act having been the work of the secret
                        committee in Macedonia which, as Mr. Daneff admitted to me lately, has had
                        relations with Boris Saratoff, ex-president of the central committee, as
                        well as with several other members of the same committee. Now, it has been
                        hinted in several newspapers which profess to be acquainted with the views
                        of Saratoff and his henchmen that it had been decided, in the hope of
                        provoking a European intervention, to render existence in Macedonia
                        impossible for foreigners, and the circumstances of Miss Stone’s capture,
                        viewed in the light of Mr. Thomson’s letter, seem to me to afford strong
                        grounds for assuming that Saratoff has begun to put his scheme into
                        execution. It is also stated here in many quarters that Saratoff is
                        contemplating leaving the country for Odessa, and, in consideration of the
                        desirableness of ascertaining whether this crime can be brought home to him
                        and his associates, I have thought it my duty to acquaint the Bulgarian
                        Government with the facts which have come to my knowledge, warning them at
                        the same time that under these circumstances they would incur a grave moral
                        responsibility by allowing Saratoff to quit Bulgarian territory for the
                        present.</p>
                    <p>Not having found Mr. Saratoff, the acting minister for foreign affairs, at
                        home yesterday morning, I called on Selim Bey, the acting Ottoman
                        commissary, and, on learning that he had no news to give beyond the fact
                        that the brigands were believed by the Turkish authorities to be Bulgarians,
                        I confidentially communicated to him the information I had received,
                        without, however, disclosing the source, and urged upon him the importance
                        of preventing the brigands from escaping into Bulgarian territory. Selim Bey
                        promised to inform his Government forthwith and said he would do his best to
                        obtain the particulars necessary in order to establish the connivance of the
                        Macedonians here, whose undoubted complicity in the outrages daily committed
                        in the province had already formed the subject of much animated but sterile
                        correspondence with the Bulgarian Government.</p>
                    <p>Having subsequently made two unsuccessful attempts to see Mr. Saratoff (the
                        minister) I finally called this morning on Mr. Vernazza, secretary-general
                        at the ministry for foreign affairs, and on ascertaining that he had no news
                        regarding the identity of the brigands or the result of their pursuit, I
                        communicated to him the contents of Mr. Thomson’s letter and stated my
                        reasons for suspecting the outrage to be the work of individuals acting
                        under orders from Sofia. I told Mr. Vernazza that, under the circumstances,
                        it would be regrettable were Boris Saratoff or any of his more noteworthy
                        associates allowed to put themselves beyond the reach of Bulgarian
                        jurisdiction <pb facs="1082" n="1002" xml:id="pg_1002"/> so long as involved
                        directly or indirectly in Miss Stone’s capture, as in the event of such
                        proving to be the case I had no doubt that, in the eyes of the United States
                        Government, a grave moral responsibility would be at the door of the
                        Bulgarian authorities.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Vernazza took a note of my representations which he promised to
                        communicate to Mr. Saratoff, and I shall have the honor to acquaint you with
                        the minister’s reply at the earliest opportunity.</p>
                    <p>I should be glad to know if my action so far has your approval. I am sending
                        a copy of this dispatch to the Marquis of Lansdowne.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">James McGregor</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">His Majesty’s Chargé d’Affaires.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">McGregor</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Leishman</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">His Britannic Majesty’s Agency and
                                    Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sofia</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-09-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 19, 1902</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In continuation of my dispatch of the 16th
                        instant, I have the honor to report that I called yesterday on Mr. Saratoff,
                        the minister of the interior, who is at present acting as minister of
                        foreign affairs, and repeated to him the facts already communicated to Mr.
                        Vernazza regarding the circumstances of Miss Stone’s, capture, adding that
                        according to information I had just received the brigands were supposed to
                        have taken refuge in the Rilo Mountains, and were, perhaps, at this moment
                        in Bulgarian territory. I should mention that I had this information from
                        Selim Bey, the acting Ottoman commissary, who has, moreover, received a
                        telegram from his Government confirming the suspicion that the brigands are
                        Macedonians, and is about to address a note to the Bulgarian Government
                        demanding a strict inquiry.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Saratoff thanked me for the information and promised not only to send
                        immediate instructions to the military authorities in the Rilo district, but
                        also to have Saratoff and his associates carefully watched by the police. He
                        said, however, that in the absence of a specific accusation it would be
                        difficult for the authorities to refuse Saratoff a passport supposing it to
                        be true that he intended to go to England, as the minister professed to have
                        heard was the case. Saratoff was completely ruined as far as regards his
                        influence with the Macedonians, and it was highly improbable that he could
                        have had a hand in this business.</p>
                    <p>It is possible that Mr. Saratoff may be right in saying that his namesake is
                        no longer all-powerful, and that he is out of favor with the newly elected
                        committee; but he is still the center of a circle of admirers, and it can
                        not be imagined that he will renounce what has hitherto been his means of
                        livelihood. I therefore reminded Mr. Saratoff that neither his Government,
                        nor any of his predecessors, had ever been at a loss to devise
                        administrative measures when circumstances seemed to call for them; I had
                        considered it my duty to aid the Government in its efforts to repress the
                        excesses attributed to agents of the committee and the responsibility for
                        taking action or remaining quiescent would rest with the Government.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">James McGregor.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">McGregor</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Leishman</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">His Britannic Majesty’s Agency and
                                    Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Sofia</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-09-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 20, 1902</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my dispatch of yesterday’s
                        date, I have the honor to report that, according to reliable information
                        received just as the bag is closing, Boris Saratoff left Sofia on the 15th
                        instant en route for Odessa, a fact which must have been known to the acting
                        minister for foreign affairs when I attended his reception on the 18th
                        instant.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">James McGregor.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="1083" n="1003" xml:id="pg_1003"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Dickinson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Leishman</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1902-09-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 20, 1902</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring further to the capture of Miss
                        Stone, Agent Lazzaro sent me last night a further telegram, as follows:</p>
                    <p>“Vali informs brigands’ agent caught Banitza. Stone kept some time in huts at
                        Obesnik, whence by Kresne crossed toward Melenik. Evidently not passed
                        Bulgarian frontier. Authorities Melenik, Djumabala, Nevrecop, Serres
                        continuing search.”</p>
                    <p>The statement that the agent of the brigands has been “caught” and the
                        authorities are continuing the search justifies the inference that the
                        latter may be pressing the matter so closely as to jeopardize the life of
                        Miss Stone. Naturally they are bent on catching the brigands, both for
                        vengeance and the hope of reward. * * *</p>
                    <p>If the agent of the brigands has been caught, he should be set at liberty and
                        negotiations for ransom opened at once. I telegraphed Agent Lazzaro to the
                        foregoing effect on receipt of his telegram, and also to urge Vali to
                        prevent escape of brigands across the Bulgarian border, but not to press the
                        search too vigorously. In harmony with our personal conference, all our
                        efforts at first must be directed to the rescue of Miss Stone. This will
                        lead to sufficient identification, and the punishment of the guilty parties
                        can be vigorously and safely pursued thereafter.</p>
                    <p>Agent Lazzaro also reports by written dispatch that one of the guides of the
                        brigands testifies that just before the capture of the Stone party he heard
                        Dentzo, the leader of the brigands, say that they expected to make their
                        fortunes by this capture. This, and the appearance of the agent of the
                        brigands, seems to settle definitely their purpose, and his appearance also
                        indicates that they believe they have reached a place of hiding where
                        negotiations for ransom may be safely opened.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chas. M. Dickinson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 5.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Leishman</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Diokinson</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-09-24">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 24, 1901</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to acknowledge receipt of your No. 414
                        of even date and note contents with interest.</p>
                    <p>As all the information obtained during the past two weeks tends to prove that
                        the brigands who carried off Miss Stone were Bulgarians who, according to
                        the telegram you received last evening from agent Lazzaro, have succeeded in
                        recrossing the Bulgarian frontier and are now supposed to be in the
                        neighborhood of Batak, I would urge upon you the advisability of your going
                        to Sofia at once in order to take the matter up personally with the
                        Bulgarian Government; for while Mr. McGregor is no doubt doing everything in
                        his power, I am inclined to believe that representations from the accredited
                        agent of the United States might bring the Bulgarian Government to a more
                        prompt realization of the importance of taking the most active and energetic
                        measures to secure Miss Stone’s release.</p>
                    <p>While I have no positive information on the subject, I am inclined to believe
                        that the man arrested by the Turkish soldiers, supposed to be an agent of
                        the brigands, is still in custody. I spoke to the minister for foreign
                        affairs on Saturday in regard to this man, and was informed that outside of
                        the man’s own admission that he was an agent of the brigands they had been
                        unable to obtain any information, as the man denied all knowledge of their
                        whereabouts and of the fact of his being the bearer of any demand for
                        ransom.</p>
                    <p>I can only add that the minister for foreign affairs again assured me that
                        every effort was being made to locate the brigands, and that the first care
                        would be to secure Miss Stone’s safe return to her friends.</p>
                    <p>I do not share your fear that Miss Stone’s chance of rescue has been
                        materially lessened, being rather inclined to take the reverse view, for the
                        reason that the brigands are quite sure to commence negotiations for ransom
                        the moment they feel secure, which the activity of the Turkish troops may
                        have prevented so long as they remained in Turkish territory; for even if
                        later developments should prove that the Macedonian committee has been the
                        instigator of the dastardly outrage, sordid gain in the shape of a ransom is
                        no doubt the main factor which induced the miscreants to commit the
                        deed.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John G. A. Leishman.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
