<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-06-08T16:08:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-06-08T16:08:00-05:00" n="216" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                        <head>216. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                                Chile<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d216fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss>/IL Historical Files,
                                Roger Channel, Santiago 1963–79. Secret; Immediate. Sent for
                                information immediate to Buenos Aires.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-06-08T21:08:00+00:00">June 8, 1978,
                                2108Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>145831. Subject: <persName corresp="#p_LO_1">Letelier</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_MVRK_1">Moffitt</persName> Assassination Investigation: The Paraguayan
                            Connection.</p>
                        <p>1. In consultation here with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BTD_1">Boyatt</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_PEMG_1">Propper</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BEL_1">Barcella</persName>, we have established a
                            tentative plan of action designed to elicit Chilean and Paraguayan
                            cooperation in the matter of testimony on the <persName corresp="#p_WE_1">Williams</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_RA_1">Romeral</persName> passports. Information recently received by
                                <persName corresp="#p_PEMG_1">Propper</persName>, [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] indicates that the Chilean
                            government does not intend to cooperate further in the <persName corresp="#p_LO_1">Letelier</persName> case.</p>
                        <p>2. When you have our responses to the pending <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> questions, which should be in your hands soon,<note n="2" xml:id="d216fn2">Not found.</note> you would be asked to hand
                            them to General <persName corresp="#p_OH_1">Orozco</persName> and to
                            simultaneously note that we are awaiting cooperation on such matters as
                            the Iturriaga testimony and the telephone call to the Paraguayan
                            Government in which the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> will
                            “release” Colonel Guanes to testify concerning the <persName corresp="#p_WE_1">Williams</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_RA_1">Romeral</persName> passport affair. The Paraguayan testimony
                            concerning the passports may be vital to the investigation. The
                            importance of this should not initially be made evident to the Chileans,
                            but it is probably the critical point upon which we will judge <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> cooperation. FYI. The Paraguayan
                            testimony may be key to an indictment of Contreras. End FYI. <persName corresp="#p_PEMG_1">Propper</persName> indicated that he feels you
                            should tell the Chileans that these two <pb facs="0686" n="645" xml:id="pg_645"/> requests are totally within the governments
                            ability to immediately comply with while others, such as finding
                                <persName corresp="#p_WML_1">Liliana Walker</persName>,<note n="3" xml:id="d216fn3"><persName corresp="#p_WML_1">Liliana Walker
                                    Martinez</persName> (alias) was another <gloss target="#t_DINA_1">DINA</gloss> agent. (Nicholas Horrock, “Seven
                                Indicted In U.S. Murder Of Chilean Aide,” <hi rend="italic">New York
                                    Times</hi>, August 2, 1978, p. A4) In 1990, she was identified
                                as Monica Luisa Lagos. (Malcolm Coad, “Reopening of <persName corresp="#p_LO_1">Letelier</persName> Case Ordered in Chile,”
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, April 25, 1990, p.
                                A31)</note> may not be within their power to do immediately, and so
                            cooperation will not be judged on requests such as the latter.</p>
                        <p>3. We would inform the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> that we
                            expect positive replies to both requests quickly. The first-priority
                            item should be the call to the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>4. If they do not make the phone call, we must consider how best to apply
                            pressure. We contemplate at that stage asking you to seek an interview
                            after about 3 days with an appropriate official other than Cubillos
                            close to Pinochet such as General Vidal. We have not ruled out going to
                            Pinochet himself, but we feel that there may be advantages in avoiding
                            direct confrontation with Pinochet at this point. In an interview with
                            Vidal or another official close to Pinochet, you would state the
                            imperative need for <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> cooperation in
                            obtaining Paraguayan testimony in the passport matter. You would tell
                            Vidal that we consider <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> response on
                            this particular issue to be the critical test for now of the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>’s continued cooperation. We would set
                            a specific short time for <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> response.
                            What do you feel is reasonable? You would state that failing that
                            cooperation, you expect instructions to return to the US for
                            consultations. In the event you are required to return, we would issue a
                            public statement making clear the reason for your departure. We would
                            hope and expect that this step would be unnecessary, since the threat
                            may be sufficient to obtain what we want.</p>
                        <p>5. In the meantime we will have drafted in consultation with Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName> an instruction for his
                            action in Paraguay. We would prepare a note for him to deliver to the
                            Foreign Ministry, in which we would outline the Paraguayan involvement
                            and ask for Colonel Guanes’ testimony. However, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName> would hold this note until it
                            became certain that the effort with the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> had failed and that you were leaving Chile. At that
                            time he would go to <persName corresp="#p_PC_1">Pappalardo</persName>
                            and show him the intended note. He would make every effort to convince
                                <persName corresp="#p_PC_1">Pappalardo</persName> to obtain the
                            testimony for us without forcing us to confront the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> with the note. He would try to
                            convince the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> that it can by
                            cooperating honestly maintain the posture of an uninvolved bystander in
                            the <persName corresp="#p_LO_1">Letelier</persName> case. He would
                            stress that by refusing cooperation, the <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> would be placing itself in the much more dangerous
                            position of appearing to help cover up the crime. We would be prepared
                            to deliver the note if <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> cooperation
                            were not forthcoming. He would <pb facs="0687" n="646" xml:id="pg_646"/>
                            see to it this was understood by <persName corresp="#p_PC_1">Pappalardo</persName>, and that the note would inevitably become
                            public. He would convince <persName corresp="#p_PC_1">Pappalardo</persName> of our seriousness by pointing out the fact
                            of your departure from Chile for consultations and our public charge of
                            non-cooperation against the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>6. We believe the described circumstances might be sufficient to
                            stimulate crisis consultation between <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss>, and hope this
                            will result in their agreement to cooperate. If your efforts with <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> fail to produce their cooperation, we
                            will find ourselves at the point of decision contemplated in your
                            earlier consultation with the Deputy Secretary,<note n="4" xml:id="d216fn4">Not further identified.</note> at which time it was
                            agreed that you would return for discussion of our next steps.</p>
                        <p>7. This message has been made available directly to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">White</persName>, who expects to return to
                            Asuncion about June 7 or 8. Your comments and suggestions will be
                                welcomed.<note n="5" xml:id="d216fn5">In telegram 4401 from
                                Santiago, June 9, <persName corresp="#p_LGW_1">Landau</persName>
                                responded: “I am in general agreement with the Santiago scenario set
                                forth” in telegram 145831, “but I plan to deal initially with
                                Foreign Minister Cubillos, not <persName corresp="#p_OH_1">Orozco</persName>. Depending on the response I get from
                                Cubillos it may be desirable to go directly to President Pinochet.
                                    <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> cooperation to date in the
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LO_1">Letelier</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_MVRK_1">Moffitt</persName> investigation has
                                required in almost every instance my intervention with the Foreign
                                Minister, first Carvajal then Cubillos.” (National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Foreign Policy File, D780242-0704)</note></p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_VC_1"><hi rend="strong">Vance</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>