<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>264. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Colombia</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d264</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">264</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-11-26T16:16:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-11-26T16:16:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2020005458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic rights</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="rec99jdV9ZgPMHimw" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="narcotics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85089815"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Narcotics</term>
                    <term ref="recLrhH3r9BIhQsGe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Extradition</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="guerrilla" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrillas</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-11-26T16:16:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-11-26T16:16:00-05:00" n="264"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d264">
                <head>264. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Colombia<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d264fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy File, D800567-0448. Confidential; Immediate; <gloss
                            target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>. Sent for information to La Paz,
                        Quito, Caracas, Lima, and Managua. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HEM_1"
                            >Heaphy</persName>, cleared in <gloss target="#t_ARAAND_1"
                            >ARA/AND</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>, <gloss
                            target="#t_SSO_1">S/S-O</gloss> and by <persName corresp="#p_ES_1"
                            >Eaton</persName>; approved by <persName corresp="#p_BWG_1"
                            >Bowdler</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-11-26T21:16:00+00:00">November 26, 1980, 2116Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>315451. Subject: Secretary’s Meeting With Foreign Minister Uribe November 22,
                    1980.</p>
                <p>1. Confidential Entire Text.</p>
                <p>2. Secretary met with Colombian Foreign Minister Diego Uribe for approximately
                    one half hour on November 22, 1980 for review of US-Colombian relations.
                    Minister Uribe was accompanied by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EJM_1"
                        >Eastman</persName> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BC_1"
                        >Bernal</persName> (<gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>). Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWG_1">Bowdler</persName> and Desk Officer <persName
                        corresp="#p_HEM_1">Heaphy</persName> were present.</p>
                <p>3. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MES_1">Muskie</persName> began by expressing
                    his regrets that he would not be able to travel to Colombia as Secretary of
                    State. He stressed that the US has neglected to pay proper attention to Latin
                    America but praised the mutually beneficial relations currently existing between
                    the US and Colombia. Referring to Colombia’s leadership in promoting democracy,
                    the Secretary asked for Colombia’s views on Bolivia and other critical areas in
                    Latin America.</p>
                <p>4. After inviting the Secretary to visit Colombia in a private capacity, Uribe
                    praised the Secretary’s speech before the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1"
                        >OAS</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d264fn2">For the text of <persName
                            corresp="#p_MES_1">Muskie</persName>’s November 19th remarks, see the
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, January 1981, pp.
                        33–36.</note> However, he added that although the human rights emphasis was
                    good, democratic governments have not profited much from the US because of their
                    good records. Uribe stressed that we must build on human rights to include more
                    emphasis on economic rights.</p>
                <p>5. Uribe raised the Quita Sueno Treaty issue and urged that one of the
                    Secretary’s last acts be that of resolving the Quita Sueno problem. He
                    emphasized that the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> would like to see the
                    issue concluded before the new US administration began. The Secretary replied
                    that we have sent the letter answering questions raised during the hearings<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d264fn3">The Senate Committee on Foreign Relations held
                        hearings on the Quita Sueno treaty on December 4, 1979. (Senate Committee on
                        Foreign Relations, <hi rend="italic">Nominations of Sol M. Linowitz and
                            Gerald B. Helman; To Hear Administration Testimony on Ex. A, 93-1:
                            Treaty with the Republic of Colombia Concerning the Status of Quita
                            Sueno, Roncador, and Serrana</hi>, 96th Cong., 1st sess., December 4,
                        1979, p. 1-108)</note> to the Senate Foreign Relations Committee and that he
                    would follow up with a personal appeal to the Committee to act on the Treaty.
                    (It <pb facs="0800" n="759" xml:id="pg_759"/> was clarified later to Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_EJM_1">Eastman</persName> that the letter had not yet
                    left the Department but that it was expected that it would be sent during the
                    week of November 24.<note n="4" xml:id="d264fn4">Not found.</note>) Uribe said
                    it would be a “brilliant” way to end the <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1"
                        >Carter</persName> Administration. The Secretary cautioned that there were
                    still obstacles to getting Senate action, most important of which was the
                    lameduck period of the session.</p>
                <p>6. The Secretary inquired about Colombia’s role in Central America and the
                    Caribbean. Uribe referred to previous meetings with Asst. Sec. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BWG_1">Bowdler</persName>
                    <note n="5" xml:id="d264fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWG_1">Bowdler</persName> visited Colombia in August
                        1980 and met with Turbay and other Colombian leaders. (Telegram 8567 from
                        Bogota, August 12, National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D800384-1164)</note> in which the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> had
                    reviewed its relations and activities with countries such as El Salvador and
                    Guatemala. However, he said that the real need is to find a mechanism for
                    financial assistance in economic and social areas for those countries which are
                    threatened by leftist guerrillas. He mentioned President Turbay’s Peace Fund
                    proposal which he said would require some funding. In sum, he said Colombia was
                    disposed to help. The Secretary agreed but said that the US Congress, reflecting
                    perhaps a lack of understanding on the part of the American people on the direct
                    connection between assistance and peace, was unwilling to provide adequate
                    funds. Uribe reiterated that quick expenditure in social assistance was the key
                    ingredient needed.</p>
                <p>7. The Secretary then complimented the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> for
                    its excellent cooperation in narcotics interdiction and expressed his pleasure
                    that the $16 million pro-ag was almost signed.<note n="6" xml:id="d264fn6">In
                        telegram 157 from Bogota, January 9, 1981, the Embassy reported that the
                        project agreement was signed in November and summarized the US-Colombian
                        anti-narcotics program. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy
                        File, D810013-1129)</note> Minister Uribe stated that the Turbay
                    administration had been making great progress in the area and cited the
                    prosecution of traffickers and the US—Colombian extradition treaty recently
                    ratified by the Colombian Congress. He stated that “with or without your money”
                    Colombia was proceeding against drug trafficking, because it was committed to do
                    so. He listed the narcotics cooperation agreements Colombia has already signed
                    with Ecuador, Peru, Venezuela, the Dominican Republic and Honduras.</p>
                <p>8. On Bolivia, Uribe said that the most serious problem was that <persName
                        corresp="#p_GMTL_1">Garcia Meza</persName> was so shameless that he had not
                    even promised elections but instead had spoken of a 20 year dictatorship. Uribe
                    said however, that <persName corresp="#p_GMTL_1">Garcia Meza</persName> might be
                    obliged to announce elections, which Colom<pb facs="0801" n="760"
                        xml:id="pg_760"/>bia would view as a good development. Alternatively, he
                    said we (presumably Colombia) would have to continue urging Bolivia to return to
                    democracy even though this would be a “Sisyphean undertaking.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MES_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Muskie</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
