<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>293. Telegram From the Embassy in Paraguay to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">293</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-12-28T13:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-12-28T13:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004886"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Journalist</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-12-28T13:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-12-28T13:30:00-05:00" n="293"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d293">
                <head>293. Telegram From the Embassy in Paraguay to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d293fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy File, D780001-0054. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Asuncion</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-12-28T18:30:00+00:00">December 28, 1977, 1830Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5233. Subject: Conversation With Foreign Minister on Human Rights</p>
                <p>1. Foreign Minister invited me to his office December 27 to discuss statements
                    allegedly made by US representative to <gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>,
                    Ralph Dungan: the first related to the <persName corresp="#p_AJ_1">Jack
                        Anderson</persName> column on child abuse in Paraguay<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d293fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_AJ_1">Jack Anderson</persName> and Les Whitten,
                        “Paraguayan Officials and Child Abuse,” <hi rend="italic">Washington
                            Post</hi>, December 20, 1977, p. B15.</note> and the need for the
                    government to refute these statements before presenting any more requests for
                    loans; the second had to do with Paraguay’s newfound prosperity which might make
                    it ineligible for further soft loans.</p>
                <p>2. I replied that if the government could refute <persName corresp="#p_AD_1"
                        >Anderson</persName>’s column that it would certainly be well advised to do
                    so but that I did not think there should exist any direct correlation between
                    the charges of a journalist and the response of the <gloss target="#t_USG_1"
                        >USG</gloss> to loan presentations. Secondly, I said Pargauay indeed might
                    have a problem regarding eligibility for soft loans but that if we could improve
                    the record on human rights we could then begin to treat this problem in the
                    technical context where it belongs and where there were good chances of success.
                    The Foreign Minister agreed and pointed out that Brazil, Argentina and Chile all
                    continue to receive soft loans.</p>
                <p>3. When the Minister brought up the question of a date for the Inter-American
                    Human Rights Commission (<gloss target="#t_IAHRC_1">IAHRC</gloss>) visit and
                    President <persName corresp="#p_SA_5">Stroessner</persName>’s directive not to
                    set a date for the visit until after the February 12 elections, I made the
                    following points to <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Nogues</persName>.</p>
                <p>4. The <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> was giving Washington the impression
                    that it was playing with the dates of the visit in the hope of avoiding an
                        <gloss target="#t_IAHRC_1">IAHRC</gloss> visit altogether. It was hard for
                    any knowledgeable observer to believe that there was any doubt about the outcome
                    of the February 12 elections and that it appeared to us that the crucial date
                    was more likely in early June when the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>
                    General Assembly would meet to consider, inter alia, the human rights situations
                    in various countries. Both Paraguay and the US know that the <gloss
                        target="#t_IAHRC_1">IAHRC</gloss> wants to visit Paraguay in March in order
                    that it can complete its report in time for the General Assembly. If Paraguay
                    continues its dilatory tactics the Commission could publish <pb facs="0881"
                        n="840" xml:id="pg_840"/> its report without the benefit of an on-site
                    visit. In this case Paraguay might feel it had a logical pretext to state that
                    there was no longer a necessity for a visit. Superficial diplomatic maneuvering
                    such as this was no way to treat a serious problem. The important point for the
                        <gloss target="#t_GOP_1">GOP</gloss> to remember was that President
                        <persName corresp="#p_SA_5">Stroessner</persName> had made a commitment to
                    President <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> and if Paraguay
                    wriggled out of that commitment they would face a stone wall in trying to get
                    further credits.</p>
                <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Nogues</persName> took close notes and while he
                    looked disapproving at times, he did not attempt to refute my version of the
                    Paraguayan scenario. I believe that putting Paraguay on notice will impress upon
                    this government that we know perfectly well what they are up to and that it is a
                    no-win game.<note n="3" xml:id="d293fn3">In telegram 310457 to Asuncion,
                        December 30, the Department advised <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1"
                            >White</persName>: “we applaud strong stand you took with <persName
                            corresp="#p_NA_1">Nogues</persName>” and “you may find it useful in your
                        subsequent discussions with <persName corresp="#p_NA_1">Nogues</persName> to
                        remind him that <gloss target="#t_IAHRC_1">IAHRC</gloss> will be meeting on
                        January 26 and that setting of date for visit could minimize adverse
                        statements or actions at that time.” (National Archives, RG 59, Central
                        Foreign Policy File, D780004-0451)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WRE_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">White</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
