<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>366. Telegram From the Embassy in Venezuela to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v24</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-02-01T19:11:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-02-01T19:11:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-01T19:11:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-01T19:11:00-05:00" n="366"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d366">
                <head>366. Telegram From the Embassy in Venezuela to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d366fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                        Security Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                        Material, Country File, Box 85, Venezuela, 1/79-3/80. Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_Niact_1">Niact</gloss> Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Caracas</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-02-02T00:11:00+00:00">February 2, 1980, 0011Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1045. Subject: Andean Pact Military Assistance to El Salvador. Ref: (A) San
                    Salvador 703<note n="2" xml:id="d366fn2">Dated January 31. The Embassy reported
                        on the visit to El Salvador of the Andean Pact mission. (National Archives,
                        RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D800055-0237)</note> (B) State
                        028294.<note n="3" xml:id="d366fn3">Dated February 1. The Department
                        repeated San Salvador 712, January 31, in which the Embassy reported that
                        the Venezuelan delegation “had agreed in concept to provide military and
                        anti-subversive training to Salvadoran armed forces.” (National Archives, RG
                        59, Central Foreign Policy File, N800002-0575)</note>
                </p>
                <p>1. S–Entire Text</p>
                <p>2. I called on Foreign Minister Zambrano this afternoon (February 1) to express
                    our strong concern that in view of developments in El Salvador it was imperative
                    that the <gloss target="#t_GOV_1">GOV</gloss> decide as soon as possible on its
                    participation in the proposed multilateralization of military assist<pb
                        facs="1110" n="1069" xml:id="pg_1069"/>ance to the junta. Zambrano responded
                    that the situation was extremely worrisome, and that Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_CH_2">Cardozo</persName> had reported on his recent visit there
                    in very somber terms. The question was, how can the military aid be furnished?
                    It was clear that it would require a Presidential decision as far as Venezuela
                    was concerned, he said. When I emphasized that time was short to coordinate any
                    possible multilateral efforts, and that we were on the eve of the two-week trip
                    that the President and he are making to the Middle East, Zambrano said he was
                    not sure the President would have time to focus on the proposal before departing
                    this week-end. According to Zambrano, President Herrera has suspended all
                    audiences and is concentrating exclusively on the preparations for the trip.
                    Zambrano recommended that I follow-up with <persName corresp="#p_CH_2"
                        >Cardozo</persName> who was back from his visit.</p>
                <p>3. I was able to pursue the matter with <persName corresp="#p_CH_2"
                        >Cardozo</persName> (who was in the Ministry working with the Ambassador of
                    Colombia on how the proposal should be presented to the Governments of Colombia
                    and Venezuela). <persName corresp="#p_CH_2">Cardozo</persName> said that on the
                    basis of his visit, he judged the political situation to be so grave that he
                    would not give the present junta more than thirty days of life, unless it
                    receives strong outside support. He said he expected to see President Herrera
                    tonight to propose Venezuela’s participation in the military assistance effort.
                    If the President agrees and if active military personnel are sent, it will
                    require the approval of the Senate, or at least of the Interim Comision
                    Delegada, which could be time-consuming. On the other hand, a possible
                    alternative might be to locate suitable retired military personnel willing to
                    accept the assignment plus a few selected security people and Copei Party
                    activists. He said he would have to look further into the legal implications. He
                    plans to talk tomorrow to ex-Presidents <persName corresp="#p_BR_3"
                        >Betancourt</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CR_1">Caldera</persName> to
                    assure Herrera bipartisan support. The Venezuelans would be political advisers
                    and intelligence trainers and this latter skill is badly needed, according to
                        <persName corresp="#p_CH_2">Cardozo</persName>, who claimed that the GOS and
                    the Salvadorean Armed Forces have no basic intelligence information about what
                    is happening in the country. <persName corresp="#p_CH_2">Cardozo</persName> said
                    he had to go to Washington on Sunday, February 3 but would hope to get President
                    Herrera’s approval to return by February 7 to take a small hand-picked group to
                    Salvador. Colombia’s contribution (if the <gloss target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss>
                    agrees) would be five or six instructors in the area of counter-guerrilla
                    training. The Ambassador said he plans to go to Bogota to present the proposal
                    to President Turbay and the Foreign Minister on February 8. I urged him to go
                    sooner.</p>
                <p>4. I said we strongly supported the multilateral effort, and explained the
                    importance of other groups going before our <gloss target="#t_MTT_1"
                        >MTT</gloss>.<note n="4" xml:id="d366fn4">See <ref
                            target="frus1977-80v15#d406">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XV, Central
                            America, Document 406</ref>.</note> I <pb facs="1111" n="1070"
                        xml:id="pg_1070"/> said this seemed to me to be the time for the Andean
                    countries, or at least Venezuela and Colombia, to stand up and be counted. The
                    time to do something is now. Both of my interlocutors agreed on the urgency and
                    the broader significance of the Salvadoren struggle. <persName corresp="#p_CH_2"
                        >Cardozo</persName> said all of Central America will be put at risk if
                    Salvador falls to the radicals. He did not think Honduras and Guatemala could
                    long hold out under those circumstances, and the threat to Panama and even Costa
                    Rica would be serious indeed. The Colombian Ambassador agreed.</p>
                <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_CH_2">Cardozo</persName> has promised to brief me
                    tomorrow on the results of his meeting with the President. I detect an air of
                    caution on the part of the Foreign Minister in discussing this matter. He is
                    clearly leaving it to <persName corresp="#p_CH_2">Cardozo</persName> and the
                    President. <persName corresp="#p_CH_2">Cardozo</persName> is seized of the issue
                    and is not inclined to bury his head in the sand. But he has only one more day
                    to persuade Herrera before the Middle East trip. I will work on this tomorrow
                    full day.<note n="5" xml:id="d366fn5">In telegram 1049 from Caracas, February 2,
                            <persName corresp="#p_LWH_1">Luers</persName> reported that <persName
                            corresp="#p_CH_2">Cardozo</persName> had called “to say that he had
                        gotten a green light for his plan from President Herrera,” and that they had
                        “agreed on about 8 or 10 names of trusted active military officers (3 or 4)
                        and civilians (4 to 6). The President has charged his special foreign policy
                        adviser Margarita Palacios to work with <persName corresp="#p_CH_2"
                            >Cardozo</persName> to have a team ready to go to Salvador probably a
                        week from Monday.” (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> Material, Country File, Box 85,
                        Venezuela, 1/79-3/80)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LWH_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Luers</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
