<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>33. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs
                    (Waugh) to the ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">33</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-05-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-05-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec0YIEoMSlyPKAGO" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="general-agreement-on-tariffs-and-trade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001009859"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">GATT</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-05-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-05-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="33"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d33">
                <head>33. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Economic Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_WSC1" type="from">Waugh</persName>) to the <gloss
                        type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d33fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        International Trade Files: Lot 76 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 75,
                        Memoranda to the President, January–June 1955. Secret. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_PMH1">Potter</persName> and concurred in by 10 other offices
                        or bureaus in the Department.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-05-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 26, 1955</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Request for President’s Approval of Results of Tariff Negotiations
                        Involving Japan</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The tariff negotiations for the accession of Japan to <gloss target="#t_GATT1"
                        >GATT</gloss>, which have been in progress since February 21, have been
                    successfully completed. In these negotiations, 17 countries, including the
                    United States, have negotiated reciprocal tariff concessions with Japan. The
                    results of the negotiations, especially as concerns the balance of concessions
                    obtained and granted by the United States, must be approved by the President
                    before the United States negotiators can enter into an agreement embodying the
                    concessions that have been negotiated. If the United States is to sign,
                    Presidential approval must be sought promptly since United States authority
                    under the Trade Agreements Act expires on June 11.</p>
                <pb facs="0149" n="119" xml:id="pg_119"/>
                <p>In an enclosed memorandum from the Acting Chairman of the Interdepartmental
                    Committee on Trade Agreements,<note n="2" xml:id="d33fn2">The Interdepartmental
                        Committee on Trade Agreements, also known as the Trade Agreements Committee
                            (<gloss target="#t_TAC1">TAC</gloss>), was established on June 23, 1934,
                        to make recommendations to the President on trade matters. Its membership
                        included representatives from the Departments of State, Agriculture,
                        Commerce, Interior, Labor, Defense, and the Treasury, the Tariff Commission,
                        and later the International Cooperation Administration.</note> the results
                    of the negotiation are described in detail (Tab B).<note n="3" xml:id="d33fn3"
                        >Not printed. The memorandum, signed by Acting Chairman of the Trade
                        Agreements Committee Woodbury Willoughby, contained individual annexes
                        detailing U.S. and Japanese concessions and third-country negotiations with
                        Japan.</note> A memorandum for your signature transmitting this material to
                    the President is attached (Tab A).<note n="4" xml:id="d33fn4">Not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The negotiation between the United States and Japan, after an initial setback
                    caused by Japanese misunderstanding of the negotiating techniques, proved very
                    substantial and entirely satisfactory. The United States negotiators were able
                    to obtain Japanese tariff bindings or reductions (chiefly the former) on goods
                    of which United States exports to Japan in 1953 were valued at $395 million. In
                    exchange we granted concessions binding or reducing United States tariffs on
                    goods of which imports from Japan were valued in 1953 at $123 million.</p>
                <p>The tariff negotiations between third countries and Japan were considerably less
                    comprehensive than our own, even though we intervened, where feasible, to expand
                    the scope of such negotiations by offering to make up to the third countries
                    compensation Japan could not provide. The decision of the United Kingdom not to
                    participate in the negotiations, taken early last November, made the smaller
                    European countries hesitant to negotiate especially since France took the same
                    attitude. As a result the important <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss>
                    countries reversed an earlier decision and did not negotiate with Japan. The
                    United Kingdom’s later public announcement, in mid-April, that it would not
                    accept <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> rights and obligations with Japan
                    intensified the difficulty. Moreover, since most of the countries that did
                    negotiate have little trade with Japan or buy more from Japan than they sell to
                    it, the possibilities for meaningful tariff concessions were limited.</p>
                <p>A good beginning in helping to expand Japan’s trading opportunities has
                    nevertheless been made in the third country negotiations which cover
                    approximately an additional $13 to $14 million of Japan’s export trade. More
                    importantly, we anticipate that the negotiations will lead to a favorable vote
                    by the two-thirds majority required to bring about Japan’s accession to <gloss
                        target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>. With accession, Japan will be assured the
                    very important benefits of guaranteed <pb facs="0150" n="120" xml:id="pg_120"/>
                    most-favored-nation treatment in all <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>
                    countries except those which exercise their right to refuse <gloss
                        target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> relations with Japan. This achievement alone
                    means success in one of the important economic objectives which the United
                    States has been seeking for Japan.<note n="5" xml:id="d33fn5">Japan became a
                        full member of <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> on August 11, 1955, by
                        unanimous vote of the contracting parties. The text of the “Accession of
                        Japan to the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade” is printed in <hi
                            rend="italic">Basic Instruments and Selected Documents</hi>, Fourth
                        Supplement, p. 33.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That you sign the memorandum (Tab A) to the President transmitting the
                    Committee’s recommendations.<note n="6" xml:id="d33fn6">The memorandum was
                        signed by Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_HHCJ1"
                            >Hoover</persName> on May 30, and the Committee’s recommendations were
                        approved by the President on June 3.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
