<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-11-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-11-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="71" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                    <head>71. Letter From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Economic
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KTV1" type="from">Kalijarvi</persName>) to
                            <persName corresp="#p_HEB1" type="to">Edward B. Hall</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d71fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                            Files, 411.0041/11–956. Limited Official Use. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_KTV1">Kalijarvi</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NCW1">Nichols</persName>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-11-09"><hi rend="italic">November 9,
                            1956</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <gloss target="#t_ED1">ED</gloss></hi>: The
                        enclosed memorandum<note n="2" xml:id="d71fn2">Not printed.</note> sets
                        forth some of our views with respect to the international impact of Public
                        Law 480. It has been prepared in response to your request in connection with
                        your report to the Council on Foreign Economic Policy.</p>
                    <p>In general, our experience with Title I has not been sufficient to permit a
                        definitive evaluation of all aspects of its operation. Sales <pb facs="0235" n="205" xml:id="pg_205"/> agreements have reached a large total in
                        value, but shipments of commodities have experienced a time-lag; and even a
                        longer delay has occurred with respect to loan agreements and the use of
                        foreign currencies.</p>
                    <p>The discernible results of Title I are mixed—some favorable, some
                        unfavorable. On the favorable side, a substantial quantity of commodities
                        has already moved and even larger quantities of surpluses will be moved in
                        the future. Importing countries have an opportunity to secure commodities
                        with minimum expenditure of their own resources. They are able to finance
                        economic development through long-term, low-interest loans. On the
                        unfavorable side, in spite of the restraint exercised by the Department of
                        Agriculture, there is the danger of displacing commercial markets,
                        disrupting prices and discouraging economic production. Title I programs
                        have disturbed our relations with a number of friendly foreign countries
                        exporting the same or competitive products on a commercial basis. It is
                        doubtful that the programs entered into have achieved or are likely to
                        achieve additional consumption which would not otherwise occur. The enclosed
                        memorandum is, for the most part, addressed to Title I.</p>
                    <p>The foreign policy interests of the United States have been well served by
                        Title II and those divisions of Title III which authorize donations to
                        non-profit voluntary agencies and international organizations, but even
                        these programs have been criticized on occasion by exporting countries as
                        interfering with normal marketing.</p>
                    <p>The barter operations under Title III are extremely complicated, and their
                        difficulties are not easily identifiable. In total, these transactions
                        present a danger of encouraging uneconomic production and displacing
                        competitive trade. The barter operations would profit by closer interagency
                        consultation and a more complete coordination of interdepartmental views. It
                        is the view of this Department that the size of the barter program needs to
                        be continued under strict limitations if disorganizations and distortions of
                        production and trade are to be held within manageable bounds.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KTV1"><hi rend="strong">Thorsten V.
                                    Kalijarvi</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d71fn3">Printed
                                from a copy which bears this typed
                        signature.</note></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>