<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-01-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-01-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="160" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d160">
                    <head>160. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_JLA_1">Leslie Janka</persName>
                        of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for
                        National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d160fn1">Source:
                            National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 295, Agency Files, <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>—Vol. IV—1972 [Jan–Oct 1972] [2 of
                            2]. Confidential. All brackets are in the original. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> wrote “<gloss target="#t_OBE_1">OBE</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_HK_1">HK</gloss>” in the top right-hand corner of the
                            memorandum. <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> wrote “Thru
                                <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>” and drew an arrow from
                            it to <persName corresp="#p_JLA_1">Janka</persName>’s name in the “from”
                            line. An unknown hand crossed out “Thru <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>.”</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-01-17">January 17, 1972</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>A <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> Problem</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Frank Shakespeare</persName> has written you an
                        “Eyes Only” memorandum (Tab B) complaining that he cannot respond to your
                        December 17 request<note n="2" xml:id="d160fn2">Attached but not printed. In
                            his December 17, 1971, memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Shakespeare</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> wrote that <persName corresp="#p_LMR_1">Laird</persName> had recommended to the President that the
                            administration “increase its efforts to improve our Allies’
                            understanding of U.S. security policy.” Stating that the President had
                            requested that <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> draft an action
                            plan to increase understanding of the administration’s foreign policy,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> commented: “The
                            plan should be based primarily on <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>
                            resources but should provide for close coordination with State and
                            Defense. <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> resources should be
                            diverted from lower priority programs for this purpose and the plan
                            should indicate the programs to be curtailed as well as new and expanded
                            programs.”</note> for an action plan to increase foreign understanding
                        of U.S. security policy due to the fact that <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>’s management is not provided with a “full understanding of
                        [our] real objectives. . . .”</p>
                    <p>He notes, however, that the basic work on your request has been done and can
                        be made available to you. Since we cannot readily solve his lack of
                        understanding of our security objectives and need for better guidance, the
                        attached response requests <persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Shakespeare</persName> to take his lead from the impending 1972 Foreign
                        Policy Report<note n="3" xml:id="d160fn3">The White House released the third
                            annual foreign policy report, entitled <hi rend="italic">U.S. Foreign
                                Policy for the 1970s: The Emerging Structure of Peace; A report to
                                the Congress by <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Richard
                                    Nixon</persName>, President of the United States, February 9,
                                1972</hi>, on February 9. An excerpt is printed in <ref target="frus1969-76v01#d104"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. I, Foundations of Foreign
                                Policy, 1969–1972, Document 104</ref>. The full text of the report
                            is printed in <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_NP_1">Nixon</persName>, 1972</hi>, pp.
                            194–346.</note> and build upon the work <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> has already done to develop the action plan you requested,
                        although this would prevent <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>’s using
                        the 1972 Report as the launching point for the action program, as was
                        requested.</p>
                    <p>Alternatively, you could meet more directly his problem of isolation from the
                        centers of action by inviting him in for a brief discussion of our broad
                        security objectives, but <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> is probably
                        beyond help on <pb facs="0467" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/> this matter, which
                        is State’s responsibility anyway. Your response makes a courtesy offer of
                        such a meeting.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">RECOMMENDATION:</p>
                    <p>That you sign the memo to <persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Shakespeare</persName>
                        at Tab A.<note n="4" xml:id="d160fn4">Not attached. In the margin below this
                            recommendation, <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> wrote:
                                “<gloss target="#t_HAK_1">HAK</gloss>—you should only discuss w/
                            Frank along w/other problem. Al.” Presumable reference is to an undated
                            memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Shakespeare</persName> to
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> regarding <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> coverage of the President’s trip to
                            China. In it, <persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Shakespeare</persName> noted
                            the capacity of the Voice of America to broadcast in Chinese to China,
                            in addition to the 700 hours broadcast in more than 30 other languages
                            about China to other audiences. As such, he asserted: “It is imperative,
                            therefore, both in terms of credibility for the official information arm
                            of the U.S. Government abroad, and in furtherance of U.S. policy abroad,
                            that a representative of the Voice of America be included in the
                            official party that accompanies the President on this historic journey.”
                            (National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 295, Agency Files, <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss>—Vol. IV—1972 [Jan–Oct 1972] [2 of
                            2])</note></p>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline">
                            <hi rend="strong">Tab B</hi>
                        </note>
                        <head><hi rend="strong"> Memorandum From the Director of the United States
                                Information Agency (<persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Shakespeare</persName>) to the President’s Assistant for
                                National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)</hi><note n="5" xml:id="d160fn5">Eyes
                                Only. <persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Shakespeare</persName> sent the
                                memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                                under an undated handwritten memorandum that reads: “Basic planning
                                work has been done on this matter. It is of course available to you
                                and your staff. However, the attached memo focuses on what I believe
                                to be the real problem. I have <hi rend="italic">not</hi> sent
                                copies to State or Defense. F.”</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-01-14">January 14, 1972</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>This memo is brief since the point to be made is simple, though critical.
                            We can discuss it further if you wish . . . and I hope you do.</p>
                        <p>You inform me that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR_1">Laird</persName> has expressed concern about “serious gaps in the
                            knowledge and understanding of our friends with regard to our foreign
                                <pb facs="0468" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> policy and national
                            security objectives.” Based on extensive travel and contact, I share the
                            Secretary’s concern.</p>
                        <p>You request an “action plan . . . based primarily on <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> resources” to address the situation.
                            I respectfully suggest that to submit an operations plan would really
                            mislead both you and the President as to the central and very serious
                            weakness of our foreign information program. It is not lack of plan; it
                            is lack of knowledge.</p>
                        <p>Full understanding of real objectives . . . both day-to-day and long-term
                            . . . is essential to the creation of effective communications support
                            programs. <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> management is not
                            provided with that understanding, thus the communications support
                            provided to United States foreign policy and national security
                            objectives is much weaker and less imaginative than it should be. No
                            operational action plan will correct that weakness.</p>
                        <p>The problem of poor management information is so overriding and so
                            inhibits our ability to provide the kind of support which the nation
                            deeply needs that it would be unfair to the President to respond in any
                            other way.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_SFJ_1"><persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Frank
                                    Shakespeare</persName><note n="6" xml:id="d160fn6"><persName corresp="#p_SFJ_1">Shakespeare</persName> signed “Frank”
                                    above this typed signature.</note></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>