<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>26. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1917-72PubDipv08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recb6XG1ZU9Ik84CR" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Broadcasting</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001184"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Magazine</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="26"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                <head>26. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>) to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NP_1">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d26fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 306,
                        Agency Files, Voice of America. Confidential. Sent for information. A
                        stamped notation on the memorandum indicates that the President saw it. An
                        unknown hand wrote “ret 7/2” below the stamped notation. Another unknown
                        hand wrote “<gloss target="#t_AH_1">AH</gloss>—NOTE PAGE 3” at the top of
                        the memorandum. <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> sent a copy of
                        the memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName> under a
                        July 3 memorandum, which read: “Attached is a copy of the memorandum you
                        prepared for the President dealing with Soviet jamming activities. Please
                        destroy this as I am sure Henry would be upset if he thought it had been
                        sent out of the office. Unfortunately we have a monkey which we must be
                        prepared to deal with. Please analyze the President’s instruction and see if
                        we can develop an appropriate plan which would be responsive to it, if only
                        in part, and prepare a memorandum for the President for approval. As you
                        know, this is a Pandora’s box which could work to our disadvantage. On the
                        other hand, if we were to convey the President’s decision directly to State
                        it would probably leak with serious damage to the President. Please scratch
                        your noggin on this one and give me your ideas.” (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-06-30">June 30, 1969</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Soviet Jamming of the Voice of America and our Response</item>
                </list>
                <p>This is in response to your request through <persName corresp="#p_BAP_1">Alex
                        Butterfield</persName> of June 23 which asked for a brief report of U.S.
                    reactions to increased Soviet jamming of Voice of America broadcasts.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d26fn2">In a June 23 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BAP_1"
                            >Butterfield</persName> wrote: “In the June 18 ‘Staff and Department
                        Brief’ the President read of the Soviet Union’s recently intensified jamming
                        efforts directed at Voice of America broadcasts. He would like a short
                        report from you concerning the reaction on <hi rend="italic">our</hi> part.”
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Soviet jamming of Voice of America (<gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>)
                    broadcasts, which had been a fixture of the Cold War scene, ceased abruptly on
                    June 19, 1963. For just over five years the <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>
                    reached Soviet audiences with minimal interference. Then on August 21, 1968, at
                    the time of the Warsaw Pact invasion of Czechoslovakia,<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d26fn3">See <ref target="#d1fn3">footnote 3, Document
                        1</ref>.</note> the Soviets resumed systematic jamming which has continued
                    up to the present.</p>
                <p>It is difficult to prove categorically that Soviet electronic interference
                    “recently intensified,” in part because of the practical impossibility of
                    accurately measuring reception of <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> programs
                    in all parts of the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, and in part because
                    of the use of differing types of jamming.</p>
                <p>At least for the area of Moscow, where—because of the presence of the American
                    Embassy—we are able to get regular reports on <gloss target="#t_VOA_1"
                        >VOA</gloss> reception, the Soviet jamming effort appears to have become
                    less selective and more continuous in recent months. A rough estimate would be
                    that 80–85% of the 13 hours per day of <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>
                    programs beamed to <pb facs="0107" n="55" xml:id="pg_55"/> the Moscow area
                    (central European Russia) are now subject to a significant level of purposeful
                    interference.</p>
                <p>It is harder to give an estimate for outlying areas, where U.S. travel is
                    relatively less frequent, and travel by technical personnel capable of making
                    accurate measurements is quite rare. But certainly there is less jamming in
                    peripheral areas than in and around Moscow. For some reason, for example, we
                    know of no attempt to block <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> programs in the
                    Baltic languages (Lithuanian, Latvian, and Estonian). However, all other
                    non-Russian broadcasts to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> have been
                    targets for jamming along with our Russian programming.</p>
                <p>The jamming has taken various forms. Our programming in the 25 meter band and
                    above is generally blocked by superimposition of a strong local Soviet station
                    (Radio “Mayak,” which means “beacon”), broadcasting light popular music,
                    commentary, and news. Below the 25 meter band, <gloss target="#t_VOA_1"
                        >VOA</gloss> broadcasts are generally subject to the traditional, harshly
                    unpleasant electronic buzz of the jammer.</p>
                <p>We made an early diplomatic protest, but have taken no action since, in large
                    part because we have expected that the jamming would be stopped after the
                    reconsolidation of the Soviet position in Czechoslovakia. On September 19, 1968,
                    roughly one month after jamming was resumed, then Under Secretary of State for
                    Political Affairs <persName corresp="#p_BCE_1">Charles Bohlen</persName> gave
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1">Dobrynin</persName> an aide-memoire
                    protesting the Soviet interference as a violation of the International
                    Telecommunications Union (<gloss target="#t_ITU_1">ITU</gloss>) Convention of
                        1965.<note n="4" xml:id="d26fn4">The Plenipotentiary Conference of the
                        International Telecommunication Union (<gloss target="#t_ITU_1">ITU</gloss>)
                        took place in Montreaux September 14–November 12, 1965. Members of the Union
                        approved the International Telecommunication Convention, which entered into
                        force on January 1, 1967. For the text of the Convention and additional
                        documents, see <hi rend="italic">International Telecommunication Convention;
                            Final Protocol to the Convention; Additional Protocols to the
                            Convention; Resolutions, Recommendation and Opinion, Montreaux,
                            1965</hi>. (Geneva: General Secretariat of the International
                        Telecommunication Union, n.d.) For <persName corresp="#p_BCE_1"
                            >Bohlen</persName>’s meeting with <persName corresp="#p_DAF_1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName>, see <ref target="frus1964-68v14#d302fn2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. XIV, Soviet
                            Union, footnote 2, Document 302</ref>.</note> On October 9, 1968 the
                    Soviet Embassy delivered a note to the State Department categorically rejecting
                    our protest.</p>
                <p>Since then various American officials have made informal protests to their Soviet
                    counterparts on the jamming question both here and in Moscow, but no further
                    formal action has been taken. As recently as June 18 the Assistant Director of
                        <gloss target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> for Soviet Union and Eastern Europe
                    raised the matter in a conversation with the Soviet Press Counselor, Soviet
                    Cultural Counselor, and the Managing Editor of the magazine <hi rend="italic"
                        >Soviet Life.</hi>
                    <note n="5" xml:id="d26fn5">Reference is to the bi-monthly magazine of Soviet
                        culture and history, which began publication in the 1950s.</note> The
                    Soviets gave evidence of being embarrassed by <pb facs="0108" n="56"
                        xml:id="pg_56"/> the jamming and reacted defensively; one muttered that
                    “this sort of thing reflects special circumstances.” The <gloss
                        target="#t_USIA_1">USIA</gloss> officer got the impression that the time
                    might be ripe for a new diplomatic démarche on the subject.</p>
                <p>We have other options as well. We might raise the Soviet jamming formally through
                        <gloss target="#t_ITU_1">ITU</gloss> channels, but the practical effect
                    would probably be only to increase publicity. Much the same could be said of the
                    suggestion of bringing the matter to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Our ultimate—and I think undesirable—option would be to retaliate in kind by
                    reactivating a powerful long wave <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>
                    transmitter near Munich, Germany, which when used, effectively blocks out Moscow
                    Radio broadcasts to Eastern Europe. Our use of this transmitter caused the
                    Soviets to protest through the <gloss target="#t_ITU_1">ITU</gloss> several
                    years ago and we ceased operations, but the equipment is still in place.</p>
                <p>My personal opinion is that the jamming has probably outlasted its usefulness
                    even in Soviet eyes, but once this sort of thing is set in motion, it is
                    difficult bureaucratically to stop it, unless the order comes from the very top.
                    The jamming is of course indefensible and contradicts the Soviet assertion that
                    they favor increased exchanges of information. I think that if we make real
                    progress on preparations for <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>, we should
                    point out the incompatibility of their continued jamming with U.S.-Soviet
                    cooperation on disarmament.<note n="6" xml:id="d26fn6">In the margin below this
                        paragraph, the President wrote: “K Our response has been <hi rend="italic"
                            >typically</hi> much too soft—I want a protest filed—strong, soon, &amp;
                        hard. <gloss target="#t_RN_1">RN</gloss>.”</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
