<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-12-04T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-12-04T05:00:00-05:00" n="1020" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1020">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">693.002/415: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-12-04T19:00:00+09:00">December 4, 1937—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received December 4—2:57 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>594. 1. My British colleague yesterday addressed to the Minister for
                            Foreign Affairs an informal letter dated December 2nd concerning the
                            Chinese Customs as follows: <pb facs="0903" n="896" xml:id="pg_896"/>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“My Dear Minister, I venture to enclose, for your confidential
                                    information, an extract from a telegram which I have just
                                    received from Shanghai reporting a conversation which took place
                                    on the 30th ultimo between Mr. Okamoto, Mr. Phillips, the
                                    British Consul General at Shanghai, and Mr. Hall-Patch, the
                                    British Financial Adviser, on the subject of the Shanghai
                                    Customs.</p>
                                <p>I should like to draw attention particularly to Mr. Okamoto’s
                                    statement that he could only discuss the customs question with
                                    representatives of the foreign powers ‘when he had come to an
                                    agreement with Mr. Lawford as to the control which Japan wished
                                    to exercise’. Mr. Okamoto added ‘he had already told Mr. Lawford
                                    to deposit with the Yokohama Specie Bank’.</p>
                                <p>I had understood from my last conversation with Your Excellency
                                    that Mr. Okamoto would be instructed to ascertain the views of
                                    the British representatives before he reached any agreement with
                                    the Shanghai Commissioner of Customs, and it was therefore very
                                    disappointing to me to find that on November 30th Mr. Okamoto
                                    was still holding the language ascribed to him in this telegram.
                                    Possibly revised instructions may have reached him since then,
                                    but I can not too strongly urge upon Your Excellency the
                                    desirability of taking no action vis-à-vis of the Customs
                                    Commissioner until an understanding on this matter has been
                                    reached with the representatives of the interested powers.</p>
                                <p>I feel I must take very special exception to Mr. Okamoto’s
                                    proposal that the revenues should be deposited with the Yokohama
                                    Specie Bank as a condition precedent to any discussion with
                                    representatives of the interested powers.</p>
                                <p>The need for the exertion of pressure on the customs officials is
                                    all the less apparent in that I understand that the latter are
                                    ready to give full guarantees that, pending asettlement no part
                                    of the revenue will be allowed to reach any authority of the
                                    Chinese Government.</p>
                                <p>As I am anxious not to leave my Government under any
                                    misapprehension as to the attitude of the Japanese Government in
                                    this matter, I should be very grateful if you would let me know
                                    whether Mr. Okamoto has now been instructed that no arrangement
                                    should be reached with the customs administration on any form of
                                    ‘control’ without full prior consultation with the British,
                                    United States and French representatives in Shanghai.</p>
                                <p>Believe me, my dear Minister, yours very sincerely, R. L.
                                    Craigie.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>2. Craigie considers the situation critical and fears that such pressure
                            will be brought to bear on Lawford that he will accede to the Japanese
                            demands and that we shall then be faced with a <hi rend="italic">fait
                                accompli</hi> as we were at Tientsin. He feels that there would be
                            no serious objection to agreeing to the deposit of the customs funds in
                            the Yokohama Specie Bank provided that the Japanese first guarantee (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) control of the funds by an international
                            committee of bankers and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the service of loans
                            as a first lien on the deposits. He understands that Okamoto is now
                            discussing the matter with Gauss and <pb facs="0904" n="897" xml:id="pg_897"/> feels that unless the latter takes a strong stand
                            “we shall lose the game”.</p>
                        <p>3. Craigie has written me inquiring whether I feel disposed to make
                            supplementary representations to the Minister for Foreign Affairs along
                            the lines of the last paragraph of his letter. He feels that unless we
                            continue to act in concert it will be interpreted as weakness here. My
                            representations on November 26 and 28 were as forceful and complete as
                            possible but I see no objection to addressing a further letter to Hirota
                            if the Department considers the step desirable. I have no doubt but that
                            Gauss is taking as strong a stand as his instructions and good judgment
                            warrant.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to Shanghai.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>