<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-07-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-07-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="112" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">893.0146/549</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Chief of the
                                    Division of Far Eastern Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hamilton</hi>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-07-10">July 10,
                                    1937</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Conversation:</cell>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. H. H. Kung, Chinese Minister of
                                        Finance;</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. C. T. Wang, Chinese
                                        Ambassador;</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Hornbeck;</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Hamilton.</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Present:</cell>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. P. W. Kuo and Dr. Clarence K.
                                            Young.<note n="56" xml:id="d112fn56">Advisers of Dr.
                                            Kung.</note></cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>During the course of and following a luncheon given by the Chinese
                                Ambassador at his residence at Twin Oaks, the Chinese Minister of
                                Finance, Dr. H. H. Kung, referred to the fighting which had occurred
                                at Wanpinghsien and asked what information the Department had
                                received in regard thereto. In reply Mr. Hornbeck gave a brief
                                outline of the information which we had received. Dr. Kung then said
                                that the fighting was due to aggression on the part of the Japanese
                                and that Japanese troops had no right to be in the place where the
                                fighting occurred, even under the terms of the Boxer Protocol of
                                    1901.<note n="57" xml:id="d112fn57">Signed at Peking, September
                                    7, 1901, <ref target="frus1901China#pg_312"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1901, Appendix (Affairs in
                                        China), p. 312</ref>.</note> Dr. Kung then proceeded to say
                                that in 1901 the Chinese Government had agreed to the terms of the
                                Boxer Protocol which <pb facs="0140" n="133" xml:id="pg_133"/>
                                provided that foreign governments might maintain at Peiping and at
                                certain other points foreign armed forces for the purpose of
                                protecting their legations at Peiping and to maintain open
                                communication between Peiping and the sea; that the foreign
                                governments had now moved their diplomatic establishments from
                                Peiping to Nanking; and that therefore there was no longer warrant
                                for the maintenance by foreign governments of their foreign armed
                                forces at Peiping. The Chinese Ambassador intimated that in his
                                opinion the Chinese Government should endeavor to cause foreign
                                governments to withdraw their armed forces which were stationed in
                                North China by virtue of the provisions of the Boxer Protocol.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Hornbeck said that if the Chinese Government wished to raise the
                                question with the American Government, the Chinese Government could
                                probably cause the American Government to withdraw its armed forces
                                from Peiping. He said that the Chinese Government might perhaps also
                                cause the British Government and possibly one or two other
                                governments to do likewise. He then asked the question: would Dr.
                                Kung wish to have the American armed forces withdrawn. Dr. Kung
                                immediately and emphatically replied that he did not, unless such
                                withdrawal would be concurrent with withdrawal by all the other
                                governments of their armed forces. He stated that the President had
                                asked him that question and that he had made to the President the
                                same reply.</p>
                            <p>The Chinese Ambassador said that he believed that where there was a
                                question of principle involved the Chinese Government should press
                                for the carrying out of that principle; and he intimated, although
                                he did not expressly so state, that, even should Japan not be
                                willing to withdraw its armed forces, a useful purpose might be
                                served if all the other governments were to withdraw their armed
                                forces. Mr. Hornbeck then raised the question: what would be the
                                situation should all governments, including the Japanese, withdraw
                                their armed forces from Peiping (and Tientsin). Dr. Kung and Dr.
                                Wang made no express reply to this question but Dr. Kung reiterated
                                that he was of the opinion that withdrawal by the American
                                Government of its armed forces should be contingent upon concurrent
                                action by all the other interested governments. In reply to a
                                further express question, both Dr. Kung and Dr. Wang said that the
                                Chinese were not bothered by the presence of American armed forces
                                in North China.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Hornbeck then commented at considerable length to the effect that
                                during the last few years the Chinese Government had made
                                substantial progress in many fields; that people who returned from
                                China today were almost unanimous in giving glowing accounts of the
                                constructive activities of the Chinese Government and people; that
                                progress was being made toward unifying China, in finance, in road
                                building, <pb facs="0141" n="134" xml:id="pg_134"/> in railway
                                construction, etc.; and that, in general, things in China seemed to
                                be going along extraordinarily well. He said that of course, as Dr.
                                Kung and Dr. Wang both realized, the task of reconstruction in China
                                was not yet completed and there were still many difficulties to
                                overcome. He said that in view of the situation wherein China was
                                making measurable progress in so many lines and wherein things were
                                getting along so well, would it not be advisable for China to
                                continue along this course of concentrating its attention and
                                energies upon reconstructive effort rather than for China to start
                                arguments with foreign governments; was not it advisable that China
                                pursue its program of reconstruction to such a point that when China
                                chose to raise any question with foreign governments, China would
                                have attained such progress and be in such a strong position that
                                the foreign governments so approached would readily listen to the
                                Chinese Government’s proposals.</p>
                            <p>Dr. Kung said that he realized the force of Mr. Hornbeck’s remarks
                                but that although China itself was preparing for what he felt was an
                                inevitable war with Japan, Japan was also preparing militarily, and
                                he felt that with the passage of each year Japan would become as
                                compared with China comparatively stronger. Mr. Hamilton said that
                                his view differed somewhat from this: that in his opinion what China
                                was doing in the way of effort toward internal construction and
                                building up the strength of the nation and the government was in
                                general on the constructive side, whereas he felt that many of the
                                lines along which the Japanese Government and the Japanese nation
                                were expending their energies were not constructive but were placing
                                additional strains—and weakening strains—upon the government and
                                people of Japan. Mr. Hornbeck said that he concurred in this view.
                                (Mr. Kuo indicated his concurrence.)</p>
                            <p>Dr. Wang and Dr. Kung both suggested that because of Japan’s
                                imperialistic and aggressive characteristics, it was important that
                                the United States help China. They said that some day the United
                                States would have to face Japanese aggression, unless that
                                aggression should be checked by China. Mr. Hornbeck said that the
                                United States had always been in favor of a strong, unified China.
                                He pointed out, however, that the United States did not adopt
                                certain policies or pursue certain courses toward China just for the
                                sake of helping China. He said that our policies and our attitude
                                were based upon our conception of the interests of the United
                                States, just as China’s policies and China’s attitude and the
                                policies and attitude of any other country were based upon national
                                conceptions of national interests. He said that it was fortunate for
                                us and for China that our policies and our attitude in regard to
                                China coincided with China’s own desire to build up a stable and a
                                strong nation.</p>
                            <pb facs="0142" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/>
                            <p>At several points during the conversation the Chinese Ambassador gave
                                evidence of his continued belief in the adoption of the tactics of a
                                revolutionary. He cited his own experience in connection with the
                                1911 revolution in China and stated that had a small group of
                                revolutionaries not then taken the action they did, the Republic of
                                China would not have been established, at least not at that time.
                                Mr. Hamilton commented that it seemed to him there was a definite
                                distinction between the adoption by an individual of a revolutionary
                                attitude toward a question internal to his own country and the
                                adoption by a government of revolutionary tactics which might lead
                                to war; that a person engaging in revolutionary activity in his own
                                country could, if the revolution proved unsuccessful, either flee or
                                at most lose his life. On the other hand, if persons in responsible
                                control of governmental affairs engaged in revolutionary tactics
                                which brought on war, there could be no running away by a country
                                from that war and the whole country would have to stand the
                                consequences of the war. Mr. Hamilton said that to him it therefore
                                seemed highly advisable that persons in responsible government
                                positions proceed with greater circumspection than need be observed
                                by persons not so placed. Mr. Hornbeck said that it seemed to him
                                incumbent upon persons in authority to endeavor to take the long
                                view and to estimate carefully every possible important contingency
                                and consequence which might result from any contemplated course.</p>
                            <p>Dr. Kung mentioned again that when he saw the President the President
                                had asked him whether he would like to have American forces
                                withdrawn from Peiping, and Dr. Kung stated again that he had
                                informed the President that he was not in favor of the withdrawal of
                                the American forces alone but that he was in favor only of a
                                concurrent withdrawal of all foreign armed forces.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Hornbeck complimented Dr. Kung upon his realistic approach to the
                                questions under discussion affecting China.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>