<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Counselor of Embassy in China ( (Peck) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-07-19T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-07-19T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-07-19T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-07-19T13:00:00-05:00" n="209"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d209">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/8865: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Peck</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-07-20T02:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 20, 1937—2 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 6:40 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>302. Our 301, July 19, 7 p.m.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> was delivered by a
                        subordinate official to the Japanese Counsellor of Embassy July 19, 3 p.m.,
                        and the latter regarded it as unsatisfactory because it did not deal
                        specifically with the July 11 agreement. He asked whether it was intended as
                        an answer to the Japanese <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of July 17 and
                        the bearer could not reply. According to the report the Counsellor asserted
                        his conviction that the document would not be accepted by his Government as
                        adequate and he would be willing to see the Minister for Foreign Affairs
                        before midnight to receive further oral assurances and would hold the
                        document in the meantime. On receiving this message the Minister for Foreign
                        Affairs said he would be away all day but would see the Counsellor July 20,
                        8 a.m., which appointment the Counsellor accepted.</item>
                    <pb facs="0221" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>At half past 10 the British Ambassador suggested that I call and told me
                        he had seen the Minister for Foreign Affairs that afternoon and was informed
                        of the gist of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>. He was favorably
                        impressed thinking it dignified, reasonable and conciliatory but when he
                        read the text as released he saw clearly it would not satisfy the Japanese.
                        The Ambassador said incidentally the section outlining possible methods of
                        settling the dispute embodied suggestions made by him informally to the
                        Minister for Foreign Affairs some days ago. He said the Minister showed
                        distinct signs of the strain he has been under in making a decision which we
                        both agreed threatens to involve China either in internal dissension or
                        war.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Our conversation took place in the British Embassy chancery. Shortly after
                        11 the Japanese Counsellor called by appointment and discussed the situation
                        with the Ambassador for more than one hour in his residence. The Ambassador
                        subsequently told me that he pointed out to the Counsellor that the Minister
                        for Foreign Affairs could not reasonably be expected to accept the July 11
                        agreement since he was aware neither of its contents nor implications. The
                        Ambassador urged that the agreement be fully explained to the Minister for
                        Foreign Affairs of [<hi rend="italic">at?</hi>] the forthcoming interview
                        and that the Counsellor take into consideration the difficulties confronting
                        the Minister. He intimated that upon the effort of the Counsellor to
                        straighten out this point which in itself was of trivial importance might
                        hang the issue of peace or war. The Counsellor admitted the force of these
                        arguments in part but insisted that the Japanese point of view must be
                        considered.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Ambassador and I fear that the Japanese military will force events in
                        the North and that the conversations in Nanking will be of no effect unless
                        the Chinese Government surrenders unconditionally. He stated he has
                        discussed the matter in a frank and common sense manner with the Minister
                        for Foreign Affairs and a [<hi rend="italic">the?</hi>] Japanese Counsellor
                        at their desire separately several times hoping for a compromise. He has
                        scrupulously avoided delivering messages and everything that might hint of
                        mediation. He has also courteously kept me informed for the benefit of the
                        American Ambassador and the Department.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The Chinese Foreign Office at midnight issued an account of a conversation
                        July 19, 1 p.m. between the Minister of War and the Japanese Military
                        Attaché. The Military Attaché is reported as intimating that failure to
                        withdraw “Central Government troops” from Hopei might result in bringing the
                        crisis to its final stage. To this the Minister of War is reported as saying
                            <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi> that the sending of troops as a
                        precautionary measure had been necessitated by the large <pb facs="0222"
                            n="215" xml:id="pg_215"/> increase in the Japanese forces. He asserted
                        China’s right to move troops in its own territory but intimated that
                        withdrawal of additional forces by Japan from Hopei might lead China to
                        consider similar action.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Sent to Peiping, Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Peck</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
