<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-07-19T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-07-19T21:00:00-05:00" n="210" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d210">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/8867: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in China</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Peck</hi></persName>)
                                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-07-20T10:00:00+08:00">July 20, 1937—10
                                        a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 12:05 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>304. 1. The Foreign Office unofficially “for information” issued the
                                following statement to the press last night: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“That military precautions taken by the Chinese Government
                                        are for no other purpose than self defense was emphasized by
                                        General Ho Ying Chin, Minister of War, in a talk with Major
                                        General Seirehe [<hi rend="italic">Seiichi</hi>] Kita,
                                        Japanese Military Attaché, this afternoon.</p>
                                    <p>Calling on the War Minister at 4 o’clock p.m., Major General
                                        Kita asked for the withdrawal of ‘Central Government troops’
                                        from Hopei. He intimated that failure to comply with the
                                        request may result in the aggravation of the Sino-Japanese
                                        crisis which ‘is rapidly approaching the final state’.</p>
                                    <p>General Ho told the Japanese visitor that the present tension
                                        in the north was entirely due to Japanese sending large
                                        military and air forces to Hopei since the outbreak of the
                                        Lukouchiao incident.</p>
                                    <p>The War Minister reiterated China’s desire for a peaceful
                                        settlement as well as her intention not to aggravate the
                                        situation, but declared that precautionary measures were
                                        rendered necessary on account of the dispatch of large
                                        numbers of Japanese troops to North China.</p>
                                    <p>These measures, General Ho emphasized, were purely for self
                                        defense and were without the least intent at provocation.
                                        General Ho said that all units of the Chinese Army were
                                        National forces and that there never was any distinction
                                        between ‘Central Government’ and ‘non-Central Government’
                                        troops.</p>
                                    <p>While defending China’s inalienable rights to have [<hi rend="italic">move</hi>] her troops within her own
                                        territory, General Ho intimated, however, that if Japan
                                        withdraws her newly increased forces from Hopei the Chinese
                                        Government would consider making a similar move.</p>
                                    <p>In conclusion, General Ho reminded the Japanese Military
                                        Attaché that whether or not the North China situation would
                                        be further aggravated depended solely upon the attitude of
                                        Japan”.</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>2. Sent to the Department and Peiping.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Peck</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>