<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern Affairs (
                    (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d403</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">403</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recZobsyHhwdJPklD" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085246"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Occupied territory</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="403"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/9487</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Far Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-10">August 10,
                            1937</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I perceive no basis whatever for an expectation and no foundation for even a hope
                    that considerations of finance (cost of fighting and inability or unwillingness
                    on the part of the people of Japan to pay the bills) will substantially
                    influence such decision as the Japanese may make “to fight or not to fight” in
                    connection with the present phase of their movement of expansion.</p>
                <pb facs="0379" n="372" xml:id="pg_372"/>
                <p>The Japanese decision will be made by the armed forces; not by the diplomats, the
                    bankers and the business men; least of all by the best informed and most
                    conservative members of the so-called “moderate” (conservative) small minority.
                    Japan is expanding and the Japanese people are almost a unit in the belief that
                    their expansion is a natural, a rightful, even a righteous, a practicable, a
                    possible, and an inevitable phenomenon.</p>
                <p>It must be remembered that Japan has not at any time in recorded history been
                    defeated in a war with a foreign country; that in all of her major military
                    efforts against foreign armed forces during recent decades Japan has been
                    victorious; that the Japanese have today every reason to believe that the only
                    foreign armed forces with whom they will have to deal are those of China; that
                    they know that the Chinese are hopelessly vulnerable because they possess no
                    Navy; that Japan can set for herself such limitations as she may choose to make
                    for the extent of the military operations, it being possible always for the
                    Japanese, in the event of unexpectedly strong resistance on the part of the
                    Chinese, to fall back on shortened lines or even to withdraw entirely from newly
                    occupied territory.</p>
                <p>It must be remembered that, whereas, in the World War, many other powers made
                    great expenditures of men and money, with consequent impairment of their man
                    power and their financial positions, Japan did no such thing; on the contrary,
                    Japan lost almost no men and added considerable increments to her national
                    wealth during the War. Such expenditures as other powers were able to make then
                    without collapse, Japan is able to make now. True, Japan is, as compared with
                    several of the occidental powers, a poor country; but, Japan is, as compared
                    with China, a nationally affluent country; the Japanese will, in my opinion,
                    neither be deterred from fighting China by financial considerations nor, if the
                    two countries fight, find herself hamstrung and compelled to forego her
                    objectives in consequence of financial exhaustion.</p>
                <p>In making the above statements, I am not undertaking to prophesy, for many other
                    factors may enter into the making of Japan’s decision. I merely wish to express
                    emphatically the opinion which is mine that the financial factor alone will play
                    little part in the matter.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
