<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Second Secretary of Legation in Canada (
                    (Key))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d444</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">444</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-08-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="444"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d444">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/9509</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Second Secretary of
                        Legation in Canada</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Key</hi>)<note n="97"
                        xml:id="d444fn97">Copy transmitted to the Department by the Minister in
                        Canada in his despatch No. 1553, August 17; received August 19.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ottawa</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-13">August 13,
                            1937</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">[Present:]</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Sir Robert Craigie (British Ambassador to
                            Tokyo)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Armour (Minister)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Key (Second Secretary of Legation)</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Following an informal luncheon given for Sir Robert and Lady Craigie at the
                    Legation on August 13, 1937, Sir Robert, the Minister and Mr. Key, Second
                    Secretary of Legation, retired to the library where the following conversation
                    ensued.</p>
                <p>At the outset, Sir Robert expressed his regret that he had been unable to go to
                    Washington for a talk with State Department officials en route to his new post,
                    but explained that there had been two reasons for this.</p>
                <p>In the first place, he was somewhat pressed for time. In the second place, he
                    felt that his presence in Washington at this particular time would probably have
                    given rise to misapprehension on the part of the Japanese: the latter might
                    think that his purpose in coming to Washington was to hatch some scheme for
                    concerted Anglo-American action against the Japanese. It was particularly in
                    order to avoid creating any such unwarranted suspicions, on the part of the
                    Japanese, that he had decided against proceeding to Washington. He added that he
                    would be grateful if the reasons for his failure to come to Washington were made
                    known to the Department should the Minister shortly be communicating to
                    Washington. The Minister stated that he shared Sir Robert’s views about the
                    desirability of not stirring up Japanese susceptibilities unnecessarily and
                    would be glad to inform the Department of what Sir Robert had told him.</p>
                <pb facs="0409" n="402" xml:id="pg_402"/>
                <p>Turning to the general outlook in the Far East, Sir Robert felt that it was
                    indeed gloomy. Until recently, his government had felt that, what he termed, the
                    “civilian” and moderate groups in Japan had been making steady progress and that
                    a more tolerant attitude towards China was being created: Japanese public
                    opinion was more and more coming around to the view that peaceful methods of
                    composing Sino-Japanese differences must be sought. Notwithstanding the ever
                    present danger of assassination, civilian leaders had become increasingly bold
                    in their utterances and actions. This changed situation had so alarmed Japanese
                    military groups that they had felt impelled to put a stop to it, hence the
                    present military adventures in China. The present war fever in Japan and the
                    strong public support now being given the militarists showed that, for the
                    present at least, the latter had regained the upper hand. The possibility of
                    large scale military operations by Japanese groups in China was now
                    unfortunately very real: civilian and moderate groups in Japan were apparently
                    powerless to stem the rising tide of feeling against China. The only hope was
                    that the general situation would soon improve and that the Chinese would have
                    the good sense not further to provoke the Japanese.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, it was more important than ever before to do everything possible to
                    strengthen the hands of the civilian and moderate groups in Japan. Undoubtedly
                    there were large and influential groups in Japan which were out of sympathy with
                    present Japanese policy towards China. The present military adventure was
                    costing a lot of money: soon it would be reflected in increased taxation. When
                    you touch a man’s pocketbook you touch him in a sensitive spot: further taxes
                    piled on top of the already exhorbitant taxes now levied in Japan eventually
                    could create only further unfavorable reaction to the Japanese military.
                    Although the outlook was grave and no one could foretell what would be the
                    outcome of the present military operations in China it was not unlikely that, in
                    the long run, the <hi rend="italic">intransigeance</hi> of the Japanese military
                    would serve in the end to weaken them further politically.</p>
                <p>Sir Robert expressed the view that one sure way of strengthening the hands of the
                    civilian and moderate groups in Japan was for Great Britain and the United
                    States to refrain from exerting any joint or concerted action against the
                    Japanese Government. The moment that the Japanese military could rightly claim
                    that joint Anglo-American pressure was being brought to bear on Japan, Japanese
                    public opinion would solidify in support of the military. It was therefore of
                    the utmost importance that the British and American Governments avoid the
                    possibility of giving the Japanese military even the pretext for asserting such
                    a claim. He felt it unnecessary to say that the British and Americans should
                    keep each <pb facs="0410" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/> other fully informed as to
                    what policies they would pursue and were pursuing in the Far East, but whatever
                    action might result from these policies should be taken independently. Probably
                    any steps taken would be more or less identical since both Governments view the
                    situation along the same general lines, but under no conditions should the
                    Japanese be given grounds for the belief that the British and American
                    Governments were in league against them.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, in Sir Robert’s opinion, it was extremely important that the
                    Japanese Government and more particularly the Japanese military, be made to
                    understand, beyond any doubt, that the British and American Governments hold
                    common views on Far Eastern policies. Let there be nothing to make the Japanese
                    militarists think that there was even the possibility of a rift in
                    Anglo-American relations. Sir Robert stated that in the Foreign Office there had
                    been an important and influential group which held the view that the chief hope
                    of curbing the Japanese lay in joint Anglo-American action. He had not
                    subscribed to this belief himself and felt therefore that the attitude of the
                    American Government in discouraging joint action had been most “wise”: the
                    Japanese knew perfectly well that neither in Great Britain nor the United States
                    was there any considerable group which was willing to say to Japan “you may go
                    thus far, but no further”. This had been the fundamental weakness of the
                    so-called Stimson policy. Furthermore, threats, whether or not they contained an
                    element of bluff, would only weaken the hands of the civilian and moderate
                    groups in Japan. He remarked laughingly that perhaps he should not have
                    expressed his views so frankly, as some of them ran somewhat contrary to those
                    held at the Foreign Office.</p>
                <p>Sir Robert then went on to say that it ought to be comparatively easy to adjust
                    Sino-Japanese economic relations: strictly from an economic viewpoint,
                    conditions were nearly ideal for a <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi>. Japan
                    was primarily industrial while China was essentially agricultural, thus making
                    the economics of the two countries complementary. Each was dependent on the
                    other and if only a peaceful era in their political relations could be ushered
                    in it would be to their great mutual advantage.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, even the Japanese militarists recognized Japan’s dependence on
                    China. They admitted that if Japan were to become embroiled in a war with Russia
                    it was vital for the former that China remain neutral. Nevertheless the military
                    elements in Japan were so shortsighted as constantly to aggravate the Chinese
                    and thus to make it almost certain that China would cast in her lot with the
                    U.S.S.R. in the event of a Russo-Japanese war.</p>
                <p>The Minister asked Sir Robert for his opinion as to how real was the fear in
                    Japan of the Soviet air force and particularly the important Soviet aviation
                    elements said to be concentrated in and near <pb facs="0411" n="404"
                        xml:id="pg_404"/> Vladivostok, which it has been claimed could, if required,
                    easily fly to Japan, bomb many of the leading Japanese industrial centres and
                    return to their base. Sir Robert stated that in his opinion the Japanese
                    believed it inevitable that sooner or later they would have to square their
                    accounts with the U.S.S.R. There had been considerable uneasiness in Japan about
                    the Soviet air force, but the recent purges in the U.S.S.R. had considerably
                    lessened this fear, at least among the Japanese military. The latter apparently
                    felt that the wholesale executions which had been taking place in Russia during
                    recent months had more or less disrupted the Soviet Army because so many of
                    their leading generals had been put to death. This situation was no doubt one of
                    the contributing factors to the decision of the Japanese military to undertake
                    the present adventure in China.</p>
                <p>In closing, Sir Robert stated that he was looking forward with pleasure to
                    renewing his acquaintance with Mr. Grew, with whom he had been <hi rend="italic"
                        >en poste</hi> in Berne during the World War and of whom he entertained a
                    very high opinion. The Minister stated that he felt sure that Sir Robert would
                    find Mr. Grew unusually well informed on current affairs in Japan and that he
                    was equally sure that he would find him at all times ready and willing to
                    cooperate fully.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
