<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-14T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-14T01:00:00-05:00" n="451" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d451">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/9357: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-14T15:00:00+09:00">August 14, 1937—3
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received August 14—9 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>266. 1. With respect to the press reports of the naval bombardment
                                yesterday at Shanghai, a naval informant stated to the Naval
                                    Attaché<note n="3" xml:id="d451fn3">Commander Harvey M.
                                    Bemis.</note> that as several Japanese Yangtze River gunboats
                                were leaving for a down river rendezvous yesterday afternoon they
                                were fired on from shore a few miles below Shanghai. The fire was
                                returned and the ships proceeded down river.</p>
                            <p>2. As regards blocking of the Whangpoo: two Chinese steamers and
                                several large junks were sunk by the Chinese above the naval
                                anchorage, apparently to prevent Japanese gunboats proceeding up
                                river to capture Chinese gunboats undergoing overhaul at the
                                Shanghai Whangpoo dockyard.</p>
                            <p>3. Informant further stated that 500 additional men were landed last
                                night from the <hi rend="italic">Idzumo</hi> (flagship) and other
                                Japanese ships to reinforce the naval landing force, bringing the
                                number of the latter up to 3,500. As all of the landing force is on
                                the front line, there are no reserves which makes the tactical
                                situation precarious. The use of guns from the ships present to
                                support or cover the landing force would be most dangerous to the
                                civilian population and property as it would be necessary to fire
                                over the Settlement.</p>
                            <p>4. Naval Attaché, from the statements made by informant today and
                                yesterday (Embassy’s 262, August 13, 6 p.m.), is of the opinion that
                                the Cabinet decided at the meeting this morning to send army troops
                                to Shanghai.</p>
                            <p>5. The Chief Secretary of the Cabinet, after the Cabinet meeting this
                                morning, told to press representatives that the Cabinet had
                                determined “to take concrete measures.” No other statement was made
                                and the Chief Secretary’s words are interpreted by many to mean that
                                military reenforcements will be sent to Shanghai.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Nanking.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>