<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="471" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d471">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">893.0146/575</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Adviser on Political
                                    Relations</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-16">August 16,
                                        1937</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: With further reference to
                                the question of sending reenforcements to Shanghai, may I say:</p>
                            <p>As I understand it, in 1927 the American Government, when appeal was
                                made for us to send armed forces to Shanghai, at first replied <pb facs="0429" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/> in the negative and then a
                                little later decided to send an armed force. There thereupon was
                                sent, from San Diego, a regiment of marines. To send this force
                                there was chartered a ship of the Dollar Line. The cost of
                                transportation amounted to about $120,000. From that time until now
                                we have maintained a force of marines at Shanghai.</p>
                            <p>In 1932, when reenforcements were asked for, we sent the 31st
                                Regiment, U. S. A., and a small number of marines. At the outset
                                there was some difficulty in fitting the army force into the
                                requirements of the situation at Shanghai. The 31st Regiment is
                                organized like a small army: it has an elaborate staff and is
                                prepared for field operations. For the purposes of defense
                                operations at Shanghai it possessed a superfluity of staff and of
                                equipment. Also, because of army regulations and procedure, it had
                                not the degree of elasticity for administration which prevails in a
                                detached organization of the Marine Corps.</p>
                            <p>No matter whether we send army from Manila or marines from San Diego
                                the critics will complain of the essential fact, namely, that we are
                                sending additional forces to Shanghai.</p>
                            <p>Nevertheless, I feel that we should send additional forces. The port
                                of Shanghai is a unique and extremely important political and
                                economic entity. It has been developed by international effort—over
                                a period of more than a hundred years. The “Settlement” there is
                                actually as well as in name “International”. Although it is not a
                                sovereign entity, it has long been controlled by the Powers rather
                                than by the Chinese Government. Its own municipal organization is an
                                organization wherein there exists a Council, which is elected by the
                                taxpayers and on which several Powers, including the United States,
                                are represented. At the present moment, the chairman of that Council
                                and its permanent secretary are American nationals. Under that
                                Council there functions a volunteer military organization made up of
                                volunteers from among the residents of the various nationalities.
                                Ever since 1927 there have been at the port armed forces, including
                                the American force (marines). There now exists a situation of
                                emergency. There will be operations for the sending away of a
                                considerable number of foreign nationals, especially women and
                                children. But, I do not envisage a complete “evacuation” on the part
                                of the 40,000 foreign residents. Moreover, there has been invested
                                at Shanghai a tremendous amount of capital of all nations, including
                                American, and including Chinese and Japanese. A complete abandonment
                                of the port, leaving the city to be fought over and fought for by
                                China and Japan would be calamitous to the whole world both from the
                                economic and from the political points of view. Unless other Powers
                                are prepared to make such an abandonment, the United States should
                                not abandon its responsibilities in connection with the common world
                                interest which there exists. Shanghai is the economic nerve center
                                    <pb facs="0430" n="423" xml:id="pg_423"/> of China and even in a
                                way of the whole commercial Far East. Destruction of that nerve
                                center would disorganize the economic system, insofar as organized
                                business is concerned, for the whole of China and would seriously
                                affect the trade of all parts of the world with China and even with
                                other parts of the Far East, Moreover, the system of
                                extraterritorial rights applies in regard to Shanghai, and the
                                interests and rights of the Powers there are inextricably
                                interwoven. We must keep in mind the fact that the situation and the
                                problem there are unique and cannot be compared, as regards
                                similarities, with the situation and problems at any other port in
                                the world.</p>
                            <p>No matter whether we now or within a few days find that a “state of
                                war” exists; no matter whether we apply the neutrality act; no
                                matter whether we ultimately decide to evacuate all of our nationals
                                from all parts of China; no matter whether in course of time we make
                                such a decision effective (it would take time to do it); no matter
                                what changes in attitude and in policy we may make with regard to
                                the Far East; the situation at Shanghai now is one in which
                                responsible officers on the spot have asked for reenforcements. The
                                British Government is already sending reenforcements. The French
                                Government is reported to be preparing to send reenforcements (from
                                Indochina). We would assume a very grave responsibility and we would
                                be on this account in an unenviable position from point of view of
                                world opinion if we responded in the negative to the recommendations
                                of our own officers in the premises.</p>
                            <p>We could give orders today for the Navy Department to have the Marine
                                Corps prepare the marines at San Diego for embarkation. There will
                                elapse between now and the period when embarkation could be effected
                                a period of perhaps ten days or a little more. Should the situation
                                change so as to make inadvisable actual embarkation at the moment
                                when embarkation is possible, we could then cancel the orders.</p>
                            <p>I feel strongly that the orders should be given and that publicity
                                should be given to the fact that they have been given.</p>
                            <closer><signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps">ornbeck</hi>]</signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>