<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations ( (Hornbeck))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d550</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">550</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-08-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-08-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-08-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-08-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="550"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d550">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/9831</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Adviser on Political Relations</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Hornbeck</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-08-28">August 28,
                            1937</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Chinese Ambassador called today at 11:30 on his own initiative.</p>
                <p>There were exchanged some observations with regard to the military situation in
                    China.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that, referring to an earlier conversation, he had received
                    from the Chinese Ambassador in London information that Dr. Quo had had a further
                    conversation with the British Minister for Foreign Affairs. Mr. Eden had stated
                    that the British Government was prepared to support any course of action (in
                    regard to the Nine Power Treaty?) which the American Government might choose to
                    embark upon. The Secretary inquired whether the Ambassador thought that any
                    course of action not involving force would be effective. The Ambassador replied
                    that he thought that for effectiveness force would be essential. The Secretary
                    inquired whether the Ambassador could state what naval forces the British
                    Government had in Far Eastern waters. The Ambassador replied to the effect that
                    he did not [know?] but that he did not think that they had a very strong
                    force.</p>
                <p>In the course of the conversation, the Ambassador stated that the Chinese
                    Government and the Soviet Government had entered into a non-aggression
                        pact.<note n="78" xml:id="d550fn78">Signed at Nanking, August 21, 1937,
                        League of Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">clxxxi</hi>, p.
                        101.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary pointed out that the American Government had done more than any
                    other government by way of expressing views, voicing principles applicable to
                    the Chinese-Japanese situation and urging that hostilities be avoided and peace
                    be kept.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">tanley</hi>] K. H[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >ornbeck</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
