<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-04-23T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-04-23T21:00:00-05:00" n="64" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d64">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/8597: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-04-24T10:00:00+08:00">April 24, 1937—10
                                        a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 11:45 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>179. Our 167, April 19, noon.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Domei, Shanghai, reports today that Kawagoe, now in that city
                                    pending departure for Japan April 28, stated in an interview
                                    yesterday: (1) through mutual concessions alone can China and
                                    Japan hope to adjust their relations and there can be no
                                    readjustment if one party seeks to realize its own program and
                                    that alone; (2) he had repeatedly told Wang Chung Hui that what
                                    China needs most is a clear realization of the factors involved
                                    in Japan’s national existence and growth; (3) Japan on her part
                                    must (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) fully understand China’s
                                    unification movement and the Central Government’s growing
                                    strength, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) make a thorough study of
                                    the real nature of the National Government and the development
                                    of its various branches, (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) keep
                                    constantly in mind the nature of China’s national unification;
                                    otherwise there will be no hope of readjusting Sino-Japanese
                                    relations; (4) China is as much interested as Japan in
                                    readjusting mutual relations and there is no divergence in views
                                    between Nanking and Tokyo on the necessity of breaking down the
                                    current deadlock; (5) economic cooperation will naturally follow
                                    readjustment of relations.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>He said he had noted China’s wishes for abolition of the East
                                    Hopei régime and suppression of smuggling and “intimated that
                                    the Chinese authorities appeared to be ready to make certain
                                    concessions” in regard to the import tariff.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>He gave noncommittal comment on “rumors of China’s <hi rend="italic">rapprochement</hi> with Russia and economic
                                    cooperation with Great <pb facs="0084" n="77" xml:id="pg_77"/>
                                    Britain”. In regard to “reports of projected Anglo-Japanese
                                    cooperation in China” he said “he had not observed any leanings
                                    in that direction in British circles in Nanking”.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Sent to the Department, by mail to Peiping, Shanghai,
                                    Tokyo.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>