<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d76</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">76</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjP7nK0m2r7YYXK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recvWez8hh14JTSSl" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recQt10IdeXz66A6d" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-foreign-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005831"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign Service</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-05-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="76"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/8644</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2419</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-05-14">May 14,
                            1937</date>.<lb/>[Received June 1.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It cannot be denied that Japan’s policy toward
                    China has undergone a marked change during the past few months, but many <pb
                        facs="0104" n="97" xml:id="pg_97"/> observers doubt that there has been any
                    real change in Japan’s basic policy. This basic policy was, and now is, to
                    dominate China in one way or another, thereby dominating the whole of the Far
                    East south of Siberia. Japan formerly sought to attain this end through
                    aggressive attempts to obtain political and economic control of China, but
                    China’s apparent determination, exhibited in various ways during the past few
                    months, to resist such attempts at control, has caused Japan to alter its method
                    of approach. As near as the Embassy can judge the present situation, Japan now
                    hopes to attain and maintain a strengthened position on the Asiatic mainland
                    through friendship and economic cooperation with China, rather than by actual
                    political control of that country.</p>
                <p>There have been many indications in recent months of this change in Japan’s
                    methods of attaining its ends. The reaction in Japan to China’s growing strength
                    and unity was one of astonishment and consternation. However, the Japanese are
                    intelligent enough to realize the changed conditions in China and to appreciate
                    the wisdom of shaping Japan’s policy in such a way as to be able to deal with
                    the altered situation. The demand for a policy of friendship and cooperation
                    with China has come from many quarters of the Japanese nation. It was perhaps
                    the Japanese diplomats and consular officers stationed in China who first
                    realized the changed conditions and advised their Government accordingly. They
                    were followed by businessmen engaged in trade with China, and later even a
                    section of the Japanese military realized the fact that the blustering,
                    aggressive tactics of the past were no longer effective. Since then, politicians
                    in Japan, and most of the Japanese newspapers and magazines have come to
                    appreciate the situation and are urging a changed policy toward China. It is
                    true that some sections of the Japanese nation, who have been badly informed or
                    who are reluctant to relinquish their former views, still cling to the idea that
                    China can be coerced into compliance with Japanese demands, but the bulk of the
                    nation now realizes that this course is dangerous.</p>
                <p>During recent months three men of considerable prominence in Japan have advocated
                    a changed policy toward China. The Embassy has already reported by telegraph and
                    despatch the views of Mr. Naotake Sato, the Minister for Foreign Affairs, in
                    regard to China. It will be remembered that he advocated treating China “on a
                    basis of equality” and indicated that past errors in negotiations with China had
                    been due to the fact that Japan had a sense of superiority in its dealings with
                    that country. It is true that Mr. Sato later was compelled, presumably by the
                    more chauvinistic elements in the Government, to modify his statement so far as
                    to say that he did not mean that Japan should deal patiently with China if China
                    broke the rules of international justice, but nevertheless it appears to be
                    certain that <pb facs="0105" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/> Mr. Sato still hopes to be
                    able to deal with China in much the same manner as he would deal with the United
                    States or Great Britain. Mr. Sato apparently is fully aware of the realities of
                    the situation and has shaped his course accordingly.</p>
                <p>Mr. Kenji Kodama, the chairman of a recent Japanese economic mission to China, on
                    his return to Japan, according to the press, expressed the view that Japan
                    should realize that China is now a strong, unified nation and must be dealt with
                    accordingly. The press assumes that Mr. Kodama advised the Foreign Office to
                    adopt a changed policy towards China more in keeping with changed conditions, in
                    order to improve economic relationships between the two countries.</p>
                <p>Mr. Shigeru Kawagoe, the Japanese Ambassador to China, was recently recalled to
                    Japan to confer with the Foreign Office on China policies. The press has been
                    hounding Mr. Kawagoe in an attempt to discover what advice he has given in this
                    connection, and it appears reasonably certain that his views were along the
                    following general lines: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>China is progressing rapidly, and national unity of that country is
                            becoming a reality.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Japan should realize that the actual power in China lies with General
                            Chiang Kai-shek and a section of the national army.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The actual control by the Chinese Government of China is great and
                            extensive, “comparable to that of the Japanese Government in
                            Japan”.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>These three men represent the Japanese Foreign Office, the Foreign Service in
                    China, and Japanese industrialists and financiers. As such they speak with a
                    certain amount of authority, and the Japanese nation appears now to be
                    considering and adopting their views. The Japanese press is inclined to urge the
                    Government to seek the friendship of China and to “reconsider its aggressive
                    policies”. There seems to be little doubt that with this pressure a new policy
                    toward China will evolve, but this is not held to mean a loss of prestige to the
                    Japanese Government. It simply means that Japan is adapting its policies to meet
                    changed conditions. It is true that the idea of treating China on a basis of
                    equality and reciprocity is very different from Japan’s aggressive policy of
                    only a few months ago, but, as the <hi rend="italic">Japan Times</hi> pointed
                    out editorially, the policy is different because China itself is now different.
                    It was impossible previously to deal with China, according to the Japanese view,
                    on a basis of equality, because China was not, in strength, unity, and stability
                    of Government, on a par with other great nations. Now that China has attained a
                    degree of unity and stability, Japan sees no disgrace in altering its policies
                    accordingly.</p>
                <p>It is difficult to say what attitude the Army will take toward the policy of
                    conciliation and friendship with China, as the Army spokesmen <pb facs="0106"
                        n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> have been silent on the subject during recent
                    months. There is no doubt that a section of the Army believes that a “weak
                    policy” toward China will only result in the stronger determination of Nanking
                    to resist Japan, but there also appears to be a section of the military,
                    represented by the men in high positions at the present time, who are inclined
                    to adopt the civilian view of treating China more or less on a basis of equality
                    and reciprocity.</p>
                <p>However, it will undoubtedly be very difficult to persuade the military to
                    surrender the gains they have made in North China, such as the Hopei-Chahar
                    Political Council, the East Hopei Autonomous Régime, the Tangku Truce
                        Agreement,<note n="7a" xml:id="d76fn7a">Agreement between the Chinese and
                        Japanese military authorities, May 31, 1933; for text, see <ref
                            target="frus1931-41v01#pg_120">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 120</ref>.</note> and the Ho–Umezu
                        Agreement.<note n="8" xml:id="d76fn8">Alleged secret agreement between the
                        Chinese War Minister and the Japanese Commander in North China, May–July,
                        1935; see despatch No. 332, March 27, 1936, from the Ambassador in China,
                            <ref target="frus1936v04#pg_89">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1936, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 89</ref>.</note> The opposition of the
                    Japanese military to any relinquishment of such gains now appears to have caused
                    a compromise between the liberal policies of Mr. Sato and the chauvinistic
                    policies of the past. After the return of Mr. Kawagoe to Japan to confer on
                    China policies, there was a meeting of the representatives of the Foreign Office
                    and the War and Navy Ministries to discuss the proposed “new deal for China”.
                    The results of the discussion have not been officially announced and the
                    versions of the proposed “new deal” published in the press vary somewhat in
                    detail, although all express the same general theme. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kokumin</hi> outlines the new China policy as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <list>
                            <item>“1. Japan will not selfishly fail to appreciate that the Nanking
                                Government’s power is gradually expanding as long as the special
                                position of Japan in North China is not infringed on.</item>
                            <item>2. It will guard closely, however, against the growing tendency
                                for peace and order in North China to be disturbed as a result of
                                the compromise between Nanking and the Chinese Communists.</item>
                            <item>3. Negotiations for adjustment of relations shall be started as
                                soon as possible. The first matters to be negotiated on shall be
                                exclusively economic, and political questions shall be avoided for
                                the time being.</item>
                            <item>4. For smooth trade and economic co-operation in North China, the
                                lowering of high tariffs against Japanese goods shall be made an
                                urgent question for negotiation.</item>
                            <item>5. Abolition of the East Hopei régime and acquisition of the
                                political power in North China, which Nanking reportedly means to
                                demand of Japan, if brought up by the Chinese at this time would
                                tend to aggravate relations further. Thus the prudence of the
                                Chinese regarding these matters is fully anticipated.</item>
                            <item>6. Japan will co-operate with China against any nation attempting
                                to sacrifice the latter and will reject any negotiations that would
                                bring China under international control. At the same time, it will
                                avoid friction with the other countries interested in China.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0107" n="100" xml:id="pg_100"/>
                <p>It will be observed that these policies provide for Japan’s recognition of
                    China’s increasing strength and unity, but nevertheless do not contemplate the
                    relinquishment by Japan of its “special position” in North China. The policies
                    also do not contemplate the immediate abolition of the East Hopei Autonomous
                    Régime or the further consolidation of Nanking’s influence in North China. As
                    the abolition of the East Hopei Autonomous Régime and the extension of Nanking’s
                    control over North China appear to be the principal demands made by China as a
                    preliminary to further negotiations, it does not appear likely that the proposed
                    “new deal for China” will be acceptable to China as a basis for negotiations.
                    Japan apparently proposes to inaugurate negotiations with China with a “clean
                    slate” and on a basis of equality, but does not propose to abolish the results
                    of past aggression. It is difficult to see how this compromise policy can be
                    effective in promoting friendship between the two countries.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi> C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
