<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Grew) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d843</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">843</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-12-04T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-12-04T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040838"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-12-04T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-12-04T06:00:00-05:00" n="843"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d843">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94/11461: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Grew</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-12-04T20:00:00+09:00"
                            >December 4, 1937—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received December 4—4:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>595. Department’s 327, December 3, 4 p.m.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The procedure in Japan with regard to declaration of war is that action is
                        initiated by the Government but the instrument is signed and promulgated by
                        the Emperor only upon the advice of the Privy Council. Probably only a very
                        restricted circle would know of any such decision in the present instance if
                        and when made by the Government but we hope through personal contacts in
                        various quarters to be informed if and when the Privy Council has the matter
                        under consideration.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>It is not a Japanese trait to take decisions hastily.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Although Japan is aware that neither the League nor the Nine Power Treaty
                        nations are eager to take coercive measures against Japan, the Japanese
                        Government is reluctant as I have reason to believe to create a further
                        issue with the League without good reason. We believe that unless conditions
                        arise which would materially impede the successful attainment of Japanese
                        objectives in China, such as the continuous flow of arms and munitions to
                        China from abroad in substantially large quantities or the supply of foreign
                        credits to China or some other form of material assistance to China, the
                        Japanese Government will endeavor to avoid placing the League in a position
                        where its member nations would have automatically to apply economic
                        sanctions or overtly proclaim its impotence.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>My British colleague has reported to his Government that the decision as
                        to a declaration of war will depend on the amount of arms and munitions
                        brought into China and he tells me that the flow of such arms and munitions
                        from Hong Kong is steadily increasing. <pb facs="0766" n="759"
                            xml:id="pg_759"/> We have agreed promptly to exchange such information
                        as may come to us.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Another informant in close touch with Japanese naval officers considers a
                        declaration of war “almost inevitable” and states that those officials who
                        wish to avoid trouble with Great Britain are “fast losing ground.” While the
                        navy, in the event of a declaration of war, fully intends to exercise the
                        procedure of visit and search of all vessels entering Hong Kong, naval
                        officers are convinced that England is in no position to do anything about
                        it. The foregoing obviously represents certain naval views.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>We have had this matter under close observation from the very beginning
                        (see our 509, November 2, 2 p.m.). Since that time rumors have been current
                        that the Japanese Government has reached an affirmative decision on this
                        matter to be effective as of various dates. The report mentioned in the
                        Department’s 315, November 24, 6 p.m., is a case in point. These dates have
                        come and gone without a declaration of war. We are continuing to watch for
                        developments and we shall not fail to inform the Department as soon as any
                        significant indication is observed.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
