<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-01-26T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-01-26T02:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recLVtmipNOLIF0A1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85122588"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Silver</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-01-26T02:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-01-26T02:00:00-05:00" n="9"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/13951: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-01-26T15:00:00+08:00"
                            >January 26, 1937—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received at midnight.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>44. My 7, January 7, 4 p.m. The developments of the last two weeks may be briefly
                    described as consisting in efforts of the National Government to counteract the
                    rapidly growing influence of the Chinese Communist forces in the northwest
                    especially in and around Sian and to induce the leaders and forces under Yang Hu
                    Cheng and those comprising the “Northeast army” formerly under Chang Hsueh Liang
                    to break off their alliance with the Red forces, to accept the policies of the
                    National Government in Sino-Japanese relations and to obey the Government’s
                    mandates in appointment to official posts. <pb facs="0022" n="15" xml:id="pg_15"
                    /> The situation is still extremely obscure with the negotiations mainly in the
                    hands of Chiang Kai-shek who remains at his home in Fenghua and receives
                    representatives. It is generally believed that Yang Hu Cheng and the
                    Northeastern army are both unwilling and so far unable to withdraw from their
                    close association with the Communist forces under the banner of armed resistance
                    to Japanese encroachments. It is reported that in an effort to make easier the
                    acceptance by the Government of the submission of the three allies on the basis
                    of resistance to Japan the Communist forces have renounced their most radical
                    doctrines and that all three insist they do not demand immediate war but only
                    formal adoption of armed resistance as a policy.</p>
                <p>It is commonly reported that the Government some months ago sent to Sian a large
                    quantity of silver possibly as much as 18 million dollars and large quantities
                    of war munitions in preparation for possible retirement of the Government to
                    Sian in the event of hostilities with Japan and that it is his physical
                    possession of the silver and munitions which enables Yang Hu Cheng to protract
                    the negotiations with Chiang Kai-shek. Peck was informed by military officers in
                    Sian on January 15 that the allied forces there had plentiful supplies of money
                    and arms sent by the Government for so-called bandit suppression. It is
                    impossible on the basis of conflicting reports to anticipate when the
                    Government’s authority over Shensi and portions of Kansu will be firmly
                    re-established or the way in which the Government will dispose of the Communist
                    forces there.</p>
                <p>Sent to the Department, Peiping, Hankow, Shanghai.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
