<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1937v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">915</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1937-12-18T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1937-12-18T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-12-18T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-12-18T06:00:00-05:00" n="915"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d915">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">124.93/410: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hankow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-12-18T19:00:00+08:00"
                            >December 18, 1937—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received December 18—3:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>84. Prior to receipt of Department’s 11, December 16, 7 p.m., I had prepared the
                    following: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The inauguration of a new government in Peiping claiming to be the
                            government of China and successor to the Government which had its seat
                            at Nanking indicates the line which Japanese policy will follow. This
                            new government will be recognized by Japan and will assume [<hi
                                rend="italic">take?</hi>] over various functions, political as well
                            as fiscal obligations of the old Government in those areas occupied by
                            the Japanese Army. This will include customs, salt, currency, internal
                            taxes, et cetera. Japan will enter into arrangements with this new
                            government regarding these matters and the powers will be presented with
                            those arrangements as already accomplished. Following the technique used
                            in Manchuria Japan will enter into understandings with the new
                            government, leaving old Government in the position at least vis-à-vis
                            Japan and its protégé of an outlaw. Japanese forces will operate against
                            the soldiers and officials of the old Government and against provincial
                            forces of provinces still loyal to it as against Communists and
                            bandits.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>It is expected that very shortly the Japanese will proceed against
                            Hankow and against Canton. Opinions differ as to whether this will be
                            done simultaneously or at different times. It is extremely doubtful that
                            the Chinese will be able to prevent the Japanese from occupying Hankow.
                            This means that the Government will have to leave Hankow and retreat
                            further into the interior. Ministry of Finance has made arrangements to
                            proceed to Chungking next week. Part of Ministry of Foreign Affairs has
                            already gone, leaving Minister and Vice Ministers here. In such an
                            eventuality I shall be under the necessity of deciding whether I shall
                            go to Chungking or such other place in the interior as the Government
                            may choose as a retreat, or go elsewhere, either to Hong Kong or to
                            Shanghai. Both Peiping and Nanking seem to me to be out of the picture
                            at least for the present. While Hong Kong remains as a possibility in
                            view of the fact that air connection between Hong Kong and Chungking
                            will be continued, it is objectionable on the grounds that my presence
                            there under the British flag might be misinterpreted. While Shanghai is
                            not a desirable place as it will be entirely cut off from the Government
                            to which I am accredited, it would be preferable in view of the presence
                            there of other Missions.</item>
                        <pb facs="0828" n="821" xml:id="pg_821"/>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Personally I should be willing and ready to go to Chungking with the
                            Government although it is entirely probable that I would find myself,
                            with the possible exception of the newly appointed Soviet
                            Ambassador—provided he presents his credentials—the only Chief of
                            Mission in residence.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Replying to Department’s queries: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>It would be desirable for some member of the Embassy staff to
                                    continue contact with the Chinese Government at Chungking. Peck
                                    is of the opinion that he, as Counselor and long resident near
                                    the Government, should continue here at Hankow and follow
                                    Ministry of Foreign Affairs to Chungking thus continuing to the
                                    end such support as our Government has given the Chinese
                                    Government throughout recent years, particularly subsequent to
                                    the Washington Conference. While I agree with his point of view
                                    it seems necessary to point out that, with the exception of the
                                    Soviet Government which has been forced by circumstances to
                                    place its Chargé at the seat of the present Chinese Government
                                    with every apparent intention of following it to Chungking,
                                    other Governments appear to have considered it unnecessary to
                                    keep representatives with the Chinese Government of greater rank
                                    than a First or Second Secretary. While the German Ambassador
                                    accompanied by his Counselor is here, he is in a quandary as to
                                    what he shall do under present circumstances and I apprehend
                                    that he will leave Hankow at the same time I do although I have
                                    not consulted with him in regard to this matter. The British
                                    have a Second Secretary here and it is my understanding that he
                                    will follow the Government to Chungking. The French have a
                                    Consul Adjoint who will also go to Chungking; the Belgians a
                                    Second Secretary; Italians a First Secretary who is about to be
                                    relieved, as a routine rotation of service, by the Italian
                                    Counselor. I should like to have the Department’s instructions
                                    as to whether it desires Peck to remain here with one or two
                                    members of the staff, or whether we might designate Language
                                    Officer Drumright<note n="41" xml:id="d915fn41">Everett F.
                                        Drumright, Consul at Hankow.</note> as a Second Secretary
                                    with orders to proceed to Chungking leaving Jenkins here to fill
                                    his place in the Consulate.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>It is difficult for me to estimate the reactions of the
                                    Chinese Government and people to my departure at this time. They
                                    will naturally feel that I have joined my British, French, and
                                    Italian colleagues in deserting the ship, but I have made no
                                    secret of my intention not to go to Chungking. I could explain
                                    that important questions required me to proceed to
                                    Shanghai.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The Government intends sooner or later to leave Hankow. I have
                                    already mentioned plans of Ministries of Finance and Foreign
                                    Affairs.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>It would probably be easier for me to go now than later, for
                                    to go when the Japanese are about to arrive at Hankow would
                                    accentuate the idea of desertion.</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>Departure by ship may be open for 3 or 4 days longer. H. M. S.
                                        <hi rend="italic">Capeshire</hi> has just left for Shanghai
                                    December 18, 9 p.m.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
