<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-09-18T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-09-18T14:00:00-05:00" n="979" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d979">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">693.002/367: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-09-18T15:00:00-04:00">September 18, 1937—3
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>214. On September 6 the Department received an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> from the British Embassy<note n="89" xml:id="d979fn89">Not printed.</note> stating that the British
                            Embassy at Tokyo had been instructed, with reference to measures which
                            the Japanese contemplate taking with regard to the Chinese Government
                            revenues at Tientsin, to remind the Japanese Government of the
                            substantial British interests in both the Chinese Customs and Salt
                            Administrations and in the revenues therefrom and to request assurances
                            from the Japanese Government that it intends to respect those British
                            interests. In reply to the British Government’s inquiry whether or not
                            the American Government contemplated action along similar lines, we
                            stated that we had the matter under consideration.</p>
                        <p>On September 15 the Department received another British <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi><note n="89" xml:id="d979fn90">Not printed.</note>
                            which stated, with reference to reports that the Chinese Customs house
                            at Taishan, Kwangtung Province, had been captured by the Japanese, that
                            the British Embassy in Tokyo had again been instructed to draw the
                            attention of the Japanese Government to the importance which the British
                            Government attaches to the preservation of the Chinese Customs
                            Administration. In reply to an inquiry with regard to parallel action by
                            the American Government, we have stated that you have been authorized to
                            consult with your British colleague and, in your discretion, to make an
                            approach to the Japanese Government in the matter.</p>
                        <p>The Department suggests that such approach be along the following lines:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The American Government has an interest in the preservation of
                                    the Chinese Maritime Customs and of the Chinese Salt
                                    Administration and has an interest in the safeguarding of the
                                    revenues of those administrations. Reports of measures which the
                                    Japanese contemplate taking with regard to Chinese Customs and
                                    Salt Administrations at Tientsin and reports of Japanese
                                    military action directed against Chinese Customs houses on the
                                    coast of Kwangtung Province, with particular reference to the
                                    attack on the Customs house at Taishan, have come to our
                                    attention and we desire to invite the attention of the Japanese
                                    Government to those reports. The American Government holds the
                                    view that the integrity of the Chinese revenue administrations
                                    should be carefully respected and it has confidence that <pb facs="0873" n="866" xml:id="pg_866"/> the Japanese
                                    Government holds a similar view and will act in conformity
                                    therewith.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>