<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Blaine to Mr. Phelps.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1892</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1891-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1891-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-05-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-05-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="146"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Phelps</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-05-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 19, 1891</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 421.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your No. 434, of the 29th ultimo,
                    further relating to the passport No. 1202 issued October 10, 1891, by your
                    legation, to Alexander Block. The correspondence inclosed with your dispatch
                    answers the object the Department had in view in writing its instruction No.
                    404.</p>
                <p>It appears that the father, who is understood to have died in the United States
                    in 1881, abandoned his family in 1879, and that the friends of young Block’s
                    mother brought her and her son to Germany in 1880; that she died in 1882, and
                    that about 1889 the son was apprenticed by one Julius Heilbronner, a leading
                    leather merchant of Nuremberg, Bavaria; that in consequence of the decision of
                    the royal district government application was made to you for a passport in the
                    youth’s behalf. “The passport, after some hesitation,” you say to Consul Black,
                    “is issued upon the ground that Block, who was born in the United States, is not
                    personally responsible for his coming to this country (Germany) as a young
                    child, and upon the supposition that he will definitely return to the United
                    States on or before the attainment of his majority.”</p>
                <p>Your caution appears a wise one that he should return to the United States before
                    attaining the age of 21 years.</p>
                <p>While the granting of a passport is, under the circumstances, approved, it is
                    well to say frankly that should a claim be made by the German authorities for
                    military duty, the case of this young man, who has not been in the United States
                    since 1880, knows absolutely nothing about his father, comparatively little
                    about himself, and does not even speak the English language, affords doubtful
                    grounds for hopeful appeal in his behalf.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James G. Blaine.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
