<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Blaine to Mr. Lincoln.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1892</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1891-12-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1891-12-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-12-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-12-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="166"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Lincoln</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-12-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 19, 1891</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 656.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose for your information, having reference
                    to your dispatches numbered 475 and 477, of June 17 and 20 last, respectively,
                    in relation to copyright, a copy of a note which I have addressed to the British
                    minister at this capital on the 19th instant in the matter of the refusal of the
                    Canadian Government to grant copyright protection in that country to citizens of
                    the United States. The fourth section of the Canadian copyright act provides
                    that copyright may be obtained by “any person domiciled in Canada or in any part
                    of the British possessions, or any citizen of any country which has an
                    international copyright treaty with the United Kingdom.”</p>
                <p>The question now, however, would seem to be not whether the Dominion Government
                    correctly applies its own law of copyright, but rather whether the assurance
                    given in Lord Salisbury’s amended note of June 16, 1891, and upon which the
                    President’s proclamation rests in granting reciprocal copyright privilege to all
                    subjects of Great Britain, correctly represents the treatment accorded to
                    American citizens by “the law of copyright in force in all British
                    Possessions.”</p>
                <p>As the President’s proclamation now stands citizens of the Dominion of Canada
                    enjoy full privilege of copyright in the United States equally with all British
                    subjects whatever, and on a footing of perfect equality with citizens of the
                    United States. If the reciprocal arrangement <pb facs="0311" n="223"
                        xml:id="pg_223"/> which was thus entered into rests on a grave
                    misapprehension in an important particular, it is very desirable that the true
                    facts of the situation should be promptly and fully understood, to enable the
                    President to execute the act of March 8, 1891.</p>
                <p>If a prompt disposition of the matter is likely to be thereby aided, you are
                    authorized to bring the subject directly to the attention of Lord Salisbury,
                    laying stress upon the urgency of the inquiry that has been addressed to Sir
                    Julian Pauncefote.</p>
                <p>I also inclose a letter from Messrs. Munn &amp; Co., of the 11th instant, which
                    served as a basis to my note to the British Minister.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James G. Blaine.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 656.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss type="from">Munn &amp; Co.</gloss>, to the <gloss type="to"
                                >President</gloss>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-12-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">December 11, 1891</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: We learn from your official message to the
                        Senate and House of Representatives, dated 9th instant, that international
                        copyright has been secured with Great Britain and the British Possessions,
                        the laws of those countries permitting to our citizens the benefit of
                        copyright on substantially the same basis as to their own citizens and
                        subjects.</p>
                    <p>We inclose an official letter from the Canadian registrar, dated August 22,
                        1891, which denies the right of American citizens to obtain copyright
                        protection in Canada, and is to that extent contradictory of the
                        message.</p>
                    <p>The matter is one of considerable importance to our citizens who at present
                        are unable to obtain any protection in Canada, although registration is
                        allowed to Canadians in this country.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Munn</hi> &amp; Co.</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure to inclosure in No. 656.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Jackson</persName> to Messrs.
                                <gloss type="to">Munn &amp; Co</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ottawa, Canada</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-08-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">August 22, 1891</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen</hi>: You ask to be advised whether, under
                        section 4 of “The copyright act,” chapter 62, of Revised Statutes of Canada,
                        citizens of the United States can be admitted to the privileges of
                        registration of copyright in Canada on their complying with the conditions
                        of printing and publishing in Canada, in view of the provisions of the
                        United States copyright act of March last, and the proclamation of the
                        President.</p>
                    <p>In reply I am directed to say that the enactment and proclamation referred to
                        do not constitute an “International copyright treaty,” and that therefore
                        citizens of the United States can not register under our act.</p>
                    <p>I remain, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">J. B. Jackson</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Registrar.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
