<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1891-09-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1891-09-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="17" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d17">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Pacheco</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States in Guatemala and Honduras</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-09-02"><hi rend="italic">September
                                    2, 1891</hi></date>. (Received September 17.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 60.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                        your instructions No. 8, of July 23, 1891, and to report that by referring
                        to Mr. Mizner’s No. 188, of October, 18, 1890, you will find therein a
                        paragraph reading as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>I will, by the next mail, communicate with the Provincial Government
                                of Salvador on the subject of Consul Myers being refused a pass to
                                leave the country.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>I have made diligent search throughout our legation records but do not find
                        anything to show that Mr. Mizner ever wrote to the Government of Salvador on
                        the above subject. If he did, it does not appear on our books.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the needed information from Mr. Atherton, cable operator at La
                        Libertad in July, August, and September last, I would likewise respectfully
                        call your attention to Mr. Migzer’s No. 187, of October 18, 1890, and also
                        his No. 203, of November 10, 1890, wherein he reports in the former— <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>That Mr. Atherton, the cable operator at La Libertad, is now in
                                Panama, and that I have sent to him for a written statement of the
                                control exercised over his office by the authorities of
                                Salvador.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>And in the latter dispatch he goes on to say: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Mr. Whitney has just returned and informs me that he had several
                                conversations with Mr. Atherton, who stated distinctly that it is a
                                part of the contract between the cable company and the Government of
                                Salvador that the Government should have supervision of the
                                correspondence, and that, as a matter of fact, during the late war
                                in July and August last the authorities of Salvador did place a
                                guard of soldiers over the cable office in La Libertad, controlling
                                its business. Mr. Atherton, still being in the employ of the cable
                                company, did not, for apparent reasons, feel disposed to reduce
                                these matters to writing.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Permit me to say, in this connection, that I can not find further information
                        to report from the records here.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">R. Pacheco.</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>