<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Shannon to Mr. Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1892</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1892-01-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1892-01-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1892-01-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1892-01-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="21"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d21">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Shannon</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Managua</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-01-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 30, 1892</hi>
                        </date>. (Received March 2.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 58.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my No. 45, of January 7, 1802, I
                    have the honor now to report that his excellency, the minister of foreign
                    affairs of Salvador, has addressed me another and fuller communication in reply
                    to my note regarding the yet unfulfilled conditions of Mr. Mizner’s agreement,
                    consequent upon the violation and occupation by the military forces of that
                    Government of the United States consulate at San Salvador in July, 1890.</p>
                <p>In obedience to your instruction numbered 21, of November 20, 1891, I beg to
                    herewith transmit this reply, accompanied by a translation.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Cutts Shannon.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure No. 58.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Gallegos</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Shannon</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">San Salvador</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-01-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 11, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: There has been received at the
                        offices of this ministry, under my eharge, the courteous note of your
                        excellency, dated the 15th ultimo, relative to the incident of the violation
                        of the United States consulate during the revolutionary disturbances which
                        occurred in this capital the middle of last year, in consequence of which
                        the American legation, then in charge of Mr. Mizner, proposed to this
                        Government certain conditions of agreement, which your excellency
                        enumerates, and then states that the first three conditions having been
                        fulfilled, there still remains pending the question of pecuniary indemnity,
                        on account of which the legation of your excellency, trusting to the offers
                        made by the secretary-general of the provisional government to Lieut.
                        Denfield, now presents two inventories prepared by Mr. Myers, from which it
                        appears that the property of the American Government destroyed in the
                        consulate amounts to $137.50, and the value of the private property of <pb
                            facs="0119" n="31" xml:id="pg_31"/> the consul so destroyed, $2,172.65,
                        the reimbursement of which sums by this Government is requested.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency adds that in the opinion of the American Government Mr. Myers
                        is entitled to some additional compensation on the ground of injuries and
                        sufferings to which he was subjected during the events referred to, and so
                        that official makes a further claim for the sum of $15,000, but regarding
                        which the Government of your excellency desires only that the Salvadorian
                        Government may do whatever justice shall seem to require, this point being
                        reserved for a later consideration.</p>
                    <p>Finally, your excellency calls the attention of this Government to the
                        circumstance of Mr. Myers having been prevented from communicating directly
                        with his Government and with his legation, and to the circumstance of his
                        having been refused a passport to leave the Republic, except on the
                        condition that his exequatur be withdrawn at the same time, and in proof of
                        which your excellency appends a declaration of Mr. W. P. Fletcher, these two
                        last charges being presented as important factors in this disagreeable
                        affair, requiring some satisfactory explanation and reparation.</p>
                    <p>I immediately brought to the knowledge of the President-General of the
                        Republic the note of your excellency and its several annexes, and in
                        obedience to instructions received I now reply, declaring first of all, to
                        your excellency that if, not only in the appreciation of the facts which
                        occurred, but also of the claim based upon them, the opinion formed by this
                        Government does not fully agree with the conclusions reached by the legation
                        under the charge of your excellency, still not less firm on that account is
                        the purpose which guides my Government in seeking to define the nature and
                        responsibility of the facts referred to, not only in just regard for that
                        which the dignity and the rights of the nation demand, but also in
                        consideration of the relations of friendship which happily unite the two
                        Republics.</p>
                    <p>I also desire to call the attention of your excellency to the circumstance
                        that even before it was able to duly appreciate the facts which occurred in
                        the American consulate, since the Republic was in the midst of a trying
                        crisis which absorbed its whole attention, my Government sought to remove
                        all doubt regarding its deferential and respectful attitude toward the
                        American Government in acceding to the conditions that Mr. Mizner demanded
                        by publicly honoring the American flag, and in like manner placing the
                        consul, Mr. Myers, in possession of the consulate, of which he considered
                        himself to have been temporarily deprived.</p>
                    <p>This course of action on the part of my Government, it is hoped, will be
                        estimated at its just value by the illustrious Government of your excellency
                        in reconsideration of the incident which gave rise to it, and in view of the
                        claim now made.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency, referring to the conditions of the agreement proposed by Mr.
                        Mizner, states there is still pending the condition relative to indemnity,
                        and according to the inventories prepared by Mr. Myers, copies of which are
                        furnished me, there is claimed, on this ground, the reimbursement of $137.25
                        as the value of the property of the American Government destroyed in the
                        consulate, and $2,172.65 as the amount of the private property so destroyed
                        belonging to the consul. My Government at once confirms, in this respect,
                        the offers made by the secretary-general to Lieut. Denfield, since it
                        recognizes the principle of justice upon which they rest. But, if it is an
                        indisputable duty that an indemnity should be granted for damages caused to
                        private property by the forces of the Government, so it is also of universal
                        justice and constant practice among nations that the appraisal of such
                        damages can not be left, in any case, to the individual decision of the
                        interested parties, and much less be extended so as to equal the total value
                        of the property so damaged; this class of claims being always subject to
                        those general laws which each nation prescribes for itself, indemnification
                        being regarded as a public debt for its recognition and payment.</p>
                    <p>It is not the purpose of my Government, in making these observations, to cast
                        any doubt upon the honorable character of Consul Myers, or discusss the
                        accuracy of the figures which he presents as the amount of damages suffered.
                        The sole object it has in view is one inspired by higher motives, and
                        consists in not going beyond the limits of its friendly complacency toward
                        the worthy functionaries of the American Government by relaxing in their
                        favor the empire of the laws, which are equally obligatory upon them as upon
                        Salvadoreans. Otherwise there would result, besides the discredit of our
                        institutions, the injustice of establishing a difference of conditions,
                        leaving to our native citizens an inferior place.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency will permit me, in regard to this point, to recall the fact
                        that the prerogatives which by international law are granted to consuls have
                        for their sole object to facilitate the discharge of such duties as belong
                        to them, without recognizing that they have any diplomatic character or
                        enjoy the exemptions which are peculiar to public agents. Therefore, the
                        protection of person and property which is to be extended to consular
                        officials is subject to the same conditions as that which is extended to
                        citizens, and has for its basis the obligation of opening to them the
                        tribunals, and granting them the same freedom in the use of judicial
                        proceedings as the natives themselves enjoy.</p>
                    <pb facs="0120" n="32" xml:id="pg_32"/>
                    <p>Setting out from this principle, my Government believes that the claim
                        presented by Mr. Myers for the indemnification of the losses which he
                        declares were suffered in his property and in that of the American
                        Government, as a result of the events of July, 1890, can not be limited for
                        the present to the mere fixing of a sum of money, so as to demand its simple
                        reimbursement, without there being first held, in due form, those
                        proceedings which the laws of the country prescribe and require as
                        indispensable, before the tribunals established by the laws for proving and
                        appraising of damages sustained, which indemnification, in like manner, is
                        to be regulated according to general provisions.</p>
                    <p>As regards the compensation, which, in the opinion of the Government of your
                        excellency, ought to be paid to Consul Myers on the ground of injuries and
                        sufferings to which he declares he was subjected during the events referred
                        to, the ministry under my charge, in the absence of data which the
                        interested party should have laid before the tribunals of the country,
                        instituted an inquiry by the departmental governor, in order to ascertain
                        what in reality took place, and I am sorry to have to state to your
                        excellency that from information thus obtained it appears that so far from
                        Mr. Myers having suffered the slightest injury he was the subject of special
                        consideration among the various families about him, who extended to him the
                        most cordial hospitality, notwithstanding the difficult and unfortunate
                        circumstances of the moment, it being further shown from the testimony
                        alluded to that the consul had failed to make suitable return for the
                        attentions which were lavished upon him, and rather gave ground for
                        well-merited and bitter censures, which in deference to that official the
                        Salvadoreans wished to overlook.</p>
                    <p>My Government, Mr. Minister, does not doubt that Mr. Myers may have
                        experienced on that occasion painful privations and sufferings imposed by
                        the circumstances, and all the more, if one takes into account the rather
                        pusillanimous spirit of which he gave evident proofs; but it does not
                        believe that, finding himself in the same general situation as that to which
                        the entire community was subject on account of the events referred to, in
                        themselves exceptional, this could justly be made the ground for a claim in
                        his favor, it being frequently the case that governments are powerless to
                        prevent occurrences of this nature, and that even among nations better
                        organized they sometimes happen as a chastisement to communities.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, this point being reserved by your excellency for a mutual and
                        ulterior consideration, my Government will respectfully await such
                        indications as your excellency may have the goodness to offer upon the
                        subject, not doubting that, animated by a spirit of rectitude and justice,
                        some satisfactory solution will be reached.</p>
                    <p>Finally, I take pleasure in giving to your excellency a frank explanation of
                        the manner in which this Government regards the facts upon which are based
                        the charge that Mr. Myers was prevented from communicating directly with the
                        American legation, and that of having refused him a passport to leave the
                        Republic, unless upon the condition of withdrawing his exequatur at the same
                        time.</p>
                    <p>I suppose your excellency is well informed of the circumstances under which
                        occurred the incident alluded to. The capital of the Republic had been
                        occupied by the troops of José Maria Rivas, who betrayed the government of
                        Gen. Ezeta, at a time when his forces were defending the frontier against
                        the armed intervention of the Government of Guatemala. The rebellion had
                        established itself in the heart of the Republic, and it was necessary to
                        display extraordinary activity and energy to overthrow it and reëstablish
                        the action of the authority. In such difficult circumstances the Government,
                        without giving truce to the rebellion, withdrew from Santa Ana a part of the
                        army and suddenly attacked the barracks of the capital before it had been
                        twenty-four hours in the power of the rebels, recovering the capital two
                        days later and reëstablishing the empire of law. As soon as the firing began
                        the neighbors of the American consul opened communication between their
                        houses and the house of that official, considering, with reason, that they
                        would be occupied by the forces in attacking the artillery barracks, which
                        was situated in front of them, as indeed happened, and, in company with the
                        consul, they took refuge in a house on the borders of the town, some 600
                        yards from the consulate, which during the attack offered free access to the
                        troops to pass to the point from which the fire was directed against the
                        enemy; the flag, probably for this reason, now being lowered, and Mr. Myers
                        experiencing those injuries and sufferings of which he complains, Hardly had
                        the capital been recaptured, although the frontier was in part uncovered,
                        when Mr. Myers, without giving due credit to what had occurred, proposed to
                        forward the telegram of which your excellency inclosed me a copy, and in
                        which Gen. Ezeta appears as a simple military officer in command of
                        disorganized troops, launching himself upon the capital, regardless of
                        everything, carrying in his train destruction and disorder; when, without
                        violating the truth, the consul could very well have informed his Government
                        of the facts in a manner at once respectful to the chief of the nation and
                        the well-regulated conduct which his forces had observed on that occasion,
                        with out staining, even indirectly, the good name of the representative of
                        authority and of the army of the Republic, especially at a moment when they
                        had been most exalted <pb facs="0121" n="33" xml:id="pg_33"/> by their
                        energetic and successful efforts for the reëstablishment of order. Thus,
                        undoubtedly, the secretary-general of the Provisional Government understood
                        it from the first, and so, without refusing to Mr. Myers permission to
                        inform the Department of State at Washington of what had occurred, he
                        limited himself to simply proposing that the form of his telegram should be
                        modified in the terms known to your excellency, altering only what could
                        unjustly redound to the discredit of the Republic, although even as to the
                        other points, such as those relative to the destruction of the residence and
                        of the consulate, the truth was exaggerated to a marked degree. Mr. Myers,
                        as your excellency can see from the declaration of Mr. Fletcher, did not
                        wholly reject the revision of his telegram, but reserved for himself to
                        declare afterwards if he would accept or not the substitution of one
                        telegram for the other, and in regard to which it does not appear that he
                        came to any final decision. Mr. Myers, therefore, was not prevented from
                        communicating with his Government in any manner whatever, and although there
                        was exercised a species of censure in respect to the telegram which he
                        proposed to send to Mr. Blaine on the second day of August, 1890, for the
                        excellent reason I have mentioned, still that exceptional measure had a
                        legitimate basis in the abnormal condition of affairs then existing, the
                        Republic being in a state of siege, a situation which suspends the guarantee
                        of inviolability of correspondence.</p>
                    <p>To this reason might be added still another—that the telegram alluded to may
                        not, in strictness, be considered as an official act or report exclusively
                        relating to the exercise of the consular functions, the only case where
                        officials of that class are to be recognized as independent of the State in
                        whose territory they reside, according to treaties; the telegram being for
                        that reason subject to the law of the state of siege, which authorizes the
                        intervention that was exercised by the authority.</p>
                    <p>For similar reasons may be justified, in like manner, the condition imposed
                        on Mr. Myers for issuing to him the passport which he requested so as to
                        leave the Republic, since the guarantee of free emigration, which our
                        institutions recognize, is another of those guarantees which are suspended
                        by the state of siege; and if this would be perfectly legal in its common
                        application, still, treating of the special case relative to Mr. Myers,
                        whose departure from the country had for its evident object, as your
                        excellency recognizes, to nullify the action taken by the Government
                        respecting the telegram which it was proposed to send, I believe that for
                        still stronger reasons there could be denied to that official the passport
                        which he asked, and there could not only be imposed upon him the condition
                        of withdrawing his exequatur, but it could be withdrawn at once.</p>
                    <p>I indulge the hope that your excellency will be able to justly appreciate the
                        considerations herein set forth, taking always into account, as one of the
                        most important data to judge of their merit, the exceptional circumstances
                        in which the events occurred, and the significant proofs of deference with
                        which my Government endeavored at first to soften the harshness of the
                        situation to which Consul Myers was necessarily subjected, and to make
                        amends afterwards, by public demonstrations of honor, for whatever could in
                        any manner be considered as lowering or humiliating for the American
                        Government, for which my Government has ever entertained, and still
                        entertains, the most profound respect and distinguished consideration.</p>
                    <p>I remain, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Salvador Gallegos.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
