<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sir Julian Pauncefote to Mr. Foster.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1892</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1892-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1892-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recuY33deeMLOZJV6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123713"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Smuggling</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1892-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1892-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="258"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Julian Pauncefote</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">British Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-11-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 15, 1892</hi>
                        </date>. (Received November 17.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your note to this legation of
                    the 10th August last, and to the conversation which Mr. Herbert held with you on
                    the 3d ultimo, respecting the complaint of the United States Government against
                    the action of the Canadian Pacific Railway in regard to Chinese immigration into
                    the United States, I have the honor, in accordance with instructions which I
                    have received from the Earl of Rosebery, to inclose for your information copy of
                    a dispatch on the subject which has been addressed by his lordship to Mr.
                    Herbert.</p>
                <p>I have the honor at the same time to assure you that you are mistaken in
                    supposing that the previous communications of the United States Government in
                    regard to the question of Chinese immigration have been treated with
                    indifference.</p>
                <p>Those communications have received, on the contrary, very careful and friendly
                    consideration, and Lord Rosebery desires me to state that the subject shall
                    again be pressed on the attention of the Canadian ministers. But both on account
                    of the attitude of the Chinese Government in regard to the treatment of its
                    nationals in British colonies and in consequence of the vast length and natural
                    features of the Canadian frontier the question is beset with great
                    difficulties.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Julian Pauncefote.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss type="from">Earl of Rosebery</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to"
                                >Herbert</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-09-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">September 20, 1892</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your dispatch No. 219 of the
                        11th ultimo, inclosing copy of a note which you have received from the
                        Secretary of State, remonstrating strongly against the action of the
                        Canadian Pacific Railway in transporting Chinese persons, by contract, from
                        China to certain points in the United States.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Foster is mistaken in supposing that the previous representations made by
                        the Government of the United States with regard to Chinese immigration from
                        Canada have been treated with indifference. They have received very
                        attentive consideration and have formed the subject of considerable
                        correspondence between Her Majesty’s Government and that of the
                        Dominion.</p>
                    <p>I inclose herewith extracts from minutes of the Canadian privy council
                        showing the grounds on which the Canadian ministers have felt unable to take
                        action in the direction desired by the United States, and I may add that, in
                        view of the strong remonstrances which have been received from the Chinese
                        Government against the legislative restrictions already imposed on Chinese
                        in Canada and the Australian colonies, Her Majesty’s Government could not
                        urge the government of Canada to propose any fresh measures of that
                        nature.</p>
                    <p>The Canadian government, however, as will be seen in the minutes, have
                        expressed their willingness to prevent in all proper and legitimate ways the
                        violation of the laws of the United States by the citizens of the Dominion,
                        and the present representation of the United States Government shall be
                        forwarded to them without delay, with a request that it may receive their
                        prompt attention.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rosebery.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0411" n="323" xml:id="pg_323"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Report of a committee of the privy council.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1891-04-15">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">April</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">15, 1891</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The committee of the privy council have had under consideration a further
                        dispatch, dated December 27, 1890, from Lord Knutsford, inquiring when a
                        reply may be expected on the subject of the resolution of the Senate of the
                        United States (in which the House of Representatives had concurred)
                        respecting the proposal that negotiations would be entered into with Great
                        Britain and Mexico, with a view to securing treaty stipulations with those
                        governments for the prevention of the entry of Chinese laborers from the
                        Dominion of Canada and Mexico into the United States contrary to the laws of
                        the United States.</p>
                    <p>The subcommittee of council to whom the matter was referred observe that the
                        frontier between the United States and Canada has a length of over 3,500
                        miles extending from the Atlantic to the Pacific Ocean, and this frontier is
                        for the most part a mere geographical line dividing large open expanses of
                        land and water.</p>
                    <p>It is not seen how it would be possible to apply effective police protection
                        along a line extending across the continent of America, even were it found
                        desirable to do so.</p>
                    <p>The subcommittee state that the total number of residents in Canada of
                        persons of Chinese origin as established by the last census (1881) was only
                        4,383.</p>
                    <p>It is not probable that at the present time this number is materially
                        exceeded; an estimate based upon the best information attainable places the
                        number at present in Canada at less than 6,000.</p>
                    <p>Persons of Chinese origin who enter Canada pay a per capita tax of $50,
                        whereupon their legal right to freedom of movement from point to point in
                        the Dominion is the same as that of any other subjects or citizens of
                        foreign countries who enter Canada. There is no Canadian law by virtue of
                        which restrictions could be placed on Chinese residents in Canada to fetter
                        their freedom of movement any more than on any other foreign resident.</p>
                    <p>The Dominion are therefore of opinion that no practical way exists by which
                        effect could be given to the request embodied in the resolution of the
                        Senate and House of Representatives of the United States above referred
                        to.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Extracts from a report of the privy council.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-02-19">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">February</hi> 19, 1892</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The committee of the privy council have had under consideration a dispatch
                        dated May 19, 1891, from Lord Knutsford, respecting the proposal that
                        negotiations should be entered into between the United States, Great
                        Britain, and Mexico with the view of preventing the entry of Chinese
                        laborers into the United States by way of Canada or Mexico.</p>
                    <p>The minister of customs has, after careful investigation, reason to believe
                        that the reputed entrance of Chinese laborers into the Ignited States from
                        or via Canada has been exaggerated, and that such reports are largely due to
                        sensational newspaper items having little or no foundation in fact, as in
                        the case narrated in the dispatch of Lord Salisbury to Sir J. Pauncefote,
                        bearing date February 11, 1891, wherein it is stated that the United States
                        minister had informed him (Lord Salisbury) that “it happened that a Chinaman
                        had found himself on the bridge between the United States and Canada at
                        Niagara unable to go south on account of the law of exclusion from the
                        United States, or north on account of the poll tax in Canada,” which
                        incident was upon investigation at the time of its reported occurrence found
                        not to have occurred.</p>
                    <p>That Chinamen do sometimes succeed in evading the United States exclusion act
                        by smuggling themselves into the United States from Canada is probably true,
                        and it is certainly true that they sometimes succeed in evading the payment
                        of the capitation tax imposed under the Chinese immigration act by smuggling
                        themselves from the United States into Canada, but it is believed that in
                        neither case in numbers sufficient to cause anxiety or to warrant an
                        expenditure on the part of Canada necessary to effectually prevent such
                        smuggling, even were it found practicable.</p>
                    <p>Chinamen leaving Canada for the United States or elsewhere violate no
                        Canadian law. They are entitled to the same freedom of movement as citizens
                        of any other country. “Certificates of leave” are provided for by the
                        Chinese immigration act, and can not be refused them when applied for. The
                        Chinese immigration act does not, however, permit of reentrance into Canada
                        except on payment of the prescribed capitation tax or the production of a
                        “certificate of leave.”</p>
                    <p>The minister further observes that the United States Government, in asking
                        that the Chinese who may have left Canada without a certificate of leave
                        should be readmitted without payment of the capitation tax, is asking that
                        Canada do what it refused to do under like or similar circumstances.</p>
                    <pb facs="0412" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/>
                    <p>Chinese laborers, former residents of the United States and holders of
                        certificates taken out in good faith and confidence, entitling them under
                        the act of May 6, 1882, chapter 126 of the United States Statutes at Large,
                        to leave the United States and return thereto, found themselves on their
                        return, under the provisions of the exclusion act of September 13, 1888,
                        chapter 1015 of said statutes, absolutely debarred from admittance to that
                        country. <hi rend="italic">Vide</hi> extracts hereto attached from the
                        United States acts above referred to, as well as copy of a circular issued
                        by the United States Treasury Department, dated August 1, 1891, embodying
                        the decision of the Supreme Court of the United States, in which Mr. Justice
                        Field in delivering the opinion of the Court remarks, referring to the act
                        of 1888: “And it further declared no certificates of identity under which by
                        the act of May 6, 1882, Chinese laborers departing from the country were
                        allowed to return, should thereafter be issued, and it annulled every
                        certificate of the kind which had been previously issued, and provided that
                        no Chinese laborer should be permitted to enter the United States by virtue
                        thereof.” <hi rend="italic">Vide</hi> also the Canadian act, chapter 67,
                        Revised Statutes, hereto attached, particularly sections 8, 13, 17, bearing
                        upon the same subject.</p>
                    <p>The minister can only repeat the words embodied in the report on the
                        reference jointly to him and to the minister of agriculture, of a copy of
                        Lord Knutsford’s dispatch of the 18th November last, that he is of opinion
                        that no practical way exists by which effect could be given to the request
                        embodied in the resolution referred to of the Senate and House of
                        Representatives of the United States and he does not think he would be
                        justified in recommending any further legislation of a restrictive character
                        against the Chinese who are in the Dominion, and who have made Canada their
                        home under the law as it now exists, particularly in the direction suggested
                        by the American minister in London to Lord Salisbury as set forth in his
                        lordship’s dispatch of May 14, viz, that Canada should by legislation assume
                        the responsibility of placing officers on the frontier to “assist the United
                        States in enforcing the provisions of the statutes of that country” in
                        preventing Chinese from crossing the frontier without the permission of the
                        United States authorities.</p>
                    <p>The minister desires, however, that his lordship be assured that it is now
                        and always has been the desire of the Canadian government to prevent in all
                        proper and legitimate ways the violation of the laws of the United States by
                        the citizens of the Dominion.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
