<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-11-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-11-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="346" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d346">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Curry</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-11-22"><hi rend="italic">November 22, 1887</hi></date>.
                            (Received December 5.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 280.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The interest which attaches to the case of the
                        missionary, Mr. Doane, and the importance of the principles involved, induce
                        me to send, without delay, the inclosed letter from the acting minister of
                        state. With a clear admission of the improper action in the Philippine
                        Islands against Mr. Doane, is coupled a plea for delay on the question of
                        indemnity until a decision has been reached by the local tribunals. The
                        declaration that the property of the mission shall be respected and the work
                        of propagating the gospel may be freely continued, will be received with
                        satisfaction by a government one of whose basal principles is absolute
                        liberty of worship.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. S. M. Curry.</hi></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-11-08"><hi rend="italic">November 8,
                                1887</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: The minister of ultramar has sent me
                            all the data referring to the incident of the Caroline Islands, which
                            originated your note of 17th September, containing a claim for indemnity
                            in favor of the American missionary, Mr. Doane, for losses suffered in
                            consequence of his imprisonment and voyage to Manila.</p>
                        <p>From the information received by the Spanish Government it results that
                            on the occurrences which gave rise to the suit instituted against Mr.
                            Doane, no decision has been given, the superior governor of the
                            Philippine Islands having confined himself to replace things in the
                            situation which he believed they should be according <pb facs="0499" n="411" xml:id="pg_411"/> to right before the imprisonment of said
                            gentleman, because he considered that, owing to the antecedents of the
                            question, they had unduly acted against said missionary.</p>
                        <p>Such being the state of the case, the Government do not believe that it
                            can yet proceed to the examination of the question about indemnity,
                            because if the final decision of the tribunals were averse to Mr. Doane
                            the claim for damages put forward to-day would not be well-grounded; as
                            it would be based upon facts and actions upon which no sentence has been
                            passed.</p>
                        <p>But if upon this point I have to postpone an answer, I will certainly not
                            do it respecting the assurances given by General Terreros to the United
                            States consul in Manila and to Mr. Doane, assurances which the Spanish
                            Government indorses by affirming again that all property lawfully
                            acquired by the North American mission in the Caroline Islands shall be
                            respected, and likewise affirming that it may freely continue its work
                            of propaganda of the Gospel, with the understanding that on its turn the
                            mission will not only respect the Spanish laws, but that it will oppose
                            no difficulty to the Catholic mission with which the Government wishes
                            it may live in the best harmony.</p>
                        <p>The Government of the Regency, which wishes to maintain the feelings of
                            cordial friendship with the United States, hopes that the North American
                            Government will help it in that civilizing mission.</p>
                        <p>I avail myself, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">T. G. Aguera.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>By authority.</p>
                            <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Chargé d’Affaires of the United
                                States.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>