<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Newberry to Mr. Foster.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1892</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d456</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">456</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1892-08-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1892-08-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1892-08-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1892-08-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="456"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d456">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Newberry</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-08-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 18, 1892</hi>
                        </date>. (Received September 1.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 515.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have prepared the following telegram, which I
                    will send in a few hours, as it is now 3 o’clock a.m.: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Said Pacha</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minister of Foreign Affairs, Pera:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>I have received to-day from Mr. Bartlett of Bourdour the following
                            telegram, which I hasten to communicate to you for your information:
                            “Last night they burned down my house totally. Our lives also are
                            greatly in danger.” I hold the Imperial Government responsible for the
                            security of the lives of Mr. Bartlett and his family, and I trust that
                            immediate steps will be taken to that end.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Newberry</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chargé.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Some ten days ago I called upon the Grand Vizir and left with him a memorandum of
                    Mr. Bartlett’s case, and he promised to have immediate orders sent that Mr.
                    Bartlett should not be further molested. I then wired Bartlett that such orders
                    had gone. A week went by and Bartlett answered that the local authorities denied
                    all knowledge of such orders. Another visit to the Porte and further peremptory
                    telegraphic orders were sent. Mr. Gargiulo saw the telegram, which was in
                    Turkish and it was all that could be desired. This morning I wired Bartlett as
                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The Grand Vizir informs me final orders had gone to Vali of Conia,
                            allowing you to complete your building. Telegraph me if permit
                            refused.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Newberry</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chargé.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>And the result of all this has been the destruction of Bartlett’s house. By the
                    word “they” he means either Greek or Armenian community. They have both been
                    intriguing with mutaseriff of Bourdour against Bartlett and have been
                    magnificently successful in delaying his missionary work.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">H. R. Newberry</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires ad interim.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
