<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Denby to Mr.
                                Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1892</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d68</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">68</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1892-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1892-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85063084" lcsh-match="exact">Hunger</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862" lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249" lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="reci0GubnZFV3spJe" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011003316" lcsh-match="bad_close">Infant</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1892-02-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1892-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="68" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d68">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1892-02-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 1, 1892</hi>
                        </date>.
                            (Received March 21.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1470.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose, herewith, a
                        clipping from the North China News, which contains an account of the recent
                        Mongolian insurrection, written by a Chinese priest.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 1470.—From the North
                                China News.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The rebellion in Mongolia.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>We append a translation of a letter written by a Chinese priest from the
                            center of the terrible scenes which have been enacted in the north. The
                            letter is dated 15th December, and has just reached Shanghai.</p>
                    <p>There are in Mongolia two sects, the Taoists (Tsai-li) and the
                            Rationalists (Kin-tan-tao) whose members, gathered from every class of
                            people, literati, merchants, laborers, officials, and the like, have
                            long been infamous in the country for their injustice and wickedness.
                            One of their leaders, named Hu-Yong had, in particular, become, the
                            terror of the inhabitants on account of his burglarious habits. Finding
                            himself watched by the local mandarins, who waited for a good
                            opportunity to seize him, he fled away to Sankiatz in the district of
                            Kienchang, where he had many partisans and could, with their help,
                            continue his life of rapine.</p>
                    <p>The crop last year having been almost destroyed, the people of that
                            district were soon reduced to misery. Impelled by hunger they applied,
                            about the beginning of August, to the petty magistrates and to the rich
                            merchants for grants of rice, promising to repay them in the autumn.
                            Every one in China knows what such promises are worth. The merchants
                            promised to comply with the request, and a day was appointed <pb facs="0176" n="88" xml:id="pg_88"/> on which an equal distribution
                            of rice was to be served out to every person, whether a native or a
                            stranger. In the meanwhile, however, the crafty merchants secured the
                            help of Hu-Yong, and when two days after a long file of men and women,
                            bag in hand, walked up to the rice shop they found the brave standing by
                            the front door. There was a moment of hesitation, but hunger was
                            stronger than fear. They rushed on the man who, knocked down and
                            trampled under foot by the crowd, was soon a corpse. Fearing the
                            consequences of their act and anticipating retaliation from the dead
                            man’s confreres the people agreed to lay the blame on the Christians,
                            and the rumor was soon circulated throughout the town that the
                            Christians were guilty of the crime. Without inquiring into the facts of
                            the case, the Rationalists took up the cry; threats of death were freely
                            uttered against the Christians, and a riot became imminent. Message
                            after message was sent to the yamên, but the appeals for protection were
                            disregarded by the local mandarin, who contented himself by saying the
                            reports were unfounded and there was nothing to fear. In short, help was
                            refused.</p>
                    <p>This was the state of affairs when, on the 16th of the tenth moon
                            (November 17), a violent mob rushed to the residence of the missionaries
                            at Sankiatz, broke into the house, seized the Chinese priest, Ling,
                            stole all they could lay their hands on, and burnt church, house, and
                            orphanage. Of all the persons living there, men, women, and orphans, not
                            a single one was left alive; some were burnt in the house, others killed
                            on the spot. Some who escaped from the building were soon overtaken and
                            slaughtered. Then the mob scattered in all directions in search of new
                            victims, and wherever houses of Christians were found the inhabitants
                            were murdered, their property stolen, and the houses burnt to the
                            ground.</p>
                    <p>The fiendish work is not over yet. Two victims are still captive. Father
                            Ling is dragged to a temple and tied fast to one of the two masts in
                            front of it. He is called upon to apostatize, but threats are vain; he
                            remains firm. Guns are then leveled at him and he is shot dead; his body
                            is immediately ripped up and pulling from the still panting body the
                            heart, liver, and lungs, the murderers fix these ghastly trophies to the
                            top of the mast. There remains a woman with child. Kerosene is poured
                            over the poor mother and they burn her alive.</p>
                    <p>After this first exploit, in which some hundred Christian families were
                            thus slaughtered, the rioters proceeded to Pingchünchow. Another appeal
                            for protection was made to the subprefect Wen Pu-ni, but though renewed
                            several times, it was always in vain. The rioters, however, were not yet
                            so bold as to act openly. They sent a message to the mandarin. They had
                            not, they said, taken arms against the Government; they only asked him
                            to carry out their revenge against the Christians by burning and
                            destroying their houses. This strange license being granted them, they
                            entered the town, sacked and burned down the church, the orphanage, and
                            houses of the Christians. Far from opposing them, the officials and
                            soldiers of the yamên, in the hope of sharing in the booty, kindly
                            invited the plunderers to search out all the Christians, and proclaimed
                            that any person who should give shelter to Christians would be treated
                            as such. The complaisant Wen Pu-ni in the meantime was spreading the
                            rumor that in the residence of the missionaries there was hid a huge
                            heap of bones—bones of children devoured by cannibal foreigners, of
                            course—and sent this piece of news by letter to Gen. Yeh, who is said to
                            be one of the Kin-tan-tao.</p>
                    <p>Gen. Yeh no sooner received the letter than he issued a proclamation
                            against Christians and sent copies of it everywhere. The calumny was
                            believed, and equally exasperated against the Kin-tan-tao men, the
                            Tsai-liman, and the Christians, the people rose up against them, the
                            former rioters openly declared themselves, and a regular rebellion now
                            broke out.</p>
                    <p>Ch’aoyang Hsien was soon occupied by thousands of rebels; the prisons
                            were broken open, all criminals were let loose, and the rage of the
                            rebels was turned against the inhabitants. Their property was seized,
                            and themselves butchered. Several noble families were massacred and so
                            few people escaped in that great town and the surrounding districts,
                            that for a distance of several hundred li not a family has been
                            spared.</p>
                    <p>A certain Chu, one of the ringleaders, assumed the title of emperor, and
                            to give himself greater prestige, took as wives and concubines several
                            of the wives and daughters of the massacred nobles.</p>
                    <p>Another leader named Wei Lao-tao, renowned for magic, art, gave his
                            soldiers a spell which was supposed to preserve them from death. Every
                            morning they were to swallow a magic pill intended to give them courage.
                            On their flags was written “Hsing Ta Ming” (let us raise the dynasty of
                            the Ming), “Mich Ta Ts’ing” (and destroy the present dynasty of the
                            Ts’ing); and also “Yong hwa fu kuei tsai men” (honor, riches, dignities
                            are to us).</p>
                    <p>In every town or village through which the rebel forces passed they
                            proceeded to kill all the inhabitants.</p>
                    <p>Fortunately, after a time, Li Hung-chang sent troops against them. On the
                            20th of the tenth moon (November 21), the first battle was fought. The
                            rebels numbered upwards of ten thousand men. Wei Lao-tao had taken up
                            his position on an imperial <pb facs="0177" n="89" xml:id="pg_89"/>
                            chariot formerly given by the great Kang Hsi to the temple of Kuanti,
                            and on which chariot the idol is seated for the annual pageant. Whilst
                            the troops of Li Hung-chang attacked the rebels in front, the soldiers
                            of the subprefect of Kinchang Hsien fell on their rear; they were thus
                            defeated, four hundred and seventy men were killed, more than a hundred
                            made prisoners, and Wei Lao-tao himself was slain. The remainder escaped
                            to Sankiatz, but the Jeho forces followed them up, slaying some forty of
                            them.</p>
                    <p>The rebels of the Kintantao sect still numbered upwards of ten thousand
                            men. Several more battles were fought. The rebels, though superior in
                            number, being badly drilled and too confident in their magic, were
                            defeated and their sham emperor made prisoner. Two mandarins were also
                            killed.</p>
                    <p>I hear that among the rebels there are many rioters who came here from
                            Kiang-nan after the disturbances.</p>
                    <p>Among the Imperial troops there are also many wicked men doing great harm
                            to the populations they have come to defend. This year the crop failed
                            again and the number of the poor has considerably increased. The few
                            families who are still well off have been robbed by the Imperial
                            soldiers of all the provisions they had in store. They can not obtain
                            protection from the mandarins, as these only care to get rich at the
                            people’s expense.</p>
                    <p>Here is a new instance of the cruelty of the rebels. A mandarian, unable
                            to oppose them, had piled up on several carts his family, his
                            provisions, and his riches. He had just arrived at the foot of the
                            mountains when he was overtaken by the rebels, despoiled of all he had,
                            and slain. The next morning, wishing to make certain that they had left
                            nothing unplundered, the rebels came again to the spot and there
                            discovered an infant crying for food. Unmoved by this pitiful sight,
                            they caught hold of the child, seized it by the legs and pulled them
                            apart, tearing the poor infant in two. Would to God that this may be the
                            end of our calamities.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
