<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-10-04T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-10-04T12:00:00-05:00" n="105" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d105">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01/10–449: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Netherlands</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Steere</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Hague</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-10-04T18:00:00+01:00">October 4,
                                    1949—6 p. m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received October 4—4:03 p. m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>881. We called to attention of Chief Political Section Foreign Office
                            editorial in today’s <hi rend="italic">Nieuwe Rotterdamse Courant</hi>
                            on China. Principal points made in article were:</p>
                        <p>As matters now stand, Communist Government is a reality and Nationalist
                            Government is “not much more than a fiction”. There is, therefore, every
                            reason for other countries besides Russia to recognize <pb facs="0109" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> Communist Government <hi rend="italic">de
                                facto. De jure</hi> recognition would create more difficulties for
                            many governments other than Russia since they are bound to the “old
                            state” by treaties. The democracies are afraid of resigning themselves
                            to real situation China. Furthermore, <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi>
                            recognition would give Russia an ally in SC.<note n="73" xml:id="d105fn73">Security Council of the United Nations.</note> If
                            three big Western democracies wish to avoid SC becoming paralysed, “they
                            might feel obligated to give <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> recognition
                            to the Chinese People’s Republic sooner than they intended. This might
                            not be a bad thing. It is after all no use running away from
                            reality.”</p>
                        <p>Foreign Office official said that except for sentence re treaties, he was
                            forced to admit that there was a good deal of sense in article. He
                            continued that he did not feel that recognition Communist Government
                            could be postponed for a very long time, but he was careful to add that
                            Holland would thoroughly study opinions of big powers and that Holland
                            would not precipitate any action re recognition.</p>
                        <p>Official also informed us that extensive Netherlands Embassy property in
                            Peking now in charge of by [<hi rend="italic">a</hi>] junior official.
                            Accordingly today telegram being sent to Nanking that, before
                            Netherlands Ambassador leaves, Counselor should make trip to Peking
                            ostensibly for inspection of Embassy. If necessary, added official,
                            Counselor’s stay in Peking “could be extended for some time”.</p>
                        <p>Sent Department 881; repeated Moscow 5, London 97.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Steere</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>