<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Political Adviser in Japan ( (Sebald) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d116</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">116</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-10-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-10-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-10-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-10-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="116"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d116">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01/10–749: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting Political Adviser in Japan</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sebald</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-10-07">October 7,
                            1949</date>.<lb/>[Received October 7—6:59 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>395. Following is gist of information supplied by Ratnam, First Secretary, Indian
                    Mission in Japan, recently returned on <hi rend="italic">General Gordon</hi>
                    from 5-month stay Nanking, part time as Chargé:</p>
                <p>British Ambassador in China, Sir Ralph Stevenson, strongly recommends immediate
                    recognition Chinese Communist regime by British Government for economic reasons
                    and on principle that this is only realistic approach to Chinese problem.
                    Recognition according to Chinese Communist definition must be <hi rend="italic"
                        >de jure</hi> or not at all and must be on a reciprocal basis. Ratnam claims
                    in discussions with British Ambassador he advised against immediate recognition
                    until assured that China not [<hi rend="italic">now?</hi>] essential in solution
                    of larger world problem. Ratnam also confident Indian Government will not
                    immediately recognize Chinese Communists unless influenced by UK to follow
                    latter’s lead. He furthermore convinced precipitate recognition by UK solely on
                    economic grounds will eventually result “in chasing rainbow” as Marxist
                    indoctrination Chinese Communist administrators ensures eventual direct or
                    indirect (by extortionate taxation) confiscation foreign properties. He believes
                    that when foreigners have been utilized strengthen Communist regime, their
                    usefulness will be at an end and foreigners thrown out. Ratnam personally thinks
                    precipitate recognition would be mistake and that China situation should be
                    carefully watched especially with reference possibilities continued major
                    opposition by Chinese National Government.</p>
                <p>From his observations and numerous conversations with Soviet Embassy friends
                    Nanking, Ratnam convinced entire Chinese Communist effort is directed on
                    high-level centralized basis by Soviet Russia although he unable obtain any
                    information disclosing connection between Soviet Embassy personnel and Chinese
                    Communists. He states entire pattern Chinese Communist regime from top to bottom
                    closely follows Soviet Russian pattern and that in no instance could he discover
                    any divergence from usual Soviet organization or policy line. While greatly
                    impressed with self-discipline Chinese Communists and apparent immediate
                    improvement in administration after take-over, Ratnam attributes these factors
                    to utter ruthlessness with which Communist policies carried out among Chinese
                    people.</p>
                <p>Comment upon Ratnam: Considered an able and intelligent observer. Excuses his
                    admitted associations with Japanese pro-Communists <pb facs="0116" n="106"
                        xml:id="pg_106"/> as necessary in order find out how Communist Party
                    operates and states followed similar associations for same reason in China. In
                    light these proclivities, consider above remarks unusually revealing.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sebald</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
