<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at Shanghai ( (McConaughy) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-11-30T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-30T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recb140a4efc2e771d" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Warships</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-30T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-30T04:00:00-05:00" n="1172"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1172">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">393.115/11–3049: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McConaughy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-30T17:00:00+08:00"
                            >November 30, 1949—5 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 30—8:49 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4992. Consulate General observes with increasing concern attacks by Chinese
                    Nationalist worships on American merchant ships. In the case of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Flying Cloud</hi>, which was heavily fired on November 15 and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Sir John Franklin</hi> which was similarly attacked on
                    November 28, the fact that no casualties occurred can only be attributed to good
                    fortune. While fully realizing that the Department has already taken clear
                    position that ships’ owners and masters bringing ships into Shanghai do so on
                    their own responsibility, Consulate General raises for Department’s
                    consideration the question whether now that American lives have been in great
                    actual danger, some stronger discouragement to the entry of ships would not be
                    advisable. Consulate General understands that no reply received from Chinese
                    Government in answer to US protest of firing on <hi rend="italic">Flying
                        Cloud</hi>, and it is apparent that no orders have been issued to Chinese
                    warships to stop attacks on American merchant ships. Possibly no responsible
                    Chinese Government in existence with authority to enforce such orders if issued.
                    In view of fact that protest re attacks on <hi rend="italic">Flying Cloud</hi>
                    were ineffective in preventing heavier attack on second American ship, it may be
                    expected that Nationalists will be further emboldened if no effective deterrent
                    found. As a means of preventing loss of American lives, Consulate General
                    believes that unless the US Government is prepared to protect American ships
                    from attack or bring such pressure to bear on Nationalist Government as would
                    ensure their safe passage American shipping companies should be impressed with
                    serious danger involved in entering Shanghai, and at least urged to consider
                    carefully desirability of postponing further ship calls here in absence safe
                    conduct until armed interference withdrawn. Particularly blockade runners should
                    hesitate to take passengers. Of immediate concern is the outward voyage of <hi
                        rend="italic">Sir John Franklin</hi>, scheduled to leave Shanghai about
                    December 6. Entry of this ship in defiance of all efforts by Nationalist
                    warships to prevent it would seem to make it more likely that an all-out effort
                    will be made to prevent her escape. Re Deptel 1927 [<hi rend="italic">1929</hi>]
                    September 20, Consulate General proposes to warn prospective American passengers
                    of grave risks to be anticipated if ship again proposed to defy Nationalist war
                    vessels.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">McConaughy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
