<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul at Tsingtao (
                        Strong
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1254</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1254</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-03-01T22:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-03-01T22:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-03-01T22:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-03-01T22:00:00-05:00" n="1254" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1254">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.3393/3–249: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Tsingtao</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Strong</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tsingtao</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-03-02T11:00:00+08:00">March 2, 1949—11 a. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received March 2—5:01 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>105. [To Nanking:] Reference emergency planning mutuality believed achieved with
                    US Naval forces except: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Consul General believes protection whether ashore or afloat should be
                            granted all non-Asiatics who desire it plus Filipinos; of some 800 such
                            persons expected reside here should emergency arise, believe only small
                            percentage seek refuge; Consul General desires lay plan aid them do so.
                            Naval forces concept calls for sanctuary ashore for Americans plus other
                            designated foreigners (designating authority unnamed) who may appear at
                            concentration point; reluctant take other than American aboard.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Consul General feels duration emergency would be brief, those placed
                            afloat for safety to be allowed return ashore thereafter if so <pb facs="1243" n="1233" xml:id="pg_1233"/> desire whether in ship’s
                            boats or in boats provided from shore by Consul General; consider return
                            of Americans would promote US interests; most Americans remaining here
                            have chosen accept Communist rule. Naval concept envisages evacuation
                            from area following embarkation.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Moral obligation exists evacuation ECA Chinese staff imported from
                            Shanghai whose presence here essential until last moment. Plans should
                            specifically include authority embark said ECA Chinese certified by
                            Consul General. Plans now exclude all Chinese.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>Embassy please note paragraph 3 X 4 page 4 AQ 5 ComNavWesPac OP order
                                2–49.<note n="46" xml:id="d1254fn46">Not found in Department of
                                State files.</note> Believe this paragraph not fit situation
                            Tsingtao where intended withdraw rather than engage in combat.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Admiral Badger stated earlier he expects retain several vessels Tsingtao even
                    after given up as main fleet station and previous acceptance by Rear Admiral
                    Rees of return of civilians ashore after order restored would, barring the
                    unexpected, such as extended period disorder or need for naval vessels elsewhere
                    or threat by Communist to US vessels, appear indicate needs of local foreigners
                    as visualized by Consul General can be met.</p>
                <p>Would appreciate Embassy’s comment and clarification.</p>
                <p>Navy and Marine officers concerned have been most friendly, cooperative re
                    plans.</p>
                <p>Sent Nanking 90, repeated Department 105.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Strong</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
