<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-07-28T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-28T06:00:00-05:00" n="1315" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1315">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">393.1115/7–2849: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McConaughy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-07-28T19:00:00+08:00">July 28,
                                    1949—7 p. m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received July 28—10:05 a. m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2946. ReDeptel 1479, July 26, evacuation American citizens. Consulate
                            General recommends arrangements be made bring in APL<note n="9" xml:id="d1315fn9">American President Lines.</note> transport, <hi rend="italic">General Gordon</hi>, under safe-conduct September 13
                            sailing following day. Have discussed problem with Downs, APL local
                            agent, who is wiring urgent recommendation to his principals divert <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi> here as indicated. <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi> would be scheduled enter Shanghai [garble] mentioned if
                            normal shipping were reopened and could make this call en route from
                            Kobe to Hong Kong with minimum expense. Other APL ships <hi rend="italic">President Cleveland</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi> have much smaller passenger capacity 550 each compared
                            1800 for <hi rend="italic">Gordon. Cleveland</hi> on normal schedule
                            would call here September 1 which probably too early for completion
                            necessary negotiations and <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi> September 22
                            which unnecessarily late. Every day may count if situation continues
                            deteriorate.</p>
                        <p>Have requested President [of] American Association make immediately
                            canvass American community determine number prospective evacuees. Also
                            consulting consular colleagues obtain estimates probable number other
                            foreign nationals. However, I do not believe we should wait results this
                            survey to open negotiations. Satisfied number wishing leave will be more
                            than sufficient justify call of ship if Communist exit permits
                            forthcoming. Availability permits cannot be determined with certainty
                            until vessel formally booked call here since means and date
                            transportation is required information for application blank. Believe
                            submission large number applications may have salutary effect on
                            Communist authorities and will certainly smoke them out on hostage
                            issue.</p>
                        <p>Recommend immediate fast tempo negotiations with APL executives who have
                            already been alerted by Downs. If OffEmb Canton can expedite
                            safe-conduct from Nationalists to include personal and household effect
                            evacuees as well as incoming and outgoing mail, project will be greatly
                            furthered. There is risk Communists who argue we are instigators
                            blockade will resent bringing in only one ship. They may <pb facs="1287" n="1277" xml:id="pg_1277"/> make granting permit for <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi> conditional on assurances from APL [that]
                            other ships will be scheduled on defiance blockade if necessary. APL, of
                            course, will not endeavor run blockade. If safe-conduct could be
                            obtained for additional APL ships, that would be desirable but believe
                            all our initial efforts should be concentrated on <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Most serious drawback may be problem paying off servants and other
                            employees American evacuees. The three or four British heads families
                            leaving on <hi rend="italic">Anchises</hi> tomorrow obliged pay
                            equivalent from US dollars 1,500 to dollars 3,600 as severance bonuses
                            to household servants. We will deal with this vexing problem when we
                            come to it, not allowing it deter us from making evacuation arrangement.
                            Meanwhile I am suggesting to American Association that it discreetly
                            advise Americans planning leave it may be wise start training [<hi rend="italic">trimming?</hi>] servant staffs now.</p>
                        <p>Call of <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi> can be canceled on short notice if
                            necessary.</p>
                        <p>British wish bring in several small “relief” ships at regular intervals
                            from Hong Kong. They think use term “evacuation ship” would be
                            unfortunate in its implications and would prefer some other designation.
                            Call of <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi> would not interfere their plans
                            and some British nationals undoubtedly would take passage on <hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Preliminary instructions prior to meeting Executive Committee American
                            Association August 1 would be helpful.</p>
                        <p>Sent Department; repeated Nanking 1650, EmbOff, Canton 925, ConGen,
                            Canton 130, Hankow 57.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">McConaughy</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>