<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Consul at Shanghai (
                        McConaughy
                    )Repeated to the Ambassadors in the
                        United Kingdom and Norway as Nos. 2934 and 366, respectively.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1337</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1337</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-08-17T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-08-17T17:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="quarantine-blockade" subject="blockade" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919" lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-08-17T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-08-17T17:00:00-05:00" n="1337" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1337">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.79693/8–1249: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Consul at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">McConaughy</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="23" xml:id="d1337fn23">Repeated to the Ambassadors in the
                        United Kingdom and Norway as Nos. 2934 and 366, respectively.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-08-17T18:00:00-04:00">August 17, 1949—6 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1631. Ref urtel 3212 Aug 12<note n="24" xml:id="d1337fn24">Not printed.</note>
                    and related messages Dept desires clarify its position. Dept has opposed
                    establishment internal air service with Amer assistance in Commie territory and
                    has solicited adoption similar stand by UK and other friendly govts because it
                    believed not in our interest to assist Commies to create internal mechanism of
                    high value to consolidation their political control of area. Dept remains of
                    this view on basis of which it requested NWA to discontinue negots with Commies
                    for such service.</p>
                <pb facs="1310" n="1300" xml:id="pg_1300"/>
                <p>Re establishment shuttle service Shanghai–Hong Kong originally proposed by
                    Jardine-Matheson and subsequently by NWA per urtel 2947 July 28, Dept believed
                    and still believes such service would provide Commies easy access to outer air
                    world and hence militate against early restoration scheduled services into
                    Shanghai on established basis. Latter is objective of US Govt and believed
                    likewise to be objective Brit, French and other govts concerned, as well as that
                    of NWA and PAA.<note n="25" xml:id="d1337fn25">Pan American Airways.</note> Dept
                    desires point out however that prerequisite to such scheduled operation wld be
                    assurance unmolested entry and exit by both Nats and Commies since resort to
                    night flights for purpose running “blockade” wld obviously involve undesirable
                    risk incidents. Dept prepared support in any appropriate manner both NWA and PAA
                    in restoration regular services on above basis but frankly doubts early
                    feasibility.</p>
                <p>Dept has recognized value proposed shuttles to relieve claustrophobia Shanghai
                    fon community. Dept however has believed that provision facilities for
                    evacuation is the first objective and could best be accomplished by surface
                    vessels and as you know has been active this connection. In light increased
                    pressure for evacuation, contd uncertainty safe passage for ships and disturbing
                    delays grant exit permits by Shanghai Commies, Dept entirely prepared reexamine
                    air shuttle possibilities with exclusive emphasis on evacuation fon nationals
                    from Shanghai. For such operation however approval both Nats and Commies clearly
                    desirable if not in fact essential. Accordingly any such plans shld be projected
                    on basis most likely to be acceptable to both Nats and Commies, which in Depts
                    view wld be specific number special flights from Shanghai to Okinawa by NWA
                    and/or PAA. Dept on your recommendation will immed seek safe passage from Nat
                    Govt for any definite proposal such service. Similarly prepared attempt
                    facilitate special shuttle by these lines or joint air service with
                    Jardine-Matheson or other sponsorship from Shanghai to Hong Kong provided
                    emphasis and operation in fact clearly based on evacuation. Dept. however
                    dubious securing Nat approval to Hong Kong flights on any basis acceptable to
                    Commies and vice versa.</p>
                <p>You are authorized to convey gist foregoing in confidence to NWA and PAA reps,
                    Committee Amer Association and, to extent applicable, to Jardine-Matheson.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
