<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Congressional Relations ( (McFall))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="223"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/11–3049</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Assistant Secretary of
                        State for Congressional Relations</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                    >McFall</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-30">November 30,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell>Senator Alexander Smith</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Secretary</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>H—Mr. McFall</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Senator Smith opened the conversation by stating that he had come to see the
                    Secretary just to give him the benefit of some observations that he felt quite
                    strongly about in connection with Far Eastern developments.</p>
                <p>He first made reference to what he considered to be a “divided military authority
                    in the Far East”. It was pointed out that General MacArthur<note n="49"
                        xml:id="d223fn49">General of the Army Douglas MacArthur, Supreme Commander,
                        Allied Powers in Japan.</note> had complete control of both the economic and
                    military problems in Japan and the surrounding islands and that the U.S. Navy
                    was apparently in control in China, and in his and several others’ opinions this
                    provoked a state of affairs that was most undesirable and inefficient. The
                    Senator did not appear to be too clear in his own mind as to what he thought
                    should be done, but the Secretary gave him to understand that we had no military
                    control of any kind in China now (the Navy having been withdrawn) and that any
                    military decisions affecting China rest in the Pentagon Building. The Secretary
                    told Senator Smith that we were giving consideration to the possibility of
                    establishing an ambassador-at-large somewhere in the general area of the Far
                    East who might be used to tie in loose ends and <pb facs="0216" n="206"
                        xml:id="pg_206"/> serve as a focal point for representing our interest in
                    that area. It was emphasized, however, that no decision had been made on this
                    subject as yet.</p>
                <p>The Senator next expressed his serious concern about the disadvantages that would
                    accrue to the United States in the recognition of China. He stated that it was
                    his considered opinion that the ground for the current Chinese development had
                    been laid in Russia as long as twenty years ago and that the Russians had worked
                    assiduously on the fulfillment of their aggrandizement in this direction since
                    that time. He stated that he could see no possibility whatsoever of any Titoism
                    developing in China and that he felt any commercial advantages that might be
                    gained out of recognition of the Communist regime would not compensate for the
                    psychological defeat that would be ours as a result of recognition. The
                    Secretary then told him that he had read the Senator’s letter<note n="50"
                        xml:id="d223fn50">November 5, <ref target="#pg_173">p. 173</ref>.</note> to
                    him about China with interest and that he wanted to assure him that in the first
                    place no thought would be given to recognition until <hi rend="italic">at
                        least</hi> three factors had been served—(1) that all or substantially all
                    of the territory of China had actually been conquered; (2) that any government
                    to be recognized had shown its fitness to comply with international obligations;
                    and (3) that there was an evident will on the part of the people to accept the
                    government that had been established. The Senator then asked him what he thought
                    England would do regarding recognition. The Secretary replied that he believed
                    they would certainly do nothing until after the conference in January with the
                    Dominions, upon which occasion there was a probability that this issue would be
                    canvassed thoroughly. What they would do thereafter the Secretary indicated he
                    could not predict. The Senator stated that he had a talk with Chiang Kai Shek
                    and “many other influential Chinese leaders”. He stated that he had had
                    extensive conversations with K. C. Wu<note n="50a" xml:id="d223fn50a">Former
                        Mayor of Shanghai.</note> for whom he had a very high regard. (It appeared
                    that he had confined himself rather closely to the Chiang Kai Shek coterie in
                    his discussions on China.) At this point in the conversation a complete
                    difference of opinion arose between the Secretary and the Senator as regards
                    Chiang Kai Shek “absconding” with the Chinese government funds. The Senator
                    opined that he felt the Generalissimo took the only feasible course open to him
                    in taking the government funds with him to Formosa. The Secretary replied that
                    he could not share that thought in any way, that he felt the taking was
                    absolutely wrong and that no fair view of the situation could permit of any
                    other judgment. After a valiant but completely unsuccessful effort on the part
                    of the <pb facs="0217" n="207" xml:id="pg_207"/> Senator to convince the
                    Secretary that he should modify his view on Chiang, the Senator concluded by
                    stating that it was obvious they shared different feelings on the subject but
                    the main thing now was the future, not the past, and he then repeated his
                    fervent hope that we would not accord any recognition to the Communist
                    Government, certainly in the immediate present. The Secretary indicated he did
                    not feel there was any real difference of opinion on that, that while he could
                    not say we would <hi rend="italic">never</hi> recognize the Communist Government
                    he wanted to repeat the assurance that he would exercise every form of caution
                    and considered study before any move in this direction was made. The Senator
                    seemed to be satisfied with this statement.</p>
                <p>Next the Senator brought up the question of Formosa. He stated that he had talked
                    to “many military authorities” in the Far East who had told him that they
                    regarded the retention of Formosa as of the utmost strategic importance to the
                    United States. He said that his own personal view was that it was to our
                    compelling interest to hold on to the island by any means short of actual war,
                    and that he felt we should pursue the possibility of adopting one of two
                    alternatives by way of protecting our interests in that area—(1) to arrange, if
                    possible, a trusteeship of the island by the United Nations (he conceded that
                    this was probably not practicable) or (2) a military occupation on our part of
                    Formosa. It was his thought that such a military occupation would protect our
                    strategic interests in that area which he regarded as “still strictly speaking a
                    part of Japan,” even though by the Cairo Declaration<note n="51"
                        xml:id="d223fn51">For text of statement by President Roosevelt,
                        Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek, and British Prime Minister Winston S.
                        Churchill, see <ref target="frus1943CairoTehran#pg_448">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conferences at Cairo and
                            Tehran, 1943, p. 448</ref>.</note> we had permitted the Chinese to take
                    over. The Senator stated that he felt “it would be better for Communists to try
                    to dislodge us from the island first before we would have to come in later and
                    try to do the same thing with them”. The Secretary said he felt the Senator
                    should know that this subject is receiving constant consideration, that there
                    had been a half dozen meetings with the National Defense on the subject, with
                    another one arranged for this week, and that there is some difference of opinion
                    among military authorities as to the strategic importance of the island. The
                    Secretary said he hoped a firm decision concerning the matter would be
                    forthcoming at an early date.</p>
                <p>In passing, the Senator at this point told the Secretary he wanted to pay a
                    tribute to the resourcefulness of Consul General Karl Rankin in Hong Kong, who,
                    he stated, was a man of real ability and was doing a fine job under difficult
                    circumstances.</p>
                <pb facs="0218" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/>
                <p>The Senator next presented a suggestion which he asked the Secretary to turn over
                    in his mind. He proposed the setting up of a combined sub-committee of the House
                    Foreign Affairs and the Senate Foreign Relations Committees to go to the Far
                    East with the idea of acting in an advisory capacity to Jessup, Fosdick and
                        Case<note n="52" xml:id="d223fn52">Raymond B. Fosdick and Everett Case on
                        July 30 were appointed consultants to the Department on Far Eastern
                        matters.</note> in their investigations of the situation in the Far East.
                    The Senator seemed to feel this would be helpful to both Committees of the
                    Congress in working on Chinese and other related problems in the future. The
                    Secretary reminded him that the Department feels that a matter of this kind
                    should be brought before the full Foreign Affairs and Foreign Relations
                    Committees for discussion and made no commitment on the Senator’s recommendation
                    for the creation of the special group.</p>
                <p>The Senator told the Secretary that his report,<note n="53" xml:id="d223fn53"
                        >Report to the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, November 29, 1949, <hi
                            rend="italic">Congressional Record</hi>, vol. 96, pt. 1, pp. 156–160,
                        Exhibit A.</note> which he will give to the Committee, of his trip to the
                    Far East, will be mailed to the Secretary and to me within the next day or
                    so.</p>
                <p>On departing the Senator expressed to me his firm resolve to do everything he
                    possibly can to prevent any political considerations from being brought next
                    Congressional session into questions concerning our foreign policy, as he felt
                    it was of transcendent importance that we avoid any appearance of any domestic
                    disaffection for our foreign policies in the trying times in which we find
                    ourselves.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
