<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in India (
                        Henderson
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d234</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">234</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-12-06T11:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-12-06T11:30:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" subject="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-06T11:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-06T11:30:00-05:00" n="234" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d234">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01/12–649</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-06T22:00:00+05:30">December 6, 1949—10 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received December 7—4:31 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1518. 1. During final talk with Bajpai today before his departure on 8th for New
                    York, he touched briefly again on China. He said that GOI had not yet received
                    indication of US reaction to India’s statement of position regarding Chinese
                    recognition (Embtel 1489, December 2). He hoped that US would understand that in
                    recognizing China, GOI was not undertaking to “flirt” with Chinese Communists
                    or, for that matter, with Soviet or any other Communists. GOI fully recognized
                    Communist danger and had no illusion regarding present tie-up between Communist
                    China and Communist Russia. GOI, however, would be in embarrassing position if
                    Burma and other Asian powers should recognize Communist China while India held
                    back. Furthermore, if GOI should wait until after UK recognition it would be
                    charged internally with following in UK’s footsteps rather than having foreign
                    policy of its own.</p>
                <pb facs="0226" n="216" xml:id="pg_216"/>
                <p>2. Bajpai said that although GOI was continuing formally its present policy of
                    neutrality between two power blocs, it was in practice making more and more
                    decisions “based on merit” in harmony with Western policy, particularly US
                    policy, rather than with Soviet policy. Illustration of GOI’s determination not
                    to appease Chinese Communists was its decision to make representation regarding
                    Ward regardless fact that Ward had been released (paragraph 3 Embtel 1489). In
                    fact GOI had made representation whereas UK had failed to do so.</p>
                <p>3. In response my query, he showed me copy of note handed to Chinese Communist
                    government. This note recited facts relating to case of Ward and Stokes<note n="66" xml:id="d234fn66">William N. Stokes, Vice Consul at Mukden.</note> as
                    received from US Government and closed with following statement: “The Government
                    of India wishes to express their concern over the facts disclosed by the
                    Government of the US, since they constitute a departure from diplomatic
                    usage.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
