<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul General at Shanghai (
                        Cabot
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d302</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">302</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-01-26T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-01-26T08:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-26T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-26T08:00:00-05:00" n="302" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d302">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">894A.01/1–2649: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Shanghai</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cabot</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-26T21:00:00+08:00">January 26, 1949—9 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received January 27—12:01 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>263. Joshua Liao, Formosan Re-emancipation League leader, (mytel 2449, November
                    17 to Department,<note n="41" xml:id="d302fn41">
                        <ref target="frus1948v07#pg_585">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, China, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, p. 585</ref>.</note> repeated Nanking
                    1855) has again approached Consul General. Expressing concern over reported
                    recent arrival Taiwan of American military equipment, Liao protested against
                    further American aid serving to “facilitate oppression” Taiwanese by Central
                    Government “SS troops” and voiced appeal that US assist or at least remain
                    neutral toward “spontaneous” Taiwanese revolt which Liao professed to expect
                    near future. Also stressed his hope following the revolt American army units in
                    Formosa would assist in disarming Government forces.</p>
                <p>Liao claimed natives well armed and trained and sure of success “this time”.
                    Intimated that revolt would likely start upon fall of Nanking taking open
                    underground form (sabotage and assassination) depending on revolutionaries’
                    strength. He implied he himself would prefer await establishment new Chinese
                    Nationalist coalition government before making decision to launch revolt but
                    that some of his associates were growing restive. He insisted that revolt will
                    be neither anti-American nor Communist inspired.</p>
                <p>Liao admitted knowledge Nationalists have 6 divisions in Formosa. View this
                    admission and of other remarks, it is suspected that he may envisage “success”
                    in terms less of military victory than of world dramatization of his people’s
                    predicament which will gain attention and sympathy of UN.<note n="42" xml:id="d302fn42">United Nations.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0287" n="277" xml:id="pg_277"/>
                <p>Sent Nanking 202, repeated Department, Taipei 13, pouched Hong Kong.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Cabot</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
