<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="384" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d384">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">894A.00/5–2449</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Livingston T.
                                Merchant</persName> to the Director of the Office of Far Eastern
                            Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Butterworth</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-24">May 24, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>United States Government policy with respect to Formosa was established in
                        NSC 37/2,<note n="60" xml:id="d384fn60">February 3, <ref target="#pg_281">p.
                                281</ref>.</note> approved by the President on February 3, 1949, and
                        in NSC 37/5,<note n="61" xml:id="d384fn61">March 1, <ref target="#pg_290">p.
                                290</ref>.</note> approved by the President on March 3, 1949. In
                        essence, this policy was designed to secure the denial of Formosa to any
                        Communist or Communist-dominated government on the Mainland. The means
                        available to secure this objective were stipulated to be diplomatic and
                        economic support of the governing group on the Island. A show of force or
                        the employment of U.S. military forces for the security or defense of
                        Formosa was specifically ruled out at this time. The documents under
                        reference took into account the JCS study of the strategic importance of
                        Formosa and contemplated that, as soon as we knew with what group we must
                        deal, there would be an immediate approach to the Governor for the purpose
                        of securing from him certain assurances in return for which ECA would
                        proceed with its suspended industrial reconstruction program on the
                        Island.</p>
                    <p>In February the groundwork was being laid for peace negotiations, later to
                        prove abortive, in Peiping between the Communists and representatives of
                        Acting President Li Tsung-Jen. Despite the fact that Governor Chen had been
                        appointed by and owed his primary loyalty <pb facs="0348" n="338" xml:id="pg_338"/> to the Gimo, the risk was recognized that from the
                        peace negotiations there might emerge a coalition government which could
                        claim wide support and which could successfully extend its authority over
                        Formosa. Despite the importance which this risk gave to reaching promptly an
                        understanding with Governor Chen, the Department reached the conclusion that
                        delay in committing to Chen full support through the ECA program originally
                        envisaged was justified by the fact that he typified the unenlightened
                        leadership of the most reactionary element in the KMT and by definition
                        appeared incapable of providing Formosa with the sort of liberal government
                        which alone could ameliorate the hatred of the Formosans for their Mainland
                        rulers and in so doing build up political stability on the Island which
                        would minimize, if not eliminate, its susceptibility to Communist
                        infiltration and ultimate seizure of control from within.</p>
                    <p>The primary reason for delay was our knowledge that the Acting President
                        desired to replace Chen Cheng with General Sun Li-jen, an American trained
                        officer of integrity, competence and liberal philosophy. To date his efforts
                        have been unsuccessful for reasons which are now clear from the open battle
                        between Li and the Gimo for undisputed personal control of the remaining
                        treasure, territory and armed forces not yet under Communist control. In
                        this personal conflict for power, Formosa has become the key pawn and Chen
                        Cheng’s exclusive loyalty to the Gimo is plain.</p>
                    <p>In this interval during which no direct discussions were held with Governor
                        Chen, ECA continued to hold its projected industrial reconstruction program
                        in suspense. ECA proceeded, however, with its scheduled importation of
                        nearly fifty thousand tons of fertilizer for Formosa. Certain medical
                        supplies and odds and ends of flour and cotton yarn were likewise brought in
                        by ECA, in part for the purpose of financing its own local currency
                        expenditures, thereby to avoid contributing in any way to the rampant
                        inflation. JCRR likewise proceeded with its planning for a program on
                        Formosa directed at the well-being of the farmers and comprehending such
                        operations as seed improvement and hog cholera serum manufacture.</p>
                    <p>During this same period, Chen Cheng entrenched himself in power, traveled and
                        talked freely around the Island, but accomplished little to improve either
                        the material or the political lot of the Formosans.</p>
                    <p>In November 1948 and in successive waves thereafter, rich refugees and units
                        of the armed forces streamed into Formosa from the mainland. The total of
                        such immigrants is variously estimated to run between five hundred thousand
                        and a million. The present troop strength on the Island is now estimated to
                        exceed two hundred thousand. The economic impact of this migration has been
                        tremendous. Many of the <pb facs="0349" n="339" xml:id="pg_339"/> civilian
                        refugees attempted to finance themselves by inward remittances while in the
                        case of the Army, Navy and Air Force the National Government looked to the
                        provincial treasury to feed and support them. The latter could do so only by
                        printing additional currency.</p>
                    <p>On April 20 the civil war erupted again with the Communist crossing of the
                        Yangtze, and with this development the immediate risk of a legal voluntary
                        turnover of Formosa to a new government participated in or dominated by the
                        Communists disappeared. The resumption of the war moreover sharpened the
                        conflict between Li and the Gimo and accumulating evidence suggests, almost
                        to the point of certainty, that the Gimo will raise his standard on
                        Formosa—to sit it out there until the third World War breaks out, a war
                        which he regards not only as inevitable but imminent. The Gimo no doubt
                        regards Formosa as secure. The CAF headquarters is there as are certain
                        naval units. The troops on the Island are still increasing as units are
                        withdrawn by sea from the Shanghai area and landed on Formosa. Moreover, the
                        Island is self-supporting in so far as food is concerned and in the vaults
                        of the Bank of Taiwan is nearly US$90,000,000 in gold. Finally, Chen Cheng
                        has provided a refuge for dozens of the Gimo’s oldest and most loyal
                        subordinates.</p>
                    <p>The developing situation described above requires a reconsideration of US
                        policy with respect to Formosa, with a view to recalculating the chances of
                        success for the policy as now laid down and for the purpose of exploring
                        alternative courses of action. The following factors are important in any
                        such reexamination: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>It is the firm resolution of the present Government of Formosa to
                                defend the Island against any Communist military assault and to seek
                                out and suppress any Communist internal activity. The United States
                                does not need to say or do anything to support or reinforce this
                                resolution since it is based on the strongest of all instincts,
                                personal self-preservation.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>An immediate military assault on the Island by the Communists
                                seems improbable (i.e., within the next six months). The preparation
                                of the necessary military expedition would seem to require at least
                                that length of time and there is no evidence yet at hand that the
                                Communists are directing their primary attention to Formosa.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>The Formosan population is restless and deeply resentful of their
                                Chinese rulers. They do not appear, however, to possess a
                                revolutionary organization, leadership or the arms to produce more
                                than a futile uprising which it would be within the means and
                                purpose of the Government quickly and bloodily to suppress. The
                                Formosans yearn for independence as children yearn for candy. They
                                have a child-like faith in the United States and its relative
                                disinterestedness which overt support of Chen Cheng would go far
                                toward destroying.</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>In the past six months the economy of Formosa has deteriorated
                                seriously and rapidly primarily because the population has suddenly
                                been increased by between ten and twenty percent and the new
                                arrivals <pb facs="0350" n="340" xml:id="pg_340"/> have been
                                economically non-productive. In these changed circumstances a total
                                ECA program at the annual rate of, say, twenty-five million dollars
                                U.S. could not positively and constructively affect the Island’s
                                economy and thereby, as originally hoped, bring political stability
                                in the wake of a net advance of the people’s livelihood.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>To summarize and over-simplify, we find ourselves faced on Formosa with a
                        situation very similar to that which confronted us on the Mainland a year
                        ago. The Government in power is corrupt and incompetent. Self preservation
                        dictates that it advance our national interest in the process of attempting
                        to preserve its own collective personal neck. The people which it rules hate
                        not only the Government but will hate any foreign country which morally and
                        materially gives its support to that Government. Yet there is no
                        possibility, short of the dangerous and risky effort to finance and promote
                        a <hi rend="italic">coup d’etat</hi>, that the present Government will be
                        replaced or alter its character in the direction of liberal political rule
                        and wise economic action.</p>
                    <p>It would seem practically that we are confronted by three possible lines of
                        action.</p>
                    <p>First would be to pursue and execute the policy laid down in NSC 37/2 and
                        37/5. Admittedly, this would have the advantage of action. The implicit
                        expression of support to the present Government would presumably encourage
                        them spiritually. The economic assistance if properly formulated and
                        directed would slow down, though not cure, the current economic decay. We
                        would, however, see the reservoir of Formosan goodwill to America drop
                        sharply and we would hand the Mainland Communists a ready-made irredentist
                        weapon for their propaganda. We would increase, rather than reduce the
                        vulnerability of many Chinese on the Island as well as the Formosans
                        themselves to Communist agitation.</p>
                    <p>The second course is briefly outlined in Taipei’s telegram no. 142 of May 4.
                        Essentially this would entail forthright action by the United States on a
                        bolder, more costly scale. The irredentist issue thereby created would of
                        course be far more serious than in the case of course one above. It would
                        involve acceptance of the fact that we would place ourselves on the
                        psycshological defensive and even more important, it would implicitly commit
                        United States Armed Forces to defend the Island if it came under
                        assault.</p>
                    <p>The third course available is substantially that envisaged in the closing
                        paragraph of Taipei’s telegram no. 141 of May 4. It means relying on the
                        present Government’s personal interest in resistance, providing some
                        economic aid of a character designed to reach and directly affect the little
                        men of Formosa, particularly the farmers. It is admittedly a policy of
                        calculated inaction colored with opportunism <pb facs="0351" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/> and it should be accompanied by vigorous secret
                        spadework with those friendly governments which, like ourselves, are
                        concerned with the strategic importance of Formosa. This spadework should be
                        directed to the ultimate raising of the issue of Formosa in the UN,
                        preferably as a result of an appeal by the native population, supported, if
                        such can be encouraged or arranged, by Mainland elements on the Island.</p>
                    <p>No one can have had very high hopes that economic and diplomatic steps alone
                        could guarantee the denial of Formosa to a government unfriendly to us. When
                        they choose to put their minds on it, the Communists should be able to take
                        over the Island either by assault or more likely by an infiltration which
                        would include getting at not only the troops but very possibly individual
                        leaders of military units on the Island. The JCS has made clear its
                        unwillingness to contemplate at this time the commitment of U.S. Armed
                        Forces to the defense of Formosa, the only action which could guarantee the
                        security of Formosa from our point of view. If this is a reasonable
                        assessment of the situation and the possibilities of achieving our ends,
                        then it should behoove the United States to guard its moral position not
                        only on Formosa and in China but throughout all Southeast Asia by minimizing
                        its association with a governing group which has already in a larger theater
                        demonstrated its incompetence and unpopularity.</p>
                    <p>Accordingly, I recommend adoption of course three described above. This will
                        entail the Department reopening the matter in the National Security Council.
                        This should be done promptly. Assuming NSC agrees, then the Department
                        should issue an official public statement along the lines of the statement
                        which was to have been made to Governor Chen under NSC 37/2. This should be
                        accompanied by an active effort to explain to key members of the Congress
                        and responsible newspapermen the underlying elements and difficulties in the
                        Formosan situation.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Livingston</hi> T. <hi rend="smallcaps">Merchant</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>