<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Consul at Taipei (
                        Edgar
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d480</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">480</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-12-20T02:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-12-20T02:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-20T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-20T02:00:00-05:00" n="480" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d480">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/12–2049: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Taipei</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Edgar</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Taipei</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-20T15:00:00+08:00">December 20, 1949—3 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received December 20—8:24 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>857. Provincial political crisis has developed over Wu appointments in new
                    Government. What he calls his “social revolution” for Taiwan is encountering
                    expected difficulties (see mytel No. 858 dated December 20, 1949 for published
                    details).</p>
                <p>K. C. Wu tells me privately he cannot make changes now and maintain dignity. Also
                    still believes Chiang Wei-chuan is best representative of people although
                    unpopular with intellectuals and Taiwanese vested interests. Latter have control
                    of PPC. Wu suspects C. C. Huang’s group of causing alarming recent rise in black
                    market rate <pb facs="0458" n="448" xml:id="pg_448"/> citing their control local
                    banks and newspapers. Also suspects Chen Cheng of fostering resistance. States
                    lack of time precluded fuller advance negotiations which would have resolved
                    differences.</p>
                <p>C. C. Huang tells me he has attempted be mediator in fight. Has high hopes for Wu
                    administration but concurs in dislike of Chiang Wei-chuan, and Ju Peng Teh. To
                    avoid charge of PPC revolt against Nationalist Government, he had PPC pay
                    respectful call on Generalissimo after passing resolution. Generalissimo urged
                    cooperation and continuance of session but members failed reassemble this
                    morning as scheduled. At PPC call on Chen Cheng yesterday, Chen suggested
                    compromise plan including seating of new government and early resignation of
                    objected commissioners. Chen presented this to Wu late last night. Wu’s reaction
                    still unknown although morning press suggests general acceptance.</p>
                <p>Wu tells me he has received calls by leaders of local laborers, dock workers, et
                    cetera pledging support and expects to win out over vested interests of doubtful
                    probity, intellectuals, and local reactionaries.</p>
                <p>Wu has had 2-hour talk with Craig and Tarring on local economic problems and both
                    parties came away well impressed.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edgar</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
