<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="523" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d523">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.20 Mission/4–449</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Fined Report by Major General <persName type="from">David
                                G. Barr</persName>, Director of the <gloss type="to">Joint United
                                States Military Advisory Group in China</gloss>
                        </hi><note n="49" xml:id="d523fn49">Prepared for the Joint Chiefs of Staff;
                            copy transmitted to the Department on April 4 by the Department of the
                            Army. JUSMAG after departing from China on January 29, operated in Tokyo
                            until it suspended activities on March 3, 1949.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-28">28 February 1949</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>[Here follow four sections, “Introduction,” “JUSMAGChina,” “Special
                        Activities”, and “Miscellaneous”.]</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">V. <hi rend="italic">Future Plans</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>18. Continuation of JUSMAGChina</p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>General—JUSMAGChina was forced to leave China long before its
                                mission was accomplished. Whether that mission, to create a modern
                                    <pb facs="0506" n="496" xml:id="pg_496"/> armed force in keeping
                                with the needs and resources of China, could ever be accomplished is
                                questionable. Even with a considerable outlay of American personnel
                                and large supplies of military aid over a long period of years, an
                                armed force comparable in effectiveness to that of even mediocre
                                United States troops probably cannot be produced within a
                                decade.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>United States policy—The policy of the United States has been to
                                oppose Communism. If this policy is continued on the mainland of
                                Asia, the present Chinese Nationalist Government or a non-Communist
                                successor, with all its weaknesses, is the only possible agent.
                                There is no alternative short of armed intervention. Active military
                                support of this Government by the United States will require
                                advisors who can, for all practical purposes, command the Chinese
                                Armed Forces, and will require a large amount of aid in the form of
                                arms, ammunition and materials. The cost of this will be great,
                                perhaps excessive; whether <hi rend="italic">too great</hi> is
                                beyond the scope of this report. Regardless of United States
                                policies, desires and willingness, no advisory group can accomplish
                                much unless actively desired by the Chinese and fully supported by
                                them.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Conditions—Should JUSMAGChina be reactivated, the following
                                conditions are essential: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>That United States policy be one of active opposition to
                                        Communism on the mainland of Asia.</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>That United States policy be for the continuation of
                                        military aid to China for a prolonged period, the
                                        distribution of this aid to be controlled by the United
                                        States.</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>That the prohibition against operational advice be relaxed
                                        and that advisors be furnished in accordance with
                                        needs.</item>
                                    <label>(4)</label>
                                    <item>That the Chinese actively desire an advisory group and
                                        that there be definite <hi rend="italic">written</hi>
                                        agreement between the governments concerned, as to mission,
                                        scope and functioning and as to responsibility for logistic
                                        support.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Views of Deputy Director—See recommendations A and B, page 23,
                                Annex 4.<note n="50" xml:id="d523fn50">Not printed.</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">VI. <hi rend="italic">Recommendations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>19. Continuation of JUSMAGChina</p>
                    <p>I recommend that JUSMAGChina be reactivated only if the following conditions
                        are met in full:</p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That United States policy is one of active opposition to Communism
                                on the mainland of Asia.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That United States policy is to continue military air [<hi rend="italic">aid</hi>] supplies to China for a prolonged
                                period, the distribution of this aid to be controlled by the United
                                States.</item>
                            <pb facs="0507" n="497" xml:id="pg_497"/>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That the prohibition against operational advice is relaxed and
                                that advisors are furnished in accordance with needs.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That the Chinese actively desire an advisory group and that there
                                is definite <hi rend="italic">written</hi> agreement between the
                                governments concerned as to its mission, scope and functioning and
                                as to responsibility for logistic support.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>20. JCS directive</p>
                    <p>I recommend that, in event of reactivation, the present JCS directive be
                        revised to accomplish the following:</p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Provide a single Director who will have command responsibility for
                                the coordination, operation and common administration of the group
                                and who will not at the same time be chief of an advisory
                                division.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Authorize operational advice and entry of advisors into combat
                                areas at the discretion of the Director.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>21. Allotment of advisors</p>
                    <p>I recommend that, in event of reactivation, advisors be provided on a scale
                        approximately as follows:</p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To the Ministry, to the Supreme Staff, and to the Headquarters of
                                the Major Forces: the minimum to further the development attained
                                during the past two years. If reactivation took place in the near
                                future, this group of top level advisors would number about
                                150.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To general and special service schools: approximately four
                                officers and two enlisted men per school.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To training centers and units in training: three officers per
                                center and one officer and one enlisted man per division and per
                                regiment.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To Air Force and Navy installations: on a scale comparable with
                                the above with due consideration for their existing strength and
                                resources.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>22. Allotment of overhead</p>
                    <p>I recommend that, in case of reactivation, common services, exclusive of
                        air-lift, be furnished by the Department of the Army and that air-lift be
                        furnished by the Department of the Air Force; that the administrative
                        overhead, exclusive of air-lift, be a minimum but that initial plans provide
                        about 400 military for this purpose.</p>
                    <p>23. Supply</p>
                    <p>I recommend that, in event of reactivation, supply be based on the Far East
                        Command with maximum direct delivery to the largest JUSMAGChina group and
                        that theater stocks be held to minimum consistent with scheduled
                        deliveries.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">David</hi> G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Barr</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>