<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d582</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">582</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recn8b1d7iCOsszeq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100445"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum products</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recmLoDjMiF4yt3cM" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">U.S.
                        Congress</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec0t1KvI4owTG5qK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recR0zhXxdC8M9meR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic recovery</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recSj13D27GJZ1DiT" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="582"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d582">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.93/11–1449</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Secretary of State</hi>
                    <note n="44" xml:id="d582fn44">Transmitted to the Assistant Secretary of State
                        for Far Eastern Affairs (Butterworth).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-14">November 14,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Possible Aid to the Forces Still Opposing the Chinese
                        Communists</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The President handed me the attached undated, unsigned memorandum with respect to
                    possible aid to the forces still opposing the Chinese Communists. He asked that
                    I read this and return it to him.</p>
                <p>As the Secretary will have to discuss this matter with the President when he
                    returns it on his next visit, please prepare an evaluation to form the basis of
                    such discussion.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">I</p>
                    <p>Russia’s atomic bomb—Russian pressure for recognition of her acknowledged
                        satellite, the Chinese Communist Government—the abandonment of Canton—all in
                        a few weeks—force the United States again to decide what it is going to do
                        about China.</p>
                    <p>Taken together, these events portend ominous consequences if the Chinese
                        Communists are allowed to overrun all China for Russian account. If the
                        Communists are allowed to consolidate all China—if no free space is left in
                        which the liberal elements in China can find a base to reorganize—it is only
                        a question of time when all Asia is beyond the possibility of cooperation
                        with the West and is in the anti-American orbit.</p>
                    <p>With the highlands of South China in enemy hands, the lowlands of Burma,
                        French Indo-China and Siam can not be held.</p>
                    <p>Without at least a year’s delay in the Soviet timetable in China, even India
                        will not dare to take the side of the West and risk being a Poland. The back
                        door to Russia will then be completely closed. She can strike toward Western
                        Europe or toward Alaska, without her old fears of complications in the rear
                        of her trans-Ural war production.</p>
                    <p>In order to secure this long-term objective, the Russians have been most
                        persistently and painstakingly supporting the Chinese Communists. Besides
                        turning their powerful propaganda machine in the U.S. <pb facs="0593"
                            n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/> to win support for the Chinese Communists as
                        mere agrarian reformers, Russia has poured vast quantities of Japanese and
                        Czech arms into the Communist armies, and has assigned numerous advisers to
                        the staffs of the Communist Generals, besides planning out all their
                        campaigns for them. They have also sent entire detachments of Mongolian,
                        North Korean and Japanese artillery, cavalry and technical troops to support
                        the Communists. Contrasted with that, since the end of the war, U.S.
                        assistance to China had been by fits and starts, and American Military
                        advisers were precluded by their directives from giving any operational
                        advice to the Nationalists.</p>
                    <p>The recent abandonment of Canton without more of a fight was a necessary
                        logistical decision on the assumption that the U.S. had not made up its mind
                        whether to help. In three months an allotment of funds advanced from the
                        Formosan reserve by agreement between Chiang Kai Shek and the Executive Yuan
                        that it would be the budget for an entire year, had become exhausted (see
                            footnote).<note n="*" xml:id="d582fn1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Secret—Not to be published or quoted</hi>
                            <p>By the end of May the Central Bank reserves consisted of (<hi
                                    rend="italic">a</hi>) 4,000,000 oz. of gold and (<hi
                                    rend="italic">b</hi>) silver and foreign exchange to the total
                                value of U.S. $20,000,000. During the last four and a half months,
                                over and above any tax receipts which the long-exhausted countryside
                                could furnish, the military and civilian expenditure of the
                                Government absorbed all the silver and foreign exchange and nearly
                                2,000,000 oz. of gold, which latter, at the Chinese market rate of
                                U.S. $40 per oz., was equivalent to U.S. $80,000,000. The drain on
                                the reserves was therefore at the rate of U.S. $22,000,000 per
                                month. Even at that the troops and civilian officials were poorly
                                paid with consequent low morale. Computing at this rate of
                                expenditure, the remaining 2,000,000 oz. of gold in reserve could
                                only last the Government another three months.</p>
                            <p>The above figures were never published despite insidious attacks
                                against the Generalissimo for not giving the troops sufficient funds
                                from Taiwan reserves, because knowledge of this rate of exhaustion
                                would give comfort to the enemy. [Footnote in the source text.]</p>
                        </note> This was due to the heavy fighting in the determined stand before
                        Canton as the Communists pressed for a symbolical victory at the time of the
                        Russian bid for the recognition of their puppet government.</p>
                    <p>To give up Canton was a terrifically cruel decision to take but the desperate
                        Chinese leaders could only make their plans on the worst assumption; i.e.
                        that U.S. aid might never arrive and that they would have to husband their
                        remaining resources of money for last-ditch stands in more easily defendable
                        locations. There they might have a better chance of surviving until any
                        American help that might come would arrive.</p>
                    <p>Canton was not fought for—because at the going rate of attrition there would
                        have been no money left to fight with anywhere—Canton or anywhere in a short
                        while. Not to have defaulted would have been like the charge at
                        Balaklava—“magnificent, but not war.” The abandonment of Canton rightly
                        understood does not mean the Chinese are giving up the war. Rather it means
                        that they are intelligently trying to continue it.</p>
                    <pb facs="0594" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/>
                    <p rend="center">II</p>
                    <p>President Truman and Congress have stated their eagerness to help
                        non-Communist China in any feasible way. With the fall of Canton it is time
                        to resurvey the scene with a view to answering the following questions: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>What areas can and should be held against the Communists?</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>What forces are available to hold such areas?</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>What leadership is available—civilian and military?</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>What assistance could the U.S. give?</item>
                            <label>E.</label>
                            <item>What means are available for such assistance?</item>
                            <label>F.</label>
                            <item>What are the prospects of success?</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">A. <hi rend="italic">What areas can and should be held
                            against the Communists?</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The military situation in China today is comparable to that of the critical
                        period during the war with Japan. The main objective was and is to defend
                        the eastern boundaries of the provinces of Szechuan, Kweichow and Kwangsi.
                        Attack and defense problems are expected to revolve around the familiar
                        pattern of the previous struggle, but there is one major advantage to the
                        Chinese Government that was not present during the war with Japan.</p>
                    <p>This is the possession of the islands of Taiwan and Hainan—the so called
                        “twin eyes of the Chinese dragon.” The importance of Taiwan is recognized.
                        Equally important is the island of Hainan, because it links the Nationalist
                        mainland with the outside world. The beachhead of Hainan is the Laichow
                        Peninsula, and running thence through the mountainous terrain to link up
                        with South West and Western China, Southwestern tip of Kwangtung, Kwangsi,
                        Kweichow, Szechuan, Sikang and Yunnan (see map<note n="45" xml:id="d582fn45"
                            >Map not attached to file copy.</note>). This bloc will be a barrier to
                        the downhill infiltration of Chinese Communists into French Indo-China,
                        Siam, Burma and India.</p>
                    <p>This bloc is economically self-sufficient, particularly in rice supply, as
                        follows: <table cols="2" rows="7">
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">(1) Szechuan</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">—large surplus.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">(2) Sikang</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">—small shortage, to be met from Szechuan
                                    surplus.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">(3) Yunnan</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">—insufficiency, to be met from Szechuan
                                    surplus.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">(4) Kwangsi</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">—self-supporting.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>(5) Kweichow</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">—small shortage.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">(6) Hainan Island</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">—short 40,000 tons a year, to be supplied
                                    from Taiwan.</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">(7) Taiwan</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">—self-supporting. It is proposed that an
                                    additional 150,000 tons of fertilizers shall be authorized for
                                    Taiwan under the E.C.A. economic aid program to increase the
                                    rice yield by some 150,000 tons for Hainan for military and
                                    other requirements.</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0595" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft">B. <hi rend="italic">What forces are available to hold such
                            areas?</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Troops of doubtful quality or loyalty have already been eliminated or have
                        deserted, but there remains a loyal fighting force of over a million men:
                            <table cols="3" rows="7">
                            <row>
                                <cell>Taiwan</cell>
                                <cell role="num">250,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Laichow Peninsula and Kwangsi</cell>
                                <cell role="num">300,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Hainan</cell>
                                <cell role="num">50,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Kweichow-Hunan border</cell>
                                <cell role="num">100,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Szechuan and Sikang</cell>
                                <cell role="num">300,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Yunnan</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom" role="num">100,000</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">1,100,000</cell>
                                <cell>men</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>In the mountainous areas to which they have retreated, if they are well paid
                        and munitioned, they could easily hold their ground against any force the
                        Communists could send against them.</p>
                    <p>In addition to the ground troops, there are intact the main body of the Air
                        Force and the Navy, which the U.S. Government helped to develop and
                        train.</p>
                    <p>The Air Force personnel number 100,000 men, which is far superior to anything
                        the Communists possess.</p>
                    <p>The Navy personnel number 50,000 men, which has been conducting an
                        astonishingly effective blockade of Communist ports.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">C. <hi rend="italic">What Leadership is available?</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>New dynamic leadership is required to infuse new life into the fighting
                        forces. Any change of leadership which the U.S. wishes made in order to make
                        aid effective will be acceptable. The U.S. only needs to “indicate” what its
                        opinions are.</p>
                    <p>Very tentatively it is suggested that the Commander-in-Chief should be
                        Lieutenant General Sun Li Jen, a Virginia Military Institute graduate in his
                        late forties, trained in India with General Stilwell, who made an
                        outstanding record both during the World War and in fighting the Communists.
                        He is well and favorably known to Americans, and is now Commander-in-Chief
                        of the troops in Taiwan. He is a relatively young man but enjoys general
                        confidence and will be definitely acceptable to both the Generalissimo and
                        Acting President Li Tsung Jen, who can be counted on to give their entire
                        support. If, in addition, it is known that American support in the shape of
                        a military mission and financial and material aid will be back of General
                        Sun, he will have complete authority over all the fighting forces, and will
                        not be interfered with.</p>
                    <p>Equally important is a new civilian leadership. To coordinate with military
                        reorganization, the Western trained liberals in China, who are crystalizing
                        around Dr. Hu Shih to form the new Chinese Liberal Party, should be given
                        political power to form a new cabinet. This new cabinet will command the
                        enthusiastic support of all anti-Communist <pb facs="0596" n="586"
                            xml:id="pg_586"/> elements. Again, whatever the U.S. “indicates” as
                        desirable can be arranged. At this present juncture a “revolution by
                        consent” could be obtained from the Kuomintang so that these liberals will
                        be installed. It is the intent of the Chinese Liberal Party to inaugurate
                        immediate military reforms, and to have a civilian as Minister of
                        Defense.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">D. <hi rend="italic">What assistance could the U.S.
                            give?</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>For the maintenance of troops, $40,000,000 a month is required. This is
                        broken up into: <table cols="3" rows="15">
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">1. Procurement of military supplies,
                                    consisting of the following major items:</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">$10,000,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Small arms</cell>
                                <cell>1.8 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Small arms ammunition</cell>
                                <cell>3.0 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Trench mortars and shells</cell>
                                <cell>.8 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Petroleum products</cell>
                                <cell>1.2 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Arsenal materials</cell>
                                <cell>.6 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Air and Navy spare parts</cell>
                                <cell>.8 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Air and Navy ammunition</cell>
                                <cell>.6 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Vehicles and parts</cell>
                                <cell>.6 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Miscellaneous</cell>
                                <cell>.6 million</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">2. Pay and maintenance for military
                                    personnel and operations:</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">$30,000,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Army personnel (in combat
                                    areas)</cell>
                                <cell>numbering</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,100,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Air Force personnel</cell>
                                <cell>numbering</cell>
                                <cell role="num">100,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">Navy personnel</cell>
                                <cell>numbering</cell>
                                <cell role="num">50,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 2em">International Volunteers</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>The above are of course, only tentative estimates which may be modified after
                        investigation by the U.S. Aid Field Mission mentioned below.</p>
                    <p>It is proposed that a budget should be made up for the five months up to and
                        including February–1950, when the U.S. Congress will have been in new
                        session for a month and will be in a position seriously to reconsider the
                        China situation. This budget would amount to $200,000,000; i.e. the
                        $40,000,000 per month detailed above.</p>
                    <p>To implement and supervise aid operations, it is proposed that a U.S. Aid
                        Field Mission be created, to be headed by a high-ranking U.S officer
                        appointed by the President.</p>
                    <p>The U.S. Aid Field Mission shall have broad powers covering allocation,
                        disbursement, and supervision of the U.S. Aid Fund, under policy directives
                        approved by the President. What is most important is that the Mission should
                        be able to give operational advice to the new Commander-in-Chief.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">E. <hi rend="italic">What means are available for such
                            assistance?</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Fortunately the bulk of these funds are already available, if the U.S.
                        Government decides to employ them.</p>
                    <pb facs="0597" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/>
                    <p>They are: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The $75,000,000 China Military Aid Fund recently authorized by
                                Congress;</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Some $80,000,000 still available under the 1948 China Aid Act for
                                which no current or expectant procurement authorizations are
                                pending; and</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>$45,000,000 of stockpiling appropriation which could be made
                                available in a way later described.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Both (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)<note n="†"
                            xml:id="d582fn2">In the case of (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), current
                            legislation requires that the uses should be consistent with the purpose
                            of the China Aid Act. To ensure that the President shall have a free
                            hand to apply the fund in what he considers to be the most direct and
                            effective way, it should be kept in mind that eventual action would be
                            taken to secure supplementary Congressional authorization to the effect
                            that the fund may be used “without regard to the provisions of the
                            Economic Cooperative Act of 1949.” [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                        may be used in the manner and under terms and conditions to be determined by
                        the President.</p>
                    <p>To provide the $45,000,000 in (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>), China would be able
                        to make available to the United States, for purposes of stockpiling of
                        strategic materials, such export commodities as antimony, tin, tungsten,
                        tung oil and bristles.</p>
                    <p>Under present conditions an annual export of U.S. $30,000,000 worth of the
                        above-mentioned commodities can easily be made from the
                        government-controlled area. The amount can be considerably increased if
                        transportation facilities could be improved.</p>
                    <p>To be on the safe side, however, it is proposed that only $22,500,000 per
                        year be delivered. It is therefore suggested that out of the fund made
                        available to the Army and Munitions Board under the Stockpiling Act (Public
                        Law 520, 79th Congress), $45,000,000 shall be allocated for the acquisition
                        over the next two years of strategic materials in China. To assist in the
                        military exigency and to stimulate China’s export and economic recovery, it
                        is further suggested that a lump sum advance payment of such $45,000,000
                        should be made available to the new Chinese Government, through and under
                        the supervision of the U.S. Aid Field Mission.</p>
                    <p>Against this payment, it is suggested that the Chinese Government undertake
                        to make delivery as follows: <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2" rows="2">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Availability</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                                        >Production per year</hi>)</cell>
                                <cell cols="4">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Deliveries</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell cols="4">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Total Deliveries</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="2">
                                    <hi rend="italic">1st year</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell cols="2">
                                    <hi rend="italic">2nd year</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell cols="2">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Quantity</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Value</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Tin</cell>
                                <cell role="num">6,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">8,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$16,000,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Tungsten</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">500</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">500</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">800,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Bristles</cell>
                                <cell role="num">15,000</cell>
                                <cell>cases</cell>
                                <cell role="num">10,000</cell>
                                <cell>cases</cell>
                                <cell role="num">10,000</cell>
                                <cell>cases</cell>
                                <cell role="num">20,000</cell>
                                <cell>cases</cell>
                                <cell role="num">7,400,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Tung oil</cell>
                                <cell role="num">50,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">20,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">20,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell role="num">40,000</cell>
                                <cell>tons</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#border-bottom" role="num">20,800,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#right">Total:</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">$45,000,000</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>From these three sources (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), (<hi rend="italic"
                            >b</hi>) and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>), a total of $200,000,000 would
                        be available for the resistance budget through February–1950.</p>
                    <p>There remains what may be left of the gold reserve in Taiwan, which, along
                        with tax receipts, could be used to maintain the currency, <pb facs="0598"
                            n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/> defray administrative expenses, or be pooled
                        for military purposes under the overall allocations of the U.S. Aid Field
                        Mission.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">F. <hi rend="italic">What are the prospects of success?</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Chinese Communist troops are flung out on long lines, ill-served by
                        transportation. They have now arrived at Chinese mountain positions which
                        the Japanese Imperial Army, with much better organization, with sea
                        transportation, and much better fighting qualities and morale, were never
                        able to penetrate. The quality of the Chinese Communist troops has sharply
                        deteriorated as repeated clashes recently have shown. In addition, the
                        ideology and methods of the Communist leaders have alienated the population
                        which at first welcomed them and believed in their impossible promises.</p>
                    <p>Canton could have held out indefinitely had it not been for the heavy cost of
                        upkeep and the major decision to eke out the remaining reserves for the
                        longest possible time without foreign aid.</p>
                    <p>Ensconced in such difficult terrain, the Nationalist troops—with pay
                        assured—with new military and political leadership—and, above all, with the
                        tremendous morale uplift given by definite U.S. support—have every reason to
                        believe that these limited self-sufficient areas could be held: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>As a maximum, until such time as the situation in
                                Communist-controlled areas furnished a chance for successful
                                military counter offensive from such free areas.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>Probably worth just as much, until such time as the very existence
                                of a free China in such free areas would lead to internal
                                dissatisfaction arid a self-starting counter revolution in the
                                Communist-controlled areas by the constant incitation of the
                                inherent Chinese desire to be free of foreign domination.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">At the very least</hi>, long enough—a year or
                                two—to give a chance to organize a line of Asiatic resistance to
                                Communism further back, by containing the military and revolutionary
                                resources which a Soviet organization, having conquered and
                                consolidated China, could turn loose, one by one, on much easier
                                targets to the south. And finally, if Nationalist China completely
                                collapses and the member nations in Asia change their alignment, the
                                balance of power in the Assembly and in the Security Council of the
                                United Nations will be changed to the lasting detriment of the
                                U.S.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Chinese people and army have been struggling against a disguised foreign
                        invasion for many years. They have suffered from repeated reverses. Feeling
                        isolated and frustrated, they need a new hope which only the restoration of
                        U.S. aid will furnish. <hi rend="italic">But time is of the
                        essence</hi>.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
