<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Deputy ECA Administrator (
                        Foster
                    ) to the Minister-Counselor of Embassy in
                        China (
                        Clark
                    ), at Canton</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d643</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">643</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-06-27T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-06-27T11:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-06-27T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-27T11:00:00-05:00" n="643" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d643">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.50 Recovery/6–2449: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Deputy ECA Administrator</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Foster</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Minister-Counselor of Embassy in
                        China</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Clark</hi>
                    </persName>), <hi rend="italic">at Canton</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-06-27T12:00:00-04:00">June 27, 1949—noon.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Ecato 271. [Re] Toeca 2110<note n="31" xml:id="d643fn31">Not printed; see
                        footnote 25 to telegram No. 2350, June 19, 11 a. m., from the Consul General
                        at Shanghai, <ref target="#pg_649">p. 649</ref>.</note> repeated Canton
                    Shaeca 261; ECASha 226, repeated Wash Toeca 285; Toeca 204 repeated Shanghai
                    ECASha 199; ECASha 190 repeated Wash Toeca 203.<note n="32" xml:id="d643fn32">ECA messages not found in Department of State files.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Amplification marching orders you requested Toeca 204 now possible due
                        better understanding application policy to complicated situation
                        Shanghai.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>In interpreting marching orders for Shanghai, you and SRO should be guided
                        by following general principles: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>You are to seek earliest possible liquidation ECA responsibilities
                                Shanghai consistent with need for making orderly arrangements and
                                adhering to ECA policies.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>You should avoid any arrangement which would be open to
                                interpretation that it assists Communist government or provides for
                                any continuing help for Communist areas flowing from ECA program.
                                For example, Plan One in Toeca 2110, June 17, suggested setting up
                                revolving fund to finance additional raw cotton imports into
                                Shanghai. This would violate principle of no continuing help to
                                Communist areas.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Main emphasis under present changed conditions should be on making
                                sure ECA residual stocks serve humanitarian purposes.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Methods and procedures must be left to you within principles
                                established in marching orders as modified by this cable.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                            <item>St. Louis<note n="33" xml:id="d643fn33">George W. St. Louis,
                                    Assistant Deputy for Operations of ECA China Mission.</note>
                                should keep ECA/W<note n="34" xml:id="d643fn34">ECA/Washington.</note> as closely and promptly informed as
                                possible. Major decisions, or decisions involving political
                                questions not dealt with in this cable, should be referred to
                                Washington.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In line with above principles, Plan One is not acceptable because of the
                        revolving fund feature. It appears that Plan Two is impractical in view of
                        impossibility expect welfare agencies to handle problems involved in
                        managing, processing, and distribution of large amounts of cotton under
                        present conditions in Shanghai. Therefore, we believe that general scheme in
                        draft resolution Toeca 2110 appears to be the best arrangement under the
                        circumstances.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The priority for the allocation of local currency proceeds should be
                        generally in the following order: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) ECA
                        administrative expenses, <pb facs="0664" n="654" xml:id="pg_654"/> (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) welfare agencies and projects previously receiving
                        aid such as Chien Tang sea wall, (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) administrative
                        expenses of Embassy and Consulate. If use of proceeds for Embassy and ConGen
                        administrative purposes raises political questions with Communists, you
                        should refer matter to Washington, and avoid any breakdown of negotiations
                        on this account.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Plan should if possible be formalized in some way in writing, and should
                        be subject of full report from SRO with copies of any basic agreements or
                        exchanges of letters.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Cotton should be sold not subject to quality claims and price should be
                        invoice value landed Shanghai. Weight to be taken as determined by Shanghai
                        Controller. Twenty percent sample should be drawn at time of weighing and
                        sent to Kobe when feasible for classing for ECA purposes.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Following are some specific queries which are cited both as considerations
                        in your negotiations and as points which final SRO report on this operation
                        should be sure to cover: Why replace SAC<note n="35" xml:id="d643fn35">Shanghai Assistance Committee.</note> with <hi rend="italic">Ad
                            Hoc</hi> Committee? What personnel proposed for membership new
                        committee? This important in view proposed powers. Do you consider
                        collective guarantee mill owners association members effective insurance of
                        full payment to beneficiaries?</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>In line with above instructions, St. Louis authorized to negotiate final
                        arrangement subject to above principles and in consultation with American
                        Consulate General and Ambassador, if available.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Careful presentation this problem in your Toeca 2110, June 17, much
                        appreciated here and greatly assisted rational consideration of problem on
                        this end.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>This cable represents views of both Department and ECA, including Lapham
                        and Griffin.<note n="36" xml:id="d643fn36">Both returned to Washington after
                            completing their work with the ECA China Mission.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Repeated Shanghai as Ecato 1436.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Foster</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
