<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Acting President of China (
                        Li
                    ) to President Truman
                    
                    Presented to President Truman by Dr. Kan
                        Chieh-hou on June 22. A letter along similar lines, dated May 5, was
                        addressed to the Secretary of State and presented to Acting Secretary Webb
                        by Dr. Kan on June 9. In telegram telCan No. 379, June 24, 2 p. m., the
                        Secretary directed the Embassy Office in Canton to convey his acknowledgment
                        and to express his “hope to have the opportunity of discussing the substance
                        of your letter with Dr. Kan at an early date”.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d665</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">665</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-05T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="665" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d665">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.93/5–549</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting President of China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Li</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="10" xml:id="d665fn10">Presented to President Truman by Dr. Kan
                        Chieh-hou on June 22. A letter along similar lines, dated May 5, was
                        addressed to the Secretary of State and presented to Acting Secretary Webb
                        by Dr. Kan on June 9. In telegram telCan No. 379, June 24, 2 p. m., the
                        Secretary directed the Embassy Office in Canton to convey his acknowledgment
                        and to express his “hope to have the opportunity of discussing the substance
                        of your letter with Dr. Kan at an early date”.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Canton</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-05">May 5,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: Throughout our war of
                    resistance against Japanese aggression, the United States of America
                    continuously extended to us her moral and material assistance, which enabled our
                    country to carry on an arduous struggle of eight long years until final victory
                    was achieved. The sincere friendship thus demonstrated by the United States has
                    contributed not only to strengthen further the traditional ties between our two
                    countries but to win the deep gratitude and unbounded goodwill of the people of
                    China.</p>
                <p>This policy of friendly assistance was continued when some years ago General
                    George C. Marshall, under instructions from your good self, took up the
                    difficult task of mediation in our conflict with the Chinese Communists,<note n="11" xml:id="d665fn11">December 1945 to January 1947; for correspondence
                        on his mission to China, see <ref target="frus1945v07#pg_745">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, pp. 745</ref>–<ref target="frus1945v07#pg_828">828</ref>, and <ref target="frus1946v09">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1946, vols, <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>
                        </ref> and <ref target="frus1946v10">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">x</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> to which he devoted painstaking effort. All this work was
                    unfortunately rendered fruitless by the lack of sincerity on the part of both
                    the then Government and the Chinese Communists.</p>
                <p>In spite of this, your country continued to extend its aid to our Government. It
                    is regrettable that, owing to the failure of our then Government to make
                    judicious use of this aid and to bring about appropriate political, economic and
                    military reforms, your assistance <pb facs="0710" n="700" xml:id="pg_700"/> has
                    not produced the desired effect. To this failure is attributable the present
                    predicament in which our country finds itself.</p>
                <p>The situation in China has now entered a very critical phase indeed and has
                    occasioned widespread anxiety among all classes of the Chinese people. I venture
                    to think that it is also a matter of deep concern to Your Excellency.</p>
                <p>If nothing were done to reinforce the position of the Chinese Government so as to
                    enable it to stem the tide of communist infiltration, and if, in consequence, it
                    should one day become necessary even to evacuate the Pearl River valley, the
                    very last line of defence for the Nationalist cause, not only would the whole of
                    China be subjected to Communist control but all the countries of East Asia would
                    soon fall behind the Iron Curtain of the Cominform,<note n="12" xml:id="d665fn12">Communist Information Bureau.</note> a contingency fraught
                    with grave consequences.</p>
                <p>During the last three months when the country has come under my administration, I
                    have spared no effort to seek peace with the Chinese Communists, but their
                    persistent design to carry out their decision of communizing the whole of China
                    has doomed this endeavor to failure.</p>
                <p>For the safeguard of China’s democratic freedom and national independence, I feel
                    that I am in duty bound to lead my Government in a defensive campaign of
                    resistance against the tyrannical force of Communism. At the same time, I am
                    convinced that fundamental reforms must speedily be introduced in the political,
                    economic and military fields before the confidence of the people can be
                    restored, the morale of the armed forces bolstered up, and the crisis facing us
                    averted.</p>
                <p>On the basis of this conviction, I have made up my mind to surmount every
                    difficulty and remove every obstacle in the way of consummation of the policy
                    just outlined. I firmly believe, however, that to the implementation of this
                    policy the continued assistance of your country is still indispensable. In
                    asking for your further aid, I can assure you that my Government will make the
                    most careful and best use of whatever may be offered to us.</p>
                <p>Dr. C. H. Kan is an old friend of mine, who possesses an accurate understanding
                    of the traditional relations between our two countries and of the situation now
                    prevailing in China. I have asked him to come and call on you in the capacity of
                    my personal representative. I should appreciate it if you would receive him and
                    feel free to discuss with him everything that relates to the subject matter of
                    this letter.</p>
                <p>With kindest personal regards [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Li Tsung-jen</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
