<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>102. Telegram 5142 From the Embassy in Iran to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d102</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">102</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-12-01T04:55:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-12-01T04:55:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-12-01T04:55:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-12-01T04:55:00-05:00" n="102"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d102">
                <head>102. Telegram 5142 From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Iran</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d102fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Files 1970–73, POL 17 US-IRAN. Secret; <gloss target="#t_NoDis1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>. In Telegram 196031 to Tehran, December 2, the Department
                        agreed that the official story should be that the Ambassador’s car had been
                        struck by a hit-and-run driver. (Ibid.)</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d102fn2">Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> notified the Department that
                        the previous evening, he and his wife had been the victims of an abduction
                        or assassination attempt that would not be publicized.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1970-12-01T09:55:00+00:00">December 1, 1970, 0955Z</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Attempted Abduction and/or Assassination of Ambassador and Wife</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>My wife and I dined informally with Court Minister Alam last evening (Nov
                        30) because he wished to discuss with me some matters which deeply concerned
                        Shah. Only Minister of Economy Ansary and wife were present. My wife and I
                        left Alam’s home to return to Embassy residence about 11:00 p.m. midway
                        between Alam’s residence and Embassy on a broad boulevard a large car
                        containing three or four men (estimated age mid-twenties) overtook us and
                        swerved toward us forcing our car toward curb. Since this was eve of holiday
                        (celebrating end of Ramazan) we and our driver Haikaz initially assumed car
                        occupants were simply exuberant celebrants of forthcoming holiday. However,
                        when Haikaz refused to be forced further toward curb, car swerved in,
                        striking left side of our car in deliberate attempt to force us to curb and
                        cut us off. Assailants did succeed in virtually bring us to a halt. At same
                        time second car took positon behind us. In rapidly moving movie type
                        scenario, two men jumped out of car, one with pistol pointed at us shouting
                        and gesticulating for us to get out. I instructed our chauffeur, Haikaz, who
                        behaved superbly, to go full speed ahead and he skillfully disengaged from
                        the car which had forced us towards curb and accelerated, maneuvering our
                        Cadillac between assailant’s car and jube, whereupon man with pistol fired
                        pointblank at us as we dropped to floor (bullet loging in door frame by rear
                        seat). At same time second man hurled ax at rear side window shattering it
                        completely with ax coming to rest with us on floor of our car.</item>
                    <pb facs="d102-02" n="2" xml:id="d102-02"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I reported incident to Court Minister Alam immediately upon return to
                        Embassy and he in turn at once reported to Shah and PriMin. entire Iranian
                        security apparatus was immediately alerted and started investigation. Prime
                        Minister called me personally to express deep regret and proposed that
                        special Iranian security guard be provided for both my wife and me. I have
                        accepted this offer and will handle in way which we hope will not be too
                        obtrusive.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Although no one except few of my closest associates knows of attack, in
                        view of condition of car and fact that Iranian guards at Embassy and
                        household personnel and motor pool people are aware that there was some
                        incident, knew that something happened will in due course leak out. Embassy
                        personnel have simply been told we had auto accident but nobody hurt.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I am particularly anxious that this matter be treated publicly in way
                        which will not <gloss target="#t_RPT1">rpt</gloss> not embarrass <gloss
                            target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>. Accordingly, Court Minister Alam (after
                        consultation with Shah and PriMin Hoveyda) and I have agreed that we will
                        volunteer no statement about incident but if we are queried response will be
                        that while returning to residence from a dinner last evening our car was
                        sideswiped by a hit-and-run driver who was proceeding at a high rate of
                        speed and that car suffered broken window and some other damage but nobody
                        hurt. We can not speculate on whether accident was deliberate on part of
                        hit-and-run driver or simply result of very bad driving for which Iran is
                        known.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>I trust foregoing will be held very closely in Dept on need-to-know basis
                        and that nothing will be said or volunteered by anyone. If Dept should be
                        queried, request it reply as agreed with Alam in para 4 and that I be
                        notified of query. Thus far nobody has a clue as to who was behind attack or
                        what motivated it but since other of my principal associates could possibly
                        also be targets we are reviewing urgently our security procedures.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Finally I will in due course propose our driver Haikaz for very special
                        award for without his courage, coolness and skill there would not have been
                        a happy ending.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
