<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>114. Telegram 722 From the Embassy in Iran to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d114</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">114</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-02-12T05:01:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-02-12T05:01:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="organization-of-petroleum-exporting-countries" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-petroleum-exporting-countries">OPEC</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-02-12T05:01:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-02-12T05:01:00-05:00" n="114"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d114">
                <head>114. Telegram 722 From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Iran</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d114fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Files 1970–73, PET 3 <gloss target="#t_OPEC1">OPEC</gloss>. Secret;
                        Priority; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Repeated to London. In
                        Telegram 476 from Jidda, February 14, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TNG1"
                            >Thacher</persName> wrote, “we should avoid any action tending to
                        endorse the arbitrary short deadlines and coercive legal measures by which
                        U.S. corporations were forced on very short notice commit themselves to
                        payments of billions of dollars over the next few years.” (Ibid.) In
                        Telegram 28309 to Tehran, February 19, <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                            >Rogers</persName> informed Zahedi that “The settlement just reached
                        with the companies is of great importance … in assuring stable market
                        arrangements during the five-year period of the agreement. Of particular
                        importance to the negotiations and us were the assurances given in this
                        respect at the time of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName>’s
                        visit.” (Ibid.)</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d114fn2">Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> and his British counterpart
                        rejected the oil companies’ request for a formal démarche to Iran to resolve
                        remaining disputes with <gloss target="#t_OPEC1">OPEC</gloss>. The U.S.
                        ambassador favored a message from the President to the Shah to help cement
                        the final deal.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1971-02-12T10:01:00+00:00">February 12, 1971, 1001Z</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subj:</head>
                    <item>Oil Situation (Briefing by Companies)</item>
                </list>
                <p>Following is summary of briefing given to U.S., U.K., French Ambassador and Dutch
                    Charge by company <gloss target="#t_Rep1">rep</gloss>s Piercey (ESSO), Carlyle
                    (Shell), Kirchner (Continental), Montigue (<gloss target="#t_CFP1">CFP</gloss>)
                    on morning Feb 12:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Piercey as spokesman said companies had “collapsed” and met virtually all
                            <gloss target="#t_OPEC1">OPEC</gloss> demands in meeting in Paris with
                            <persName corresp="#p_AJ4">Amouzegar</persName> which he characterized
                        as “very good.” However, there were still some matters to be sorted out
                        relating to a small posted price difference (he mentioned one cent)
                        marketing allowance (one-half cent a barrel) and a few other items.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>He then went on to say that the most important element of solution still
                        not settled related to freight differential in Mediterranean due to to
                        favored geographic position (State 22654, para 3A). <gloss target="#t_OPEC1"
                            >OPEC</gloss> Gulf producers had originally taken position that if
                        presently justifiable frieght differential for Libya is not reduced with
                        drop in freight rates, OPEC wants Persian Gulf prices increased comparable
                        amount. Piercey said companies had made an offer which would limit their
                        liability. While <persName corresp="#p_AJ4">Amouzegar</persName> in Paris
                        had seemed receptive to this offer which was very best companies could make,
                        he had not actually accepted it. Therefore companies felt <pb facs="d114-02"
                            n="2" xml:id="d114-02"/> that time might come in next few days when
                        governments (basically US and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>) should
                        intervene with <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> on this matter on which
                        an agreement depended.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>US and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Ambassadors replied that they had
                        already taken this matter up informally with Court Minister Alam on Feb 4
                        (Tehran 605) urging he look into it. Without instructions from their
                        governments the US and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Ambassadors did not
                        believe that they could make any formal demarches to the <gloss
                            target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>. Furthermore in view of the extreme
                        sensitivity of the Shah, any such demarches at the government level at this
                        juncture could do harm and be counter-productive.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>The company representatives said they understood this but dependable
                            assurances for a five-year agreement were so vitally important that
                            perhaps if an agreement was actually reached and signed, it could be
                            nailed down by some diplomatic note to the Shah. British Ambassador
                            explained that Embassies did not send diplomatic notes to Shah but that
                            we fully understood the importance of a dependable 5 year agreement and
                            as the situation evolved we would have to remind the desirability of
                            trying to do something that would nail down a bit more the assurances
                            which <gloss target="#t_OPEC1">OPEC</gloss> might give to companies.</p>
                        <p>Comment</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>After above meeting I met privately with <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                        Ambassador wright for purpose of discussing possibility of nailing down
                        further such assurances as Iran and other <gloss target="#t_OPEC1"
                            >OPEC</gloss> members might give to companies re five year agreement.
                        Since Shah had given such assurances to <gloss target="#t_UNSEC1"
                            >UnSec</gloss> Irwin in latter’s capacity as presidential emmissary. I
                        told Wright that if agreement reached between producers and companies, I
                        would recommend we consider possibility of message from President to Shah
                        expressing gratification that agreement had been reached making reference to
                        importance of assurances for five year period, etc. On his part Wright
                        undertook to ask London to consider a formal foreign office statement in
                        same sense following agreement. He felt this <pb facs="d114-03" n="3"
                            xml:id="d114-03"/> was best way for British to nail down assurance since
                        if there were parallel messages from both President and <gloss
                            target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> PriMin Heath to Shah, latter might feel that
                        it was a ganging up job and be resentful. If agreement is reached and
                        whether or not there is a presidential message (which tentatively I believe
                        could be useful but wish to reserve final judgment until after conclusion of
                        present talks) we believe it would be extremely helpful if other important
                        consuming governments, particularly Japan and Western Europeans, make formal
                        and public declarations nailing down the fact that the agreement is for five
                        years.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Companies meeting with <gloss target="#t_OPEC1">OPEC</gloss> Gulf
                        committee at 1530 local Feb 12.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
