<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-04-15T03:17:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-04-15T03:17:00-05:00" n="125" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d125">
                        <head>125. Telegram 1935 From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Iran</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d125fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Files 1970–73, PET 3 <gloss target="#t_OPEC1">OPEC</gloss>.
                                Confidential. Repeated to Dhahran, Jidda, Kuwait, London, and
                                Tripoli.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d125fn2">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> alerted the Department
                                that the Shah hoped to bridge the gap between the recent Persian
                                Gulf oil settlement and the more favorable terms that Libya had just
                                secured.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-04-15T08:17:00+00:00">April 15, 1971, 0817Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Shah’s Concern Over Libyan Oil Settlement</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>When I saw Shah April 14 he spoke critically of Libyan oil
                                settlement, saying oil companies always made greater concessions to
                                radical producing states than to their moderate producing state
                                friends. He said he was sending FonMin <persName corresp="#p_AJ4">Amouzegar</persName> to London to discuss with oil companies
                                Libyan settlement with view to finding some way to partially bridge
                                gap between Gulf settlement and excessive terms given Libya.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I reminded Shah of assurances he had given us and oil companies
                                that terms of Gulf settlement would not be changed for five years
                                even if Libya received more than Gulf producers. I also observed
                                that large part of disparity between Gulf and Libyan settlement was
                                result of Libya’s favored geographic position and low sulphur
                                content of its oil. I concluded by saying that Iranian production
                                and offtake so far this year was running substantially ahead of last
                                year and that <pb facs="d125-02" n="2" xml:id="d125-02"/> therefore
                                I thought Iran was doing extremely well.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Shah replied that he would honor his word re five year assurances
                                but would seek some way outside terms of Tehran settlement to help
                                bridge disparity between Gulf and Libyan prices. For example, oil
                                exported from Basra was obliged to pay a “port tax” and he had in
                                mind possibility of port tax on oil lifted from Kharg Island. I said
                                such a step would be serious disappointment to oil companies and
                                Iran’s friends.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>