<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-05-30T10:05:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-05-30T09:05:00-05:00" n="200" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d200">
                        <head>200. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d200fn1">Source: Library of Congress, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box TS–28,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Telcons,
                                Geopolitical Files, Iran, Memcons, Notebook 30 May 72–15 September
                                73. Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. The conversation
                                took place in the Saadabad Palace in Tehran. According to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry Kissinger</persName>’s memoirs, the
                                President during this visit also agreed that, “without American
                                support, the existing Kurdish uprising against the Baghdad
                                Government would collapse. American participation [in the effort to
                                aid the Kurdish insurgency] in some form was needed to maintain the
                                morale of such key allies as Iran and Jordan…” (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, Years of Renewal, pp.
                                582–3.) No record of this conversation was found.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d200fn2">The Shah, President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, and his Assistant
                                for National Security Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, discussed the Moscow Summit and its
                                significance to the Middle East.</note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1972-05-30T17:35:00+03:30" to="1972-05-30T18:35:00+03:30" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">May 30, 1972, 5:35 to 6:35
                                p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <pb facs="d200-01" n="1" xml:id="d200-01"/>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS:</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PMR1">Mohammed Reza Pahlavi</persName>,
                                Shahanshah of Iran</item>
                            <item>The President</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, Assistant
                                to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> welcomed the President warmly to
                            Tehran. He congratulated the President on the success of our foreign
                            policy and the Moscow Summit in particular. It was a masterpiece of
                            strength on one side and dexterity on the other. Our friends, the Shah
                            emphasized, were indeed reassured. But the Shah was worried about “this
                            region” [the Middle East].</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="underline">President</hi> thanked the Shah for his welcome
                            and his kind words. When we arranged this trip, he explained, it all had
                            to come together. Going to China made the Russian trip possible. Taking
                            strong action in Vietnam [the May 8 measures] did not thwart the Moscow
                            Summit. There was no reason for euphoria or for the assumption that the
                            Soviet leaders had changed their long-term goals. What convinced us of
                            that was Soviet behavior in the 1971 India-Pakistan crisis. The Soviet
                            leaders placed security considerations above Communism. What was on
                            their mind was Europe and almost certainly China; they were trying to
                            outflank the Middle East.</p>
                        <p>The United States, the President continued, was proceeding on a
                            step-by-step basis. We made agreements where it was in the common
                            interest. The President had told BREZHNEV we would see Indochina
                            through, but he had told him a confrontation with the US was more likely
                            in the Middle East. The Politburo wanted better relations with us. We,
                            for our part, wanted better relations with them. But we wanted to make
                            sure no small crises would blow into big ones.</p>
                        <p>We appreciated the Shah’s role in South Asia, the President said. His
                            personal view was that if India with the support of Soviet arms had
                            gobbled <pb facs="d200-02" n="2" xml:id="d200-02"/> up West Pakistan,
                            other states would have been in danger—not from the Indians, because of
                            their incompetence, but from the Soviets. We came to visit Iran because
                            we considered it symbolic of our strong support for our friends. We
                            would not let down our friends.</p>
                        <p>The President then asked Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> if he had anything to add.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                            </hi> summed up the Soviet strategy of selective detente. They would
                            make settlements on some matters with some adversaries in order to
                            isolate others, particularly the Chinese. We had to be careful. It was
                            important to establish the principle of great-power restraint. We had
                            sought to bring this home to the Soviets.</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> expressed his agreement that a policy
                            of confrontation was impossible. There were key areas, he stressed,
                            which could not be neglected—such as Europe and the Middle East. The
                            Shah gave the figures on Europe’s and Japan’s dependence on oil from the
                            Middle East. Libya’s oil would go dry in another decade and a half, he
                            said. The US would have to get more and more of its oil from the Middle
                            East. We could not allow ourselves to get in a position where we could
                            be cut off. That crazy fellow Mossadegh did it, the <hi rend="underline">President</hi> remarked. He was nuts, the <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> agreed.</p>
                        <p>Last year, two months after signing the treaty with the Soviets the
                            Indians attacked, the Shah said. He didn’t want to be told that the
                            Soviets were restraining their clients. “We will not hand over our
                            country. We will pursue a scorched earth policy. They will have to shoot
                            their way in.”</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="underline">President</hi> asked the <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> if our allies were afraid of the Summit. Not if you have
                            the right allies, the Shah replied. If they are self-reliant they will
                            welcome it. If they have the principle of fighting until the last
                            American they will not welcome it. Iran, like Israel, must be able to
                            stand alone. The Shah therefore hoped that we had more blue suiters
                            available; Iran also had to have the most modern weapons. We could not
                            have a situation where the US cut off arms to any client of the Soviet
                            Union. He was afraid the Soviets would establish a coalition of the
                            Kurds, the Baathists, and the Communists; the Kurdish problem instead of
                            being a thorn in the side could become an asset to the Communists.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                            </hi> asked what could be done. Turkey needs strengthening, the <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> replied. Iran can help with the
                            Kurds.</p>
                        <pb facs="d200-03" n="3" xml:id="d200-03"/>
                        <p>How about Greece, the <hi rend="underline">President</hi> asked. The <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> replied that the King was a nice man but
                            a fool. He was objectively worried about Papandreou. The colonels must
                            be supported. The King could stay if he kept quiet.</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="underline">President</hi> asked about Afghanistan. The <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> replied that the King of Afghanistan was
                            lazy. There were pressures in West Pakistan and Pushtunistan and
                            Baluchistan. This would then encircle Iran and give the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> a corridor to the sea. The Shah had
                            warned Yahya about his stupidity, but he could not accept this naked
                            deliberate aggression.</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="underline">President</hi> then discussed the circumstances
                            under which we would restore economic aid to India. The <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> remarked that if we could give some aid
                            to India to save Pakistan, that was okay. But the main problem was to
                            save West Pakistan. The <hi rend="underline">President</hi> agreed that
                            the Shah was right, and suggested they talk the next day about this.
                            Iran could be a proxy for Pakistan, the <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi>
                            suggested. <hi rend="underline">Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                            </hi> noted that we then had to reestablish Pakistan’s arms program to
                            make Pakistan eligible for third-country transfers from Iran. That we
                            must do, the <hi rend="underline">President</hi> agreed. Otherwise
                            Pakistan will be jumped. The <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> pointed out
                            that he was offering Afghanistan everything.</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="underline">President</hi> then said that the US was willing
                            to reconsider the question of the US naval deployment in the Persian
                            Gulf. The <hi rend="underline">Shah</hi> stated that he had wanted to
                            exclude the other major powers from the Gulf after the British left and
                            had therefore expressed concern about the small US naval force. But
                            after the Soviet-Indian treaty there was something to be said for
                            showing the flag there. Iran nevertheless was the only country capable
                            of dealing with any situation without any outside help. He would study
                            it.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>