<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>307. Intelligence Memorandum No. 0865/72</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d307</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">307</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="recmWDaOvRW5J41xt" type="compound-subject"
                        category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general">military
                        relationship</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145303"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Naval ships</term>
                    <term ref="recgO0zWiwmY4SEHo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Air access</term>
                    <term ref="recu3GH1ojKcJBA1c" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85111861"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Reconnaissance aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090254"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Natural resources</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Refinery</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="rec8PCbWGrkAaOOXZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001000124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developed countries</term>
                    <term ref="recNHstTN4mCmPSgR" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="missile-defense" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011305" lcsh-match="good_close">Air defense</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                    <term ref="rec101e79d141fc02f" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="new-states">New states</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-05-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-05-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="307"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d307">
                <head>307. Intelligence Memorandum No. 0865/72<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d307fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, <gloss
                            target="#t_OCI1">OCI</gloss> Files, Job 79T00832A, Box 8, Folder 8,
                        Moscow and the Persian Gulf, No. 0865-72. Secret; No Foreign Dissem.
                        Prepared in the Office of Current Intelligence and coordinated within the
                        Directorate of Intelligence. This memorandum was included in the
                        Presidential Briefing materials for <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName>’s May 1972 trip to Iran.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d307fn2">The memorandum analyzed Soviet
                        policies in the Persian Gulf, with a focus on Moscow’s relations with Iraq
                        and Iran.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-05-12"
                        >May 12, 1972</date>
                </dateline>
                <pb facs="d307-01" n="1" xml:id="d307-01"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="underline">Moscow and the Persian Gulf</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Soviet policies in the Persian Gulf have followed a consistent course over
                        the past five years. During this period, Moscow has probed the area,
                        seeking—as opportunities arose—to extend its political and military
                        influence into a region of traditional Russian concern. Iran, Iraq, and
                        Kuwait have been responsive to Soviet overtures. Moscow has been
                        particularly successful in using economic openings with Tehran and Baghdad
                        to foster the growth of policies more friendly to the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. After Kuwait gained independence in
                        1961, the Soviets moved quickly to establish a diplomatic mission. In 1970,
                        Soviet representatives in Kuwait arranged for Kuwaiti oil to be delivered to
                        Japan, a Soviet customer, in return for the shipment of Soviet crude to
                        Kuwait’s clients in Europe.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Iran is now the fourth largest recipient of Soviet economic aid and the
                        second largest recipient of East European aid. Although this assistance
                        still represents only a small part of the total financing for Iran’s
                        economic development program, Soviet activity is the dominant foreign
                        activity in the northern part of the country and is important in other
                        sectors. The largest Soviet project in Iran is the Isfahan steel mill, which
                        the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> agreed to undertake after the West
                        turned it down as economically unfeasible. As repayment for most of its
                        credits, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> is taking a billion
                        dollars worth of natural gas from Iran over the next decade. </item>
                    <pb facs="d307-02" n="2" xml:id="d307-02"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> also has emerged as Iran’s third
                        largest arms supplier. The most recent agreement brought Soviet military aid
                        to Iran to a total of more than $350 million. Tehran’s purchases have been
                        confined to conventional armaments, such as artillery and armored personnel
                        carriers. The Shah prefers not to purchase sophisticated arms from Moscow in
                        order to avoid becoming dependent on the Soviets for technical assistance
                        and spare parts.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Soviet-Iraqi ties have developed rapidly and have led to the signing of a
                        Treaty of Friendship and Cooperation on 9 April. Last fall Moscow agreed to
                        deliver to Iraq military equipment worth about $250 million. AAA guns,
                        anti-tank rockets, armored personnel carriers, and fighter aircraft were
                        included. Several months ago, according to a clandestine source, Soviet SA–3
                        surface-to-air missiles were unloaded at the port of Umm Qasr, and Iraq
                        probably has more than enough equipment for four SA–3 firing units. The
                        Iraqis presumably have acquired this low-altitude air defense system under
                        the arms agreement signed in October.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Article Nine of the Treaty of Friendship and Cooperation could, moreover,
                        lead to a greater Soviet military presence in Iraq. That article states, “In
                        the interests of the security of both countries, the high contracting
                        parties will continue to develop cooperation in the strengthening of their
                        defense capabilities.” This is a careful formulation and raises the
                        possibility of reciprocity in the Soviet-Iraqi military relationship; the
                        formulation was not in the Soviet treaties with Egypt and India. The
                        friendship treaty with India had no defense provision, and the treaty with
                        Cairo was designed “in the interests of…the United Arab Republic” to
                        strengthen only Egypt’s defense capability.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>In view of logistic constraints on Soviet operations in the Indian Ocean,
                        the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> might be interested in obtaining
                        support facilities in Iraq similar to those now available to the Soviet Navy
                        in the Mediterranean. Such facilities would increase the on-station time of
                        Soviet naval ships in <pb facs="d307-03" n="3" xml:id="d307-03"/> both the
                        Indian Ocean and the Persian Gulf. In addition, the Soviets could seek air
                        access to speed the exchange of naval crews and replacement of parts and to
                        provide landing facilities for naval reconnaissance aircraft.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>At the moment, Iraq does not have a sufficient maintenance and repair
                        capacity to handle Soviet naval ships. The facilities of Basra, Iraq’s only
                        large port, are in continuous use; those at the small port of Umm Qasr would
                        have to be expanded to provide effective support. Umm Qasr does have a
                        natural deep harbor with a large anchorage area, and the Iraqi Air Force has
                        excellent facilities nearby. The Iraqi Air Force, moreover, has with Soviet
                        assistance just built six military airfields that could be used to support a
                        Soviet naval presence in the Indian Ocean.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The friendship treaty also stated that the Soviets’ involvement in
                        developing Iraq’s industry and natural resources would be strengthened. This
                        involvement has been increasing since 1969 when the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss> committed at least $170 million to Iraq’s national oil
                        industry. The Soviets agreed to provide equipment and technical services for
                        projects, primarily in the North Rumaila oil field in southern Iraq, and
                        they are slated to build a refinery at Mosul. Soviet personnel are also
                        surveying a proposed pipeline from Baghdad to Basra and an extension of the
                        pipeline from Baghdad to northern Iraq. Most of this aid is to be repaid in
                        crude oil deliveries.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>In the long term, an increase in Soviet political influence in the Persian
                        Gulf would offer Moscow an opportunity to exercise some influence over the
                        gulf oil industry. The Soviets have been cautious about this, however, and
                        with good reason. The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> is not only
                        self-sufficient in oil, but is a large net exporter of oil and is likely to
                        remain so throughout this decade. The Soviets, moreover, would be reluctant
                        to pay hard currency for Persian Gulf oil and have shown no desire to absorb
                        more than a fraction of the oil produced there.</item>
                    <pb facs="d307-04" n="4" xml:id="d307-04"/>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Moscow’s assistance to the oil-producing nations at present is confined
                        mainly to production operations. The Soviets are not able to supplant the
                        various international companies in marketing petroleum. In this field Soviet
                        technical expertise and machinery are in disrepute, and it is difficult for
                        the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to provide transport facilities.
                        Therefore, Moscow’s policy has been merely to urge producer governments to
                        demand maximum revenues from Western companies and to avoid incurring any
                        obligations to purchase or dispose of the oil. The Soviets are also
                        inhibited, of course, by the recent Arab tendency to exclude foreign
                        political influence from the oil industry.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>The departure of the British and the emergence of the newly independent
                        states of Bahrain, Qatar, and the United Arab Emirates in the second half of
                        1971 has presented the Soviets with new openings for expanding their
                        presence in the Gulf. Soviet President <persName corresp="#p_PNV1"
                            >Podgorny</persName> quickly cabled Moscow’s official recognition of all
                        three soon after independence, but only in the case of the United Arab
                        Emirates did he publicly convey Moscow’s “willingness to establish
                        diplomatic relations.” The foreign ministry of the United Arab Emirates
                        revealed in February that an agreement to exchange diplomatic representation
                        had been concluded, but pressure from Saudi Arabia caused the Emirates to
                        delay the establishment of a Soviet Embassy in Abu Dhabi, the capital. Saudi
                        pressure has also caused Bahrain and Qatar to refuse to exchange
                        representatives with the Soviets.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>As in the case of Kuwait in the 1960s, the Soviets will continue to press
                        for a diplomatic presence in these new states and in Oman, as well An Abu
                        Dhabi source remarked privately earlier this month that the United Arab
                        Emirates was “resisting” Soviet pressures and that the opening of a Soviet
                        Embassy is several months away. The Soviets also may offer limited economic
                        aid programs to the new governments. This would enable Moscow to gain
                        greater knowledge of the area and to improve the Soviet image throughout the
                        Gulf.</item>
                    <pb facs="d307-05" n="5" xml:id="d307-05"/>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>The Soviets are being cautious about encouraging subversive activity in
                        the area. They have established contact with the Popular Front for the
                        Liberation of Oman and Arab Gulf and the Bahraini National Liberation Front
                        and apparently have provided some small arms and limited funds to the former
                        through Yemen (Aden). As in the case of Aden, however, Moscow will wait
                        until a radical element has given evidence of being able to endure before
                        channeling more substantial equipment and support to the liberation
                        movement. Meanwhile, Soviet propaganda has become less enthusiastic over the
                        prospects for success of liberation movements in the area.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>Although greater Soviet involvement in the Gulf area is virtually a
                        foregone conclusion, there are limits on Moscow’s freedom to maneuver. In
                        the first place, greater Soviet attention to the Gulf could disturb the
                        friendly relations that currently exist between the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss> and Iran. The Soviet assistance programs in Iran are large
                        and important. They are being implemented more rapidly than Soviet programs
                        in other less developed countries; only India and Egypt receive larger
                        amounts of Communist aid. The political and economic benefits that have
                        accrued to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> from its trade and aid
                        ties with Iran have become important policy considerations in Moscow.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>The Soviets have been telling Tehran that the Soviet rapprochement with
                        Iraq is not aimed against Iran. On several occasions during the past year,
                        the Soviets tried to reassure the Iranians regarding Baghdad’s intentions
                        and stressed Moscow’s desire to expand its ties with Iran. Last November,
                        for example, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> refused a request by
                        Iraq that Moscow protest Iran’s seizure of islands in the Persian Gulf.
                        According to a clandestine source, moreover, the Soviets rejected an Iraqi
                        request that the friendship treaty include a guarantee the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would intervene if Iraq were attacked by
                        Iran.</item>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>While the Soviets could use naval facilities in the Indian Ocean for their
                        ships, they have not assigned a high priority to securing such facilities in
                        the Gulf itself. One Soviet official has <pb facs="d307-06" n="6"
                            xml:id="d307-06"/> described the Gulf as a “mousetrap for all ships.” In
                        any event, it will remain difficult for the Soviets to carry on naval
                        activity in the Indian Ocean and the Persian Gulf as long as the Suez Canal
                        remains closed. Soviet military activity could also stimulate increased
                        cooperation among the smaller Gulf states, as well as strong reactions from
                        Iran and Saudi Arabia.</item>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>The Soviets probably will continue to encourage radical groups in the
                        area, but will be discreet in order that their efforts remain undetected.
                        They will not provide substantial assistance to the liberation movements and
                        will not commit their own forces to any attempt to overthrow the
                        conservative Gulf regimes. In view of the fragile political structure in the
                        area, however, it is well to remember that even a minimal Soviet effort to
                        support subversive groups could have considerable impact.</item>
                    <label>18.</label>
                    <item>In sum, the Soviets probably will continue to follow the policy they have
                        pursued over the past five years with significant success, particularly in
                        their relations with Iraq and Iran. Even better ties with Iraq can be
                        expected, and the Soviets will use their influence to try to push the
                        Baghdad government closer to their other major Arab clients, Egypt and
                        Syria. The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> will avoid taking sides in
                        the disputes between Iran and Iraq, hoping the Shah will come to accept the
                        greater Soviet involvement with Baghdad. In the long run, a stronger Soviet
                        political position and a more obtrusive military posture can be expected
                        throughout the Persian Gulf.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
