<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>11. Special National Intelligence Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="11"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d11">
                <head>11. Special National Intelligence Estimate<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d11fn0">Source: Department of State, PPS Files: Lot 67 D 548, Near
                        and Middle East 1958. Secret. A note on the cover sheet indicates that this
                            <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss>, submitted by the <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, was prepared by <gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                            >CIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>, and the intelligence
                        organizations of the Army, the Navy, the Air Force, and the Joint Staff. All
                        members of the Intelligence Advisory Committee (<gloss target="#t_IAC1"
                            >IAC</gloss>) concurred with this estimate except the representatives of
                        the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_FBI1"
                            >FBI</gloss> who abstained on the grounds that the topic was outside
                        their jurisdiction.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> 30–58</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1958-02-20">February 20, 1958</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">PROSPECTS AND CONSEQUENCES OF ARAB UNITY MOVES</p>
                <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                <p>To estimate the prospects and implications of the Syrian-Egyptian union and the
                    Iraq-Jordan federation.</p>
                <p rend="center">Summary and Conclusions</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Both the Syro-Egyptian union and the Iraq-Jordan federation, although
                        influenced by long-range developments and plans, came into being to meet
                        immediate political needs. <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                        probably agreed to go forward with the union at this time because he was
                        convinced that it was necessary in order to forestall a Communist takeover
                        in Syria, as well as because he saw a propitious moment for realization of
                        long-laid plans on his own terms. The federation was created to counter the
                            <pb facs="0075" n="41" xml:id="pg_41"/> anti-conservative pressures
                        generated by the union throughout the Arab world.<note n="1" xml:id="d11fn1"
                            >The word “union” will hereinafter be used to refer to the Syro-Egyptian
                            union, officially known as the United Arab Republic. The word
                            “federation” will refer to the Iraq-Jordan federation. [Footnote in the
                            source text.]</note> (Paras. 8, 24–25)</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The persistent and widespread appeal among Arabs of the concept of Arab
                        unity was the foundation upon which both the union and federation were
                        constructed. Of the two, the union, under <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName>, the leader and symbol of Arab radical nationalism,
                        almost certainly has a greater popular appeal in the whole area, and will
                        exert a continuing attraction upon the radical elements in the conservative
                        states. The creation of the two groupings emphasizes the polarization of the
                        area between radical and conservative forces and the contest for area
                        leadership between Egypt and Iraq will be stimulated. Since both groupings
                        proclaim the idea of Arab unity, surface cordiality may be maintained, but
                        at least covert hostile activities are likely between them. (Paras. 11–12,
                        20–21, 32)</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> will face formidable problems
                        in keeping the union together and maintaining stability within the two
                        component states, but we believe that the union can carry through for at
                        least a year or so on its present momentum. If <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName> were removed from the scene within this period, Egypt
                        and Syria would probably revert to their independent status. It is unlikely
                        that conservative forces would then succeed to power in either state and any
                        successor regimes would be likely to adopt a neutralist foreign policy.
                        (Paras. 13–19)</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Iraq-Jordan federation will also have serious internal problems
                        principally due to the radical Arab nationalist orientation of Jordan’s
                        ex-Palestinian population and to Jordan’s economic problems. If the
                        federation survives its initial difficulties, however, and is able to
                        capitalize on the economic resources of Iraq, its long term prospects would
                        be favorable. (Paras. 28–30)</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The creation of the two Arab groupings increases Israel’s apprehensions
                        with respect to the eventuality of military action. (Para. 38)</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">2½ lines of 2-column source text not declassified</hi>]
                        We believe that, although the Soviets suffered tactical reverses in Syria,
                        they will adapt their policy to the situation and seek to use the union as a
                        bridge to Africa and a means of weakening the conservative states. While the
                        Soviets are likely to take much the same attitude toward the federation as
                        do the leaders of the union, they will covertly seek to undermine the
                        conservative regimes. (Paras. 39–40)</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The success of the Iraq-Jordan federation will probably depend heavily
                        upon US diplomatic and material support. Overt US hostility to <pb
                            facs="0076" n="42" xml:id="pg_42"/> the Syro-Egyptian union would almost
                        certainly strengthen the union. On the other hand, public expression of US
                        support for the idea of Arab unity, coupled with a relaxation of overt
                        pressures upon <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>, might
                        influence <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> to bring the
                        Syro-Egyptian union into a more truly neutral position and might produce a
                        more favorable area reaction to discreet US support of the Iraq-Jordan
                        federation (Paras. 41–44)</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Here follows the “Discussion” section comprising paragraphs 8–44.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
