<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>133. Memorandum From the Director of Intelligence and Research (Gumming) to
                    Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State Dulles</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-08-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recCKwTsbSNQld1dB" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064628"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imperialism</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-08-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="133"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                <head>133. Memorandum From the Director of Intelligence and Research (<persName
                        type="from">Gumming</persName>) to Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_DJF1" type="to">Dulles</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d133fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 786.00/8-2258. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1958-08-22">August 22, 1958</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Intelligence Note: <hi rend="italic">Attitude of New Iraqi Leaders, Press
                            and Radio toward the US and pro-Western Arab Regimes</hi>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Assurances of the Iraqi regime’s friendly feelings toward the West, desire to
                    cooperate on an independent basis, and intention to honor prior commitments and
                    contracts are reiterated daily by Prime Minister Qasim in his contacts with US
                    representatives and in press statements. Nevertheless, a steady anti-American
                    trend is gathering momentum. It has thus far included minor acts of harassment
                    and non-cooperation, a growing atmosphere of public hostility, and a spate of
                    external and internal propaganda that is increasingly directed specifically
                    against the US, as well as against the openly Western-aligned Arab governments
                    of Lebanon and Jordan. There is no evidence that Qasim has taken any action to
                    prevent or mitigate this trend, or even that he sincerely wishes to do so. In
                    view of the growing split within his own government, however, Qasim is probably
                    no longer in a position to make a strong defense either of US interests or of
                    Iraqi independence of action vis-à-vis Egypt, whatever his personal preferences
                    may be.</p>
                <p>In the field of propaganda, the press of the new order has been somewhat more
                    moderate than the radio, although never free from <pb facs="0371" n="337"
                        xml:id="pg_337"/> anti-imperialist bias with certain anti-US overtones. The
                    first newspaper to appear after the revolution was <hi rend="italic"
                        >al-Yaqdha,</hi> long suspended under the former regime, which was formerly
                    published by Siddiq Shanshal (Minister of Guidance in the new Iraqi Cabinet)
                    under aegis of the Istiqlal Party. Always fanatically nationalist, anti-Jewish
                    (as distinct from anti-Zionist), and highly critical of the US, the paper in its
                    reincarnation has followed these lines as well as eulogizing Nasir and the
                    Egyptian and Iraqi revolutions. Shortly afterward <hi rend="italic"
                        >al-Jumhuriya</hi> made its first appearance, in obvious imitation of the
                    Egyptian government’s press vehicle, and immediately became the quasi-official
                    mouthpiece of the new government. It has printed all official statements,
                    including those of reassurance to the West, but the tone and content of the news
                    are very close to that of its Cairo counterpart.</p>
                <p>Baghdad radio has been oriented to the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> line
                    since an August 4 broadcast attacking the government of Jordan. Beginning about
                    two weeks after the revolt, <gloss target="#t_FBIS1">FBIS</gloss> monitors
                    identified two voices announcing on the station as an Egyptian and a Syrian.
                    Condemnations of the <persName corresp="#p_alSN1">Nuri</persName> regime have
                    gradually identified it more and more with the US, as well as “imperialism”
                    generally. A scare-line of impending plots against the new Republic is also
                    being developed: an accidental petroleum tank fire and the show-trial of
                    ex-Chief of Staff Daghestani are being so played as to enhance this line.
                    Rabble-rousing speeches of Deputy Prime Minister Abd al-Salam
                        <persName>Arif</persName> also have been featured. Representative excerpts
                    are attached as an annex.<note n="1" xml:id="d133fn1">Attached but not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>A similar memorandum has been addressed to the Under Secretary.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
