<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-10-13T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-10-13T23:00:00-05:00" n="138" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d138">
                        <head>138. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Iraq</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d138fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 787.00/10–1458. Confidential. Transmitted in two sections and
                                repeated to Amman, Ankara, Beirut, Cairo, Damascus, Jidda, Karachi,
                                London, Tehran, and Tel Aviv.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Baghdad</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-10-14T07:00:00+03:00">October
                                    14, 1958, 7 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1312. Three months have now passed since coup which brought Brigadier
                                <persName corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName> to power. It might at
                            this stage prove helpful to depict and assess some aspects of present
                            scene and to attempt some forecast, hazardous though it be, of what
                            coming months probably hold in store.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Troops are still camped in Embassy compound and stand guard at
                                other foreign missions, though perhaps in lesser force. Diplomatic
                                and private visitors are still challenged at Embassy gates, as are
                                American officials. I myself was denied entrance a few days ago,
                                until identified, although in official car with flag displayed.
                                Administration of Embassy, though perhaps a shade easier than during
                                July, August and September, is still hampered by petty and
                                unreasonable restrictions. <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> has
                                still not yet permitted us free access <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> offices.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Press and radio keep up steady attacks on US, its posture in past
                                and its current official policies. Our actions are sweepingly damned
                                as “imperialistic” and usually linked with “British imperialism”.
                                Terminology of these attacks is increasingly “Made-in-Moscow”.
                                Public added to this fire of hatred almost nightly by the trials of
                                officials, military and civilian, of former governments, these
                                trials being widely publicized by radio, television and press. It is
                                for us in the Embassy a sickening sight to see our former firm
                                friends and active supporters of the free world pilloried by a petty
                                military “judge” who also conceives of himself as a
                                prosecutor.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>We have confirmation from a number of sources that grumblings
                                among shopkeepers and particularly among workmen is steadily
                                growing. Promises made so loudly and widely in early days following
                                coup of a fuller and freer life are in no way materializing. That is
                                immediate basis of growing discontent.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>What of the government? In last analysis no government in western
                                conception of that term exists in Iraq today, three months after
                                coup. Individual cabinet ministers manage now and then to issue
                                regulations. In few instances cabinet as a whole has approved “Laws”
                                but up to now they are on paper only. Content of these laws, many of
                                which are ill-conceived and hastily drafted, has in several cases
                                required repeated clarification (e.g., laws on rent control, labor
                                and cropsharing). There is <pb facs="0379" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/>
                                widespread paralysis of even routine in first weeks following coup
                                of top layer of trained men comparable, in a measure, to our civil
                                service. Their replacements have been found, are of low caliber
                                indeed. In spite of daily cabinet meetings, there is as yet no
                                coordinated government program in any field, and how could there be?
                                Although cabinet includes handful of men with previous experience
                                this level, this government is woefully lacking in men experienced
                                in the challenging task of governing. This lack is particularly
                                noticeable in the economic development field. The individuals
                                holding cabinet positions have right up to today still nothing more
                                to guide them than the oft-repeated general policy statement of the
                                Prime Minister that Iraq is to be independent; Iraq wants to raise
                                the living standards of the people; Iraq wants to be friends with
                                all nations, east and west, that want to be friends with her; and
                                above all Iraq wants to cooperate closely with other Arab
                                states.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Economy of country is stagnant chiefly because development program
                                which was main pump primer in past has been allowed to grind to
                                halt. Government’s fumbling efforts to manage economy have caused a
                                lack of confidence among the business community which no number of
                                highly publicized but in substantial trade agreements with Soviet
                                Union and Soviet bloc countries can dispel.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Inevitably, even though coup was carried out most effectively by a
                                very small group of conspirators, differences as to the courses to
                                be followed developed early among them. Tensions, primarily among
                                the military but also among certain civilian members of regime, soon
                                came to surface. Momentarily <persName corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName> is on top. <persName>Arif</persName>, second
                                in July 14 plot, has been deprived of military and political power
                                positions and left October 12 to become Iraqi Ambassador in Bonn.
                                The known Baathist members of the cabinet were removed or demoted at
                                same time as <persName>Arif</persName> fell from grace. Thus most
                                important elements working toward union with <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, or at the least toward very close collaboration
                                with <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>, have been
                                removed from center of government. The group that seems to influence
                                    <persName corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName> most at present
                                is made up of members of the National Democratic Party led by Kamal
                                Chaderchi and Mohammed Hadid. This group, unfortunately, is naive to
                                the extreme concerning danger which communism holds for Iraq.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName>, we believe, is
                                anti-Communist, and may be making a sincere effort to hold
                                Communists in check. We do not think, on basis of reports we have
                                received from diplomatic colleagues and reports emanating from Iraqi
                                sources, that Communists played a major role in having
                                    <persName>Arif</persName> and Baathist Ministers removed from
                                power. Communists do not today have that much influence with the
                                regime. By weakening of Baathist influence, however, Communists
                                undoubtedly gain much more room for maneuver. Communists also have
                                potential for attack on another point through returned Kurdish
                                leader Mulla Mustafa Barzani. He has spent last eleven years in
                                exile in Soviet Union. <pb facs="0380" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/> His
                                appeal to a majority of Iraqi Kurds is strong and his ability
                                disrupt stability almost endless. Thus we believe that today
                                greatest potential threat to stability and even existence of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName>’s regime lies in
                                hands of Communists.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>As of today, three months after coup, <persName corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName>’s regime is by no means firmly entrenched.
                                There exist strong pressures on it from without and within regime;
                                there is no solid unanimity and tensions are rampant. We are in for
                                weeks, perhaps even months, of uncertainty. Certainly weeks just
                                ahead are critical. Future stability is dependent on <persName corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName>’s ability to withstand the
                                various pressures being brought to bear on him and to lead country
                                back to normal existence.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Up to now <persName corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName>’s regime,
                                whether deliberately or not, has in the main been carrying out a
                                predominately wrecking operation. We think some of those around him
                                are finally beginning to realize that it is much simpler to effect a
                                coup and tear down government than it is to govern.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>From my personal experience and observation covering these past
                                four years in Iraq, I would say that with the murder of <persName corresp="#p_alSN1">Nuri</persName>, illiberal as he may at times
                                have been in dealing with domestic issues, Iraq sacrificed her best
                                leader toward an eventual life of dignity and decency and her
                                strongest bulwark against recurrent chaos, if not savagery. A number
                                of well placed and knowledgeable Iraqis have been quoted to me
                                within the past few days as having said, in effect, that within ten
                                years at most a monument would be erected in Baghdad to <persName corresp="#p_alSN1">Nuri</persName>.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I hope, in fact I believe, they are right.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_GWJ2"><hi rend="strong">Gallman</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>