<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>161. Special National Intelligence Estimate</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d161</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">161</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recb6XG1ZU9Ik84CR" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Broadcasting</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recgHSq0J1Seyqrw9" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033502"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Coup</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-02-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="161"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d161">
                <head>161. Special National Intelligence Estimate<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d161fn0">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_OCB1"
                            >OCB</gloss> Files: Lot 61 D 385, Iraq Documents. Secret. A note on the
                        cover sheet indicates that this special estimate, submitted by the <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, was prepared by the <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>, the
                        intelligence organizations of the Army, the Navy, the Air Force, the Joint
                        Staff, and the Director of the National Security Agency. All members of the
                            <gloss target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss> concurred with this estimate on
                        February 17 except the representatives of the <gloss target="#t_AEC1"
                            >AEC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> and the Assistant
                        to the Secretary of Defense for Special Operations, who abstained on the
                        grounds that the subject was outside their jurisdiction.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss> 36.2–59</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1959-02-17">February 17, 1959</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">THE COMMUNIST THREAT TO IRAQ</p>
                <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                <p>To estimate prospective developments in Iraq over the next few months and their
                    implications for Western interests in the Middle East.</p>
                <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Iraq is the scene of a determined and so far effective Communist drive
                        toward power. Prime Minister Kassim may be a Communist, though we think it
                        more likely that he is an Iraqi nationalist who believes he needs Communist
                        support to protect himself against the designs of the <gloss
                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and the Western Powers. Whatever his
                        desires, we doubt his ability to stem the movement toward a Communist
                        takeover of his regime, and we believe that his area for maneuver is
                        shrinking rapidly. (Paras. 6–11)</item>
                    <pb facs="0416" n="382" xml:id="pg_382"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Many politically conscious Iraqis are beginning to see that Kassim’s
                        policy of co-operation with the Communists involves threats to Iraqi
                        independence and to their own interests. Only the army has the capability
                        for effective action against the Kassim regime. However, potential
                        opposition—both civilian and military—to the present trend is unorganized,
                        leaderless, and unlikely to take action unless given stimulus by <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>, who wields considerable influence
                        as the symbol of Arab nationalism. (Paras. 11–13, 16)</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>We believe that <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> will seek by
                        all means at his disposal to bring about a counterrevolutionary move in
                        Iraq, even if it involves serious risk of damaging his relations with the
                        Soviets, and that he will be prepared to accept at least provisionally an
                        independent Iraqi nationalist regime. (Paras. 17–18)</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>We do not believe that the Soviets, at present, consider their interests
                        or prestige so heavily involved in the Iraqi situation that they would
                        accept the risks and disadvantages involved in any overt intervention to
                        block a nationalist counterrevolution against Kassim. If they saw such a
                        move coming, however, they would be likely to step up their efforts and
                        their timetable. If as time goes on, growing Communist power in Iraq should
                        involve heavier Soviet commitments to the Iraqi regime, the Bloc would
                        become increasingly disposed to accept the risks of responding to requests
                        for assistance in maintaining a pro-Communist regime in power. (Para.
                        27)</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Communist initiatives in Iraq, whether or not they succeed in
                        consolidating control there, are likely to increase Arab suspicions of the
                        Soviets and might bring about a more genuine neutrality. A successful
                        counterrevolutionary move, however, would probably not change basic Pan-Arab
                        nationalist policies toward the West. (Paras. 21, 28)</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="center">Discussion</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">I. The Present Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Iraq is the scene of a determined and so far effective Communist drive
                        toward power. This drive threatens important US interests: the maintenance
                        of assured Western access to Middle East oil, the denial of the area to
                        Soviet control, and the security and stability of non-Communist governments
                        in the area as a whole. The Iraqi situation has already reshaped many of the
                        issues which dominate the Middle East scene, for it poses new and critical
                        problems not only for the West, but for Iran and other states in the
                        area.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>After seven months in power, Prime Minister Kassim remains something of an
                        enigma even to a number of Iraqis who have been associated with him in the
                        revolutionary government. There is no conclusive evidence that Kassim is
                        himself a Communist or disposed to turn Iraq <pb facs="0417" n="383"
                            xml:id="pg_383"/> over to Soviet domination, and he continues to profess
                        a philosophy of ardent Arab nationalism, opposition to foreign influence,
                        and dedication to the ideas of Iraqi independence and of “positive
                        neutralism.” He has made a few anti-Communist gestures, and has left certain
                        key internal security posts, e.g., the Ministry of the Interior, in the
                        hands of anti-Communists.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>At the same time, Kassim has shown himself unwilling or unable to take
                        effective action against the steady drive of the Iraqi Communists and their
                        Soviet backers to consolidate a growing position of power within the country
                        and the government. He has resisted repeated demands by senior army officers
                        for a crackdown on local Communists. He continues to countenance the
                        presence in a number of key positions of men who are probably Communists,
                        for example his own chief aide and the Director of Broadcasting. Some
                        important ministries have been infiltrated by known Communists. Iraqi
                        representatives at inter-Arab and Afro-Asian conferences have consistently
                        advocated actions beneficial to the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                        and opposed to the interests of both Pan-Arabism and the West. Kassim has
                        done little about the manifest ability of the Communists to use “the street”
                        in organized mob demonstrations and mass pressure tactics. And when
                        confronted in early February with the group resignation of six
                        anti-Communist civilian cabinet ministers—some of them recognized opposition
                        figures of long standing—he replaced them with men less friendly toward
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> and no more likely than
                        their predecessors to pose effective resistance to the Communists.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Although Kassim may be a Communist moving deliberately to advance Soviet
                        control of Iraq without risking the adverse repercussions of a sudden
                        takeover, we think it more likely that his course of action has been
                        dictated by other motives and circumstances. There is evidence that he is a
                        neurotic and unstable individual; that he is lacking in qualities of
                        decisiveness and leadership; and that he is prey to fears for his regime and
                        his own position in it. In particular, Kassim has probably been genuinely
                        concerned about the dangers of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and US
                        interference in Iraq. Iraqi Communists, working through such channels as the
                        Communist-infiltrated National Democratic Party, have assiduously exploited
                        Kassim’s fears and his need for support and assurance.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Whatever Kassim’s private attitude toward the Communists and their
                        sympathizers, the net effect of his conduct has been to increase their power
                        and opportunities until they are now the most effective and unified
                        political organization in the country. We believe it likely that Kassim
                        still feels that he is in control and is using the Communists for his own
                        purposes, but we have little confidence in his ability to free himself from
                        dependence upon them even if he should elect to try.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Non-Communist nationalist elements are still far more numerous in Iraq
                        than the Communists and their sympathizers, but they are on <pb facs="0418"
                            n="384" xml:id="pg_384"/> the defensive and their prevailing mood
                        appears to be one of uncertainty and growing frustration. Many prominent
                        civilian and military figures have been jailed. The recent mass resignation
                        of anti-Communist cabinet ministers may have been undertaken in the hope of
                        forcing Kassim to take action to reverse present trends, but it is equally
                        possible that the move was made out of sheer despair. An increasing number
                        of groups in Iraq are beginning to perceive the threat that the Communists
                        pose to their particular interests. This includes both secular nationalist
                        and religious groups. There is a beginning awareness of Kassim’s growing
                        dependence upon the Communists and the threat this poses to Iraqi
                        independence. Even the hitherto Communist-collaborating National Democratic
                        Party—the last civilian backers of Kassim—shows signs of fearing the
                        Communist thrust for power and may part company with the Iraqi Communist
                        Party. We believe, however, that the civilian opposition lacks the
                        organization and leadership necessary to take any effective initiative
                        against Kassim and his Communist allies.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>The Iraqi public—generally favorable to the revolution and still strongly
                        influenced by <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>—is divided and
                        uncertain, reflecting the conflicting forces at play in the country. The
                        Pan-Arab Baath Party retains some ability to call out demonstrators, but the
                        Communists are showing increasing superiority in influencing “the street.”
                        Much will depend upon whether Iraqi nationalists can muster public support
                        before the Communists succeed in discrediting them, by accusing them of
                        playing into the hands of <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> and
                        the “imperialists.”</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>Although we have only limited information about the political orientation
                        of the army, we believe that it constitutes the chief potential source of
                        resistance to the trends prevailing under Kassim’s government. Most of the
                        officer corps is almost certainly nationalist in sympathy, and while some
                        Communist penetration of the armed forces has probably taken
                        place—attracting at least a certain number of opportunists—the great
                        majority of officers remain non-Communist or anti-Communist. However,
                        Kassim’s regime has bid for the sympathy of the officer corps by supplying
                        the armed forces with impressive amounts of Soviet equipment and by liberal
                        pay and promotion policies. Like the civilian nationalists, however, the
                        army leaders will probably move, if at all, only if given some stimulus to
                        action, some guidance and some assurance of outside support. In the
                        meantime, the army’s capability for action against the Kassim government and
                        the Communists is being steadily undermined by Kassim’s systematic
                        reshuffling of assignments and by his creation of a new division of selected
                        units presumably designed for the protection of the government.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0419" n="385" xml:id="pg_385"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">II. Prospective Developments</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>We do not believe that the Communists plan a sudden coup or a forceful
                        seizure of power. In our opinion they would prefer to move gradually toward
                        actual control of Iraq, seeking to take over strategic positions and groups
                        one by one, but leaving an ostensibly independent regime. In particular, we
                        believe that they would not attempt a final consolidation of power until
                        they have successfully penetrated or neutralized the army. We believe that
                        it will be some months before they can accomplish this.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>As Communist power grows, it is possible that Kassim will become concerned
                        over the threat from this quarter, and he might attempt to remove the
                        Communists from positions of influence and to limit the activities of Soviet
                        representatives in Iraq. To date, however, we have seen no evidence that
                        Kassim is thinking in these terms. Particularly while suspicions of the West
                        and of the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> remain uppermost in his mind,
                        we believe that any significant change of course on his part is
                        unlikely.</item>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>We have already mentioned the apparent lack of will and leadership among
                        potential anti-Communist and anti-Kassim forces—both military and in the
                        public at large. If these forces are to be moved to action, some assurance
                        of support will probably have to come from <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName>, since any counterrevolutionary movement in Iraq
                        which appeared to be Western-inspired would have little chance of success.
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> has made one serious
                        attempt to overthrow the Kassim government and is seeking to build assets
                        for another.<note n="1" xml:id="d161fn1">
                            <p>On February 28, <persName corresp="#p_EJSD1">John S.D.
                                    Eisenhower</persName> included the following information on Iraq
                                in his “Synopsis of State and Intelligence Material reported to the
                                President”:</p>
                            <p>“An Iraqi official has reported an attempt to assassinate Qasim on
                                February 22. Fifteen arrests reportedly ensued.</p>
                            <p>“A late item on February 28 indicates that a coup by Iraqi army
                                elements backed by Nasir is scheduled between 2–5 March. Plotters
                                plan to assassinate Qasim. It is estimated that unless army units in
                                Baghdad join the conspiracy, a successful coup would be dubious.</p>
                            <p>“The President also read <gloss target="#t_SNIE1">SNIE</gloss>
                                36.2–59 which pertains to the situation in Iraq.” (Eisenhower
                                Library, Whitman File, <persName>Eisenhower</persName> Diaries)</p>
                        </note> He will almost certainly continue to work assiduously to develop and
                        exploit every possible lead to a counterrevolution in Iraq. He has important
                        resources at his disposal. In addition to his own network of agents and
                        friends, he has the authority and influence that stem from his widespread
                        acceptance as a successful leader of Arab nationalism. As Communist power
                        increases in Iraq, non-Communist Iraqi groups—military and civilian—are
                        likely to become increasingly conscious of this threat and ready to
                        compromise with <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> as the only
                        effective source of help. In the right <pb facs="0420" n="386"
                            xml:id="pg_386"/> situation <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName>’s propaganda machine could be used to exert a
                        formidable influence upon the Iraqi people and army to turn them against the
                        Kassim regime and their Communist allies.</item>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> is almost certainly aware of
                        the risks to himself attendant on a fight with the Communists in Iraq. He
                        would become subject to charges by the Communists and some Iraqi
                        nationalists that he is doing the dirty work for Western imperialists. More
                        importantly, he would be inviting a direct clash with the <gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, at the risk of losing the extensive
                        military and economic support he has been receiving from that source.
                        Finally, he almost certainly retains grave suspicions that the West—and his
                        enemies in the area—might seize the opportunity to undermine him while he
                        was embroiled with the Communists in Iraq and clashing with the Soviets.
                        Nevertheless, we believe that <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                        views the Communist threat in Iraq as a critical challenge to his whole
                        position and aspirations in the area, and is almost certainly determined to
                        muster his resources to combat it. He appears to believe that his efforts
                        will not cost him Soviet assistance, but he might be willing to accept
                        serious risks of such a loss in a final showdown on Iraq.</item>
                    <label>18.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s hostility to the trend in
                        Iraq will probably serve to make Kassim even more suspicious of nationalist
                        elements in his own country and more prone to depend on the local Communists
                        and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> for support and assistance.
                        Kassim’s suspicions would be compounded should he believe that a <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>–Western rapprochement were in the
                        making. Kassim will be alert to <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>-inspired
                        plots and will attempt to neutralize or destroy <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName>’s assets in Iraq. Even so, Kassim’s policies might
                        stimulate a counterrevolutionary effort in Iraq while there is still a
                        chance of success. Even though such a counterrevolutionary effort might be
                        in part the creation of <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>, and
                        its leaders might accept some loose affiliation with the <gloss
                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, they would almost certainly insist on a
                        considerable degree of independence for Iraq. We believe that <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> would regard this as preferable to
                        an Iraq under Communist domination.</item>
                    <label>19.</label>
                    <item>In the event of an outright clash between the Kassim regime and a
                        counterrevolutionary effort, there is some chance that neither side would
                        win a clear victory. The resulting period of disorder might lead to the
                        factioning of the army, and a period of chaos with any or all of the
                        contending factions calling for outside intervention.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">III. Implications of a Communist Takeover in Iraq</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>20.</label>
                    <item>If and when it became apparent that a Communist-controlled regime had
                        actually come to power in Iraq, this would almost certainly provoke an acute
                        crisis in the Middle East. Friends of the West and neutralists in the area
                        would both feel acutely this threat to their security. There would be
                        insistent pressures on the US to “do something.” At the <pb facs="0421"
                            n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> same time, the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss> would issue a series of ominous warnings and threats to
                        stave off intervention.</item>
                    <label>21.</label>
                    <item>Communist control of Iraq would establish the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss> in the heart of the Middle East—contiguous to Syria, Saudi
                        Arabia, Jordan, and Kuwait, and outflanking two US allies, Turkey and Iran.
                        Such an extension of Soviet power into the area would serve to strip the
                        Soviets of their former immunity from charges of “imperialist” motives in
                        the area. It might also lead to the moderation of Arab hostility toward the
                        West and make Arab neutralism more genuine. Nevertheless, it would amount to
                        an impressive Soviet victory which would influence the leanings of area
                        opportunists.</item>
                    <label>22.</label>
                    <item>A Communist-controlled Iraq would also threaten Western access to Middle
                        East oil. Although we estimate that such a government might initially prove
                        fairly reasonable with respect to permitting continued Western access to
                        Iraqi oil—in the interests of receiving continued revenue and of avoiding
                        drastic Western response—it would at a minimum insist on substantial
                        modifications in the terms and conditions under which Iraqi oil flows to the
                        West. In any case the future of the Iraq Petroleum Company would be
                        unpromising indeed—with ultimate nationalization likely. And while such a
                        move would not constitute an irreparable blow to the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                            >UK</gloss>—so long as it had Kuwait oil available—it would be serious
                        in itself and additionally so because it would weaken Britain’s hold in
                        Kuwait and throughout the oil-producing areas of the Persian Gulf.</item>
                    <label>23.</label>
                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> is far from oblivious to this
                        danger. At the same time, continuing British hostility to <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> has prompted the <gloss
                            target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> to hope that Kassim might provide a feasible
                        alternative between a <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName>-dominated and a Communist-dominated regime in Iraq and an
                        effective rival to <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> for
                        influence in the Arab world at large. The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                        has been the more inclined to indulge in these hopes because it has received
                        somewhat better treatment from the Kassim regime than has the US. There are
                        now indications that at some levels and in some parts of the British
                        Government it has been concluded that these are futile hopes. Further rapid
                        consolidation of leftist forces in Iraq would probably increase <gloss
                            target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> sentiment in favor of a <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> effort to stop the Iraqi
                        Communists.</item>
                    <label>24.</label>
                    <item>The Turks, Iranians, Israelis, and French have hitherto shown more concern
                        over the disadvantages to them of a pro-<persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName> takeover in Iraq than over the Communist threat
                        there. However, there is already evidence of some change in the attitude of
                        the Turks and especially of the Iranians. Both will press insistently for
                        increased US support and commitments to meet the danger. A Communist Iraq
                        would increase the potential of the Tudeh Party in Iran considerably. Iran
                        would be particularly sensitive about any Iraqi attempt to interfere with
                        access to Iranian oil ports. Turkey and Iran would be tempted to take
                        further steps to <pb facs="0422" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/> influence events
                        in Iraq, but would take no significant action without requesting US
                        support.</item>
                    <label>25.</label>
                    <item>Of all area states, Israel is most concerned lest the Communist threat in
                        Iraq bring <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> and the West closer
                        together, or lest a successful pro-<persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName> countermove in Iraq should confirm <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> as undisputed leader of a united
                        Arab world. Growing tension between the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> may lead
                        to an improvement in Soviet-Israeli relations. At the same time, Israel’s
                        policy will be conditioned by its knowledge of the importance of its ties
                        with the West.</item>
                    <label>26.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s past policies of doing
                        business with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would be discredited
                        and his claims as leader of the Pan-Arab unity movement contested as a
                        result of the establishment of a Communist government in Iraq. He would
                        moreover be faced with greatly increased problems of subversion within his
                        own <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, particularly in Syria. However, if
                        he continues to challenge the Soviet-Communist role in Iraq, his relations
                        with and his influence in the other Arab states are likely to
                        improve.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">IV. Implications of an Arab Nationalist Counteraction in
                        Iraq</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>27.</label>
                    <item>We do not believe that the Soviets, at present, consider their interests
                        or prestige so heavily involved in the Iraqi situation that they would
                        accept the risks and disadvantages involved in any overt intervention to
                        block a nationalist counterrevolution against Kassim. If they saw such a
                        move coming, however, they would be likely to step up their efforts and
                        their timetable. If as time goes on, growing Communist power in Iraq should
                        involve heavier Soviet commitments to the Iraqi regime, the Bloc would
                        become increasingly disposed to accept the risks of responding to requests
                        for assistance in maintaining a pro-Communist regime in power.</item>
                    <label>28.</label>
                    <item>If a non-Communist nationalist government is re-established in Iraq, the
                        Pan-Arab nationalists in the several Arab states led by <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> are likely to continue a policy and
                        a posture like that of the past. Their position regarding Israel and Algeria
                        will remain much the same. They will hope to upset the regime in Jordan, to
                        eject the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> from its privileged position in
                        the Arabian Peninsula, and to move toward the imposition of Arab controls
                        over Arab oil.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
