<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>203. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and
                    South Asian Affairs (Jones) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State
                    Herter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d203</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">203</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recCP2IC3LozXMzXn" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="rec3b4QX8ohh76TF3" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004886"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Journalist</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="203"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d203">
                <head>203. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and
                    South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_JGLJ1" type="from">Jones</persName>)
                    to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1" type="to">Herter</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d203fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 787.00/9–2859. Top Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MAH1"
                            >Meyer</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1959-09-28">September 28, 1959</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Statement to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> re the Situation in
                        Iraq</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Pursuant to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> action 2068, April 17, 1959,<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d203fn1">See <ref target="#d176fn12">footnote 12, Document
                            176</ref>.</note> an inter-agency committee was established to concern
                    itself with the situation in Iraq and to consider feasible courses of action
                    with a view to preventing a Communist take-over in that country. The
                    Department’s <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Assistant Secretary was named
                    chairman of the group.</p>
                <p>The inter-agency group held a number of meetings during April, May and June under
                    the chairmanship of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JJD2">Jernegan</persName> was brought home and
                    his views were extremely helpful to the Committee’s deliberations as well as to
                    the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>, before whom Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_JJD2">Jernegan</persName> appeared personally.</p>
                <p>In its deliberations, the inter-agency committee agreed that the policy outlined
                    in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5820/1 entitled “Statement of United
                    States Policy toward the Near East”<note n="2" xml:id="d203fn2">
                        <ref target="#d51">Document 51</ref>.</note> continued to be valid, and no
                    change of this basic policy was required. With reference to specific courses of
                    action, the Committee felt that dramatic military or political action by the
                    United States was not desirable, that the most effective restraint on Communism
                        <pb facs="0519" n="485" xml:id="pg_485"/> in Iraq is that exercised by the
                    Arab peoples themselves, and that our best efforts could be along the lines of
                    encouraging Qasim, particularly through third parties such as Afro-Asian
                    representatives, to maintain an independent Iraq resistant to the Communist
                    threat.</p>
                <p>When the situation in Iraq appeared to be improving (Tab B),<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d203fn3">Tab B is a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_RWM1"
                            >Rountree</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>,
                        June 17, reporting on events in Iraq since May 21 and the work of the
                        interagency committee. (Department of State, <gloss target="#t_SP1"
                            >S/P</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot 62 D 1,
                        Iraq, The Situation, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action 2068)</note>
                    the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> accepted a recommendation on June 22 by
                    the inter-agency group that further weekly reports by the Committee to the
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> would be discontinued unless there
                    occurred a substantial change in the situation in Iraq.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d203fn4">See <ref target="#d194">Document 194</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Since there have been some recent somewhat disturbing developments in Iraq, the
                    inter-agency committee under my chairmanship met again to examine the Iraqi
                    situation on September 24. It was agreed to report to the <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> that the meeting was held, that the situation
                    in Iraq was reviewed, that at the moment there appears to be no reason to alter
                    policies and action courses previously agreed upon, but that the Committee would
                    meet again when further information and evaluations are available including
                    particularly the views of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JJD2"
                        >Jernegan</persName>. In this connection, we have sent a telegram to
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JJD2">Jernegan</persName> asking for an
                        assessment<note n="5" xml:id="d203fn5">Telegram 920 to Baghdad, September
                        28. (Department of State, Central Files, 787.00/9–2859)</note> and his
                    preliminary response<note n="6" xml:id="d203fn6">
                        <p>In telegram 787 from Baghdad, September 29, the Embassy informed the
                            Department that telegram 784 from Baghdad (September 28), which crossed
                            telegram 920 to Baghdad, “gives our best estimate present situation.”
                            The Embassy did not see any reason to change U.S. policies since U.S.
                            capabilities for influencing the situation remained extremely limited,
                            and believed that U.S. intervention, either direct or indirect, would
                            only make matters worse. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)</p>
                        <p>In telegram 784 from Baghdad, the Embassy submitted a general estimate on
                            Iraq during the last 7 weeks, stating that the “pattern of events during
                            the period has been inconsistent, with factors unfavorable to Communist
                            cause running parallel to another sequence which has benefited
                            Communists. But momentum of anti-Communist trend has slowed, while
                            circumstances which favor Communists have assumed greater importance,
                            especially in past two weeks.” The Embassy concluded that <persName
                                corresp="#p_QGAK1">Qassim</persName>’s ability to maintain a
                            “balance” was declining, and outspoken nationalist criticism might impel
                            him to turn once again to the Communists for support. (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Ibid.</hi>)</p>
                    </note> may be available to you before the meeting Wednesday morning.<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d203fn7">September 30.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>That you report to the Council that the inter-agency committee concerned
                        with Iraq pursuant to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> action 2068 of
                        April 17 met on September 24, that it reviewed the situation in Iraq
                        including the September <pb facs="0520" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/> 20
                            executions,<note n="8" xml:id="d203fn8">See Tab A.</note> that it was
                        felt that at the moment there appears to be no need to alter the basic
                        policy established by <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5820/1 and the
                        courses of action previously agreed upon by the Committee, but the Committee
                        intends to keep close surveillance on the situation in Iraq and meet again
                        after further information and evaluations are available, particularly from
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_JJD2">Jernegan</persName>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>If there is a request at the Council for an account of significant
                        developments in Iraq since the last report by the Committee on June 17, you
                        may wish to draw upon the summary attached herewith as Tab A.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>That you indicate that you will again report to the Council concerning
                        Iraq following the next meeting of the inter-agency committee.</item>
                </list>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Tab A<note n="9" xml:id="d203fn9">Top Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Summary of Events in Iraq Since Late June</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In reviewing the situation since the latter part of June, the intervening
                        period can usefully be divided into the time up to August 11 and the period
                        since then.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Between late June and early August the following favorable
                            developments took place: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>The Popular Resistance Forces which had been heavily
                                    infiltrated by the Communists were first disarmed and
                                    subsequently all but disbanded by Qasim. Training was
                                    discontinued and even the wearing of <gloss target="#t_PRF1"
                                        >PRF</gloss>-type uniforms in public has been
                                    forbidden.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>A number of strongly anti-Communist newspapers, including
                                    several that had been sacked by Communist-led mobs at the time
                                    of the Mosul revolt, re-emerged. They have continued up until
                                    the present to take a line strongly antagonistic to Communist
                                    activities in Iraq.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>The influence of the moderate Ministers of Foreign Affairs and
                                    Finance appeared to be on the increase and there was an apparent
                                    lessening of anti-Western suspicions on the part of the Iraqi
                                    Government.</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>Qasim reaffirmed his ban on political party activity and
                                    publicly rebuffed Communist efforts to press the formation of a
                                    United National Front.</item>
                                <pb facs="0521" n="487" xml:id="pg_487"/>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item>Finally, the Communists badly overplayed their hand at the
                                    time of the July 14 celebrations of the first anniversary of the
                                    revolution. Communist supporters were involved in bloody
                                    atrocities and murders in Kirkuk which moved the Prime Minister
                                    to public expression of horror and public castigation of the
                                    “anarchists” responsible for these events. This stand on Qasim’s
                                    part, and concomitant measures taken by the military authorities
                                    against the student unions and other Communist infiltrated
                                    organizations, greatly heartened nationalist and anti-Communist
                                    elements in Iraq.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The resurgence of the nationalists shortly reached such dimensions
                            that Qasim apparently again became nervous for his own position and
                            became convinced that his policy of seeking to maintain a balance
                            between the Communists and nationalists was in danger. In any event it
                            was suddenly announced on August 11 that Brig. Gen. Tabaqchali and a
                            number of other senior officers suspected of involvement in the Mosul
                            revolt would, contrary to prevailing expectations, be brought to trial
                            before the so-called People’s Court of Col. Mahdawi. These officers were
                            all considered to have nationalist leanings. This decision began a train
                            of events which have increased tensions in Iraq. <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>On August 13, Qasim, apparently stung by the defiant attitude
                                    of Tabaqchali and other defendants in the opening session of
                                    their trial before the People’s Court on the previous day,
                                    publicly gave the court president, Col. Fadhil Mahdawi, his
                                    unqualified support and endorsement. This move discouraged the
                                    hopes of anti-Communist elements who consider that by his words
                                    and deeds Col. Mahdawi had shown himself to be favorably
                                    inclined toward, if not the actual ally of, the Communists in
                                    Iraq.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Large numbers of Communist students who had been rounded up
                                    after the Kirkuk massacre were ordered released by Qasim and
                                    allowed to return to their studies with an admonition to stay
                                    out of politics.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>A Communist-dominated coalition slate won the Journalist
                                    Association elections, with the result that the Board of the
                                    Association, which has the power to close down publications by
                                    expulsion of publishers from membership, is largely in the hands
                                    of the Communists and their sympathizers.</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>The execution on August 25 of five military officers and one
                                    civilian earlier convicted of participation in the Mosul revolt
                                    provided a further indication of the way the wind was blowing.
                                    This was followed on September 20 by the sudden carrying out of
                                    the death sentences handed down earlier by Col. Mahdawi’s Court,
                                    of the 13 nationalist officers headed by the popular Brig.
                                    Tabaqchali. The immediately preceding execution of Sa’id Qazzaz,
                                    Minister of Interior under Nuri Sa’id, and three old regime
                                    police officials was apparently intended partly as a sop to the
                                    Communists and partly to counter criticism that no old regime
                                    executions had been carried out whereas 23 of the thirty
                                    officers sentenced <pb facs="0522" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/> to
                                    death in connection with the Mosul rebellion have been put to
                                    death.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>While developments since August 11 have clearly been to the disfavor
                            of the nationalist elements, it seems premature to conclude that the
                            Communists have made corresponding gains. As late as two days ago, Qasim
                            declared publicly that Iraq will maintain its policy of neutrality and
                            will become a satellite of no country. Qasim’s actions against
                            nationalist elements since August 11 quite probably were designed to
                            establish respect for his authority in the face of recurring rumors of
                            anti-Qasim conspiracies allegedly supported by <persName
                                corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>. Undoubtedly they have earned
                            for Qasim bitter nationalist hatred. Despite a few relatively mild
                            disturbances in reaction to the September 20 executions, Qasim seems as
                            of the moment still to have the internal security situation under
                            control. However, the army on which Qasim depends for his authority
                            appears deeply riven by Communist-nationalist conflict.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
