<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-08-09T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-08-09T05:00:00-05:00" n="273" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d273">
                        <head>273. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Israel</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d273fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 033.84A88/8–959. Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution.
                                Repeated to Tehran and London.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Tel Aviv</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-08-09T12:00:00+02:00">August 9,
                                    1959, noon</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>136. Ben-Gurion told me in confidence following lunch at residence August
                            8 that <persName corresp="#p_EA3">Abba Eban</persName> plans to leave
                            for Iran week August 10 and requested I talk Eban Weizmann Institute
                                today.<note n="1" xml:id="d273fn1">On July 24, the Shah announced
                                that Iran had extended Israel de facto recognition, but emphasized
                                that such recognition had been in existence since 1949
                                notwithstanding the fact that the Iranian envoy had been recalled
                                from Tel Aviv in 1951. The Shah added that there was never any
                                question of extending de jure recognition to Israel. The Shah’s
                                announcement occasioned sharp criticism in the Arab world,
                                especially from President <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>, and the United Arab Republic’s
                                representative in Tehran was declared persona non grata by the
                                Iranian Government.</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0682" n="648" xml:id="pg_648"/>
                        <p>Prime Minister indicated he had had important secret talk Major General
                                <persName corresp="#p_BGT1">Bakhtiar</persName> of Iran about July
                            27.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BGT1">Bakhtiar</persName> whom Ben-Gurion described
                            as “No. 2 man Iran who had ear of Shah” made following points:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Iran more or less forced to conclude recent bi-lateral pact
                                    US;<note n="2" xml:id="d273fn2">See <ref target="#d267">Document
                                        267</ref>.</note> that Iran now felt “let down” by US as
                                Turkey and Pakistan received substantial arms while Iran was not
                                with result Iranian 200,000 Roman army’s equipment now becoming
                                obsolete.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Raised question Iranian-Soviet relations and specifically queried
                                Ben-Gurion “should they (Iran) turn to Russia?”</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Prime Minister said he stated to <persName corresp="#p_BGT1">Bakhtiar</persName> Iran had no alternative but to stay closely
                            allied West and that Iran clearly protected by US.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BGT1">Bakhtiar</persName> commented on latter point
                            and reportedly said “we are proud, independent and we want to be able to
                            defend ourselves.”</p>
                        <p>Further, Ben-Gurion made point to <persName corresp="#p_BGT1">Bakhtiar</persName> that Iran should continue raise standard of
                            living its people to which <persName corresp="#p_BGT1">Bakhtiar</persName> replied this is “also Shah’s view”.</p>
                        <p>I indicated that we knew Iran somewhat concerned Soviet broadcasts but
                            that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> believed that broadcasts might
                            go on whatever Iranian policy; that as regards arms this not a new
                            question and involved absorptive and technical capacity of Iran to make
                            use military equipment and economic aid. Added that I not familiar
                            details but happy report <persName corresp="#p_BGT1">Bakhtiar</persName>’s comments to Department and sure they would be
                            carefully considered.</p>
                        <p>Ben-Gurion then said in view “important” to strengthen Iran; that US
                            “appeared” to be doing more for <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> than for Iran which clear friend; and that US as
                            he understood it had done and was doing more militarily for Turkey and
                            Pakistan than for Iran.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister emphasized his belief that if more could be done
                            militarily strengthen Iran and if Iran felt psychologically more clearly
                            supported by US then this feeling and evidence this support might in
                            turn encourage Afghanistan to “turn away more from Russia, more toward
                            West”.</p>
                        <p>Finally Ben-Gurion said several Israeli “cultural” and agricultural
                            experts had been to Iran at latter’s request and one Israeli now working
                            consultant Iranian Ministry of Agriculture.</p>
                        <p>In strict confidence Ben-Gurion indicated <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> policy, details of which not clearly known “our people”
                            based in part strengthening Israeli relations with Turkey, Iran,
                            Ethiopia, Sudan and “maybe later” with Iraq.</p>
                        <pb facs="0683" n="649" xml:id="pg_649"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Efforts to strengthen Israel’s relations
                            with Iran in particular and expression of concern over security of Iran
                            and future course of Iran vis-à-vis <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> are significant in view of Israel’s dependence on Iran
                            as source of oil for Eilat pipeline for which contract recently signed
                            with Rothschild group. Ben-Gurion’s comments also indicative his clear
                            belief importance US support for Iran to security and independence
                            entire area.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_ROR1"><hi rend="strong">Reid</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>