<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-06-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="356" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d356">
                        <head>356. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern
                            and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>) and the Assistant Secretary of State for Policy
                            Planning (<persName corresp="#p_SGC1" type="from">Smith</persName>) to
                            Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_DCD1" type="to">Dillon</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d356fn0">Source:
                                Department of State, PPS Files: Lot 67 D 548, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> and Middle East. Top Secret.
                                Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RHC2">Henry C. Ramsey</persName> of
                                    <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss> and cleared with <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RGF1">Reinhardt</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-06-30">June 30,
                                    1959</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Use of Force to Maintain Access to Persian Gulf Oil</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>For the past several months an intra-Departmental committee
                                chaired by <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss> and consisting of
                                representatives of <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss>
                                and <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss> has studied the
                                practicability of maintaining access to essential requirements of
                                Near Eastern oil by the use of military force within the purview of
                                (Tab II) <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5820/1<note n="1" xml:id="d356fn1"><ref target="#d51">Document
                                51</ref>.</note>—the latest statement of US policy on the Near East.
                                Paragraph 23 of this document, which was approved last fall,
                                provides that the US should be prepared to use force as a last
                                resort, either alone or in support of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, to insure that the quantity of oil available from
                                the Near East on reasonable terms is sufficient, together with oil
                                from other sources, to meet Western Europe’s requirements. The
                                criterion relates the use of force, as a “last resort”, only to the
                                supply of Western Europe’s essential oil requirements. This is the
                                only test of the use of force established in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5820/1.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The study (Tab I),<note n="2" xml:id="d356fn2">The study, June 9,
                                    was attached, but is not printed.</note> of which we suggest
                                that you read only the covering memorandum of conclusions and
                                recommendations, is transmitted herewith. It reaches three broad
                                conclusions: That (a) the criterion for the use of force
                                unilaterally or in support of the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>,
                                as provided in paragraph 23 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                5820/1, is unrealistic since (i) “last resort” situations are
                                unlikely to occur and (ii) the criterion does not cover situations
                                short of a “last resort” under which the British might invoke force
                                in the Persian Gulf area to protect what are considered to be vital
                                national interests; (b) the adverse consequences of the use of force
                                to maintain access to Near Eastern oil on reasonable terms would be
                                such as to make military force impracticable in the long-term; and
                                (c) serious divergencies exist between the British and ourselves on
                                the issues and situations which might justify the use of force in
                                the Persian Gulf area, especially in respect of Kuwait.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The study recommends that (a) paragraph 23 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5820/1 be reviewed for purposes of
                                developing, if possible, more realistic policy <pb facs="0823" n="789" xml:id="pg_789"/> guidance on the circumstances under
                                which force might be invoked in the Persian Gulf area (this would
                                not require the reopening of the whole of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5820/1 to review, which we would oppose at this
                                time); (b) an effort be made to determine whether divergent
                                    US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> views on the use of force
                                in the Persian Gulf area can be reconciled; (c) the US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> study adjustments which may be
                                required in the area to insure continued peaceful access to
                                essential oil requirements on reasonable terms; and (d) US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> contingency military planning
                                continue against the possibility that situations may arise requiring
                                the use of force to prevent an expansion of Soviet influence in the
                                area.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Certain of these recommendations—(c) and (d)—are being implemented
                                at present. You are of course aware of the contingency military
                                planning which continues in London. We have also recently received a
                                voluminous <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> study, presented by the
                                British Embassy, on Middle East oil concessions which an
                                inter-Departmental committee is now studying. Thus no further action
                                is called for at present under these recommendations.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>We believe that recommendations (a) and (b) should be activated,
                                though we do not at this time believe that it would be productive to
                                discuss further with the British our differing approach to the use
                                of force in the Persian Gulf area. Rather, we recommend that the
                                proposed review of paragraph 23 should examine whether these
                                divergent US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> views can be
                                reconciled and whether it is in our interest to make the effort. We
                                also believe this study might well be forwarded to the Secretary of
                                Defense for his information and that he also be informed of what
                                further action we propose to take on the study’s
                                recommendations.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendations:<note n="3" xml:id="d356fn3"><persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>
                                    approved both recommendations on July 20. The letter to the
                                    Assistant Secretary of Defense forwarding the study is <ref target="#d68">Document 68</ref>.</note></hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>That you authorize review of paragraph 23 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5820/1 along the lines proposed
                                herein.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>That you authorize forwarding of the study to the Secretary of
                                Defense as proposed.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>