<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>39. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-01-17T21:10:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-12-29T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="rec23ea53997c6eb17" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Baghdad Pact</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recdxnUU66ZyvZBYH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Intelligence estimate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-29T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-17T21:10:00-05:00" n="39" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d39">
                <head>39. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>At the 375th Meeting of the National Security Council on August 7, Director of
                    Central Intelligence <persName>Dulles</persName> gave his regular briefing on
                    “Significant Developments Affecting U.S. Security.” Included in this briefing
                    was the following review of the Middle East: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> reported that the Lebanese rebels were
                            pushing toward a victory involving withdrawal of U.S. forces and the
                            exile of the President-elect. Guerrilla activity, but no serious
                            fighting, was taking place. <persName corresp="#p_CC7"
                                >Chamoun</persName> still intended to serve out his term, but might
                            change his mind in exchange for an important post abroad. General
                                <persName corresp="#p_CGF2">Chehab</persName> appeared relaxed, and
                            was not pressing for withdrawal of U.S. forces.</p>
                        <p>“The situation in Jordan had not improved, Mr.
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> reported. Syria had closed its frontier,
                            cutting Jordan off from land contact with the outside world, a
                            development which could have serious effects in the future. At present,
                            the supply situation was somewhat easier—although <gloss
                                target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> remained close—because Israel had
                            relaxed its opposition to overflights. The financial situation in Jordan
                            was so baa that the money-changers would take dollars only at a
                            discount. There was growing talk in Jordan that the King should
                            abdicate. The British took a grim view of the situation, and believed
                            that Jordan’s fate would be decided in the next thirty days.</p>
                        <p>“Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> said the new Iraqi leaders were nervous
                            over the U.S. force build-up in Lebanon. They believed we had more
                            troops in Lebanon than were needed to control the situation there, and
                            feared that our build-up might be directed against Iraq. The <gloss
                                target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> was encouraging this view and sending
                            large numbers of experts into Iraq. Although Iraq had made no move yet,
                            indications were that it would leave the Baghdad Pact but would not
                            enter the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>“Reports were coming in, said Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName>, on
                                <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s dissatisfaction with
                            the union with Syria. <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                            perhaps wishes now that the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> was a
                            looser confederation of a type that Saudi Arabia and Iraq would join.
                            There was also some dissatisfaction in Syria among Army officers and
                            merchants.</p>
                        <p>“[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (5 lines of source text) not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>“In Saudi Arabia, said Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName>,
                                <persName>Faisal</persName>, the dominant figure, would try to make
                            peace with <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> on any terms
                            that would not impair the independence of Saudi Arabia. It was reported
                            that Saudi Arabia and Egypt had just concluded an agreement for the
                            return of the Egyptian military mission to Saudi Arabia. King Saud might
                            be sent for along vacation soon. British concern over Kuwait was
                            increasing. The ruler of Kuwait had refused a U.K. request for
                            permission to land troops to protect the airstrip, and was considering
                            joining the Arab League to propitiate <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                                >Nasser</persName> and relieve the pressure for joining the Arab
                            Union.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Agenda item 2, “The Situation in the Near East,” consisted of a briefing by
                        <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gordon Gray</persName> on the continuing National
                    Security Council Planning Board discussion on the Middle East; see <ref
                        target="#d38">Document 38</ref>. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName>
                    stated that the Board’s deliberations would result in one or more reports for
                    future National Security Council consideration. In addition, <persName
                        corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName> informed <pb facs="0172" n="138"
                        xml:id="pg_138"/> the Council that the Central Intelligence Agency was
                    preparing a Special National Intelligence Estimate, see <ref target="#d40"
                        >Document 40</ref>. (Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records) The Council noted <persName
                        corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName>’s briefing and the Planning Board’s work in
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 1958. (Department of State,
                        <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    (Miscellaneous) Files: Lot 66 D 95, Records of Action by the National Security
                    Council)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
