<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-03-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="176" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                        <head>176. Message From British Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ESA1" type="from">Eden</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d176fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> Papers, White House Memoranda. Secret.
                                Received with a covering note of March 29 from <persName corresp="#p_SSRH1">Scott</persName>. A copy, attached to a
                                memorandum of conversation by <persName corresp="#p_KDMK1">Key</persName>, dated March 29, is also in Department of State,
                                Central Files, 793.00/3–2955.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic">[<placeName>London</placeName>,]</hi>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-03-28"><hi rend="italic">March 28,
                                1955</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Thank you very much for your further message about the offshore
                                islands.<note n="2" xml:id="d176fn2">Transmitted in <ref target="#d171">Document 171</ref>.</note> My colleagues and I
                            are grateful for your willingness to defer action in the Security
                            Council at the present moment. Please do not think we do not understand
                            the difficulties of your position. We recognise the danger that the
                            Chinese Communists may precipitate a conflict. That incidentally is one
                            reason why we are anxious to find some means of getting <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> out of the coastal
                            islands before an attack can develop. Meanwhile we are at one with you
                            in wanting to deter the Communists from attacking. But I do not consider
                            that action in the Security Council will deter them. Our Chargé
                            d’Affaires at Peking thinks that it is more likely to cause them to
                            attack than to restrain them.</p>
                        <p>As regards the wording of the draft resolution, a number of things have
                            happened since our minute of January 26 was agreed. The Chinese have
                            shown us clearly that they are not prepared to agree to any cease-fire
                            and the Soviet Union have equally made clear that they do not think any
                            solution can be found through the Security Council. Moreover, in my
                            statement of March 8<note n="3" xml:id="d176fn3">See <ref target="#d144fn3">footnote 3, Document 144</ref>.</note> I
                            stated Her Majesty’s Government’s position on this whole question. It
                            would be very difficult indeed to debate this issue without any
                            reference to our formally expressed views. <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName>’s recent speech<note n="4" xml:id="d176fn4">In a
                                statement on March 24 in the Canadian House of Commons, Foreign
                                Secretary <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName> had stated
                                the Canadian view that a distinction could be made, politically and
                                strategically, between Formosa and the coastal islands and had urged
                                a peaceful solution to the crisis. The text of the statement is in
                                    <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> Papers, White
                                House Memoranda.</note> shows how the free nations differ over
                            Quemoy and Matsu. We share the Canadian’s views. Thus any debate in the
                            Security Council far from rallying world opinion might only serve to
                            reveal our differences. No amendment of the wording of the resolution
                            could avert this danger.</p>
                        <p>You are worried about Bandung. I agree. The Chinese will certainly do all
                            they can to get the conference to give them its approval and we must try
                            to stop this. But I believe that if we initiate a debate in the Security
                            Council the Asians will simply regard us as expressing Western views and
                            as trying to forestall them at Bandung. I am sure that the effect on
                                <persName corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NU1">U Nu</persName> for example would be <pb facs="0445" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/> bad. I think we would do far
                            better to work on the Asian leaders themselves to warn them against
                            giving the Chinese the green light and to urge them to press for the
                            renunciation of force. This is likely to appeal particularly to the
                            Asians. Pressure from the Asians is likely to be more effective in
                            deterring the Chinese than anything we can say in the Security Council,
                            which they have discounted already. I have therefore instructed Her
                            Majesty’s Representatives in the countries in which I think we may have
                            some influence to urge this on the Governments to which they are
                            accredited. It would be very helpful if your Ambassadors could do the
                            same.</p>
                        <p>In all this I do not want you to think that we are trying to exercise a
                            veto on you. We are not. We are concerned only about the best means of
                            achieving our common objective. I understand your desire to bring in the
                            Security Council at the shortest possible notice if there should be a
                            flare-up. It occurs to me that the New Zealanders might help in this now
                            by instructing their delegate to send a letter to the President of the
                            Council on the following lines:—He had hoped for a meeting of the
                            Security Council at which all interested parties would have been
                            represented; since this could not take place he thought that his
                            colleagues would be interested to see the resolution which he would have
                            put forward had the meeting happened; he was therefore circulating it
                            but he was not asking for it to be discussed at present, particularly
                            since fortunately no fighting was now taking place. If something like
                            this were put forward I have it in mind that it might enable you to
                            claim the necessary priority for the resolution to be discussed first at
                            a later meeting if the need arose. If you think there is anything in
                            this perhaps our experts in New York could examine the idea more
                            closely. I assume of course that we would not press the issue to a
                            debate without further consultation as envisaged in paragraph 5(D) of
                            the Working Party’s report. Will you let me know what you think of this?
                            It might go part way to meet your objective though I still think the
                            less action we take in the Security Council before Bandung the
                                better.<note n="5" xml:id="d176fn5"><p>Telegram 5023 to London,
                                    April 1, transmitted the following message for delivery to
                                        <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Eden</persName>:</p>
                                <p>“Dear <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Anthony</persName>:</p>
                                <p>“Thanks for your message of March 28. We are considering the
                                    suggestion that the present Resolution should be submitted by
                                    New Zealand in a letter to the President of the Council. I
                                    appreciate that in making this suggestion you have gone a
                                    considerable way to meet our point of view and for this I thank
                                    you. On the other hand I see difficulties in explaining why this
                                    curious and novel course is being followed. <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Foster</persName>.” (Department of State,
                                    Central Files, 793.00/4–155)</p></note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>