<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>182. Memorandum From the Director of the Executive Secretariat (Scott) to the
                    ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d182</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">182</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-03-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-03-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-03-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-03-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="182"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                <head>182. Memorandum From the Director of the Executive Secretariat (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SSRH1" type="from">Scott</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                        >Secretary of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d182fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> Library, White House Central Files, Confidential
                        File, Formosan Question. Secret. Also directed to the Under Secretary. The
                        source text is a carbon copy.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-03-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 31, 1955</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Summary of Taipei Telegram 671<note n="2" xml:id="d182fn2">Dated March 30.
                            (Department of State, Central Files, 793.00/3–3055) A copy is attached
                            to the source text.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>An informal survey of American military and civilian officials in Taiwan<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d182fn3">Telegram 671 from Taipei stated that 30 key
                        officials, drawn from all the U.S. agencies represented in Taipei and
                        selected on the basis of experience and interest, had been consulted in the
                        survey.</note> reveals that these officials do not think that morale in
                    Taiwan has changed significantly over the past year. Native Taiwanese tend to
                    feel that the Mutual Security Treaty has increased the security of their home
                    island and are not overly concerned with developments tending to decrease the
                    likelihood of a counter-attack on the mainland. Mainland emigres have been
                    heartened by the Treaty and disturbed by developments which appear to defer even
                    further their chances of returning home. Most of this group, however, has long
                    realized that a return to the mainland will be long and hard so were not greatly
                    shocked by recent developments tending to confirm that view. Subversion is well
                    under control in Taiwan, according to the officials surveyed. The state of
                    Chinese-American cooperation continues to be satisfactory despite some
                    recriminations over our attempts to get a cease-fire in the Taiwan Strait and
                    our failure to commit ourselves on the defense of Matsu and Quemoy. The Taiwan
                    public has however, become increasingly confused about the direction of US
                    policy toward China as the result of press reports from Washington in the past
                    few days. What effect this confusion will have, our Embassy says, is not
                    discernible at the moment.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
