<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-01-19T15:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-19T15:45:00-05:00" n="19" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d19">
                        <head>19. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington,
                            January 19, 1955, 3:45 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d19fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 793.00/1–1955. Top
                                Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">McConaughy</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-01-19T15:45:00-05:00">January 19, 1955, 3:45
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Defense of Off-Shore Islands</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">George Yeh</persName>, Chinese
                                Foreign Minister</item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Wellington Koo</persName>,
                                Chinese Ambassador</item>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName>, Assistant
                                Secretary, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">McConaughy</persName>, Director,
                                    <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Secretary said that he would state a position which the President was
                            prepared to consider if it was acceptable to the Chinese Government: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Provide U.S. sea and air cover for the evacuation of the
                                    Tachen Islands.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Announce that under present conditions and pending appropriate
                                    action by the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, the U.S. is
                                    prepared to join with the Republic of China in maintaining the
                                    security of Quemoy.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Initiate the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action in the
                                    Security Council which has been considered for some
                                    months:—namely, call on Communist China, and presumably other
                                    countries, to cease military activities in the area of the
                                    Off-shore Islands.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he believed that the announcement as to the protection
                            of Quemoy would largely offset the adverse morale factor <pb facs="0075" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/> involved in a withdrawal from the Tachens.
                            The action could be represented as a regrouping designed to concentrate
                            the Chinese Government forces in more tenable positions. It could be
                            held out as a trimming down operation. It could be emphasized that China
                            and the U.S. will stand shoulder to shoulder in a consolidated
                            position.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that we could not count on concrete Security Council
                            action as a result of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> initiative.
                            A Soviet veto would have to be anticipated. A Communist veto should
                            enable the Chinese Government to command a greater degree of
                            international support.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that the President considered that a Joint Resolution
                            of Congress would be required, since we would have to be prepared if
                            necessary to engage in hostilities with Communist China. We might find
                            it necessary to strike at Communist positions on the Mainland. Such
                            action could not be taken without Congressional authority. He had
                            arranged a meeting with leaders of both Houses of Congress tomorrow
                            morning January 20. He would point out that the Administration considers
                            it necessary that Quemoy be held by the Chinese Government. The port of
                            Amoy, which was commanded by the island of Quemoy, would be an ideal
                            staging ground for an invasion of Formosa if its effective use was not
                            denied to the Communists. This would justify provisional action by the
                            U.S. of the nature contemplated. It was a grave step which might lead to
                            war with Communist China.</p>
                        <p>As to Matsu, the Chinese Government would have to decide whether to try
                            to hold it. The Secretary said his strong advice would be to pull out.
                            It could be done under cover of the Tachen operation. If the Chinese
                            Government endeavored to hold on to Matsu, it would be eventually
                            snapped off. The U.S. could not extend its coverage to Matsu and the
                            position was not believed to be defensible. A good concentration and
                            balance of Chinese forces could be achieved between Formosa, the
                            Pescadores and Quemoy. Any additional off-shore island positions would
                            represent an over-extension of Chinese Government forces. Other
                            positions could not be held without an expenditure of resources out of
                            relation to the value of such positions. It did not make sense to tie up
                            major forces to hold a bunch of rocks. The U.S. was not prepared to make
                            any commitment apart from Quemoy. On the other hand, it was realized
                            that if all the off-shore island positions were abandoned there would be
                            a very bad effect on morale throughout the Far East. The question was,
                            what do you do to offset the effect of withdrawal from some of the
                            positions? We would join forces to hold a reduced position, giving up
                            the untenable positions which over-extend available Chinese forces.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> asked if
                            the President proposed to accomplish this by Executive Order and not
                            under the Treaty?</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said this was correct.</p>
                        <pb facs="0076" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> said presumably the
                            Chinese Government would announce a regrouping operation.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that concerted action would be required. Presumably
                            the Chinese Government would announce its intention to regroup, saying
                            that it would no longer endeavor to hold those positions which were of
                            no vital strategic significance, and would concentrate its forces on
                            Formosa, the Pescadores and Quemoy. Probably the U.S. would announce
                            that without awaiting the ratification of the Treaty, the U.S. would
                            take interim action to assure the security of Quemoy, which was
                            considered essential to the protection of Formosa and the Pescadores.
                            “Security” in this context had a broad connotation. It would mean that
                            either U.S. Forces or Chinese forces would be empowered to attack a
                            build-up on the Mainland which seemed to be aimed at Quemoy, Formosa and
                            the Pescadores. We would not have to wait for an actual attack.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said he would
                            communicate the U.S. proposals at once to his Government. Meanwhile he
                            hoped that the Secretary would make every effort to keep the subject sub
                            rosa.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he would urge the Congressmen to maintain secrecy. He
                            would do this with all the earnestness at his command.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said that even if his
                            Government accepted the kind offer just outlined, it would require
                            considerable planning and preparation. There would have to be an
                            effective pretense of maintaining normal conditions while the
                            preparations went forward.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary agreed, and said he thought that the U.S. would be prepared
                            to send forces into the Tachen area to protect it pending the
                            withdrawal.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> asked if <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> action after the evacuation was
                            contemplated? Would the Tachens in effect be given to the
                            Communists?</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said this was correct.</p>
                        <p>Amb. <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Koo</persName> said if his Government
                            accepted, it would be necessary to make plans in advance, and move very
                            rapidly in the execution of the plans.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he thought the Joint Resolution might require two or
                            three days’ debate in Congress, perhaps more. The matter might be
                            referred to Committees of Congress. The Secretary knew that Senator
                                <persName corresp="#p_GSWF1">George</persName> was extremely
                            reluctant to take any action which might lead to war with Communist
                            China. He wanted our commitments limited strictly to Formosa and the
                            Pescadores. The Secretary did not know whether Senator <persName corresp="#p_GSWF1">George</persName> and the rest of the Democratic
                            leadership of the two Houses would go along. The Democrats controlled
                            Congress. Strong bipartisan support of the proposal by the Congress and
                            the American people would be a necessity.</p>
                        <pb facs="0077" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> asked if the Secretary
                            could defer his consultations with Congress until he had time to hear
                            from President <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang</persName>?</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he did not think so. He said it was necessary to begin
                            to educate the members of Congress. He would not define the
                            Administration proposal so clearly in his conversation with the
                            Congressional leaders tomorrow. But he wanted to get their reaction to
                            the basic questions. He wanted to begin to crystalize the issues and the
                            thinking. The President would probably present the detailed proposal
                            later. The Secretary thought the situation was so acute that we could
                            not afford to wait.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said he thought he
                            could get an answer in six hours or so.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he would make it clear that the proposed course of
                            action requires the concurrence of the Chinese Government. The U.S.
                            would of course want to consider the ideas of the Chinese Government. As
                            to substance, the proposal was very much in the interest of the Chinese
                            Government. If the Chinese Government rejected the proposal, it would
                            lose the whole business.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that in order to maintain our own self respect, we
                            could not play a fuzzy game any longer. That game was played out. The
                            Chinese Communists had already begun to probe and were exposing the
                            indecision. The U.S. must now make clear its position and be prepared to
                            carry out the obligations it was now prepared to assume. Otherwise the
                            U.S. reputation would become tarnished. The U.S. could not afford to
                            back down from any position which it assumed, or to be exposed in a
                            bluff. We must decide how far our interests require us to go and then we
                            must deliver on our commitments. As he saw it there were three choices:
                            to try to hold all the off-shore islands; to disclaim responsibility for
                            any of the off-shore islands which would result in the eventual loss of
                            all of them; or to concentrate on Quemoy as the closest and most
                            important, and hold it. This third choice was so much better than the
                            others that there was no real choice. The problem was with Congress. We
                            must begin to educate Congress as to the requirements of the present
                            situation. Of course the talks would not commit the Chinese Government,
                            nor would they be so definite as this conversation.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said it was hard to persuade soldiers to die in a hopeless
                            cause. He thought it was questionable whether the garrison on the
                            Tachens would fight if they had no hope. He supposed they would fight if
                            they could be sure of support which would give them hope. He did not
                            doubt the strong will to fight of the Chinese forces if they had
                            assurances of adequate backing.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said he was very happy
                            to know that the U.S. Government had come to a definite decision. He
                            agreed that fuzziness had existed for too long. Although the Chinese
                            military capabilities were <pb facs="0078" n="50" xml:id="pg_50"/> very
                            limited, the decision was a difficult one, which the <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Generalissimo</persName> could not make alone. The
                            President of the Executive Yuan (the Premier) would be consulted, and
                            probably a secret session of the Cabinet would be convened. He did not
                            say the proposition would be rejected, but the matter was one of great
                            moment and considerable delicacy. He agreed that the Tachens had only
                            limited strategic value for the Chinese Government. But if they fell to
                            the Chinese Communists, he felt they would have a far greater strategic
                            significance for the Communists.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary expressed some doubt about this, pointing out that no
                            airfields could be built in the Tachens.</p>
                        <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> agreed but he pointed
                            out that the Tachens control the northern entrance to the Formosa
                            Strait.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that he felt we could not fool around the fringes of
                            the problem any longer. It was necessary for all concerned to speak very
                            frankly. The assumption of joint responsibility for the protection of
                            Quemoy would be a very serious step by the U.S. It might take a little
                            time to get Congress fully informed on the problem, perhaps a week or
                            so.</p>
                        <p>The Foreign Minister and the Ambassador said they would despatch an
                            urgent message to Taipei.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>