<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>288. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, July 6,
                    1955</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d288</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">288</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-07-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-07-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="rec_korean_war" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="korean-war" subject="korean-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85073119" lcsh-match="exact">Korean War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-07-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-07-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="288"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d288">
                <head>288. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, July 6,
                        1955<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d288fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Central Files, 790.00/7–655. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_AGV1"
                            >Allen</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-07-06">July 6,
                            1955</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Far Eastern Situation</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Krishna Menon</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGL1">G. L. Mehta</persName>,
                        India</item>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>NEA—<persName corresp="#p_AGV1">George V. Allen</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said his Government felt it
                    important that the Far Eastern situation should not be brought up “in a big way”
                    at the forthcoming “Summit” conference at Geneva. He hoped we could give the
                    impression there that the matter was being handled “on another <pb facs="0660"
                        n="632" xml:id="pg_632"/> track”. He said he had talked with Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> along this line at San Francisco, and
                    indicated that <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> concurred.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that following his talk with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> on July 1, he had been thinking the matter over, and one
                    idea had occurred to him as a possibility. He wanted to throw this idea out
                    merely as something to talk about, since the United States had reached no firm
                    decision on it. His idea was that the direct contacts now being maintained
                    between United States and Red Chinese representatives on a sporadic and
                    low-level basis at Geneva might be raised to a higher level and the scope of the
                    talks expanded. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said he
                    thought Moscow or New Delhi might be a suitable location for such expanded
                    discussions since the Red Chinese had responsible Ambassadors in both places.
                    The Secretary asked what was wrong with Geneva, where the initial contact had
                    already been established. The United States could send someone of higher rank to
                    Geneva for the purpose.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said he thought the success of
                    such talks would depend on the subject matter to be discussed. The Secretary
                    responded, in emphatic tones, that he had made it abundantly clear in public
                    declarations as well as in private conversations that the United States would
                    not negotiate behind the back of Formosa. If our position on this point was
                    still not clear to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>, he wished
                    to repeat it again so there could be no doubt on the point or reason for raising
                    it again. He said that there were a number of marginal things which could be
                    discussed if the Red Chinese wanted to talk. For example, the press this morning
                    had spoken of U.S. maneuvers around the Islands of Penghu.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d288fn2">According to notes of the Secretary’s staff meetings,
                            <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> asked at his July 5 staff
                        meeting whether the United States was holding naval maneuvers near Penghu
                        “as the Chinese Communists charged”. At the July 7 staff meeting, <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> stated that he had been informed
                        by the Pentagon that there was no basis for reports of U.S. naval maneuvers
                        in the Taiwan–Penghu area. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Secretary’s Staff
                        Meetings: Lot 63 D 75)</note> If this disturbed Peking, we were quite ready
                    to talk about it.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said the question of general
                    relations between the United States and Red China would have to be discussed
                    sometime. The Secretary agreed, but again emphasized that timing was of the
                    greatest importance. Moreover, he was confused regarding the subjects the Peking
                    authorities wanted to talk about. He had received some information indicating
                    that they did not want to talk with the United States about Formosa since they
                    regarded Formosa as an internal matter. If conversations could be started at
                    Geneva, we would soon find out what they wanted to talk about.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> characterized the Chinese as
                    great compromisers and expressed the opinion that once talks were started, they
                    would be <pb facs="0661" n="633" xml:id="pg_633"/> willing to discuss many
                    things. To make the talks fruitful, the question of the Americans in China and
                    Chinese in the United States should be disposed of, in order to create an
                    atmosphere conducive to favorable results. If it should happen that the Red
                    Chinese released the American flyers, he thought the situation would be much
                    better.</p>
                <p>The Secretary agreed heartily. He could not guarantee that the American public
                    would, even then, be enthusiastic about Red China, but at least a negative force
                    would have been eliminated.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> asked whether it was possible
                    for the Secretary to make a public declaration stating that all Chinese
                    nationals in the United States were free to return to China if they wished. The
                    Secretary said that if direct talks were to be undertaken, he would prefer to
                    reserve such a public declaration until that time. He thought the Chinese
                    Communists themselves might prefer to have any declaration grow out of the
                    talks. He pointed out that the latest complaint we have had from Peking was not
                    that we are holding Chinese in the United States but that we are pushing them
                    back to China. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said this
                    highlighted the need for machinery to handle the question, to satisfy both sides
                    that their nationals were given adequate consular protection. He did not think
                    that higher-level discussions would be adequate until a more favorable basis for
                    them was established.</p>
                <p>The Secretary asked whether Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>
                    thought the Red Chinese wanted to talk with us directly or through
                    intermediaries. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> thought they
                    were ready to talk directly with us, but he felt confident that in the meanwhile
                    steps towards a relaxation should be taken. He mentioned the questions of
                    prisoners of war and the embargo against trade with Red China were subjects on
                    which progress might be made now.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that if all points of disagreement could be disposed of
                    before-hand, direct talks would not be necessary. He emphasized again that if
                    the Peking authorities did not want to talk, his suggestion should be dropped
                    and no more time wasted on it. He asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> once more whether he thought the Chinese wanted to talk
                    with us directly or through intermediaries. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> repeated that he thought they wanted to talk directly, but
                    commented that the level of the officials to carry on the talks would have to be
                    considered. The Secretary said he was quite open-minded on this point and that
                    if the Red Chinese did not like Geneva, some other place could be
                    considered.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> returned to the question of
                    trade embargoes and the American flyers. The Secretary pointed out that there
                    were two kinds of restrictions on trade with Red China, the international
                    restrictions imposed by a number of nations, and an additional embargo which was
                    self-imposed by the United States. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> thought it would <pb facs="0662" n="634" xml:id="pg_634"/>
                    be helpful if trade with China could be placed on the same level as trade with
                    Russia. The Secretary replied that this was already true, in effect, since the
                    trade which the United States voluntarily renounced did not hurt the Chinese
                    Communists, who could buy the commodities from any one else they wished. We were
                    merely losing business to Hong Kong. The only embargo which really hurt the
                    Chinese was the international one.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> reverted to the question of
                    Chinese in the United States, and asked whether the United States position was
                    that they were free to go back to China. The Secretary said that his statement
                    was correct. There might be one or two cases in which some question was still
                    pending, but he did not believe we would insist on holding the individuals
                    involved even in these cases. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>
                    mentioned that the Peking authorities thought that many Chinese in the United
                    States wanted to return to China but were not able to do so. The Secretary said
                    the Red Cross or somebody else could find out whether this was correct.
                    Referring again to the Red Chinese complaint that we are forcing Chinese to
                    leave, he said he would be very happy if the Chinese would reciprocate by
                    putting “pressure” on Americans to get out of China. He thought that if
                        <persName corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName> really wanted better
                    relations with the United States, he would release all the Americans in China
                    within twenty-four hours.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said that <persName
                        corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName> was a reasonable man and wanted good
                    relations with us. The problem was to convince <persName corresp="#p_CE1"
                        >Chou</persName> that Americans reciprocated this desire. He asked whether
                    Americans who wanted to visit China would be permitted to do so. (He probably
                    had in mind American journalists but he may also have been thinking of relatives
                    of the flyers.) The Secretary said that he did not think it made much sense for
                    additional Americans to go to China as long as those already there were being
                    held as prisoners. With reference to the Indian offer to assure that Americans
                    visiting China would be treated properly, he said that the United States could
                    not rely on third countries to protect American citizens.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> then asked directly, “Then,
                    there is no likelihood of a relaxation to enable Americans to visit China?” The
                    Secretary said he saw none at the moment.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> then said that the only
                    concrete result of his several talks with the Secretary seemed to be the
                    Secretary’s suggestion for a step-up in the level and scope of direct
                    conversations. Was any progress possible on the question of a cease-fire? The
                    Secretary said that the United States had stated many times that it desired a
                    cessation of hostilities and declared that he was not impressed by people who
                    were ready to agree to a cease-fire only if they got what they wanted without
                    firing. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said that the shooting
                    and threats of shooting were not only from one side. The Secretary reminded <pb
                        facs="0663" n="635" xml:id="pg_635"/> him that the United States had
                    obtained a commitment from <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName> to avoid initiating hostilities without our consent. He
                    then reenforced his previous statements that the use of force should be
                    renounced by Peking. He had certainly expected India to support this position.
                    He was therefore greatly surprised that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> seemed to be supporting the Peking thesis, which openly
                    avowed the use of force.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> answered, with considerable
                    emotion “No, no, no! As recently as last week, my Prime Minister even pursuaded
                    the Russians to join in a communiqué in Moscow condemning the use of force in
                    settlement of the Formosa question”.<note n="3" xml:id="d288fn3">Reference is
                        apparently to a sentence in a joint statement issued on July 22 by <persName
                            corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BMNA1"
                            >Bulganin</persName> at the conclusion of a visit by <persName
                            corresp="#p_NPJ1">Nehru</persName> to Moscow expressing the hope “that
                        it will be possible by peaceful means to satisfy the legitimate rights of
                        the Chinese People’s Republic in regard to Taiwan.” For text, see <hi
                            rend="italic">Documents on International Relations</hi>, pp.
                        472–475.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said
                    India’s support for Peking extended only to the fact that China should be
                    united. He recalled that India had supported this position when China was
                    governed by <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>. He declared
                    that he had never said that Peking should take the islands by military action.
                    He added that he was determined, above everything else, not to allow his
                    conversations in San Francisco and Washington to affect United States-Indian
                    relations adversely. He did not want India’s motives to be suspect by either
                    side.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he had gained the impression that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> thought <persName corresp="#p_CE1"
                        >Chou</persName>’s position was a reasonable one. Yet <persName
                        corresp="#p_CE1">Chou</persName>’s avowed position was that if he could not
                    get the islands by peaceful means, he would take them by force. If he had
                    misunderstood Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>’s position, he
                    would be glad to be corrected. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>
                    repeated that India had stated, in Moscow of all places, that it was wrong to
                    use force. The Secretary said he was very glad that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> was not endorsing <persName
                        corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName>’s position.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said he did not wish to see the
                    United States become involved in the Chinese civil war. The Secretary pointed
                    out that Soviet Russia had taken the position that the Korean war was a civil
                    war, but the world knew that it was something much bigger. He said the problem
                    of the unification of China was similar to that of Korea, Germany and Indochina
                    and that the United States opposed the use of force in any of these situations.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> repeated that his Government’s
                    position in opposition to the use of force was well known. The Secretary said he
                    had always thought that was India’s position. He did not believe that India
                    would use force, for example, to take Goa. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> said this was entirely correct. The Secretary said, “Then
                    let Red China take the same position regarding Quemoy and Matsu”. He thought
                    that until Peking began to see that there <pb facs="0664" n="636"
                        xml:id="pg_636"/> were moral principles higher than the use of brute force,
                    they would probably not get along with the United States very well.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>, still excited by the
                    Secretary’s implication that India supported the use of force, declared that in
                    twenty years the United States would recognize the correctness of India’s
                    position in the present discussions. He said his role was not to justify the
                    attitude of either side. The Secretary said he did not doubt in any way
                    whatsoever the Indian Government’s good intentions in undertaking to achieve a
                    settlement. He repeated, however, that the World must be held together by some
                    sense of principle. He remarked that he had fought for economic aid for India on
                    a basis of principle, despite the fact that many people questioned this aid in
                    view of India’s foreign policy. He had also supported aid for Yugoslavia even
                    though, as he had pointed out in San Francisco, the United States Government
                    differed from that of Yugoslav Government in every respect except one—the
                    Yugoslav determination to defend its independence. The principle involved was
                    the democratic one of allowing Governments to differ on foreign policy without
                    affecting the United States attitude on the aid question. The renunciation of
                    the use of force was another high moral principle that civilized nations should
                    adopt.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> asked whether reconciliation
                    was not also a high principle. The Secretary said it was, and that if India
                    could help remove the concept of force from the minds of the Chinese Communists,
                    steps towards reconciliation would be possible. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> said that India had already used its strong endeavors in
                    this direction. “If you could let us impress Peking”, he added, “that we had
                    access to your mind, we could be more effective”. The Secretary said he had
                    opened every possible recess of his mind to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> during their several long conversations.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said he was leaving for London
                    tomorrow and would like to return to Washington to talk with the Secretary again
                    on July 12 or 13, before the Secretary left for Geneva. The Secretary said he
                    would be able to give very little attention to anything except the Geneva
                    Conference during these days. He remarked that he had spent more time talking
                    with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Krishna Menon</persName> during the last
                    three weeks than he had with any other foreign diplomat during a similar period
                    since he had been Secretary of State. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> protested that he was not a diplomat. The Secretary said,
                    smiling, “Well, whatever you call yourself”. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1"
                        >Menon</persName> said that in view of the Secretary’s schedule, it probably
                    would be useless for him to return to Washington before Geneva.</p>
                <p>When Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> was accompanying Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> to the elevator, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> remarked in a tone of hopelessness,
                    “Your Secretary has said to me in so many words: ‘Go away, you are not serving
                    any useful purpose’”. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> said that
                    the Secretary had given him a <pb facs="0665" n="637" xml:id="pg_637"/> very
                    direct and simple task, which should be easy and agreeable for any Indian to
                    carry out. His task was to persuade the Red Chinese to renounce the use of
                    force. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> said he could not go
                    back to Peking without something more than this in hand.</p>
                <p>Subsequently, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> informed Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">Allen</persName> that he planned to return to
                    Washington July 24.<note n="4" xml:id="d288fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Krishna Menon</persName>, together with
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGL1">Mehta</persName> and Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, saw President <persName
                            corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> at 4:15 p.m. on July 6,
                        according to the President’s appointment diary. (<persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> Library, President’s Daily Appointments) No
                        memorandum or telegraphic report of the conversation has been found in
                        Department of State files or <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName> Library, but <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                            >Eisenhower</persName>’s diary entry for July 14, 1955, states that
                            <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> had visited him twice, in
                        the company of Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, “to
                        talk about establishing some basis of mediation between Red China and
                        ourselves. I have bluntly told him, both times, that the American people
                        will not consider using the lives and freedom of their own citizens as a
                        bargaining material. Since Red China, in violation of her solemn word given
                        in the Korean Armistice, unjustly held some of our men prisoners—men that
                        China herself admits were in uniform when captured—we will not make
                        important political concessions on the grounds that this would be
                        recompensed by the return of some of these men. We maintain that China
                        cannot be regarded by us as a civilized nation ready to work with us in good
                        faith until <hi rend="italic">after</hi> they have released these prisoners,
                        such release to be without any promise of concessions on our part other than
                        the assurance that all Chinese in our country are free to go back to China
                        whenever they may desire. This <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName>
                        does not accept.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, DDE Diaries)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
