<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>72. Telegram From the Ambassador in the Republic of China (Rankin) to the )
                    to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-02-02T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-02-02T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-02-02T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-02-02T05:00:00-05:00" n="72"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                <head>72. Telegram From the Ambassador in the Republic of China (<persName
                        corresp="#p_RKL1" type="from">Rankin</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                        >Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d72fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 293.9322/2–255. Top Secret; Priority. Received at 9:20 a.m. Repeated
                        to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> eyes only for <persName
                            corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>, by the Department as Telegram 390 to
                        New York, February 2, 1955.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Taipei</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-02-02T18:00:00+08:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 2, 1955—6 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>511. Department’s 421,<note n="2" xml:id="d72fn2">
                        <ref target="#d69">Document 69</ref>.</note> 422,<note n="3" xml:id="d72fn3">
                        <p>Telegram 422 to Taipei, February 1, reads as follows:</p>
                        <p>“Your 499 [<ref target="#d68">Document 68</ref>] crossed our 421 which
                            sets forth definitive US position. We are now considering what kind
                            official statement can be made here consistent with position taken in
                            421 in the event President <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang</persName>
                            responds favorably to issuing statement recommended to him by <persName
                                corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName>. You will be further advised.”
                            (Department of State, Central Files, 293.9322/1–3155)</p>
                    </note> 423.<note n="4" xml:id="d72fn4">Telegram 423 to Taipei, February 1,
                        instructed <persName corresp="#p_RKL1">Rankin</persName> to deliver formally
                        in writing that portion of telegram 421 to Taipei which was marked as a
                        statement. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 993.72/2–155)</note> Upon receipt
                    Department’s 421, I decided to do as subsequently instructed in Department’s 423
                    re United States position statement on off-shore islands. While asking yesterday
                    afternoon for urgent appointment with President, I gave Acting Foreign Minister
                    verbatim text of actual statement<note n="5" xml:id="d72fn5">A copy is <hi
                            rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, Taipei Embassy Files: Lot 62 F 83.</note> so
                        <pb facs="0222" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/> he could prepare personally a
                    careful translation into Chinese for use when I saw <persName corresp="#p_CKG1"
                        >Chiang</persName> (I talked with President for hour and quarter this
                    morning with Acting Foreign Minister as interpreter.)</p>
                <p>After going over text in detail <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang</persName>
                    asked me to explain phases “under present circumstances” and “at this time” (in
                    third numbered paragraph Department’s 421). Did they mean that we would do thus
                    and so now but not in the future? I replied I should not attempt to read
                    anything additional into the statement, but added my personal view was that
                    these phrases were intended to relate our policy to specific conditions, such as
                    existed today, rather than to hypothetical circumstances which were
                    unforeseeable and might never occur. At same time I did not regard statement as
                    applying solely to present situation. President asked that I request further
                    clarification from Department.</p>
                <p>Next point on which <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang</persName> laid stress was
                    whether effect of Congressional resolution would continue after ratification of
                    Defense Treaty. I did not comment on this.</p>
                <p>Third item President raised was importance of some United States public statement
                    at same time Chinese announced Tachen evacuation. He appears to have sent
                    further instructions to Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1"
                        >Yeh</persName> in this connection. I referred to paragraph (number 4 in
                    Department’s 421) in US statement just given him and asked if he had received
                    details from <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> of what Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> said. He indicated his
                    information was meager. Said I am so sad few actual details at hand but could
                    envisage essential considerations. First, Senate would be willing to leave large
                    authority in hands of President as Commander in Chief, but would not easily
                    yield any of its power over international agreements. Also there was question of
                    relative advantages of formal announcement re 1 or 2 islands and more general
                    position which might avoid appearance of inviting Red aggression on any islands.
                    I supposed military men should favor second alternative. I also reminded
                    President that conversations in Washington had gone through several phases
                    during past two weeks. What had seemed definite at one point might necessarily
                    have changed subsequently in light of new developments. I repeated that while I
                    believed these remarks pertinent they were not based on intimate knowledge of
                    details.</p>
                <p>Under above circumstances and view fact defense pact hearings now in progress and
                    should not be jeopardized, I recommended acceptance of position statement I had
                    just given him as satisfactory basis for requesting US aid in Tachen evacuation.
                    I suggested he not insist on further explanation of phrases mentioned above,
                    adding that when good faith is absent no use of words can bind a nation but when
                    good faith present, as in this case, one need have no concern over details of
                    wording.</p>
                <pb facs="0223" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/>
                <p>President expressed appreciation of my remarks and quoted Chinese proverb to
                    effect one never asks friend to do the impossible. He now understood US would
                    not mention Kinmen and Matsu in public pronouncement but urged appropriate
                    statement be issued nevertheless. He expressed hope US might agree to some
                    mention of Kinmen and Matsu in Chinese statement on Tachen withdrawal but I gave
                    him no encouragement at this point.</p>
                <p>President then mentioned present Commonwealth Prime Ministers Conference<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d72fn6">Held in London, January 31–February 8.</note> and
                    expressed concern over reported proposal Free Chinese give up all of offshore
                    islands in return for ceasefire. He asked US to put <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss> straight on this point. (I made no comment but cannot imagine US
                    agreeing to reported Commonwealth scheme.)</p>
                <p>Finally President said that after Tachen evacuation he was considering proposal
                    in security council condemning Soviet aggression against China. Revival of this
                        project<note n="7" xml:id="d72fn7">The reference is apparently to a
                        resolution originally proposed by the Republic of China at the Fourth
                        Session of the General Assembly in 1949, resubmitted in revised form in
                        1952, further amended, and adopted by the General Assembly on February 1,
                        1952, as Resolution 505 (VI), which declared that the Soviet Union had
                        failed to carry out the Sino-Soviet Treaty of August 14, 1945. For the
                        resolution, see <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N.</gloss> document A/2119, p. 4;
                        for the treaty, see Department of State, <hi rend="italic">United States
                            Relations With China</hi> (Washington: Government Printing Office,
                        1949), p. 585.</note> would represent effort to label actual aggressor in
                    fighting of last five months.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RKL1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rankin</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
