<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-02-02T19:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-02-02T19:35:00-05:00" n="74" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d74">
                        <head>74. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the Republic of
                                China</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d74fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 293.9322/2–255. Top Secret;
                                    <gloss target="#t_Niact1">Niact</gloss>; Limit Distribution.
                                Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BRR1">Bowie</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PH1">Phleger</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">McConaughy</persName>. Notations in <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName>’s handwriting on a draft
                                copy state that he approved and that he read paragraph 5 over the
                                telephone to Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName>, who concurred. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                                ROC Files: Lot 71 D 517, 1954–1955, Offshore Islands)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-02-02T19:35:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">February 2,
                                        1955—7:35 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>433. Reurtel 511.<note n="2" xml:id="d74fn2"><ref target="#d72">Document
                                    72</ref>.</note> You are instructed to seek audience with
                                <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Generalissimo</persName> and reiterate
                            that our 421<note n="3" xml:id="d74fn3"><ref target="#d69">Document
                                    69</ref>.</note> states definitive US position as approved by
                            President on matters therein covered. Specifically would add following
                            comments re questions raised.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Continuance in effect of Congressional Resolution not related to
                                ratification of Defense Treaty. It continues until President shall
                                determine that peace and security of area is reasonably assured by
                                international conditions created by action of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> or otherwise and shall so report to
                                Congress.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In paragraph 3 <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 421
                                phrases “under present circumstances” and “at this time” reflect
                                necessity under resolution that President retain full discretion
                                regarding actions with respect to related areas so that he may act
                                promptly as situations develop. US intentions firm as to situation
                                under present conditions.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>US position regarding any reference to Quemoy or Matsu in Chinese
                                public statement remains as stated in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 421. Accordingly, you were quite right in not
                                encouraging any hope for US approval of such reference. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KVKW1">Koo</persName> who raised same point night of
                                    31st<note n="4" xml:id="d74fn4">See <ref target="#d70">Document
                                        70</ref>.</note> have since been told we cannot concur in
                                proposed insertion and reasons therefor.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>You should expressly confirm to President <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang</persName> that British have been
                                apprised of our position as to offshore islands and they understand
                                it fully.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Prompt indication re Chinese Government intentions as to
                                withdrawal from Tachens seems to us essential. Further delay risks
                                withdrawal in face Communist attack, which would make difficult to
                                present evacuation as voluntary redeployment for strategic purpose
                                of strengthening defenses of Formosa. Moreover, US Navy cannot
                                continue indefinitely to keep the forces now deployed in the area on
                                    <pb facs="0227" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/> an around-the-clock
                                alert basis in their present positions, state of deployment and
                                    alert.<note n="5" xml:id="d74fn5">Telegram 521 from Taipei,
                                    February 3, reported that <persName corresp="#p_RKL1">Rankin</persName> requested an interview with President
                                        <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang</persName> on an urgent
                                    basis but learned that <persName corresp="#p_CKG1">Chiang</persName> would not be able to see him until the
                                    next day. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                    293.9322/2–355)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HHJ1"><hi rend="strong">Hoover</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>