<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1899-03-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1899-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="271" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d271">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hay</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">White</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-03-06"><hi rend="italic">March 6,
                                1899</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 787.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Inclosed herewith please find a dispatch,
                            with inclosure from Consul-General Guenther dated February 20, 1899, in
                            relation to a summons issued to him as a witness to testify in a certain
                            case against Ludwig Bettag for alleged violation of his military
                            duty.</p>
                        <p>There is no exemption from summons stipulated in the consular convention
                            of 1871 between the United States and Germany; and such privilege can
                            not be claimed unless it can be shown that the consul-general is
                            entitled to such immunity in virtue of the most-favored-nation clause,
                            which provides that our consuls in Germany “shall enjoy all privileges,
                            exemptions, and immunities which have been granted, or may in future be
                            granted, to the agents of the same rank of the most favored nation.” You
                            will determine whether such immunity exists.</p>
                        <p>But by express stipulation of said Article III, Mr. Guenther, not being a
                            citizen of Germany, enjoys “personal immunity from arrest or
                            imprisonment, except in the case of crime.” The menace of the fine,
                            arrest, and imprisonment, not for any crime, against the consul-general,
                            appears to be gratuitous, and wanting in the respect due from <pb facs="0395" n="303" xml:id="pg_303"/> one friendly government toward
                            the consular officer of another; and, if carried into execution, would
                            appear to be a flagrant violation of the express treaty engagement.</p>
                        <p>Article V provides that “the offices and dwellings of consuls missi, who
                            are not citizens of the country of their residence, shall be at all
                            times inviolable. The local authority shall not, except in the case of
                            the pursuit for crime, under any pretext invade them.”</p>
                        <p>While Mr. Guenther’s office and dwelling are inviolable, he is threatened
                            with arrest and imprisonment outside, or by virtual imprisonment inside,
                            his office and dwelling, if he fails to obey the process, either by
                            arresting him outside of his dwelling and office or inside thereof; or,
                            if it is not sought to arrest him outside, to virtually imprison him
                            within by making it impossible for him to go out without being subject
                            to arrest and imprisonment.</p>
                        <p>It appears, moreover, that the summons is addressed to him as
                            consul-general of the United States, and he is, as such officer,
                            required, in answer to question one, attached to the process, to give
                            evidence, “from papers to be shown,” whether “Bettag is an American
                            citizen.” The papers referred to are evidently those belonging to the
                            consular archives. This would seem to be violative of Article V, which
                            provides that “the consular archives shall be at all times inviolable,
                            and under no pretense whatever shall the local authorities be allowed to
                            examine the papers forming part of them.” While the papers are protected
                            from seizure or examination, the thing prohibited is sought to be
                            accomplished by compelling the consul to show them or to disclose their
                            contents.</p>
                        <p>In connection with this instruction you are referred also to instruction
                            No. 140, July 31, 1894 (inclosed herewith), to Consul-General Mason, as
                            to the immunity of consuls from giving information obtained in the
                            capacity of consul of the United States.</p>
                        <p>You will bring the matter to the attention of the German Government and
                            make known the views of this Government touching the conduct observed
                            toward Consul-General Guenther.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                787.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Guenther</persName> to
                                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate-General</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Frankfort on the Main</hi></placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-02-20"><hi rend="italic">February 20, 1899</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 6.]</seg></opener>
                            <p>I have the honor, in conformity with paragraph 77 of the Consular
                                Regulations, to report that the following correspondence in the
                                German language has passed between this consulate-general and the
                                royal court of Frankfort on the Main, which is hereby translated to
                                English:</p>
                            <p>“In the process against Ludwig Bettag, of Dudenhofen, for violation
                                of his military duty, you are summoned for examination as a witness
                                by order of the royal court in its place of business, court-house,
                                room 24, before the royal court assessor, Mr. Wick, Tuesday,
                                February 21, 1899, at 10 a.m. Witnesses who do not appear without
                                sufficient excuse are to be sentenced, according to paragraph 50 of
                                the penal code, to pay the costs occasioned by such nonappearance,
                                also to a fine not to exceed 300 marks; and if this is not paid, to
                                imprisonment not to exceed six weeks—producing them by arrest is
                                also admissible.</p>
                            <p>“In case that you have left the domicile stated in this summons, or
                                if you should change it before the day of trial, you are required to
                                give such notice without delay.</p>
                            <p>“Frankfort on the Main, February 16, 1899.</p>
                            <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Barmers</hi>,<lb/>“<hi rend="italic">Clerk of the Royal Court 6</hi>.</p>
                            <pb facs="0396" n="304" xml:id="pg_304"/>
                            <p>“You shall be examined as to— <list>
                                    <item>“1. Whether, from papers to be shown, it appears that
                                        Bettag is an American citizen.</item>
                                    <item>“2. Whether, the possession of American citizenship is
                                        necessary to enter the American Army as a musician.</item>
                                    <item>“3. In how much time a certification of the acquisition of
                                        American citizenship, in case of this being so, can be
                                        received from America.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>“To the consul-general of the United States of North America, Mr.
                                Guenther, present, Niedenau 78.”</p>
                            <p>In answer to this summons, I sent the following note to the royal
                                court: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfort on the
                                        Main</hi>, <hi rend="italic">February 20, 1899</hi>.</p>
                                    <p>“The undersigned, consul-general of the United States of
                                        America, received, in the evening of the 18th of this month,
                                        a summons dated February 16, 1899, to be examined as a
                                        witness in the process against Ludwig Bettag, of Dudenhofen.
                                        R. H. 127/99. St. A. Frankenthal. The undersigned is always
                                        willing to comply with the wishes and requests of the
                                        authorities in the German Empire, provided they are made in
                                        proper form and are conformable with his official duties and
                                        his views of them.</p>
                                    <p>“Said summons, however, especially in its form under threats
                                        of fines and imprisonment and eventual arrest, is a
                                        violation of the consular convention between Germany and the
                                        United States, and the undersigned is compelled to complain
                                        of such treatment and most respectfully but decidedly
                                        protest.</p>
                                    <p>“In addition he would add that he is perfectly willing to
                                        answer the questions relative to the Bettag case, as far as
                                        he is able to, provided the royal court requests him to do
                                        so in the same proper manner as would be done by the
                                        American authorities under similar circumstances toward
                                        consular officers of the German Empire in the United
                                        States.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>With great respect,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Richard Guenther</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                Consul-General.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                787.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Rockhill</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Mason</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1894-07-31"><hi rend="italic">July 31,
                                        1894</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 140.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the receipt of
                                your dispatch No. 288, of the 9th instant, reporting that you have
                                been summoned to appear as a witness in court in a suit brought by
                                Julius Teufel against Henry Nickel for defamation of character, it
                                being sought to obtain from you testimony concerning statements
                                submitted to you by the said Nickel alleging that Mr. Teufel had
                                undervalued certain surgical goods exported to the United
                                States.</p>
                            <p>The information regarding which your testimony is desired was
                                conveyed by Mr. Nickel to you in your capacity of consul-general of
                                the United States, and as such officer you took action and
                                communicated the statements to the Department, thereby making them a
                                part of the records of your consulate.</p>
                            <p>It is provided in Article V of the treaty of 1871 with Germany that
                                the consular archives shall be at all times inviolable; and where
                                communications are from their nature confidential, for the
                                cognizance of the consul’s Government only, it is clear that
                                consular officers should not be called upon to testify regarding
                                them.</p>
                            <p>The Department, therefore, can not authorize you to testify in the
                                case, on the ground that whatever knowledge you may have is official
                                and privileged, because concerning only your relation to your own
                                Government.</p>
                            <p>It is also very probable that Germany has a treaty with France, or
                                with some other country, giving consular officers the privilege of
                                declining to appear in courts as witnesses. In such event, the
                                position now taken would be fortified by the provisions regarding
                                privileges and immunities granted to the most favored nation
                                contained in Article III of the treaty of 1871 with Germany.</p>
                            <p>From the inclosed letter from the Treasury Department you will see
                                that the Secretary of the Treasury is of the opinion that your
                                appearance as a witness would be detrimental to the interests of
                                this country.</p>
                            <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">W. W. Rockhill</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Third Assistant
                                Secretary.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>