<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Powell to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1899</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d362</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">362</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1899-04-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1899-04-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1899-04-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1899-04-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="362"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d362">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Powell</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Port au Prince, Haiti</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-04-10">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 10, 1899</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 547.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I transmit under this cover copies of the
                    correspondence that has passed between the foreign office and the legation
                    concerning the complaint made by Dr. J. B. Terres of an attempt to arrest one of
                    his employees. This correspondence may be considered as a continuance of
                    dispatch No. 545, April 6.</p>
                <p>The inclosed correspondence having been received since the above dispatch was
                    sent, this completes the history of the case, which has been settled without any
                    unpleasant feeling being left.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. F. Powell.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lafontant</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Powell</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State for Foreign Relations</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Port au Prince</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-04-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">April 8, 1899</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: Confirming to you the declarations
                        that I have had the honor to make to you at our late interview, I am pleased
                        to give you the assurance that in ordering, on the request of Mr. the chargé
                        d’affaires of the Dominican Republic, the arrestation to be expelled of a
                        Dominican who is in the service of Dr. Terres, vice-consul-general of the
                        United States of America, my colleague of the department of the interior had
                        in no wise the intention to violate the dwelling of an accredited agent of
                        the United States, nor to commit any infraction of the international
                        laws.</p>
                    <p>The order, moreover, not having any sequence, and the agent of the authority
                        having stopped in view of the protestation of Dr. Terres.</p>
                    <p>You will kindly remember that in my dispatch of the 31st March, in reply to
                        the one in which you made known to me the incident of which you thought to
                        have a cause of complaint, I gave you the same assurances.</p>
                    <p>I have not failed to remark to you how much it would have been painful for
                        the Government, that you could believe for a single instant that a minister
                        of the Republic could have given an order of a nature to disturb the good
                        relations that unite the two republics and to which my Government attaches
                        such price.</p>
                    <p>Please accept, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">N. S. Lafontant</hi>.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0473" n="377" xml:id="pg_377"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Powell</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Lafontant</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Port au Prince, Haiti</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-04-10">
                                <hi rend="italic">April 10, 1899</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have your favor dated April 8. I am glad to
                        know from you that it was not the intention of your honorable colleague, the
                        minister of state for the interior, Hon. Tancrede Auguste, to violate any
                        right of international courtesy that pertains to foreign representatives
                        accredited to your Government, and that you have, on the part of your
                        Government, promptly disavowed any such intention.</p>
                    <p>I heartily agree with you on the very pleasant way this incident has been
                        closed, showing the strong and kindly feeling of your Government for that of
                        mine, which I trust will continue to grow more binding as each advance in
                        years.</p>
                    <p>I have the pleasure also to inform you in this dispatch that the two
                        Dominicans referred to are not and have never been in the employ of our
                        vice-consul-general, Dr. J. B. Terres.</p>
                    <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">W. F. Powell.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
