<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1899-05-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1899-05-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="569" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d569">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Merry</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States of America</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">San José, Costa Rica</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-05-07"><hi rend="italic">May 7,
                                        1899</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 248.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On arrival at Port Limon yesterday I
                            cabled you as follows: “Entered into an arrangement Mosquito Territory
                            customs duties by payment to British consul, subject to decision of the
                            Government of the United States and the Nicaraguan Government, as to de
                            facto government, of which you will have unquestionable proof. Request
                            leave of absence one month, consul of the United States, San Juan del
                            Norte, to make a report to the Department of State. Reply by telegraph
                            to San José. Mosquito Territory quiet at present. British war ship
                            probably remain until ours has returned.” To which, twenty-four hours
                            subsequently, I received the following answer: “Mosquito Territory
                            arrangement approved, subject to determination of law and equity. Leave
                            of absence granted.” The last sentence I have cabled Commander Dayton,
                            at Colon, to avoid the necessity for his calling at Limon en route
                            northward, as I am anxious to have him relieve the <hi rend="italic">Proserpine</hi> at Bluefields, soon as possible. I had said to Mr.
                            Sanson that while Colonel Torres remains the port will have the
                            protection of a war ship. He then assured me that Torres will leave for
                            Managua on 14th, as his “court-martial” has nearly concluded its
                            “evidence.”</p>
                        <p>I beg to inclose herewith (inclosures Nos. 1 and 2) copies of my letter
                            requesting the British consul, Mr. Bingham, to accept the trust, and his
                            acceptance thereof. The clause No. 5 relating to request that the matter
                            be settled within four months’ time was put in the agreement at the
                            request of the merchants, although I was not favorable thereto. I
                            inclose herewith copy of letter (inclosure No. 3) handed me by the
                            merchants of Bluefields, just prior to my departure. Before leaving a
                            number of affidavits had been prepared, proving the de facto Government
                            of Reyes between February 3 and 25. I urged them to carefully prepare
                            these affidavits, to go forward by United States Consul Sorsby direct,
                            or through this legation. Although insistent upon aggressive military
                            action upon my arrival, they were apparently satisfied when I left, but,
                            whether satisfied or not, I did not go to Bluefields to increase the
                            friction or to settle the interminable Mosquito question with military
                            power, although if American interests are to be regarded worthy of
                            support, I respectfully suggest that it should be finally disposed
                            of.</p>
                        <p>With assurances, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William Lawrence Merry</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Minister.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0677" n="581" xml:id="pg_581"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Merry</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Bingham</persName>, Her Britannic
                                    Majesty’s consul at Bluefields</hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States of America</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Bluefields, Nicaragua</hi></placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-05-03"><hi rend="italic">May 3,
                                1899</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Permit me, on behalf of the United
                                States Government, to request you to receive in trust the amount of
                                $19,673.33, Nicaraguan currency, claimed from five American
                                establishments here due to the customs authorities of Bluefields.
                                The inclosed copy of agreement made between Hon. Joaquin Sanson and
                                myself is selfexplanatory. If we shall be able to prove, as I have
                                no doubt we can, that the government of General Reyes, between the
                                3d and 25th of February, 1899, was the only effective and thede
                                facto government in Bluefields, the amount will be, under this
                                agreement, repaid to the merchants, who have already paid these
                                duties once. We hold that to have refused payment to Reyes’s
                                government would have resulted in the seizure of their goods, with
                                material injury to their business. That was sufficient duress then,
                                as it is now, to force payment of duties. But it is not my province
                                at this time to argue the case. I make this request on behalf of my
                                Government and our citizens, that it may go on record as one more
                                proof of the mutual good will now happily existing between our
                                respective Governments, and with entire confidence in your
                                acceptance.</p>
                            <p>With assurances, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William Lawrence
                                        Merry</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States
                                        Minister.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bingham</persName> to
                                    Mr. <persName type="to">Merry</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">British Consulate</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bluefields</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-05-04"><hi rend="italic">May 4,
                                    1899</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                                receipt of your communication, dated the 3d instant, in which you
                                request me, on behalf of the United States Government, to receive on
                                trust, in accordance with the terms of an agreement made between
                                yourself and the minister of foreign affairs of Nicaragua, copy of
                                which you inclosed me, the amount of $19,673.33, Nicaraguan
                                currency, claimed from certain American establishments in this city
                                as due to the customs authorities of Bluefields.</p>
                            <p>I shall have much pleasure in accepting the trust with which you
                                honor me.</p>
                            <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">H. F. Bingham</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Her Britannic Majesty’s
                                Consul.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic"><gloss type="from">American merchants of
                                        Bluefields</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Merry</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bluefields, Nicaragua</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-05-04"><hi rend="italic">May
                                            4, 1899</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William Lawrence
                                    Merry</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">United States Minister to
                                    Central America.</hi></p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your friends, the American business
                                men of Bluefields, can not permit you to leave this port without an
                                expression of their esteem and regard for the admirable manner and
                                zeal you have shown in withstanding, under very trying
                                circumstances, the tyranny of Nicaraguan officials.</p>
                            <p>We fully appreciate the situation, and the praiseworthy manner in
                                which you have discharged the onerous and responsible duties
                                appertaining to your position have won from us our full confidence
                                and belief in the integrity of the entire proceedings.</p>
                            <p>We thank you for all the assistance rendered, and only those
                                concerned can fully appreciate the relief sustained.</p>
                            <p>With best wishes,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. W.
                                    Petersen.</hi></signed><lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">The New Orleans
                                    and Central American Trading Co.</hi>,<lb/><signed>Per <hi rend="smallcaps">Jos. W. Beer.</hi></signed><lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Allen &amp;
                                        Caldwell.</hi></signed><lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel Weill.</hi></signed><lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Sam D. Spellman.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>