<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1899-05-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1899-05-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="583" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d583">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Dudley</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Lima, Peru</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-05-24"><hi rend="italic">May 24,
                                1899</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 260.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith two
                            copies and a translation of a supreme decree of the 9th instant, the
                            purpose of which is to prescribe a mode of legal proof to be followed by
                            those desiring to marry outside the Roman Catholic Church, by availing
                            themselves of the provisions of the civil marriage law of the 23d of
                            December, 1897. The law legalizes civil marriage when both parties to
                            the contract are non-Catholics, and when, one only of the parties being
                            of that church, the ecclesiastical authority refuses to perform the
                            ceremony.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Irving B.
                            Dudley.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">marriages between noncatholics.</hi></head>
                            <p>Whereas the laws existing np to 1897 only permitted marriages between
                                Catholics, the sole object of the law of December 23d of the same
                                year being the habilitation of non-Catholics.</p>
                            <p>The said law not containing any provision prescribing the manner of
                                proving the non-Catholicity of the contracting parties, an essential
                                and primary condition of its application.</p>
                            <p>This, in the execution of the law, has led to discussions and created
                                obstacles the suppression of which is urgent by the prescription of
                                legal and ready means for the previous presentation of the requisite
                                proofs.</p>
                            <p>Neither has any kind of proceeding been established to facilitate the
                                carrying out of the law in the case of a denial by the
                                ecclesiastical authorities of permission to marry in case of a
                                diversity of creeds.</p>
                            <p>In exercising the faculty paragraph 5 of article 94 of the
                                constitution confers upon me, I decree: <list>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 1. Non-Catholics having
                                        recourse to the judicial authorities for the object of
                                        contracting matrimony in accordance with the said law, shall
                                        accompany their petition with a document probatory of the
                                        religion to which they belong.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 2. Persons belonging to no
                                        religion, or who are able only with great difficulty to
                                        produce the required probatory document, shall substitute
                                        for the same a sworn written declaration, accompanied with
                                        those of at least two persons of well-known standing,
                                        residents in the place, testifying to the fact of the
                                        petitioners not having been baptized in the Catholic
                                        Church.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 3. The judge shall
                                        personally receive the sworn verbal ratification of the
                                        petitioner’s statements and of the witnesses’ declarations,
                                        and shall extend the corresponding documents.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 4. If the petitioners are
                                        unable to present the necessary witnesses at the place where
                                        their petition is presented, but give the assurance of the
                                        existence of the same either in the Republic, or abroad, the
                                        corresponding requisitorial letters shall be extended for
                                        the taking of the declarations.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Art</hi>. 5. Persons petitioning for
                                        a civil marriage on account of the ecclesiastical authority
                                        having refused to them the dispensation of the impediment
                                        offered by a diversity of creeds, shall accompany their
                                        petition with an authentic proof (certificate) of the said
                                        refusal.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>In the case of the petitioners showing the impossibility for them to
                                obtain the required certificate, the judge shall personally demand
                                the same of the competent ecclesiastical authority, and on receipt
                                of the reply shall give the corresponding decree.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">Given at the Government House in
                                        <placeName>Lima</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-05-09">May 9, 1899</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">José J. Loayza.</hi></item>
                                        <item><hi rend="smallcaps">N. de Pierola</hi>.</item>
                                    </list></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>