<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Loomis to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1899</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d757</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">757</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1899-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1899-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1899-06-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1899-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="757"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d757">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Loomis</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-06-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 30, 1899</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 301.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to your instruction of June 13, 1899,
                    No. 268, in which I am directed to bring to the attention of the Venezuelan
                    Government the fact that inconvenience and annoyance are caused our consular
                    officers at Venezuelan ports by reason of the Hacienda law, requiring masters of
                    foreign vessels to deposit their ship’s papers with port authorities instead of
                    with the consul, as our law provides, I beg leave to say I presented the matter
                    to the minister of foreign affairs in a note and have received his answer, a
                    translated copy of which I inclose.</p>
                <p>Upon receiving your instroctions I went at once to the President, after sending
                    my note to the foreign office, and had a long talk with him on the subject. I
                    went very fully into the case and told him that I was also in receipt of
                    complaints on the same score from the consuls at La Guaira and Puerto
                    Cabello.</p>
                <p>I cited the Venezuelan law upon the point at issue and was able to relate several
                    instances in which the steamers of the American mail line had been detained long
                    beyond their appointed hour for departure <pb facs="0877" n="781"
                        xml:id="pg_781"/> through the whim of port officials and for no adequate
                    reason whatsoever.</p>
                <p>The President freely and fully acknowledged the Venezuelan law was at fault and
                    earnestly promised, of his own accord, personally to bring the matter to the
                    attention of Congress at its next session and to formally urge the repeal or
                    amendment of the law in conformity with my request.</p>
                <p>I am trying to persuade him to suspend, provisionally, the operation in the
                    clause of the Hacienda law relating to the deposit of ships’ papers, but he
                    thinks his authority is not sufficient, unless he should do so as a war measure
                    during a revolution.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis B. Loomis.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mathieu</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Loomis</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of Foreign Affairs,<lb/>United States
                                    of Venezuela</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-06-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 27, 1899</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: The subject of your communication
                        of yesterday, in regard to a modification of the Venezuelan custom laws as
                        to the deposit of ships’ papers, has, as your excellency knows, been
                        presented several times by the representatives of the United States, but the
                        Government has never been able to accede to the request of your Government
                        because its attributes are limited in cases of this nature. The law touching
                        this point is a part of the general law regulating the finance department,
                        and any modification of said law can be made only by Congress.</p>
                    <p>In 1883 your legation presented this same request and the Government disposed
                        of the matter in the only way possible.</p>
                    <p>Afterwards, in 1885 and 1888, your Government still insisted upon a
                        consideration of this point, and in September, 1888, this ministry, in a
                        communication to his excellency, Mr. Scott, recalled the fact of the
                        Government’s desire to submit the question to the Senate. Later, in 1891, in
                        reply to a communication from Mr. Scruggs, the Government again replied that
                        it could not decide a question with which Congress alone was empowered to
                        deal.</p>
                    <p>And if Congress has not definitely decided the question in all these years it
                        is due to the fact that it is difficult to harmonize the modification sought
                        with other important points of the fiscal laws.</p>
                    <p>I propose, however, to inform the President of the request just made by your
                        excellency, in order that he may determine in what manner it shall be again
                        presented to Congress or to the legislative commission just established.</p>
                    <p>I renew, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">J. Calcano Mathieu.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
