<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1899-09-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1899-09-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="94" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d94">
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hay</persName> to Mr.
                                        <persName type="to">Choate</persName></hi>.</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-09-06"><hi rend="italic">September 6,
                                        1899</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 205.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Government of Her Britannic
                                Majesty has declared that its policy and its very traditions
                                precluded it from using any privileges <pb facs="0224" n="132" xml:id="pg_132"/> which might be granted it in China as a weapon
                                for excluding commercial rivals, and that freedom of trade for Great
                                Britain in that Empire meant freedom of trade for all the world
                                alike. While conceding by formal agreements, first with Germany and
                                then with Russia, the possession of “spheres of influence or
                                interest” in China in which they are to enjoy special rights and
                                privileges, more especially in respect of railroads and mining
                                enterprises, Her Britannic Majesty’s Government has therefore sought
                                to maintain at the same time what is called the “open-door” policy,
                                to insure to the commerce of the world in China equality of
                                treatment within said “spheres” for commerce and navigation. This
                                latter policy is alike urgently demanded by the British mercantile
                                communities and by those of the United States, as it is justly held
                                by them to be the only one which will improve existing conditions,
                                enable them to maintain their positions in the markets of China, and
                                extend their operations in the future. While the Government of the
                                United States will in no way commit itself to a recognition of
                                exclusive rights of any power within or control over any portion of
                                the Chinese Empire under such agreements as have within the last
                                year been made, it can not conceal its apprehension that under
                                existing conditions there is a possibility, even a probability, of
                                complications arising between the treaty powers which may imperil
                                the rights insured to the United States under our treaties with
                                China.</p>
                            <p>This Government is animated by a sincere desire that the interests of
                                our citizens may not be prejudiced through exclusive treatment by
                                any of the controlling powers within their so-called “spheres of
                                interest” in China, and hopes also to retain there an open market
                                for the commerce of the world, remove dangerous sources of
                                international irritation, and hasten thereby united or concerted
                                action of the powers at Pekin in favor of the administrative reforms
                                so urgently needed for strengthening the Imperial Government and
                                maintaining the integrity of China in which the whole western world
                                is alike concerned. It believes that such a result may be greatly
                                assisted by a declaration by the various powers claiming “spheres of
                                interest” in China of their intentions as regards treatment of
                                foreign trade therein. The present moment seems a particularly
                                opportune one for informing Her Britannic Majesty’s Government of
                                the desire of the United States to see it make a formal declaration
                                and to lend its support in obtaining similar declarations from the
                                various powers claiming “spheres of influence” in China, to the
                                effect that each in its respective spheres of interest or influence— <list>
                                    <item>First. Will in no wise interfere with any treaty port or
                                        any vested interest within any so-called “sphere of
                                        interest” or leased territory it may have in China.</item>
                                    <item>Second. That the Chinese treaty tariff of the time being
                                        shall apply to all merchandise landed or shipped to all such
                                        ports as are within said “sphere of interest” (unless they
                                        be “free ports”), no matter to what nationality it may
                                        belong, and that duties so leviable shall be collected by
                                        the Chinese Government.</item>
                                    <item>Third. That it will levy no higher harbor dues on vessels
                                        of another nationality frequenting any port in such “sphere”
                                        than shall be levied on vessels of its own nationality, and
                                        no higher railroad charges over lines built, controlled, or
                                        operated within its “sphere” on merchandise belonging to
                                        citizens or subjects of other nationalities transported <pb facs="0225" n="133" xml:id="pg_133"/> through such
                                        “sphere” than shall be levied on similar merchandise
                                        belonging to its own nationals transported over equal
                                        distances.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>The recent ukase of His Majesty the Emperor of Russia, declaring the
                                port of Ta-lien-wan open to the merchant ships of all nations during
                                the whole of the lease under which it is to be held by Russia,
                                removing as it does all uncertainty as to the liberal and
                                conciliatory policy of that power, together with the assurances
                                given this Government by Russia, justifies the expectation that His
                                Majesty will cooperate in such an understanding as is here proposed,
                                and our ambassador at the court of St. Petersburg has been
                                instructed accordingly to submit the propositions above detailed to
                                His Imperial Majesty, and ask their early consideration. Copy of my
                                instruction to Mr. Tower is herewith inclosed for your confidential
                                information.</p>
                            <p>The action of Germany in declaring the port of Kiaochao a “free
                                port,” and the aid the Imperial Government has given China in the
                                establishment there of a Chinese custom-house, coupled with the oral
                                assurance conveyed the United States by Germany that our interests
                                within its “sphere” would in no wise be affected by its occupation
                                of this portion of the province of Shang-tung, tend to show that
                                little opposition may be anticipated from that power to the desired
                                declaration.</p>
                            <p>The interests of Japan, the next most interested power in the trade
                                of China, will be so clearly served by the proposed arrangement, and
                                the declaration of its statesmen within the last year are so
                                entirely in line with the views here expressed, that its hearty
                                cooperation is confidently counted on.</p>
                            <p>You will, at as early date as practicable, submit the considerations
                                to Her Britannic Majesty’s principal secretary of state for foreign
                                affairs and request their immediate consideration.</p>
                            <p>I inclose herewith a copy of the instruction sent to our ambassador
                                at Berlin bearing on the above subject.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, etc.,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay</hi>.</signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>