<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1898-05-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1898-05-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="133" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Day</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Denby</persName>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-05-26"><hi rend="italic">May 26,
                                1898</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1590.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the receipt of your
                            dispatch No. 2908 of April 7,1898, with its inclosures, setting forth
                            the facts of the murder, on or about February, 1898, of a man named Wong
                            Goni Sing, brother of Wong Fook, both of whom, it is claimed, were born
                            citizens of the United States. It is further claimed by the brother of
                            the murdered man that injustice is being done him by the failure of the
                            Chinese Government to take proper measures for the investigation of the
                            crime and apprehension and punishment of the offenders. Your mediation
                            with the Chinese Government is asked, and you request instructions from
                            this Government as to whether the men referred to are citizens of the
                            United States, and as to what action, if any, you shall take.</p>
                        <p>The courts of the United States have conclusively held that children born
                            to Chinese persons in this country are born citizens of the United <pb facs="0300" n="204" xml:id="pg_204"/> States by virtue of the first
                            clause of the fourteenth amendment to the Constitution.</p>
                        <p>From the petition and papers inclosed by you it would appear that both
                            Wong Fook and his murdered brother, Wong Goni Sing, were born in this
                            country and have remained citizens thereof. If such is the case, and any
                            injustice such as complained of is being done, the interest of this
                            Government is of course aroused, and any needed protection to the
                            surviving brother is to be extended.</p>
                        <p>Before any action can be taken, however, this Government must be
                            satisfied that the facts of citizenship of the brothers or at least of
                            the surviving brother, are well assured. If the brothers were of
                            Caucasian race a certain degree of presumption, in addition to facts
                            stated, would exist in their favor, but being of Chinese race and
                            descent this presumption is wanting. With the fullest desire to protect
                            the interests of the surviving brother, if he be an American citizen,
                            you should, without unnecessary delay, and by correspondence with the
                            United States consul at Canton, satisfy yourself as to whether or not
                            Wong Fook and his brother were born in the United States and continued
                            to be citizens thereof, unless you are already satisfied thereof. The
                            consul in Canton should be in position, by means of direct examination
                            of the claimant and others, and of documents, etc., if any exist, to
                            determine as to the birthplace and citizenship of the brothers. If you
                            shall find that they were citizens, and that the surviving brother is a
                            citizen, and shall further find that injustice is being done by delay or
                            negligence, as claimed, you will at once, upon reciting the essential
                            facts to the Chinese Government, request an immediate and thorough
                            investigation of the affair, with a view to apprehending and punishing
                            the offender. Or if, while determining the citizenship of the claimant
                            and his brother, delay is occasioned, and there is reasonable ground to
                            believe that they may be citizens of the United States, you will then
                            call the attention of the Chinese Government to the case, on behalf of
                            one who claims to be a citizen of the United States, in order that the
                            delay may not be attended by loss of evidence against the offenders.</p>
                        <p>You will understand that it is the purpose of this Government to protect
                            the life, interests, and property of its citizens in foreign lands to
                            the fullest extent, while at the same time careful not to be made the
                            means of redressing the grievances of citizens of other countries in
                            foreign lands.</p>
                        <p>You will keep the Department informed of the conclusions to which you
                            come as to the birthplace and citizenship of these brothers, and the
                            action taken by you.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully, yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">William R. Day.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>