<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Tower to Mr. Sherman.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1898</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1898-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1898-01-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1898-01-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1898-01-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="17"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d17">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tower</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Sherman</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-01-11">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 11, 1898</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 37.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report to yon herewith, for
                    your information, the ease of Siegfried Abeles, a naturalized citizen of the
                    United States, domiciled in the city of New York, who was held by the criminal
                    court at Leitmeritz, in Bohemia, to have evaded the military service to which he
                    was subject by birth, and whose name was inscribed upon the list of deserters,
                    under the military laws of the Austro-Hungarian Empire. By the intervention of
                    this legation, Mr. Abeles has been recognized as an American citizen, his name
                    stricken from the list of deserters, and his freedom from liability to perform
                    military duty in Austria-Hungary established.</p>
                <p>The facts are as follows: Siegfried Abeles was born in Neustraschitz, in Bohemia,
                    on the 8th of August, 1871. He obtained a permit to travel in the year 1891,
                    before he had been enrolled for military duty in Bohemia, and went to America,
                    where he still resides. He was naturalized before the United States district
                    court in and for the southern district of New York on the 4th day of December,
                    1896. It was during the period from 1891 to 1896, while he was absent in
                    America, that he was adjudged to have evaded military duty at home.</p>
                <p>On the 1st of July, 1897, Adolf Abeles, a merchant of Raudnitz, in Bohemia,
                    appealed to this legation, saying that he is the father of the said Siegfried
                    Abeles, the circumstances of whose case he narrated, as will be seen by the
                    translated copy of his communication, which is respectfully submitted herewith,
                    and begged that he might have the assistance of the representative of the United
                    States in securing for his son the privileges which he is entitled to as an
                    American citizen under the convention entered into by the United States and the
                    Empire of Austria-Hungary. The purpose of Mr. Abeles, as he has since informed
                    me, was to establish the citizenship of his said son and to have his name erased
                    from the list of deserters, in order that, after an absence of nearly seven
                    years, he may return to his home to visit his, parents, who, being well advanced
                    in years, greatly desire to see him again.</p>
                <p>After having received Mr. Adolf Abeles’s appeal I wrote to him, on the 16th of
                    July, 1897, acknowledging its receipt, and I informed him that, before I could
                    present his case to the Austro-Hungarian foreign office, it would be necessary
                    for me to have the certificate of naturalization of his son Siegfried Abeles, or
                    a certified copy of it, in order to ascertain his citizenship. In reply to this
                    letter Mr. Abeles sent me the certificate of naturalization of his son, which,
                    proved that he was admitted to citizenship of the United States before the
                    United States <pb facs="0107" n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/> district court in and for
                    the southern district of New York, as above mentioned.</p>
                <p>I addressed a note thereupon to the Count Goluchowski, minister of foreign
                    affairs, in which I inclosed to him the certificate of naturalization of
                    Siegfried Abeles and called his attention to the fact that, not-withstanding his
                    American citizenship, the said Abeles had been adjudged by the court at
                    Leitmeritz to have evaded military duty and his name had accordingly been
                    entered upon the military lists of the district as a deserter. I repeated to him
                    the assertion of Mr. Adolf Abeles that his son is not a deserter and that under
                    the convention of 1870, entered into by the United States and Austria-Hungary,
                    he could neither be held to military service nor be made liable to trial and
                    punishment for nonfulfillment of military duty.</p>
                <p>I requested the minister of foreign affairs to cause due inquiry to be made by
                    the proper authorities with a view to having relief granted and justice done to
                    this citizen of the United States, that, if the facts were found such as had
                    been represented, the name of Siegfried Abeles might be removed from the list of
                    deserters, and that, as an American citizen, he might enjoy freely within the
                    limits of the Austro-Hungarian Empire all the privileges intended to be
                    reciprocally enjoyed by the citizens of each of the high contracting parties
                    within the territory of the other under the said convention of 1870.</p>
                <p>I have now received, from the minister of foreign affairs, a note dated the 11th
                    of January, 1898, in which he inclosed to me the certificate of naturalization
                    of Siegfried Abeles, and announced that the legal naturalization of the said
                    Abeles “is now fully affirmed, the necessary steps taken to terminate the
                    proceedings instituted against him for having evaded military duty, and that his
                    name will be dropped from the list of those liable to military duty, according
                    to the provisions of the treaty of September 20,1870, and he be recognized and
                    treated as an American citizen.”</p>
                <p>The minister of foreign affairs adds that “the father of Siegfried Abeles will be
                    acquainted by the authorities of his district with the dispositions which have
                    been made.”</p>
                <p>A copy of the whole correspondence relating to this case is respectfully
                    submitted herewith.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charlemagne Tower.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 37.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Abeles</persName> to the <gloss
                                type="to">United States Legation</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Raudnitz</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1897-07-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 1, 1897</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Honorable Legation</hi>: My son, Siegfried Abeles, who
                        was born at Neustraschitz, in Bohemia, on August 8, 1871, received
                        permission to go to Germany for two years.</p>
                    <p>While traveling through Germany he reached Bremen in the year 1891. There he
                        got into great distress, having neither money nor work to sustain himself.
                        In this emergency a company of Galicians assisted him and proposed that he
                        should go with them to America. Being inexperienced he accepted this offer
                        of the company who promised to pay all his expenses. He hoped that in
                        America he would find work more readily than in Germany, and that, as soon
                        as he could obtain the necessary means, he would return to his native
                        country.</p>
                    <pb facs="0108" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/>
                    <p>As the time was approaching when he would become liable to military duty, I
                        made inquiry whether my son could not report to the Austrian consul in New
                        York to be enrolled. In compliance with information received on that point I
                        instructed my son to report to the Austrian consul in New York for
                        enrollment; and my son then went to the consulate to be examined and
                        enrolled if found able bodied.</p>
                    <p>The consul told him, however, to make a petition to the Bezirkshauptmann at
                        Raudnitz, in Bohemia, and plead for a prolongation of his permit to travel,
                        and also to request that a certificate be given him to extend his travels to
                        America. The Austrian consul further advised him to write to the
                        Bezirkshauptmann at Raudnitz to forward the conscription lists to America in
                        order that his name might be properly enrolled. Thereupon I addressed the
                        Bezirkshauptmann at Raudnitz, but neither the passport nor the conscription
                        lists were forwarded to the consul in New York.</p>
                    <p>Although Siegfried Abeles subsequently reported again to the consulate in New
                        York, no enrollment was made because there were no conscription lists. After
                        a lapse of five years my son became a naturalized citizen of the United
                        States.</p>
                    <p>In the meantime investigations were made by the district criminal court at
                        Leitmeritz, in order to ascertain the liability of my son to military duty,
                        and his violation of paragraph 45 of the military law of April 11, 1889, No.
                        41; but they were discontinued until further developments.</p>
                    <p>Afterwards I, as father, applied to the district criminal court at Leitmeritz
                        under date of January 30, 1896, and requested that the proceedings should be
                        resumed, stating that my son had been naturalized in the southern district
                        of New York. I inclosed the certificate issued by the court, and asked that
                        his name be struck from the list of those liable to military duty.</p>
                    <p>On May 28, 1897, the district criminal court in Leitmeritz replied that there
                        was no cause for a resumption of the proceedings in this case.</p>
                    <p>This decision of the above named court at Leitmeritz is not in conformity,
                        however, with the provisions of the treaty between Austria-Hungary and the
                        United States of September 20, 1870, according to which emigrants of Austria
                        Hungary who have uninterruptedly resided at least five years in the United
                        States, and who during that time have become naturalized citizens of the
                        United States, will be regarded by the Government of Austria-Hungary as
                        American citizens and treated as such, and vice versa. (Here Article II of
                        the treaty of 1870 is quoted at length.)</p>
                    <p>Therefore, according to this international convention, Siegfried Abeles can
                        not be held to have violated paragraph 45 of the military law, because he
                        was not enrolled as a recruit, and because he had not yet reached the age
                        which rendered him liable to military service at the time he emigrated.</p>
                    <p>As Siegfried Abeles has been declared to be a deserter from the military
                        service, it might happen that, while paying a visit to his parents, he might
                        be arrested and held until his innocence could be proved. But since my
                        request to the court at Leitmeritz for resumption of proceedings has been
                        left without result, I would most respectfully ask—</p>
                    <p>That the honorable legation, alter investigation of this case, would
                        condescend to cause the cancellation of the name of this United States
                        citizen, Siegfried Abeles, from the rolls of persons liable to military duty
                        in the Austro-Hungarian Empire.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Adolf Abeles.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0109" n="13" xml:id="pg_13"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 37.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tower</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Abeles</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1897-07-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 16, 1897</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your application made to this
                        legation on behalf of your son, Siegfried Abeles, who, you tell me, is a
                        naturalized citizen of the United States and whose name now stands upon the
                        list of deserters from military duty in the Austrian service. You ask the
                        intervention of this legation with the Imperial and Royal authorities to
                        have his name removed from the list so that he may return to Raudnitz upon a
                        visit.</p>
                    <p>In order that I may present this case to the Imperial and Royal foreign
                        office here, it will be necessary for me to have the certificate of
                        naturalization of Siegfried Abeles, or a certified copy of the same. With
                        that document in hand to prove his citizenship, I will see what may be done
                        to obtain for him the relief he seeks.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charlemagne Tower</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Minister.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>In reply to the foregoing letter, Mr. Adolf Abeles sent to this legation
                            the certificate of naturalization of Siegfried Abeles, issued by the
                            United States district court in and for the southern district of New
                            York on the 4th of December, 1896.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 37.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tower</persName> to Count
                                <persName type="to">Goluchowski</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1897-08-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">August 23, 1897</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: A complaint has been made at this
                        legation by Mr. Adolf Abeles, a merchant of Raudnitz, on behalf of his son,
                        Siegfried Abeles, setting forth that the name of the said Siegfried Abeles
                        is retained upon the list of those who have failed to perform military duty
                        in the Imperial and Royal army of Austria-Hungary, and that the said
                        Siegfried Abeles is classed as a deserter, although he emigrated some years
                        ago to America and has become a duly naturalized citizen of the United
                        States.</p>
                    <p>The facts of the case appear from Mr. Adolf Abeles’s statement to be as
                        follows: Siegfried Abeles was born on the 8th of August, 1871, in
                        Neustraschitz, in Bohemia. In the year 1891, having obtained a permit to
                        travel, he went to Bremen, in Germany; and in the same year he sailed from
                        Bremen to America. Having resided in the United States uninterruptedly for
                        five years, he was admitted to become a citizen of the United States of
                        America by the United States district court in and for the southern district
                        of New York on the 4th of December, 1896. In the meantime, and during his
                        absence in America, the said Siegfried Abeles was adjudged by the K. K.
                        Kreisals Strafgericht in Leitmeritz to have evaded military duty, and his
                        name was accordingly entered upon the military lists of the district as a
                        deserter.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Adolf Abeles complains that, although he has appealed to the said
                        honorable court to remove the charge of desertion which it <pb facs="0110"
                            n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/> has decreed against his son, and although he has
                        placed in evidence before it the certificate of naturalization of his son to
                        show that Siegfried Abelesis a duly naturalized citizen of the United States
                        of America, yet the said honorable court has refused to relieve Siegfried
                        Abeles from the charge of desertion or to take his name from the list of
                        those who are liable to trial and punishment under the Imperial and Royal
                        laws of Austria-Hungary for nonfulfillment of military duty.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Adolf Abeles asserts, however, that his son is not a deserter, and that
                        under the provisions of the convention concluded on the 20th of September,
                        1870, between the United States of America and the Empire of Austria-Hungary
                        he can neithér be held to military service nor does he remain liable to
                        trial and punishment for the nonfulfillment of military duty; but that, on
                        the contrary, as he has not transgressed any of the provisions, especially
                        of Article II, of the aforementioned convention, and as he has resided
                        uninterruptedly at least five years in the United States, and during such
                        residence has become a naturalized citizen of the United States, he should
                        now be treated as such.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to submit this case to your excellency’s attention, and to
                        request that your excellency will cause due inquiry to be made by the proper
                        Imperial and Royal authorities with a view to having relief granted and
                        justice done to this citizen of the United States; that, if the facts of the
                        case be found such as I have had the honor here to present them to your
                        excellency, the name of Siegfried Abeles may be removed from the list of
                        deserters, and that, as an American citizen, he may enjoy freely within the
                        limits of the Imperial and Royal Austro-Hungarian dominions all the
                        privileges which are intended to be reciprocally enjoyed by the citizens of
                        each of the high contracting parties within the territory of the other under
                        the aforesaid convention of September 20,1870.</p>
                    <p>In support of the statement made by Mr. Adolph Abeles, I have the honor to
                        inclose to your excellency herewith the certificate of naturalization of
                        Siegfried Abeles, issued on the 4th of December, 1896, by the district court
                        of the United States held in and for the southern district of New York.</p>
                    <p>I beg that your excellency will have this document returned to me, in order
                        that I may send it back to Mr. Abeles.</p>
                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charlemagne Tower.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 37.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Count <persName type="from">Welshersheimb</persName> to
                            Mr. <persName type="to">Tower</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-01-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 11, 1898</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In reply to the esteemed note of August
                        23,1897, No. 19, relating to the citizenship of Siegfried Abeles, the
                        contents of which were communicated to the Imperial and Royal ministry of
                        foreign affairs, I now have the honor of informing the honorable envoy of
                        the United States of America, Mr. Charlemagne Tower, that notice has been
                        received from the above-mentioned ministry that, in view of the legal
                        naturalization of the person aforesaid in the United States, which is now
                        fully affirmed, the necessary steps have been taken to terminate the
                        proceedings instituted against him for having evaded military duty, and that
                        his name be dropped from the list of those liable to military duty,
                        according <pb facs="0111" n="15" xml:id="pg_15"/> to the provisions of the
                        treaty of September 20,1870, and he be recognized and treated as an American
                        citizen.</p>
                    <p>The father of Siegfried Abeles, Mr. Adolf Abeles, a merchant living in
                        Raudnitz, will be acquainted by the authorities of his district with the
                        dispositions which have been made.</p>
                    <p>While the undersigned has the honor of returning herewith the inclosure
                        contained in the above-mentioned esteemed note, he avails himself, etc.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Welsersheimb</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">For the Minister.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
