<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1899-01-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1899-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="365" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d365">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Buck</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokyo, Japan</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-01-09"><hi rend="italic">January 9,
                                1899</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 237.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that on the
                            20th ultimo a bill increasing the land tax on rural property by 0.8 per
                            cent and that on urban property by 2.5 per cent was passed by the lower
                            house by a safe majority, thanks to the support of the Liberal party and
                            of some independents. This makes the total tax on rural property 3.3 per
                            cent (0.7 per cent less than proposed by the Government) and on urban
                            property 5 per cent. The operation of this law is conditional upon the
                            simultaneous reassessment of the taxable values of lands, where
                            inequalities of incidence now occur, which reassessment is assured by a
                            bill passed at the same time. The changes made by the committee of the
                            lower house reduced by about half the revenues to have accrued from the
                            bill as introduced by the Government, which provided for a general
                            increase from 2.5 to 4 per cent on all lands. The period of operation of
                            the law is set at five years.</p>
                        <p>A series of Government bills for increasing the revenue to be derived
                            from the sake tax, which includes the increase of the tax on various
                            kinds of sake from 6 and 7 to 12 yen per koku, and on alcohol and
                            spirits from 8 to 13 yen per koku, the prohibition of private brewing
                            for domestic use, and the limitation of the holders of licenses to brew
                            to those manufacturing a considerable amount has also been passed. From
                            this source additional revenue of at least 23,000,000 yen is
                            expected.</p>
                        <p>These two important revenue measures being inadequate quite to meet the
                            expenses of carrying out the post bellum programme, in order to make up
                            the deficit, recourse is being had to a number of smaller means of
                            swelling the national revenue, to wit, to a bill for empowering the Bank
                            of Japan to increase its issue of notes, such issue to be taxed at 1.5
                            per cent, a bill amending the income tax, a bill amending the statutory
                            tariff, so as to raise the duties on Chinese sake, alcohol, and tobacco,
                            and a bill extending the tobacco monopoly to imported tobaccos, of which
                            the Government would thus become the sole purchaser. These bills are now
                            in various stages of passage.</p>
                        <p>Of legislation of interest to foreigners in Japan may be mentioned bills
                            now in the hands of committees providing for changes in the press laws,
                            by which the restriction upon nationality is removed, and any resident
                            of the age of at least 21 may edit, publish, or print a paper in Japan,
                            and also a modification of the business tax law (No. 33, issued 1896),
                            in the sense that when there are stores or other business premises at
                            several places in Japan and abroad, if the capital is not
                            differentiated, the portion of it that is employed at each place of
                            business in Japan shall be estimated and the tax shall be imposed upon
                            that portion, though some of the business premises be in places where
                            the law is not operative.</p>
                        <p>Early in the session of the present Diet a sum of 20,000,000 yen was
                            voted to be transferred to the Crown property from the Chinese
                            indemnity, and was formally accepted by the Emperor. The same spirit of
                            solicitude for the welfare of the Imperial family is to be seen in a
                            vote of funds for the repair and preservation of some of the ancestral
                            imperial tombs.</p>
                        <pb facs="0530" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/>
                        <p>The above sums up the important legislation thus far. It is undoubted
                            that the Government is deeply indebted to the Liberal party for their
                            stanch support, by which alone the necessary laws could be passed. While
                            the present cabinet will in all probability remain in office until the
                            end of the present session of the Diet, it is generally believed that
                            thereafter a number of portfolios will be given to Liberals, and the
                            premier’s portfolio, very likely, to Marquis Ito, who, though not yet
                            actually a member of any party, has always had cordial relations with
                            the Liberals.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">A. E. Buck.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>