<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1898-09-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1898-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="436" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d436">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Newel</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Day</persName>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Hague</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-09-13"><hi rend="italic">September 13,
                                    1898</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 156.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to state that the
                            inauguration of Her Majesty Queen Wilhelmina took place in Amsterdam on
                            the 6th of September, 1898.</p>
                        <p>On the 5th of September, Her Majesty the Queen, accompanied by the
                            Queen-Mother, and attended by four Dutch Indian princes, a full court
                            suite, a guard of honor composed of representatives from all the elite
                            families of the city of Amsterdam and the province of N. Holland, and
                            further by detachments of troops selected from all branches of the army
                            and navy, made her public entry into Amsterdam.</p>
                        <pb facs="0610" n="514" xml:id="pg_514"/>
                        <p>The town was en fete, the streets being gaily decorated, and throngs of
                            people enthusiastically greeted Her Majesty en route from the railway
                            station to the palace.</p>
                        <p>The inauguration ceremony, which took place at 11 o’clock a.m., in the
                            Nieuwe Kerk, an imposing edifice adjacent to the palace, was of very
                            impressive character. The United First and Second Chambers of the
                            States-General had been summoned to a special and extraordinary session
                            in the church, and all were present except the three socialist members.
                            In addition thereto there were present the immediate royal relatives of
                            the sovereign, the whole of the diplomatic corps, the cabinet ministers,
                            the chief officials from the Government departments, the judges, the
                            principal army and navy officers, all those who had in any way assisted
                            in the education of Her Majesty, a very large representation of the
                            elite of the country, and a very numerous body of representatives of the
                            press. The building was crowded with a splendidly dressed audience,
                            space being left for only 50 of the public, who, in order to secure
                            admission, took their stand before 6 o’clock a.m.</p>
                        <p>The Queen, attended by her court in full state, proceeded on foot from
                            the palace to the church, and, just in front of the Queen-Mother, who
                            stood awaiting her, took up her position on a throne specially placed
                            for this occasion on a dais, around which were gathered the royalty, the
                            diplomatic corps, and the Government representatives.</p>
                        <p>In a clear, distinct, and most touching manner the young Queen pronounced
                            the speech from the throne—a copy of which is herewith transmitted in
                            duplicate, together with translation—and then raising her right hand
                            pronounced the oath prescribed by the constitution.</p>
                        <p>The speech was heard with rapt attention, and at its close the heralds
                            proclaimed Her Majesty Queen, and there followed hearty cheering from
                            all parts of the building, the acclamation being taken up immediately
                            after by the crowd outside the building.</p>
                        <p>Subsequently each member of the States-General in turn took the oath of
                            allegiance, which done, Her Majesty left the church in the same manner
                            that she had come, amidst renewed cheering, the ringing of bells, and
                            firing of cannon.</p>
                        <p>In Amsterdam, from the 6th till the 9th, there was a rapid succession of
                            festivities, at most of which Her Majesty with a full suite attended,
                            engrossing the general attention.</p>
                        <p>On the 9th instant the Queen made her public entry into The Hague, and
                            between that date and to-day, the 13th instant, there has been a
                            repetition of the festivities of last week in Amsterdam, The Hague vying
                            with the capital in doing their Queen honor.</p>
                        <p>On the 15th instant there will be a grand naval review at the mouth of
                            the river Maas; the ordinary session—1898–99—of the States-General will
                            be opened on the 20th instant; and on the 22d a review of the troops and
                            a military display will take place on the eastern side of the country,
                            and at all these events Her Majesty will appear.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stanford Newel.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No.
                                    156—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gentlemen, Members of the States-General</hi>:
                                In early life, by reason of the decease of my never-to-be-forgotten
                                father, God called me to the throne which I ascended under the wise
                                and beneficent regency of my dearly loved mother.</p>
                            <p>On the completion of my eighteenth year I assumed the sovereignty, as
                                my proclamation has announced to my loved people.</p>
                            <pb facs="0611" n="515" xml:id="pg_515"/>
                            <p>The hour has now arrived at which I, in the midst of my loyal
                                States-General, invoking God’s holy name, bind myself to the Dutch
                                nation to maintain its precious rights and liberty.</p>
                            <p>I therefore confirm this day the firm bond existing between myself
                                and my people, and the ancient tie between the Netherlands and the
                                House of Orange is sealed anew.</p>
                            <p>My calling is a high one, the task a grand one which God has laid
                                upon my shoulders. I am happy and thankful that it is my lot to
                                govern the people of the Netherlands—a people small in numbers, but
                                great in virtue, mighty both by nature and character.</p>
                            <p>I deem it a great privilege that it is my life’s task and duty to
                                dedicate all my powers to the welfare and prosperity of my loved
                                fatherland. I adopt the words of my loved father as my own:</p>
                            <p>“The House of Orange can never, never do enough for the
                                Netherlands.”</p>
                            <p>In the accomplishment of my task I shall need your help and
                                cooperation, gentlemen, members of the House of Representatives. I
                                am convinced that you will accord it me in full measure.</p>
                            <p>Let us work together for the happiness and prosperity of the
                                Netherlands people. Let that be the main object in life of us
                                all.</p>
                            <p>May God bless your work and mine, that it may tend to the good of our
                                Sutherland.</p>
                            <p>I swear to the Netherlands people that I will ever guard and maintain
                                the constitution. I swear that I will defend and preserve the
                                independence and territory of the Kingdom with all my power; that I
                                will protect the general and private liberty and rights of my
                                subjects, and will adopt all lawful means at my disposal to the
                                preservation and promotion of the welfare of the general public and
                                the private individual, as becomes a good sovereign.</p>
                            <p>“So help me God Almighty.”</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>