<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Woodford to Mr. Day.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1898</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d541</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">541</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1898-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1898-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recBTfVgprHsl1J9K" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85047074"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Famine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1898-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1898-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="541"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d541">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Woodford</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Day</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-03-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 6, 1898</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 166.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt this
                    morning of Department dispatch by telegraph in cipher, which I translate as
                    follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>, <hi rend="italic">March 4,
                                1898.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Woodford</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Minister,
                                Madrid:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Spanish chargé d’affaires presented here yesterday matter covered in
                            yours fourth. Explained to him that vessels are the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Montgomery</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nashville</hi>, small cruiser
                            and gunboat. <hi rend="italic">Montgomery</hi> has called at Cuban ports
                            recently. At the request (of) relief committee these ships will take
                            load of supplies Key West to Matanzas and Sagua next week. This is the
                            most prompt and efficient means of getting supplies to people greatly in
                            need.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Day.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>My dispatch to which you refer as dated March 4 was delivered at the telegraph
                    office here in Madrid on Thursday evening, March 3, at about half past 9
                    o’clock, Madrid time. If Señor du Bosc saw you on March 3, he must have had
                    instructions from Minister Gullon at the same time that Gullon was seeing me and
                    getting me to send his request.</p>
                <p>I can see no just ground of complaint by the Spanish Government because the
                    United States put war vessels at the disposal of charity to feed starving women
                    and children. The United States is not responsible for the policy of
                    reconcentration, with its horrible results of famine, disease, and wholesale
                    murder. Spain has no just cause of complaint, but should be grateful that our
                    people and Government are <pb facs="0775" n="679" xml:id="pg_679"/> doing so
                    much to protect Spanish citizens against the results of Spanish methods of
                    administration and warfare. I appreciate all the difficulties of the present
                    Liberal Government, but I am not sure that it is wisest to be over punctilious
                    with them in these matters of detail in the performance of a great work of
                    humanity and charity. I shall be very careful and very considerate in my
                    conversations and correspondence with the Spanish foreign office, but I am
                    inclined to tell the Spanish minister very courteously, but so that he will not
                    misunderstand me, that our Government and people can not see old men, women, and
                    children dying with starvation by our very shores and not help them in the most
                    prompt and effective manner.</p>
                <p>I have the honor, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stewart L. Woodford.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
