<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Woodford to the President.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1898</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d549</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">549</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1898-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1898-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1898-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1898-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="549"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d549">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Woodford</persName> to the <gloss
                            type="to">President</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-03-19">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">March</hi> 19, 1898</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 46.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: This morning I called at Señor
                    Moret’s house and showed him a telegram which I proposed to send you. He said
                    that he could not approve it officially, as he had not yet the necessary
                    authority, but that he would personally work with me to secure the results
                    therein indicated. After leaving him I then telegraphed you in cipher as
                        follows:<note n="1" xml:id="d549fn1">Ante, <ref target="#pg_692">p.
                            692</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Señor Moret said to me this morning that justice to the Queen required him to
                    assure me in the most positive manner that she had not been privy to or
                    cognizant of any suggestion that she wished to talk with me about any possible
                    cession of Cuba, either to the insurgents or to the United States; that she
                    wished to hand over his patrimony unimpaired to her son when he should reach his
                    majority; and that she would prefer to abdicate her regency and return to her
                    Austrian home rather than be the instrument of ceding or parting with any of
                    Spain’s colonies. * * * I am sure that Mr. Moret to-day regards this [parting
                    with Cuba] as inevitable, and is only seeking the way in which to do it and yet
                    save Spanish honor. He will probably fine the way to do it, even if he has to
                    sacrifice himself. I hope this last may not be necessary. I do not believe it
                    will be. Spain needs such men as he to-day, men of faith, courage, and sincerely
                    patriotic purpose. * * *</p>
                <p>Please note what I say in my dispatch about April 15. I do not suggest a time
                    limit officially stated. That might embarrass you as well as the Spanish
                    Government. But I do regard it as very essential that they should see that the
                    United States mean business, and mean it <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. * * *</p>
                <p>Your resolute and wise action in getting authority from Congress to put the
                    nation in condition both for defense and attack has made peace not only
                    possible, but to-day I think it probable on such terms as you suggest. You see
                    how my faith has strengthened.</p>
                <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stewart L. Woodford.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
