<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1898-04-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1898-04-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="713" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d713">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Jones</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Sherman</persName>.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Buenos Ayres</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-04-28"><hi rend="italic">April 28,
                                1898</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 497.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my No. 491, of the 6th
                            instant, I have the honor to inclose herewith copy and translation of a
                            note from the minister of foreign relations of yesterday’s date, wherein
                            in reply to my note of the day before announcing that Congress has
                            declared a state of war to exist between the United States and Spain, he
                            promptly advises me of his Government’s attitude of neutrality.</p>
                        <p>I also confirm on the overleaf my telegram of yesterday’s “date advising
                            you of this fact.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">François S. Jones.</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chargé d’Affaires ad interim.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No.
                                    497—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Ministry of Foreign Relations</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Buenos Ayres</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-04-27"><hi rend="italic">April 27, 1898</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Chargé d’affaires</hi>: I have had the honor
                                to receive your note of yesterday’s date by which, in compliance
                                with orders from your Government, you are good enough to communicate
                                to me that, in view of the joint resolution of the Congress of the
                                United States, approved the 20th instant, directing intervention to
                                secure the independence of the island of Cuba, the Spanish
                                Government informed the minister of the United States at Madrid on
                                the following day that it considered the above-mentioned resolution
                                equivalent to a declaration of war.</p>
                            <p>In taking cognizance of the deplorable circumstance which compromises
                                the stability of two nations with which this Republic entertains the
                                most cordial relations, His Excellency the President charges me to
                                inform you, for communication to your Government, that he will at
                                all times observe neutrality in accordance with the principles
                                consecrated by international law.</p>
                            <p>Praying for the early termination of the war, I reiterate the
                                assurances of my distinguished consideration.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Alcorta.</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>