<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sir Julian Pauncefote to the Secretary of State.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1898</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d876</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">876</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1898-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1898-04-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1898-04-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1898-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="876"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d876">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Sir <persName type="from">Julian Pauncefote</persName> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">British Embassy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1898-04-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 27, 1898</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Pro Memoria.</hi>]</p>
                <p>In a note dated the 5th instant the United States Government requested the
                    undersigned to obtain permission by telegraph from the Canadian government for
                    four vessels to proceed from the Great Lakes to the Atlantic coast through the
                    canals that are under the control of the Dominion of Canada.</p>
                <p>The permission was immediately granted, and the vessels, two of which are armed
                    revenue cutters, are now in Lake Ontario, awaiting the opening of navigation.
                    Since then war has been declared between the United States and Spain, and the
                    usual proclamation of neutrality has been issued by the Queen.</p>
                <p>After careful consideration, Her Majesty’s Government are of opinion that
                    permission given before the outbreak of war for the four United States vessels
                    to pass through the canals should not now be withdrawn, provided that the United
                    States Government are willing to give an assurance that the vessels in question
                    will proceed straight to a United States port without engaging in any hostile
                    operation.</p>
                <p>Her Majesty’s Government are further of the opinion that the vessels should not
                    be furnished with more coal and stores than are necessary to take them to New
                    York or some other United States port within easy reach.</p>
                <p>In communicating the above to the United States Government, the undersigned has
                    the honor to express the hope that the assurance desired by Her Majesty’s
                    Government will at once be given, in order that the facilities granted before
                    the outbreak of war in respect of the four vessels above mentioned may still be
                    extended without any breach of neutrality.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Julian Pauncefote.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
