<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>204. Telegram From the Embassy in Cambodia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d204</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">204</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-06-17T01:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-06-17T01:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-06-17T01:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-06-17T01:00:00-05:00" n="204"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d204">
                <head>204. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Cambodia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d204fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 751H.00/6–1755. Secret; Priority. Repeated to New Delhi, Ottawa,
                        London, Paris, Saigon, Vientiane, and Bangkok.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Phnom Penh</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-06-17T13:00:00+07:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 17, 1955—1 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1228. Full text of Prince <persName corresp="#p_SN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s open
                    letter to Cambodian Government is at considerable variance with summary prepared
                    from radio monitor service as reported <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>
                        1221.<note n="2" xml:id="d204fn2">Dated June 16, not printed. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 751H.00/6–1655)</note> Complete translation is
                    embodied in my next telegram.<note n="3" xml:id="d204fn3">Telegram 1229 from
                        Phnom Penh, June 17, not printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                        751H.00/6–1755)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0488" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                <p>This morning I called upon Royal High Councillors <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam
                        Sary</persName> and Khim Tit, knowing that former was undoubtedly author of
                        <persName corresp="#p_SN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s open letter. I said since
                    US was co-signatory of agreement May 16 we of course wished to know what Prince
                        <persName corresp="#p_SN1">Sihanouk</persName> had in mind in discussing
                    this accord in his open letter and in demanding that International Control
                    Commission make a finding upon it as being within purview of Geneva agreement or
                    a violation of that pact.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam Sary</persName> and Khim Tit said real purpose of
                        <persName corresp="#p_SN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s statement was to under cut
                    political opposition in country which had been using stick of our <gloss
                        target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss> agreement to beat horse of forthcoming
                    elections. They said opposition had even gone to extreme of seeking to subvert
                    troops by claiming that Royal Government had “sold” Cambodia to Americans.
                    Unless some dramatic measure were taken to end this issue, <persName
                        corresp="#p_SN1">Sihanouk</persName> felt <gloss target="#t_MDA1"
                        >MDA</gloss> agreement would become a major dispute in elections. He
                    likewise felt International Commission should be made to fish or cut bait.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam Sary</persName>, who had undoubtedly masterminded
                    this operation, said key paragraph of <persName corresp="#p_SN1"
                        >Sihanouk</persName>’s open letter is embodied in following challenge:</p>
                <p>“If International Commission judges that Royal Government exceeds these limits
                    (of Geneva Accord) it should officially notify this to Royal Government. If
                    Royal Government refuses to follow recommendations of International Commission,
                    duty of latter is to react officially against such refusal in one way or
                    another.”</p>
                <p>According to involute reasoning of <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam Sary</persName>
                    this challenge to commission cannot be met by <gloss target="#t_ICC1"
                        >ICC</gloss> because Cambodians are confident Canadian member will not vote
                    for a finding that our agreement of May 16 violates Geneva Accord. Since he says
                    by Geneva undertaking <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> must reach decision on
                    all “important” matters by unanimity, <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam
                        Sary</persName> reasons that commission will not be able to make a finding
                    against Cambodian Government but will be limited to reporting its own
                    disagreement back to Geneva powers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam Sary</persName> has outsmarted himself on this
                    point. Article XXI of Geneva agreement<note n="4" xml:id="d204fn4">For text of
                        the Agreement on the Cessation of Hostilities in Cambodia, July 20, 1954,
                        see <ref target="frus1952-54v16#pg_1531">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1952–1954, vol. XVI, p.
                            1531</ref>.</note> is specific on cases which require a unanimous
                    decision by <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> and these do not cover present
                    issue. Article XX would seem to govern commission’s voting procedure and
                    Canadian Commissioner has already indicated to us that he fears being outvoted
                    by Poles and Indians.</p>
                <p>I told Crown Councillors I had no intention of seeing members of <gloss
                        target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> at this juncture and had instructed all members
                    of my official family to refrain from contact with Commission as we wished to be
                        <pb facs="0489" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> sedulous not to influence
                    decisions of Commission. However, I was fairly sure from my previous knowledge
                    of reasoning of Commission Chairman <persName corresp="#p_PG1"
                        >Parthasarathi</persName> that he would not at first seek a unanimous
                    decision that our <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss> agreement violated Geneva,
                    but would seek a unanimous decision to query Cambodian, and possibly US
                    Governments, on certain moot points. This type of unanimous vote, I thought,
                    Indian chairman might in fact achieve, and in consequence it behooved Cambodian
                    Government to be prepared to defend agreement of May 16 as not being a violation
                    of Geneva.</p>
                <p>Councillors concurred in this reasoning and said I could assure my government
                    there was no thought on part of Cambodian Government to go back on agreement of
                    May 16. They said they had debated that issue in their own minds before signing
                        <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss> accord and were firmly determined to
                    live up to provisions of May 16 exchange of notes. As for refutation of possible
                    charges by <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>, they had already prepared
                    extensive brief in reply to an “informal” letter from <persName corresp="#p_NJ1"
                        >Nehru</persName> to Prince <persName corresp="#p_SN1">Sihanouk</persName>
                    in which Indian Prime Minister expressed his doubts as to propriety of Cambodian
                    Government having signed agreement of May 16. I asked Councillors for copy of
                    text of <persName corresp="#p_SN1">Sihanouk</persName>’s reply, but they said
                    they would have to submit this question to their master as it was a personal
                    letter transmitted to <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName> through Indian
                    Minister in Phnom Penh. They thought, however, <persName corresp="#p_SN1"
                        >Sihanouk</persName> would not object to their giving me a summary of his
                    reply. Furthermore, they said that if commission should demand a statement from
                        <gloss target="#t_RKG1">RKG</gloss>, they would wish to consult with me in
                    advance of making a response.</p>
                <p>Khim Tit and <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam Sary</persName> said if in ultimate
                    result May 16 accord were called into question by <gloss target="#t_ICC1"
                        >ICC</gloss> and a finding were made that it violated Geneva agreement, they
                    would most certainly present issue to Cambodian people, apparently by some sort
                    of plebiscite or referendum, the result of which would be an overwhelming
                    popular demand that Cambodia receive US aid according to terms of agreement of
                    May 16. In that event, said <persName corresp="#p_SS1">Sam Sary</persName>, “the
                    will of the people will be overriding”.</p>
                <p>As indicated above, I intended to leave members of commission severely alone for
                    time being. However, since commissioners are not free agents but are acting in
                    accordance with government instructions, Department may wish at their respective
                    capitals to indicate US attitude.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MCR1">
                            <hi rend="strong">McClintock</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
