<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>275. Letter From the Secretary of Defense (Wilson) to the ) to the Secretary
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d275</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">275</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-02-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-02-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rec8f8ab487d399bce" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="mutual-defense-assistance-program">Mutual Defense Assistance Program</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-02-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-02-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="275"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d275">
                <head>275. Letter From the Secretary of Defense (<persName corresp="#p_WCE1"
                        type="from">Wilson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                        State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d275fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 751J.5/2–1655. Top Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-02-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 16, 1955</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I refer to the request of the U.S.
                    Minister to Laos, as outlined in Legtel 193 from Vientiane, dated 22 December
                        1954,<note n="2" xml:id="d275fn2">See <ref target="#d270fn3">footnote 3,
                            Document 270</ref>.</note> and to other pertinent messages and
                    despatches related thereto, whereby he requests a Joint Chiefs of Staff review
                    of a concept for proposed U.S. support of Laotian Forces.</p>
                <p>The Joint Chiefs of Staff have reviewed Minister <persName corresp="#p_YCW1"
                        >Yost</persName>’s recommendations and consider that, from a military point
                    of view, they cannot recommend the provision of Mutual Defense Assistance
                    Program support of Laotian forces over which the United States, under the terms
                    of the Geneva Accords, would have no control. However, in view of the fact that
                    political considerations may be overriding, the Joint Chiefs of Staff did set
                    forth their views,<note n="3" xml:id="d275fn3">See <ref target="#d264">Document
                            264</ref>.</note> not to be considered as a recommendation, as to
                    Laotian forces which would be required in order to maintain internal security in
                    that country.</p>
                <p>In considering the Geneva Accords restriction against the introduction of
                    military personnel into Laos, which specifically mentions instructors other than
                    French, the Joint Chiefs of Staff concluded that there would be only a
                    negligible opportunity for the United States to exercise appropriate control
                    over any U.S. military assistance furnished to Laos.</p>
                <p>In relation to the above, there are three possible courses of action for
                    providing supervision over the end-use of U.S. military equipment by Laotian
                    forces, all of which would require the cooperation of, and liaison and
                    administrative arrangements with the French. They are as follows: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>Monitor the end-use of U.S. military matériel and equipment provided
                            Laotian forces by using only French military personnel in supervisory
                            roles.</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Authorize supervision, in conjunction with the French, by the U.S.
                            Army attaché section attached to the Legation, Vientiane.</item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>Provide qualified U.S. civilian personnel to be attached to the U.S.
                            Embassy, Vientiane and to work in a supervisory role in conjunction with
                            the French.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The complete lack of U.S. supervision if course of action a were adopted would be
                    unacceptable from a military standpoint for obvious reasons.</p>
                <pb facs="0641" n="607" xml:id="pg_607"/>
                <p>The Army attachés at Vientiane (course of action b.), have a primary mission with
                    which end-use supervision of aid programs would seriously interfere; an
                    appreciable build-up of the attaché section would make the U.S. suspect to
                    violation of the Geneva Accords; only general supervision through liaison with
                    the French could be exercised; and the division of responsibility, with
                    considerably less than effective results from a military point of view, would
                    make this arrangement completely unsatisfactory.</p>
                <p>Course of action c., although not considered feasible by the Department of
                    Defense, is the only one which possibly offers a minimum opportunity for U.S.
                    supervision. Even though civilians with military backgrounds might be employed
                    for this purpose, the number obtainable probably would limit U.S. supervision to
                    that of a general nature. The division of responsibility, with considerably less
                    than effective results from a military point of view, would make this
                    arrangement unsatisfactory.</p>
                <p>The Department of Defense concurs in the views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff on
                    this subject, including their statement on force levels. However, for political
                    reasons, the Department of Defense will agree to the selection and financial
                    support of U.S. civilians to be employed for the supervision of military aid
                    programs to Laos provided the Department of State or the Foreign Operations
                    Administration will assume responsibility for the necessary administrative
                    support, including housing, messing and clerical assistance. Therefore, it is
                    requested that the Department of State determine, through Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_YCW1">Yost</persName>, the number of civilian personnel
                        required.<note n="4" xml:id="d275fn4">This was done in telegram 304 to
                        Vientiane, February 25. In addition, the telegram noted that it was
                        “imperative [Lao] Army be quickly reorganized into tighter, more efficient
                        force” at the 23,650 level with divisional organization. <persName
                            corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>’s letter of February 16 and the
                            <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> memorandum of January 21 were
                        summarized in this telegram. (Department of State, Central Files,
                            751J.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/2–1855)</note> When this
                    information has been provided to the Department of Defense, and the Department
                    of State has indicated concurrence in the proposal relating to administrative
                    support as outlined above, the Department of Defense will select and assign
                    suitable personnel for this mission.</p>
                <p>Continued U.S. military support of Laotian forces will be contingent upon the
                    effectiveness of these forces in absorbing and assimilating U.S. military aid;
                    the effectiveness and rate of progress of the French military mission in
                    training Laotian personnel, both officers and enlisted, to man properly the
                    forces to be supported; and future developments in the military and political
                    situation in VietNam.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">C.E. Wilson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
