<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>296. Letter From the Secretary of State’s Special Assistant for Mutual
                    Security Affairs (Nolting) to the Director of the Foreign Operations
                    Administration () to the Director of the Foreign Operations Administration
                    (Stassen))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d296</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">296</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="recYxvE0eBIY2TGf8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="military-balance" lcsh-match="no_match">United States Army</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States aid</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-05-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-05-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="296"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d296">
                <head>296. Letter From the Secretary of State’s Special Assistant for Mutual
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1" type="from">Nolting</persName>)
                    to the Director of the Foreign Operations Administration (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SHE1" type="to">Stassen</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d296fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 751J.5/2–1655.
                        Secret. For drafting and clearance procedures of this letter, see <ref
                            target="#d295">
                            <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                        </ref>. A marginal note by <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>
                        reads: “Concurred in by U &amp;<gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss> subject to
                        later review of amounts.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-05-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 31, 1955</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SHE1">Stassen</persName>
                    </hi>: I refer to the letter of February 16, 1955, from the Secretary of Defense
                    to the Secretary of State<note n="2" xml:id="d296fn2">
                        <ref target="#d275">Document 275</ref>.</note> containing the views of the
                    Joint Chiefs of Staff on force levels necessary to maintain the internal
                    security of Laos, the maximum cost of such force levels, and a statement of the
                    willingness of the Department of Defense, for political reasons, to provide
                    civilian personnel for the supervision of United States military aid programs in
                    Laos. A copy of this letter has been furnished the Foreign Operations
                    Administration by the Department of State.</p>
                <p>It is the established policy of the United States Government to give financial
                    support where necessary to friendly nations in certain threatened areas to
                    protect their territories from foreign aggression and internal subversion. The
                    defense of Laos, by virtue of its geographic position, is highly important for
                    the security of Southeast Asia and for the entire free world.</p>
                <p>Current political and administrative problems faced by the Lao Government
                    preclude the possibility of an immediate reorganization and concurrent reduction
                    in force to conform to the concept set out in the letter of the Secretary of
                    Defense. Therefore, it is requested that you provide financial support for
                    maintenance of the Lao National Army at the current strength of 29,000. It is
                    expected, however, that the Lao Government will reduce its forces as rapidly as
                    possible to the 23,650 level deemed adequate for the maintenance of internal
                    security. The Department of State has requested the American Minister at
                    Vientiane to produce with the United States Army Attaché a joint recommendation
                    on feasible target dates for this reduction and reorganization.</p>
                <p>The American Minister at Vientiane is negotiating a bilateral agreement with the
                    Lao Government on direct forces support, which will serve as the basis for
                    financial aid to the Lao Government and permit forward planning on expenditure
                    of military assistance funds. In negotiating this agreement, the American
                    Minister has been instructed to inform the Lao Government that continued United
                    States aid is contingent upon Lao Government acceptance of the force level <pb
                        facs="0689" n="655" xml:id="pg_655"/> and organization determined by United
                    States representatives to be most effective for maintaining internal security in
                    Laos.</p>
                <p>With respect to supervision of American financial assistance, the United States
                    is precluded from establishing a Military Assistance Advisory Group by the terms
                    of the Geneva Agreement on the Cessation of Hostilities in Laos. Representatives
                    of the Department of Defense, the Foreign Operations Administration, and the
                    Department of State are now conferring on arrangements for the assignment of
                    qualified civilian personnel to be attached to the Legation or the United States
                    Operations Mission at Vientiane. Joint recommendations on staffing requirements
                    for the supervision of American aid funds have been received from the Legation,
                    the United States Army Attaché, and the United States Operations Mission,
                    assisted by a two-member survey team detailed from the Military Assistance
                    Advisory Group and the United States Operations Mission in Saigon.</p>
                <p>It has been agreed that the Department of Defense will furnish civilian personnel
                    to be responsible for the following: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>Determining military end-item requirements.</item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>Supervising end-item use by the Lao armed forces.</item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>Controlling the delivery of military end-items.</item>
                        <label>4)</label>
                        <item>Evaluating the adequacy of the development and effectiveness of the
                            Lao armed forces.</item>
                        <label>5)</label>
                        <item>Advising the Country Team on Lao force levels, bearing in mind the
                            views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</item>
                        <label>6)</label>
                        <item>Reviewing and making recommendations to the Country Team on the costs
                            of maintaining the agreed force levels.</item>
                        <label>7)</label>
                        <item>Assisting and advising the Country Team in screening Lao military
                            expenditures.</item>
                        <label>8)</label>
                        <item>In conjunction with the above-enumerated responsibilities, generally
                            advising on military matters.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In accomplishing this mission, the supervisory personnel supplied by the
                    Department of Defense will operate as an integral part of the Country Team.</p>
                <p>It is hoped that, for its part, the Foreign Operations Administration will
                    augment the Controller’s staff of the United States Operations Mission in
                    Vientiane as required to discharge its responsibilities under Executive Order
                    Number 10575 in the administration of Direct Forces Support and Defense Support
                    programs.</p>
                <p>The Department of State will arrange to provide the necessary additional
                    administrative support, including housing, subject to the usual reimbursement
                    for such services by the appropriate agencies.</p>
                <p>The civilian military specialists furnished by the Department of Defense will
                    assist the United States Operations Mission Controller personnel in a
                    comprehensive study of the cost of supporting the 23,650 force level. The
                    Country Team will review the aid programs for Laos, the American Minister and
                    the Director of the United <pb facs="0690" n="656" xml:id="pg_656"/> States
                    Operations Mission giving due consideration to the absorptive capacity of this
                    undeveloped country of 1.5 million people. Results of the careful cost analysis
                    and realistic review may well call for downward revision of the $46 million
                    figure tentatively allocated for the support of the Lao National Army, despite
                    the necessity of retaining a 29,000 troop strength for several months during
                    Calendar Year 1955.</p>
                <p>This letter has the concurrence of the Office of the Secretary of Defense.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Frederick E. Nolting, Jr</hi>.</persName>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d296fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
