<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>315. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-01-06T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-01-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXODnXWMHfVPqSC" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances">Military cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recCxB7N65K8Uxxym" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ground forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-01-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-06T14:00:00-05:00" n="315" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d315">
                <head>315. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>In a memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_SWJ1">Sebald</persName> suggested that the Department of State
                    raise the question of bilateral military talks between <pb facs="0725" n="691"
                        xml:id="pg_691"/> Thailand and Laos (see <ref target="#d310">Document
                        310</ref>) at a Department of State-Joint Chiefs of Staff meeting on October
                    14. (<persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Sebald</persName>’s memorandum, October 13, is
                    in Department of State, Central Files, 751J.5/10–1355) At the meeting, the issue
                    was discussed as follows:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">“Military Coopération between Thailand and Laos</hi>
                </p>
                <p>“Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Sebald</persName> discussed the desirability of
                    encouraging military cooperation between Thailand and Laos and outlined the
                    program contained in Bangkok’s telegram 856. He asked for <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> concurrence to a telegram to Bangkok which
                    would express our agreement in principle to this program.</p>
                <p>“Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> said he personally saw
                    no harm in encouraging the Thais and Laotians to get together. Admiral <persName
                        corresp="#p_BAAA1">Burke</persName> questioned a sentence in Bangkok’s 856
                    which reads ‘create impression in mind Thai and Laotians of US intention provide
                    substantial support in event armed attack’. He felt it was most unwise to create
                    any ‘impression’. We should know what we are going to do in this area and be
                    ready to back it up. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> fully
                    agreed with Admiral <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Burke</persName>’s comment.
                    Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> said he regarded the
                    Laotian situation as a test of <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>. If we do
                    nothing affirmatively <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> will collapse. If
                    we take a strong stand he feels we will be able to control the situation.
                        <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">General Taylor</persName> wondered whether we
                    should engage our prestige with ground forces in this area and seemed to have
                    serious reservations about the advisability of extensive commitments here.
                    Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> replied that our
                    prestige was already engaged. Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1"
                        >Radford</persName> said the Joint Chiefs would take a further look at this
                    problem.” (Department of State, State–<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                    Meetings: Lot 61 D 417)</p>
                <p>On the next day, the Department of State, with Department of Defense approval,
                    sent the following telegram to Bangkok and Vientiane:</p>
                <p>“Your 856 repeated Vientiane 181.</p>
                <p>“Concur in principle recommendations a, b, c, d, e. Addressees should coordinate
                    manner and timing approaches to Lao Thai authorities and other details
                    implementation. Impending visit Lao military mission to Thailand may give
                    opportunity express views to two governments. No impression should be given Thai
                    or Lao authorities that US does or does not intend provide military forces.</p>
                <p>“Transmit details your jointly recommended plan action soonest before any
                    approaches made to Thai or Lao in order fullest Washington support can be
                    rendered.” (Telegram 1248 to Bangkok, 283 to Vientiane; <hi rend="italic"
                        >ibid.</hi>, Central Files, 751J.5/9–2355)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
