<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-08-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="372" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d372">
                        <head>372. Memorandum of Discussion at the 292d Meeting of the National
                            Security Council, Washington, August 9, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d372fn1">Source: Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Records. Top Secret; Eyes Only.
                                Drafted by Marion W. Boggs on August 10.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1956-08-09">August 9, 1956</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>[Here follow a paragraph listing the participants at the meeting and
                            agenda items 1–3.]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">4. Significant World Developments
                                Affecting U.S. Security</hi></p>
                        <p>The Director of Central Intelligence said that negotiations between the
                            Royal Government of Laos and the Pathet Lao—the latter are sponsored by
                            North Vietnam and control two northern provinces in Laos—have been under
                            way, and an agreement in principle is about to be reached. This
                            agreement, if concluded, will result in substantial gains for the
                            Communists; that is, in gains which must be considered substantial in
                            view of the exposed position of the area. Under this agreement the
                            Government of Laos would adopt a policy of neutralism, establish
                            friendly relations with neighboring countries, refrain from ties with
                            other countries, and permit 1000 men from the Pathet Lao provinces to
                            enter the Army of Laos. The Pathet Lao, for its part, would recognize
                            that the authority of the Royal Government of Laos extends throughout
                            Laos. Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> said that in this situation a
                            great deal depends on Free World and North Vietnamese <pb facs="0825" n="791" xml:id="pg_791"/> action. The agreement between the
                            Government of Laos and the Pathet Lao may be the first step in Communist
                            penetration of the Laotian Government; on the other hand, if the Laotian
                            Government is effective in building up its security forces, the
                            situation may not be lost. Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> thought,
                            however, that the situation in Laos warranted close study, especially
                            study of the possibility that the Communists now had an opening wedge,
                            preliminary to taking over.</p>
                        <p>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> said he had been
                            in the area just last week, and that the negotiations referred to by Mr.
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> were scheduled to start the day after
                            his departure. While there, he learned that President <persName corresp="#p_NDD1">Diem</persName> was more worried about Laos than
                            about Cambodia, because the Laotians were felt to be capricious. It
                            looked as if the Laotians were about to give in and let the Communists
                            enter the government. <persName corresp="#p_Diem1">Diem</persName>, he
                            added, was about to exchange diplomatic representatives with Laos.
                            Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> then expressed
                            some reservations concerning the efficiency of the armed forces of Laos.
                            Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> said that a great deal of effort had
                            been devoted to training security forces in Laos. Admiral <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Radford</persName> asked whether Mr.
                                <persName>Dulles</persName> was referring to training under the
                            French. Mr. <persName>Dulles</persName> said he referred to training
                            under the United States. The Secretary of State said that the training
                            had been in Thailand. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen
                                Dulles</persName> said the security problem was complicated by the
                            long frontier of Laos.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow discussion of the Burmese-Chinese border situation and
                            agenda item 5, “The Suez Canal Situation” (for text, see <ref target="frus1955-57v16#pg_165">volume XVI, page 165</ref>.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">Marion W.
                                Boggs</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>