<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-07-12T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-07-12T08:00:00-05:00" n="456" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d456">
                        <head>456. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d456fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 751J.00/7–1257. Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution.
                                Repeated to London and priority to Vientiane.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-07-12T14:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">July 12,
                                        1957—2 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>243. Reference: <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> sent Paris
                                163.<note n="2" xml:id="d456fn2">Telegram 163 to Paris, sent also to
                                Vientiane as 43, July 11, reads as follows:<p>“Request your views
                                    soonest whether it would be helpful in achieving our objective
                                    or in clarifying French position if we asked French here or
                                    Paris use their resources Laos to assist in obtaining <persName corresp="#p_KDS1">Katay</persName>’s investiture. Should
                                    French be reluctant we would propose request they at least take
                                    no action frustrate <persName corresp="#p_KDS1">Katay</persName>’s bid. We recognize French leak to <persName corresp="#p_SP2">Souvanna</persName> and possibly <persName corresp="#p_PP1">Petsarath</persName> would be inevitable.”
                                        (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 751J.00/7–1157)</p></note> We
                            would think approach to French requesting they use their resources Laos
                            to assist in obtaining <persName corresp="#p_KDS1">Katay</persName>’s
                            investiture would result in no good and probably some harm.</p>
                        <p>French would most likely decline request on grounds “such intervention in
                            internal affairs Laos” undesirable and incompatible with delicacy French
                            role as former protecting power. This attitude may not correspond with
                            actual French activities Laos but it is almost surely one Foreign Office
                            would take.</p>
                        <p>Should we then request they at least take no action frustrate <persName corresp="#p_KDS1">Katay</persName>’s bid, Foreign Office would
                            probably reply, possibly with some indignation, this of course would be
                            their attitude.</p>
                        <p>We agree with Department’s observation word of our approach would
                            inevitably leak back to <persName corresp="#p_SP2">Souvanna</persName>.</p>
                        <p>While we believe approach of type suggested unlikely be helpful in
                            achieving our objective or clarify French position and would probably
                            leave some strain in atmosphere with French, we plan today in general
                            conversation with Foreign Office re Laos make clear we would like see
                                <persName corresp="#p_KDS1">Katay</persName> succeed at this time.
                            We will state that since <persName corresp="#p_PS2">Phoui</persName> has
                            twice declined, <persName corresp="#p_SP2">Souvanna</persName>’s
                            personal prestige too closely tied up with coalition idea, and <persName corresp="#p_PP1">Petsarath</persName>, agreed in US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>-French conversations, dangerous because
                            of his soft attitude toward <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> we believe
                                <persName corresp="#p_KDS1">Katay</persName> best available
                            candidate at present. French would have opportunity present their views
                            and should they subsequently work against <persName corresp="#p_KDS1">Katay</persName> they would be doing so in full knowledge United
                            States attitude and in direct contradiction their earnest plea in
                                US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>-French meeting for cooperation
                            and frankness. We believe this action on our part would not prejudice
                            Department’s decision should Department wish instruct us make more
                            positive approach.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HA1"><hi rend="strong">Houghton</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>