<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-01-18T14:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-18T14:30:00-05:00" n="6" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d6">
                        <head>6. Minutes of a Meeting, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>’ Office, Department of State, Washington, January
                            18, 1955, 2:30 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d6fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 670.901/1–2155. Secret. Drafted
                                by McAuliffe, who is not listed among the participants in the
                                meeting, on January 21. The source text bears the following
                                handwritten notation by <persName corresp="#p_OCRL1">O’Connor</persName>: “OK for dist RO’C”.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-01-18T14:30:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">January 18,
                                        1955, 2:30 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Afro-Asian Conference, Secretary’s Office, 2:30 p.m., January 18,
                                1955</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCCW1">McCardle</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Robertson</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KDMK1">Key</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRR1">Bowie</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Sebald</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Roosevelt</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SCC1">Stelle</persName></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> submitted to the
                            Secretary for approval a draft circular telegram<note n="2" xml:id="d6fn2">Not found in Department of State files.</note> to our
                            Missions in friendly Afro-Asian countries. He recalled that we had
                            previously circularized our Embassies suggesting that the governments
                            concerned withhold a decision as to whether or not to attend the Bandung
                            meeting. On balance, the Working Group now believes we should decide
                            whether or not to advise our friends to attend; and, if the decision be
                            affirmative, to persuade them to send the ablest possible
                            representatives.</p>
                        <p>After reading the suggested circular telegram the Secretary expressed
                            general agreement with its tenor and said he wished to voice <pb facs="0046" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/> a few questions. First, the
                            Secretary noted that the phrase at the end of the first paragraph,
                            “could only be misunderstood by free world”, seemed to imply that our
                            friends in Asia and Africa are not a part of the free world. The
                            Secretary suggested that the phrase “by free world” be deleted, and “by
                            non-Communist nations not participating in Conference”, substituted. The
                            Secretary then asked what will transpire at Bandung which will be
                            disadvantageous to United States interests.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> replied that a
                            resolution on Morocco might well be adopted which would embarrass France
                            and possibly, the United States. Mr. <persName>Robertson</persName>
                            added that any resolution adopted at Bandung unanimously, that is in
                            concert with Communist nations, would have a very bad effect in the
                            United States, particularly in Congress. Mr.
                                <persName>Robertson</persName> also emphasized that the people of
                            China would be represented at Bandung by the Chinese Communist
                            Government and that this very fact was diametrically opposed to United
                            States policy and to the position we have championed in the United
                            Nations. The Secretary then asked what type of resolution the Communists
                            might introduce at Bandung in addition to Tunisia, Morocco, South Africa
                            and the Congo,—the colonialism theme, which they would obviously try to
                            exploit. Mr. <persName>Robertson</persName> said the Communists might
                            try to win unanimous support for a resolution endorsing the <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nehru</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_CE1">Chou
                                En-lai</persName> Five Principles.<note n="3" xml:id="d6fn3">First
                                set forth in the agreement of April 29, 1954, between India and the
                                People’s Republic of China on trade between Tibet and India, the
                                five principles were: (1) mutual respect for each other’s
                                territorial integrity and sovereignty; (2) nonaggression; (3)
                                noninterference in each other’s internal affairs; (4) equality and
                                mutual benefit; and (5) peaceful coexistence.</note> Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> added that there might be
                            a resolution endorsing the admission of Communist China to the United
                            Nations. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Sebald</persName> suggested
                            that a resolution condemning nuclear tests in the Pacific was a
                            possibility.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said we must work up a list of subjects that will possibly
                            be raised by the Communists during the Bandung meeting. In effect, we
                            shall need to make a briefing book for our friends. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> expressed agreement and
                            added that we should also prepare a number of positive resolutions which
                            our friends might introduce. The Secretary nodded and said that this
                            would raise another problem, namely how we would communicate with our
                            friends before and at Bandung without letting this liaison become public
                            knowledge. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> said
                            communications to Bandung are less than good and that this condition
                            will make it more difficult for us to render assistance.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary then asked the meeting when the United States should “adopt
                            a public position” toward the Conference. Is it appropriate for the
                            United States to make its views known at the present <pb facs="0047" n="13" xml:id="pg_13"/> time, he asked? In reply Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> said that we should at this
                            stage consult with the United Kingdom; Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> expressed a caveat, lest we overplay publicly
                            the United States position and thus unwittingly publicize a conference
                            which we do not welcome. The Secretary said he might possibly include a
                            few remarks in a foreign policy speech on February 16 at the Waldorf
                                Astoria<note n="4" xml:id="d6fn4">In his address before the Foreign
                                Policy Association on February 16, the Secretary did not
                                specifically mention the Afro-Asian Conference. For text, see
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, February 28,
                                1955, p. 327.</note> just before proceeding to Bangkok.<note n="5" xml:id="d6fn5">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> and his party left Washington on February 18
                                to attend the meeting in Bangkok of the Council established under
                                the Southeast Asia Collective Defense Treaty. The Council met
                                February 23–25. Thereafter <persName>Dulles</persName> visited
                                several Asian countries and arrived back in Washington on March
                                    6.<p>For texts of the Southeast Asia Collective Defense Treaty
                                    and the Pacific Charter, both signed at Manila on September 8,
                                    1954, by representatives of Australia, France, New Zealand,
                                    Pakistan, the Philippines, Thailand, the United Kingdom, and the
                                    United States, see 6 UST 81 and 91, respectively.</p></note> Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> said he favored a
                            reply to a question at a press conference in the near future, since
                            unfriendly elements abroad are now up-playing the apparently negative
                            U.S. position to our detriment. In support of this, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName> cited the heavy press play in
                            India, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                            referred to recent radio broadcasts from Moscow.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary questioned the wording in paragraph 4 of the suggested
                            telegram noting that no reference to African, as distinguished from
                            Asian states, was made in this paragraph. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName> explained that the British had
                            considerable misgivings regarding attendance by such non-Arab African
                            states as the Gold Coast and the Central African Federation. The
                            Secretary said he surmised we are witnessing the beginning of a new
                            Communist drive into Africa. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen
                                Dulles</persName> added that such a Communist thrust had been long
                            expected but delayed until now because they lacked trained people to man
                            the program.</p>
                        <p>… Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> reported that
                            Iran was unenthusiastic about the Conference and that Lebanon was
                            waiting to learn of the Arab League’s decision. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> said the Turks, who were
                            solidly behind us and were certainly not dupes, would need a special
                            solid instruction from us before they would attend. Mr.
                                <persName>Robertson</persName> said if our Chief of Mission has
                            close relations with a foreign government he should speak very frankly;
                            he should not encourage the conference; he should not minimize the
                            dangers attendant on it; he should point out the many pitfalls to be
                            expected.</p>
                        <p>When the Secretary inquired whether invitations had actually been
                            despatched by the sponsoring nations, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SWJ1">Sebald</persName> replied that Embassy New Delhi had reported that
                            invitations were now ready to be sent. The Secretary said he would not
                            be surprised if various <pb facs="0048" n="14" xml:id="pg_14"/>
                            countries invited began to have doubts once they had a chance to look at
                            the conference a little more closely. He said he didn’t think we should
                            push forward too quickly in our planning since the whole Bandung
                            Conference could conceivably collapse due to the weaknesses inherent in
                            it. Mr. <persName>Robertson</persName> expressed his wholehearted
                            agreement with the Secretary. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> said that in his view the most that could be
                            expected was a postponement of the conference and not a cancellation,
                            since the Prime Ministers of the sponsoring nations had taken a public
                            position from which there was no easy face-saving retreat. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> said the Indonesians are
                            pushing very hard to hold the conference before their local elections.
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName> reported the trend
                            in the Near and Middle East was to attend the meeting, and that the
                            January 22 Arab League meeting to discuss the proposed Pact between
                            Turkey and Iraq, might also deal with the Afro-Asian Conference problem.
                            The Secretary noted the injection of this new element might cause
                            something less than a unanimous decision on the part of the Arab League.
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName> demurred saying that
                            if the Arab states should split on the Turkey–Iraq issue it would be in
                            the Arab character to present a united front on another issue such as
                            this one.… Egypt and Libya have pretty firmly decided to attend the
                            meeting, and that chances are that all Arab states will attend, Mr.
                                <persName>Roosevelt</persName> said. After being informed that the
                            French attitude paralleled that of the British, the Secretary said the
                            telegram under discussion was generally satisfactory but that it should
                            not affirmatively back the conference nor should it give that
                            impression. He said that we should be careful in all our public
                            statements to include the phrase “if a conference is held”. We should
                            not accept the fact that the conference will be held as a matter of
                            course; indeed, we would all be relieved if it never came off.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> suggested that
                            point 1 of paragraph 5 be amended, and his amendments were agreed to by
                            the meeting. The discussion then turned to point 3 of paragraph 5 and
                            substitute language was agreed on. The Secretary observed that the words
                            “free world” recur many places in the telegram. He recalled having used
                            this phrase in a speech in Egypt and the considerable comment it
                            occasioned. He subsequently learned that the Egyptians equate “free
                            world” with the West. He said he feared this phrase might create an
                            unfortunate impression in many other foreign minds and that, he
                            preferred the word “non-Communist”. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> commented that the Bandung conference was
                            dangerous to us, not only because of the resolutions that would be
                            adopted, but also because of the personal associations between Communist
                            and non-Communist leaders which would be formed there.</p>
                        <p>Returning to the text, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJD1">Jernegan</persName> expressed his dissatisfaction with the first
                            portion of the telegram, saying it was a simple repetition <pb facs="0049" n="15" xml:id="pg_15"/> of our earlier message to the
                            Chiefs of Mission and that it might be construed to mean that the U.S.
                            sought to block the conference. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> admitted that our representatives in the field
                            might try to read more into the telegram than it actually contained.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said we wish that the conference were not held; but if it
                            is to be held, we must try to get the best representatives of friendly
                            countries to Bandung, and they must be armed with the best available
                            information. The United States is in an awkward position because we do
                            not know whether the conference will be held. On the one hand, we cannot
                            afford to be simply negative, the Secretary said; but if we are unduly
                            constructive we might help the sponsors. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> estimated that chances were two-to-one that
                            the Bandung meeting would occur. The Secretary and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> agreed that the only
                            cohesive force was the group of sponsoring powers and that the nations
                            being invited are quite ignorant of the status of the invitations. The
                            Secretary then added that it seems likely that many nations will
                            hesitate to decline the invitation until the last minute and will
                            ultimately accept.</p>
                        <p>Acknowledging that we are not too well informed on the present situation
                            Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRR1">Bowie</persName> advised that we pick a
                            date on which to fix the U.S. position. If we wait too long, he said, we
                            shall not have time to do adequate preparatory work and inform our
                            friends. The Secretary said he saw no reason why we should delay making
                            preparations, concerting with the British, and determining what the
                            Communist and Neutralist nations planned to do at Bandung. We should
                            proceed with perfecting our ideas and our resolutions, and the means by
                            which we would convey them to our friends. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> reaffirmed his view that Chiefs
                            of Mission need additional guidance. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> disagreed saying the U.S. cannot send any
                            guidance until the nations to be invited have received their
                            invitations.</p>
                        <p>Summing up, the Secretary said he thought it best to wait a few days
                            before sending any circular. In his judgment, the situation had not yet
                            crystallized. Indeed we know little more now than at the January 7
                            meeting after which the field had been circularized. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> reaffirmed his view that the
                            Chiefs of Mission need more guidance as to our thinking in the
                            Department if they are to succeed in persuading foreign governments not
                            to take a public position. The Secretary noted that, in all probability,
                            no government would receive an invitation for a few days yet, and that
                            the invitations might contain some inkling as to the agenda or
                            procedures at Bandung. This might help us and our friends to determine
                            the path we are to follow. Recalling the difficulties we faced in
                            organizing the Geneva Conference, the Secretary said that the sponsoring
                            nations face similar and possibly greater problems in preparing for
                            Bandung. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> agreed,
                            noting that many of the nations invited do not <pb facs="0050" n="16" xml:id="pg_16"/> recognize Communist China or the Associated States.
                            The Secretary closed the meeting by observing that if we make our
                            decision too soon we may well help the sponsoring powers to make Bandung
                            a success.<note n="6" xml:id="d6fn6">At another meeting held on January
                                25, attended by many of the same officials, <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> informed Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> nothing additional had been
                                learned concerning the nature of the Afro-Asian Conference but that
                                by then it seemed certain the conference would be held. “Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> suggested that the
                                time had come to send the circular cable discussed at the January 21
                                meeting. He thought it the consensus of the group that we should now
                                state that we were in favor of our friends going to the Conference.”
                                After some discussion the Secretary agreed to sending an instruction
                                along those lines. See <ref target="#d8">Document
                                        8</ref>.<p><persName corresp="#p_MCCW1">McCardle</persName>
                                    then “proposed the establishment of an Interdepartmental Working
                                    Group to ‘knock down or take over’ the Conference. The most
                                    feasible means seemed to be the presentation of a general
                                    resolution, so worded the Conference would have to pass it.” The
                                    Secretary agreed to the Working Group and “stated that the
                                    resolution should include parts of the Pacific Charter, and
                                    references to the fraternity of men and to cooperation on the
                                    basis of sovereign equality.” (Memorandum of conversation by
                                    McAuliffe, January 27; Department of State, Central Files,
                                    670.901/1–2755)</p></note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>