<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>122. Telegram From the Mission to the European Communities to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d122</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">122</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-12-30T11:50:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-12-30T11:50:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recdbjtxjnHuY2yic" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ministerial meeting</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Detente</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-12-30T11:50:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-12-30T11:50:00-05:00" n="122"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d122">
                <head>122. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission to the European
                        Communities</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d122fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL 1 <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> W–US. Limited Official Use.
                        Repeated to London, Bonn, The Hague, Luxembourg for the Embassy and USEC,
                        Paris for the Embassy and <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss>, Rome, and
                        Geneva and passed to <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Brussels</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1965-12-30T16:50:00+00:00">December 30, 1965,
                        1650Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Ecbus1">Ecbus</gloss> 525. Ref: Circusito 293.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d122fn2">This telegram, December 17, noted the growing appearance in
                        the Western European media of the line that the United States was tired of
                        European squabbling and preoccupied with Vietnam, and asked for a report on
                        significant developments on the subject. (Ibid., POL <gloss target="#t_EUR1"
                            >EUR</gloss> W)</note> Joint Mission/USIS. Up until the outcome of
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Ministerial Meeting and <persName
                        corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> visit to Washington, there was clear and
                    growing belief that U.S. was losing interest in Europe and Atlantic
                    partnership.</p>
                <p>Four general lines were stressed: <list>
                        <label>A)</label>
                        <item>Washington, tired of European internal squabbling, was in process of
                            soft-pedaling 20-year policy favoring European integration and reluctant
                            to take further initiatives to revitalize Atlantic partnership
                            idea;</item>
                        <label>B)</label>
                        <item>War in Viet-Nam occupies America’s full time and attention and U.S.
                            therefore interested only in peace and quiet in Europe;</item>
                        <label>C)</label>
                        <item>Washington, intent on detente with Soviet Union, prepared to make
                            great concessions at Europe’s expense, to come to terms with other
                            superpower; and</item>
                        <label>D)</label>
                        <item>U.S. unwilling to confront French on important issues of <gloss
                                target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> or nuclear problems and Europe would
                            do better to accept maximum of <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                                Gaulle</persName>’s theses on organization of Europe rather than
                            confront <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> without U.S.
                            support.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Lack of authoritative reaffirmation of U.S. policy toward Europe and Atlantic
                    partnership in troubled period after June 30 <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>
                    crisis contributed much to foster this uncertainty and doubt. It was reinforced
                    by press judgments such as: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Europe Bulletin</hi>, November 9, “… absence of clear
                            indications from Washington” as to its support of Rome Treaty encourages
                            those who “would make the whole of Europe into vast free-trade area
                            excluding agriculture.”, and</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Le Monde</hi>, Washington correspondent Alain Clement
                            on November 21, “At present point of stagnation in American foreign
                            policy, Mr. <persName>Johnson</persName>’s only choice is between a
                            sweeping movement, or sinking into bog of somnambulistic routine … the
                            weakness of his intermittent leadership in this important field is
                            largely responsible for the weakening of American authority abroad.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0328" n="298" xml:id="pg_298"/>
                <p>Mission was also much troubled by extent to which this feeling was expressed
                    privately, but almost without exception, by participants in European Parliament
                    session in Strasbourg November 23–26.</p>
                <p>This mood so deep seated that returning leader grantees generally express
                    surprise at real extent U.S. interest in and support for Europe.</p>
                <p>Even among those in Commission who have formally expressed to us their belief
                    that official U.S. silence on <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> crisis was
                    prudent and welcome, qualifier began to creep in that U.S. should, without
                    involving itself in crisis, restate clearly its general policy on Europe before
                    it was too late.</p>
                <p>In addition to results of French elections, which have had their own impact on
                    European political opinion, U.S. handling of <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> Ministerial demonstrated clearly that U.S. prepared to stay in
                    Europe and develop and improve existing structure without reference to French
                    intransigence. Secondly, reference in <persName corresp="#p_EL1"
                        >Erhard</persName> visit communique<note n="3" xml:id="d122fn3">For text of
                        the joint Johnson-<persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> communique,
                        December 18, see Department of State Bulletin, January 10, 1966, pp.
                        50–51.</note> to support for European unity was most useful, but
                    unfortunately not picked up in European press as far as we aware. Both these
                    developments have had helpful effect, but are not in themselves by any means
                    adequate, in Mission judgment. What is needed is statement in context which will
                    attract widespread attention in Europe.</p>
                <p>This suggests to us that significant portion of President’s State of Union
                    address must effectively treat these Europeans concerns and reaffirm our policy
                    towards and our role in Europe lest this adverse trend of opinion be
                        resumed.<note n="4" xml:id="d122fn4">For text of the State of the Union
                        address, January 12, 1966, in which President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1"
                            >Johnson</persName> briefly mentioned that the United States would take
                        new steps to help strengthen the unity of Europe and the Atlantic community,
                        see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States:
                                <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B. Johnson</persName>, 1965</hi>,
                        Book I, pp. 3–12.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Fessenden</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
