<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-02-18T19:52:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-02-18T19:52:00-05:00" n="132" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                    <head>132. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and
                            European Regional Organizations</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d132fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, DEF 4
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CH4">Cleveland</persName> and approved by Spiers. Passed
                            to <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-02-18T19:52:00-05:00">February 18, 1966, 7:52 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>4020. <gloss target="#t_NATUS1">NATUS</gloss>. For <persName corresp="#p_FPJ1">Farley</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_CH4">Cleveland</persName>. Meeting of Nuclear Planning Working Group went
                        extremely well.<note n="2" xml:id="d132fn2">The Nuclear Planning Working
                            Group of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Special Committee of
                            Defense Ministers met in Washington February 18. For text of the press
                            release issued at the conclusion of this first meeting, see Department
                            of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, March 7, 1966, p. 368.</note>
                        Ministers had done their homework, partly on the special flight together
                        Wednesday. Discussion around table among them achieved an intimacy and a
                        relevance quite out of the ordinary for international meetings, especially
                        on so complex a subject.</p>
                    <p>It quickly emerged that there was a consensus on the adequacy of existing
                        strategic nuclear forces, though perhaps there were still some <pb facs="0346" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> questions about whether more of
                        the total force should be in Europe (the “<gloss target="#t_MRBM1">MRBM</gloss> issue”). It was therefore decided to try to capture and
                        record this consensus as part of the concluding action document which sets
                        forth the Working Group’s future program of work.</p>
                    <p>As you will see from the agreed conclusions (in separate telegram),<note n="3" xml:id="d132fn3">Circular telegram 1573, February 18. (Department
                            of State, Central Files, DEF 4 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>)
                            The agreed conclusions accepted that the size of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> strategic nuclear forces was adequate
                            to deter a large-scale Soviet attack, but there appeared to be no way to
                            prevent unacceptable damage to the West from an all-out nuclear
                            exchange. The Defense Ministers also instructed their Deputies to
                            prepare studies for further consideration on tactical nuclear forces and
                            participation in nuclear planning by non-nuclear Alliance
                            members.</note> work program for next two months places considerable
                        responsibility on Deputies in Paris, and implies sizeable analytical tasks
                        both in Washington and in <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss>. Please
                        arrange early date for me with General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> for discussion of where we stand on Special
                        Committee work and discussion of how Working Group III Deputies can best
                        work with <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss>.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                                <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>