<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>133. Message From President Johnson to Prime Minister to Prime Minister
                    Wilson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">133</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recFNTAI3hc5KYJyr" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general">Nuclear
                        policy</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="133"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                <head>133. Message From President <persName type="from">Johnson</persName> to Prime
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_WJH2" type="to">Wilson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d133fn1">Source: Department of State,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName> Diaries: Lot 64 D 327.
                        Secret. A typed note at the top of the source text reads: “The following
                        message was transmitted directly to Prime Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName> from President <persName
                            corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> on February 20, 1966.” A copy of
                        the message was transmitted to London in telegram 4853, February 20, for
                            <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName>’s information. (Ibid.,
                        Presidential Correspondence: Lot 67 D 262)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-02-20">undated</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>As you leave for Moscow, I want to share my thoughts with you on one further
                    problem that you have occasion to discuss with the Russians. This is the problem
                    of relations between the negotiations on non-proliferation and our efforts to
                    get an agreed Atlantic nuclear policy. I think we have to walk a careful line
                    between contending groups which would give one or the other of these related
                    problems an overriding priority.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Government continues to assert that any form of cooperation with Bonn
                    in the nuclear field is dangerous. While this position <pb facs="0347" n="317"
                        xml:id="pg_317"/> may in part reflect a genuine concern about the Germans
                    getting control over nuclear weapons, it is also plain that the Soviets are
                    seeking to use the issue as a means of causing trouble in the <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Alliance.</p>
                <p>The main point of Soviet tactical pressure in the coming weeks is likely to be
                    the language of the non-proliferation treaty. They will be pressing for language
                    which would bar what they call “access” to nuclear weapons by non-nuclear
                    powers. Their evident purpose is to foreclose the possibility of nuclear
                    arrangements in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> which would involve the
                    Germans more intimately in the business of nuclear defense.</p>
                <p>We are inclined to think that the best way to counter the Soviets on this—and to
                    get on with a constructive treaty—is to focus discussion on the true meaning of
                    proliferation, and, at the same time, to convince Moscow that we will not sign a
                    treaty which would rule out <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> nuclear
                    arrangements which would not, in fact, involve proliferation.</p>
                <p>In our new draft treaty, we have suggested that proliferation results when a
                    non-nuclear nation acquires its own national control, or the right or ability to
                    fire nuclear weapons without the concurrent decision of an existing nuclear
                    nation. In addition, there should be no increase in the number of states and
                    organizations which have control of nuclear weapons. In general, the draft
                    represents an attempt to come to grips with the real problem of proliferation
                    without sacrificing the legitimate interests of the non-nuclear members of the
                    Alliance.</p>
                <p>In any case, I think it most important that we not let the Soviets maneuver us
                    into a position which would arouse strong and honest resentment in Germany. To
                    let them do this would be no service to the cause of non-proliferation, since it
                    would increase the very dangers that the Soviets constantly stress.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Government is surely not blind to one further aspect of this
                    matter—namely, that there is on this issue, a pronounced difference of emphasis
                    between your public opinion and ours. They are bound to see advantage in trying
                    to exploit that difference to set us against one another. We must be careful not
                    to fall into that trap.</p>
                <p>My own view is that we should keep an absolutely even handed view of these twin
                    problems. A sound non-proliferation agreement and a sound Atlantic nuclear
                    policy are in truth mutually consistent and reinforcing. I do not accept the
                    argument that we must finally solve the Alliance nuclear problem before there
                    can be a treaty. But I think we should equally reject the notion that we can
                    push aside the Alliance problem now, and go along with a treaty which would rule
                    out, or drastically narrow, possibilities for a <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> nuclear arrangement which would not result in
                    proliferation.</p>
                <p>On non-proliferation, we can meet the legitimate interests of the Soviet
                    Government because they are the same as our own. But we must not let the Soviet
                    use this most important issue to undermine German <pb facs="0348" n="318"
                        xml:id="pg_318"/> confidence in our willingness to treat their nuclear
                    problem seriously and constructively. This course naturally tempts some in
                    Moscow, but it is no more in the Soviet interest than in ours.</p>
                <p>I thought it would be useful for me to give you this indication of my own
                    thinking, because of the great advantage which comes to us both when we stand
                    together.</p>
                <p>I hope you will have a good trip and I send you once again my best wishes for
                    success in your effort to get Soviet help in reconvening a Geneva
                        Conference.<note n="2" xml:id="d133fn2">On February 26, following his return
                        from Moscow, Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName>
                        reported that the 3-day visit was “hard pounding.” He noted the Soviet
                        obsession with the prospect of Germany obtaining access to nuclear weapons.
                        In this regard, <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName> told the
                        President that he had assured Moscow of his and U.S. opposition to German or
                        European independent nuclear deterrents and that nuclear sharing within
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> or an <gloss target="#t_MLF1"
                            >MLF</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ANF1">ANF</gloss> force was the best
                        means of meeting legitimate German demands. The Prime Minister concluded
                        that he had probably not convinced the Soviet Union, but had given it
                        something “to chew over.” (Ibid.)</note> I am doing what I can to keep the
                    public discussion here from complicating your task, but it is an understatement
                    to say that I do not control it completely.<note n="3" xml:id="d133fn3">Printed
                        from and unsigned copy.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
