<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>158. Telegram From the Embassy in France to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d158</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">158</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-04-22T12:20:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-04-22T12:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-04-22T12:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-04-22T12:20:00-05:00" n="158"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d158">
                <head>158. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d158fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, DEF 4 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Secret; Immediate.
                        Repeated to the other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> capitals and
                        passed to the White House and <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-04-22T17:20:00+00:00">April 22, 1966,
                        1720Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>7054. I saw <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de Murville</persName> this
                    afternoon at five o’clock and he delivered to me the French reply to our
                    aide-memoire of April 12 (text in telegram to follow).<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d158fn2">The French text and the Embassy’s translation were
                        transmitted in telegram 7053 and 7055 respectively, April 22. (Ibid.) For
                        text, see <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current Documents,
                            1966</hi>, p. 336.</note> I read the reply and told <persName
                        corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName> that I was disappointed that the French
                    Government had not considered it suitable to accept the suggestion we had made
                    for the termination. I said this suggestion would have provided a legal basis
                    for the common consent provided for in the agreements as well as certain
                    additional time to complete practical measures. I added that following my visit
                    this week to some of our bases in France I could tell him that it would be
                    physically impossible to complete the closing of the bases within the time
                    fixed.</p>
                <pb facs="0403" n="373" xml:id="pg_373"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName> said that they were not denouncing
                    the agreements, to which I replied that I thought we should not have a play on
                    words since in effect they were terminating the agreements by unilateral action
                    whereas the agreements specifically provided in four of the cases for their
                    termination by mutual consent if they concurred before the expiration of the
                    treaty. I told him I did not know what the American reaction would be but I
                    could only take note of the fact that his government was in violation of the
                    terms of the existing agreement. I also told him that we could not accept the
                    one year date fixed in the French memorandum and if we did negotiate it would
                    have to be under some form of juridical protest in regard to this date.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName> said that the date was of course
                    something that could be discussed and that it was not intended to be an absolute
                    fixed date in all cases. I repeated what I had said previously. I pointed out
                    that the reference to military authorities in suggesting Paris as a locale might
                    give the idea that it was a French proposal that it should be a military
                    discussion. <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName> said no, this was
                    definitely not the case and the only reason the military had been mentioned was
                    to underline the fact that there were competent American military on the spot
                    here in Paris. He said what they envisaged from their side was Beaumarchais and
                    de <persName corresp="#p_DGJC1">la Grandville</persName>. I told him that we
                    wouldn’t have any ideas as to our negotiating team until we had accepted the
                    idea in principle.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName> then asked me what did I think
                    about publishing the aide-memoire and I said as a personal opinion I thought it
                    would be desirable to publish it since there had been a great deal of
                    speculation in the French press as to its contents, some of which had been very
                    close to the mark. <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName> said it was
                    immaterial to them whether it was published or not and he had only thought there
                    should be an end to the “polemics” in the press.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that the French would publish on Sunday for Monday morning papers
                    unless the Department has other ideas, in which case we will notify the Foreign
                    Office over the weekend. If we hear nothing the French will go ahead with the
                    agreed arrangement.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">
                            <hi rend="strong">Bohlen</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
