<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-04-29T08:50:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-04-29T08:50:00-05:00" n="160" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d160">
                    <head>160. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Germany</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d160fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, DEF 4
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Confidential. Repeated to
                            London and Paris.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-04-29T13:50:00+00:00">April 29, 1966,
                            1350Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>3507. Subj: <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, France and Germany. Ref:
                        Paris’ 1133.<note n="2" xml:id="d160fn2">Telegram 1133, April 26, suggested
                            that West Germany would be tempted to take advantage of the present
                            crisis in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, but the fact remained
                            that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> was forcing it to
                            take positions that it would not have asserted on its own initiative.
                            (Ibid.)</note> For the Secretary and the Under Secretary.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>I welcome the expression of views in <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> on the effects of the France-<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> crisis on Germany. The possible
                            consequences outlined in the <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss>
                            would clearly represent the most desirable outcome. It is to be hoped
                            that events will follow such a course. No doubt Germany’s role will be
                            enhanced by <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s recent
                            actions, and it will be a challenge for US policy in the period ahead to
                            encourage Germany to play a responsible role in the Atlantic Alliance
                            and in Europe. At the same time, there remains in Europe a deep distrust
                            of Germany. Nor must we close <pb facs="0406" n="376" xml:id="pg_376"/>
                            our eyes to the possibility that other, less desirable consequences
                            could derive from a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>-wide
                            confrontation with France—in which the FedRep is called upon to play a
                            key role.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Two points in this respect will bear particularly close watching. One
                            is the effect on the FedRep’s European policy—if an estrangement with
                            France should occur. If the present confrontation results in a
                            withdrawal of French forces from the FedRep, German public opinion will
                            not react with exhilaration. Many will see in it a defeat for the
                            carefully nurtured German-French friendship—and for Europe. Many will
                            ask themselves with whom Germany could now seek to build Europe. After
                            dinner last evening Min <persName corresp="#p_WL5">Westrick</persName>,
                            State Sec <persName corresp="#p_HKU1">Von Hase</persName>, and
                            Baden-Wurttemberg Min Pres <persName corresp="#p_KKG1">Kiesinger</persName> all expressed dismay at the possible
                            withdrawal of French troops. They greatly fear the political
                            consequences of a French withdrawal, which they seem to feel is now
                            quite possible.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>If as a result of a French-German rift, European unity seems
                            increasingly less attainable, there will inevitably be a tendency here,
                            as we have pointed out, to turn more actively toward the other elusive
                            goal of German policy—reunification. The problem which would then
                            confront us—as well as Germany’s other partners—is the extent to which
                            we can in fact help Germany to attain this goal. In this game, key cards
                            are held by the other side.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">
                                <hi rend="strong">McGhee</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>