<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-05-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-05-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="163" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                    <head>163. Memorandum by <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Dean
                            Acheson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d163fn1">Source:
                            Department of State, Central Files, DEF 4 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>.
                            Attached to the source text are a transmittal memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, May 13, and a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> to the President, also dated May
                            13, saying that the memorandum had been prepared at Rostow’s suggestion
                            and that he and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> agreed
                            that it formed a good basis for further guidance on negotiations with
                            France over <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" when="1966-05-13">Undated</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p rend="center">BROAD LINES OF APPROACH TOWARD NEGOTIATIONS WITH FRANCE IN
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> CRISIS</p>
                    <p>In approaching any negotiation it is important to understand clearly the
                        relationship of the parties. Are they seeking a common object and sparring
                        for compatible individual advantage—as in a horse trade? If so, bargaining
                        is the avenue to agreement. If, however, one has taken a position from which
                        it will not recede, and from which it cannot be forced to recede, there is
                        small room for negotiation.</p>
                    <p>In the past weeks the French government has been at pains to demonstrate the
                        latter is its attitude towards <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. It
                        will not discuss its <pb facs="0409" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> decisions
                        that French troops must be withdrawn from commitment to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> command and French officers from service
                        in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> commands. Similarly its demands
                        that all <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and U.S. command headquarters
                        and all U.S. troops, facilities and supplies must be withdrawn from France
                        are not subject to negotiation. All that can be discussed are “practical
                        measures” for carrying out these decisions, a deadline for which the French
                        government has arbitrarily set. Even the French Ministry of Defense admits
                        that so far as <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> facilities and
                        headquarters are concerned these dates cannot be met.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has responded that its troops and
                        facilities will be withdrawn from French territory as soon as this can be
                        done without prejudice to military security. There are no negotiations
                        required about withdrawal.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has offered to negotiate the
                        amendment or cancellation of the agreements under which the facilities were
                        established. It has not been thought compatible with the dignity of the
                            <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> to accept unilateral cancellation of
                        agreements made for the life of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Nor
                        has acceptance of unilateral cancellation seemed appropriate when the <gloss target="#t_GOF1">GOF</gloss> simultaneously offered to discuss new
                        agreements about reentry into France in time of war. The French government
                        has not answered the offer to negotiate the agreements. The draft
                        aide-memoire submitted by you to the President<note n="2" xml:id="d163fn2">This particular draft has not been further identified.</note> seeks to
                        make the record clear on this important point, without haggling about our
                        withdrawal.</p>
                    <p rend="center">What Can Be Negotiated and Its Importance</p>
                    <p>The impressive fact is how little of any real importance is open to
                        negotiation in the France-<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> crisis.</p>
                    <p>The indisputable fact is that France wants everything French out of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, and everything <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>—especially everything American—out of France. This, if one
                        may say so, poses a rather clear cut issue.</p>
                    <p>In the political field it is paralleled by another equally clear cut
                        difference. As was made clear to Senator Church in Paris recently,<note n="3" xml:id="d163fn3">Senator Church’s conversation with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> on May 4 was summarized in
                            telegram 7498 from Paris, May 5. (Department of State, Central Files,
                            POL <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> W) His May 19 report to the
                            President on his discussions with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                                Gaulle</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName>, and other European
                            leaders is in the Johnson Library, National Security File, Memos to the
                            President, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>, Box 7,
                            Vol. 3.</note> the French government wants a European settlement by
                        Europeans, i.e., by “the underlying reality of Europe … Russia in Eastern
                        Europe and France, England and to a lesser extent Italy in Western Europe …
                        the other countries of Europe were so much dust ….” The agreement would seek
                        a “reunited Germany without nuclear arms and the withdrawal of foreign
                        forces from such a Germany, including, of course, military forces <pb facs="0410" n="380" xml:id="pg_380"/> of the United States.” To most
                        Western Europeans simple mathematics makes this appear as Soviet domination
                        of Europe. Our allies have not seen this issue of policy as a
                        misunderstanding which can be talked out. The parties are not separated by
                        details. They are poles apart.</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Fourteen, to be sure, have matters
                        which must be talked out with the French; but they are of relatively minor
                        importance. How insistent will the French be in pushing a hurried evacuation
                        of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> establishments? In limiting <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> overflights? In pinching off the flow of
                        oil across France? Is it in the interest of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> to cloak the withdrawal of France from the Alliance? How
                        valuable is French liaison with the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                        commands, and how much reliance can be placed on an agreement to use French
                        facilities in time of conflict.</p>
                    <p>The matters which stand out from the mechanics of leaving France are: <list>
                            <label>1)</label>
                            <item>The presence of French troops in Germany.</item>
                            <label>2)</label>
                            <item>Allied overflights through French air space.</item>
                            <label>3)</label>
                            <item>Continued transportation of oil across France.</item>
                            <label>4)</label>
                            <item>Reentry rights into facilities in France in case of war.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>There is also a matter which concerns chiefly the United States—the
                        termination of valid bilateral agreements.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">1) The presence of French troops in Germany</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The presence of all foreign troops in Germany is governed by a series of
                        agreements of 1954, one of which requires their being committed to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> command in case of conflict. The French
                        government has given notice of the cancellation of this commitment so far as
                        their forces are concerned (two and one-third divisions and some air units)
                        on July 1st.</p>
                    <p>Both the Germans and the other allies have seen the issues raised here by the
                        French as primarily political rather than military. The Germans have
                        accordingly informed the French, with the unanimous concurrence of the other
                        thirteen allies, that the continued presence of French troops in Germany
                        would be welcomed provided a new agreement was reached regarding their
                        mission and their commitment to <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss>
                        command in the time of conflict. To make this specific the note proposed
                        that the transfer of command take place when all other troops in Germany
                        should have come under <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss>’s command.
                        This proposal was to resolve the ambiguity introduced by the French
                        interpretation of the NAT as committing them to defend against “unprovoked”
                        attack. Both French and German positions may be negotiable.</p>
                    <p>Despite dialectical form, the heart of the allied position is that unless
                        troops in Germany are unequivocally there on a joint allied defense mission
                        under the treaty, their status reverts to occupation forces in what General
                            <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> described to Senator
                        Church as a defeated and <pb facs="0411" n="381" xml:id="pg_381"/> divided
                        country. The divisive effect of such a result is a net loss to the
                        Alliance.</p>
                    <p>On the basis of current intelligence, the <gloss target="#t_GOF1">GOF</gloss>
                        is discussing this week whether or not to negotiate this matter. Apparently
                        it would wish in any event to withdraw the troops after the February–March
                        French elections. It may decide to do so during the summer.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">2) Allied overflights through French air space</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The right to conduct military overflights in France is of very substantial
                        importance to us and the Alliance. Without the use of French air space
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> air communications between
                        Northern Europe and the Mediterranean area are possible only by following a
                        long and wasteful route over the Atlantic. The right to continue training
                        flights over France is equally important, since air space over Germany, the
                        UK and the <gloss target="#t_Benelux1">Benelux</gloss> countries is not as
                        suited for such flights because of traffic congestion and recurrent bad
                        weather. Aware of this, the French have reduced overflight agreements with
                        the U.S. and other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries to a
                        month-to-month basis.</p>
                    <p>French need to overfly other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries
                        and to have access to information from the early warning system should
                        provide the Alliance with strong bargaining position in negotiating
                        continued overflight rights. Without such information and overflight rights
                        the Force de Frappe would lose whatever credibility it now has.</p>
                    <p>However, reports of General <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                        Gaulle</persName>’s discussion of this matter indicate he rules out the
                        possibility of a Soviet attack on Europe, and hence regards of little
                        immediate value French access to air defense information and foreign air
                        space. Nevertheless, the situation itself puts some pressure on the <gloss target="#t_GOF1">GOF</gloss>. To take an extreme position would be
                        inconsistent with that of an ally. It would suggest more neutrality or
                        hostility. This together with the keener appreciation of the situation held
                        by the French military may maintain tolerable overflight rights.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">3) Continued transportation of oil across France</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The last French aide-memoire, while contemplating ending the flow of oil
                        across France through our pipeline to U.S. forces in Germany, indicated some
                        realization of the high-handedness of this action. It suggested France might
                        not insist upon terminating use in one year. This action is so outrageous as
                        to warrant a rather full and public exploration of the grounds put forward
                        as justification for it and a claim for just compensation for the
                        nationalization of the facility. The aide-memoire recently forwarded to the
                        President lays the foundation for this.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">4) Reentry rights into facilities in France in case of
                            war</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_GOF1">GOF</gloss> has offered to discuss this subject
                        with the interesting qualification that it cover only situations in which
                        both nations are at war. <pb facs="0412" n="382" xml:id="pg_382"/> Since the
                        only wars concerned are those which involve action under Article 5 of the
                        NAT, the qualification indicates awareness of the possibility that the U.S.
                        might be at war in Europe when France might not be. This qualification ought
                        to be plumbed to see how firmly it is held and what it may mean.</p>
                    <p>If significance is attached to it, the value of reentry rights obtainable is
                        much diminished. One would certainly not be justified in placing much
                        reliance on them in planning for the security of our large forces in
                        Germany. Nevertheless, they would be worth negotiating to have a framework
                        of agreement regarding, and possibly custodial forces maintaining, some
                        facilities which another French government might make really useful.</p>
                    <p>The exercise of negotiating the agreement, therefore, could well be
                        worthwhile, as was the negotiation of the Austrian State Treaty. One can
                        never tell when a document of this sort can come in handy. The United States
                        would not be justified in making any concessions of importance to get
                        it.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">
                                <hi rend="strong">Dean Acheson</hi>
                            </persName><note n="4" xml:id="d163fn4">Printed from a copy that bears
                                this typed signature.</note>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>