<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-05-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="165" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d165">
                    <head>165. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant and Deputy Special
                        Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName type="from">Rostow</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Bator</persName>) to
                        President <persName type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d165fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Memos
                            to the President, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>,
                            Box 7, Vol. 3. Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-05-18">May 18, 1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> is the next big item on the foreign
                        policy agenda: <list>
                            <item>—<persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> will be seeing
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName> on May 23, and we
                                should decide whether you should reply to <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName>’s long letter before
                                then;</item>
                            <item>—On June 6–8, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> foreign
                                ministers will be meeting as a group for the first time since
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> made his move.
                                We have been working with <persName corresp="#p_TGM1">Thomson</persName> on a draft joint statement you should see
                                before it becomes final. In the meantime,</item>
                            <item>—Bob McNamara will be sending you his recommendations on
                                relocation of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and U.S.
                                facilities in a few days.<note n="2" xml:id="d165fn2">A copy of <hi rend="italic">McNamara</hi>’s recommendations, dated May 25,
                                    which stated that the Department of Defense was prepared to move
                                    U.S. personnel and facilities out of France as promptly as
                                    practicable, is ibid., Papers of <persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Francis M. Bator</persName>, Box 28, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Bilateral
                                    Negotiations.</note>
                            </item>
                            <item>—On French troops in Germany (the hottest near-term political
                                issue), the U.S.-UK-German working group in Bonn has circulated to
                                the Fourteen its report on how we should negotiate.<note n="3" xml:id="d165fn3">A copy of this report was transmitted in
                                    telegram 3661 from Bonn, May 7. (Department of State, Central
                                    Files, DEF 4 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>)</note> It
                                suggests a fairly tough initial line, and we shall have to decide
                                what fallback position to take and when, in the light of a French
                                reply which will come soon.</item>
                            <pb facs="0415" n="385" xml:id="pg_385"/>
                            <item>—On other defense arrangements with France (overflights, the oil
                                pipeline, wartime re-entry) we have a draft aide-memoire<note n="4" xml:id="d165fn4">This draft of the aide-memoire is attached as
                                    Tab B to the source text, but is not printed.</note> which we
                                have held at State’s request until we could get your guidance on the
                                general negotiating position.</item>
                            <item>—Under <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Dean Acheson</persName>’s
                                chairmanship, State and Defense have been working hard on the
                                nuclear issue, and on constructive proposals for the Alliance, in
                                response to NSAM 345.<note n="5" xml:id="d165fn5">
                                    <ref target="#d159">Document 159</ref>.</note> The nuclear part
                                of the package will be ready at the end of the week.</item>
                            <item>—You should consider a major speech on European policy before
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> goes to Moscow
                                (June 20). Many Europeans (including Lecanuet)<note n="6" xml:id="d165fn6">Jean Lecanuet, French Senator.</note> have
                                suggested its wisdom at this stage.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>How we play our hand during the next several weeks will not only help
                        determine the future shape of the Alliance, but will seriously affect German
                        and European politics, and might even affect our own.</p>
                    <p>We will need Presidential guidance specifically on: (1) our <pb facs="0416" n="386" xml:id="pg_386"/> negotiating position on French troops in
                        Germany, (2) whether to send another aide-memoire on defense arrangements to
                        the French, and (3) our overall negotiating stance.</p>
                    <p>There is a further reason for early Presidential involvement. Some of your
                        advisers—notably <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>—are a bit shellshocked from
                        newspaper stories suggesting that they are at odds with you. This is bad
                        business for us and makes the Europeans, particularly the Germans, uneasy.
                        Your giving them a day in court, and then your personal guidance, should
                        permit us to be—and appear to be—a united and purposeful government.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Procedure</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>At Tab A is a tight, crisp memo by <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Dean
                            Acheson</persName><note n="7" xml:id="d165fn7">
                            <ref target="#d163">Document 163</ref>.</note> which Secretaries
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> have agreed should serve as a
                        basis for discussion with you. It covers all the major issues, but does not
                        attempt to lay out negotiating strategy or tactics. After reading it—you
                        will wish to read it in full—and perhaps an in-house session with the two of
                        us, we recommend an early extended meeting with Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName>, et al. (One topic for
                        discussion would be the draft aide-memoire at Tab B.)</p>
                    <p>The rest of this memo contains our thoughts on what might be the agenda for
                        such a meeting: (1) U.S. objectives in the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> crisis; (2) <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                            Gaulle</persName>’s objectives; (3) our public position vis-a-vis
                            <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>; (4) our negotiating
                        position on French troops in Germany; (5) whether to send an aide-memoire or
                        communicate our response in some other way; and (6) general negotiating
                        instructions.</p>
                    <p rend="center">1. U.S. Objectives</p>
                    <p>There is little disagreement on essential U.S. interests. We must try to: <list>
                            <item>—maintain an effective integrated deterrent, providing for the
                                security of U.S. and Allied forces in Europe;</item>
                            <item>—maintain solidarity among the Fourteen. (This requires that our
                                position vis-a-vis the French appear to the others as reasonable on
                                its merits, while generating sufficient realism and determination
                                among the Fourteen to face the expensive problem posed for us by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s high-handed
                                and disruptive decisions. It also requires that we continue to make
                                clear our commitment to an evolving constructive <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, which can serve as a base for a
                                policy of bridge-building to the East.)</item>
                            <item>—minimize the strain on German politics by (1) helping <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> resolve the French troops
                                issue along lines most acceptable in terms of long-run German
                                politics, and (2) by making generally clear that they can count on
                                U.S. support when they want to be firm, and on U.S. understanding
                                for any efforts to keep the Franco-German rift to a minimum;</item>
                            <item>—impose a price on <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                                    Gaulle</persName>, while leaving an empty chair for France.
                                (Punishing <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> verbally
                                is not serious or useful business. But it is essential for our
                                security—and for the negotiation—that we be (and appear to be)
                                capable of mounting an effective integrated deterrent without
                                France. He remains, despite his stance, politically vulnerable in
                                his domestic politics to isolation from the rest of the
                                West.)</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">2. What <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> is
                        after</p>
                    <p>How he actually will play his hand we don’t know. He evidently wants maximum
                        freedom of action and yet appear to the French people to have the protection
                        of the Alliance. Much depends on what he gets or doesn’t get in Moscow, and
                        on the unity of the Fourteen. His operational goals in relation to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> are probably somewhere on a spectrum
                        bounded by: <list>
                            <label>(a)</label>
                            <item>a neutralist position: with French troops out of Germany; France
                                out of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>; and no special defense
                                arrangements with the U.S. or other Allies; and</item>
                            <label>(b)</label>
                            <item>a diluted <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>: where France
                                keeps her troops in Germany; maintains her membership in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> planning groups and early warning
                                network; permits allied overflights; and <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> remains in Paris.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>During his Moscow trip, it is a fair bet that he will try to get the Russians
                        to hold out just enough of a promise of movement toward German <pb facs="0417" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> unity to bedevil German political
                        life without cutting the ground from under Ulbricht. If the Russians don’t
                        play, he is more likely to opt for a diluted <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and against a neutralist position.</p>
                    <p>What is clear, irrespective of what happens in Moscow, is that as a
                        negotiator he will go to great lengths to be in a position of granting
                        favors and not asking them.</p>
                    <p rend="center">3. The importance of how we look</p>
                    <p>The safest bet is that except on overflights, the French will be unreasonable
                        and negotiations will be unsuccessful. <hi rend="italic">The issue which is
                            not addressed in the <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName> memo
                            is what posture we strike in testing <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                                Gaulle</persName>’s intentions.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Here there is a difference of emphasis among your advisers: <list>
                            <item>—Sect. <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName> believe that we must, both
                                in public and private, talk about the serious consequences of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s unilateral
                                decisions, and to take a fairly hard line. Their reasons are: this
                                is an expensive, difficult business he has imposed on us, and if we
                                fudge over what he has done, the European (and perhaps U.S.) public,
                                parliaments, and Congress will not put up the resources to maintain
                                an integrated deterrent. The Italians and Danes, for example, might
                                slide away towards detached positions; and the Germans might move
                                towards bilateralism vis-a-vis both Paris and Washington.</item>
                            <item>—Sect. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> doesn’t
                                want to argue with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>
                                much, but simply get on with the job of building an integrated,
                                streamlined deterrent without France, negotiating in the quietest
                                way possible.</item>
                            <item>—<persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Bator</persName> has (in Rostow’s
                                view, correctly) emphasized for some time the need for us to take
                                positions which (1) do not get beyond what <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> can manage in domestic
                                politics, and which (2) do not unduly strain political life in other
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> countries. He wants to be
                                sure that, if <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> will
                                not accept those minimum conditions which we and the Germans must
                                really insist upon, it will be clear to the world that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> alone is responsible for
                                the breakdown—that the monkey is on his back.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The State Department has tended to take positions a bit harder than those we
                        could live with and let others water them down in negotiation.</p>
                    <p>The other way to play it is to state positions closer to the minimum; hold to
                        them; and avoid the charge of being unreasonable with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>.</p>
                    <p>The State Department should be heard attentively, because they are on the
                        firing line. But Rostow’s net view (in which <persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Bator</persName> concurs) is: <list>
                            <item>—We probably will not be able to avoid some public discussion of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s position,
                                given Church, Fulbright, etc.; but that discussion and statements of
                                our differences should be precise and temperate.</item>
                            <item>—The key to the negotiation is action to put <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> in a position where it can live
                                and operate with or without France.</item>
                            <pb facs="0418" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/>
                            <item>—We are strong enough to state moderate positions and hold to them
                                in negotiations with both France and our Allies.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The balance here is so delicate that each key issue must be looked at
                        separately.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">4. French troops in Germany—how we negotiate</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>As you know, until now the French troops (2–1/3 divisions and some air units)
                        have been committed to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> command in time
                        of crisis. <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> has said that
                        this commitment will end on July 1. The Germans maintain that commitment
                        destroys the legal basis for keeping French troops on German soil. <hi rend="italic">Whatever the legal case, French presence without a new
                            agreement is unacceptable as a matter of German politics—it would smell
                            of occupation</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The Germans—with our full support—have told the French that their troops are
                        welcome to stay “provided a new agreement is reached regarding their mission
                        and their commitment to <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss> command in
                        time of conflict.” This condition is subject to several interpretations—the
                        key is what we mean by “commitment” and whether we really mean <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss> command (as opposed to some
                        face-saving, common but two-hat command arrangement).</p>
                    <p>The joint U.S./UK/German negotiating paper (which is now in the hands of the
                        Fourteen) takes a tough initial line—insisting that the French publicly
                        undertake a commitment to assign these troops to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> when those members of the Alliance with troops in Germany
                        agree that a state of emergency exists. He is thus asked to give up a veto
                        which he now holds as a full member of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                        and to undertake a commitment formally tougher than, for example, ours. On
                        the other hand, the question is posed because of the unilateral actions he
                        has taken.</p>
                    <p>Nobody thinks <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> will agree to
                        this; it is meant as an opening tactic from which we are willing to retreat.
                        The question is how and when. (The “when” is critical because it was agreed
                        between <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> and the Germans in
                        Bonn that a new German-French agreement must be under negotiation by July 1,
                        or the French must begin withdrawing their troops.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The outlines of a reasonable fall-back position are fairly
                            clear</hi>. We would ask <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                            Gaulle</persName> to commit France: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>to a meaningful military mission for the two divisions;</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>to join in peacetime planning and joint maneuvers;</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>to place her forces under common command in time of crisis;</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>to reaffirm Article V of the Treaty (the mutual security
                                provision) without any qualification.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">ball</persName> is now in the French court.
                        Our intelligence indicates that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                            Gaulle</persName> will ignore our maximum conditions and inform the
                        Germans he <pb facs="0419" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/> will remove his troops
                        by July 1, 1967. He will try to blame the Germans—and us—for not making an
                        agreement, and strengthen rising domestic pressures on <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> to soften his line.</p>
                    <p>Whatever he does, we must avoid being subject to the charge that we presented
                        impossible conditions to the French and that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                            Gaulle</persName>’s negative response is justified. It must be
                        understood that our initial offer is just that. The operational questions
                        are: <list>
                            <item>—whether we let a confrontation build in this matter between now
                                and July 1; or</item>
                            <item>—whether we indicate to the French that we could live with
                                something short of the initial proposal;</item>
                            <item>—and, if so, by what route we put on the record that our proposal
                                was not a final proposal, and that it is <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> (and not the Germans, U.S., UK) who is
                                being unreasonable.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Operationally, we must await the French reply and then consult closely the
                        Germans and others.</p>
                    <p rend="center">5. Whether to send the aide-memoire</p>
                    <p>The Aide-Mémoire is a formal list of sharply stated specific questions and
                        legal positions having to do with overflights, wartime re-entry, use of our
                        oil pipeline across France, etc. <hi rend="italic">The issue is not whether
                            these questions get asked, but how</hi>—whether we ask them in a formal
                        aide-memoire, which will be in the papers the next day, or through private
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_LCE1">Lucet</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName>
                        conversations based on an informal list of questions.</p>
                    <p>The status of these defense issues varies. On overflights, we may be able to
                        strike a straightforward bargain: overflights in return for continued French
                        access to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> air defense information and
                        air space. The pipeline issue is tougher (and is discussed in detail in the
                        aide-memoire). However we handle it, we will probably want to make our own
                        separate alternative arrangements. The question of access to French
                        facilities in wartime is also cloudy, but probably worth trying to
                        negotiate. (In each case—and whatever bargain we strike—our military
                        planning will have to be hedged for the possibility that the French will not
                        perform.)</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">The issue of whether to send the aide-memoire comes down
                            to whether we want another public show of our legal position or a quiet
                            clarification</hi>—knowing throughout that we are unlikely to be
                        satisfied whichever tack we take. The two of us would vote for the quiet
                        approach; but before making up your mind, you should hear the case for the
                        aide-memoire from Sect. <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_ADG2">Acheson</persName>.</p>
                    <p rend="center">6. General negotiating instructions</p>
                    <p>After going through these papers and hearing the arguments, you will wish to
                        give marching orders on our general negotiating position.</p>
                    <pb facs="0420" n="390" xml:id="pg_390"/>
                    <p>We would suggest that, in a <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, et
                        al, meeting, you make clear that: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>in our public position you want to minimize any suggestion of a
                                direct Washington/Paris confrontation;</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>if public exposition of our differences is required, it should be
                                in terms of an integrated military alliance versus bilateralism or
                                fragmentation of the West;</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>you do not wish the U.S. to be in a position of begging anything
                                of the French;</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>we should proceed with the Allies to plan the prompt movement of
                                people and equipment out of France;</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>on French troops in Germany, you wish us to be exactly as sturdy
                                as <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName>, but we should not
                                push him into positions that are costly in terms of his domestic
                                politics unless he is pressured by his Gaullists into positions
                                which would endanger the security of our troops, or the integrity of
                                    <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> command
                                arrangements;</item>
                            <label>(6)</label>
                            <item>with respect to Allied overflights and French access to Allied
                                communications and intelligence, we should indicate our hope that
                                both can be maintained; but our planning should be based on the
                                possibility that we shall have to operate without overflights; we
                                should make clear to the French that we regard these two as an
                                inextricable package;</item>
                            <label>(7)</label>
                            <item>with respect to the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> oil
                                pipeline, we should plan for a capability sufficient to help defend
                                Western Europe without reliance on the French, while seeing what we
                                can negotiate after <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                                Gaulle</persName>’s return from Moscow;</item>
                            <label>(8)</label>
                            <item>without public acknowledgment, our plans and actions should convey
                                that we are moving to maintain an effective collective defense
                                without France, while trying to make fair and even-handed
                                arrangements to keep France in a close working relationship with the
                                Alliance.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Our willingness to do without the French—and our actions which indicate our
                        preparedness to do without them—constitute our best negotiating cards, given
                            <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s sensitivity to
                        “isolation”; but in fact as well as in posture there is enough ambiguity in
                            <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s commitment so that it
                        would be imprudent to be dependent on France, during his time, in a period
                        of crisis or conflict.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <list>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">
                                        <hi rend="strong">Walt</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>
                                        <hi rend="strong">FMB</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>