<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-06-09T05:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-06-09T05:30:00-05:00" n="176" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                    <head>176. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d176fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, DEF 4 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">McGhee</persName> and approved in <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>
                            on August 12. The source text is labeled “Part 2 of 11.”</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1966-06-09T11:30:00+01:00">June 9, 1966, 11:30 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>French-<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Issue</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">U.S.</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                                <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MGGC2">George C.
                                        McGhee</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Llewellyn
                                        Thompson</persName>, Ambassador-at-Large</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SJR3">J. Robert Schaetzel</persName>,
                                    Deputy Assistant Secretary, European Affairs</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>
                            </hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Ludwig Erhard</persName>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Gerhard Schroeder</persName>, Federal
                                    Minister of Foreign Affairs</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName>Ludger Westrick</persName>, Minister for Special
                                    Tasks</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HKU1">Von Hase</persName>, Press
                                    Chief</item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Karl Carstens</persName>, First State
                                    Secretary, Foreign Office</item>
                                <item>Horst Osterheld, Foreign Affairs Adviser</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The Chancellor thanked the U.S. for the support given Germany in the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> crisis up to this point. He hoped that we
                        could continue together to a successful conclusion. He posed this question
                        to the Secretary: “How do you evaluate the prospects for both the bilateral
                        and multilateral negotiations with France?” He did not wish the bilateral
                        German-French negotiations to occupy the center of the total
                        negotiation.</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> replied that France has
                        posed for the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> a far-reaching problem.
                        They have not attempted to look into the future in order to improve <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>—instead they have retreated 100 years to
                        policies which have in the past led to disaster. We will be dealing with the
                        French on many issues ranging from French troops in Germany to the continued
                        use of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> pipeline in France. The
                        question he wished to raise with the Chancellor is, “Why <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> does what he does. We know what
                        he does, but why?” If <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> is
                        deeply dissatisfied with the present situation, serious problems lie ahead
                        for us. Does the Chancellor have any thoughts on this?</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor replied that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>
                        talks of Europe—however, he considers the Europe of the six to be useful
                        only in its economic and financial significance—not in any political sense.
                        Moreover, he does not consider these or the remaining countries of Europe,
                        including the <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss>
                        <pb facs="0443" n="413" xml:id="pg_413"/> countries, in terms of any
                        European confederation. He seeks only a Europe under French hegemony. He has
                        in the past tried to persuade Germany to join in forming such a Europe.
                        However, Germany considers that this would be an act of treason against
                        Europe. It is clear that <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>
                        wants to get the U.S., at least U.S. influence, out of Europe. He will seek
                        in Moscow a protectorate of the Soviet Union and France over Germany.</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> rejoined that the U.S.
                        considers itself European—indeed, more European than most Russians. He
                        considers that the 14 have in Brussels agreed to “continue what we need to
                        do.” France is not an important world power—in Europe it ranks fifth, fourth
                        and third, respectively, in population, wealth and military forces. France
                        is not in fact important enough to force the future of the 450 million
                        people of the Atlantic area to its will. Let <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                            Gaulle</persName> react as he chooses. He must not interfere with our
                        getting the job done.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> agreed, but said that he was
                        anxious not to see Franco-German friendship shattered. Germany must live
                        with France. What did the U.S. people think about the importance of
                        France?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> said that in a recent
                        poll in America 76 percent of the people were for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, 6 percent against; 74 percent were against <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s policy, 6 percent for. This
                        illustrates the attitude of our people towards <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> and <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. What
                        concerned him was that through the division of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> we are missing an opportunity to take advantage of the
                        widespread disarray now existing in the Communist world.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> replied that this was exactly
                        the German attitude. The question is: Should we come to terms with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> or not? The U.S. and U.K. are,
                        for example, not interested in the terms granted the French for the
                        stationing of their troops in Germany, since both have troops here on the
                        same basis. Would the U.S. and the U.K. put up with France being given a
                        favored position? (The Chancellor appeared to be asking this question half
                        seriously—half rhetorically.)</p>
                    <p>The Secretary replied that he could tell the Chancellor in great confidence
                        that French Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve de
                            Murville</persName> had told him yesterday in Brussels that the French
                        Air Forces will be withdrawn from Germany.<note n="2" xml:id="d176fn2">No
                            record of this conversation has been found.</note> This was because
                        their reaction in the event of hostilities would be automatic, which the
                        French want to avoid. We should not retreat from the positions taken during
                        the <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> visit to Bonn<note n="3" xml:id="d176fn3">See <ref target="#d156">Document 156</ref>.</note>—nor
                        in the subsequent decisions taken by the 14. Let’s see what it is that
                            <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> offers. The U.S. fully
                        understands that Germany does not wish to have occupation troops in Germany.
                        We do for our part, however, have a <pb facs="0444" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/> very real military interest in the status of other troops in Germany. We
                        need to know what the French troops will do in the event of war. In the
                        Secretary’s judgment <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> will
                        probably not accept automatic involvement—or foreign command—in the event of
                        war.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> said that he was glad to hear
                        what the Secretary had said. Germany’s defense, one might say, consists of
                        various layers. It is impossible to organize unless all elements know what
                        the others will do. He is not optimistic that we will be able to reach
                        agreement with <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> on the troop
                        issue. When thinking of whether or not to make concessions—we must remember
                        that <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> must not only deter but be in a
                        position to fight.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary said that we must not show an anti-French attitude—but should
                        proceed quietly. Couve had yesterday given evidence that he would retreat
                        when challenged. He didn’t know what would come out in the end.</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor asked how the U.S. expected to come out in its own bilateral
                        negotiations with France. The Secretary replied that we would be delayed
                        beyond the time limit set by the French in moving some of the big
                        installations we had in France. He did not believe, however, that they would
                        be confiscated by the French. In dealing with the oil pipeline, for example,
                        we want to be sure that oil will come out of the other end when we need
                        it.</p>
                    <p>The Chancellor referred to <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName>’s
                        forthcoming visit to Moscow. He was not concerned as to the outcome, since
                        he could see no possible “joint line of policy.” <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> wants “to have his back free” in negotiating for
                        the future of Europe. <persName corresp="#p_EL1">Erhard</persName> said he
                        particularly feared, in this connection, the “softening up” of Europe. He
                        was glad to know that his own Foreign Minister had spoken in Brussels
                        against a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>-Warsaw Pact discussion. He
                        considered that this would be dangerous. What were the Secretary’s
                        views?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> replied that there had
                        been no official discussion of the <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                            Gaulle</persName> visit between U.S. and the French. Couve had, however,
                        in his personal discussions with the Secretary, promised that there would be
                        “no surprises.” The Soviets are not likely to value very highly French
                        ability to deliver in any agreements made. As he had said in the recent
                            <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> meeting, America would expect to be
                        present in any negotiation for the future of Germany and Europe. We are in
                        Europe and we have interests here, and we will play a role in any
                        negotiations about its future.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary commented that the upcoming negotiations between <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and France are likely to be very tough.
                        The Chancellor asked if he has any timetable in mind for these negotiations.
                        The Secretary replied that the French troop issue was perhaps the most
                        important. It would tend to set the timetable. If this drags on
                        interminably, a very unfavorable impression will be created. The Chancellor
                        commented that the bilateral <pb facs="0445" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/>
                        German talks with the French will involve only legal questions affecting the
                        status of the French forces. No agreements on these matters would be finally
                        approved except in agreement with the 14.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary replied that the real trouble in Brussels was with Canadian
                        Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MPJ3">Martin</persName> and the
                        Danes. The five nations named to negotiate with the French on the troop
                        issue are a solid group. If they stick together, he believes we will
                        prevail. There may be troubles along the way, but not in the final
                        stages.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>