<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-08-06T13:25:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-08-06T13:25:00-05:00" n="191" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d191">
                    <head>191. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and
                            European Regional Organizations</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d191fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, DEF 4
                            FR–US. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BEJ1">Beigel</persName>;
                            cleared by <persName corresp="#p_GJI1">Getz</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SWJJ1">Stoessel</persName>, <gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss>, and OASD/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss>; and
                            approved by Vest. Repeated to the other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> capitals.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-08-06T14:25:00-04:00">August 6, 1966, 2:25 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>23304. <gloss target="#t_NATUS1">NATUS</gloss>. Ref: Paris 1801.<note n="2" xml:id="d191fn2">Telegram 1801, August 5, asked for a summary of the
                            status of U.S.-French bilateral talks. (Ibid.)</note> You should inform
                        next meeting of 14 of status US bilateral discussions with France along
                        following lines: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>Two meetings have been held at sub-ministerial level to identify
                                problems relating to withdrawal of US forces and materiel from
                                France. US indicated that while it did not accept deadline of next
                                April 1 for such withdrawal, it nonetheless is planning removals as
                                rapidly as feasible. It was made clear, however, that a period
                                beyond April 1 will be required to complete removals of logistics
                                facilities. These discussions are to continue as US relocation plans
                                are completed.</item>
                            <pb facs="0472" n="442" xml:id="pg_442"/>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>Two meetings have also been held at ministerial level regarding
                                right of re-entry by US forces and materiel into military facilities
                                in France at time of a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> alert,
                                or in other circumstances such as Berlin crisis. French side made
                                clear no US military personnel or stocks could remain in France in
                                peacetime. They will seek clarification whether exception could be
                                made for pipeline operation. Couve further made clear that his
                                instructions were that no re-entry would be possible except after
                                declaration by war by France. He was willing to seek clarification
                                whether France might agree to re-entry on occasion of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> alert in which France
                                participated. This will be subject of further discussion in
                                September. US indicated that it would wish utilize certain airfield,
                                depot and communication facilities as well as pipeline in time of
                                emergency so they would be fully operational in event of
                                hostilities.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                                <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>