<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>192. Letter From Foreign Minister Schroeder to Secretary of State to
                    Secretary of State Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d192</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">192</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-08-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-08-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-08-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-08-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="192"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d192">
                <head>192. Letter From Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SG3" type="from"
                        >Schroeder</persName> to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3"
                        type="to">Rusk</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d192fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, DEF 4 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Confidential; <gloss
                            target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>. Translation. The German language
                        original is attached to the source text.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-08-08"
                            >August 8, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Dear <persName corresp="#p_DSP1">Dean</persName>,</p>
                <p>I am writing to you today about certain press reports alleging that the United
                    States Administration intends to reduce the number of American forces in
                    Germany. Some of these reports are said to stem from background information
                    given to journalists by American officials, reference being made among others to
                    a talk between Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> and Herr
                    Gillesen of the <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</hi>. I do not
                    know whether such conversations actually took place, and even less whether their
                    contents have been accurately reproduced by the journalists, nor is there any
                    need for me to tell you that my own judgment has not been influenced by these
                    press reports, but I have the feeling that these apparently quite numerous
                    background talks about American troops in Germany do not do American-German
                    relations any good. It is inevitable that such statements, <pb facs="0473"
                        n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/> however carefully phrased, are given a sharper and
                    more sensational accent in the press, which of course has a particularly
                    detrimental effect on a matter of such delicacy.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, <persName corresp="#p_HKU1">Herr von Hassel</persName> has told me
                    about his Paris talks with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                    who, I was pleased to hear, dissociated himself from the press reports and
                    stated in particular that the 15,000 or so troops withdrawn from Germany would
                    be replaced by the end of the year. But I wonder all the more whether it would
                    not be better to refrain altogether from giving to the press such intensive
                    background information on the question of American troops in Germany, since it
                    is obviously not possible to achieve the right and intended effect by means of
                    such talks.</p>
                <p>In my opinion this matter can only be dealt with satisfactorily if our two
                    Governments exchange their views very frankly and confidentially in as small a
                    group as possible. I hope that the Chancellor’s visit to Washington at the end
                    of September will offer an opportunity for it. I am, dear
                        <persName>Dean</persName>, very much looking forward to seeing you again on
                    that occasion.<note n="2" xml:id="d192fn2">On August 8, <persName
                            corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> sent a short 2-paragraph reply in which
                        he expressed appreciation for this letter and said that the subject of
                        American troop levels should be discussed during the Chancellor’s
                        forthcoming visit to Washington. (Ibid., Presidential Correspondence: Lot 67
                        D 272)</note>
                </p>
                <p>With kind regards,</p>
                <p>Yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Schroder</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="3" xml:id="d192fn3">Printed from a copy that indicates <persName
                                corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> signed the German language
                            original.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
