<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>216. Message From President Johnson to Prime Minister to Prime Minister
                    Wilson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d216</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">216</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-11-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-11-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="216"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                <head>216. Message From President <persName type="from">Johnson</persName> to Prime
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_WJH2" type="to">Wilson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d216fn1">Source: Department of State,
                        Presidential Correspondence: Lot 67 D 272. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis1"
                            >Nodis</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName> was
                        informed of the message in telegram 85292 to London, November 15.
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-11-15">November 15, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I am immensely heartened by your courageous announcement about joining the <gloss
                        target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss>. Your entry would certainly help to strengthen
                    and unify the West. If you find on the way that there is anything we might do to
                    smooth the path, I hope you will let me know.</p>
                <p>The report from <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">John McCloy</persName> on the
                    Trilateral talks is encouraging, despite the real difficulties we still face.
                        <persName corresp="#p_TGM1">Thomson</persName> made an excellent
                        contribution.<note n="2" xml:id="d216fn2">The second round of trilateral
                        talks took place at the Department of State November 9–10, with <persName
                            corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TGM1"
                            >Thomson</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Carstens</persName>
                        again representing their countries. In this round they discussed questions
                        of military capabilities, the defense burden, and the foreign exchange
                        problems resulting from the stationing of troops in Germany. Summaries of
                        the meetings were transmitted to Paris in telegrams 82537, 83122, and 83129,
                        November 10. (Ibid., Central Files, DEF 1 <gloss target="#t_EUR1"
                            >EUR</gloss> W) The text of an agreed tripartite minute, which outlined
                        the steps necessary to deter aggression, was transmitted to Paris in
                        telegram 83128, November 10. (Ibid., DEF 6 <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                            >NATO</gloss>) For text of the communique issued at the conclusion of
                        the second round, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                        December 6, 1966, p. 867.</note> I am hopeful that we can get a genuine
                    return from this exercise—militarily, politically and financially.</p>
                <p>The immediate snag, which <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Carstens</persName>
                    confirmed, is the inevitability of delay on the German side. While they can
                    fruitfully continue to work with us in the Trilateral Group, it would be
                    impossible for them to reach a responsible government position on these matters
                    in time to keep the present schedule. We should surely give the Germans a chance
                    to get themselves a government.</p>
                <pb facs="0522" n="492" xml:id="pg_492"/>
                <p>I know we agree that we must move together in order to maintain <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> as a credible deterrent and as a stabilizing
                    influence, especially in Germany. Your presence in Germany is as important to us
                    as your presence in the East, which I assume remains as we last discussed
                    it.</p>
                <p>I understand, as you know, the importance to you of being able to justify a
                    change in your announced program, in view of the pressures inherent in your
                    difficult but promising policies of economic adjustment. Would it help if I
                    placed in the United Kingdom in the near future $35 million in orders beyond
                    those already agreed to? I think I could do so on assurance from you that you
                    will stay with us and the Germans in completing this fundamental review of the
                    military, political and financial basis for the US–UK presence in Germany,
                    making no change in your troop and supply dispositions there until after the
                    completion of the review, and then that you will concert with us on any such
                    changes in the light of that review. This procurement would supplement the
                    accruals of dollars to you associated with the recent shift of our forces and
                    installations to Britain from the Continent.</p>
                <p>I may get some heat from Congress on this, and cannot move definitively until I
                    have talked it over with some of my people on the Hill. I think I can persuade
                    them to go along on the basis outlined here.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> and our government officials are
                    working on plans to handle deficits that result from the presence of our troops
                    abroad through a multilateral clearing arrangement that should help neutralize
                    balances, and contribute to an ultimate resolution of the monetary problem. That
                    may take some time to negotiate. If successful, such an arrangement should help
                    to satisfy some of our critics in Congress, and move the Germans to accept their
                    own proper responsibilities.</p>
                <p>I cannot stress too strongly the need for progress towards more equitable
                    patterns for dealing with the various responsibilities we all bear throughout
                    the world. As we both know, some of the criticism I get here on the subject is
                    justified. And, as you can imagine, the new Congress will not be easier to
                    persuade than its predecessor.</p>
                <p>I very much hope that the arrangements proposed here will help you to join us in
                    keeping this exercise on the tracks. Let us keep in close touch on this.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d216fn3">Printed from an unsigned copy.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
