<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-11-24T13:27:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-11-24T13:27:00-05:00" n="220" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d220">
                    <head>220. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in France</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d220fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, DEF 4
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Repeated to London and
                            Bonn.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-11-24T18:27:00+00:00">November 24, 1966,
                            1827Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>7885. During my call at the Elysee today I asked <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> if there was anything he could tell me as to his
                        view of France’s relationship to the Alliance and <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> in the coming years. He said he envisaged France’s
                        relations with <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> becoming “more and more
                        difficult” as time passed. He said the organization of the Alliance had been
                        set up to deal with the threat of war but it was not to be expected that
                        this semi-state of mobilization could be carried on when the threat of war
                        was visibly diminishing. However, he said that France would remain in the
                        Alliance since the danger had not been totally eliminated, and there was
                        also he added the question of Germany: it was preferable to have Germany
                        inside a Western Alliance. In his view however he felt that <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> as an organization would be progressively
                        weakened as time passed and as the danger receded. He repeated when I raised
                        again the question that France had no intention of withdrawing as matters
                        now stood in the world.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">
                                <hi rend="strong">Bohlen</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>