<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-04-06T16:13:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-04-06T16:13:00-05:00" n="245" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d245">
                    <head>245. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Mission to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and
                            European Regional Organizations</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d245fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> 8–2. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_GJI1">Getz</persName> and Palmer, cleared by <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> and
                                <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>, and approved by <persName corresp="#p_SGSJ1">Springsteen</persName>. Repeated to the other
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> capitals.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-04-06T16:13:00-05:00">April 6, 1967, 4:13 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>168946. <gloss target="#t_NATUS1">NATUS</gloss>. Joint State/Defense Message.
                        Subj: <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Consultation. Ref: (a) Paris
                        14574; (b) Paris 14402.<note n="2" xml:id="d245fn2">Telegram 14574, March
                            21, reported a discussion of consultation among the Fourteen. Telegram
                            14402, March 18, summarized <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Brosio</persName>’s views on consultation with France. (Both
                            ibid.)</note>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>This message deals first with question of French participation in
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> consultation and second with
                            further study of consultation and procedures.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>We believe that regardless of how one divides stages of phases of
                            consultation, general approach should be to encourage as much French
                            participation in consultation as possible. We concur your view that any
                            attempt get French to accept Athens Guidelines or other arrangements
                            made in NPG/<gloss target="#t_NDAC1">NDAC</gloss> would be exercise in
                            futility and might cause French and Fourteen unnecessary headaches.
                            There should be clear understanding among Fourteen that France would not
                            be allowed to <pb facs="0585" n="555" xml:id="pg_555"/> inhibit
                            discussions or decision-making at any point in time of consultation
                            cycle. Should France have different views from its Allies, the Fourteen
                            could note them and go on with the task at hand.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>This policy could also be applied to French participation in studies
                            on procedures for consultation. France could participate in studies to
                            the extent it desired but would not be allowed to impede the progress of
                            such studies. This of course implies <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>
                            as venue for studies, but we believe that Fourteen should first develop
                            an agreed position on dealing with possible French obstruction, e.g., be
                            prepared if French obstructionism develops to move studies back to
                                <gloss target="#t_DPC1">DPC</gloss>
                        </item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>We believe that it would be sufficient for Fourteen to reach agreement
                            on this general approach without further elaboration and without asking
                            the French for any assurances that they will not attempt to inhibit such
                            consultation.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Foregoing comments should not be interpreted as disagreement with your
                            procedural suggestion in para 8 of Paris 14402. We agree that major
                            effort should be to: (1) make concrete improvements in Alliance’s
                            consultation capability, and (2) utilize this capability more fully. We
                            also agree that prolonged study of consultation in the abstract is not
                            very promising. However, we understand some other Allies and <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Brosio</persName> value such studies more highly
                            than does the US. We do not wish to create impression by taking strong
                            stand against further studies that US either lukewarm about consultation
                            or reneging on Ministerial commitment. We, therefore, agree that if
                            strong sentiment develops for pursuing study tasks set forth in <gloss target="#t_DPC1">DPC</gloss>/D(66)32<note n="3" xml:id="d245fn3">Not
                                found.</note> further, US should acquiesce.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>We recall that Ministerial decision on follow-up studies was that
                                <gloss target="#t_DPC1">DPC</gloss> in permanent session would
                            decide which body should carry out these studies (para 1C Paris
                                9137).<note n="4" xml:id="d245fn4">Telegram 9137, December 15, 1966,
                                summarized a session of the <gloss target="#t_DPC1">DPC</gloss> on
                                December 14. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> 3
                                FR(PA))</note> We believe such studies could be undertaken by either
                                <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> or the <gloss target="#t_DPC1">DPC</gloss>. Where subject matter is appropriate, NPG or <gloss target="#t_NDAC1">NDAC</gloss> could take cognizance. Specifically,
                            NPG is charged with developing plans and procedures for reaching crisis
                            decisions involving potential or actual use of nuclear weapons (e.g.,
                            host country consultation). Other studies should attempt not to
                            duplicate this effort.</item>
                    </list>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                                <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>