<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>43. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Germany</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-10-29T20:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-10-29T20:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-10-29T20:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-10-29T20:30:00-05:00" n="43"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                <head>43. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Germany</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d43fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, DEF(<gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss>). Secret; Priority; <gloss
                            target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Drafted by Thomas M. Judd (<gloss
                            target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_BNA1">BNA</gloss>),
                        cleared by <persName corresp="#p_TWR2">Tyler</persName>, and approved and
                        initialed by <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>. Also sent to
                        London, Moscow, Paris for the Ambassador and <persName corresp="#p_FTK1"
                            >Finletter</persName>, and Rome.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-10-29T20:30:00-05:00">October 29, 1964, 8:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1251. <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss>. Following <gloss target="#t_Noforn1"
                        >Noforn</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss> only, is summary
                    discussion <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> nuclear matters and <gloss
                        target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> during talks British Foreign Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_GWPC1">Patrick Gordon Walker</persName> had with
                    Secretary, Under Secretary, and other officials October 26–27.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d43fn2">Memoranda of <persName corresp="#p_GWPC1">Gordon
                            Walker</persName>’s conversations are ibid., Conference Files: Lot 66 D
                        110, CF 2439–2440.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0124" n="94" xml:id="pg_94"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GWPC1">Gordon Walker</persName> emphasized what he had to
                    say represented preliminary thinking Labor Government and should not be regarded
                    as concrete proposals. Labor recognized time had come for decision on nuclear
                    matters within alliance and <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> had no intention
                    create delay. He thought by time of anticipated <persName corresp="#p_WJH2"
                        >Wilson</persName> visit to U.S. <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> would
                    be prepared for more definitive discussion.</p>
                <p>What <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> was thinking of was, <persName
                        corresp="#p_GWPC1">Gordon Walker</persName> said, a larger nuclear force
                    consisting of British V-bombers, British Polaris submarines, if <gloss
                        target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> decided to buy a certain number of them (three
                    or four), an equivalent number of American Polaris submarines, and a
                    mixed-manned element (<gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss>), which would play a
                    less conspicuous role than originally planned. UK element would be committed
                    unconditionally with no “national interest” withdrawal clause. Whole force would
                    be co-targeted with U.S. national nuclear deterrent. Britain would like veto in
                    new force but considered American veto essential.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GWPC1">Gordon Walker</persName> went on to say <gloss
                        target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> would prefer not to participate in mixed-manned
                        <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> element of proposed new force except
                    perhaps on token basis. He thought Labor Government would be able to cope with
                    political opposition in UK to <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> if <gloss
                        target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> part larger force. On other hand, Labor was
                    opposed to <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> as isolated step and would be
                    most unhappy if U.S. went ahead alone with Germany on <gloss target="#t_MLF1"
                        >MLF</gloss>. <persName corresp="#p_GWPC1">Gordon Walker</persName> also
                    repeatedly stressed his conviction that Germany would not be satisfied for long
                    with participation in <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> unless it part of
                    larger force he had outlined.</p>
                <p>Secretary and Under Secretary in turn emphasized our aim was to draw Germany
                    permanently to West. While there was little present German insistence on nuclear
                    capability, future pressures could bring about dangerous change in German
                    attitude unless solution reached which Germany could reconcile with her national
                    interest. <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> would give Germany both
                    propinquity to weapons and share in control which should satisfy German
                    aspirations for long time to come. Our preliminary reaction was that even though
                    UK were to commit its Polaris submarines to proposed new force, this would fall
                    short of minimum degree participation by UK required. Failure UK participate
                    substantially in <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> could be taken by Germans
                    as form of discrimination—<gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> was considered by
                    British as being good enough for Germany but not good enough for UK.</p>
                <p>Exchange of views between <persName corresp="#p_GWPC1">Gordon Walker</persName>
                    and U.S. officials did not clarify exact reason Labor Government’s opposition to
                    British participation in mixed-manned element. Both financial and political
                    considerations were mentioned by <persName corresp="#p_GWPC1">Gordon
                        Walker</persName>. Point he stressed most repeatedly as real problem with
                        <gloss target="#t_MLF1">MLF</gloss> was that it would not satisfy Germany in
                    long run.</p>
                <pb facs="0125" n="95" xml:id="pg_95"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GWPC1">Gordon Walker</persName> agreed at end of
                    conversation that it was highly desirable that initiative for creation of new
                    force, if British decided to put forth firm proposals, should come from UK and
                    Germany, rather than U.S. and UK. No direct or implied commitment was made
                    either by U.S. or UK participants in view mutual recognition UK thinking still
                    tentative. Secretary welcomed “ferment of ideas” on nuclear matters taking place
                    in Labor Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Ball</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
