<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-06-21T20:19:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-06-21T20:19:00-05:00" n="91" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d91">
                    <head>91. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d91fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, DEF 4 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>. Drafted and approved by
                                <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-06-21T21:19:00-04:00">June 21, 1965, 9:19 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>6571. For Ambassador from Under Secretary. Ref: <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 7218.<note n="2" xml:id="d91fn2">In telegram 7218, June
                            21, received in the Department of State at 10:50 a.m., <persName corresp="#p_BCE2">Bohlen</persName> “seriously” hoped that <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> would be “very prudent” in his
                            bilateral discussions on the state of the Alliance during his
                            presentation to the North Atlantic Council in July. The Ambassador also
                            expressed his feeling that the United States might not be far enough
                            along in its own thinking to have profitable discussions. (Ibid.)</note>
                        I do not contemplate imprudence.</p>
                    <p>We had a useful first conversation with Lord Hood with regard to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> problems and he expressed a willingness
                        to meet me in Paris for further conversation. I hope to have exploratory and
                        totally non-committal conversations with other representatives who may come
                        from other capitals for the meeting of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Council. I shall also tell <persName corresp="#p_CMMC1">Couve</persName>, if I see him, that we are of course looking forward
                        to any proposals the French Government may put forward regarding the
                        revision of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> although I understand the
                        government is not expecting to make such moves until next year.</p>
                    <p>The position of the United States Government at the moment is that we do not
                        have definitively formulated views but are simply soliciting the suggestions
                        of other governments in a very preliminary manner.</p>
                    <p>I do not expect this matter to get into the public domain to any great
                        extent. In the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> session we held last
                        March we were successful in maintaining a high degree of security.<note n="3" xml:id="d91fn3">Documentation on <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>’s presentation to the North Atlantic Council March
                            31–April 1 on various international problems is ibid., Conference Files:
                            Lot 66 D 347, CF 2484.</note> If, however, the French Government hears
                        rumors that we may be talking about the Alliance, tant pis.</p>
                    <p>On basis our talks today with UK, German and Italian Embassies here and with
                            <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">Brosio</persName> through <persName corresp="#p_FTK1">Finletter</persName>, probability is that <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting <pb facs="0251" n="221" xml:id="pg_221"/> will take place on July 13 instead of July 7;
                        bilaterals would be scheduled for July 12 and possibly morning of 14th. This
                        might enable participation of Schroeder and <persName corresp="#p_FTK1">Fanfani</persName> at <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                        discussions, which important in its own right. I have definite impression
                        that both Foreign Ministers wish handle bilaterals themselves.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                                <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>