<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Chile ( (Collier))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1926v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d305</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">305</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1926-06-01T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1926-06-01T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-06-01T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-06-01T12:00:00-05:00" n="305"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d305">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">723.2515/2380: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Collier</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-06-01T13:00:00-04:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 1, 1926—1 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>99. Your No. 182, May 30, 5 p.m.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>All factors required for dealing with whole problem in some definite way
                        now seem to be before us. <pb facs="0587" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>We have received reasonably complete reports covering actual
                                conditions affecting plebiscite. These reports have been carefully
                                reviewed and analyzed here. Mr. Stimson’s conclusions accord
                                entirely with views you and General Lassiter have expressed. … Among
                                persons who are in position to form unbiased opinion on facts, I
                                have not been able to find any difference of opinion. Conclusion on
                                issue of frustration is unanimous, outside Chilean circles.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Respective positions of Chile and Peru on subject of settlement by
                                negotiation have now been defined with practical certainty. Peru
                                will accept neutralization or a bona fide Bolivian-corridor
                                solution, and would possibly agree to transfer of entire disputed
                                territory to Bolivia on terms to be arranged. On other hand Chile
                                has indicated that she will not consider any solution which does not
                                look to a division of the territory by which the bulk would be
                                assigned to her, comprising everything that could be utilized for a
                                corridor; thus she would be left free to make her own bargain with
                                Bolivia. This attitude, which has been firmly maintained, absolutely
                                blocks road to a negotiated settlement.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Plebiscitary process has reached stage where it must be dealt with
                                decisively. General Lassiter can no longer pursue Fabian policy
                                without gravest consequences. He is insisting daily, with a
                                justification which I cannot deny, that final program be outlined at
                                once. His position has come to be virtually impossible. Action on
                                his part is a matter of days, not of weeks. It must be realized that
                                General Lassiter, as chairman of the Plebiscitary Commission, has
                                his own heavy responsibilities. I do not have right to dictate to
                                him. There are some things which I can not conscientiously ask him
                                to do, and there are some things which it is probable that he would
                                refuse to do if I made the request. General Lassiter has shown
                                utmost patience and a disposition to cooperate, but I am bound to
                                recognize that there is limit beyond which he cannot go; he has just
                                about arrived at that limit.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>It is amid these circumstances that you file an urgent plea for at least
                        three weeks’ additional time and you request me to issue pronouncements
                        which are boldly calculated to influence public opinion in Chile and thus to
                        force modification of Government attitude. I can guarantee nothing as far as
                        time is concerned. It is my honest guess that final crisis at Arica cannot
                        be delayed beyond this week and it may come any moment. Edwards has already
                        notified General Lassiter that he proposes to press issue for determination
                        during present week. Undoubtedly he is acting under instructions. In matter
                        of public statements, I am obliged to enforce distinction between statements
                        of fact that you are to issue for purpose of correcting misunderstanding or
                        misrepresentation of acts of this Government, and <pb facs="0588" n="456"
                            xml:id="pg_456"/> statements the only justification for which is to
                        bring indirect pressure to bear on Government of Chile. The authorized
                        statement which you issued to the press on May 31<note n="9"
                            xml:id="d305fn9">Not printed. Ambassador Collier was authorized to issue
                            a personal statement on the declarations made between Sept. 1925 and May
                            1926 by the Chilean Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Under Secretary
                            which expressed a desire for settlement outside the plebiscite.</note>
                        falls within first category. I am not disposed to go further, and I feel
                        strongly that to go over the head of the Chilean Government and appeal to
                        Chilean public is procedure which cannot be defended no matter how desirable
                        end sought may be. I am inclined, however, to approve your suggestion with
                        reference to Secretary Hoover, and I shall take up matter with him at
                        once.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>There is only one way whereby Chile can avoid disastrous consequences
                        otherwise inevitable, and that is (1) by instructing Edwards to arrange with
                        General Lassiter to hold up issue on plebiscite, and then (2) by modifying
                        her intransigent attitude in the negotiations here in Washington. The
                        Government of Chile will have to take both these measures quickly or it will
                        have to accept full responsibility for consequences.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>A message just received from General Lassiter<note n="10"
                            xml:id="d305fn10">Telegram of May 31, 10 p.m.; not printed.</note>
                        states that Edwards has requested meeting of Plebiscitary Commission at
                        earliest possible moment to fix date of election.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kellogg</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
