<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-05-23T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-05-23T01:00:00-05:00" n="573" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d573">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/7411: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-05-23T14:00:00+08:00"><hi rend="italic">May 23,
                                        1926—2 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received May 23—10: 30
                                a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>226. 1. Department’s 104, May 21, 1 p.m., greatly appreciated, I shall
                            inform the press that Mayer is proceeding to Canton under instructions
                            from the Secretary of State of the United States to consult with the
                            American consulates in South China in regard to the situation in that
                            region where a number of recent outrages against Americans and their
                            interests have caused increasing concern to the American Government.</p>
                        <p>2. [Paraphrase.] I also think Mayer should be instructed, but not for
                            publication, that, although his mission is chiefly for the purpose of
                            personal contact between the Legation and the consuls general at Canton
                            and Hongkong, he should use any opportunity that seems favorable to tell
                            the Canton officials that we cannot understand their attitude regarding
                            foreigners in general and Americans in particular, which we believe to
                            be inexcusable from the point of view of justice and international
                            friendship. Should there be an appropriate opportunity I think that
                            Mayer could, with advantage, try to impress upon the Canton officials
                            the unfortunate effect upon public opinion in the United States which
                            their treatment of American citizens is having, pointing out that
                            American sentiment has hitherto been very favorable to the Chinese and
                            particularly to the Cantonese who comprise the greater part of the
                            Chinese residents in America.</p>
                        <p>3. To avoid possible misinterpretations, Mayer will go to Canton without
                            stopping at Hongkong on the way, but will stop there for several days on
                            his way back, giving an opportunity for him to have informal
                            conversations with Hongkong officials. I suggest that Tredwell be given
                            instructions to cooperate in every way with Mayer and to go to Canton to
                            confer with Mayer and Jenkins, if and when Mayer so requests him. It
                            would be well to have Chamberlain<note n="8" xml:id="d573fn8">Culver
                                Bryant Chamberlain, vice consul at Swatow.</note> also present at
                            any such conference and I request that he be authorized <pb facs="0841" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/> to go to Canton for a brief visit, unless
                            the exigencies of the situation at Swatow prevent it. [End
                            paraphrase.]</p>
                        <p>4. In order that Mayer’s mission may be expedited and conducted in the
                            most economical manner, it may prove desirable for him to use naval
                            transportation between Tientsin and Shanghai, or vice versa. I
                            respectfully suggest that the Navy Department be requested to authorize
                            the commander in chief of the United States Asiatic Fleet to cooperate
                            with the Legation in every way practicable. I am informing the commander
                            in chief of Mayer’s [apparent omission] as well as Canton, Shanghai and
                            Hongkong.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>