<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1926v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d644</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">644</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1926-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1926-09-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019102796"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Boycott</term>
                    <term ref="recBIWbnPJBWQERtR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-09-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-09-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="644"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d644">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A4e/652</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Memoire</hi>
                </p>
                <p>His Majesty’s Government have noted with great interest the correspondence that
                    has passed recently between the Minister for Foreign Affairs of the Canton
                    Government on the one part, and the United States Consul-General at Canton and
                    the United States Minister at Peking on the other in regard to the proceedings
                    of the Chinese Customs Tariff Conference and other matters relating to the
                    status of the Canton Government.</p>
                <p>Copies of this correspondence were published in the <hi rend="italic">Peking and
                        Tientsin Times</hi> of the 21st July and in the <hi rend="italic">Hong Kong
                        Daily Press</hi> of the 5th July last, and consist in a telegram sent
                    apparently on July 20th by Mr. Eugene Chen to the American Minister at
                        Peking<note n="21" xml:id="d644fn21">Apparently refers to note of July 14
                        from the Chinese Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs at Canton to the
                        American consul general, <ref target="#pg_844">p. 844</ref>.</note> and in
                    Mr. MacMurray’s reply thereto,<note n="22" xml:id="d644fn22">See despatch No.
                        298, July 24, from the Minister in China, <ref target="#pg_846">p.
                        846</ref>.</note> as also in a letter addressed on 30th June last by the
                    American Consul General at Canton to Mr. Eugene Chen and the latter’s reply
                    dated July 2nd.<note n="23" xml:id="d644fn23">See article from the <hi
                            rend="italic">Canton Gazette</hi>, July 5, 1926, <hi rend="italic"
                            >ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_669">p. 669</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>His Majesty’s Government are interested in this exchange of views not only
                    because they were participators with the United States Government in the tariff
                    negotiations at Peking, which have now been suspended until an undetermined date
                    in the autumn, but because they are themselves at present in negotiation with
                    the Canton authorities for the settlement of the boycott of British goods which,
                    for the past year, has caused very grave injury to the colony of Hong Kong and
                    British trade in general.</p>
                <p>It seems to them that this correspondence may indicate that the United States
                    Government may be considering such important questions as the position of the
                    Canton administration in regard to the central authority at Peking, the mutual
                    relations of the two bodies as affecting the work of the Tariff Conference, and
                    the prospects of that work in the future; and in view of the attitude of the
                    Canton Government <pb facs="0987" n="855" xml:id="pg_855"/> as revealed in Mr.
                    Eugene Chen’s communications, they would be glad to know what course the United
                    States Government intend to pursue as regards both the liquidation of the
                    promises made in the Washington Customs Tariff Treaty and the resumption of
                    general tariff negotiations, and on what footing they propose to treat with the
                    Canton Government in the future.</p>
                <p>His Majesty’s Ambassador would be grateful for any information that the Secretary
                    of State may be able to give in reply to this enquiry on the part of His
                    Majesty’s Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Manchester, Mass.</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-09-17">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 17, 1926</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received September 20.]</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
