<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in China ( (MacMurray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1926v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d734</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">734</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1926-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1926-07-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Allocations</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-07-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="734"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d734">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/4954</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-07-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 30, 1926</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received September 1.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 686</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    the Department’s instruction No. 232, of May 28, 1926,<note n="29"
                        xml:id="d734fn29">Not printed.</note> transmitting a copy of a letter dated
                    May 21, 1926, from the American Group of the Chinese Consortium in regard to the
                    use of revenues of the Chinese Maritime Customs.<note n="29" xml:id="d734fn28"
                        >Not printed.</note> The Department requested that I submit my comments by
                    telegraph. Although the Department in its telegraphic instruction No. 132, of
                    July 1, 5 p.m.,<note n="29" xml:id="d734fn27">Not printed.</note> indicated that
                    no comments were desired by telegraph in addition to those contained in my
                    telegram No. 242, of June 8, 1926, sent before the receipt of the present
                    despatch, I think it advisable to submit these additional observations by
                    mail.</p>
                <p>Referring to the memorandum of December 2, 1921, compiled by the Chinese
                    Secretary of the Legation,<note n="29" xml:id="d734fn26">Not printed.</note> on
                    the subject of the practice followed in effecting releases of surplus customs
                    revenue, I desire to state that Mr. Peck regrets that in this memorandum he
                    neglected to state that Article 6 of the Bankers Arrangement of 1912 was
                    cancelled by action taken at the Diplomatic Body meeting of April 7, <pb
                        facs="1086" n="954" xml:id="pg_954"/> 1913. In writing the memorandum he
                    consulted only the correspondence files of the Legation, which curiously enough,
                    contain no reference to this action. My own compilation of treaties was not
                    available to him and he neglected to search the files of Dean’s circulars, which
                    in the year 1913, were not routed through the Chinese Secretariat.</p>
                <p>The memorandum was correct in stating that the Chinese Government and the
                    interested Powers all have appeared at least to act on the assumption that the
                    Chinese Government was not privileged to utilize surplus customs revenues until
                    “released” by the Powers. Requests from the Government for such releases have
                    been made repeatedly, the last one as recently as July 14, 1926. (See Diplomatic
                    Circular No. 174, of July 20, 1926, a copy of which is attached hereto.<note
                        n="30" xml:id="d734fn30">Not printed.</note>) On occasion these requests
                    have been refused, and sometimes on grounds not connected with the service of
                    the specified obligations secured on the customs revenue—e. g., the identic note
                    to the Chinese Foreign Office of November 5, 1918, in which the reason given for
                    refusing the release was the continuance of civil war. (See the Legation’s
                    despatch D. No. 2318, November 6 [<hi rend="italic">8</hi>], 1918.<note n="30"
                        xml:id="d734fn25">Not printed.</note> It was this irregularity of procedure,
                    of course, which caused the Department to observe in its telegraphic instruction
                    No. 3, January 5, 1921,<note n="31" xml:id="d734fn31">
                        <ref target="frus1921v01#pg_494">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1921, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 494</ref>.</note> that it welcomed “the
                    opportunity to revert to a more regular procedure”.</p>
                <p>I do not understand that the Chinese Government itself has interposed any
                    sustained or strong objection to the manner in which, in practice, the Powers
                    have thus extended their quasi-control of the customs revenue under the 1912
                    arrangement. This control, or trusteeship, has necessarily been exercised
                    through Sir Francis Aglen, Inspector-General of Customs, since in the 1912
                    arrangement the Powers secured the consent of the Chinese Government that all
                    Maritime Customs revenues should be deposited to his credit. This arrangement
                    has given the Inspector-General an almost despotic power over this revenue—a
                    power which he wields solely by virtue of the support he receives from the
                    interested foreign Legations. The Chinese Government feels itself powerless to
                    dispense with Sir Francis so long as the British Legation and the other
                    Legations support him. As a general thing, I am convinced, the Government
                    appreciates to the full the unimpeachable integrity and devotion to Chinese
                    interests of the present Inspector-General, but there have been times when a
                    harassed Minister of Finance has been highly incensed at the point blank refusal
                    of the foreign Inspector-General to release funds to his order.</p>
                <pb facs="1087" n="955" xml:id="pg_955"/>
                <p>Until 1921 Sir Francis always met demands from the Government for customs funds
                    with the statement that the Government must first secure the consent of the
                    interested Legations. After the mandates of March, 1921, establishing the
                    consolidated internal loan service (devised by Sir Francis in consultation with
                    the late Mr. Chow Tzu-chi) he recognized the authority of those mandates,
                    although, in doing so, he did not consult the foreign Legations. In devoting to
                    the consolidated internal loan service the millions of customs revenue required
                    therefor, Sir Francis not only did not ask the consent of the Powers, but he
                    flatly denied any weight to their arguments as to the superior rights of senior
                    foreign loans. Yet, when it has been a question, since 1921, of petty
                    allocations for the support of plague prevention work, etc., the Chinese
                    Government, apparently at his insistence, has still asked the consent of the
                    Powers, just as it did before 1921. In this connection the Department’s
                    attention is invited to the Note of the Chinese Foreign Office dated July 14th,
                    enclosed herewith,<note n="32" xml:id="d734fn32">Not printed.</note> which
                    states quite frankly that the officiating Inspector-General replied to the
                    request for funds that “the consent must be obtained of the Foreign Ministers
                    concerned.”</p>
                <p>Sir Francis Aglen has undoubtedly met with great difficulty in conserving the
                    Customs revenue for the purpose of meeting the legal obligations of the Chinese
                    Government and for uses calculated to promote the Government’s own real welfare.
                    On a number of occasions the Chinese Government has attempted to secure
                    immediate use of funds allocated to the service of internal loans under the
                    terms of the Mandates of 1921. In these circumstances Sir Francis has insisted
                    that those terms be carried out and that the Government keep faith with the
                    bondholders. I understand that in defence of the internal loan service he is
                    guided by the belief that popular support of the Government will be increased by
                    widespread investment in Government bonds. There can be no doubt that his
                    announced support of these bonds has been the essential factor inducing the
                    Chinese public to purchase them, and that he feels keenly his moral duty toward
                    the purchasers. In furtherance of his policy, he wishes to add more issues to
                    the bonds thus secured. This leads him to reject the claims of previously
                    concluded foreign loans, as presented by the Legations. He is thus brought into
                    conflict with the very Governments upon whose support he is entirely dependent
                    for his control over Customs funds, as given to him by the 1912 Bankers’
                    Agreement. (MacMurray’s <hi rend="italic">China Treaties</hi>, page 946.)</p>
                <p>Adverting once more to the Foreign Office Note of July 14, 1926, I have the honor
                    to state that I pointed out to my colleagues in an observation placed on the
                    circular what appeared to me to be an important principle involved in the
                    continuing nature of the allocation <pb facs="1088" n="956" xml:id="pg_956"/> to
                    which assent was requested. The same principle is raised in the hypothecation of
                    the customs revenues for the service of bonds. I venture to quote below the
                    observation to which I have referred: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The note of July 14 from the Wai Chiao Pu introduces an innovation which
                            appears to me to be fundamental, in that it requests not merely the
                            release of an ascertainable balance but a commitment to assent to
                                releases<note n="33" xml:id="d734fn33">$50,000 monthly, beginning
                                from July 1926.</note> month by month for an indefinite period,
                            without the possibility of foreseeing whether the balance requested will
                            be available in any given month in the future. In my understanding of
                            the matter, so long as the 1912 agreement remains in effect, the body of
                            interested Ministers have a fiduciary obligation to assure that the
                            indemnities and specified loan services are duly met; and although they
                            have no discretion as to the uses to which the Chinese Government may
                            put any balances in excess of the funds necessary for the indemnity and
                            loan services, it is their function to assure that no releases are made
                            until satisfied of the existence of such surplus at the time. I cannot
                            escape a feeling that by consenting to the present request they would
                            vitiate this principle and forego what is both a right and a duty to
                            protect the security of the indemnities and foreign loans specifically
                            charged upon the customs revenue.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It is an unlooked for situation that has now arisen out of the international
                    action taken in 1912. The Powers acquired, and still exercise, a trusteeship
                    over the whole customs revenue, but in respect to obligations that require only
                    a portion of the whole. In regard to the disposition of the remainder, they have
                    informed the Chinese Government most emphatically that they exercise no control
                    whatsoever. They have, in fact, latterly refused even to express an opinion as
                    to the way that it should be used. But at the same time they continue to insist
                    upon an arrangement that places the control of this surplus in the hands of a
                    particular officer of the Government of foreign nationality.</p>
                <p>The Department will have noted in the Senior Minister’s memorandum to the Chinese
                    Foreign Office of May 12, 1926<note n="34" xml:id="d734fn34">See telegram No.
                        114, June 4, to the Minister in China, <ref target="#pg_948">p.
                        948</ref>.</note> (see Diplomatic Circular No. 118, of the same date<note
                        n="35" xml:id="d734fn35">Not printed.</note>) a statement that the
                    interested Heads of Legation “do not desire to interfere with any arrangement
                    arrived at between the Chinese Government and the Inspector-General of Customs
                    with regard to the disposal of this surplus revenue”. The original draft of this
                    communication was presented by the British Minister in accordance with
                    suggestions given him, as I understand, by Sir Francis Aglen. At any rate my
                    British Colleague observed at the meeting of the interested Ministers that he
                    thought it would strengthen the hands of the Inspector-General. In deference to
                    the unanimous judgment of my colleagues, I concurred in the draft; but when the
                    Senior Minister proposed inserting the same <pb facs="1089" n="957"
                        xml:id="pg_957"/> phraseology in a similar memorandum to the Foreign Office
                    in the following month, I suggested that its inclusion was unnecessary, and my
                    suggestion was adopted. (See Diplomatic Circular No. 142, of June 11th, and
                    copies of observations placed thereon.<note n="35a" xml:id="d734fn35a">Not
                        printed.</note>)</p>
                <p>It may be questioned whether, if the Protocol Powers were to follow to its
                    logical conclusion their present announced policy of leaving the Chinese
                    Government free to dispose of the surplus customs revenue at its will, they
                    should not announce to the Government their willingness to limit the
                    applicability of the 1912 Bankers’ Agreement to that portion of the customs
                    revenue required for the service of foreign obligations specifically secured
                    thereon. That done, there would remain no means of foreign pressure to prevent
                    the Chinese Government from restoring, to a large extent, if it so desired, the
                    conditions existing before 1911, when the Inspector-General of Customs had no
                    control over customs revenue, but was merely the head of the collecting agency.
                    I do not suggest that it would be advisable to withdraw international support
                    from the Inspector-General in this way; on the other hand, in view of
                    arrangements now in contemplation for debt consolidation and purposes similarly
                    requiring definite security upon customs revenues, I am definitely of the
                    opinion that it would be preferable to insist that the control of those revenues
                    should remain in the hands of such a foreign official. I have invited the
                    Department’s attention to this point principally because it seems to supply the
                    only discernible basis for the impression that prevails with many Chinese, and
                    some foreigners, that the foreign Legations control the Maritime Customs
                    revenue.</p>
                <p>Incidentally I may remark that some inconsistency is to be found in the fact that
                    in China it is the British Minister who wishes to “strengthen the hands of the
                    Inspector-General” (British), while among the foreign governments it is the
                    British Government that has expressed most anxiety not to overload the customs
                    revenue with foreign obligations, and not to appear to increase foreign control
                    over that revenue.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">J. V. A. MacMurray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
