<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-02-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="818" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d818">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.74/661</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Major General <persName type="from">James G.
                                    Harbord</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                        York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-02-11"><hi rend="italic">February 11,
                                    1926</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received February
                            12.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I acknowledge the
                            receipt of your letter of February 9th,<note n="49" xml:id="d818fn49">Not printed.</note> enclosing the views of Colonel Davis<note n="49a" xml:id="d818fn49a">See telegram No. 25, Jan. 14, from the
                                Minister in China, <ref target="#pg_1045">p. 1045</ref>.</note>
                            regarding the proposal of the Japanese Government that the present
                            controversy regarding radio matters in China be settled by adopting the
                            Japanese proposal of the radio consortium.</p>
                        <p>Colonel Davis has very clearly stated the arguments against a consortium.
                            It is unnecessary, possibly ungrateful, to reiterate our hope that the
                            State Department will push this matter to a conclusion at a very early
                            date. Our loyalty to its position on the “Open Door” has cost us already
                            half a million dollars in money paid out, which sum is increasing by a
                            little less than $9,000 each month. We are quite convinced that a
                            consortium for wireless communication in China would be very much better
                            for China than no wireless communication at all. We very much appreciate
                            the earnest support which our Federal project has in the past had from
                            the State Department, and respectfully urge that there be no relaxation
                            in such support. We do feel, however, that the moment the State
                            Department becomes convinced that there is no likelihood of the Chinese
                            going forward with our contract, no political objection to a consortium
                            should be allowed to stand in the way of our making such arrangements as
                            have been open to us for a long time.</p>
                        <p>I note that you desire Mr. Brown or myself to come to see you when in
                            Washington, in order to talk these matters over. Thank you for the
                            invitation, and it will be accepted at the first opportunity.</p>
                        <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. G. Harbord</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>