<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State ( (Olds))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1926v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">98</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1926-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1926-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1926-02-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1926-02-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="98"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d98">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">462.11 W 892/663</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Olds</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1926-02-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 3, 1926</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The German Ambassador came in this afternoon at my invitation and I discussed
                    with him the possibility of reaching some general agreement for the final
                    disposition of all outstanding claims of a <pb facs="0258" n="126"
                        xml:id="pg_126"/> pecuniary nature against Germany. I pointed out that in
                    the first place there is a certain amount of unfinished business pending before
                    the Mixed Claims Commission.<note n="19" xml:id="d98fn19">Set up under the
                        agreement of Aug. 10, 1922, between the United States and Germany; see <ref
                            target="frus1922v02#pg_240">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1922, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 240</ref> ff.</note> This includes
                    certain claims known as the sabotage claims. A second large class of claims is
                    those pending in the Department which have never been sent to the Mixed Claims
                    Commission because they were filed subsequent to the date fixed by the Executive
                    Agreement, and, therefore, do not fall within the jurisdiction of the Commission
                    as it is defined at present.</p>
                <p>I suggested the desirability of making some arrangement for prompt disposition of
                    both classes of claims. With respect to the claims already before the
                    Commission, the only complication arises from the Black Tom and other cases
                    known as the sabotage claims. For obvious reasons it would be embarrassing to
                    have these cases go to trial, and I expressed the hope that a way might be found
                    to settle them without trial.</p>
                <p>With respect to the claims which were filed too late for presentation to the
                    Commission under the Executive Agreement, I pointed out that these claims were
                    apparently not barred by the provisions of the treaty and that there is
                    considerable doubt as to whether they could be effectually barred by an
                    executive agreement not ratified by the Senate.</p>
                <p>In conclusion I asked the Ambassador whether he had seen a draft of a proposed
                    agreement on this whole subject which had been prepared, and as I understood it,
                    approved by the American and German Agents.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador seemed to be entirely familiar with the situation. He first dealt
                    with the sabotage claims, stating that whatever else Germany may have been
                    responsible for in the way of violations of neutrality prior to our entrance
                    into the war, she was not responsible for these particular claims. He was
                    prepared to admit that a trial of these sabotage cases would be unfortunate.
                    Nevertheless, he was advised by his Government that it was ready to prove
                    absolutely that Germany was not responsible, and he was sure that his Government
                    would not entertain any suggestion by which Germany would be called upon, even
                    by implication, to admit liability. I inquired whether it might not be possible
                    to include the sabotage claims with the late claims and others in an omnibus
                    award. The Ambassador finally agreed that this would be worth considering.</p>
                <p>Passing to the late claims, the Ambassador insisted that they were barred by the
                    Executive Agreement and that if Germany was to admit them now she ought to have
                    some compensation. This brought us to the real point of the discussion.
                    According to the Ambassador, Germany will make no agreement covering the late
                    claims or the sabotage <pb facs="0259" n="127" xml:id="pg_127"/> claims or
                    anything else which is not contingent upon the return of the alien property fund
                    to its German owners. The Ambassador was emphatic on this subject. He said he
                    would be willing, of course, to put up any proposal that might be made, but he
                    was perfectly sure that an unconditional agreement covering the American claims
                    would have absolutely no chance of approval by his Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>R[<hi rend="smallcaps">obert</hi>] E. O[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >lds</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
