<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>EXHIBIT G.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1902app1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d126</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">126</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1893-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1893-01-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1893-01-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1893-01-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="126"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d126">
                <head>EXHIBIT G.</head>
                <p>The memorial of Claus Lutjens, commonly known and called by the name of Charles
                    Lutjens, to the Department of State of the United States, respectfully
                    shows:</p>
                <p>That the said Claus Lutjens makes this claim and memorial in his own right and
                    for his own benefit;</p>
                <p>That the above-named Claus Lutjens is now, and was at the time when the claim
                    hereinafter set forth had its origin, a duly naturalized citizen of the United
                    States, and presents herewith a duly certified copy of his naturalization
                    papers, and a duly qualified and registered voter in the city and county of San
                    Francisco, State of California;</p>
                <p>The said Claus Lutjens claims from the Russian Government the sum of $10,000,
                    being the entire sum hereby claimed; the claimant believes that the sum so
                    claimed would not reimburse him for the losses sustained by the wrongful act of
                    the authorities of the Russian Government, hereinafter set forth; and that this
                    claimant has received no money or other equivalent or indemnification from
                    insurance or otherwise for the whole or any part of the loss or injury upon
                    which this claim is founded.</p>
                <p>That the said claim is based upon the following facts and circumstances, to
                    wit:</p>
                <p>The said Claus Lutjens, in the pursuit of his regular and legitimate business,
                    was at all the times herein mentioned the owner of the American schooner <hi
                        rend="italic">Kate and Anna</hi>, which said schooner was enrolled and
                    registered in the port of San Francisco, and said schooner was regularly cleared
                    from said port for a fishing and hunting voyage in the North Pacific Ocean, or
                    elsewhere, as the master might direct, having at the time on board said vessel a
                    hunting and fishing outfit, consisting of rifles, shotguns, powder, and hunting
                    and fishing gear, all of which will more fully and at large appear by the
                    certified copies of the original enrollment or registry of said schooner and
                    certified copies of the original clearance papers and outward manifest of said
                    schooner, which are herewith filed, and that the reason why the originals of all
                    of said papers were and are not filed is that all of said original papers were
                    and are in the United States custom-house at San Francisco, Cal.</p>
                <p>That said Claus Lutjens, owner of said American schooner <hi rend="italic">Kate
                        and Anna</hi> as above set forth, was then, and at all the times hereinafter
                    mentioned, the duly acting and qualified master of said schooner, and is now and
                    was at the time when the claim herein set forth had its origin a citizen of the
                    United States of America and of the State of California; that the said schooner
                        <hi rend="italic">Kate and Anna</hi> on the 1st day of March, A. D. 1892,
                    under command of the said master, and with a good and sufficient crew and a
                    hunting and fishing outfit on board, as aforesaid, did set sail and depart from
                    the said port of San Francisco, bound for the North Pacific Ocean, said vessel
                    being <pb facs="0298" n="276" xml:id="pg_276"/> at that time and at all the
                    times hereinafter mentioned seaworthy and in all respects fit for the voyage
                    which it took as herein mentioned; that the master and crew proceeded with said
                    vessel on their voyage without disaster of any kind until the 12th day of
                    August, A. D. 1892, and that prior to said day and in the open Pacific Ocean,
                    more than 30 miles south of the Commander Islands, and not in Russian waters,
                    had killed and taken 124 seals, worth in the open market $1,767, all of which
                    were caught and killed on the voyage from San Francisco, and more than 30 miles
                    south of the Commander Islands, and not in Russian waters; and that on said 12th
                    day of August arrived at 54° 9′ north, longitude 168° 21′ east, by correct
                    observation, and had not sealed in said place, nor at any place within 30 miles
                    south of said Commander Islands or in Russian waters at all, and no boats being
                    out at said time from said vessel, either for hunting or fishing, and no one
                    from said vessel being either hunting or fishing, and said schooner then sailing
                    in a southwesterly course.</p>
                <p>Said latitude 54° 9′ north, longitude 168° 21′ east, by correct observation is
                    more than 30 miles from Copper or Bering Islands on the high seas, and not in
                    Russian waters; when, at said time, and in the latitude and longitude above
                    mentioned, on the 12th day of August, A. D, 1892, as aforesaid, and not being at
                    the time hunting or fishing, and not having at any time fished or hunted seals
                    in Russian waters, but being at said time on a southwesterly course, as
                    aforesaid, the Russian war cruiser <hi rend="italic">Zabiaca</hi> was at all
                    times herein mentioned a steamer regularly commissioned as a war cruiser, and
                    belonging to the Russian Government, armed for offensive and defensive warfare,
                    and acting under the authority and by the directions of the said Russian
                    Government, steamed toward said schooner and fired a blank charge, which was an
                    order for said schooner to heave-to. I accordingly heaved-to, and said cruiser
                    steamed alongside said schooner, and I was ordered to come on board the cruiser
                    with the schooner’s papers; I accordingly went on board with my papers, showed
                    my log book and other papers to the captain of said cruiser, who then ordered me
                    to send my sealskins to said cruiser, to stop sealing, and to go home. I then,
                    under said orders, and being forced to do so by said cruiser, sent on board said
                    cruiser 124 sealskins; and being then fearful of arrest and confiscation of my
                    schooner by said cruiser, I stopped sealing and sailed for San Francisco, at
                    which port I arrived on the 23d day of September, A. D. 1893.</p>
                <p>While on board said cruiser <hi rend="italic">Zabiaca</hi> the captain thereof
                    wrote in my log book the following, to wit:</p>
                <p>“Schooner <hi rend="italic">Kate and Anna</hi> was arrested in 54° 9′ north
                    latitude and 168° 21′ longitude, though not in Russian waters exactly, but she
                    has been sealing at the sealing grounds of Commander Islands. The con traverse
                    could not be witnessed by the log book, so the seals are confiscated, but the
                    vessel was not taken, and got free.</p>
                <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">B. de Livron</hi>,<lb/>”<hi rend="italic"
                        >Captain of H. S. M. Russian Cruiser ‘Zabiaca.’</hi>
                </p>
                <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">August</hi> 12, 1892.”</p>
                <p>My original log book, containing said writing by said Russian captain, is now in
                    my possession, and will be produced by me in support hereof when required.</p>
                <p>By said wrongful seizure by the Russian cruiser <hi rend="italic">Zabiaca</hi>,
                    as aforesaid, I have been damaged as follows, to wit: In the sum of $1,767,
                    United States gold coin, by the seizure of the 124 seal skins above set forth,
                    and in the sum of $8,233, United States gold coin, by the breaking up of my
                    voyage from the threats and wrongful armed interference of said Russian war
                    cruiser <hi rend="italic">Zabiaca.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That I, as master of said schooner, <hi rend="italic">Kate and Anna</hi>, duly
                    protested at the time to the captain of said Russian war cruiser against the
                    seizure of said seal skins, and against all the other acts herein complained of;
                    that on the 18th day of October, A. D. 1892, I duly noted a protest against said
                    seizure and said acts with Harry J. Lask, a notary public in and for the city
                    and county of San Francisco, State of California; and on said day, before said
                    notary public, I duly made a regular marine protest.</p>
                <p>That the seizure of said seal skins and all of said acts by the said war cruiser,
                    by the officers thereof, and by the Russian officials, were in violation of the
                    law of nations and of the right of citizens of the United States, and in
                    contravention to the treaties existing between the United States of America and
                    Russia, and that this claim is founded upon the principles of international law
                    and the rights which every nation and every person has upon the high seas, and
                    upon the fact that all the above mentioned acts by the Russian Government and
                    its officials were in violation thereof.</p>
                <p>Wherefore I hereby request the interposition of the Government of the United
                    States of America against the Russian Government for the presentation of this
                    claim against said Russian Government.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">In witness whereof the above-named claimant has
                        subscribed his name and affixed his seal to this memorial <date
                            calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-28">this 28th day of January, A. D.
                            1893</date>.</dateline>
                    <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Claus Lutjens</hi>.</signed> [<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >seal.</hi>]</closer>
                <pb facs="0299" n="277" xml:id="pg_277"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">State of California</hi>, <hi rend="italic">City and
                            County of San Francisco, ss:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Claus Lutjens, being duly sworn, says: My true name is Claus Lutjens,
                        although I am sometimes known and designated by the name of Charles
                        Lutjens.</p>
                    <p>I am the person making and subscribing the above memorial to the Department
                        of State.</p>
                    <p>I have read the foregoing memorial, and know the contents thereof; it is true
                        of my own knowledge except as to those matters which are therein stated on
                        information and belief, and as to those matters I believe it to be true.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Claus Lutjens.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Subscribed and sworn to by the said Claus
                            Lutjens, known to me to be a credible witness, before me, <date
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-28">this 28th day of January, A.
                                D. 1893</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <seg rendition="#left">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</seg>
                        <signed rendition="#right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Harry J. Lask</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Notary public in and for the City and County of San
                                Francisco, State of California.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">State of California</hi>, <hi rend="italic">City and
                            County of San Francisco, ss:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I, M. C. Haley, county clerk of the city and county of San Francisco, State
                        of California, and ex officio clerk of the superior court thereof (which
                        court is a court of record, having a seal), do hereby certify that Harry J.
                        Lask, whose name is subscribed to the annexed instrument, and: thereon
                        written, and before whom the annexed oath or affidavit was taken, was, at
                        the time of taking such oath or affidavit, a notary public in and for the
                        city and county of San Francisco, residing in said city and county, duly
                        authorized to take the same, and an officer duly authorized by the laws of
                        said State to take and certify the acknowledgment and proof of deeds to be
                        recorded in said State. And further, that I am well acquainted with the
                        handwriting of such officer, and verily believe that the signature to such
                        jurat or certificate is genuine.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">In witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand
                            and affixed the seal of the said superior court, at my office in said
                            city and county, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1893-01-31">this 31st
                                day of January, A. D. 1893</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <seg rendition="#left">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</seg>
                        <signed rendition="#right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. C. Haley</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Clerk.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p>I, Eugene R. Garber, presiding judge of the superior court of the city and
                        county of San Francisco, State of California, do hereby certify that said
                        court is a court of record, having a clerk and seal. That M. C. Haley, who
                        has signed the annexed attestation, is the duly elected and qualified county
                        clerk of the city and county of San Francisco, and was, at the time of
                        signing said attestation, ex officio clerk of said superior court. That said
                        signature is his genuine handwriting, and that all his official acts, as
                        such clerk, are entitled to full faith and credit.</p>
                    <p>And I further certify that said attestation is in due form of law.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Witness my hand <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1893-01-31">this 31st day of January, A. D.
                            1893</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Eugene R. Garber</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Presiding Judge of the said Superior Court.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">State of California</hi>, <hi rend="italic">City and
                            County of San Francisco, ss:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>I, M. C. Haley, county clerk of the city and county of San Francisco, and ex
                        officio clerk of the superior court of the city and county of San Francisco,
                        State of California, do hereby certify that the Hon. Eugene R. Garber, whose
                        name is subscribed to the preceding certificate, is presiding judge of the
                        superior court of the city and county of San Francisco, State of California,
                        duly elected and qualified, and that the signature of said judge to said
                        certificate is genuine.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">In witness whereof, I have hereunto set my hand
                            and affixed the seal of the said court, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1893-01-31">this 31st day of January, A. D.
                            1893</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <seg rendition="#left">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</seg>
                        <signed rendition="#right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. C. Haley</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">County Clerk and Clerk of Court.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
