<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1892-09-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1892-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="139" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                                <head>EXHIBIT III.</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" from="1892-07-07" to="1892-09-23" type="content-date">June 22/July 7–September 11/23,
                                            1892</date>]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>In conformity with order No. 160 of the commander of the Pacific
                                    Squadron dated the 11th September, 1892, the commission
                                    appointed by that order, and composed of the Ship’s Captain
                                    Hessen, president; Ship’s Captain Zarine, Captains of Frigate de
                                    Livron and Philissow, and of the auditor chief counselor of the
                                    college Yanevitch Yanevsky, members, with Lieutenant Petrow,
                                    executive officer, proceeded to execute the work intrusted to
                                    them, took cognizance of the circumstances of the seizure of the
                                    American whaling bark <hi rend="italic">Cape Horn
                                    Pigeon.</hi></p>
                                <p>From the report of Lieutenant von Cube, who seized said bark, it
                                    appeared that he had been detailed from aboard the first-class
                                    cruiser <hi rend="italic">Vitiaz</hi> aboard the schooner <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi>, seized by the cruiser for illegal
                                    seal fishing, for the purpose of conducting her to Vladivostok
                                    during the voyage, when in 46° 33′ latitude north and 140° 30′
                                    longtitude east he sighted the bark <hi rend="italic">Cape Horn
                                        Pigeon</hi>, and, suspecting it of engaging in the same <pb facs="0316" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/> illegal industry, he
                                    sent his Second Ship’s Ensign Simansky with armed sailors to
                                    ascertain what vessel it was, and what its mission. Having
                                    learned from the bark’s Captain Thomas Scullun, who returned
                                    with Lieutenant Simansky, that it was a whaling vessel having
                                    aboard at that moment the product of two whales killed by him,
                                    Lieutenant von Cube found it impossible to abandon his first
                                    intention. Moreover, on examining the log book and the
                                    navigation chart of the bark, he was convinced that the latter
                                    had on several occasions approached the Russian coast of the sea
                                    of Okhotsk, where whaling is absolutely interdicted to
                                    foreigners. Furthermore, Lieutenant von Cube was confirmed in
                                    this opinion by the circumstance that at the approach of the
                                    schooner the bark had hoisted a signal, which, according to
                                    Captain Scullun’s explanation, had been intended for the
                                    schooner <hi rend="italic">Mary H. Thomas</hi>, expected that
                                    same night, and which also engaged in whaling and sealing. In
                                    view of these facts, Lieutenant von Cube considered it incumbent
                                    upon him, in the interest of the Russian Government, to conduct
                                    said bark to Vladivostok in order that the question might be
                                    decided at once whether or not she should be confiscated. But
                                    not having at his disposal a crew sufficiently numerous to put a
                                    portion of it upon the bark, and not wishing to trust to the
                                    bark’s crew, he decided to go aboard the bark with his entire
                                    crew, and to keep with him the bark’s captain he transferred the
                                    captain’s mate, with the entire crew of the bark, aboard the
                                    schooner <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi> and ordered them to repair
                                    to Vladivostok. The <hi rend="italic">Cape Horn Pigeon</hi>
                                    arrived at Vladivostok on the 7th September and the schooner
                                    several days earlier.</p>
                                <p>The commission at once took cognizance of the statements relating
                                    to this affair, as well as of the documents in evidence, such as
                                    the log book kept by Lieutenant von Cube on the schooner <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi>, and afterwards on the bark <hi rend="italic">Cape Horn Pigeon</hi>, the log book of the
                                    latter kept by Captain Scullun, the sailing papers of the bark
                                    taken from the captain by Lieutenant von Cube, the navigation
                                    chart of the bark and the instructions given to commanders of
                                    Russian cruisers on being sent north, to regulate their conduct
                                    when boarding and seizing schooners suspected of marauding.</p>
                                <p>From the above-mentioned documents and the examination of said
                                    bark made by the commission (of which the protocol is hereunto
                                    attached) results the following:</p>
                                <p>1. The bark <hi rend="italic">Cape Horn Pigeon</hi> having left
                                    Vladivostok on June 22 (7th July) of this year without obtaining
                                    the permission sought for to take whales in the bays and coast
                                    waters of the Sea of Okhotsk, caught two whales in said sea; she
                                    sighted the first of these and began the chase at 5 miles from
                                    the island of Askold, but was not successful in catching it
                                    there.</p>
                                <p>During her cruise to the west of Cape Aniva, she communicated
                                    several times while at sea with the schooner <hi rend="italic">Mary H. Thomas</hi>, which, according to Captain Scullun’s
                                    statement, is engaged in whaling and sealing.</p>
                                <p>2. Whaling in the Sea of Okhotsk is not interdicted to foreigners
                                    except in the bays, the gulfs, and straits, and in coast waters
                                    or along shore. It is even permitted to foreign fishing vessels
                                    in cases of extreme necessity to enter the bays and gulfs,
                                    provided they do not enter into such negotiations with the
                                    inhabitants as are forbidden by law.</p>
                                <p>3. Upon the bark were found the oil and bone of two whales
                                    killed, as said the captain, in the Sea of Okhotsk, in that part
                                    wherein whale fishing is permitted; but although the statements
                                    of the captain were confirmed by the log book and the chart, the
                                    commission did not consider this fact sufficiently proven.</p>
                                <p>4. The conduct of Lieutenant von Cube at the time of the seizure
                                    of the bark is considered by the commission perfectly regular,
                                    inasmuch as overhauling a suspicious vessel, in a suspicious
                                    locality, he could not do otherwise than seize it and submit to
                                    an investigation as to the legitimacy of the seizure by a
                                    superior authority. The commission will not fail to notice here
                                    that the mere feat alone of detaining a bark with a crew
                                    numbering 30 men by the much less numerous crew of the schooner
                                    shows the initiative spirit and resolution of Lieutenant von
                                    Cube.</p>
                                <p>In consequence of the preceding and the impossibility of
                                    establishing the fact that the two whales had been taken by the
                                    bark in that portion of the Sea of Okhotsk where whaling is
                                    prohibited, the commission is of opinion that the position of
                                    the bark near the Russian coasts does not of itself constitute
                                    an illegal act, and it declares that for this reason the bark
                                        <hi rend="italic">Cape Horn Pigeon</hi> can not be convicted
                                    of having engaged in illegitimate business, and it does not see
                                    sufficient motives for its confiscation.</p>
                                <closer>(Signed) Members: <lb/>
                                    <signed>
                                        <list>
                                            <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Yanevitch-Yanevsky</hi>,
                                                Presiding Counsellor of College.</item>
                                            <item>Captain of Frigate <hi rend="smallcaps">Philissow</hi>,</item>
                                            <item>Captain of Frigate <hi rend="smallcaps">de
                                                  Liveon</hi>,</item>
                                            <item>Ship’s Captain <hi rend="smallcaps">Zaeine</hi>,</item>
                                            <item>President, Ship’s Captain <hi rend="smallcaps">Hessen</hi>,</item>
                                            <item>Executive Officer, Lieutenant <hi rend="smallcaps">Petrow</hi>,</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>