<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>EXHIBIT B B.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1902app1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1868-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1868-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reclNKKiGeWi0buDd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146352"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Whales</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1868-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1868-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="43"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                <head>EXHIBIT B B.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">Note.</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">No. 2530.]</p>
                <p>The undersigned, gerant of the Imperial ministry of foreign affairs, referring to
                    the note which General Clay, envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of
                    the United States of America, had the goodness to address to the chancellor of
                    the Empire, dated March 4 (16) last, has the honor to inform him that he has
                    just been put in possession of information which, according to the desire of the
                    Federal Government, the Imperial cabinet had hastened to request from the
                    ministry of marine, concerning the incident which occurred in the Sea of Okhotsk
                    between an American whaler and a vessel of the Imperial navy.</p>
                <p>Here is what appears from this information:</p>
                <p>The schooner <hi rend="italic">Aleoute</hi>, under the command of Lieutenant
                    Etoline, had been sent on a mission from Nicolaievsk to Oudsk to revictual that
                    country. He was obliged by the great quantity of floating ice to enter the Gulf
                    of Tougoursk; there he encountered on July 14, at about 20 miles south of the
                    Strait of Chantarsk, near the eastern coast, the American whaler <hi
                        rend="italic">Java</hi> occupied in melting the fat of a whale which it had
                    just captured. Considering that, according to the laws in force, foreign whalers
                    are interdicted from fishing in the Russian bays and gulfs at a distance less
                    than 3 miles from shore, where the right of fishing is reserved exclusively to
                    Russian subjects, Lieutenant Etoline requested the captain of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Java</hi> to leave the Gulf of Tougoursk, which he thereupon
                    did.</p>
                <p>The same day the <hi rend="italic">Aleoute</hi> set sail for the Bay of Mangou,
                    where she arrived the day following the American whaler <hi rend="italic"
                        >Caroline Foot</hi>, the captain of which, accompanied by the captain of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Java</hi>, presented himself before Lieutenant Etoline and
                    declared that he had no right to interdict his fishing for whales wherever he
                    thought fit. Lieutenant Etoline replied that there were established rules in
                    regard to the matter, and that if they insisted on infringing them he would find
                    himself obliged to prevent them from so doing.</p>
                <p>The captain of the schooner <hi rend="italic">Caroline Foot</hi> having stated
                    that he came into the Gulf of Tougoursk on account of injuries, Lieutenant
                    Etoline offered him every assistance in his power, and on his request delivered
                    him 7 poods of biscuits from the stores of the <hi rend="italic">Aleoute</hi>,
                    after which the two vessels went to sea.</p>
                <p>The 19th of July, that is to say, four days after, the schooner <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aleoute</hi> encountered a whale, at which the commander fired a practice
                    shot. At this moment he perceived at about 16 miles distance an unknown sail and
                    a little after three boats, of which the nearest was at least 3 miles away, in
                    the direction in which the shot had been fired. That night all these
                    disappeared.</p>
                <p>This incident is entered in the log book of the <hi rend="italic">Aleoute</hi> in
                    the following terms:</p>
                <p>“July 19, at 9 o’clock at night, at anchor in the Bay of Mongou; fired a trial
                    shot at a whale.”</p>
                <p>From these data General Clay may easily convince himself that the incident in
                    question must have been greatly exaggerated and perverted to make it to be
                    represented as a grievance on the part of the American whaler in regard to the
                    commander of the <hi rend="italic">Aleoute.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Following the statements exchanged between them of the pretention of right on the
                    part of the captain of the <hi rend="italic">Java</hi> to fish wherever he found
                    it convenient and of the necessity under which Lieutenant Etoline found himself
                    to remind him of the existence of laws governing the right of fishing in the
                    territorial waters of a foreign State, it is possible that the commander of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Java</hi> may have in fact taken as a menace directed
                    against him the practice shot fired from the <hi rend="italic">Aleoute.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>But it is incontestable that the commander of the <hi rend="italic">Aleoute</hi>
                    was within his rights when he reminded the American captains of the laws in
                    force and of the obligation he was under to cause them to be respected. He
                    certainly did not pass the limits of his right in firing, four days after, a
                    cannon shot at a whale floating in Russian waters. He had not the least
                    intention of giving to the American whalers useless <pb facs="0102" n="86"
                        xml:id="pg_86"/> notice, since they went away without difficulty, and the
                    distance which separated the <hi rend="italic">Aleoue</hi> from the vessel and
                    boats at that moment in sight excluded all such idea.</p>
                <p>Lieutenant Etoline proceeded in regard to them conformably to the good relations
                    between the two countries, since he offered his assistance in repairing their
                    injuries and provided them with supplies. Finally the commander of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Aleoute</hi> did not believe it his duty to inform the Russian
                    authorities of this incident, since it seemed to him insignificant, and since
                    for his part his conscience was clear that he had not passed the limits of his
                    rights nor failed in his duties.</p>
                <p>The undersigned flatters himself with the hope that the Federal Government, being
                    informed of these details, will consider the incident closed.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile he seizes the occasion to renew to General Clay the assurance of his
                    most distinguished considerations.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Westmann.</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">St. Petersburg</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-07-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 31, 1868</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
