<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Denby to Mr. Blaine..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1890</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d140</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">140</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1890-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1890-07-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1890-07-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1890-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="140"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d140">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Blaine</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-07-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 25, 1890</date>. (Received September
                        22.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1123.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose a translation of a
                    communication bearing date June 16, 1890, lately sent to me by the Tsung-li
                    yamên; also a translation of another communication bearing date June 17, <pb
                        facs="0292" n="188" xml:id="pg_188"/> 1890; also copies of my replies to
                    these two communications. The delay in forwarding these papers was caused by my
                    absence from Peking. It will be seen that the first of these communications
                    relates mainly to the act of October. 1888, being the Chinese exclusion act, and
                    that it recites that substantially similar inquiries were made by the Chinese
                    minister at Washington of yourself and of your predecessor. While it must be
                    admitted that under the fourth article of the treaty of 1880 it is entirely
                    competent for the yamên to address complaints to me touching any legislative
                    act, nevertheless, under the circumstances, it seemed prudent for me not to take
                    up the proposed discussion until I had presented the matter to you and received
                    your instructions. I answered the yamên in that sense. The communication of June
                    17 is mostly directed against the lately proposed Chinese enumeration bill and
                    the San Francisco ordinance which has for its purpose to confine Chinese
                    residents to certain designated localities. I have replied to the yamên that my
                    information was that the enumeration bill had been laid on the table in the
                    Senate, and that the ordinance mentioned would be tested in the courts before
                    any action would be had under it. It seemed to me unnecessary to discuss at this
                    time the provisions of either measure.</p>
                <p>This conduct is in accordance with the treaty, which applies only to measures “as
                    effected.”</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 1123.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Tsung-li-yamên</gloss> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Denby</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-06-16">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 16, 1890</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: Research reveals the fact that
                        all the treaties entered into between China and the United States, beginning
                        with that of the twenty-fourth Tao Kuang (1844, western style); then that of
                        the eighth Hsien Teng (1858); that of the seventh Tieng Chit (1868), and
                        that of the sixth Kuang-hsü (1880), four in all, originated on the part of
                        the United States. Further, the proposed treaty, the draft whereof was
                        jointly discussed by us in the year Kuang-hsü (1888), was also put forward
                        by the Department of State under the last Administration, the original idea
                        not coming from China. Notwithstanding this, His Excellency, the former
                        President, set this treaty aside, and without premonition put in operation a
                        new statute absolutely prohibiting the coming of Chinese laborers into the
                        United States, a statute widely at variance with the Chinese-American treaty
                        of the seventh Tung Chit (1868), and a violation of the treaty of the sixth
                        Kuang-hsü, wherein China authorized the restriction by the United States of
                        the immigration of Chinese laborers. The fifth article of the treaty entered
                        into between China and the United States in the seventh year of Tung Chit
                        (1868) speaks of the mutual advantage of the free migration and emigration
                        of their citizens and subjects, respectively, from the one country to the
                        other, for the purposes of curiosity, of trade, or as permanent residents.
                        The sixth article further says, * * * “Chinese subjects visiting or residing
                        in the United States shall enjoy the same privileges, immunities, and
                        exemptions in respect to travel or residence as may there be enjoyed by the
                        citizens or subjects of the most ‘favored nation.’”Again, the treaty of
                        Kuang-hsü (1880) between China and the United States says that whenever the
                        coming of Chinese laborers to the United States, or their residence therein,
                        affects or threatens to affect, the interests of that country, or to
                        endanger the good order of any locality within the territory thereof, the
                        Government of China agrees that the Government of the United States may
                        regulate, limit, or suspend such coming or residence, but may not absolutely
                        prohibit it. The limitation or suspension shall be reasonable. Under these
                        circumstances, the ratification by His Excellency the former President, on
                        the 26th day of the eighth moon last year (western style, the 1st of
                        October), of the statute enacted by Congress prohibiting immigration of
                        Chinese laborers is beyond belief. Further, this yamên had previously, viz,
                        on the 15th day of the eighth moon of that year (September 19), sent a
                        dispatch to Your Excellency submitting for your consideration <pb
                            facs="0293" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> three additional clauses to the
                        new treaty. To this, however, Your Excellency has never replied. The Chinese
                        minister to the United States also submitted these three clauses in a
                        dispatch to the Department of State. He, too, received not a word in reply.
                        The new treaty, however, was rejected and a new statute was enacted in place
                        of it. This method of dealing does not seem to us to agree with the spirit
                        which animates the treaties of our two countries, and fails to accord with
                        the several decades of friendship between us. Since the enacting of this new
                        law Chinese going to and from the United States have all met with
                        interference. His Excellency Mr. Chang, former minister to the United
                        States, first on the 25th day of the twelfth moon of the fourteenth
                        Kuang-hsü (January 26, 1889), later on the 26th of the first moon of the
                        fifteenth Kuang-hsü (February 22, 1889), wrote to the former Secretary of
                        State on this subject. In reply to these dispatches he received an answer
                        from the Honorable Secretary, in which he merely intimated that as the
                        President was about to go out of office he certainly would not ratify any
                        legislation enacted in violation of treaty. He did not reply to any of the
                        other important matters submitted to him.</p>
                    <p>After Mr. Blaine had entered on his duties as Secretary of State the former
                        minister, Mr. Chang, on the 10th day of the sixth moon, fifteenth Kuang-hsü
                        (July 7, 1889), wrote a dispatch making urgent inquiries for information and
                        demanding that the law enacted by Congress the preceding year, prohibiting
                        Chinese laborers from entering the United States, be repealed.</p>
                    <p>These communications were exceedingly explicit in their statement of the
                        case.</p>
                    <p>In reply, however, the Department merely stated that haste would be made in a
                        careful consideration of, the subject. As to the manner in which this
                        consideration has been conducted, no information has as yet been given. This
                        yamên observes that the Chinese minister, in his three dispatches above
                        referred to, has, in the main, substantiated his position by quotation from
                        the successive treaties between the United States and China. Now, by
                        reference to the <ref target="frus1881#pg_173">Foreign Relations of the
                            United States, 1881, pp. 173</ref>, <ref target="frus1881#pg_185"
                            >185</ref>, and <ref target="frus1881#pg_198">198</ref>; and to the
                        statutes of the United States, March 1843, 5th chapter, p. 624; and to the
                            <ref target="frus1870#pg_332">Foreign Relations of the United States of
                            1870, p. 332</ref>; and to the Congressional Record, 1888, 19th chapter,
                        pp. 8451, 8452, 8453; and to the message of President Hayes, March 1, 1879,
                        to the Forty-fifth Congress, vetoing a bill; and to the message to Congress
                        of President Arthur, April 4, 1882—by reference to these various documents
                        kept on record by the United States Government, referring to statutes and
                        matters with which Your Excellency is well acquainted, it may be easily
                        ascertained why the Department of State persistently refused to give
                        definite answers. Sincerely interested, as Your Excellency is, in the
                        relation of our countries, you probably are aware that the law now in
                        operation, contrary to treaty stipulations, interferes with Chinese subjects
                        in their efforts to gain a livelihood, as well as violates the several
                        treaties themselves. Last year at the opening of Congress His Excellency the
                        President, in his message to that body, stated that the failure to ratify
                        and exchange the new treaty negotiated between China and the United States,
                        and the legislation of the last session of Congress consequent thereto, had
                        left some questions open, to the deliberation of which it was now his duty
                        to request Congress to approach with justice and equity, etc.</p>
                    <p>This yamên has not heard from Your Excellency whether or not during these
                        months any such deliberations have been entered into by the Congress of your
                        country.</p>
                    <p>His Excellency Mr. Tsui, our present minister, has frequently written to the
                        Department on the subject, but receives no replies. We request, finally,
                        that Your Excellency will clearly indicate to us what article of the treaty
                        it is that your honorable Congress relied on in enacting the new law of last
                        year. Should statutes be enacted without adherence to the treaties, then the
                        Chinese residents in the United States must, in time to come, suffer varied
                        and repeated hardships. This result, we fear, can not be avoided. The
                        Chinese have gone to America because repeated treaties have authorized them
                        to go and come at their pleasure, and to enjoy there the advantages of
                        citizens of the most favored nation. For this reason the residents on the
                        coasts of China have gone to the United States in large numbers to gain
                        their subsistence. There they have accumulated considerable property. Now
                        that suddenly their going to and fro is prohibited, to whose charge shall be
                        given their homes and property in America? The new law enacted by Congress
                        is totally at variance with the treaties, and we consider it a violation of
                        the spirit which prompted your country in its repeated requests to China to
                        execute treaties with it. It forms an entirely new episode in the relations
                        of the two countries, and, though there was a disagreement with France in
                        1798, the instance is one which is seldom met with in the history of the
                        United States with other countries.</p>
                    <p>Your Excellency is thoroughly conversant with the treaties between China and
                        the United States; we therefore request you at once to write to the
                        Department of State to secure the repeal of the laws in violation thereof.
                        We hope, also, to receive an answer in this important matter.</p>
                    <p>A necessary communication, etc.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0294" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 1123.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Tsung-li-yamên</gloss> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Denby</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-06-17">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 17, 1890</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: It is customary to speak of the
                        relations between China and the United States as characterized by continuous
                        cordiality. The treaties which China has on various occasions entered into
                        with the United States have all been animated with the intention to protect
                        the interests of American citizens. The United States, however, because of
                        discrimination against Chinese laborers, have repeatedly enacted laws in
                        violation of treaty, and all having for their object the maltreatment and
                        injury of Chinese subjects. We have lately received from His Excellency Mr.
                        Tsui, minister to the United-States, a communication, wherein he says that
                        the Lower House of the United States Congress has had under discussion
                        recently the enacting of a vexatious law requiring the enumeration of the
                        Chinese in the United States, in California; moreover, a statute has been
                        recently enacted driving out and expelling the Chinese from the larger
                        cities. On reading this, very great was our indignation and grief. The
                        second article of the supplementary treaty between China and the United
                        States of the sixth Kuang-hsü (1880) says that Chinese merchants “and
                        Chinese laborers who are now in the United States shall be allowed to go and
                        come of their own free will and accorded all the rights, privileges,
                        immunities, and exemptions which are accorded to citizens and subjects of
                        the most favored nation.” Article in says: “If Chinese laborers or Chinese
                        of any other class, now either permanently or temporarily residing in the
                        territory of the United States, meet with ill treatment at the hands of any
                        other persons, the Government of the United States will exert all its power
                        to devise measures for their protection and secure to them the same rights,
                        privileges, immunities, and exemptions as may be enjoyed by the citizens or
                        subjects of the most favored nation, and to which they are entitled by
                        treaty.” The vexatious law for the enumeration of the Chinese seems to be
                        not only a contradiction of the “favored-nation” clause in the successive
                        treaties between China and the United States, but a violation of the
                        Constitution on which your Government is built. In the law for the driving
                        out and expulsion of the Chinese and the limitation of their residence
                        hereafter to a particular locality no inquiry has been made as to whether
                        they had property or not. They are all alike to be forced into one narrow
                        place and not allowed the usual privileges of residence. After 60 days those
                        not driven out shall be ordered to prison. We do not know whether the
                        Chinese now residing in the United States are all those who in former times
                        went thither under the treaty which your Government entered into with China
                        in order to authorize their going. Their strength, however, was availed of
                        and their labor used. Afterwards, as soon as the railroad had pierced
                        through to California, and when business flourished, the virtues of the
                        Chinese were no longer remembered, and they were regarded as enemies. At
                        first hostility arose, then there was burning of houses, then there was
                        expulsion of Chinese; now they are to be forced to live in one locality and
                        be allowed no residence elsewhere. It seems that they are to be gathered
                        together to inflict further injuries on them. This is a contradiction of
                        those words of the treaty which say they may “go and come of their own free
                        will and accord,” while the proposed imprisonment after 60 days is a
                        nullification of that treaty clause which speaks of enjoying the advantages
                        of the subjects of the “most favored nation.” Should such acts as these
                        originate with the citizens or subjects of another country, should they so
                        insult and ill treat the Chinese laborers, the Government of your honored
                        country would be in duty bound to “exert all its power to devise measures
                        for their protection,” and thus fulfill its treaty obligation. Now, however,
                        contrary to all our expectations, these oppressions and these insults come
                        from the United States, whose relations with us it is customary to designate
                        as cordial. We are humbly of opinion that in the law of nations reciprocity
                        is considered most important. Suppose that China should conduct herself
                        towards American citizens in a similar manner, we ask whether the Congress
                        of the United States would not reproach China with a violation of the
                        treaty? And would Your Excellency sit still and make no inquiries of us?
                        Change your point of observation. At this time China can not refrain from
                        expressing her feelings, and it is just that she should do so. The whole
                        truth is that this class of Chinese laborers, although living beyond the
                        outer seas, are not the less the children of China, and she is unable to
                        cast them from her breast. It is our duty, therefore, to communicate with
                        Your Excellency and to express the hope that you will write to the
                        Department of State to abrogate the laws requiring enumeration and forced
                        restriction of residence. We hope for an early reply. We further wish that
                        you would transmit to the Department of State a request to speedily reply to
                        the dispatch of last year from His Excellency Mr. Tsui, the present
                        minister, sent during the second intercalary mouth, and that of the former
                        minister, Mr. Chang, and thus show some concern for the important matter of
                        the good relations of our countries.</p>
                    <p>A necessary communication, etc.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0295" n="191" xml:id="pg_191"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 1123.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to the <gloss
                                type="to">Tsung-li-yamên</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-07-26">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 26, 1890</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 7.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Highness and Your Excellencies</hi>: I have the
                        honor to acknowledge the receipt of your communication of June 16, 1890. I
                        seize the earliest opportunity after my return to Peking to reply to the
                        same.</p>
                    <p>You set out in detail the dates of the treaties and make some observations on
                        their origin. You proceed to comment on the act of Congress of October,
                        1888, relating to the exclusion of the Chinese laborers, which act you
                        severely criticise. You further state that I sent no reply to your
                        communication of the 15th day of the eighth moon of the fourteenth year of
                        Kuang-hsü (September 20, 1887), I beg leave to say that I acknowledged the
                        receipt of your communication. I forwarded it to my Government. I have
                        received no advices from my Government touching the three suggestions made.
                        You further state that you have addressed, through your minister at
                        Washington, the present Secretary of State and his predecessor on this
                        subject and are without a reply. You cite various documents and Presidential
                        messages. You then make some comments on the alleged injustice of the act of
                        Congress of which you complain, and you request that I take up this
                        discussion with you, and that I clearly indicate to you what article in the
                        treaty it is that Congress “relies on in enacting the new law of 1888.” You
                        proceed to detail the alleged hardships to which Chinese subjects will be
                        subjected by the operation of the new statute, and you severely criticise
                        the said statute. You request me, in conclusion, to write the Secretary of
                        State to secure the repeal of the said law.</p>
                    <p>In reply to this communication, I have to say that I have sent to the
                        Department of State a translation of your communication.</p>
                    <p>I think that under the circumstances detailed by you it is best for me to
                        await the instructions of my Government before taking up the discussion of
                        the matters stated. I must therefore beg of you to await a more specific
                        reply to your communication until I shall have received the instruction of
                        the Honorable Secretary of State.</p>
                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 1123.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Denby</persName> to the <gloss
                                type="to">Tsung-li-yamên</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-07-26">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 26, 1890</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 8.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Highness and Your Excellencies</hi>: I have the
                        honor to acknowledge the receipt of the communication of Your Highness and
                        Your Excellencies of June 17, 1890.</p>
                    <p>I seize the earliest opportunity after my return to Peking to reply to it.
                        You therein state that the United States “have repeatedly enacted laws in
                        violation of treaty, and all having for their object the maltreatment and
                        injury of Chinese subjects.” Under the treaty of 1880 it is competent for
                        the Government of China to bring the attention of the Government of the
                        United States or that of the minister to China to the consideration of any
                        legislative measure which may be found to work hardships upon the subjects
                        of China.</p>
                    <p>As I understand this provision, it is applicable to laws that have been
                        enacted by Congress and have received the sanction of the Executive, or been
                        passed over his veto in accordance with the Constitution, and that have
                        become valid and are in force. A complaint made in the general addressed to
                        newly proposed laws which are not in force would require much time for
                        discussion, and such time might be uselessly expended. You state that you
                        have been informed by your minister at Washington that the Lower House of
                        Congress has had under discussion recently the enacting of a vexations law
                        requiring the enumeration of the Chinese in the United States. You have
                        probably been informed by your minister before this time that the said bill
                        failed in the Senate, was laid on the tables, and will in all human
                        probability not become a law. It is unnecessary to waste any time in the
                        discussion of this measure.</p>
                    <p>You refer, also, to the ordinance lately passed by the city of San Francisco.
                        That city passed an ordinance by which the residence of Chinese subjects was
                        restricted to certain designated localities. If this ordinance be
                        antagonistic to the treaties, as Your Highness and Your Excellencies claim,
                        then it will be set aside by the courts and held to be naught and void.
                        Under our system of government it is not competent <pb facs="0296" n="192"
                            xml:id="pg_192"/> for any State or city to enact laws contrary to the
                        provisions of existing treaties. I have not learned that the Chinese consul
                        or the Chinese residents of San Francisco are much alarmed at the passage of
                        the ordinance in question. Until the courts shall have decided that the said
                        ordinance is legal and binding, and some action that is prejudicial to the
                        Chinese has been had thereunder, it would seem to be unnecessary to discuss
                        its provisions.</p>
                    <p>I have sent to the Secretary of State a translation of your communication,
                        and I am sure that it will secure the attention that its importance
                        warrants.</p>
                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Denby.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
