<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1890-01-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1890-01-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="193" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Blaine</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hurtado</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-01-31"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 31,
                                1890</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to recall to your
                            attention the claim against the Government of Colombia growing out of
                            the suspension in 1886 of the Panama Star and Herald, a newspaper
                            published in Colombia by an American corporation.</p>
                        <p>The facts in the case may briefly be summarized as follows:</p>
                        <p>The Star and Herald and La Estrella de Panama Company, limited, was
                            incorporated on or about the 17th of December, 1883, under the laws of
                            the State of New York. The company was organized by citizens of the
                            United States, employs American capital, and has its principal office in
                            the city of New York. On March 25, 1886, Gen. Santo Domingo Vila, then
                            civil and military governor of the national department of Panama,
                            addressed to the editor of the Starand Herald a personal note, inclosing
                            copies of certain telegrams and suggesting their publication, if the
                            editor should deem it expedient, the language employed being “‘si lo
                            tiene á bien y lo considera conducente.” As the telegrams gravely
                            reflected upon General Montoya, a brother officer of Gen. Santo Domingo
                            Vila, the editor of the Star and Herald very properly, desiring to hold
                            aloof from the political controversies prevailing in Colombia, as well
                            as to avoid a suit for libel, did not make the suggested publication.
                            Moreover, in adopting this course, he was acting in accordance with the
                            warning given him by the President of Colombia in the preceding year,
                            when a circular order was issued for the suspension of all newspaper
                            offices throughout the Republic until after the meeting of a convention
                            then about to be called for the revision of the national
                            constitution.</p>
                        <p>The President of the Republic subsequently excepted the Star and Herald
                            from the operation of the order, but in so doing cautioned the editor to
                            observe “strict circumspection as to political subjects.”</p>
                        <p>No complaint has been made that the editor of the Star and Herald
                            disregarded this injunction. Gen. Santo Domingo Vila invited him to
                            violate it, and, besides, to expose himself to prosecutions. The editor,
                            adhering to the wise and proper course which he had theretofore been
                            pursuing, and also acting upon the discretion expressly left him, did
                            not publish the telegrams. As above stated, the note of Gen. Santo
                            Domingo Vila, inclosing the telegrams, bore date of March 25, 1886. On
                            the following day, the 26th of March, he, as the civil and military
                            governor of the national department of Panama, issued an order summarily
                            suspending the publication of the Star and Herald and announcing as the
                            reasons for his action that the editor of the paper had refused to
                            publish documents of importance relating to the policy of reform in the
                            administration of the department, “without even having the courtesy to
                            answer the polite private note (<hi rend="italic">esquela</hi>) which
                            accompanied them.” The suspension of the paper was continued until May
                            24, 1886, when the President and secretary of interior of the Republic
                            commanded Gen. Santo Domingo Vila to reëstablish it, or, in default
                            thereof, to surrender his office into the hands of General Rengifo. On
                            the day following Gen. Santo Domingo Vila replied that the term of
                            suspension had expired and at the same time tendered his resignation as
                            civil and military governor, which was accepted.</p>
                        <pb facs="0377" n="273" xml:id="pg_273"/>
                        <p>During the suspension of the paper protests were made on the part of this
                            Government against the action of Gen. Santo Domingo Vila, but, although
                            that action was manifestly arbitrary and wrongful and has never been
                            defended, the suspension was permitted to continue for 2 months. It was
                            attended with serious detriment, not only to the rights of the company
                            under the treaty as an American corporation, but also to its pecuniary
                            interests. Had the acts complained of been committed in time of war,
                            that fact might have been referred to as in some measure a palliation of
                            them, though not as a justification; but they were perpetrated in time
                            of peace, when the civil laws were in full force, by the officer whose
                            duty it was to see that those laws were maintained. It is now nearly 4
                            years since the Star and Herald was suspended, but the company has been
                            afforded no redress at the hands of the Colombian Government for the
                            grave wrong inflicted. Such redress, it is thought, should now be
                            tendered.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">James G. Blaine.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>