<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Pratt to Mr.
                                Blaine.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1890</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">412</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1890-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1890-06-03T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079" lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418" lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recfIX2Uumy8inHEq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85144526" lcsh-match="exact">Wages</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675" lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1890-06-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1890-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="412" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d412">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Pratt</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Blaine</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Teheran</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-06-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 3, 1890</date>.
                            (Received July 12.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 459.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my dispatch No. 458 of the 27th
                        ultimo, I have the honor to report that I have just received a letter from
                        Her Britannic Majesty’s consul-general, Col. C. E. Stewart, informing me of
                        the active steps he had taken to secure the arrest of the Armenian, Minas,
                        who made the murderous assault upon Mrs. Wright on the 14th of last month,
                        and also a letter from Mrs. Wright’s husband, the Rev. John N. Wright,
                        giving in minute detail an account of the said incident.</p>
                <p>Copies of the letters above mentioned I herewith respectfully submit for your
                        consideration, with copies of my answers to the same, which I trust will
                        meet with your approval.</p>
                <pb facs="0772" n="662" xml:id="pg_662"/>
                <p>At my request the prime minister, His Highness the Eminé Soultan, has
                        appointed this afternoon to see me in regard to the affair in question, when
                        I shall repeat to him the contents of the aforesaid communications and
                        request that the accused criminal be taken, under strong military escort, to
                        the capital of the province, Tabreez, there to be tried in the presence of
                        Consul-General Stewart, who, I will inform him, is designated to act as my
                        representative at the trial to ensue.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Spencer Pratt</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 459.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Colonel <persName type="from">Stewart</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Pratt</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Ooroomeeyah</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-05-24">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 24,
                                1890</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Pratt</hi>: Excuse my writing you on this
                            paper and in an unofficial form, but lam at Ooroomeeyah and just before
                            the post went out received a telegram from the governor of Salmas
                            telling me that the assassin of Mrs. Wright has been arrested by the
                            governor’s men and is being brought to Salmas. The missionaries
                            themselves had promised a reward of 25 tomans for the capture of the
                            man, but I also furnished 25 tomans more, as I thought it necessary to
                            stimulate the zeal of the men sent in pursuit of the assassin.</p>
                    <p>Before I had arrived at Salmas the governor had done nothing. It is true
                            he was absent some 13 miles from the town of Dilman, which is the
                            headquarters of the Salmas district.</p>
                    <p>I at once rode off 13 miles to the governor, woke him out of his sleep,
                            and got him to go into the mountains with me to follow out a trace of
                            the assassin which I had obtained.</p>
                    <p>It was too late then, as the man had escaped 4 days previously, to arrest
                            the assassin, but I had a very rough and hot ride and showed the
                            governor that I was really in earnest about the matter.</p>
                    <p>The trace I had obtained through the missionaries was duly followed up
                            and has finally led to the capture of the man.</p>
                    <p>After I had seen him the governor did exert himself to capture the
                            man.</p>
                    <p>I have written to the authorities in Tabreez informing them of the
                            capture of the assassin.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Wright, though not even now out of danger, is likely to recover. On
                            the 21st it was feared she would die, but she rallied.</p>
                    <p>As I am absent from Tabreez on business here, I would ask that you should
                            take what steps you may consider necessary to obtain due punishment of
                            the man. I shall, I hope, be back in Tabreez by about the 10th or 11th
                            of June and shall be happy to do whatever you may wish about seeing that
                            the man receives such punishment as you may desire.</p>
                    <p>Orders must, I think, come from Teheran about the case.</p>
                    <p>I think the prompt measures I took for the arrest of the attempted
                            assassin and the interest I showed in the matter will insure protection
                            to the missionaries for the future.</p>
                    <p>Now remains the question of what punishment the assassin should receive
                            from the Persian authorities.</p>
                    <p>Yours, sincerely,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">C. E. Stewart.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 459.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wright</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Pratt</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Oola,
                                        Salmas</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-05-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 22,
                                1890</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: On the 14th instant, at 3.30 p.m., a
                            dastardly attempt was made to assassinate my wife.</p>
                    <p>Minas, the would-be murderer, who came here from Ooroomeeyah, and is a
                            graduate of our college there, had been teaching the school in this
                            village for us the past winter. Last fall we gave him a room in our
                            house, as he was a stranger and came to us well recommended. But,
                            finding in the course of time that he and our maidservant were <pb facs="0773" n="663" xml:id="pg_663"/> too intimate (though we had no
                            idea that they were criminally so at that time), we removed him from our
                            yard in February last to a room in an adjoining yard belonging to our
                            premises. But Minas still found a way to get with Asli, our maidservant,
                            when we sent her out to walk with the children or on our roof. We
                            rebuked her for thus allowing him to follow her everyplace. Still, we
                            had no definite idea of any criminal intercourse between them.</p>
                    <p>But on the night of the 13th instant, at 11 p.m., my wife awoke, and,
                            finding our maid was not in the adjoining room with our little boy, she
                            began to look about the house for her and finally found Asli coming up
                            the stairs from the yard.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Wright, suspecting Asli and Minas had been there together, watched
                            his way to his room (which she could do from our bed-room window).
                            Before long Minas passed from our yard through a gate which was in the
                            wall between our yard and his, having in some way found a key which
                            would unlock the padlock on it.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Wright called to him twice, but he slipped rapidly along our wall
                            and soon disappeared in his yard.</p>
                    <p>This made it evident to us that the teacher and Asli had been living
                            immoral lives. So next day, after seeing Mr. Mechlin, we decided to
                            dismiss him at once.</p>
                    <p>About 3.30 p.m. I called him to our dining room and told him why we
                            dismissed him. Mrs. Wright and another woman were in the room, the
                            former cutting out a frock for Jennie, our daughter.</p>
                    <p>There was nothing unusual in Minas’s appearance. He took his dismissal as
                            a matter of course, and asked me if I would pay him the balance due on
                            his wages and horse hire to Ooroomeeyah.</p>
                    <p>“Certainly,” I replied, and arose and went into an adjoining room to get
                            the money. But scarcely had I shut down the open safe when I heard
                            heartrending screams. My brother-in-law, who happened to be present with
                            me, and I at once rushed into the dining room.</p>
                    <p>To our utter amazement we found Minas had attempted to murder my wife and
                            was just fleeing from the door opposite us.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Wright, as she cut the garment, had her left shoulder turned towards
                            Minas, who sat on a divan on the opposite side of the room.</p>
                    <p>As soon as I was fairly out of the room, without a word, he suddenly
                            sprang upon Mrs. Wright and with a dagger, which he at the same moment
                            drew from his sleeve, he first attacked her at the left side of the
                            spinal column, piercing into her left lung. As Mrs. Wright began to turn
                            toward him, he let the next blow fall on top of her left shoulder,
                            cutting an artery, from which the blood spurted as from a fountain. As
                            she turned still further, he attempted to cut her throat, but only
                            succeeded in making an upward cut under her jaw, near the base of the
                            tongue. Twice more he struck, but, Mrs. Wright being now fully turned
                            toward him, one blow struck her in the right wrist and the other in the
                            back of the right hand, inflicting fearful wounds. This was all done so
                            quickly that, although we ran for the door the moment we heard the
                            screams, it was all finished before we entered the room.</p>
                    <p>As Minas descended the stairs he met our gatekeeper running toward them,
                            and, making a thrust at him with his dagger, passed and went out of the
                            yard gate.</p>
                    <p>I at once gave word to the villagers to arrest him, through the said
                            gatekeeper and my brother-in-law, and, leaving that work for them, we
                            gave ourselves at once to the more necessary work of caring for Mrs.
                            Wright. So profuse was the flow of blood that before I could tear open
                            her clothes and close the two wounds in her back and shoulder she had
                            little left in her. I held these gashes shut for upward of half an hour
                            before Mr. Mechlin arrived; then we sewed these two up as best we could
                            and fastened all with court-plaster. She was so faint we did not think
                            it best to attempt to sew up the other wounds, so we fastened them as
                            best we could with court-plaster and bandages.</p>
                    <p>To add to the difficulty, Mrs. W. showed every symptom of having a
                            miscarriage; indeed, this seemed the greatest danger of all.</p>
                    <p>We telegraphed at once to Ooroomeeyah for a doctor, but for various
                            causes it was 2 full days before Dr. Samuel, a Nestorian physician,
                            arrived. During all this time Mrs. Wright’s wounds had not been properly
                            dressed or bandaged, because none of us had had any experience in such
                            matters before.</p>
                    <p>You can better imagine than realize the anxious suspense we were in
                            during this time. During the week which has passed since the calamity
                            Mrs. Wright has suffered greatly, and still remains so very weak that
                            she may die any day.</p>
                    <p>The shock which her nervous system sustained is so great that it greatly
                            complicates matters. At the same time that we sent the telegram to
                            Ooroomeeyah for a doctor (<hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>, within an hour
                            after the assassination) we gave word in Dilman to the governor of
                            Salmas, Hadji Khan, or rather to his son, Aziz Khan, who was “naibi
                            hukuveat” in his father’s temporary absence at Charu, 3 hours’ ride
                            distant.</p>
                    <p>The naibi hukuveat excused himself by saying it was fast time, and the
                            men could not leave until they had eaten in the evening, and that his
                            father had taken most of them away anyhow.</p>
                    <pb facs="0774" n="664" xml:id="pg_664"/>
                    <p>On hearing this reply I sent the same man again, hut he found the naibi’s
                            door shut up, and no one would answer his call.</p>
                    <p>It went on thus from Wednesday, the 14th, at 4 p.m., till Sunday, 18th,
                            and the authorities did absolutely nothing to arrest the murderer.</p>
                    <p>We offered a reward of 25 tomans soon after the crime was committed for
                            the arrest of the perpetrator, but nothing was done.</p>
                    <p>On Saturday, the 17th, very providentially, Her Britannic Majesty’s
                            consul-general, Col. C. E. Stewart, who happened to be on his way to
                            Ooroomeeyah, stopped at my house to remain with us on the Sabbath.</p>
                    <p>On hearing the news of the crime and the neglect of the Government to do
                            anything toward arresting Minas, he was much moved and at once sent a
                            note to the naibi hukuveat, with the request that he send it at once to
                            his father in Chafu. Sunday morning the consul went himself to Charu
                            (and got there just as his note sent the previous day did) and told
                            Hadji Khan he must at once send to arrest that young assassin, or that
                            he would telegraph both to you and the British minister about his
                            negligence.</p>
                    <p>The governor, now fully scared, began at once to take vigorous measures
                            to trace the steps of Minas. Colonel Stewart went with him in person
                            that day to see to it. Since then Hadji Khan has been doing what he can
                            to overtake Minas, but the 3½ days’ grace he had gave him such a start
                            that the odds are against the governor. He has traced him up till he
                            passed into Turkish territory, near Bârh Kalēh, and has sent a telegram
                            and his own “filorda” (bridle holder) to Bârh Kalēh to request the
                            Persian consul there by all means to capture him.</p>
                    <p>23d, a.m.—Word came last evening that Minas had got a passport at Bârh
                            Kalēh for Van and had started on with an Armenian guide the day before
                            the governor’s men arrived.</p>
                    <p>Three Persians and a servant of the Persian consul at Bârh Kalēh followed
                            right on after him with the hope of overtaking him before he could enter
                            Van, but I doubt if they would succeed in doing so.</p>
                    <p>Colonel Stewart offered a reward of 50 tomans and expenses of capture the
                            day after his arrival, in addition to the 25 tomans we had offered
                            previously.</p>
                    <p>The probabilities are that the traitor will be arrested sooner or later.
                            We will await orders from you as to what disposal shall be made of
                            him.</p>
                    <p>Colonel Stewart left us yesterday (Thursday) for Ooroomeeyah and will go
                            from there on south and around Lake Ooroomeeyah for nearly 2 weeks. He
                            will be a guest at the house of Dr. J. P. Cochran.</p>
                    <p>We feel ourselves under very great obligations to Colonel Stewart and to
                            Her Britannic Majesty’s Government for the timely and vigorous aid
                            given; and I know I only voice the desire of this station and of the
                            mission when I say I hope you will, on the part of yourself and of our
                            Government, write him a letter of thanks; and, while I do not know what
                            our Government is prepared to do in such cases, I feel that Her
                            Britannic Majesty’s consul-general and his Government should be fully
                            reimbursed for expenses incurred in attempting to defend our lives and
                            having the criminal arrested. He would not consent to receive aught from
                            us, saying he had only done his duty.</p>
                    <p>This morning (the tenth day) Mrs. Wright seems a little better, and we
                            are now somewhat encouraged to hope for her ultimate recovery, but I
                            doubt if she will ever be again what she was before.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 24.—News has reached us this morning that
                            Minas was captured last Thursday afternoon, the 22d instant, 4 hours
                            east of Van, by the man who followed him up from Bârh Kalēh. They
                            brought him at once towards Salmas, and he has just now (Saturday noon)
                            arrived at Dilman.</p>
                    <p>We have sent Hadji Khan, the governor of Salmas, word, by the man he sent
                            to inform us of Minas’s arrival, that we leave the matter of his
                            punishment entirely with you and the English consul, Colonel Stewart, as
                            well as the settlement of the amount to be paid out for the pursuit and
                            arrest. It will probably be not less than 100 tomans.</p>
                    <p>Hadji Khan said he would at once telegraph Colonel Stewart, at
                            Ooroomeeyah, of Minas’s arrest and imprisonment at Dilman and await his
                            instructions.</p>
                    <p>I leave the matter of his punishment entirely with you and Colonel
                            Stewart, feeling sure that justice will be done and that he will be made
                            an example, so that other evildoers may fear the results of their
                            crimes.</p>
                    <p>Of course, he should not be put to death unless Mrs. Wright should yet
                            die; but the punishment due for premeditated and deliberately attempted
                            murder should be meted out to him.</p>
                    <p>Yours, very truly,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John N. Wright.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0775" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 459.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Pratt</persName> to
                                Colonel <persName type="to">Stewart</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-06-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 3,
                                1890</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Sir</hi>: I beg to acknowledge your letter
                            of the 24th ultimo, from Ooroomeeyah, the contents of which 1 have read
                            with great interest.</p>
                    <p>By to-day’s mail, which is now about to close, I have only time to
                            hastily express to you my sincere thanks for the energy you have
                            displayed in the pursuit of Mrs. Wright’s dastardly assailant, whose
                            ultimate capture would in all probability never have been effected but
                            for your personal exertion and the direct and timely pressure which you
                            brought to bear upon the local governor of Salmas, who I must have
                            brought to task for neglect of duty.</p>
                    <p>You may rest assured your prompt and decisive action in this matter, of
                            which I shall immediately inform the honorable Secretary of State, will
                            be duly appreciated by the American Government.</p>
                    <p>Upon receiving the first intimation of the assault upon Mrs. Wright, and
                            whilst the would-be assassin was still thought to be at large, I caused
                            the most positive orders for the latter’s arrest to be telegraphed by
                            the prime minister, His Highness the Eminé Soul tan, to His Excellency
                            the Emir Nizan, at Tabreez, as well as to the governor of the district
                            of Salmas.</p>
                    <p>This evening I am to have an interview with His Highness the Eminé
                            Soultan in regard to Mrs. Wright’s case and the punishment of the
                            criminal, who, I consider, should be made to fully expiate the enormity
                            of his crime, in order both to vindicate the law in the present instance
                            and establish an example for the future.</p>
                    <p>In closing, let me request that you will kindly inform me as to the total
                            amount you have thus far expended in connection with this matter, in
                            order that I may refund you the same.</p>
                    <p>I gladly accept the offer you have so courteously made to represent me in
                            the prosecution of the case in question, and am happy to say that this
                            is entirely in accordance with His Excellency Sir Henry Drummond Wolff’s
                            views in the premises.</p>
                    <p>Believe me, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Spencer
                            Pratt.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 4 in No. 459.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Pratt</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Wright</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Teheran</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1890-06-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 3,
                                1890</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: I have received your letter of the
                            22d ultimo, and have read with horror and indignation the account it
                            gives of the murderous assault made upon your wife, Mrs. Wright, on the
                            afternoon of the 14th.</p>
                    <p>Upon receipt of the first intimation of this crime, and before any
                            particulars thereof had yet reached me, I at once brought the matter to
                            the attention of the prime minister, His Highness the Eminé Soultan,
                            who, at my instance, dispatched the most peremptory telegraphic orders
                            both to the governor of Salmas and to the Emir Nizam, at Tabreez, for
                            the immediate pursuit and arrest of the criminal Minas, who was then
                            still supposed to be at large.</p>
                    <p>Two days later the Emir Nizam telegraphed that the said arrest had been
                            effected in Turkish territory, and that the prisoner would be returned
                            to Salmas. This was confirmed by a telegram from Colonel Stewart, from
                            whom I have just now received a letter exposing the culpable neglect
                            displayed by the local authorities in permitting the criminal’s escape
                            and informing me of the steps he (Colonel Stewart) had been forced to
                            take to insure the latter’s ultimate capture. I am to have an interview
                            with His Highness the Eminé Soultan this evening, when I shall lay all
                            of the above facts before him and ask that the prisoner Minas be sent
                            under heavy guard to Tabreez, there to be tried in the presence of
                            Colonel Stewart, who the British minister has kindly consented to allow
                            to represent me on the occasion.</p>
                    <p>I have written Colonel Stewart to advise me as to the expenses he has
                            thus far incurred in this affair, so that I may refund him the amount. I
                            have also instructed the colonel to so prosecute the case in question
                            that the perpetrator of this monstrous deed shall be made to pay the
                            full penalty of his crime, in order to satisfy justice in the present
                            instance and serve as an example for the future.</p>
                    <p>It is my earnest prayer that Mrs. Wright may yet recover from the effects
                            of her wounds.</p>
                    <p>I have duly cabled what has occurred to our Government.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely, yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Spencer
                            Pratt.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
