<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-11-14T16:08:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-11-14T16:08:00-05:00" n="105" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d105">
                    <head>105. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Arab Republic</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d105fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                            Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                            1964–66, AID (US) 9 <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. Secret;
                            Immediate; Limdis. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SHM1">Symmes</persName>; cleared by Officer in Charge of Near Eastern
                            Economic Affairs George M. Bennsky, Jones, and AID Deputy Assistant
                            Administrator for Near East and South Asia Walter G. Farr, Jr.; and
                            approved by <persName corresp="#p_TPH2">Talbot</persName>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-11-14T16:08:00-05:00">November 14, 1964, 4:08 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>2794. For Ambassador from <persName corresp="#p_TPH2">Talbot</persName>.
                            <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1637.<note n="2" xml:id="d105fn2">Telegram 1637 from Cairo, November 11, conveyed
                                <persName corresp="#p_BLD2">Battle</persName>’s disappointment with
                            the apparent unwillingness in Washington to proceed with a $20 million
                            commodity loan to the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. He concluded:
                            “New administration must give early sign of continuation cooperative
                            effort or a new policy will exist here whether we intend it or not.”
                            (Ibid.)</note> Appreciate fully your concern that presenting Egyptians
                        with alternatives to commodity loan might be regarded as attempt to renege
                        on an agreement whose requirements they feel have been met. Agreeing with
                        Embassy position that continued inaction in field of economic cooperation
                        could bring an end to our policy of seeking to broaden areas of common
                        interest with the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and recognizing
                        practical difficulty if not impossibility moving forward on commodity loan,
                        we have sought to provide another basis for moving ahead. The State/AID
                        proposals carried by <persName corresp="#p_MWBJ1">Macomber</persName>
                        supplemented by Aidto 198<note n="3" xml:id="d105fn3">Not found.</note> we
                        believe can be presented as an economically useful token of US intent to
                        carry forward on current policies.</p>
                    <p>Commodity loan is hamstrung by our inability to demonstrate to Congressional
                        and other inquirers’ complete satisfaction second requirement or evidence
                        that U.S. aid does not in fact pay part of foreign exchange costs of a
                            <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> “occupation” of Yemen. We can hardly
                        claim progress on third condition, given presence over 50,000 Egyptian
                        troops in Yemen (latest intelligence community estimate) as against less
                        than 30,000 when Yemen costs discussed with <persName corresp="#p_KAM2">Kaissouni</persName> in October, 1963. While <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>-Saudi detente on Yemen hopeful, know from our experiences
                        through 1963 the danger of claiming “major progress” on <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                        <pb facs="0268" n="236" xml:id="pg_236"/> performance until actual and
                        substantial drawdown takes place. If the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                        should opt for the $20 million program loan, they must understand that we
                        cannot proceed until Egyptian performance permits us to defend the loan
                        against domestic criticism.</p>
                    <p>This being the case, we propose moving forward by offering an alternative
                        which we believe could be presented to Egyptians as more advantageous and
                        more immediately available. We note that, since our agreement in principle
                        supply $20 million to help meet chronic foreign currency shortage, Kuwaiti
                        loan of over $90 million has been received. Any current balance of payments
                        strains for which <gloss target="#t_UARG1">UARG</gloss> had earmarked
                        commodity loan can be covered to some extent by at least part of increases
                        in the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 65 Title I program requested by
                            <gloss target="#t_UARG1">UARG</gloss> over that remaining in the present
                        multiyear agreement. The sector loan-project loan package added to this
                        should serve as adequate symbol of US intent to restore aid momentum.</p>
                    <p>Neither we nor the Egyptians should labor under illusion that program (i.e.,
                        commodity) or project loan for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 65 is major
                        benchmark passing of which will ensure smoothing of course of future
                        assistance. <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> 480 agreement which is core of
                        our economic cooperation program remains to be negotiated for years
                        subsequent to ’65. Our flexibility in this and working toward a future
                        Western approach to counter Soviet influence will to a large degree be
                        dependent on Egyptian action in meeting its commitments under present <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss> 480 agreement, in managing its economy, and
                        on Egypt’s political posture in the area and on the world scene. We are
                        gratified by recent reports that <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> and his key lieutenants are giving <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> economic problems their personal attention.
                        Strong argument can be made we should not come between them and their
                        decision to face and reappraise unpleasant economic realities. They know
                        from qualified foreign economists what needs to be done. Their willingness
                        take bitter medicine necessarily will be one of principal determining
                        factors in future US–<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> economic
                        cooperation.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="strong">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>