<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-11-30T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-11-30T11:00:00-05:00" n="111" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                    <head>111. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the United Arab
                            Republic</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d111fn1">Source: National
                            Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss>
                            59, Central Files 1964–66, POL 23–8 <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>.
                            Confidential; Priority.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Cairo</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-11-30T18:00:00+02:00">November 30, 1964, 6 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>1904. I called this morning on Prime Min <persName corresp="#p_SA7">Ali
                            Sabri</persName> at his request. He began conversation by saying not
                        necessary repeat all the things <persName corresp="#p_FM5">Fawzi</persName>
                        had said to me.<note n="2" xml:id="d111fn2">Telegram 1885 from Cairo,
                            November 28, reported <persName corresp="#p_BLD2">Battle</persName>’s
                            meeting that day with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_FM5">Fawzi</persName>. (Ibid.)</note> Then stated interested in use of
                        phrase “pre-arranged and premeditated” (Sabri’s words) in note and in
                        conversation. He asked that I give him any evidence we had this point. I
                        stated there could be no doubt of pre-arrangement if one examined nature of
                        incident and its success from point of view those who wished it. I said that
                        if he read carefully my statement and our note, he would see that I had
                        never stated by whom incident arranged and had refrained carefully from any
                        charge Egyptian involvement. I said I had done this and reported my govt no
                        Egyptians involved even in light of numerous rumors and reports to contrary.
                        I had avoided carefully overemphasizing these rumors for fear of
                        exacerbating situation. I was now authorized to accept the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> note expressing deep pain and the statement
                        of willingness to negotiate compensation,<note n="3" xml:id="d111fn3">Telegram 1886 from Cairo, November 28, transmitted the text of the
                                <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> note delivered that day.
                            (Ibid.)</note> subject, or course, to successful working out matter. I
                        said my prime purpose now was to overcome bad effects this incident but that
                        it was impossible for me to do it alone. I must have their help. I said they
                        had failed comply basic customs in matters of this kind and that throughout
                        night of incident many of American and foreign press as well as others
                        repeatedly asked me, “have you heard from Egyptian Govt?,” to which I of
                        course had to reply in negative. I said I could only compare this with
                        custom through centuries and for example recent example in Sudan, where half
                        of Cabinet called to express regret for incidents, of which he aware since
                        his govt involved in same circumstances. He said he had not been aware of
                        custom and thought that sending Chief of Police with his expression
                        adequate. I said his expression concern had reached me only in the note and
                        had not been conveyed by Chief of Police. I told him that I had arrived two
                        months ago with great hope and great expectation strengthening our
                        relations. I still had them and wished to overcome problems surrounding this
                        incident, but he must help and help more than he had done before and after
                        incident. I said good relations two-way street, that I would do my part, but
                        that I could do <pb facs="0277" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/> no more than that.
                        He said, “What would you like me to do?” I said, prevent creation situations
                        such as <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> press treatment issues involving
                        US. I told him I would like to inform US press that he had called me in
                        today to repeat expressions given me by Dr. <persName corresp="#p_FM5">Fawzi</persName> of <gloss target="#t_GUAR1">GUAR</gloss> regret and
                        willingness to discuss compensation. He acceded.</p>
                    <p>Sabri repeated desire as expressed by Pres <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> in his recent speech to maintain good relations with
                        US. I said this also our desire, repeating again it was a two-way street. We
                        then sat for minutes in which neither of us spoke. I made no move terminate
                        conversation. He then repeated strong desire good relations. I said that
                        before leaving I wished to tell him that humanitarian mission conducted in
                        Congo had been completed, that large number hostages had been evacuated, and
                        that Belgian troops and US planes transporting them now out of area. I said
                        I had noted <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> press treatment given
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> statement this morning and
                        said I had sent off tel immediately asking for guidance. Response from
                        Washington had indicated statement taken out of context and had referred to
                        Congolese land movements.</p>
                    <p>Conversation very firm, slightly tense, but ended reasonably pleasantly. I
                        will talk with American press later today.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="strong">
                                <persName corresp="#p_BLD2">Battle</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>