<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>223. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">223</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec8rqhima3V9LICS" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="border-administration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006006662"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Cross-border</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recZOfMQQ0T1ERq22" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="border-administration" subject="border-administration" lcsh-match="no_match">Border incidents</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-06-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-06-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="223"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d223">
                <head>223. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d223fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1964–66, POL 32–1
                            ISR–<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. Confidential. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_WWD1">Wolle</persName> on June 9.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1965-06-08">June 8,
                            1965</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Arab-Israel Border Situation; Palestine Liberation Army</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM4">Mordechai Gazit</persName>, Minister,
                        Israeli Embassy</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Shimon Moratt</persName>, Counselor, Israeli Embassy</item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Rodger P.
                            Davies</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_WWD1">William D.
                            Wolle</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM4">Gazit</persName> said that the Foreign Ministry in
                    Jerusalem had reiterated June 7 to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BW2"
                        >Barbour</persName> that the Israeli Government seriously desires a return
                    to tranquility in the border areas and that it wishes to cooperate with the
                    Jordanian authorities to bring this about. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BW2"
                        >Barbour</persName> in recent days had also been given copies of messages
                    sent by the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> to the Jordanian and Lebanese
                    governments via the <gloss target="#t_MAC1">MAC</gloss>s containing lists of
                    individuals suspected of Fatah connections. There were 29 names on the list for
                    Jordan and a single name on the list for Lebanon.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM4">Gazit</persName> said his government hoped the
                    United States Government would go back to King <persName corresp="#p_HIT1"
                        >Hussein</persName> in a follow-up to his initiative with Ambassador
                        <persName>Barnes</persName> several days ago<note n="2" xml:id="d223fn2"
                        >Telegram 732 from Amman, June 3, reported a discussion between <persName
                            corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName> and <persName>Barnes</persName>
                        concerning the background of the recent incidents on the Jordan-Israel
                        border. <persName corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName> said concerning Fatah
                        that Jordan was not sponsoring the group, was completely opposed to its
                        alleged activities, and was making every effort to control the border
                        against infiltrations. He expressed willingness to have his comments
                        communicated to Israeli officials. (Ibid., POL 31–1 ISR–JORDAN) On June 4,
                            <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName> gave <persName
                            corresp="#p_GM4">Gazit</persName> the substance of telegram 732,
                        stressing that the information must be held very closely within the Israeli
                        Government. (Ibid.)</note> and, in addition to stressing to the King the
                    Israeli desire for a return to peace along the border, would raise a number of
                    specific points relating to the recent border events. These points had been
                    enumerated to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BW2">Barbour</persName>, but Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_GM4">Gazit</persName> said he would mention some of
                    them as examples. For one thing, the <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> does
                    not understand why the official Jordanian letter to the Security Council
                    concerning the May 31 Jerusalem incident<note n="3" xml:id="d223fn3">The
                        Jordanian letter, dated June 4, responded to a June 1 Israeli letter
                        charging that Jordanian Army posts had opened fire the previous day across
                        the armistice demarcation line into Israeli territory. (<gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> documents <gloss target="#t_S1"
                        >S</gloss>/6415 and <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/6397)</note> is at odds
                    with what has been learned from the Jordanians themselves to be the real
                    explanation. The <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> wonders what kind of
                    punishment <pb facs="0504" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/> Jordan will impose on the
                    army captain arrested because of that incident, which it considers to have been
                    most serious. Israel fails to understand Jordan’s apparent inability to spot
                    saboteurs moving toward the border, since groups of several persons rather than
                    simply individuals have been involved in some cross-border incidents.</p>
                <p>The Israeli Government would continue to supply information concerning Fatah
                    complicity in the sabotage incidents, said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM4"
                        >Gazit</persName>, though it could hardly supply such a quantity that it
                    became in effect a branch of the Jordan security services. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GM4">Gazit</persName> expressed gratitude on behalf of the
                    Israeli Government for the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>’s readiness to
                    transmit such information and more general messages to Jordan on its behalf. He
                    went on to note that his government believed the onus was now on King <persName
                        corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName> to see that border tranquility was
                    restored.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName> said that U.S. intelligence
                    confirmed the serious desire and efforts of King <persName corresp="#p_HIT1"
                        >Hussein</persName> to keep potential saboteurs in check. He noted that it
                    was a little too much to assert that Jordan had absolute control of such
                    activities. Nearly 200 Israeli soldiers had, after all, moved almost unnoticed
                    well into Jordan territory during the May 27–28 raids, and even the Israeli
                    security forces could not detect individuals or groups of infiltrators
                    immediately on entry into Israel. He stressed that the <gloss target="#t_USG1"
                        >USG</gloss> was quite convinced that any further Israeli military raids
                    would push the Jordanians into some sort of military reaction.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM4">Gazit</persName> referred to <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO1">PLO</gloss> efforts to raise a Palestine Liberation Army
                    and stated his government was impressed by the serious steps in process,
                    particularly in Gaza. He spoke of the seriousness with which the <gloss
                        target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> viewed the question of keeping <gloss
                        target="#t_UNRWA1">UNRWA</gloss> ration cards from <gloss target="#t_PLA1"
                        >PLA</gloss> conscriptees. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName>
                    agreed this was a serious question, reiterated the steps the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> had taken with <gloss target="#t_UNRWA1"
                        >UNRWA</gloss> officials regarding it, and expressed again the hope that
                    this issue would be kept out of the press since the glare of publicity would
                    render <gloss target="#t_UNRWA1">UNRWA</gloss> action much more difficult.
                    Regarding the <gloss target="#t_PLO1">PLO</gloss>, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName> said it seemed clear that the Arab
                    states principally concerned were holding the organization at arm’s length.
                    There was a danger, however, in the extent to which the Chinese Communists could
                    make good on Peking’s reported promises to Shuqairy of funds, arms and
                    training.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM4">Gazit</persName> read brief passages from a <gloss
                        target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> letter to the Security Council regarding the
                    June 1 explosions at Yiftah and Beit Guvrin,<note n="4" xml:id="d223fn4">Dated
                        June 4; not printed. (<gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> document <gloss
                            target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/6414)</note> and spoke briefly of two more
                    recent border incidents. At Beit Qama (about 13 miles north of Beersheba and 6
                    miles from the Jordan border) an Israeli watchman had come upon four intruders
                    cutting the fence <pb facs="0505" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> around a water tower
                    and had thereby prevented damage to the installation. At Jisr Shaikh Hussein the
                    Jordanians had fired across the border for 45 minutes with no apparent cause.
                    Mr. <persName>Moratt</persName> commented that the Jordanians now claimed to
                    have repulsed two Israeli attacks, neither of which in fact ever existed. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName> commented that the Jordanians
                    undoubtedly were apprehensive about possible incursions. He emphasized that the
                        <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> is counseling restraint on all parties
                    concerned although our leverage in one location (Damascus) is at an extremely
                    low level.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
