<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>316. Letter From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and South
                    Asian Affairs (Hare) to the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                    International Security Affairs () to the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense
                    for International Security Affairs (Hoopes))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">316</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-08-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recco4TvraiYB3Tfh" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007556"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-08-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="316"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d316">
                <head>316. Letter From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near Eastern and South
                    Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HRA2" type="from">Hare</persName>) to the
                    Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for International Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_HTW1" type="to">Hoopes</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d316fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1964–66,
                        DEF 12–5 ISR. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WWD1"
                            >Wolle</persName> on August 18 and cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SHM1">Symmes</persName>, Padelford of <gloss
                            target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>/RA, and Warren of G/<gloss target="#t_PM1"
                            >PM</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-08-22">August 22, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Dear Tim:</p>
                <p>We have given careful consideration to your letter of June 30<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d316fn2">Not found.</note> regarding certain weapons and components
                    requested by the Government of Israel in connection with the A–4F package.</p>
                <p>I continue to agree with you that the United States should stand by the decision
                    that the Sidewinder 1–C air-to-air missile, the Bullpup B air-to-ground missile,
                    the Rockeye II cluster anti-tank weapon and the tail warning radar should be
                    refused to Israel on general policy grounds. I also remain of the opinion that
                    we should continue to avoid specifying to the Israelis reasons for our refusal
                    to comply with their requests. As I mentioned in my letter of August 1,<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d316fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HRA2">Hare</persName>’s August 1 letter to <persName
                            corresp="#p_HTW1">Hoopes</persName>, concerning an Israeli request to
                        produce military equipment for the A–4 aircraft, agreed that there was no
                        objection to Israeli production of non-lethal stores and fittings but that
                        the United States should refuse authorization for Israeli production of any
                        lethal items. (Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                            >RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: <gloss
                            target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 70 A 6648, 452.1 Israel)</note> we see no
                    requirement in discussion of their requests to distinguish between “military”
                    and “security” as opposed to “political” or other considerations and in fact see
                    obvious disadvantages in making such distinctions.</p>
                <p>It is our opinion that, as with the four items mentioned above, the United States
                    should also refuse to sell napalm bombs and fuzes to Israel on general policy
                    grounds. This is a type of weapon that raises particularly sensitive reactions
                    among the Arabs, as among others. I am not convinced by the arguments advanced
                    thus far by the Israelis that we should provide even limited quantities of
                    napalm equipment. To provide napalm after Israeli use of it in the July 14
                    retaliatory raid on Syria and the August 15 incident with Syria would indeed
                    risk substantial political liabilities in our relations with the Arabs.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_HRA2">Raymond A. Hare</persName>
                        </hi>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d316fn4">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
