<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-12-08T19:13:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-12-08T19:13:00-05:00" n="359" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d359">
                    <head>359. Telegram From the President’s Special Assistant (<persName type="from">Rostow</persName>) to President <persName type="to">Johnson</persName> in Texas<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d359fn1">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Israel,
                            Vol. VI. Secret. The telegram was received at the <gloss target="#t_LBJ1">LBJ</gloss> Ranch at 6:52 p.m. on December 8. A
                            handwritten “<gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>” on the telegram indicates
                            that it was seen by the President. A notation in an unknown handwriting
                            reads as follows: “Walt: Let <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> tell Abe Feinberg do not want this—unless they
                            want an enemy.”</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-12-09T00:13:00+00:00">December 9, 1966,
                            0013Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>CAP 661223. Information. Forewarned is forearmed and you should be aware that
                        the Israelis are now zeroing in on our proposed small military aid package
                        for Jordan. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HA3">Harman</persName> was in
                        to see me this afternoon<note n="2" xml:id="d359fn2">A memorandum of the
                            December 8 conversation is ibid.</note> and conveyed the clear message
                        that the Israeli Government is very much concerned that anything we do for
                        Jordan will unsettle the delicate military balance in the area. We will be
                        sending you more formally in the next day or two a specific proposal on
                        Jordan. Defense still has not quite wrapped up all the details, but it is
                        fair to say that the package will be minimal and will not seriously affect
                        the Israeli-Jordanian military balance. However, we will have to reckon with
                        an Israeli reaction no matter what we do. We are on firm logical ground in
                        saying that we would be doing nothing more for Jordan than already planned
                        if the Israelis had not raided on 13 November. After all, we are only
                        picking up the pieces in a mess they created. But regardless of how firmly
                        we take that line, the Israelis have regained their composure and are going
                        to be pretty tough to deal with.</p>
                    <p>We will include recommendations for handling the Israeli side of the problem
                        when we send our final proposal to you. However, I wanted you to be
                        forewarned of this aspect of the problem in case someone should try to reach
                        you at the Ranch.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>