<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>377. Telegram From the Embassy in Israel to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-01-11T08:21:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-01-11T08:21:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recLA85IoR5zyxTTT" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91006127"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Nuclear power</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-01-11T08:21:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-01-11T08:21:00-05:00" n="377"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d377">
                <head>377. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Israel</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d377fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1967–69,
                        AE 13 ISR. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>. Repeated to
                        Cairo.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Tel Aviv</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-01-11T13:21:00+00:00">January 11, 1967,
                        1321Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2339. Ref: State 96223.<note n="2" xml:id="d377fn2">Telegram 96223 to Tel Aviv,
                        December 3, instructed <persName corresp="#p_BW2">Barbour</persName> to
                        focus on the question of <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> safeguards in
                        his coming meeting with <persName corresp="#p_EL2">Eshkol</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName>. (Ibid., DEF 12 NEAR <gloss
                            target="#t_E1">E</gloss>)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>In conversation with <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName> Jan 10 (<gloss target="#t_PM1"
                            >PM</gloss>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EL2">Eshkol</persName> on vacation and I did not wish
                        delay discussion further) I urged that <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                        reconsider carefully its stand on <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss>
                        safeguards. Drawing particularly from <gloss target="#t_reftel1"
                            >reftel</gloss>, I stressed importance we give to this matter, our
                        confidence and reasons therefore that <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss>
                        system inspection need not endanger <pb facs="0768" n="736" xml:id="pg_736"
                        /> Israeli security or reveal commercial secrets, and our view that
                        unilateral Israeli accession to <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss>
                        safeguards would be positive contribution to world peace, raising esteem in
                        which Israel held in world and working in Israel’s own self interest.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName>’s response centered about three
                        points: (A) “national dignity” (B) national security (C) domestic political
                        considerations.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Re (A) national dignity. <persName corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName>
                        objected to Israel’s being asked to give up something while the same demands
                        were not being levied on <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. He rejected
                        idea that somehow Israel “owed <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                        something” in this matter. Israel’s own peaceful disposition on area nuclear
                        matters had been made abundantly clear in recent statements by himself (<hi
                            rend="italic">Realite</hi> interview and “Meet the Press”) and by Israel
                        Delegation in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. His researches showed him
                        he said that a basic premise of arms control agreements was mutual
                        recognition of sovereignty, right to existence of partners in agreements.
                        There seemed to be no disposition on part <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                            >UAR</gloss> make such elemental concession in case Israel. Instead one
                        only heard talk of war of liberation. He wondered whether <gloss
                            target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> was not seeking do too much to increase
                        range of assurances to <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and not taking
                        sufficient account Israel’s concerns. He said Israel’s hopes for progress in
                        this problem rested largely on the achievement of general non-proliferation
                        treaty.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In my rejoinder I emphasized we not pushing Israel to take action under
                        assumption Israel owed <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> anything. Rather
                        we felt this was something Israel could do that would serve its own self
                        interest and broader interests world peace. Nuclear variable lent whole new
                        dimension to Middle East arms race and was regarded by us with utmost
                        seriousness. We were not asking Israel to do anything we would not ask
                            <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, though in case latter, in view
                        paucity its nuclear facilities, this almost academic question at this
                        time.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>As for possibilities general non-proliferation agreement we were hopeful,
                        but its prospects were uncertain and we could not rely on it solely as a
                        check to M.E. race at this stage.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Re (B) national security. In response my question <persName
                            corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName> said that nuclear facilities in plural
                        he had referred to in conversations Nov 2 were various components of Dimona
                        complex and there no others. <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> concerned
                        that details of Dimona lay out would become known to <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                            >UAR</gloss> through inspections and thence through important Egyptian
                        presence at <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> headquarters. Inquiry had
                        been made to Israeli reps in Vienna and consultations undertaken with
                        experts in Israel and both agreed inspection carried substantial security
                        risk.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>I countered with reminder that under <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss>
                        procedures <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> would have say in who
                        inspectors would be and that Israel’s presence or lack thereof on <gloss
                            target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> Board of Governors would not affect
                        protection it would enjoy in this respect.</item>
                    <pb facs="0769" n="737" xml:id="pg_737"/>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Re (C) domestic political considerations. <persName corresp="#p_EA3"
                            >Eban</persName>’s point here was closely related to “national dignity”
                        argument. He asked how <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> could explain to
                        Israeli people if it were to unilaterally accede to <gloss target="#t_IAEA1"
                            >IAEA</gloss> inspection while the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                        does nothing. Israeli people would wonder where national equality was
                        then.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>I suggested that Israeli people might very well understand such an action
                        as we would: as a logical next step in the unilateral reassurances that
                        Israel has already given to world about its nuclear intentions. It might
                        even be argued that such unilateral action would be more palatable to
                        Israeli public opinion than a bilateral agreement with <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>, though I recognized that bilateral
                        agreements would ultimately be desirable.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName> said that he would again consult
                        the <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> and experts on the various
                        technical problems. He agreed to take up with <gloss target="#t_PriMin1"
                            >PriMin</gloss> the suggestion that my next meeting on this subject be
                        with both of them. <persName corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName> suggested that
                        we consider putting in writing future exchanges on the subject. I said I
                        hoped we would not formalize our discussions to this extent at this stage.
                        It seemed to me that if we felt we needed to put things in writing we could
                        use informal bout de papier procedure. He agreed.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>In parenthetical remarks near end of discussion of subject <persName
                            corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName> expressed <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                            >GOI</gloss> satisfaction with talks with Ambassador Bunker. Said <gloss
                            target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> feeling was that water is essential aspect
                        of desalting project not nuclear power. Any means technically feasible to
                        get required water would be satisfactory to Israelis.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>I closed with expressed hope <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> would
                        give this subject careful priority attention it merited. <persName
                            corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName> said he would be in touch as soon as he
                        had had further discussions.</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Foregoing is summary lengthy conversation
                        being reported more fully by airgram.<note n="3" xml:id="d377fn3">A
                            memorandum of the conversation was enclosed with airgram A–414, January
                            16. (Ibid., AE 13 <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss>)</note> Believe
                        I covered all points of <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> with in
                        some cases additional what, I hope, were supporting arguments. No doubt but
                        that the going is heavy. MFA Assistant DirGen Bitan, who was present at
                        conversation, said later at lunch he thought progress along lines we were
                        pressing was unlikely. No doors have been shut however and I did not detect
                        in <persName corresp="#p_EA3">Eban</persName>’s remarks any desire to stop
                        our exchanges. It would of course be quite helpful if we could convey to
                        Israelis some sign of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> give in practical
                        matter of <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> inspection.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_BW2">Barbour</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
