<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>88. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Jordan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d88</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">88</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1964-08-12T18:51:00-05:00" notAfter="1964-08-12T18:51:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccfPriXIHvxyBuS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Arms buildup</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recakeAztvHvxtY4X" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2013002394"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">MIG</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="alliances" subject="summit-meeting" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007171" lcsh-match="exact">Summit Conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-08-12T18:51:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-08-12T18:51:00-05:00" n="88"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d88">
                <head>88. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Jordan</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d88fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1964–66,
                        DEF 19–3, US–JORDAN. Secret; Immediate. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_KAI1">Killgore</persName>; cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SHM1">Symmes</persName>, in draft by Bunte, and in substance
                        by <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_SJD1">Stoddart</persName>; and approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_TPH2">Talbot</persName>. Repeated to Cairo, London, and
                            <gloss target="#t_CINCSTRIKE1">CINCSTRIKE</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_CINCMEAFSA1">CINCMEAFSA</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1964-08-12T19:51:00-04:00">August 12, 1964, 7:51 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>86. Amman’s 84 to Department;<note n="2" xml:id="d88fn2">Telegram 84 from Amman,
                        August 11, reported that Barnes met with King <persName corresp="#p_HIT1"
                            >Hussein</persName> on August 10, read the President’s message (<ref
                            target="#d85">Document 85</ref>), and continued along the lines of
                        telegram 78 to Amman (<ref target="#d84">Document 84</ref>). (National
                        Archives and Records Administration,<gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Files 1964–66, DEF 19–3 US–JORDAN)</note> Deptels 64, 76 and 78 to
                        Amman.<note n="3" xml:id="d88fn3">For telegram 64 to Amman, see <ref
                            target="#d82">Document 82</ref>. Telegram 76 to Amman, August 7, stated
                        that in a meeting with <persName corresp="#p_TPH2">Talbot</persName> and
                            <persName corresp="#p_MWBJ1">Macomber</persName> before leaving
                        Washington, <persName corresp="#p_KGA2">Khammash</persName> said he found
                        the U.S. package insufficient to withstand pressures from the United Arab
                        Command. He handed back the resume, saying he would prefer not to have to
                        give it to the King. The telegram instructed the Embassy not to give the
                        King the resume until officials in Washington could consider possible
                        revisions in the manner of presentation. (National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1964–66,
                        DEF 19–3 US–JORDAN)</note> Department commends your presentation to King
                        <persName corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName> of <gloss target="#t_USG1"
                        >USG</gloss> position on arms for Jordan which we had all foreseen would be
                    unpleasant to King’s ears. While <persName corresp="#p_HIT1"
                    >Hussein</persName>’s over-all reaction negative, we were encouraged by King’s
                    apparent recognition of at least some of dangers and disadvantages to Jordan
                    inherent in <gloss target="#t_UAC1">UAC</gloss> arms buildup and by his stated
                    intention postpone any final decisions until over-all situation has been
                    clarified by September Summit Conference. In accordance his request, you should
                    provide King with copy of resume of <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> position
                    on sale of military equipment as contained in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 64 beginning with “A. General” and concluding at the end of
                    paragraph “C. Aircraft.” Paragraph D should not be contained in summary handed
                    to King.</p>
                <p>In oral presentation to King before handing him summary of <gloss
                        target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> position you should stress once again that
                        <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has done more for <pb facs="0235"
                        n="203" xml:id="pg_203"/> Jordan in past and will unquestionably do more in
                    future to preserve basic integrity of Jordan than any other country or group of
                    countries. In light of problems posed for <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> by
                    Jordan’s arms request, our response to King cannot be viewed as other than
                    generous. We are glad King apparently sees this with respect to ground
                    equipment, as judged by his remark that our suggestions can probably be drawn up
                    in such priority order as to satisfy <gloss target="#t_UAC1">UAC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>We continue to maintain that a supersonic fighter squadron for Jordan makes no
                    military, political or economic sense. In view total number of supersonic
                    fighters at disposal various countries represented on <gloss target="#t_UAC1"
                        >UAC</gloss>, we unable understand why supersonic squadron for Jordan could
                    and should have assumed such apparently overriding importance. If <gloss
                        target="#t_UAC1">UAC</gloss> had been looking for issue most likely to
                    render permanent damage to US-Jordanian relationship as well as threat to area
                    stability no better could have been found than ordering Jordan to accept
                    supersonic fighter squadron. King says key to present issue is F–104 squadron.
                    This is very issue which faces <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> with such
                    impossible choices.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName>’s argument that Israel might well
                    not be upset if Jordan acquired supersonic US squadron may be well taken.
                    However, apart from internal economic effects on Jordan, this misses main point,
                    namely, if <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> provides Jordan with supersonics
                    that symbolize offensive modern military power, little will be left of its Near
                    Eastern arms policy of avoiding becoming major supplier of offensive weapons to
                    countries involved in Arab-Israel context. If we provide supersonics to Jordan,
                    our arguments against providing similar and possibly larger quantities of
                    material to other countries, including Israel and other Arab states, would lose
                    validity. Once embarked on, end of this road would be clear—a polarized
                    situation in Middle East with Arabs lined up with Soviet Union and US in such
                    ill repute in area that King Hussein could no longer afford political liability
                    of being associated with us. We ask the King to search his mind carefully. If he
                    will do so we believe he will see validity of our position.</p>
                <p>In summary, we see Jordan’s acquisition of supersonic fighter planes at this time
                    as beginning of process that may ultimately destroy relations with US. A <gloss
                        target="#t_MIG1">MIG</gloss> squadron for Jordan would be little if any
                    better from our point of view. Congress will simply not understand how Jordan
                    needs such extensive US support if it can afford an expensive supersonic
                    squadron. We think King has good arguments that will make sense to most of other
                    Arab leaders. We hope the King will make these arguments with full force and
                    effect in coming meetings with his fellow Arab leaders. The King must know from
                    past experience that we are with him. We would hope he would remain in close
                    consultation with us and not close any doors at Summit.</p>
                <pb facs="0236" n="204" xml:id="pg_204"/>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. At very least we hope you will get
                    assurances from King that in meetings with <gloss target="#t_UAC1">UAC</gloss>
                    next week he will avoid any commitments that will foreclose further discussions
                    with us. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
