<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-08-01T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-08-01T18:00:00-05:00" n="117" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                        <head>117. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Cuba</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d117fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 737.00/8–158. Confidential; Priority.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Havana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-08-01T18:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">August 1,
                                        1958—6 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>169. Had two hour meeting with <persName corresp="#p_BZF1">Batista</persName> July 31. He was friendly and anxious to be
                            cooperative. Re lifting of suspension of constitutional guarantees,
                                <persName corresp="#p_BZF1">Batista</persName> said he was anxious
                            to do this but did not know when it would be possible because of
                            revolutionary activities.</p>
                        <p>He said he would put 1000 men at Moa Bay and 1000 men at Nicaro to defend
                            these properties if US will supply 2000 rifles and some other supporting
                            equipment.</p>
                        <p>Upon inquiry re the T–28’s I said delivery was still under consideration.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BZF1">Batista</persName> said he would again
                            open negotiations with Great Britain and Canada after my reiteration
                            paragraph 2 <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL1">Deptel</gloss> 51.<note n="2" xml:id="d117fn2">See <ref target="#d102fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                    102</ref>.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZF1">Batista</persName> then said he hoped we
                            realized we were giving aid and comfort to revolutionaries and
                            Communists by withdrawing support from <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss>. He expressed concern about stationing Marines at
                            Yateras, stating both US and <gloss target="#t_GOC1">GOC</gloss> would
                            have to watch this carefully as rebels may try to cause an incident to
                            place US in embarrassing position.</p>
                        <p>He again assured me: (A) that honest elections would he held on November
                            3; (B) that he has already invited the world press to witness the
                            elections; (C) that interest in elections would mount as November 3 drew
                            near; (D) he has no objections to a unified opposition and (E) is still
                            awaiting request from opposition parties to invite <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> to
                            send observers.</p>
                        <p>No matter who is elected, he believes they will have to keep the leaders
                            of armed forces and police intact to preserve law and order; otherwise
                            anarchy will ensue. When I asked <persName corresp="#p_BZF1">Batista</persName> whether revolutionaries would cease activities
                            upon election of either <persName corresp="#p_GSMR1">Grau</persName> or
                                <persName corresp="#p_MSC1">Sterling</persName>, he replied that
                            revolutionaries would not call off their activities after the election
                            of <persName corresp="#p_RAA1">Rivero Aguero</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GSMR1">Grau</persName>, or <persName corresp="#p_MSC1">Sterling</persName>.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_SEET1"><hi rend="strong">Smith</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>