<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>361. Instruction From the Department of State to to All Diplomatic and
                    Consular Posts in the American Republics</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d361</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">361</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-09-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recrT0TBgNbKJyC3W" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006005376"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Extremist</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recmU3mkCMXw0nKe9" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Foreign nationals</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States policy</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-09-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="361"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d361">
                <head>361. Instruction From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        <gloss type="to">All Diplomatic and Consular Posts in the American
                        Republics</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d361fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 611.37/9–1559. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HJCJ1"
                            >Hill</persName>; cleared in draft with <persName corresp="#p_SWP1"
                            >Snow</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_AOC1">Orville
                            Anderson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SRA1">Stevenson</persName>,
                            <persName>Philip Burns</persName>, Katherine Keany (<gloss
                            target="#t_USIAIAL1">USIA/IAL</gloss>), and <persName>James
                            Halsema</persName> (<gloss target="#t_USIAIOP1">USIA/IOP</gloss>); and
                        approved by <persName>Richard Phillips</persName>. Sent to Havana for
                        information only.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>–2424</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-09-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 15, 1959</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>United States Information Policy Toward the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                            >Castro</persName> Regime in Cuba</item>
                    <item>Joint State–<gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Background</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Executive Branch of the Government of the United States has, since the
                    present Cuban Government came to power last January, followed a carefully
                    calculated policy of exercising restraint and patience in its public statements
                    and actions regarding Cuba, seeking to avoid any impression that the United
                    States is hostile to the regime of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Fidel Castro</persName> or unsympathetic to the achievement within Cuba of
                    the proclaimed humanitarian objectives of the Revolution which he heads. The
                    United States Government has, in particular, sought to avoid statements or
                    actions which singly or cumulatively would suggest or imply a systematic
                    campaign against <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>. On the rare
                    occasions that it has been necessary to make statements or or take actions which
                    could be construed as less than sympathetic to <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Castro</persName> or his regime, these invariably have been the result of
                    actions taken by <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> which the United
                    States could not publicly ignore, such as measures affecting American property
                    or interests in Cuba, violations</p>
                <pb facs="0632" n="600" xml:id="pg_600"/>
                <p>by the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> regime of the basic
                    principles of the inter-American system, or damaging misrepresentations by
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> about the United States.</p>
                <p>The United States policy of restraint and patience has been designed to achieve a
                    number of objectives. By late 1959, this Government, while recognizing the
                    increasing repugnance of the Cuban public towards the excesses of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_BZF1">Batista</persName> Government and the popular desire for
                    the restoration of democratic processes, was also seriously concerned about the
                    anti-Americanism then already evident in <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Castro</persName>’s “26th of July” movement, about indications of Communist
                    leanings among important elements of the movement’s leadership, and about the
                    probability that the coming to power of <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Castro</persName>’s radical revolutionary group would seriously disrupt the
                    social, economic and political stability of Cuba.</p>
                <p>When <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> emerged as the victor of the
                    Cuban Revolution, achieving overwhelming popular support among the Cuban people
                    and colorfully capturing the imagination of a large segment of hemisphere
                    opinion, it necessarily became an objective of United States policy to establish
                    a climate free of hostility in which <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Castro</persName> could demonstrate any disposition he might have had to
                    conduct normal and friendly relations with the United States, while at the same
                    time giving a maximum opportunity for moderate elements friendly to the United
                    States to exercise a tempering influence on the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Castro</persName> Government. It thus became important from the point of
                    view of both Cuban-United States and hemispheric relations that the United
                    States avoid statements or actions which could be interpreted as being
                    unjustifiably hostile to <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> or his
                    Government, thus depriving <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> of any
                    valid excuse for using the mantle of patriotic resistance to United States
                    intervention as a cloak for the imposition of extremist social and economic
                    theories on Cuba, for infiltration of the political and military institutions of
                    Cuba by direct and indirect Communist influences, and for the systematic
                    fomenting of anti-American sentiment among the traditionally friendly people of
                    Cuba. It has been, in short, an important objective of United States policy
                    insofar as public opinion is concerned to establish that any unsatisfactory
                    state of Cuban-United States relations does not derive from the inflexibility
                    and intransigence of the United States but from policies and attitudes which
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> himself adopts.</p>
                <p>A corollary objective has been to assure that when disillusionment about
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> and many aspects of his
                    program and government should set in, it should come initially and principally
                    from Cuban, Latin American, and independent sources rather than from any public
                    statements or actions of the United States Government seeming to attack
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> and his Cuban Revolution. It
                    is already evident that in Latin America and even in Cuba the first enthusiasm
                    about the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>
                    <pb facs="0633" n="601" xml:id="pg_601"/> Revolution and its anti-dictatorship
                    claims has waned in important respects, and that public opinion is increasingly
                    focusing on certain adverse aspects of the present Cuban situation, such as: <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Democracy vs. Dictatorship Question:</hi> Although
                                <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> achieved power as the
                            most vivid symbol of the anti-dictatorship trend of Latin American
                            opinion and has continued to hold up the anti-dictatorship banner in his
                            domestic and international relationships, his regime has taken on
                            characteristics which are suspiciously like those of a dictatorship
                            itself. Among them are <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>’s
                            evident contempt for electoral and parliamentary processes for
                            expressing and controlling the execution of the popular will; his
                            disregard of independent judicial safeguards for individual liberties
                            and human rights against executive abuse; his use of deliberately
                            induced fear to control the mass media; and his pretensions—similar to
                            those of many modern authoritarian leaders—to embody in himself and his
                            movement all legitimate popular aspirations. These tendencies are
                            illuminated for hemisphere opinion by such episodes as <persName
                                corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>’s overriding of those court
                            acquittals he does not approve, by arbitrary mass arrests and other
                            forms of intimidation of all real or potential opposition, and by
                            demonstrations such as the recent July 26 rally which recall the
                            practice of other 20th Century dictatorships to organize emotional mass
                            support in lieu of submitting to elections based on rational
                            discussion.</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Export of the Cuban Revolution:</hi> Important
                            segments of Latin American opinion appear at first to have been
                            sympathetic to the carrying out within Cuba of <persName
                                corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>’s revolutionary program and to
                            have applauded the new Cuban Government’s assumption of a role of
                            leadership against the remaining dictatorships. However, there now
                            appears to be a growing realization that <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                                >Castro</persName> and his entourage view themselves as the
                            forerunners of a new type of social revolution which is to sweep the
                            Caribbean and Latin America; that for this purpose they have disregarded
                            and attempted to discredit the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> and
                            the principles of non-intervention and sought to appeal to Latin
                            American public sentiment over the heads of Government; and that despite
                            denials, they have actively supported revolutionary expeditionary forces
                            in efforts to overthrow other Caribbean Governments.</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Communism and the Cuban Revolution:</hi> Largely
                            through the efforts of the press, there has been increasing awareness
                            throughout the hemisphere that there exists a real problem in the
                            attitudes of <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> and his
                            Revolutionary leadership towards Communism, in the inter-relationships
                            between the immediate objectives of international Communism in Latin
                            America and <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>’s immediate
                            aims, and in the degree of infiltration and influence of the Cuban
                            Communist Party in the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>
                            regime. Although interpretations continue to differ widely throughout
                            the hemisphere as to the extent and significance of the influence of the
                            Communist Party in Cuba, there appears to have been some awakening to a
                            realization that the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>
                            Revolution has adopted a course of at least limited ideological and
                            practical collaboration with Communism for immediate objectives similar
                            to that of Arévalo of Guatemala, Allende of Chile and the like, distinct
                            from the non-Communist Latin American social revolutionary trends
                            represented by <persName corresp="#p_BE1">Betancourt</persName> of
                            Venezuela, <persName corresp="#p_FFJ1">Figueres</persName> of Costa
                            Rica, the APRA of Peru, and the moderate elements of the Mexican and
                            Bolivian Revolutions. The extravagant and uncritical propaganda support
                            given <pb facs="0634" n="602" xml:id="pg_602"/> to <persName
                                corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> by Communist and pro-Communist
                            groups in most Latin American countries may also be a factor in the
                            awakening of moderate opinion to the implications of the spread of
                                <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>’s concepts of
                            revolution and anti-Americanism in terms of the advancement of Communist
                            objectives at the expense of indigenous Latin American social,
                            democratic trends as well as moderate and middle class interests.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is to the interest of the United States that the tendencies of Latin American
                    opinion to become skeptical of <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> on
                    the issues of dictatorship, intervention, and Communism be intensified and
                    accelerated. Whether the end result of the pressure of Latin American opinion on
                    these issues is to cause <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> to adopt
                    more acceptable attitudes and courses of action or to reduce his public support,
                    the United States objective of isolating and eventually eliminating the
                    undesirable aspects of <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>’s
                    Revolution will be served. It remains important, however, particularly at this
                    stage, that any awakening public skepticism about <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Castro</persName> retain the appearance of being an indigenous Latin
                    American reaction and that the overt statements and actions of the United States
                    singly or cumulatively give no semblance of an effort on the part of this
                    Government to discredit <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> Responsibility</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There may be exceptional opportunities in which <gloss target="#t_USIS1"
                        >USIS</gloss> officers, principally the <gloss target="#t_PAO1">PAO</gloss>
                    and Information Officer, can help by personal contact or otherwise to achieve
                    the above-outlined objective. In such instances, <gloss target="#t_PAO1"
                        >PAO</gloss>’s should seek the prior specific approval of the Chief of
                    Mission and coordinate any action with other members of the country team
                    concerned. It is the intention of this Government that any information which may
                    assist in focusing Latin American opinion on the negative aspects of the
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> regime shall not be attributed
                    to any U.S. Government source and that there shall be no evident U.S. Government
                    connection with its origin. <gloss target="#t_PAO1">PAO</gloss>s must assure
                    that the utmost caution is used in making such information available to foreign
                    nationals, e.g., individuals controlling mass communication media. The only
                    exception, of course, would be statements or materials publicly issued on the
                    authority of the U.S. Government or its responsible officials.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Herter</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
