<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>379. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d379</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">379</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-01-01T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-12-31T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="rec6SOt1hMx6m4tne" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085495"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="recFwGxYjdvSQbu8A" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recdDEAik5EmT8luP" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="organization-of-american-states"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87007400"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Coast Guard</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recsJ9GxScV9mRtjF" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-31T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-01T06:00:00-05:00" n="379" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d379">
                <head>379. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On October 26, the Cuban Government staged a mass rally in front of the
                    Presidential Palace in Havana.</p>
                <p>During the rally the Embassy in Havana submitted to the Department a series of
                    telegraphic situation reports. These reports dealt with the mood of the crowd
                    being assembled, the volume of automobile and truck traffic around the Embassy,
                    the degree of security being provided the Embassy by the Cuban authorities, and
                    the tone and content of the various speeches delivered at the rally. Among the
                    first speakers were <persName corresp="#p_SD1">David Salvador</persName>, former
                    Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_APR1">Roberto Agramonte</persName>, and
                    President Dorticos, followed by the Chief of the Army <persName corresp="#p_CC1"
                        >Camilo Cienfuegos</persName>, who made a “definitely inflammatory speech.”
                    Che <persName corresp="#p_GSEC1">Guevara</persName> spoke next. The Embassy
                    considered his speech “not inflammatory,” but “exceptionally provocative toward
                    the United States.” The Embassy called a subsequent speech by Raul <persName
                        corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> “inflammatory” and noted that it had
                    stirred up “considerable feelings.” The final speaker was <persName
                        corresp="#p_CRF1">Fidel Castro</persName>, whose speech the Embassy
                    described as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Speech was highly inflammatory and pro-revolutionary. By same token as
                            strongly anti-American as anything he has ever done. He listed virtually
                            all local American interests as items which were not <pb facs="0675"
                                n="643" xml:id="pg_643"/> in the interests of Cuba. He talked of
                            controlling utilities and of new mining and petroleum laws. He got
                            approval From audience for re-establishment of revolutionary tribunals.
                            He got approval of execution of <persName corresp="#p_MH2"
                                >Matos</persName> and others. He repeatedly mentioned Cuban people
                            fighting to last man in caves and tunnels if necessary to repel foreign
                            invasion. He worked on theme of unreasoning fear of United States
                            Government and people of communism. He displayed his mastery in speaking
                            and in controlling audience to exceptional degree.</p>
                        <p>“Crowd was with him to the last man in his exhortations to continue work
                            of revolution, which intended to achieve the good life for all Cubans
                            regardless of opposition and attacks.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Following the rally, the Embassy reported that there were no signs of crowds near
                    the Embassy building or hostile demonstrations and that it had received reports
                    from Santiago and Guantanamo that all was quiet there. The Embassy forwarded its
                    preliminary estimate that trouble was unlikely. These situation reports were
                    combined into an unnumbered telegram from Havana, October 26. (Department of
                    State, Central Files, 737.00/10–2659) In telegram 930 from Havana, October 26,
                        <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> briefly summarized the
                    proceedings at the rally and stated that there was no necessity to change either
                    the text of the proposed note to the Cuban Government or his plans for
                    presenting it to Dorticos and Roa the following day. (<hi rend="italic"
                        >ibid</hi>., 611.37/10–2659)</p>
                <p>On October 27 at 12:10 p.m., Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> telephoned <persName corresp="#p_BJB1">Julian
                        Baird</persName> of the Department of the Treasury, in the absence of
                    Secretary of Treasury <persName corresp="#p_ARB1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Anderson</hi>
                    </persName> and Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SFCJ1"
                    >Scribner</persName>. According to a memorandum of their conversation: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Secy said he just wanted to express his personal concern about what is
                            going on from Florida to Cuba. Secy said Treasury people have been most
                            helpful. <persName corresp="#p_BJB1">Baird</persName> asked if there was
                            anything further Customs or the Coast Guard could do to be helpful and
                            Secy said he felt they were doing everything they could. <persName
                                corresp="#p_BJB1">Baird</persName> said if there was anything
                            further that could be done to just let them know and they will activate
                            the necessary action.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>At 12:30 p.m., <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> called White House
                    Press Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HJC1">Hagerty</persName> to say that, with
                    respect to Cuba, “we have taken a good many steps in this country, altho we may
                    have to review our laws to permit tighter controls.” <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> also expressed his hope that in his press conference
                    scheduled for the following day, the President could “go very strong in saying
                    we have mobilized all our resources to stop this.”</p>
                <p>At 12:35 p.m., <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> discussed the matter
                    with Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_RWB1">Rogers</persName>. A
                    memorandum of their conversation reads: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“[The Secretary] said we certainly ought to use every facility we have to
                            control the situation, and Secy said the President will probably be
                            asked about this in his press conference tomorrow. Secy said he thinks
                            we ought to study our present laws on this. <persName corresp="#p_RWB1"
                                >Rogers</persName> said from the standpoint of the criminal law now
                            on the books, there is nothing we can do since there was nothing
                            inflammatory in the leaflets. <persName corresp="#p_RWB1"
                                >Rogers</persName>, <pb facs="0676" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/> said,
                            however, there may be some aviation regulations which he has violated
                            and the FA A could prevent this. <persName corresp="#p_RWB1"
                                >Rogers</persName> said we could issue a warning statement that any
                            plane used for this purpose would be seized by the Government. <persName
                                corresp="#p_RWB1">Rogers</persName> said what he had in mind was a
                            statement worked out between State, <gloss target="#t_FAA1">FAA</gloss>,
                            Customs and Justice which would be a warning to anybody else trying this
                            and then President could indicate we have done all we can. <persName
                                corresp="#p_RWB1">Rogers</persName> said he was really not
                            enthusiastic about taking legal action for past things, but, if we serve
                            warning and then take action against future infractions we are on solid
                            ground. <persName corresp="#p_RWB1">Rogers</persName> said for instance
                            this fellow actually telephoned and asked about regulations which might
                            be violated if he did this and was told there were no regulations which
                            he would violate. <persName corresp="#p_RWB1">Rogers</persName> said
                            most criminal law requires that a person willfully violate the law and
                            that he could argue he had inquired about regulations and were told
                            there were none. <persName corresp="#p_RWB1">Rogers</persName> suggested
                            State get in touch with Yeagley in his office to work out a warning
                            statement.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>At 12:40 p.m. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> called Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName> and asked that he contact the
                    Department of Justice regarding the flights to Cuba. Their conversation
                    continued as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“<persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName> said we are, of course
                            getting out the <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> statement.
                            Secy expressed surprise that this was being done automatically since
                            Secy felt it should be reviewed by the President before it is put out.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName> said <persName
                                corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> had told them it was to be
                            released as soon as <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> saw
                            the President. Secy said it was probably too late to stop it now, but
                            President should certainly be alerted to this and that the President
                            should have known about it before it was released; Secy said he had only
                            seen it himself last night.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Fifteen minutes later <persName corresp="#p_DJC1">Dreier</persName> called
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> to say that <persName
                        corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> was then meeting with President
                    Dorticos. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> asked for a summary of
                    the statement which he could show to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName> when he met with him later that afternoon. Memoranda
                    of all these telephone conversations are in Eisenhower Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> Papers, Telephone Conversations.</p>
                <p>The text of the statement made by <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName>
                    to Dorticos and <persName corresp="#p_RR1">Roa</persName> on October 27, which
                    was subsequently released to the public, is printed in Department of State <hi
                        rend="italic">Bulletin,</hi> November 16, 1959, pages 715–718. The statement
                    was summarized in a memorandum of October 27 from <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>, which, according to a handwritten marginal notation,
                        <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> himself carried to the White
                    House. According to the memorandum, the purpose of the statement was as follows: <list>
                        <item>“(a) To clarify for public opinion in the United States, in Cuba, and
                            Latin America that the responsibility for deteriorated Cuban-United
                            States relations lies in a deliberate, concerted effort on the part of
                            the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> regime to stimulate
                            anti-American feeling despite this Government’s correct and restrained
                            policy.</item>
                        <item>“(b) To answer charges and distortions which <persName
                                corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> has made vociferously in Cuba,
                            e.g. that United States officials support or countenance clandestine
                            bombing raids over Cuba.</item>
                        <pb facs="0677" n="645" xml:id="pg_645"/>
                        <item>“(c) To encourage and give leadership to the more responsible elements
                            in Cuba who oppose Castro’s extremism.” (Department of State, Central
                            Files, 611.37/10–2759)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Shortly after 3 p.m. on October 27, <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>
                    met at the White House with President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>, Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MLT1"
                        >Merchant</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_EMJSD1">Major John S.D.
                        Eisenhower</persName>. According to Major <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>’s memorandum of the conversation, the subject of Cuba
                    was discussed as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> then brought up the
                            matter of Cuba, which is extremely uncomfortable at this time. Justice,
                            Defense, and State are working together, attempting to stop the
                            activities of counterrevolutionaries working out of Florida. These
                            efforts are handicapped by the fact that private planes fly out of 200
                            airfields in the State of Florida alone; furthermore, our laws on this
                            subject are weak and it is nearly impossible to obtain convictions. He
                            pointed out that the Air National Guard and Governor Collins of Florida
                            are being very helpful. Collins does not desire that Florida develop a
                            reputation as a hotbed of counterrevolutionaries. The President thought
                            we could take some measure such as stationing inspectors at all major
                            airfields, but admitted it was impossible to police them all. He
                            questioned why the Cubans don’t just shoot the airplanes down. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> said the Cubans have
                            been behaving very badly, particularly in connection with the Lanz case.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> is talking to
                            President Dorticos today. <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName>
                            cannot obtain an audience with <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                                >Castro</persName> who, in the Secretary’s opinion, shows signs of
                            increasing mental instability. Whenever <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                                >Castro</persName> gets into trouble, he solves his problem by
                            holding a violent mass meeting. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                                >Herter</persName> showed the President a statement which <persName
                                corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> will use in his discussion with
                            Dorticos. The President read the statement and said this matter may come
                            up in press conference tomorrow.” (Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, DDE
                            Diaries; the memorandum is also published in part in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Declassified Documents, 1981,</hi> 2221.)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>At his press conference on October 28, President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName> was asked to comment on <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Fidel Castro</persName>’s behavior. The President replied that the history
                    of U.S.-Cuban relations “would seem to make it a puzzling matter to figure out
                    just exactly why the Cubans and the Cuban Government would be so unhappy when,
                    after all, their principal market is right here, their best market. You would
                    think they would want good relationships. I don’t know exactly what the
                    difficulty is.”</p>
                <p>Later in the press conference, the President was asked whether he had ordered any
                    Federal agency to try to stop the illegal flights from Florida to Cuba. The
                    President replied: “I’ve gone through the civil angle rather than the military
                    angle. The Attorney General doesn’t just have orders, but he is really using
                    every kind of reinforced means he can to make sure that there is no violation of
                    this kind.” He noted how difficult a task it was to monitor private airfields
                    and airplanes and <pb facs="0678" n="646" xml:id="pg_646"/> indicated that the
                    State of Florida was cooperating in the effort. (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers
                        of the Presidents of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Dwight
                            D. Eisenhower</persName>, 1959,</hi> pages 751 and 753)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
