<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>414. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                    Affairs (Rubottom) to the Under Secretary of State () to the Under Secretary of
                    State (Dillon))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d414</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">414</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-12-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec0YIEoMSlyPKAGO" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="general-agreement-on-tariffs-and-trade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001009859"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">GATT</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-12-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-12-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="414"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d414">
                <head>414. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1" type="from">Rubottom</persName>) to the
                    Under Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_DCD1" type="to"
                        >Dillon</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d414fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, Central Files, 737.00/12–3059. Confidential. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_VEE1">Vallon</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_LTG1">Leonhardy</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_THR1"
                            >Turkel</persName>; concurred in by <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_P1">P</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss>;
                        and initialed by <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-12-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 28, 1959</hi>.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Action Program on Cuba</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Agreement was reached in <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> early in December
                    that the United States Government could no longer tolerate the continued
                    harassment of American property owners in Cuba, the failure of that government
                    to respond in a positive way to our repeated efforts to seek a friendly solution
                    to the problem of expropriation, and the vicious, unjustified attacks by the
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> government on the United
                    States.</p>
                <p>Although our attitude of patience and forbearance in the conduct of our relations
                    with Cuba has generally won approval in Latin America and in the United States
                    press, it is believed that in the face of these continuous provocations the time
                    has come for the United States Government to assume a more openly critical and
                    challenging posture vis-à-vis Cuba in order that our attitude to date may not be
                    considered a sign of weakness and thus give encouragement to
                    communist-nationalist elements elsewhere in Latin America who are trying to
                    advance programs similar to those of <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                        >Castro</persName>. Such programs, if undertaken, could only result in
                    undermining United States prestige abroad, <pb facs="0749" n="717"
                        xml:id="pg_717"/> exposing United States property owners to treatment
                    similar to that being received in Cuba and, in general, prejudicing the program
                    of economic development espoused by the United States for Latin America which
                    relies so heavily on private capital investment.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> believes actions can and should be taken,
                    beginning immediately, which would affirmatively undertake to overcome the
                    present impasse in our relations with Cuba. It is, therefore, proposed that the
                    following program in the time sequence indicated be instituted by the
                    Department.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Protection of American Property Owners Against
                                Harassment.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is proposed that a firmly worded, formal note be delivered early next
                            week to the Cuban Government in effect protesting the continued
                            harassment of American property owners. The note would relate to the
                            occupation of properties, seizure of land, cattle and equipment,
                            intervention in operations and other extra-legal, or quasi-legal
                            activities to which these Americans have been subjected and the fact
                            that in almost all cases they have been deprived of their rights under
                            due process of law.</p>
                        <p>It is proposed that the substance of the note be widely publicized after
                            its delivery.</p>
                        <p>Although it is not believed that the note will produce a cessation of
                            these offensive actions, its delivery and publication is considered
                            essential as a first outward step in the change of approach to the
                            Government of Cuba mentioned earlier, and as part of the record which
                            may be needed in an eventual judicial contest under international claims
                            procedures.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Resolution of the Expropriation Problem.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is proposed that, following his return to Habana on approximately
                            January 11, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> be
                            instructed to renew discussions with Cuban officials looking toward a
                            mutually satisfactory settlement of the problem of fair valuation and
                            satisfactory terms of compensation, including a proposal that the Cuban
                            Government voluntarily impose a tax (say 1 or 1–1/2 cent per lb.) on
                            sugar exports to the United States, to create a fund to be used for
                            compensating American owners of expropriated properties.</p>
                        <p>Upon failure to reach agreement, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BPW1"
                                >Bonsal</persName> would then be authorized to propose the
                            submission of the problem to a Bi-national Commission, to an arbitration
                            commission under the auspices of the International Court of Justice or
                            to the Court itself.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, and on the presumption that the Cuban Government will turn
                            down these proposals, the United States Government would undertake the
                            steps necessary to relieve itself of all contractual obligations of the
                                <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> as they relate to Cuba. This
                            would include the <pb facs="0750" n="718" xml:id="pg_718"/> denunciation
                            of the United States-Cuban Trade Agreement of 1934<note n="2"
                                xml:id="d414fn2">Signed August 24, 1934, and subsequently amended;
                                for text of the original agreement, see 49 Stat. 2559.</note> and
                            the Convention of Reciprocity of 1902.<note n="3" xml:id="d414fn3"
                                >Signed December 11, 1902; for text, see 33 Stat. 2136.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>These steps are essential and preliminary to <gloss target="#t_ARA1"
                                >ARA</gloss>’s final proposal which is the unilateral imposition by
                            the United States of an appropriate tax on all Cuban imports, the
                            proceeds of which would be used to create a fund with which to settle
                            claims of expropriated United States interests.</p>
                        <p>The details of this plan are contained in the <persName corresp="#p_WWA1"
                                >Wieland</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1"
                                >Rubottom</persName> memorandum of December 9, 1959 (Tab A).<note
                                n="4" xml:id="d414fn4">
                                <ref target="#d406">Document 406</ref>.</note> The details of the
                            plan are now under consideration by the legal division and have not yet
                            been cleared.</p>
                        <p>Although this procedure will undoubtedly take time to execute, it is
                            believed that the sequence proposed will help publicly to re-confirm the
                            correct and reasonable posture of the United States in dealing with Cuba
                            and the United States Government’s respect for its international
                            commitments. At the same time, it will permit firm dealing with the
                            recalcitrant <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> government
                            and provide for the eventual compensation of United States property
                            owners.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Publicizing the Program.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is believed that each proposal made to the Cubans, and each action
                            taken by the United States Government in carrying out the program
                            outlined in 1 and 2 above, should be accompanied by appropriate
                            publicity in order to insure that the position of United States
                            Government is made crystal clear at every step of the way.</p>
                        <p>As a first move in this direction it is proposed that, upon the departure
                            of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> for Cuba on
                            or about January 11, the Secretary publicly announce that he has
                            instructed the Ambassador to seek an immediate resumption of discussions
                            with the Cubans looking toward a friendly and mutually satisfactory
                            resolution of the expropriation and other problems confronting the two
                            governments. The Secretary would state that this effort in no way
                            implies a modification of the traditional United States position
                            favoring reasonable and legitimate agrarian reform intended to improve
                            the economic condition of peoples. He would, however emphasize our firm
                            belief that any expropriation measure carries with it the obligation,
                            long recognized under international law, for prompt, adequate and
                            effective compensation.</p>
                        <p>It is further proposed that appropriate public pronouncements by the
                            Secretary or other officials of the Department accompany the initiation
                            of the remaining proposals and action measures included in the
                            program.</p>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="0751" n="719" xml:id="pg_719"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Sugar Legislation.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Between the tenth and twentieth of January it may be expected that
                            several bills will be introduced into the Congress to modify and extend
                            existing sugar legislation. One of these will certainly be an
                            Administration bill which will include a provision granting the
                            President discretionary authority to revise foreign sugar quotas.</p>
                        <p>At the time the Administration’s position is made public, there will be
                            an excellent opportunity at a press conference to state the fundamental
                            position of the United States with respect to Cuba. It is, therefore,
                            proposed that at the time the legislation is introduced or shortly
                            thereafter, a presidential pronouncement should be made on this subject,
                            perhaps in the form of questions and answers as suggested in Tab B
                                attached.<note n="5" xml:id="d414fn5">Not printed.</note>
                        </p>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Enlisting the Cooperation of Other Latin American
                                Governments.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Foreign Minister of Brazil recently indicated to Ambassador
                                Cabot<note n="6" xml:id="d414fn6">This conversation has not been
                                further identified.</note> his concern regarding developments in
                            Cuba. Our Ambassador believes that given sufficient encouragement and
                            assurance of support, the Brazilians may be disposed to “point the
                            finger” at events in Cuba.</p>
                        <p>In order to determine the extent to which this feeling may be shared by
                            other Latin American Govenments, it is proposed that an instruction be
                            sent to all Latin American Missions outlining the position of the United
                            States Government with respect to Cuba and authorizing them to convey
                            these views to the host government. They would, at the same time, be
                            authorized to elicit the reaction of the government to this policy and
                            discreetly inquire as to the government’s own views on developments in
                            Cuba and its relations with the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                                >Castro</persName> regime. The instruction would have the dual
                            objective of clarifying the United States Government’s change of
                            approach in its policy toward Cuba, including the reasons for such
                            change and sounding out the possibilities for a stiffening of attitudes
                            toward Cuba by the other American Republics. At a subsequent time and
                            depending upon the kind of responses received, further consultations
                            with Latin American Governments may be undertaken looking toward some
                            kind of multilateral action on the Cuban question.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Countering the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                                    >Castro</persName> Propaganda Offensive.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Agreement has been reached with <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> for
                            the full time assignment to <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> of Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_CRG1">Richard Cushing</persName>. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_CRG1">Cushing</persName> will report on
                            January 11. It is proposed that he undertake the coordination of an
                            intensive though discreet campaign to counter the vicious “Hate America”
                            propaganda being spread throughout Latin America and the world by the
                                <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> Government. He will
                            use all available material including “sanitized” intelligence reports in
                            preparing a steady output for all media, not only presenting the United
                            States side of the Cuban question but mounting our own offensive in this
                            particular “cold war”.</p>
                    </item>
                    <pb facs="0752" n="720" xml:id="pg_720"/>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Supporting Operations.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_FSO1">FSO</gloss>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GGO1">George Gray</persName>, on transfer from
                                Rome and now in the Department for orientation and briefing, will
                                proceed to Habana early in January to work exclusively on problems
                                connected with the Cuban Government’s actions against American
                                property owners. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GGO1">Gray</persName> is
                                a lawyer and has already established close working relations with
                                    <gloss target="#t_CMA1">CMA</gloss> and the legal
                                division.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>The legal division has assigned Mr. <persName>Fabian A.
                                    Kwiatek</persName> to work with <gloss target="#t_CMA1"
                                    >CMA</gloss> on the legal aspects of the program described in 1
                                and 2 above. Mr. <persName>Kwiatek</persName> will assume
                                responsibility for clearing all steps contemplated in this program
                                with the various branches of the legal division. He will also
                                propose alternative course of action as necessary.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HC1">Carlos Hall</persName>, Director of
                                RAR, will give priority to all research requests connected with the
                                Cuban problem.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>That you approve the submission of a firmly worded note to the Cuban
                        Government in effect protesting the continued harassment of American
                        property owners.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>That you approve the procedures outlined in section 2 above looking toward
                        the resolution of the problem of expropriation of American properties in
                        Cuba.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>That you approve the proposal that appropriate publicity accompany these
                        actions.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>That you approve a pronouncement by the President which would set forth
                        the fundamental position of the United States with respect to Cuba, such
                        announcement to be made upon the publication of the Administration’s
                        position on sugar legislation.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>That you approve an instruction to our Missions in Latin America
                        requesting that they present the United States Government position in regard
                        to Cuba and eliciting the host government’s reaction thereto.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>That you approve the initiation of a discreet campaign to counter the
                        anti-American propaganda of the <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                            >Castro</persName> government.<note n="7" xml:id="d414fn7">
                            <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> initialed approval of
                            recommendations 1, 3, 4, 5, and 6 on December 30. He neither approved
                            nor disapproved recommendation 2. Regarding his reaction to this
                            recommendation, see <ref target="#d415fn4">footnote 4, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >infra</hi>
                            </ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
