<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>436. Memorandum of a Conference With the President, White House, Washington,
                    January 25, 1960, 11:15–11:55 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d436</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">436</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1960-01-25T11:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1960-01-25T11:55:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJK3er8LLa5C5DW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88003543"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Anti-American</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recMHJD4XLL5GtXeu" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Emissary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-01-25T11:55:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-01-25T11:15:00-05:00" n="436"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d436">
                <head>436. Memorandum of a Conference With the President, White House, Washington,
                    January 25, 1960, 11:15–11:55 a.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d436fn1"
                        >Source: Eisenhower Library, Whitman File, DDE Diaries. Secret. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_GBGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName> on January 26. The
                        time of the meeting is taken from the President’s Appointment Book. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.) Also published in <hi rend="italic"
                            >Declassified Documents, 1981</hi>, 123 C.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1960-01-25T11:15:00-05:00"
                            to="1960-01-25T11:55:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 25, 1960</hi>, <hi rend="italic">11:15–11:55
                                a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>OTHERS PRESENT</head>
                    <item>Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>, Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName>, Generals <persName
                            corresp="#p_PGWB1">Persons</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GBGAJ1"
                            >Goodpaster</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> said Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> had not wanted to return from Cuba. He
                    feels that a danger to U.S. citizens there may develop, and did not wish to be
                    away in that event. He was instructed to return, however, because Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> felt our Ambassador should not be
                    subjected to indignities. The President asked as to the experience of the
                    Spanish Ambassador on his departure, and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BPW1"
                        >Bonsal</persName> said that he was subjected to indignities. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> said the Cuban Government is trying to
                    link the U.S. to Spain through the President’s visit with Franco.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d436fn2">President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>
                        visited Spain December 21–22, 1959.</note> The President said he had gone to
                    Spain among other reasons as a means of showing a courtesy toward
                    Spanish-speaking people—a courtesy which he thought the Latin Americans would
                    appreciate.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> said there is a great
                    concern among responsible people in Cuba regarding the arming of workers and
                    peasants. He said that <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>’s group
                    think that they have discovered something new called “democratic humanism.” They
                    claim they are not anti-religious, but are trying to carry out agrarian reforms
                    which the church has supported in times past. He added that the church is trying
                    hard not to break with <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>. The
                    President said that <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> begins to look
                        <pb facs="0796" n="764" xml:id="pg_764"/> like a mad man. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> said he is a very conspiratorial
                    individual who tries to create the impression that he and Cuba are beleaguered.
                    He is an extreme Leftist and is strongly anti-American.</p>
                <p>The President said his great current problem is to keep the Congress from running
                    out completely on the sugar bill. He thought the best plan is to give the power
                    of decision to the President. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName>
                    said the press will probably ask what we plan to do regarding the sugar bill.
                    The President thought it was best simply to say that we will be sending
                    something to the Congress on this.</p>
                <p>The President said he thought the best course of action in the hemisphere would
                    be if the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> went down the line for us in
                    trying to put some restraints on <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>.
                    There may be a problem in Venezuela, he recognized.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> said Mexico is also a
                    problem—probably the greatest—but commented that <persName corresp="#p_LMA1"
                        >Lopez-Mateos</persName> has said he deplores the resort to
                    non-constitutional procedures. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1"
                        >Rubottom</persName> said it would be hard to get the fourteen votes
                    required in the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> to support the United States
                    point of view, and that even if they were obtained, the <gloss target="#t_OAS1"
                        >OAS</gloss> action would not be effective in Cuba. He thought the only
                    solution would come through the development of a moderate and responsible force
                    from within Cuba. This he thought would probably take many months. The President
                    said that supposing the situation gets worse, he would not desert our citizens.
                    If the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> is not going to support us, they show
                    themselves as fair weather friends and we may have to take other action. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> said in such circumstances
                    the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> might act along the lines we suggest.
                    This would not, however, bring a full solution, and it is better to let a
                    moderate native force build up. The President said that, if it comes to such
                    conditions, we could quarantine Cuba. If they (the Cuban people) are hungry,
                    they will throw <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> out. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> said we should not punish the
                    whole Cuban people for the acts of one abnormal man. The President said that of
                    course he agreed with this.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> next showed the President a
                    draft of a proposed statement.<note n="3" xml:id="d436fn3">Not found. In his
                        memoirs, <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> noted that he was
                        primarily responsible for the draft. (<persName corresp="#p_BPW1"
                            >Bonsal</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Cuba, <persName corresp="#p_CRF1"
                                >Castro</persName>, and the United States</hi>, p. 121. Regarding
                        the further drafting of the statement and its release on January 26, see
                            <ref target="#d438">Document 438</ref>.</note> The President edited this
                    and asked that certain further revisions be made, and that it be resubmitted
                    then.</p>
                <p>The President asked if there are evident Communist activities in Cuba. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> said the Communists have a
                    very active newspaper, and that many of the foreigners who hold influential
                    positions in the Cuban Government are under Communist influence. The President
                    asked how Cuba could make a living if it was unable to sell its sugar. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> said the present government
                    had not thought that problem <pb facs="0797" n="765" xml:id="pg_765"/> out. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> commented that a Cuban
                    emissary is now travelling in Latin America trying to build up support for a
                    meeting of the “underprivileged” countries and is getting a very cold reception.
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> said the Cubans are trying to
                    whittle down the free world and enlarge the number of uncommitted countries.</p>
                <p>The President said he was very favorably impressed with President <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMA1">Lopez-Mateos</persName> of Mexico and was hopeful he could
                    have some influence in the situation. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1"
                        >Rubottom</persName> said that <persName corresp="#p_LMA1"
                        >Lopez-Mateos</persName> is still on his trip through Latin America.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> commented that Mexico’s
                    voting record in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> has not been too good
                    from our point of view. They have voted against us on a number of occasions. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName> said this results largely
                    from a single individual, Padilla Nervo. Others such as the Foreign Minister and
                    the Ambassador in Washington are most helpful.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Herter</persName> said he foresaw two questions,
                    the first on sugar. The President said on this he would simply say the matter is
                    being studied and something will be sent to Congress. The President thought it
                    should be stressed that the Cubans will not voluntarily accept Communist
                    dictatorship over their individual lives. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HCA1"
                        >Herter</persName> said the second question is whether our Ambassador is
                    going back. The President thought on that [that?] he would say that no decision
                    has been made.</p>
                <p>The President asked that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRRJ1">Rubottom</persName>
                    inform Senator <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> and Congressman
                        <persName corresp="#p_MGD1">Morgan</persName> that he plans to make a
                    friendly but firm statement on this matter. With regard to the recall of the
                    Cuban Ambassador, the President said that we would say no decision has yet been
                    made. He asked whether there had been any demonstration against Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> on the latter’s departure. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BPW1">Bonsal</persName> said there had not been. The people were
                    quite friendly. A number of his colleagues came out to be present at his
                    departure.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GBGAJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">G.</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Brigadier General, <gloss target="#t_USA1">USA</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
