<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-08-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="22" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d22">
                        <head>22. Telegram 360 to Geneva<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d22fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/8–255. Secret;
                                Niact. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MWP_1">McConaughy</persName>; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">Dulles</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-08-03">August 3, 1955, 7:50
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d22-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d22-1"/>
                        <p>360. For <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>. Your 244
                            section 2 and Deptel 349.</p>
                        <p>Chicom points one and four obviously require some time for study. As to
                            these two points, the pace should not RPT not be forced. You might
                            suggest they be deferred until after brief recess. This would enable you
                            in your discretion make quick visit your post. In meantime points will
                            be receiving full consideration here.</p>
                        <p>Point two met by our blanket statement as to non-interference with
                            departure of Chinese which you have been authorized to make and by first
                            sentence second para our 349. Point three met by our telegram 347.</p>
                        <p>It seems to us that, given full satisfaction we have afforded on points
                            two and three, you are in strong position to press insistently for
                            release forthwith of all Americans. Hope you will be able make <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> feel that next move up to his
                            Government and that only immediate all-inclusive action on US nationals
                            will meet obligation resting on his Government in existing
                            circumstances.</p>
                        <p>FYI we are considering with top people of Immigration and Naturalization
                            Service certain problems which may arise as to Chinese aliens of various
                            categories resident in US.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1"><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>