<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-11-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-11-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="354" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                        <head>354. Telegram 1162 to Geneva<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d354fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/11–855. Secret;
                                Priority; Limit Distribution. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MWP_1">McConaughy</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CRN_1">Clough</persName>; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_RWS_1">Robertson</persName> and in
                            S/S.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-11-08">November 8, 1955, 8:01
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d354-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d354-1"/>
                        <p>1162. For <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Instructions for 25th meeting.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Tax <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> severely with
                                violation secrecy agreement represented by Daily Worker
                                article.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Department considers your revised draft renunciation of force
                                statement (your 1099) excellent. You should present it this meeting
                                unless Secretary instructs otherwise.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>By introducing draft renunciation of force statement first
                                followed by Daily Worker leak Communists have taken initiative from
                                us on this subject. Their violation agreement on private nature
                                talks makes essential for us to regain initiative and provides
                                opportunity place our case graphically before world. Subject to
                                Secretary’s concurrence you should inform <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> that unilateral release by his
                                side of substance last meeting leaves you no recourse but to set
                                record straight by releasing explanatory statement together with our
                                draft renunciation of force declaration (your 1099) immediately
                                following meeting. While publication our statement would tend to
                                freeze our negotiating position, in our view there is nothing
                                    <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> could seriously
                                object to in paragraphs one through four, and paragraphs six and
                                eight are so tightly drawn, we could not accept change in any case.
                                Explanatory statement mentioned above would be substance of
                                statement <pb facs="d354-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d354-2"/>
                                Deptel 789 as amended Deptel 805 with minor revisions. Department’s
                                suggested text will follow Wednesday.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Implementation Agreed Announcement. You should remind <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> that two months have passed
                                since PRC declared it would <pb facs="0539" n="492" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_492"/> adopt appropriate measures permit Americans
                                expeditiously return. Only two of nineteen Americans permitted
                                depart during this lengthy period. Letter from only one of remaining
                                seventeen so far has been received by British Charge and Charge has
                                not been permitted see any of them. US Govt and people will judge
                                dependence to be placed on PRC promises by its performance.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Military Personnel. Concur your omitting subject this meeting.
                                Department exploring with Defense possibility raising again in MAC,
                                but this complicated by fact that in past lists presented there
                                included all missing UN personnel, not just American.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Embargo. Listen to what <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> has to say but refrain from substantive
                                discussion this subject.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Repeat to Secretary.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HH_1"><hi rend="strong">Hoover</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>