<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-04-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="563" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d563">
                        <head>563. Letter 37 from <persName corresp="#p_MWP_1">McConaughy</persName>
                            to <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d563fn1">Source: Department of State, Geneva
                                Talks Files, Lot 72D415. Secret; Official–Informal.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">Letter No. 37</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-04-06">April 6,
                                1956</date></dateline>
                            <salute>Dear Alex:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d563-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d563-1"/>
                        <p>You were probably in Paris when we sent you the wire inviting your
                            comments on the prospective rearrangement of our renunciation of force
                            formula. We still want your comments, although since we sent you the
                            initial telegram, the Secretary has approved the idea and your <pb facs="0946" n="899" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_899"/> guidance
                            telegram for the next meeting has been dispatched. Since you will not
                            submit the reformulation at the next meeting on April 9 but merely
                            intimate there will be a new draft later, there is still time for us to
                            consider your reaction.</p>
                        <p>Our thought is that the reformulation will provide a further test of
                            Chinese Communist attitudes and will afford another token of our desire
                            to reconcile the opposing positions. We have changed the reference to
                            the Taiwan area so that it is no longer contiguous to the reference to
                            the right of individual and collective self defense. We have adhered to
                            the wording of their draft at every place where we could, and we have
                            given them a peg on which they can gracefully hang a modification of
                            their position, if they have any desire to come to an agreement. We
                            doubt that <pb facs="d563-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d563-2"/>
                            they will accept the new formula but we at least have something to gain
                            tactically by introducing it, and we do not depart from our essential
                            position. The redraft is the work of Judge Phleger. It was approved by
                            the Secretary on the afternoon of April 4 when he reviewed the entire
                            course of recent developments at Geneva.</p>
                        <p>While there may not be much material for new discussions in this
                            revision, it does at least give you a little something to chew on and
                            should take care of the meetings through the 26th of April, which is the
                            earliest date on which <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> could
                            give a Peiping reply to a revised draft introduced on April 19.</p>
                        <p>We told you in the guidance telegram yesterday about our decision to have
                            I &amp; N. S. actually ascertain if deportation would be possible in
                            each of the 50 cases of Chinese aliens in the U.S. penitentiaries. This
                            is quite a project, but the preliminary survey seems worth while.
                            Enclosed is a copy of our letter requesting the survey which gives our
                            background thinking. We are aware of your view expressed in a recent
                            letter that deportation of Chinese prisoners would not bring about the
                            release of the American prisoners since the detention of the Americans
                            is linked to political demands. We agree with you that the Chinese
                            Communists are using the American prisoners to try to extort political
                            concessions, including a Foreign Minister’s Conference. But some of the
                            people working on the matter at this end believe that the release of
                            Chinese prisoners would at least give us a better club with which to
                            hammer the Chinese Communists on the prisoner issue and might well put
                            the Chinese Communists in dutch with even their neutralist friends if
                            they fail to release the Americans following release of Chinese <pb facs="d563-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d563-3"/> prisoners.
                            Although you have commented at length on this matter in a recent letter
                            to me we invited your reaction to this proposal so that we will be sure
                            that we have your latest view on this, and also that we may have it in
                            the official record.</p>
                        <pb facs="0947" n="900" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_900"/>
                        <p>I am not surprised that you discovered discrepancies in the figures given
                            in the new Defense Department list of missing military personnel. NA
                            discovered the same discrepancies in reviewing the figures and called
                            them to the attention of Defense. Corrected sheets have been prepared by
                            Defense for your book and are forwarded herewith. There is also enclosed
                            an additional sheet with detailed information on Captain Malcolm Edens
                            which should be filed under Tab 2 in your book.</p>
                        <p>There is enclosed a copy of the “accounting” given by the Chinese
                            Communists in UNCMAC last February. We delayed sending it to you
                            expecting a more detailed report from UNCMAC, but it later turned out
                            that this was all they had. As you will see it is far from satisfactory.
                            We have been working with Defense on an instruction to UNCMAC asking
                            further specific questions about the accounting. This has not yet gone
                            out due to clearance problems in Defense, but we expect it to go shortly
                            and we will see that you get a copy. The feeling here in both State and
                            Defense was that we should exhaust all possibilities in Panmunjom before
                            we ask you to bring the matter up again in Geneva.</p>
                        <p>The Prisoner Book which we would like back if you do not need it is a <pb facs="d563-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d563-4"/> gray loose
                            leaf binder containing miscellaneous memoranda and other documents
                            collected by <persName corresp="#p_MEW_1">Ed Martin</persName> when he
                            was Prisoner Officer here. Please send it by air pouch. <persName corresp="#p_ODL_1">Dave Osborn</persName> should be familiar with
                            it. With the increasing Congressional interest in the problem of
                            Americans detained in Communist China, and queries as to what the
                            Department has done about this problem in the past, we felt this book
                            would be needed more here than in Geneva.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS_1">Robertson</persName> is having a little
                            stomach trouble again and is supposed to be taking a rest in bed.
                            However he is insisting on staying on the job for at least a couple of
                            weeks. He is planning to take two weeks rest in bed around the end at
                            this month.</p>
                        <p>It was good to get your letter No. 26. Messrs. Phleger, <persName corresp="#p_RWS_1">Robertson</persName> and Sebald read it too and
                            we all found it of particular interest. We hope you and Pat had a good
                            relaxing Easter weekend in Paris.</p>
                        <p>Regards and good luck,</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MWP_1"><hi rend="strong">Walter P.
                                        McConaughy</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Enclosures: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>Additional Sheet for Tab 2 of Defense Book.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Copy of the “accounting” by Chinese Communists in
                                        UNCMAC.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Army Telegram No. FE 800650 from CINCUNC Tokyo.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Copy of letter to General Swing.</item>
                                </list></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>