<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-05-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="601" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d601">
                        <head>601. Telegram 1870 from Geneva<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d601fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                611.93/5–1156. Confidential; Priority; Limit
                            Distribution.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-05-11">May 11, 1956, 2
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d601-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d601-1"/>
                        <p>1870. From <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> opened this morning’s
                                meeting by presentation draft previously transmitted Dept together
                                with relatively brief statement which did nothing to clarify its
                                obvious ambiguities.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I avoided any specific comment and asked series of questions
                                designed to clarify its ambiguities. I specifically asked in what
                                way draft avoided prejudicing U.S. position; whether second para.
                                intentionally excluded disputes other than those Taiwan area;
                                whether “two months” in last para. was intended limit validity
                                declaration to that period; whether last para. as whole meant that
                                FonMin conference was “only practical and feasible means”; and
                                whether “to make specific arrangements” referred to “practical and
                                feasible means” or to FonMin conference.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>He avoided any direct response my first question, saying that
                                mutual respect clause was not only “common sense” but—“also” to be
                                found in UN Charter. In reply to second question he indicated that
                                limiting to Taiwan area dispute was deliberate because my emphasis
                                on Taiwan area and since if settlement that most critical dispute
                                could be effected without war other disputes would present no
                                problem. His replies to my questions on last para. were completely
                                evasive. However “very willing hear any ideas or suggestions” I may
                                have.</item>
                            <pb facs="d601-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d601-2"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>At close of this phase referring to his statements on
                                “procrastination” and our seeking “freeze” situation in Taiwan area,
                                I pointed out talks had not made further progress because of their
                                ambiguous position thus far on renouncing force.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>I made statement on implementation along lines para. 3 Deptel 1943
                                to which I replied along usual lines stressing that last December
                                they had asked for accounting Chinese in U.S. prisons, who, I could
                                not deny, desired return China, and we had no right inquire
                                concerning Americans in Chinese prisons until we made such
                                accounting.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Next meeting Thursday May 17.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Proceeding Prague Saturday returning Geneva Tuesday.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GFC_1"><hi rend="strong">Gowen</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>