<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>603. Telegram 1875 from Geneva</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v03mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d603</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">603</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-05-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-05-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-05-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="603"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d603">
                <head>603. Telegram 1875 from Geneva<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d603fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/5–1156. Confidential;
                        Limit Distribution.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-05-11"
                            >May 11, 1956, 7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d603-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d603-1"/>
                <p>1875. From <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> opened 46th today with prepared
                        statement: As he had specifically pointed out at last meeting, US in draft
                        submitted on April 19 still required their side give up sovereignty and
                        agree to freezing status quo Taiwan area with intention long procrastination
                        without opening FonMins conference so as to permit US continue its policy
                        seizure Taiwan and interference liberation offshore islands. This was what
                        his side absolutely could not accept.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said however taking into
                        consideration my repeated request proposed declaration explicitly apply
                        Taiwan area, his side willing make another effort by offering following
                        amendment. (Here <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> read text new
                        draft previously transmitted Mytel 1866.)</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said I would certainly notice
                        his new draft specifically applied to Taiwan area principle of settling
                        disputes between two countries by peaceful negotiations without resorting
                        threat or use of force. He considered this draft had fully accommodated all
                        reasonable portions my draft.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said however he must very
                        frankly point out Sino-American dispute Taiwan area must be separated from
                        China’s internal affairs. Any attempt to interfere China’s internal affairs
                        through ambiguous words absolutely not to be permitted.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said since I had repeatedly
                        indicated at last meeting US did not harbor any such intent their side
                        therefore <pb facs="d603-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d603-2"/>
                        considered new draft should be acceptable both sides.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said since proposed declaration
                        now made specifically applicable Taiwan area in accordance my request, it
                        therefore followed that seeking and ascertaining (Chinese word had sense of
                        “determining upon”) means for solving tensions in Taiwan area must also be
                        specified. In order forestall any possible long procrastination talks
                        following announcement declaration without making concrete arrangements
                        settle disputes their draft specified we should seek and ascertain practical
                        feasible means for realization this desire including making arrangements for
                        holding Sino-American conference FonMins within two months. He believed that
                        if both sides shared sincere desire for settlement two months should be
                        sufficient.</item>
                    <pb facs="1008" n="961" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_961"/>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said their draft also provides
                        in preamble announcement declaration should not be taken as precluding
                        principle mutual respect territorial integrity sovereignty non-interference
                        each other’s internal affairs. This self-evident.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said we now approaching ninth
                        month since starting discussions second item agenda. If US really desires as
                        repeatedly stated respect their views without requiring them abandon
                        sovereignty or position then they considered both sides should agree new
                        draft without delay.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>I replied I would comment subsequently in detail on new draft. However few
                        questions I would like ask in clarification to assist in consideration it.
                        First, he had spoken of respect for views each other concerning nature
                        origin our dispute Taiwan area. I would appreciate any amplification he
                        could give on how he perceived this draft respected views US.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>I said next I noticed that second para. as I read English translation
                        appealed limit entire declaration to dispute between two countries Taiwan
                        area. Instead being declaration general applicability also having specific
                        applicability Taiwan area it seemed be now drafted in form that had
                        applicability only Taiwan area. I would appreciate any amplification that
                        regard, was declaration not to have applicability any <pb facs="d603-3"
                            n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d603-3"/> dispute between us
                        elsewhere.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>I said I would also appreciate amplification last para. Without expressing
                        opinion on substance—he well knew my opinion that regard—it seemed me
                        language ambiguous. Ambiguous two respects, from my first cursory reading.
                        With inclusion words “within two months” did it mean that whole declaration
                        had effectiveness only two months? If agreement on practical feasible means
                        not arrived at within two months period, did he consider remainder
                        declaration no longer valid?</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>I said second ambiguous point, it seemed me was phrase concerning holding
                        FonMin conf. It not clear me as this read whether this saying only practical
                        feasible means realization common desire is holding conf Fon Mins or whether
                        it meant to say holding of conf Fon Mins one of practical feasible means to
                        be considered.</item>
                    <pb facs="d603-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d603-4"/>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>I said these were questions that immediately struck me on reading draft
                        and I asked them not in sense of making comments on draft. It seemed me that
                        they questions which clearly arose in interpreting and considering his
                        draft. As clear and specific answers as he could give would be of assistance
                        in consideration his draft. It in that sense I asked them.</item>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> replied he considered draft
                        submitted this morning quite clear in text. He had also made explanations
                        various paragraphs this draft during statement this morning. He had pointed
                        out this morning draft had taken into consideration and included those
                        portions my opinion <pb facs="1009" n="962" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_962"/>
                        which reasonable. This draft represented another effort their part help our
                        talks and arrive at agreement.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said according to first para
                        this text they would accord respect to sovereignty, territorial integrity US
                        and would not attempt impair or interfere in internal affairs US. In same
                        way they expected my country respect their rights their territorial
                        integrity and also not to try interfere and [garble—prejudice] their
                        internal affairs.</item>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said to them this para matter
                        common sense concerning rights sovereign states. Principles this para also
                        to be found in UN Charter specifically provided for in Charter.</item>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said if two countries could
                        adopt and agree on these principles stated in first para then he should say
                        we would thereby lay foundation for improvement relations between two
                        countries. However such question general in extent.</item>
                    <label>18.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said next we come to second
                        para. This para <pb facs="d603-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d603-5"/>
                        specifically dealt with dispute China-US Taiwan area. Today most critical
                        issue between China-US placing them acute oppositon each other is that in
                        Taiwan area and not any other place.</item>
                    <label>19.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said they believed if Taiwan
                        question could be settled peacefully between two countries without going war
                        then all other issues between two countries would be settled same
                        way.</item>
                    <label>20.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said as to practical feasible
                        means for realization common desire as specified last para., they believed
                        should specify time limit for seeking these means so that any possible
                        procrastination following announcement can be prevented. As he said in
                        opening statement if we shared sincere desire for success discussions
                        following announcement, would not be any delay or procrastination that
                        regard.</item>
                    <label>21.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said as he repeatedly stated in
                        course talks practical feasible means they had in mind precisely FonMin
                        conf. between two countries. He also noted I had never in previous
                        discussions excluded such conference from consideration. For making specific
                        arrangements this practical feasible means, two months time certainly
                        sufficient.</item>
                    <label>22.</label>
                    <item>I replied I still not clear whether it intended that second para would
                        have any applicability to disputes other than those Taiwan area. It seemed
                        me as para now read there was implication with respect disputes other than
                        those Taiwan area principle of renunciation force and settlement by peaceful
                        negotiation might not be applicable.</item>
                    <label>23.</label>
                    <item>I said I also still not clear as to interpretation applicability of
                        declaration—whatever rest of it meant—if at end two months agreement not
                        been reached. If agreement not reached in two-month period or if settlement
                        entirely satisfactory them not reached in FonMins meeting or this meeting or
                        any other meeting did his declaration say they would again be free at that
                        time resume threat resort force?</item>
                    <pb facs="1010" n="963" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_963"/>
                    <pb facs="d603-6" n="6" type="facsimile" xml:id="d603-6"/>
                    <label>24.</label>
                    <item>I said I also not clear and did not think language clear on whether
                        declaration was stating it already been determined between us FonMins conf
                        only practical feasible means. For example last part sentence “to make
                        specific arrangements”—specific arrangements for what? For FonMins conf? For
                        seeking and ascertaining means for realization common desire? Without
                        expressing opinion at moment, it seemed me language very ambiguous as to
                        what it actually did mean. If I had difficulty understanding it, certainly
                        others would have much more difficulty.</item>
                    <label>25.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> replied as he saw it my question
                        concerning second para draft already been answered. As I had previously
                        repeatedly asked question whether peaceful settlement disputes between two
                        countries included dispute Taiwan area therefore present draft had precisely
                        answered my question. In his opening statement he had said I would notice
                        new draft specifically applied to Taiwan area principle of settling disputes
                        by peaceful negotiation without resorting threat use force. He thought this
                        sufficiently clear.</item>
                    <label>26.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said with regard third para on
                        attainment practical feasible means, if we agreed on principle settling
                        disputes Taiwan area without resort threat use force against each other then
                        it followed practical feasible means realizing this principle must be
                        sought. If we failed seek find such practical feasible means as specified
                        declaration what would be use making declaration at all?</item>
                    <pb facs="d603-7" n="7" type="facsimile" xml:id="d603-7"/>
                    <label>27.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said this para clearly says we
                        should seek practical feasible means and these means included holding
                        Sino-American FonMins. Text this para quite clear. As to specific
                        arrangements referred to this para they meant arrangements for such
                        conference—time, place, how it would be arranged. This was position their
                        side which they made clear over over again in course deliberations. That was
                        their understanding of practical feasible means referred to here.</item>
                    <label>28.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said nevertheless he would also
                        be ready listen me if I had other better practical feasible means in
                        mind.</item>
                    <label>29.</label>
                    <item>I replied I just wanted make one more comment on his statement. He had
                        often in past and again this morning talked of procrastination and necessity
                        avoiding procrastination and attempt at freezing situation Taiwan
                        area.</item>
                    <label>30.</label>
                    <item>I said I just wanted note it US which last October proposed there be
                        renunciation force specifically applicable Taiwan area as elsewhere so
                        genuine peaceful negotiations could be undertaken. It ambiguous attitude
                            <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName>’s govt. had thus far taken
                        with respect really renouncing use force Taiwan area that had prevented
                        undertaking such discussions.</item>
                    <label>31.</label>
                    <item>I said I would study his draft and comment in detail next meeting.</item>
                    <label>32.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> replied he could not agree with
                        remarks I made just now. It matter fact their side at session October 21
                        offered concrete <pb facs="1011" n="964" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_964"/>
                        draft proposed declaration on renunciation force, it not US which took this
                        first initiative. If US had <pb facs="d603-8" n="8" type="facsimile"
                            xml:id="d603-8"/> genuinely shared desire their side make this
                        declaration it would been made long ago, it would been made last year,
                        instead of carrying discussion over to present. Present draft another
                        important effort their part to make discussions success and he did not want
                        see any further delay. They hoped we able adopt this draft and reach
                        agreement speedily.</item>
                    <label>33.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said however he very willing
                        listen any positive constructive remarks had to make next meeting with
                        regard this draft.</item>
                    <label>34.</label>
                    <item>I said if <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> had nothing further
                        that matter I would like note 18 more Chinese arrived Hong Kong April 30
                        enroute <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName>’s country. This made
                        total 148 we know of that arrived by ship Hong Kong enroute his country
                        since August 1 last year. It been almost five months now since [garble]
                        American been released his country. It hard me see how his authorities could
                        expect world believe they carrying out commitment Sept 10 last year,
                        regarding Americans when facts so clearly spoke otherwise.</item>
                    <label>35.</label>
                    <item>I said my govt intends faithfully carry out pledge made our agreed
                        announcement. At same time we expected his govt do likewise. It clearly not
                        doing so.</item>
                    <label>36.</label>
                    <item>I said I had spoken many times effects this having my country. If his
                        authorities really seeking improve atmosphere surrounding talks and
                        relations between two countries situation must be corrected.</item>
                    <label>37.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> replied I had said number
                        Chinese now returned his country but these Chinese should been permitted
                        return long ago. Of 49 Chinese whose names he given me except one who
                        already returned they had no information on remaining 48.</item>
                    <label>38.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said he able tell me any
                        ordinary American <pb facs="d603-9" n="9" type="facsimile" xml:id="d603-9"/>
                        civilian now China can return my country any time he desires. If they not
                        now returned it simply because they not have desire return now. They could
                        not force them leave country or deport them because they not breached
                        Chinese law. As to question persons in prison during discussions last
                        December he requested me make investigation Chinese imprisoned US. However
                        nearly half year passed without my giving him any information on them which
                        he regretted very much. Certainly I could not tell him that persons
                        imprisoned US did not desire return his country.</item>
                    <label>39.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said if I concerned about
                        Americans imprisoned in China then must first all give them such information
                        as actually how many Chinese now imprisoned by my govt US. He could tell me
                        very frankly if US refused give accounting Chinese imprisoned US, US had no
                        right mention question Americans in prison his country.</item>
                    <label>40.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said he had said my govt not
                        satisfied with situation Americans imprisoned in China. He could tell me his
                        govt, his country, his people even more dissatisfied with situation his
                        compatriots imprisoned in US.</item>
                    <pb facs="1012" n="965" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_965"/>
                    <label>41.</label>
                    <item>I asked what Americans we were talking about last September if not about
                        those Americans detained their prisons. We were not talking about Americans
                        in abstract, we talking about specific Americans and both us knew it. There
                        was certainly no doubt between us that his authorities were committing
                        selves permit those (repeat those) Americans return expeditiously US. This
                        they had not done.</item>
                    <label>42.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said question we discussed was
                        question return civilians both countries and this dealt with in very clear
                        terms and words our agreement. Agreement did not speak about particular
                        category civilians agreement covered all civilians. They expected US
                        implement agreement accordance its terms.</item>
                    <label>43.</label>
                    <item>I said I had nothing further and asked if next Thursday 17th satisfactory.
                            <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> agreed.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GFC_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Gowen</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
