<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-08-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="696" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d696">
                        <head>696. Telegram 135 from Geneva<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d696fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                611.93/8–956. Confidential; Limit Distribution.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-08-09">August 9, 1956, 9
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d696-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-1"/>
                        <p>135. From <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> opened 55th meeting
                                with prepared statement: Since opening second item we spent ten
                                months discussing renunciation force suggested by my side their side
                                already put forward three <pb facs="1182" n="1135" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1135"/> reasonable drafts for declaration that
                                regard. Only because my side stubbornly clinging to demands
                                unacceptable their side that no agreement reached. To prevent these
                                talks from developing into meaningless stalling situation their side
                                proposed we discuss subject of embargo raised by their side under
                                second item. At last meeting I had indicated willingness hear their
                                views on question embargo but remarks I made then seemed show my
                                side doesn’t intend carry on businesslike discussion of subject and
                                seek solution. If that is position he could only regard it as
                                unreasonable. Their side had joined in discussing subject proposed
                                by my side. If my side refused discuss subject proposed their side
                                it would indeed turn these talks into unfair unequal negotiation; he
                                hoped this not intent my side.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> now specifically
                                suggested we first reach agreement on following lines: “In order
                                that subject raised by Chinese side under second item agenda may be
                                handled, both sides of these talks agree to proceed to subject of
                                embargo and seek practical settlement.” He would now like to hear my
                                views.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>I replied assumption he made was apparently that there no longer
                                any way open to us continue seek agreement on question renunciation
                                force. While true this subject proposed by me, it subject which felt
                                we both agreed went to very heart of basic disputes between us. It
                                was suggested by my side <pb facs="d696-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-2"/> as first essential step in seeking peaceful
                                settlement those disputes. I could not but continue consider it this
                                light. I therefore could not agree that we abandon efforts reach
                                agreement renunciation force. If his govt were to abandon obstacles
                                it had placed in way of reaching agreement on renunciation force
                                declaration I was satisfied we could very readily reach agreement
                                thereon. In our discussion up to May 11, two of us had been
                                proceeding—very slowly, it is true—in way which could lead to
                                agreement. He responded to my proposal of last October with draft
                                that indicated at least partial acceptance fundamental principles
                                proposal which I had made. This was in sense step forward, although
                                it was largely canceled out by his attempt introduce into that draft
                                separate matter Foreign Ministers conference as precondition for
                                agreement on renunciation force.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>I said with introduction my draft Nov 10, which expressed very
                                concretely principle of renunciation force without entangling it
                                with extraneous topics, our discussions had progressed to new stage.
                                Three weeks later on Dec 1, he had submitted new draft. Without
                                sacrificing his views as to desirability eventual meeting Foreign
                                Ministers, had in his Dec 1 draft at least tacitly accepted idea our
                                immediate task, of reaching agreement on renunciation force, should
                                not be complicated by introduction extraneous matters. I had
                                welcomed this draft of his side, and called it advance over previous
                                position. In my subsequent successive efforts continue our progress
                                towards meaningful renunciation force, I had been very careful
                                preserve, in entirety, area agreement <pb facs="1183" n="1136" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1136"/> which his Dec 1 draft
                                indicated had been reached between us. As he knew, my draft April 19
                                retained not only form but also every single word of his Dec 1
                                draft.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>I continued in contrast to efforts I made to preserve area of
                                agreement between us, his efforts since May 11 been devoted
                                eliminating basis for progress towards meaningful declaration. He
                                had done this by reverting to position of last October. He had
                                attempted establish first one precondition and then another for
                                issuance of declaration. I continue <pb facs="d696-3" n="3" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-3"/> hope his govt will reconsider
                                its present position and change its attitude so we could issue
                                really meaningful declaration renunciation force as first and
                                fundamental step to settlement disputes between us.</item>
                            <pb facs="d696-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-4"/>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>I said had agreed to inclusion in our discussion of what he termed
                                trade embargo. I had no intention of going back on this agreement.
                                My attitude toward discussion this not based on narrow procedural
                                consideration but rather on fundamental substantive relationship of
                                this matter to renunciation force. As I told him on November 3 and
                                again at last meeting I entirely willing hear any views he might
                                desire put forward with respect trade. When he did so I hoped he
                                would amplify exactly what aspects this matter he had in mind. Last
                                Nov 3 I had asked specific questions this regard to which he had
                                still made no replies. I did not believe it would serve any useful
                                purpose to make as he had in past, vague and unfounded charges
                                against my govt in exercising its unquestioned sovereign right to
                                control and regulate trade in whatever manner it deems in best
                                interest of US. Let me say again very bluntly as I had at last
                                meeting, my country did not consider there could be any advantage to
                                it in trade where goods received in that trade could be used support
                                use force against it. It would thus be obvious if discussion trade
                                matters between us to be fruitful it must be clear that such use
                                would not be made of goods received in that trade. I had stated our
                                position on this very bluntly and very frankly not with intent of
                                giving any offense or of engaging in fruitless argument, but rather
                                so that he would clearly understand our position this regard and
                                thereby contribute to constructive results our discussion. I
                                therefore hoped he would carefully consider matter of both
                                renunciation and trade in this light.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> agreed question
                                issuance renunciation force declaration at heart disputes between
                                two sides. Their patience in discussion this topic attested by ten
                                months <pb facs="d696-5" n="5" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-5"/> in
                                which they joined with us in this discussion. His side had thus
                                forwarded three successive drafts for making such declaration. Thus
                                clear their sincerity in reaching such agreement couldn’t be
                                questioned. This morning I had stated I didn’t abandon, or give up
                                subject renunciation force. But I failed put forward any views which
                                could eliminate obstacles in way of discussion this subject. He <pb facs="1184" n="1137" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1137"/> didn’t
                                think it would contribute to progress to reiterate old arguments
                                which had been put forward in our discussions. Blame of failure
                                reach agreement after ten months discussion on renunciation force
                                couldn’t be put on their side.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> asked in light my
                                statement on subject embargo this morning, could he take it had no
                                objection to opening discussion on this subject and that I would
                                agree do so? He recalled statement I made Nov 3 last year on subject
                                embargo. He recalled he had already made clear reply to that
                                statement. He said then question embargo is one of matters at issue
                                between two sides. It purpose these talks to gradually resolve, step
                                by step all disputes between two countries. He had told me
                                repeatedly policy embargo in itself unreasonable and hurts both
                                sides, and violates international principle peaceful trade. That why
                                his side resolutely opposed policy embargo. They always maintained
                                this policy embargo should be abolished. Abolition this policy
                                embargo in accordance interest both our two countries and peoples.
                                Abolition this policy embargo must not be forcibly entangled with
                                any other question or qualified with preconditions in this regard.
                                He therefore would like hear my views in regard first steps for
                                abolishing eliminating this embargo.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>I assumed he did not question sovereign right my govt control
                                trade in whatever manner it deems best interest my country. Also
                                assumed he not questioning ability my govt, cting in accordance
                                lawful processes, to determine what it considers in best interests
                                my country. Policies my govt adopts with respect trade not
                                capricious or arbitrary but determined by what it considers best
                                interest my country. He said this question must not be forcibly
                                entangled with other questions. I had not attempted establish any
                                forced—but rather very natural—relationship <pb facs="d696-6" n="6" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-6"/> between that and question
                                renunciation force. I had carefully and frankly explained again this
                                morning inevitable relationship between these two matters. I
                                believed what I said was entirely clear and would not take time
                                repeat it. Nevertheless as I had said am entirely prepared hear
                                whatever views he desired put forward on subject. I again repeated
                                that when he did so I hoped he would be specific and particularly
                                that he would clarify exactly what aspects he had in mind. Several
                                aspects to it as brought out in statement I made Nov 3. It not clear
                                yet which of those various aspects it his desire discuss.</item>
                            <pb facs="d696-7" n="7" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-7"/>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> replied deemed it
                                necessary make clear no statements he ever made carried any intent
                                interfere in internal affairs my country. If policies pursued by my
                                govt had no relation whatsoever his country he’d never raise any
                                matter this regard. His understanding trade between countries always
                                naturally advantageous to two parties or at least this trade must
                                not prejudice interest of one party. However, policies pursued by US
                                Govt do not fit in <pb facs="1185" n="1138" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1138"/> generally accepted principles international
                                trade—rather my country carrying on policy international blockade
                                and embargo in order pursue national political objective.
                                Implementation these policies has prejudiced interests other
                                countries. In fact these policies prejudicial to everybody
                                concerned. That reason why he stated this policy of embargo
                                unreasonable, should therefore be abolished. Matter of fact this
                                policy already provoked extreme dissatisfaction of peoples every
                                country. That made it all more necessary discuss this subject. That
                                was reason why this subject one of matters at issue between two
                                countries. In raising this subject it was their demand that policy
                                of embargo be lifted. Lifting of embargo would help in improvement
                                of relations between China and US. Lifting embargo not only in
                                interests Chinese people but also in interest American people. He
                                had stated he hoped I’d put forward my concrete views with regard
                                lifting embargo but my last statement still had not contained reply
                                to statement he had made. He continued hope I’d consider this matter
                                and if I found not able do so this morning, do so next
                                meeting.</item>
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>I replied he had often spoken of necessity these talks being
                                mutually advantageous. Negotiations between two countries such as
                                ours could not be one sided. However seemed to me thus far in these
                                talks results and efforts of his [garble—side] <pb facs="d696-8" n="8" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-8"/> had been directed
                                toward solely unilateral advantage. He had presumably raised
                                question of what he termed “trade embargo” because he considered it
                                advantageous his side. I had explained to him reasons US didn’t
                                consider it advantageous under present conditions. On other hand
                                renunciation force something that clearly mutual and advantageous to
                                both of us. If threat of force could, as I had so often proposed, be
                                removed it could open door to fruitful discussion of other subjects.
                                Trade policies of my country were not cause but rather effect of
                                threat force that continues exists. If that threat could be removed
                                by unequivocal renunciation force, it would remove one of causes
                                this policy. His govt had it within its power remove that
                                cause.</item>
                            <label>13.</label>
                            <item>I continued at outset these discussions I pointed out another
                                cause seriously affecting our relations was detention of American
                                citizens in his country. I pointed out at time this also could only
                                be removed by action his country. This another case in which his
                                side had sought unilateral advantage. I’d thought last Sept. we’d
                                agreed upon course action that would be of mutual advantage. Yet
                                things appeared be going backward as far as any advantage to US
                                concerned. Not only had Americans been released from his country at
                                what is apparently rate considerably slower than even before we
                                entered into agreement but any policy of what he had termed leniency
                                appeared even been dropped. Pattern now apparently being established
                                persons in prison being required serve full sentence. I noted that
                                of last three persons <pb facs="1186" n="1139" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1139"/> released from prison, all had served full
                                term sentences. I had also been disturbed note that in spite his
                                statements here and public statements his govt, one half of persons
                                in prison never communicated with UK Charge. That this not entirely
                                matter of their choice confirmed by fact Father Clifford told us he
                                had specifically been refused permission write UK Charge or to see
                                British ConGen. Father Phillips stated he specifically told agreed
                                announcement issued Sept 10 not applicable him. Apart from all other
                                consideratons this stands in strong contrast to offer of which I had
                                informed him to Indian Embassy to visit any Chinese in prison in US
                                whether had written or not.</item>
                            <pb facs="d696-9" n="9" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-9"/>
                            <label>14.</label>
                            <item>I continued whole situation is case in which his govt even yet had
                                in its power bring about improvement in relations between us. My
                                govt noted fact his authorities invited certain US newspaper
                                correspondents radio commentators visit his country. My govt
                                welcomed free exchange information between different countries
                                irrespective of whatever political or social differences might exist
                                between them. Impediment to such exchanges between our two countries
                                was one which had been set up by his country and could only be
                                removed by his country. Dept State issued public statement in this
                                regard. In order that he might have exact text, I giving him copy. I
                                particulerly drew his attention to last sentence that
                                statement.</item>
                            <pb facs="d696-10" n="10" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-10"/>
                            <label>15.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said had always held
                                view we should base our discussion issues between on basis principle
                                mutual benefit. We should not base discussion on unilateral or
                                one-sided benefit of one side. Problems could only be readily
                                resolved if we based our discussion on former principle. No problem
                                could be considered it we only considered ones own unilateral
                                benefit. We all talk about the principle and we all agree with it.
                                However, great contrast between two sides in practical carrying out
                                this principle.</item>
                            <label>16.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> asked permission cite
                                few instances in relationship between China and US. What US had in
                                fact maintained was to pursue its own unilateral benefit at expense
                                other side. It was as matter of fact US which occupying territory
                                China rather than China occupying territory US. It was US which
                                carrying on economic embargo against China and not China which
                                carrying on such policy. It quite obvious that what US doing today
                                was to pursue its unilateral benefit at expense China. Facts being
                                so how could my govt still cling to policy of own benefit while
                                prejudicing benefit this country. How could such policy one-sided
                                benefit contribute to improvement relationship between two
                                countries.</item>
                            <label>17.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> could only term absurd
                                all charges agains his country which without regard to actual facts.
                                I seemed to him to have said their side proposed policy embargo be
                                abolished solely because abolition would be in interest of China
                                alone. He must point out such categorization wrong. Original
                                objective of US in imposing such policy embargo <pb facs="1187" n="1140" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1140"/> was try create
                                difficulties for China. Objective of US was pursue own selfish
                                interest. However things had not turned out exactly in accordance
                                reasoning my govt. Reason either side proposed abolition policy <pb facs="d696-11" n="11" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-11"/> trade
                                embargo was not one which could be explained by saying this policy
                                had caused tremendous difficulty to his govt. The policy embargo had
                                actually not created any great amount difficulty to his country;
                                fact turns out to be new and industrialized China being built up.
                                This fact already been recognized by the world. Because policy
                                embargo unreasonable and violates interest all peoples of world
                                including Americans that they propose its abolition. Fact that even
                                among US authorities there also some people who recognized necessity
                                abolishing trade embargo proved that this policy damaging to
                                interest of all concerned. Number of people in US didn’t understand
                                construction of new and industrialized China. These people
                                deliberately creating false stories this regard. Now very good
                                opportunty afforded to American correspondents and newsmen to report
                                on this regard personally.</item>
                            <label>18.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> charged US had
                                consistently made propaganda saying his country iron curtain country
                                or what we have termed bamboo curtain country—and that his country
                                didn’t offer access to people of other countries to visit it. They
                                had continually been receiving many requests from American
                                newspapermen to come China report news. General principle to deal
                                with this matter now being adopted by most countries that visiting
                                by newspapermen be reciprocal. This principle which should be
                                followed is that same time American newspapermen being admitted to
                                China, Chinese newspapermen should also be admitted to US. Might ask
                                if US such a free country as we term it, would it have been able
                                admit Chinese newspapermen. His government had not asked such
                                question. His govt had acceded request newspapermen to visit his
                                country. Might say this particularly lenient step his govt. would
                                offer opportunity for correspondents of those American newspapers
                                which in past had constantly slandered his country to be able visit
                                his country themselves. This visit would also serve to promote
                                mutual understanding and friendship between peoples these two
                                countries.</item>
                            <label>19.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said now that his govt
                                accepted request various journalists and commentators to visit his
                                country, any attempt offer obstructio to these newsmen or to raise
                                absolutely <pb facs="d696-12" n="12" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-12"/> unreasonable demand in this regard he could
                                only consider improper. This would amount to deliberate obstruction
                                on part my govt against those American correspondents to make
                                personal tour his country and have facts. This would amount to
                                deliberate attempt on part US Govt to continue refuse face facts on
                                China. All this would make US by its own volition what it always
                                calls an iron curtain country. This would show US Govt deliberately
                                creating futher obstructions rather than removing existing
                                obstructions between China and US. Action taken by US Govt that
                                regard would inevitably invite condemnation of all people including
                                    <pb facs="1188" n="1141" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1141"/>
                                American press. International opinion would have its proper say on
                                merits this matter—as to which side merits on. Any attempt try seize
                                this opportunity when Chinese Govt accepting request American
                                correspondents visit China for blackmail or to demand any extraneous
                                precondition, he could only term extremely absurd.</item>
                            <pb facs="d696-13" n="13" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-13"/>
                            <label>20.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> continued far as
                                question return civilians concerned, they also see that what US Govt
                                said grossly at variance with what actually carried out. I not yet
                                given any accounting those people whose names he had given me in
                                course discussion. Number Chinese who recently returned from US have
                                told of various obstructions related to their return offered by US
                                Govt. Many these people who returned had expressed desire return his
                                country but IN and S my country made repeated attempts force or
                                induce them go Taiwan. IN and S objected to their return on grounds
                                China what we call Communist country. Some of them given
                                unreasonable time limit to departure so could not bring along
                                personal possessions—even clothing. All those actions of my country
                                violate spirit agreed announcement. This picture grossly at variance
                                either what US said regard so-called free departure Chinese from my
                                country.</item>
                            <label>21.</label>
                            <item>I replied fact remained in spite these vague charges Chinese, even
                                in accordance his own statement, steadily returning his country
                                whenever desire do so. Fact remained if any them felt were being
                                obstructed could communicate with Indian Embassy. Fact remained
                                Indian Embassy had not called our altention single case such
                                obstruction. Fact remained from very outset talks I made it clear
                                our interest was in obtaining release all Americans detained his
                                country. I thought, my people thought, my govt thought, this had
                                been agreed to by his authorities in our agreed announcement Sept
                                10. Fact remained in spite agreement between us Americans still
                                being detained in his country, and of those who remained, their
                                situation appeared to be even more unfavorable than prior issuance
                                agreed announcment; whereas even before agreed announcement some of
                                them being released prior to full term sentences that had unjustly
                                been served upon them, now appears be pattern name those that remain
                                serve full sentence.</item>
                            <pb facs="d696-14" n="14" type="facsimile" xml:id="d696-14"/>
                            <label>22.</label>
                            <item>I thus found it difficult see what advantage there been to my
                                country in issuance agreed announcement. In view this situation and
                                treatment accorded these Americans who already in his country it
                                certainly cannot be expected US Govt would approve more Americans
                                placing themselves within jurisdiction his authorities. This just
                                plain common sense, and my govt woould be delinquent of its
                                responsibility toward its citizens if it took any other attitude. If
                                he desired have Americans visit his country it entirely within power
                                his authorities remove this present impediment to their doing so; I
                                earnestly hoped they do so.</item>
                            <label>23.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> said this explanation
                                and reply regarding question civilians, especially regarding Chinese
                                civilians in US, do not appear satisfactory to him. He considered my
                                charge [illegible in the original] his <pb facs="1189" n="1142" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1142"/> country regarding American
                                civilians in China unreasonable. They did not accord with fact. He
                                therefore could not accept them. With regard question American
                                correspondents who request go China, fact was US Govt did not want
                                them go—is preventing them from doing so. He could only say this
                                against plain common sense and entirely policy directed to duping
                                people. Such policy would not bring any good to US Govt.</item>
                            <label>24.</label>
                            <item>On my indicating I had nothing further, <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> suggested next meeting Aug 21.
                                I agreed.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GFC_1"><hi rend="strong">Gowen</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>