<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>733. Letter 47 from Johnson to to McConaughy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v03mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d733</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">733</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-10-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-10-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Consular offices</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="suez-crisis">Suez crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-10-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-10-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="733"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d733">
                <head>733. Letter 47 from <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName> to
                        <persName corresp="#p_MWP_1">McConaughy</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d733fn1">Source: Department of State, Geneva
                        Talks Files, Lot 72D415. Secret; Official–Informal. <persName
                            corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName> signed the original “Alex.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">Letter No. 47</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-10-17"
                            >October 17, 1956</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Walter:</salute>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d733-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d733-1"/>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>I am starting this on Wednesday and will finish it tomorrow after the
                        meeting.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I certainly have no objection to again bringing up the POW question here,
                        but as Monroe said after his trip to Korea, I think the decision revolves
                        around whether we believe there is any chance whatever of <pb facs="1260"
                            n="1213" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1213"/> obtaining any more
                        information and, if not, whether we then intend to use the issue further
                        publicly to indict the Chicoms. If it is solely the latter I believe Geneva
                        to be the best forum. I do <hi rend="italic">not</hi> agree with the
                        statement in the draft memo enclosed with your letter (No. 56) that Geneva
                        offers a slightly better chance than Panmunjon for obtaining an accounting
                        for at least a few of the 450. I can build up a good public record on the
                        subject here and can probably embarrass <persName corresp="#p_WP_1"
                            >Wang</persName> to a certain degree, but <pb facs="d733-2" n="2"
                            type="facsimile" xml:id="d733-2"/> he is never going to give me any
                        accounting for individuals here, and we should not raise the subject here on
                        the assumption that there is any possibility he will do so. He has
                        frequently and strongly taken the position that the lists he gave me at the
                        outset of the talks accounted for all Americans in China and it cannot be
                        expected he will reverse that position.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>As a minor point with respect to numbered para (2) of the draft memo, I
                        did in fact allude to the POW question at our 56th meeting (para 16 mytel
                        173) and drew a response from him on it.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>With regard to the less likelihood of their countering with our failure to
                        account for communist prisoners if the subject is raised here, you will
                        recall that when I first raised the suject here he fortunately countered
                        only with the 14,000 sent to Taiwan which was not hard to handle, but he may
                        now be better prepared to counter with others and I will have to be prepared
                        immediately to reply if he does so. Of course, by raising the subject here
                        we will probably avoid the more difficult subject of the Koreans released by
                        Rhee.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>In this connection it is my recollection that their list may be wholly or
                        primarily based on the lists of <pb facs="d733-3" n="3" type="facsimile"
                            xml:id="d733-3"/> notification of capture that we transmitted through
                        the ICRC. It is also my recollection that a large discrepancy in these lists
                        arose from the fact that a capture form would be made out at the time the
                        man was taken with a copy to the ICRC. On arrival at Kojedo the man’s tag
                        would be missing and another would be made out with another copy to the
                        ICRC. Because of the language problem, difficulties of transliteration, and
                        sometimes through the POW giving a different name, the name would not appear
                        as identical with the first report. Thus ICRC would receive and transmit to
                        the Communists two names covering the capture of only one man. I do not
                        recall whether this appears anywhere in the records, but I know it was
                        explained to me when I made my “POW trip” to Korea with General Hull.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Also pertinent to all of this was an exchange of numbers of persons held
                        in the early days of the armistice negotiations. My memory on this is dim
                        but I believe we gave the Communists some definite numbers on those we
                        held.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>I do not recall what the circumstances are and when the communist list of
                        missing personnel mentioned in the last sentence of the first <pb
                            facs="1261" n="1214" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1214"/> para of the draft
                        memo was presented or of what it consisted. My only point is that before
                        terming it “in large part fictitious” I would want to be sure that it is not
                        in fact based upon names originating with the UNC.</item>
                    <pb facs="d733-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d733-4"/>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>My memory on our exchanges of lists of names of POWs with the Communists
                        is also very hazy. Not that it is likely to come in any detail here, but to
                        avoid possible mistakes I would appreciate a short summary of the facts in
                        this regard. I have a feeling we gave them some list early in the armistice
                        negotiations, and that they gave us one but I am just not sure whether this
                        is correct or of what they consisted. Were there also not lists given the
                        NNRC which were passed on to the Communists? I do not want anyone to go to
                        any great trouble on this but perhaps there is a pertinent summary already
                        made up. Perhaps HD would have it available or could readily make it
                        up.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Whether the subject is raised here or Panmunjon it will be important that
                        the information with respect to individuals reflect the “accounting” set
                        forth in CINCUNC’s message of March 2, 1956. That is, in our best documented
                        cases of their at one time being alive in Communist hands, the March
                        accounting attempted to dispose of them by saying they had “escaped”. Thus
                        in these “escaped” cases the issue is no longer whether they were at one
                        time alive in Communist hands, by saying they “escaped” they have admitted
                        this, but rather being able to demonstrate that such an accounting is false.
                        This is very well set forth in detail in the memo enclosed with Dave’s
                        letter of August 23. <pb facs="d733-5" n="5" type="facsimile"
                            xml:id="d733-5"/> My reason for mentioning it is that while the Memo to
                        the Service Secretaries enclosed with your letter encloses what I presume is
                        the substance of Dave’s memo, the attached “Suggestions” do not appear to
                        take account of this important point of which I would have to take account
                        before again raising individual cases here. For our purposes here I would
                        not need any large number of cases, a half dozen or so would probably serve
                        my purposes, although, of course, the more I have in my pocket the better.
                        My suggestion would be to have Ralph and Col. Monroe pick out a few of the
                        most promising cases and exhaustively run them down with the services rather
                        than spreading the effort too thin.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>My 362 did not imply that I had changed my estimate that they are most
                        likely to make a major move shortly after the elections and the opening of
                        the UNGA. With two weeks between meetings, the “next few meetings” mentioned
                        in my 362 brings us up to that point. What I have been and continue to say
                        is that they are very obviously putting themsleves in a position to carry
                        out such a move at about that time. Whether they do so, of course, remains
                        to be seen. I simply want to be sure that the Department understands and is
                        prepared for the contingency and does not desire to take any further action
                        to forestall it. Incidentally, <pb facs="d733-6" n="6" type="facsimile"
                            xml:id="d733-6"/> while our position through the Suez crisis has been
                        very <pb facs="1262" n="1215" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1215"/> consistent
                        with the position on renunciation of force I have taken here, the statements
                        of the French and British have certainly not given too much support to the
                        “universally accepted” nature of the principle.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>I was very interested in your account of the Chinese Communist initiative
                        in the publications field. Do our Treasury regulations operate so as to
                        prevent any such shipments? (I have subsequently seen the CA notice which I
                        am glad to note is encouraging the licensing for non-technical
                        publications.)</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>I had been deploring publicity under my previous instructions but had also
                        tried to make it clear we did not fear it. I entirely agree with Walter’s
                        views and will act accordingly in the future.</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>The guidance for tomorrow has just come in. It is very complete and I
                        certainly agree we are on a strong wicket in the disgraceful McCarthy
                        affair. I just can’t understand why they have done it.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="right">Thursday</p>
                <list>
                    <label>14.</label>
                    <item>Back from the meeting and have just sent off my summary to you. I do not
                        think there can longer be much doubt as to the course of action they have
                        laid out for themselves. The only question now is the timing—that is will
                        they carry out their move at the next meeting just before the elections and
                        the UNGA or will they wait until the following meeting just after the
                        elections and the UNGA. In any event, <pb facs="d733-7" n="7"
                            type="facsimile" xml:id="d733-7"/> there will in all probability be a
                        public statement following the next meeting, which will make the threat to
                        break, with the break carried out at the following meeting. One can never
                        dismiss the possibility of a bland reversal but I just do not think it is
                        likely as they have now gone almost out to the end of this limb. I hope that
                        the Secretary will have time carefully to consider the situation and that my
                        guidance will be as explicit as possible.</item>
                    <label>15.</label>
                    <item>I deliberately did not try further today to develop the threat implicit in
                        the last sentence of his prepared statement, leaving that for next time when
                        I will want to make a very carefully considered and comprehensive statement
                        in reply to his of today. I would hope that my guidance will also cover
                        whether it is desired I try to steer things in the direction of an
                        indefinite recess or a clean break, if the next meeting goes in that
                        direction.</item>
                    <label>16.</label>
                    <item>I should think it would be nice to get out our statement on implementation
                        before the next meeting. I think it would place us in a much better position
                        to meet their next move. (Incidentally, I hope you will get it to us here
                        well before release time so that we know what has been said and I can get a
                        copy over to <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> at approximately
                        its release time.) I should also think that at our next meeting I should be
                        prepared to say something on the missing POWs without getting into any
                        details.</item>
                    <pb facs="1263" n="1216" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1216"/>
                    <pb facs="d733-8" n="8" type="facsimile" xml:id="d733-8"/>
                    <label>17.</label>
                    <item>I am enclosing for comment a draft break statement which I would plan to
                        issue immediately following any meeting at which a break would occur. It
                        might, of course, be necessary somewhat to modify it to meet the exact
                        situation but I would plan to stick fairly close to its general line. As
                        this would ostensibly be an extemporaneous statement as I left the meeting
                        room it must be short and simple.</item>
                    <label>18.</label>
                    <item>In the quite likely event he does not break at our next meeting but very
                        shortly thereafter and issues a statement along the lines of his prepared
                        statement today I would propose to promptly comment along the lines of para
                        2, 3, and 4 of the enclosed break statement with such changes as the
                        circumstances require.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Regards to all,</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">U. Alexis Johnson</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">American Ambassador</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>P.S. Just an afterthought. If they are planning something timed to our
                        elections I might throw them off step and somewhat spike their guns by
                        asking for a postponement of the next meeting to Monday November 5. I am in
                        a good position to ask for it as I have never cashed in on the times I have
                        agreed to his requests for postponement. I would, of course, do it at the
                        last minute, that is on Wednesday or Thursday before the meeting and all I
                        would have to do is send him word that it was “impossible” for me to meet
                        until Nov. 5.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">
                                <hi rend="strong">UAJ</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </postscript>
                <pb facs="d733-9" n="9" type="facsimile" xml:id="d733-9"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>Enclosure<note n="2" xml:id="d733fn2">No classification marking.</note>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">DRAFT STATEMENT</p>
                    <p>I regret to announce that at today’s meeting Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> refused to agree to any date for our
                        next meeting. (or refused to meet further with me).</p>
                    <p>In effect, he refuses to meet further unless the U.S. capitulates to their
                        demand for a Foreign Ministers conference under the continued threat that
                        the Chinese Communists will resort to force if they cannot otherwise achieve
                        their ambitions in the Taiwan area. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WP_1"
                            >Wang</persName> has also demanded that the U.S. remove its existing
                        controls over trade and travel between the U.S. and China.</p>
                    <p>I have told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> that I
                        hope he will reconsider this peremptory attitude and for my part I stand
                        ready again to meet at any time to resume with him in a genuine negotiating
                        spirit search <pb facs="1264" n="1217" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1217"/> for
                        agreement on an unconditional declaration which would remove the existing
                        threat of the Chinese Communists to resort to force in the Taiwan area and
                        agree that our differences will be settled by peaceful means only.</p>
                    <p>The U.S. continues to expect the Chinese Communists to carry out their
                        commitment of September 10, 1955 and promptly to release the 10 unfortunate
                        Americans still held in their prisons in violation of that agreement.</p>
                    <p>I have informed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> that
                        any communications can be transmitted through our respective consular
                        offices here in Geneva.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
