<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>786. Letter 65 from McConaughy to to Johnson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v03mSupp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d786</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">786</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-02-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="rectduqNv1b6cCQCB" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001184"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Magazine</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="visas" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436" lcsh-match="exact">Passports</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-02-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="786"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d786">
                <head>786. Letter 65 from <persName corresp="#p_MWP_1">McConaughy</persName> to
                        <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d786fn1">Source: Department of State, Geneva
                        Talks Files, Lot 72D415. Secret; Official–Informal.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">Letter No. 65</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1957-02-11">February 11, 1957</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>Dear Alex:</salute>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d786-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d786-1"/>
                <p>1. Developments in the issue of travel of newspapermen to Communist China have
                    not been very favorable for us. The press is giving strong support to Stevens
                    and Worthy. Apparently they have been able to whip up a certain amount of public
                    support for their position. Worthy appeared on Eric Sevareid’s nation wide
                    newscast Sunday afternoon February 10 and probably evoked quite a bit of
                    sympathy for his position. Worthy left Moscow before the Embassy received our
                    instructions, and he refused to submit his passport to the Legation in Budapest
                    for restrictive endorsement. He also refused to say yes or no on the passport
                    hearing which was offered him, placing his case in the hands of the Civil
                    Liberties Union. When Worthy passed through Immigration at Boston his passport
                    (by decision) was not taken up or restrictively endorsed. As I see it this will
                    make it difficult for us to follow through in Stevens case. Look Magazine plans
                    to fight the case of Stevens and Harrington. Presumably there will be a passport
                    hearing in Washington when Stevens returns to this country. Stevens was given
                    the choice of a hearing in Moscow or Washington before restrictive action was
                    taken, and Look Magazine instructed him to choose a hearing in Washington, which
                    will presumably take place a few weeks hence.</p>
                <pb facs="d786-2" n="2" type="facsimile" xml:id="d786-2"/>
                <p>The decision to seek to restrict the passports was taken with some reluctance in
                    view of the local uncertainty but our hand was more or less forced by the press
                    release of December 28 in which it was stated flatly that the passports would be
                    made valid for return to the U.S. only. We did soften the proposed action by
                    making it clear to our Embassy in Moscow that we did not require Stevens to come
                    home. The instruction was to endorse the passport “upon departure from the
                    Soviet Union, valid for return to the U.S. only”. This would enable Stevens to
                    continue his assignment in the U.S.S.R. without interruption. However Look has
                    elected to bring him home in late March in order to fight the case.</p>
                <p>We are faced with a flat defiance of the Department by Worthy, and strong
                    resistance short of defiance in the case of Look Magazine and Stevens.</p>
                <pb facs="1369" n="1322" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1322"/>
                <p>The Secretary took a very strong position in his press conference of February 5.
                    We have been looking through the Geneva records for the best documentation that
                    we can find based on <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName>’s remarks. Of
                    course we have the <persName corresp="#p_WP_1">Wang</persName> statement about
                    the handling of the prisoners being influenced by the state of relations between
                    the two countries and the tie in between visits by American citizens and the
                    “state of relations”. We have found nothing along this line dated later than
                    September 28, 1955. I presume neither you nor Dave recalls anything later or
                    more specific than this. I understand you got a copy of the Secretary’s press
                    conference separately, but to make sure that you have it, a copy is enclosed
                    herewith. We still hope to hold the line by voluntary action of the press, plus
                    limited administrative action where necessary. No acourt action is being
                    considered but we may run into <pb facs="d786-3" n="3" type="facsimile"
                        xml:id="d786-3"/> difficulties even here with administrative passport
                    action. The line up against us is pretty solid, especially since Senator
                    Humphrey has entered the picture with a proposed Senate investigation, and since
                    the American Society of Newspaper Editors has sent a resolution to the
                    President.</p>
                <p>2. We anticipate that your instructions for the February 14 meeting will follow
                    the usual line. We expect you to hammer hard at <persName corresp="#p_WP_1"
                        >Wang</persName> on the subject of the interview of December 28 between
                        <persName corresp="#p_OC_1">O’Neill</persName> and Huang Hua in which Huang
                    Hua virtually repudiates the Agreed Announcement by saying it has no application
                    to the Americans while they are imprisoned. I sent you a copy of O’Neill’s
                    report to Prague with my last letter of January 30. I hope you received it. As a
                    precaution another copy of O’Neill’s report is enclosed herewith.</p>
                <p>3. Also enclosed is a working draft of a proposed new press release on travel to
                    Communist China. It has been drafted largely with a view to clarifying the
                    questions and ambiguities which seem to exist as a result of the events of last
                    week. Bear in mind that this has not been approved and may undergo further
                    changes if it is put out at all.</p>
                <p>4. In answer to the question raised in your letter of January 28 from Prague, the
                    Department did intend for you to have the copy of Instruction A–159 to Taipei as
                    well as the NIE 43–56.</p>
                <p>5. We are working hard on a replacement for Osborn. The Embassy in London is very
                    shorthanded now in the sections which cover both FE and Middle Eastern Affairs.
                    It would be difficult for them to spare <persName corresp="#p_MEW_1">Ed
                        Martin</persName> at all till June. I believe we could get him then. We have
                    your telegram 389 agreeing to Dave Popper as an interim measure if we can get
                    him. We intend to sound out Geneva on this today and will probably authorize you
                    to take it up <pb facs="d786-4" n="4" type="facsimile" xml:id="d786-4"/> with
                        <persName corresp="#p_GFC_1">Gowen</persName> while you are in Geneva this
                    week. We fear that Geneva will feel that they cannot spare Popper. We will work
                    out some solution in any event.</p>
                <pb facs="1370" n="1323" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1323"/>
                <p>6. Judge Goodman in San Francisco is still considering the Wirin request for a
                    passport to go to Communist China. The Judge has requested Justice to submit
                    briefs on two questions as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Whether the Court possesses the power to compel the Secretary of State
                            to validate Wirin’s passport.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Whether the Court could compel the Government to elect either (a) to
                            validate Wirin’s passport or (b) the dismissal of the indictment.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>We armed Justice with quite a bit of material for the meeting which the Judge
                    held on February 1. We endeavored to show that the Communists were using the
                    Powell-Schumann trial as a lever to force official accreditation of an officer
                    of the Court for activities in Communist China.</p>
                <p>7. We are wishing you well and hoping that at the very least you will not have
                    dental trouble to plague you this time.</p>
                <p>Regards,</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MWP_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Walter P. McConaughy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Enclosures: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Secretary Dulles’ News Conference Feb. 5, 1957</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Interview with Huang Hua on December 28, 1956</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Memorandum from [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] in
                                Karachi dated December 28, 1956 re Chinese Communist Prime
                                Minister’s visit.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Working Draft of proposed new press release re travel to Communist
                                China.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Article in N.Y. Times dated Feb. 7, 1957 re American Newspaper
                                Publishers Assoc. Resolution sent to the President.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
