<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-07-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-07-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="811" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d811">
                        <head>811. Telegram 30 from Geneva<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d811fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 611.93/7–1157.
                                Confidential; Limit Distribution.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Geneva</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-07-11">July 11, 1957, 10
                                    a.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <pb facs="d811-1" n="1" type="facsimile" xml:id="d811-1"/>
                        <p>30. From <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Hammarskjold saw me this morning to say he wanted continue to coordinate
                            with me on question missing military personnel and Downey and Fecteau.
                            He said with respect missing military personnel someone suggested
                            recently proposed congressional resolution makes it desirable take some
                            new action. However, his view was that as matter now primarily in my
                            hands here and at MAC best that he not cross wires and would do nothing
                            additional unless we asked him. I said I agreed.</p>
                        <p>With respect Downey and Fecteau same consideration applies. In reply my
                            query as to what he thought he could do he said that as <persName corresp="#p_CEL_1">Chou</persName> had taken initiative raising
                            their cases with him he could readily go back to <persName corresp="#p_CEL_1">Chou</persName> with personal communication
                            concerning them. He said argument some made against this was that it
                            would single out Downey and Fecteau from other civilians still held. I
                            said latter consideration did not seem too important to me as Downey and
                            Fecteau were not only covered by agreed announcement but also by Korean
                            armistice and thus within scope U.N. resolution under which he acting. I
                            was therefore inclined to favor such approach by him at this time. <pb facs="1425" n="1378" type="typeset" xml:id="pg_1378"/> I did not see
                            it could do any harm and it might do good in indicating that U.N.
                            interest in them still alive. Said I would inform Washington and
                            Ambassador Lodge would be in further touch with him concerning
                            matter.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GFC_1"><hi rend="strong">Gowen</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>