<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Italy (
                        Kirk
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State
                    
                    Ambassador Kirk was also U.S. Political Adviser
                        on the staff of the Supreme Allied Commander, Mediterranean Theater.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d103</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">103</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-06-07T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-07T15:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-07T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-07T15:00:00-05:00" n="103" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d103">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Austria)/6–745: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="47a" xml:id="d103fn47a">Ambassador Kirk was also U.S. Political Adviser
                        on the staff of the Supreme Allied Commander, Mediterranean Theater.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Caserta</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-07T22:00:00+02:00">June 7, 1945—10 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received June 15—10:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2512. Our 2504, June 6, 9 p.m. Evening June 4 chiefs of missions to Vienna
                    presented to Blagodatov<note n="48" xml:id="d103fn48">Lieutenant General
                        Blagodatov, Soviet Commandant in Vienna</note> and to Morosov agreed plan of
                    procedure calling for individual survey parties from each mission to examine
                    general conditions and combined parties to investigate technical matters such as
                    communication and public utilities. Russians made some objection to detailed
                    examination all facilities on ground they were tasks for permanent occupation
                    and not reconnaissance parties but eventually agreed to general scheme.</p>
                <p>Later same evening Marshal Tolbukhin received chiefs of missions and again opened
                    question of length of visit, saying zoning question is of great urgency not only
                    for Allies but also for Austria which was in great need for rehabilitation, and
                    he hoped missions’ work would be finished in 7 days. Gen. Flory did not commit
                    himself to any fixed period but said mission could start work soon as detailed
                    programs were agreed upon. Gen. Winterton stated SAC had requested Winterton to
                    remain until zoning question had been settled. Tolbukhin replied he had orders
                    that when survey was completed all missions could leave.</p>
                <p>During discussions Tolbukhin stated casually air experts might begin examination
                    June 5 of airfield designated for three western Allies. When Flory said he was
                    not aware any airfield had been designated Tolbukhin replied that London had
                    named Tulln in the Stonz section. Flory made it clear this was not his
                    understanding.</p>
                <p>Morning June 5, missions met with Russians and after preliminary discussions re
                    communications, public utilities, medical and real estate, specialists paired
                    off with Russian opposite numbers to work out details. Morosov made it clear he
                    had no objections to complete inspection of all facilities within the
                    “Stadowein”, but stated nothing outside city limits were within competence of
                    missions although airfield at Tulln could be inspected immed. Flory insisted on
                    visiting all airfields in Vienna area to render complete report on existing
                    facilities and also pointed out that question of whether city or land limits
                    were to apply to Vienna zones was still not agreed by our Govts and for this
                    reason Flory could not accept Morosov’s limitations on missions’ activities to
                    city alone. Morosov stated his instructions were likewise clear and matter would
                    have to be referred to Tolbukhin. Meeting was adjourned pending Tolbukhin’s
                    reply.</p>
                <pb facs="0139" n="129" xml:id="pg_129"/>
                <p>During meeting Morosov also brought message from Tolbukhin that latter would see
                    mission chiefs on afternoon of June 10 at which time he expected their basis
                        [<hi rend="italic">basic?</hi>] work would be completed. Morosov was asked
                    to tell Tolbukhin that Flory and Winterton would give no assurance surveys would
                    be completed by that date.</p>
                <p>In subsequent discussion re courier plane flights to Vienna for Mission, Morosov
                    stated request for permits for such flights should be answered at same time as
                    question of airfields was settled.</p>
                <p>Sent Dept rptd Moscow as 172 London as 190.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
