<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Caffery) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1056</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1056</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-11-19T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-19T13:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-19T13:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-19T13:00:00-05:00" n="1056"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1056">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EW/11–1945: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-19T19:00:00+01:00"
                            >November 19, 1945—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 20—12:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6699. From Angell No. 69.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The following countries have changed more or less substantially the
                        statistical data originally submitted for reparations claims purposes:
                        Belgium, Czechoslovakia, Egypt, Greece, India, Norway, US,
                        Yugoslavia.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>For purposes of study have tried numerous formulae for combining data and
                        eliminating undesired items from original submissions. Formula least
                        unsatisfactory for present purposes is unweighted average of each country’s
                        percentage, as stated, of (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) direct war damage, (<hi
                            rend="italic">b</hi>) war expenditures during hostilities plus
                        occupation costs, and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) military man years
                        including prisoners of war.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Application of this formula to unscreened data as now revised by
                        submitting countries yields following rounded overall reparation shares in
                        percents: US 26, France 21, UK 25, others 28. These results discussed
                        informally with Waley but not yet with Rueff or others.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Have explored screening of data submitted to eliminate or adjust items
                        which seem overstated or inappropriate. Preliminary examination suggests
                        following: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Elimination of damages to monuments and cultural and historical
                                objects from claims for direct damage as follows: For France 1
                                billion dollars, for Yugoslavia 3.6 billion dollars.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Reduction of direct damage claims as follows: <list>
                                    <label>(1)</label>
                                    <item>France 20% because property damage was valued at new
                                        replacement cost with no allowance for accrued depreciation
                                        at time of damage and because some unit costs were
                                        unreasonably high;</item>
                                    <label>(2)</label>
                                    <item>Czechoslovakia and Greece 10% each, for similar reasons;
                                        and</item>
                                    <label>(3)</label>
                                    <item>Norway 50%, because ship losses seem seriously overvalued
                                        and because items relating to occupation costs and to
                                        under-maintenance were placed under heading of direct
                                        damage.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Elimination of prisoners of war from military man years.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>This adjustment of revised submissions and use of formula proposed in
                        paragraph 2 above would give following rounded percentages for overall
                        shares: US 27, France 18, UK 26, others 29. Other formulae which are almost
                        equally defensible in theory, however, yield markedly different results.
                        Seems clear that arithmetic and formulae alone will not solve shares
                        problem. Moreover, non-comparability within several categories of raw data
                        and long time <pb facs="1410" n="1400" xml:id="pg_1400"/> which would be
                        required to get better figures make exact arithmetical basis impractical to
                        achieve.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>In private talks with Rueff over past week, prior to receipt of urtel to
                        Angell 28,<note n="39" xml:id="d1056fn39">See telegram 5326, November 15, 6
                            p.m., to Paris, <ref target="#pg_1388">p. 1388</ref>.</note> I had
                        already indicated my belief that probable French recoveries from restitution
                        plus labor reparation plus French removals from French Zone would justify
                        giving France a lower share in global remaining reparation pot than
                        statistical formulae seemed likely to suggest, and that in any event, in
                        light of growing body of information available, I thought that percent of 21
                        for France previously discussed was too high.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>In further private talk with Rueff and me yesterday, Waley presented
                        instructions from his Government to request as overall percentage US 30,
                        France 15, UK 30, others 25. These proposals rest on a defensible
                        statistical basis for UK and for small countries, but on same basis for US
                        are too high and for France too low. Waley based this revision of his
                        earlier proposals on much the same grounds I had previously given Rueff
                        outlined in paragraph 6 above. Rueff insisted his Ministers would not
                        consider seriously such a proposal for France but agreed to present it to
                        them. He also argued French share should equal or exceed total for smaller
                        countries.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>I have not yet presented all of proposals in urtel to Angell 28 to Rueff
                        or Waley for tactical reasons, but have indicated US would consider
                        reduction of its statistical share. UK does not want to benefit therefrom,
                        but Waley suggests benefit be spread ratably among other countries.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>As practical compromise, lying between extreme UK position in paragraph 7
                        above and formula results in paragraph 5 above, and after reduction of US
                        share to level you indicate, suggest as overall shares US 20, France 18, UK
                        28, others 34. Since the shares discussion will be very active by middle of
                        week and is now stalled by lack of agreement among Big Three, propose to use
                        substantially these percentages as ultimate objective in discussions with
                        heads of delegation unless otherwise instructed. Reconciliation of
                        conflicting views, however, may require some flexibility within range of one
                        or two points either way for each major group, subject to minimum of 20 for
                        US.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Am already fairly near agreement with Waley on relative size of individual
                        small country shares within whatever percentage is allotted them in total.
                        No further discussion has taken place on percentages for plant removals.
                        [Angell.]</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
