<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-12T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-12T02:00:00-05:00" n="1104" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1104">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EW/12–1245: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-12T08:00:00+01:00">December
                                    12, 1945—8 a.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 2:06 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>7122. From Angell No. 139.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>First debate on share for non-repatriable persons took place
                                December 10. General concern expressed about definition of persons
                                eligible. Sharp opposition voiced by Yugoslav and Czech delegates to
                                aid for nationals of formerly occupied countries. Nationals of such
                                countries who refuse to return are considered enemies of present
                                democratic governments and of suspect loyalty to country during war.
                                In order to satisfy conference that aid will not be extended to
                                persons of anti-democratic sympathy, I proposed to amend clause
                                defining eligible classes as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“That persons in the classes described below should be
                                        eligible for aid under scheme provided that they cannot be
                                        repatriated within a reasonable time, that they require aid
                                        for their resettlement or rehabilitation and that they are
                                        not found to have voluntarily supported the German war
                                        effort: <list>
                                            <label>
                                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>German and Austrian nationals including: <list>
                                                  <label>(I)</label>
                                                  <item>Those who are now refugees from Germany and
                                                  Austria and,</item>
                                                  <label>(II)</label>
                                                  <item>Those still resident in Germany and Austria
                                                  who were deprived of their citizenship under Nazi
                                                  laws and who do not desire to remain in Germany or
                                                  Austria.</item>
                                                </list>
                                            </item>
                                            <label>
                                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>Nationals of countries formerly occupied by the
                                                Germans who cannot be repatriated within a
                                                reasonable time and who were victims of Nazi
                                                persecution. In order to exclude persons whose
                                                loyalty to the United Nations is doubtful, aid shall
                                                be restricted to nationals of” formerly occupied
                                                countries who were victims of German concentration
                                                camps.”</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                </quote>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Informal talk with Czech and Yugoslav delegates indicates that
                                paragraph 1, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, will not be acceptable to
                                them. I hope, however, <pb facs="1465" n="1455" xml:id="pg_1455"/>
                                that it may satisfy remainder of conference. If further opposition
                                develops to this and other aspects of scheme, I shall attempt to
                                secure acceptance of principle of scheme in accordance with
                                suggestion in mytel from Angell No. 131,<note n="38" xml:id="d1104fn38">See telegram 7084, December 9, 8 p.m., from
                                    Paris, <ref target="#pg_1451">p. 1451</ref>.</note> paragraph 2.
                                However, it may be necessary to provide that specific programs of
                                aid for nationals of formerly occupied countries be subject to veto
                                of such countries. I am conscious of political aspects of this
                                suggestion. Authorization of Department for such provision urgently
                                requested if acceptable. Further delay at present stage of
                                conference will make action difficult.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>With respect to urtel for Angell No. 84,<note n="39" xml:id="d1104fn39">See telegram 5760, December 10, 7 p.m., to
                                    Paris, <ref target="#pg_1451">p. 1451</ref>
                                </note> paragraph 3, I do not consider it feasible to suggest higher
                                sum than dollars 25 million ($25,000,000). This sum believed
                                consistent with original instructions Repmem 3<note n="40" xml:id="d1104fn40">Not printed.</note> which suggested 1 or
                                2%.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Reply immediate.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Sent Dept as 7122 from Angell No. 139 repeated to London for Stevenson
                            858 from Angell No. 11. [Angell.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Caffery</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>