<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany
                        (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1163</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1163</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-11T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-11T14:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="finance" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885" lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="transportation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="prices" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518" lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-11T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-11T14:00:00-05:00" n="1163" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1163">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">660F.6231/10–1145</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-11T21:00:00+02:00">October 11, 1945—9 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 11—8:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>753. There is given below the text of a preliminary draft of the United States
                    proposal regarding establishment of Allied Export-Import Authority for Germany.
                    These tentative proposals were drawn up in the office of Fred Winant and after
                    having been informally shown to Economics, Political and Finance Divisions are
                    being turned over to the Russian representative. If the Department wishes to
                    cable comments or criticisms of the proposals, there will be sufficient time as
                    the matter will have to be submitted to the Economic Directorate even if it
                    should obtain immediate clearance by the Export-Import Sub-Committee.</p>
                <p>Paragraph 3 <hi rend="italic">d</hi> refers to funds which have been derived
                    under the existing agreement (see our telegram 487, September 10, 9 p.m. and
                    593, September 23, 3 p.m.). This paragraph is not designed to allow zonal
                    commanders to determine trade patterns nor to avoid quadripartite agreement on
                    imports.</p>
                <pb facs="1542" n="1532" xml:id="pg_1532"/>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“1. Establishment of Allied Export-Import Authority for Germany.</p>
                    <p>There is hereby established an Allied Export-Import Authority for Germany
                        which shall be an agency of the Allied Control Authority. The Allied
                        Export-Import Authority for Germany will consist of a board of directors and
                        an executive officer. The board of directors will be composed of the members
                        of the Export-Import Sub-Committee or persons designated by such members;
                        the executive officer will be chosen by and operate under the direction of
                        the board of directors; assistant executive officers will be appointed by
                        the zone commanders in each zone. The salary of the executive officer and
                        the assistant executive officers will be fixed by the board of directors and
                        will be paid out of the proceeds of German exports.</p>
                    <p>2. Functions of Allied Export-Import Authority for Germany.</p>
                    <p>The functions of the Allied Export-Import Authority for Germany are: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To authorize and if necessary to arrange for the sale of exports,
                                including the collection, storage, transportation and delivery of
                                goods, and the receipt of payment therefor.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To authorize and if necessary to arrange for the purchase of
                                approved imports, including the transportation and delivery of
                                goods, and payment therefor.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>In consultation with other interested agencies of the Allied
                                Control Authority, to formulate from time to time and to submit
                                export-import programs for approval by the Control Council or its
                                authorized agency. The first tentative program is set forth in
                                paragraph 4 and 5 below, covering the period from 1 November 1945 to
                                30 June 1946. The preliminary data on which this program is based
                                will be reviewed in the light of the latest available information,
                                and a revised program submitted by 15 December, 1945, to cover the
                                period from 1 January 1946 to 30 June 1946. Thereafter programs will
                                be reviewed quarterly and submitted semi-annually or more frequently
                                as directed by the Control Council.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To collect and analyze data necessary for the preparation of
                                export-import programs; to maintain records of import and export
                                transactions; to prepare and submit such reports as may from time to
                                time be required by the Allied Control Authority.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To exercise such other functions as may be delegated to it in
                                order to insure the proper financing and implementation of approved
                                export-import programs.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To organize its operations and employ such personnel in addition
                                to the executive officer as may be necessary to the discharge of the
                                foregoing functions.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>3. Statement of policy.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">It is agreed: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That in order to provide funds for approved imports, payment will
                                be made at the rate of not less than 80 percent of the established
                                price of all exports from current production and stock, beginning 1
                                August 1945.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That such payment will be made to approved banks for the account
                                of the Allied Export-Import Authority for Germany in <pb facs="1543" n="1533" xml:id="pg_1533"/> United States dollars or any other
                                currency acceptable to the Control Council or its authorized agency,
                                at prices fixed on the basis of policies established by the Control
                                Council or its authorized agency.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That any funds credited to the special account of the Control
                                Council set up in paragraph 4, CONL/P(45)32, approved by the Control
                                Council on 20 September 1945,<note n="88" xml:id="d1163fn88">CONL/P
                                    (45)32 is summarized in telegram 487, September 10, 9 p.m., from
                                    Berlin, <ref target="#pg_1527">p. 1527</ref>; for Control
                                    Council approval, see telegram 569, September 20, 10 p.m., from
                                    Berlin, <ref target="#pg_836">p. 836</ref>.</note> will be
                                transferred to the account of the Allied Export-Import Authority for
                                Germany. Payments made from this special account and obligations
                                incurred by the special account will be taken into consideration in
                                such transfer.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That the funds derived from such payments and transfers will be
                                used by the Allied Export-Import Authority for Germany to discharge
                                obligations arising out of import programs which have been approved
                                by the Control Council or the zonal commanders, as authorized in
                                paragraph 4, CONL/P(45) 32, approved by the Control Council, 20
                                September 1945.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That on matters pertaining to financing the Allied Export-Import
                                Authority for Germany will operate under policies established by the
                                Finance Directorate.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                            <item>That as soon as practicable a central German administrative
                                department will be set up in the field of foreign trade. At that
                                time the functions of the Allied Export-Import Authority, set forth
                                in paragraph 2 above, will be transferred to the extent deemed
                                advisable, to the German department and thereafter the Allied
                                Export-Import Authority will control and supervise the operations of
                                such department.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
