<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-07-09T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-07-09T09:00:00-05:00" n="126" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d126">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EAC/7–945: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-07-09T16:00:00+02:00">July 9,
                                    1945—4 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 4:59 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>6894. Comea 329. At request Soviet rep EAC met this morning to complete
                            text agreement on zones in Austria. Re pgh 2 my tel 6857 July 7, rptd
                            AusPolAd 17, Murphy, 21, Gousev has now recd authorization his govt for
                            inclusion in report of free transit for Allied goods and common use
                            Vienna facilities. Agreement on zones to be signed 9 p.m., tonight.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow changes to be inserted into final text of agreement on zones
                            of occupation in Austria. See the bracketed note <hi rend="italic">infra.</hi>]</p>
                        <p>Full text of covering report to zones agreement begins:</p>
                        <p>(<hi rend="italic">Title</hi>) Report by EAC to Govts of USA, UK and USSR
                            and Provisional Govt of French Rep.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Beginning of text</hi>. In submitting text of
                            agreement on zones of occupation in Austria and administration of City
                            of Vienna for consideration and approval by Govts of USA, UK, USSR and
                            Prov Govt of French Rep, the EAC recommends that the four govts issue
                            directions to their respective C-in-C in Austria as follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Personnel of the forces of occupation in Austria, including
                                    those allotted for occupation of Vienna and personnel of allied
                                    commission will have freedom of movement and communication
                                    thruout Austria in execution of their duties or when traveling
                                    on leave in accordance with regulations to be established by
                                    Allied Council.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Allied Council will make necessary arrangements for transit in
                                    Austria by road, rail, air and water for goods and supplies
                                    required by the forces of occupation in Austria, including those
                                    forces allotted for the occupation of the City of Vienna and
                                    personnel of Allied <pb facs="0169" n="159" xml:id="pg_159"/>
                                    Commission and likewise for common use of transport and
                                    communication facilities and public utility services in City of
                                        Vienna.<note n="91" xml:id="d126fn91">This article was a
                                        redraft by the Soviet Delegation of an earlier draft article
                                        approved by the United States, British, and French
                                        Delegations on June 23 and reading as follows: “There shall
                                        be freedom of transit throughout Austria by road, rail, and
                                        water for the goods and supplies required by the forces of
                                        occupation in Austria, including those forces allotted for
                                        the occupation of Vienna, and by the Allied Commission, in
                                        accordance with regulations to be established by the Allied
                                        Council”. (European Advisory Commission Files: Lot 52 M 64)
                                            <p>According to the United States Delegation minutes of
                                            the Commission’s meeting of July 9, the following
                                            exchange followed Gousev’s presentation of the Soviet
                                            redraft of the article: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Hood</hi> noted that
                                                  the Soviet draft did not mention ‘free transit’
                                                  but only stated ‘transit.’</p>
                                                <p>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Mosely</hi> commented
                                                  that in practice this did not seem to make any
                                                  great difference as the statement that
                                                  arrangements for transit would be worked out
                                                  surely meant that there would be all necessary
                                                  transit rights.</p>
                                                <p>“M. <hi rend="smallcaps">Massigli</hi> also felt
                                                  that the Soviet draft covered the point
                                                  satisfactorily and he stated that his Delegation
                                                  therefore now withdrew its reservation regarding
                                                  the tentative agreement on the airdromes.”
                                                  (European Advisory Commission Files: Lot 52 M
                                                  64)</p>
                                            </quote>
                                        </p>
                                    </note>
                                </item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Use of facilities located in the district of Innerestadt will
                                    be regulated equitably by inter-Allied governing authority
                                    (Komendatura). The Soviet C-in-C will allocate areas in
                                    territory of the Soviet zone necessary for small unit training
                                    and recreation of Allied occupation forces stationed in City of
                                    Vienna.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Living accommodation outside the City will be found in special
                                    cases for senior officers and officials by arrangements agreed
                                    between respective C-in-C. <hi rend="italic">End of text.</hi>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>This complete final text of report supercedes texts transmitted my tel
                            6761, July 5; my tel 6372 June 23 and my tel 6584 June 29.</p>
                        <p>Repeated AusPolAd 20 and Murphy 28.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>[An agreement between the Governments of the United States of
                                America, the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, and the United
                                Kingdom and the Provisional Government of the French Republic on
                                zones of occupation in Austrial and the administration of the City
                                of Vienna was signed <hi rend="italic">ad referendum</hi> at a
                                meeting of the European Advisory Commission at London on July 9,
                                1945. Notification of approval by the respective signatories was
                                given by their representatives on the Commission on the following
                                dates: the United Kingdom, July 12; France, July 16; the Soviet
                                Union, July 21; and the United States, July 24, 1945. For text of
                                the agreement and annexed maps, see Department of State, Treaties
                                and Other International Acts Series (TIAS) 1600, or 61 Stat. (pt. 3)
                                2679. For documentation regarding the agreement on zones of
                                occupation in Austria and the problem of the occupation of the
                                western zones and of Vienna, <pb facs="0170" n="160" xml:id="pg_160"/> see <hi rend="italic">Conference of Berlin</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Potsdam</hi>), volume I, pages 347–356, and volume
                                II, pages 156, 164, 167, 175–176, 181–182, 244, 310–311, 316–317,
                                368, 393, 553, 603, 668–683, 1489–1490, and 1507.]</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>