<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                        Winant
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d159</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">159</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-03-17T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-03-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-03-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="159" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d159">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EAC/3–1745</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 21791</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-03-17">March 17,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received March 23.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit a copy of a report
                    of the Allied Consultation Committee to the European Advisory Commission giving
                    the results of its conferences with the representatives of certain other Allied
                    Governments on questions relating to the surrender terms for Germany. There are
                    also enclosed copies of informal notes of the meetings of the Allied
                    Consultation Committee and an exchange of letters between the Chairman of the
                    Committee and the Chairman of the European Advisory Commission with respect to
                    the functions of the Committee. The Secretary-General,<note n="83" xml:id="d159fn83">E. P. Donaldson</note> who prepared the notes of the
                    meetings, did not prepare a report of the proceedings at the first meeting of
                    the Allied Consultation Committee which was held on December 18, 194. To make
                    the record complete it can be stated that that meeting concerned itself with the
                    election of a chairman and a discussion of the manner of handling the
                    consultation with the other Allied Governments. It was decided at that meeting
                    to submit <pb facs="0201" n="191" xml:id="pg_191"/> certain questions to the
                    Chairman of the European Advisory Commission asking for clarification as to the
                    scope of the functions of the Committee. These questions were submitted in the
                    enclosed letter (P12/26/44).<note n="83a" xml:id="d159fn83a">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_199">p. 199</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>A summary of the Surrender Instrument, which was presented to the representatives
                    who met with the Consultation Committee, was transmitted to the Department with
                    the Embassy’s despatch No. 20232 of January 6, 1944 [<hi rend="italic">1945</hi>].</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador: <lb/>
                    <signed>E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Allan Lightner, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary, U.S. Delegation<lb/>European Advisory
                        Commission</hi>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Report of the Allied Consultation Committee to the
                            European Advisory Commission</hi>
                        <note n="84" xml:id="d159fn84">Adopted at a meeting of the Committee held on
                            March 14, 1945</note>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">P12/60/45</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> I.—<hi rend="smallcaps">Introduction</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>In accordance with the instructions of the European Advisory Commission
                        contained in the last paragraph of the Chairman’s<note n="85" xml:id="d159fn85">Sir William Strang</note> letter of 6th January, 1945
                            (P12/35/45),<note n="86" xml:id="d159fn86">
                            <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_200">p. 200</ref>
                        </note> the Committee has the honour to present herewith a First Report on
                        its meetings with the representatives of the Governments of Czechoslovakia,
                        Belgium, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, Norway, Yugoslavia and Greece. The
                        representatives of these countries (whose names are given in Annex A) were
                        received in the above order, which corresponds to that in which the
                        Commission’s invitation to engage in consultation was accepted by their
                        respective Governments. The representatives of Belgium, Luxembourg and the
                        Netherlands, whose Governments had submitted a joint memorandum to the
                        Commission, were, at their request, received together.</p>
                    <p>2. At the first meeting with each group of representatives, two copies (in
                        both the English and Russian versions) of the Summary of the Instrument of
                        Unconditional Surrender in the form approved by the Commission at the
                        informal meeting held on 7th December, 1944 (P8/33/44)<note n="86a" xml:id="d159fn86a">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_168">p. 168</ref>.</note>
                        were handed to the representatives of each Government. Assurances were
                        received in each case that the minimum circulation possible would be given
                        to the document, the secret character of which was explained to those
                        present. The representatives of <pb facs="0202" n="192" xml:id="pg_192"/>
                        Czechoslovakia and of Belgium, Luxembourg and the Netherlands were informed,
                        in reply to questions, that the Committee was not authorised to communicate
                        to them the full text of the Instrument, which, for security reasons, must
                        remain secret for the present.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> II.—<hi rend="smallcaps">Conclusions and
                            Recommendations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>3. The Czechoslovak, Netherlands, Belgian, Luxembourg and Greek Governments
                        have confirmed their desire to participate with their armed forces in the
                        occupation of Germany. The Committee considers that their wishes might be
                        taken into account in considering the concrete steps to be taken to give
                        effect to the terms of Article 4 of the Agreement of 12th September, 1944,
                        on Zones of Occupation which provides for the possibility of including
                        auxiliary contingents of the Allied Powers in the composition of the forces
                        of occupation. In the Committee’s view, this question could best be answered
                        if the Commission were to authorise it to communicate to the Governments
                        concerned a summary of the Agreement on Zones of Occupation.</p>
                    <p>4. The Czechoslovak, Netherlands, Belgian, Luxembourg and Greek Governments
                        have confirmed their desire to participate in the machinery of control in
                        Germany. The Committee considers that this question could best be answered
                        if the Commission were to authorise it to communicate to the Governments
                        concerned a summary of the Agreement on Machinery of Control in Germany.</p>
                    <p>5. All the Allied Governments consulted have expressed a wish to continue the
                        consultations regarding Terms of Surrender for Germany and additional
                        requirements to be imposed under the General Article which are of special
                        concern to those Governments—in particular, economic questions such as
                        restitution and spoliation, repatriation of displaced persons, and disposal
                        of German war material. The Committee considers that this desire could be
                        satisfied by continuing at the appropriate moment consultations with this
                        Committee, or with any other competent body authorised by the European
                        Advisory Commission to continue the discussion.</p>
                    <p>6. The wishes of the Allied Governments consulted as set out in paragraphs
                        11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 22, 23, 24, 25, 30, 33 and 34 below could, in the
                        Committee’s view, be considered and given appropriate expression in the
                        forthcoming preparation of Orders, Instructions, etc.</p>
                    <p>7. The Commission may wish to consider whether or not the Allied Consultation
                        Committee should answer the desire of the Belgian, Luxembourg and
                        Netherlands Governments for an explanation of the juridical position of the
                        respective National Authorities in securing the execution of the Terms of
                        Surrender in liberated territory. This request is mentioned in paragraph 21
                        below. If the E.A.C. authorizes discussion of this subject, the Allied
                        Consultation Committee would <pb facs="0203" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/>
                        appreciate guidance from the Commission with respect to the answers to be
                        given.</p>
                    <p>8. The Committee suggests that consideration of the proposals presented by
                        the Norwegian Government, to which reference is made in paragraph 29 below,
                        should be pursued through appropriate military channels and that this
                        Committee should be authorised to inform the Norwegian representatives to
                        that effect.</p>
                    <p>9. In view of their concrete nature and importance, the wishes of the
                        Czechoslovak Government referred to in paragraph 17 below and set out in
                        Part II of the Memorandum of the Czechoslovak Minister of Foreign
                            Affairs<note n="87" xml:id="d159fn87">Jan Masaryk</note> dated 24th
                        August, 1944<note n="88" xml:id="d159fn88">Not printed. For a summary of
                            views of the Czechoslovak Government, see <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_72">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 72</ref>
                        </note> and in later documents, merit the special consideration of the
                        European Advisory Commission.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Part</hi> III.—<hi rend="smallcaps">Views of the Allied
                            Governments</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>10. The following paragraphs set out the points to which the several
                        countries attach special importance and in regard to which the Committee
                        undertook to invite the particular attention of the Commission. These points
                        have been arranged, in the sections dealing with each country or group of
                        countries, as they relate to (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the Instrument of
                        Unconditional Surrender and the Orders, etc. to be issued thereunder, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the occupation of Germany, (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Allied Control Machinery in Germany, (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)
                        further consultation or association between the Allied Governments and the
                        European Advisory Commission.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">czechoslovakia</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Instrument of Surrender.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>11. This Government considers that the Terms of Surrender should stipulate in
                        connection with the evacuation of occupied territory, that all requisitions
                        and other coercive measures should cease immediately, that no damage is to
                        be caused to public or private property, and that all agricultural and
                        industrial plants, installations, services, etc. must be left in good
                        working condition; that nothing must be exported and that persons leaving
                        the country must not carry away anything except their personal goods and
                        chattels.</p>
                    <p>12. In the view of the Czechoslovak Government, cash reserves of currency of
                        all kinds held on Allied territory by enemy military and civilian
                        authorities (but not German currency held by private persons) should be
                        included among the property to be placed at the disposal of the Allied
                        Representatives. Gold belonging to or held by the German State, public
                        corporations and banks in Germany and <pb facs="0204" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/> in neutral countries should be added to the items to
                        be held at the disposal of the Allied Representatives. If provisions to this
                        effect are not included in the Instrument of Surrender itself, but are
                        imposed by orders issued under the General Article, this Government
                        considers that the necessary orders should be worked out beforehand so that
                        they can be issued simultaneously with the signature of the Instrument or
                        immediately after the capitulation.</p>
                    <p>13. The Czechoslovak representatives suggest that the Instrument of Surrender
                        should include an acknowledgment of the responsibility of Germany for loss
                        and damage caused to the United Nations by German aggression and should
                        affirm the right of the United Nations whose territories were occupied by
                        Germany to restitution of the identifiable property seized by Germany and to
                        compensation for other property as well as for damage and loss caused during
                        the occupation.</p>
                    <p>14. A provision is suggested forbidding Germany any intercourse with, or any
                        export to, foreign countries without permission of the Allies. All German or
                        German-held assets in neutral countries should be placed at the disposal of
                        the Allied Representatives by the German authorities.</p>
                    <p>15. The Czechoslovak Government is interested in securing the release from
                        military service and auxiliary services under military organisation,
                        including the Todt organization,<note n="89" xml:id="d159fn89">An auxiliary
                            service of the German Armed Forces charged with the carrying out of
                            certain technical construction work, particularly road, rail, and
                            fortification construction. Organization Todt used forced foreign labor
                            to a considerable extent</note> of all Allied nationals (excluding
                        Germans and Magyars). Provisions to this effect should, in its view, be
                        included in the relevant article of the Instrument of Surrender, which
                        should also include a stipulation providing for the best possible treatment
                        of displaced nationals of the United Nations, especially workers, pending
                        repatriation.</p>
                    <p>16. This Government considers that German authorities should be bound by the
                        Instrument of Surrender to deliver up war criminals to justice, the
                        principal ones being handed over immediately on capitulation.</p>
                    <p>17. The Czechoslovak representatives expressed a strong desire that
                        provisions dealing with certain political questions in which their
                        Government is interested should be included in the Instrument of Surrender
                        to be confirmed by Germany by the signature of her plenipotentiaries. These
                        questions are the three included in Section II of the <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> submitted by the Czechoslovak Foreign Minister on
                        24th August, 1944 [P12B/3/44] relating to (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                        political clauses (nullification of certain treaties), (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the date of the beginning of the state of war between the
                        Czechoslovak Republic and Germany and <pb facs="0205" n="195" xml:id="pg_195"/> Hungary, and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the transfer
                        of Germans and Magyars from Czechoslovakia to Germany and Hungary.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Occupation of Germany</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>18. The Czechoslovak Government reiterates its request to be allowed to take
                        part in the military occupation of Germany.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Allied Control Machinery in Germany</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>19. The Czechoslovak Government desires to be represented on the various
                        Allied bodies, Commissions and agencies which may be set up for the
                        execution of the Instrument of Surrender and orders issued thereunder.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Further Consultation with E.A.C.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>20. The Czechoslovak Government desires to be associated as closely as
                        possible with the drafting of the additional requirements and regulations
                        designed for issue by the Allied Representatives under the General Article.
                        In particular, it wishes to be given the opportunity of making observations
                        and suggestions regarding the restitution of looted property, the question
                        of enemy currency in the occupied countries (including gold), the supply of
                        German goods and services for the economic restoration of Allied countries,
                        and the liquidation of enemy property (including incorporeal property, e.g.,
                        patents, copyrights, etc.) in Allied countries.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">belgium, luxembourg and the netherlands</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Instrument of Surrender</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>21. The representatives of these Governments have expressed concern about the
                        use in the Preamble of the Instrument of Surrender of the phrase “in the
                        interests of the United Nations”. They wish to be assured that “no
                        expression in the Instrument of Surrender leaves any doubt that all
                        obligations to be imposed thereunder have force for the benefit of each of
                        the United Nations concerned and give each of them the direct right to claim
                        their execution by the enemy”. They have asked for an explanation of the
                        juridical position of the respective national authorities in securing the
                        execution of the Terms of Surrender in liberated territory.</p>
                    <p>22. The three Governments are anxious that provision should be made in the
                        Instrument of Surrender itself for safeguarding the life and property of all
                        Allied nationals in any territory not evacuated by the enemy before
                        capitulation.</p>
                    <p>23. The attention of the Committee was drawn to the recommendations in
                        Section D of Chapter II of the joint memorandum submitted to the Commission
                        by the three Governments [pp. 7–8 of <pb facs="0206" n="196" xml:id="pg_196"/> P12C/1/44<note n="90" xml:id="d159fn90">Not printed. For a summary of the
                            views of the Governments of Belgium, Luxembourg and the Netherlands, see
                                <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_70">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 70</ref>
                        </note>] regarding disarmament and demobilisation of the German armed
                        forces, the disposal of war material and stores, the demolition of military
                        installations and fortifications, and the allocation to the victorious
                        Powers of ex-enemy munitions and war booty.</p>
                    <p>24. As regards the release and repatriation of displaced persons of Allied
                        nationality, the three Governments ask that special attention should be
                        given to the views expressed by any of them regarding the priority to be
                        accorded to individuals or categories of citizens whose early return to
                        their respective countries is required for reconstruction and
                        rehabilitation. They ask whether machinery has been set up to deal with this
                        problem and suggest that, if this has not yet been done, the establishment
                        of machinery should be considered without delay. The Belgian Government ask
                        for special consideration for the early return to Belgium of the King of the
                            Belgians<note n="91" xml:id="d159fn91">Leopold II.</note> and his
                        family.</p>
                    <p>25. The three representatives have asked for the insertion hi the Instrument
                        of Surrender of a provision by which Germany would be bound as regards each
                        Allied State to carry out her pre-war Treaty obligations in so far as she is
                        not expressly released from such obligations by the other party or parties
                        to the treaties or conventions concerned. The Belgian Representative also
                        asked for provision to be made in the Instrument of Surrender for the
                        nullification of the annexation of Belgian territory (Eupen, Malmédy and St.
                        Vith) unilaterally incorporated in the German Reich in 1940.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Occupation of Germany</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>26. The three Governments attach importance to the inter-Allied character of
                        the occupation. So far as their other military commitments permit (in
                        particular the obligations of the Netherlands Government in the war against
                        Japan), they would wish to be represented by appropriate contingents.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Allied Control Machinery</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>27. The three Governments have expressed the view that there should be a
                        permanent Central Allied Commission with adequate representation for all
                        States with a direct interest in the fulfilment of the terms of
                        capitulation, including in particular liberated countries.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Further Consultation with E.A.C.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>28. The three Governments have expressed their desire to be consulted at the
                        appropriate stage on the economic provisions to be imposed upon Germany by
                        orders issued under the General Article in respect of such matters as the
                        restitution of looted property, reparations <pb facs="0207" n="197" xml:id="pg_197"/> for damage and spoliation, the disposal of German war
                        factories and munitions plant and the allocation of German war material and
                        stores. In addition, further consultation is desired in connection with the
                        surrender of war criminals.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">norway</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Instrument of Surrender</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>29. The Norwegian representatives drew the particular attention of the
                        Committee to the proposals which their Government had submitted in their
                        memorandum of 2nd September, 1944 [P12H/3/44].<note n="92" xml:id="d159fn92">Not printed. For a summary of the views of the Norwegian Government,
                            see <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_73">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 73</ref>
                        </note> They asked whether consideration had been given to the 14 draft
                        Articles se [<hi rend="italic">set?</hi>] out in Annex A to that memorandum
                        which had been drawn up for incorporation in the Terms of Surrender to be
                        imposed upon the German authorities in Norway. The first of these Articles
                        reads as follows: “The terms shall be notified to the Germans and their
                        subordinates in Norway by two Allied plenipotentiaries, one of whom shall be
                        appointed by the Norwegian Government”. The remaining 13 Articles provide
                        detailed regulations for the control and disarmament of German forces and
                        German-controlled organisations in Norway.</p>
                    <p>30. The Norwegian Government are especially concerned with the control of
                        German shipping and shipbuilding; their representatives thought that the
                        orders to be issued under the General Article affecting such matters
                        especially affecting Norwegian interests should be issued simultaneously
                        with, or immediately after, the signature of the Instrument of
                        Surrender.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Further Consultation with the E.A.C.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>31. This Government’s representatives expressed a strong desire to be
                        associated with the Committee or with any bodies set up by the Commission in
                        the future which might be concerned with drafting orders and proclamations
                        for issue under the General Article. They were anxious that there should be
                        an opportunity of discussing matters of particular concern to the Norwegian
                        Government, particularly those relating to naval vessels and merchant ships,
                        before final decisions were reached.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">yugoslavia</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>32. The representative of this Government attended a meeting of the Committee
                        on 23rd January, when he said that he had no questions to raise at that
                        stage. It would appear from the letter addressed to <pb facs="0208" n="198" xml:id="pg_198"/> the Chairman of the Commission by the Yugoslav Prime
                            Minister<note n="93" xml:id="d159fn93">Ivan Ŝubaŝić</note> of 3rd
                        January (P12G/3/45)<note n="94" xml:id="d159fn94">Not printed</note> that
                        the Royal Yugoslav Government desire to reserve their attitude until after
                        the formation of a single Yugoslav Government in association with the
                        National Committee of Liberation in Belgrade.<note n="95" xml:id="d159fn95">For documentation regarding the interest of the United States in the
                            formation of a united Yugoslav government, see <ref target="frus1944v04#pg_1330">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 1330</ref> ff</note> It may be
                        expected that when this Government has been formed, its fully-considered and
                        documented views will be presented.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">greece</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Instrument of Surrender</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>33. At the meeting of the Committee held on 15th February, the Greek
                        representatives presented a memorandum emphasising their Government’s desire
                        that Greece’s claims against Germany should be referred to the Allied
                        Representatives who would receive the capitulation of Germany, with a view
                        to those Representatives considering the compensation to be made for the
                        loss and damage suffered by the Greek nation. In particular, the Greek
                        representatives asked “that from the war material, etc. to be held by the
                        German authorities at the disposal of the Allied Representatives, a quantity
                        be allotted to the requirements of the Greek Army sufficient to place the
                        latter on a war footing of 25 fully-equipped divisions”.</p>
                    <p>34. The further request was made that a demand should be made on the German
                        military forces who might still be in occupation of Greek territory at the
                        time of surrender for the handing over to the Greek military authorities of
                        all war equipment, military installations, etc. in that territory in good
                        condition.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Occupation of Germany</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>35. Greece desires to be invited to join in the military occupation of
                        Germany.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Allied Control Machinery in Germany</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>36. Greece wishes to be represented on the Inter-Allied Commission of Control
                        in Germany.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Further Consultation with the E.A.C., etc.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>37. The Greek representatives asked that their Government’s desire that the
                        surrender of territory and military installations shall be carried out in
                        the particular way proposed (see paragraph 34 above) should be further
                        discussed with those responsible for drafting orders for issue under the
                        General Article.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-03-14">14 March,
                                1945</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0209" n="199" xml:id="pg_199"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex A</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">List or Representatives of Allied Governments Consulted
                            by the Allied Consultation Committee</hi>
                    </p>
                    <table cols="2" rows="13">
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Czechoslovakia</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. J. Spacek, Minister
                                Plenipotentiary</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. Z. Prochazka, Minister
                                Plenipotentiary</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Belgium</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Monsieur Fernand Van Langenhove,
                                Secretary-General Ministry of Foreign Affairs</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Luxembourg</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">H. E. Monsieur Joseph Bech, Minister of
                                Foreign Affairs</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Monsieur Alphonse Als, Chef de Cabinet of the
                                Minister of Foreign Affairs</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Netherlands</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. W. Huender, Chief of the Section of
                                Postwar Problems, Ministry of Foreign Affairs</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Norway</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. C. F. Smith, Minister to Belgium</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Yugoslavia</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. J. Melander, Economic Adviser to Foreign
                                Minister</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Greece</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">H. E. Dr. Stoyan Gavrilovic, Under-Secretary
                                of State for Foreign Affairs</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">H. E. Monsieur Thanassis Aghnides, Ambassador
                                Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Major-General Ventiris</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Lieutenant-Colonel Stathatos</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Copy of a Letter Dated December 27, 1944 From the Chairman
                            of the Allied Consultation Committee</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Sobolev</hi>) <hi rend="italic">to the Chairman of the European
                            Advisory Commission</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Strang</hi>)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">P12/26/44</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir William</hi>: On behalf of my colleagues<note n="96" xml:id="d159fn96">Philip E. Mosely (for the United States),
                            Viscount Samuel Hood (for the United Kingdom), and Comte Pierre Marie de
                            Leusse (for France)</note> at the Consultation Committee I submit to you
                        the attached report for consideration by the Commission.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sobolev</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Report</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Committee which the Commission agreed on 7th December to set up to
                            conduct discussions with representatives of the European <pb facs="0210" n="200" xml:id="pg_200"/> Allied Governments would welcome
                            instructions from the Commission on the following points:— <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Whilst the Committee proposes to state, in reply to any
                                    enquiry from the representatives of the European Allied
                                    Governments, that the Instrument of Surrender, itself must be
                                    withheld at this stage because it is a document of primary
                                    military character which has immediate security significance and
                                    must accordingly receive very restricted circulation, may the
                                    Committee give an assurance that the full text will be
                                    communicated to the European Allied Governments in due course
                                    prior to the actual surrender of Germany?</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Is it within the competence of the Committee to discuss with
                                    the representatives of the European Allied Governments the
                                    questions of occupation and control machinery and to inform them
                                    of the Commission’s recommendations on these subjects, if
                                    necessary by communicating a summary of the two
                                    Protocols?</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Are the functions of the Committee— <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>to discuss with the representatives of the European
                                            Allied Governments any points raised by the latter on
                                            the summary of the Instrument of Surrender whether in
                                            regard to the subjects specified in para 2 of the
                                            summary or the subjects which will be covered by the
                                            further documents mentioned in para 3 of the
                                            summary?</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>to discuss any points arising from the memoranda
                                            submitted to the Commission by the European Allied
                                            Governments on which the representatives of those
                                            governments desire to obtain the views of the
                                            Commission?</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-29">29
                                    December, 1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 3]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Copy of a Letter Dated January 6, 1945, From the Chairman
                            of the European Advisory Commission</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Strang</hi>)
                            <hi rend="italic">to the Chairman of the Allied Consultation
                            Committee</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Sobolev</hi>)</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">P12/35/45</p>
                    <p>As you are aware, I have referred to the Commission the report of the Allied
                        Consultation Committee which you submitted with your letter of the 27th
                        December, 1944. This was discussed at the informal meeting held on 2nd
                        January, 1945, when the Commission agreed on the following answers to the
                        questions in the Committee’s report:— <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The Commission approves the proposal that, if any representatives
                                of the European Allied Governments should ask for the communication
                                of the text of the Instrument of Surrender itself, the reply should
                                be given that it is a document of primary military character which
                                has immediate security significance and must accordingly receive
                                very restricted circulation. The Commission is unable <pb facs="0211" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> to authorise the giving of
                                an assurance that the full text will be communicated to the European
                                Allied Governments in due course, but if the specific question
                                should be asked, the reply may be given that this question is being
                                considered by the Governments concerned.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>If the questions of occupation and control machinery should be
                                raised by the representatives of the European Allied Governments,
                                the Committee is authorised to inform them that proposals on these
                                subjects have been made by the Commission to the Governments
                                concerned, and are still under their consideration. At this stage
                                the Committee is unable to discuss these questions in any detail.
                                The representatives will see, however, from point (vii) of part 2 of
                                the summary and from the third part of that document that provision
                                has been made in the Instrument of Unconditional Surrender for the
                                military occupation of the whole of Germany and for the creation of
                                control machinery.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The functions of the Committee are:— <list>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>if a question is asked in relation to a subject for which
                                        provision has been made in the Instrument of Surrender, to
                                        confirm that this is so with reference to the relevant
                                        paragraph of the summary;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>if a question is asked relating to a subject which will
                                        require to be dealt with under the general article mentioned
                                        in the third part of the summary, the Committee should state
                                        that this is the case and that the consideration of it is
                                        part of the further programme of the Commission;</item>
                                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                    <item>to hear and report back to the Commission on any question
                                        which may be raised by the representatives of the European
                                        Allied Governments, to which the Committee is unable itself
                                        to give an answer.</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Members of the Committee are at liberty to report individually and consult as
                        necessary with the heads of their respective Delegations on any questions on
                        which they do not feel able to reach a conclusion, and if they can reach
                        agreement in this way it will be unnecessary for them to report back to the
                        Commission as a body. The Commission would wish, however, that the Committee
                        should report to it in any case where the Committee considers it necessary,
                        and that it should include in its report, if possible, recommendations as to
                        the course to be adopted.</p>
                    <p>The Committee should render a general report to the Commission on its
                        transactions with the representatives of each of the European Allied
                        Governments, submitting interim reports if this should be considered
                        necessary.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. <hi rend="smallcaps">Strang</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-08">8 January,
                                1945</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
