<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-22T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-22T15:00:00-05:00" n="247" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d247">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/5–2245:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                                (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-22T22:00:00+02:00">May 22,
                                    1945—10 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received 10:29 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>2887. For Matthews. Following are excerpts from minutes of a meeting
                            between General Eisenhower and the Prime Minister on May 16 at London.
                            Complete text follows by mail.<note n="77" xml:id="d247fn77">Transmitted
                                to the Department by the United States Political Adviser for Germany
                                as an enclosure to despatch 404, May 23, 1945, not printed. This
                                meeting also included the following members of the British Chiefs of
                                Staff Committee: Field Marshal Sir Alan Brooke, Air Marshal Sir
                                Douglas Evill, Admiral of the Fleet Sir Andrew Cunningham, and
                                General Sir Hastings Ismay (740.00119–Control
                                (Germany)/5–2345).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Eisenhower asked concerning the possibility of the Allied Control Council
                            for Germany being set up in the near future. He mentioned that the
                            Council would serve as a clearing house for the settlement of many
                            urgent problems and, even if the Russian representative had to refer
                            everything to Moscow, the Council at least would provide a rapid means
                            of communication with the Russian authorities.</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister said he did not think the Allies should assume full
                            responsibility for Germany but should be responsible only for seeing
                            that she never was in a position to start another war. German problems
                            should be handled by Germans. He was not averse to making use of
                            suitably qualified Germans to deal with and reorganize German internal
                            problems. Some of the German Generals in our hands already, who were
                            suitably qualified and whom the German people would obey, might be
                            employed for this purpose. The Prime Minister felt that the control of
                            Germany should remain a SHAEF responsibility until some other body was
                            able to take it over.</p>
                        <p>Sir Alan Brooke<note n="78" xml:id="d247fn78">British Field Marshal,
                                Chief of the Imperial General Staff.</note> agreed that for the time
                            being SHAEF should continue to be responsible for the control of
                            Germany.</p>
                        <p>Eisenhower mentioned that the Allied Commander’s authority did not extend
                            to matters of detailed administration. Though the work of administration
                            was now being coordinated at his headquarters the staff handling it was
                            divided into US and British sections. Both the British and the Americans
                            were prepared to set up the Control Council elements and to get them
                            quickly working.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister referred to a memorandum from the Foreign Office
                            pointing out that the proposals in SCAF 392 (my telegram 2675, May 16, 4
                                p.m.<note n="79" xml:id="d247fn79">Not printed; SCAF was a military
                                communications indicator.</note>) could not be adopted without
                            consulting the French and the Russians.<note n="80" xml:id="d247fn80">For a discussion of General Eisenhower’s proposal to prolong the
                                existence of SHAEF, see Pogue, <hi rend="italic">The Supreme
                                    Command</hi>, <ref target="#pg_511">p. 511</ref>.</note> If it
                            were wished to keep SHAEF in <pb facs="0313" n="303" xml:id="pg_303"/>
                            being then the declaration regarding the defeated Germany would have to
                            be made by SHAEF on behalf of the Allied Governments. The Russians, if
                            this were proposed, would be offered an opportunity of pressing for the
                            immediate withdrawal of all forces to the zones of occupation agreed
                            upon. It was considered better, under the circumstances, to leave the
                            situation as it was. The Foreign Office memorandum pointed out that the
                            need to establish some German government was becoming ever more
                            apparent. The Prime Minister said he agreed that the setting up of the
                            Control Council was of great importance and that the question should
                            receive urgent consideration.</p>
                        <p>Other points from the interview included a statement by the Prime
                            Minister [<hi rend="italic">General Eisenhower</hi>] that he had issued
                            instructions that rations for non-working prisoners of war should be
                            immediately reduced to 2,000 calories. He would examine the matter
                            further to ascertain whether further reduction was possible. With
                            reference to enemy equipment, especially aircraft, the Prime Minister
                            said he had been concerned to learn that it was our policy to destroy
                            such equipment and he did not agree and he thought we should save all
                            the enemy equipment we could as we might need it to equip the liberated
                            nations. The Prime Minister thought it possible that we could transfer
                            enemy plants and set up our own factories to maintain such
                            equipment.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>