<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation Between General Mark W.
                            Clark and Ing. Leopold Figl
                    
                    Sent to the Department as enclosure to despatch
                        565, December 10, from Vienna; received December 19.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d470</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">470</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-12-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-08T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="470" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d470">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">863.00/12–1045</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation Between General <persName>Mark W.
                            Clark</persName> and <persName>Ing. Leopold Figl</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="44" xml:id="d470fn44">Sent to the Department as enclosure to despatch
                        565, December 10, from Vienna; received December 19.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-08">December 8,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Ing. Figl, who had been entrusted by the Political Cabinet with the formation of
                    a new Austrian Government following the national elections of November 25, 1945,
                    presented himself at General Clark’s office without previous announcement and
                    was immediately received by the General. He handed the General a signed copy of
                    a letter dated December 8, 1945, which he had sent to the Allied Council giving
                    the names of the members of the new Cabinet together with a brief covering
                    letter of the same date addressed to General Clark. (Translations of these
                    communications are attached.)<note n="45" xml:id="d470fn45">Neither
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Figl started in by saying that he hoped the Allied Commission, at its meeting
                    on December 10, would approve the Cabinet so that it could get to work. He
                    stressed the point that he hoped that the Nationalrat and the Bundesrat could be
                    called together by December 17, and proceed with the election of a President so
                    that the Government could be officially installed and operating by Christmas. He
                    asked for <pb facs="0687" n="677" xml:id="pg_677"/> General Clark’s support to
                    this end, and the General said that he would do everything that he could to
                    help. General Clark pointed out, however, that the Allied Council itself would
                    only have authority to give its approval to the Cabinet and make a
                    recommendation to the Governments of the occupying powers that recognition be
                    extended to the new government.</p>
                <p>In response to a question, Mr. Figl stated that it had been agreed that Dr.
                    Renner would be elected President, and he had no doubts that he would
                    accept.</p>
                <p>General Clark said that he could give no assurances, of course, as to what action
                    the Council would take because there was the definite possibility that the
                    Soviets might object to one or more names on the list. The General added that
                    the Soviets were surprised and disappointed at the result of the elections and
                    they would probably scan carefully the list of the new Cabinet. He furthermore
                    stated that a few days ago he had visited Marshal Koniev at Baden where the
                    matter of the new government had been discussed and at that time he had assured
                    Marshal Koniev that if there were any Nazis or Fascists proposed as members of
                    the new government he would certainly support action looking toward their
                    removal. Mr. Figl said that there were no such people in the new Cabinet and
                    that nearly all of them had long concentration camp records.</p>
                <p>General Clark said that he wanted to speak quite frankly with Mr. Figl about
                    certain matters, and one of them was that it must be clearly understood that the
                    Allied Council would remain the supreme authority in Austria. Mr. Figl agreed,
                    but he pointed out that the Government must have power in administrative and
                    economic matters throughout Austria so that it could go ahead with its work. To
                    this General Clark replied that he was in accord and furthermore said his
                    position was that the Government should be given more and more authority as it
                    showed that it was capable of efficient functioning. In this connection, General
                    Clark pointed out that he was quite certain that there would be a change in
                    Soviet policy as follows: During the life of the Renner Government the Soviets
                    had constantly supported the idea of giving the Government more authority and
                    the Allied Council less, whereas now he felt that the Soviets would want to give
                    the Government less authority and the Allied Council more.</p>
                <p>General Clark told Mr. Figl that he was doing everything he could in the way of
                    working out an agreement for the reduction of Allied troops. This pleased Mr.
                    Figl very much. Mr. Figl estimated that there were between 700,000 and 800,000
                    Soviet troops in the country and said that it would be so much better for
                    Austria if the total number of troops of all powers were reduced to 100,000. Mr.
                    Figl made it quite clear that he did not expect the reduction to take the form
                    of each power having the same number of troops in Austria. The most that <pb facs="0688" n="678" xml:id="pg_678"/> he hoped for was a percentage
                    reduction which would bring the total number down without equalization.</p>
                <p>There followed a discussion of the food situation in Austria and Mr. Figl
                    described the situation in Lower Austria as catastrophic. General Clark said
                    that he fully realized this and that he had sent a personal message to Governor
                        Lehman<note n="46" xml:id="d470fn46">Herbert H. Lehman, Director General of
                        the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.</note> and was
                    working constantly to the end of getting an adequate UNRRA program started in
                    Austria. The General said that in the British, French, and American zones
                    conditions were better than in Lower Austria but even in the three western zones
                    the people had a very low standard of living, barely sufficient to get them
                    through the winter. He said it was no solution to the problem to pull food out
                    of the west and give it to Lower Austria as this would only have the effect of
                    pulling everybody down to extremely low living standards. The General frankly
                    stated that he would not lower the standards in the American zone in order to
                    provide food for Lower Austria because the United States felt a responsibility
                    for its zone and he was going to meet this responsibility.</p>
                <p>General Clark said confidentially to Mr. Figl that if at times he might appear to
                    be critical of the Soviets it was only because he was trying to be helpful and
                    that to get anywhere he had to employ different strategies on different
                    occasions. He said that it was his practice to talk just as frankly with Marshal
                    Koniev as he talked with Mr. Figl and he said that this had resulted in the
                    development of the very best of relations between him and the Marshal. General
                    Clark emphasized that one must bear in mind at all times that four-power
                    cooperation and unity were absolutely essential in the interests of Austria, and
                    he told Mr. Figl that the Austrian Government on its part should do everything
                    to make such cooperation easier and not harder. Mr. Figl indicated 100%
                    understanding of this viewpoint, and said that such would be the policy of the
                    Government.</p>
                <p>The conversation closed on an extremely cordial note by General Clark’s saying
                    that his door was always open to Mr. Figl and that he wanted Mr. Figl to come
                    and see him any time and tell him about the Government’s problems. The General
                    said that he would always be disposed to help in any way that was in his power.
                    Mr. Figl expressed deep appreciation and made some extremely complimentary
                    remarks to General Clark about the latter’s great prestige in Austria and the
                    feeling of high respect and admiration possessed by all Austrians for the
                    General’s outstanding work and accomplishments.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
