<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="58" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d58">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Austria)/4–2145</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of the British Embassy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Makins</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Director of the Office of European Affairs</hi>
                                (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-21">April 21,
                                1945</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Doc</hi>: With reference to our
                            conversation on April 19th about Austria, we have now heard from London
                            that the Prime Minister has decided, in the circumstances, not to send a
                            message himself to Stalin on this subject. Instead, instructions have
                            been sent to His <pb facs="0092" n="82" xml:id="pg_82"/> Majesty’s
                            Chargé d’Affaires in Moscow to approach the Soviet Government through
                            normal channels.</p>
                        <p>2. I enclose a paraphrase of the instructions which have been issued to
                            Mr. Frank Roberts.<note n="60" xml:id="d58fn60">British Chargé in the
                                Soviet Union.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Yours ever,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Roger Makins</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Paraphrase of Instructions sent to His
                                    Majesty’s Chargé d’affaires in Moscow on April</hi> 21<hi rend="smallcaps">st</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>His Majesty’s Government have learned with pleasure of the statement
                                made by Marshal Stalin to Mr. Harriman that, now that Vienna had
                                been captured, it was urgently necessary to settle the respective
                                zones in Vienna, and of the proposal that United States, British and
                                French Governments should send their officers at once to Vienna to
                                work out the necessary arrangements on the spot.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>His Majesty’s Government gladly accepts this proposal and
                                    welcomes the statement issued by the Soviet Government on April
                                    8th affirming that the Soviet Government stands firmly by the
                                    Allied declaration issued at Moscow in 1943.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Besides working out in Vienna the division of the Vienna zones
                                    and airfields, it is urgent that the four powers should arrive
                                    at an agreed policy in regard to the establishment of interim
                                    control machinery for Austria and that the representatives on
                                    European Advisory Commission should be instructed to settle this
                                    latter question without delay.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>There are other important political and economic questions
                                    which will arise in Austria. His Majesty’s Government are sure
                                    that the Soviet Government will agree that our common purpose
                                    might well be prejudiced by unilateral action on the part of any
                                    one of the occupying powers in regard to the removal of
                                    industrial plant and equipment regardless of whether or not this
                                    was German owned, or the elimination without regard to their
                                    attitude towards the Nazis, of Austrians who might be useful in
                                    re-establishing Austrian administration and economy. His
                                    Majesty’s Government propose therefore that representatives to
                                    be sent to Vienna should be empowered to deal with such
                                    questions and that the Soviet Commanders on the spot should
                                    meanwhile be instructed to hold their hand. His Majesty’s
                                    Government would also urge the importance of taking all possible
                                    steps to maintain Austrian agriculture in full
                                    production.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>