<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany
                        (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d618</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">618</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-08-20T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-08-20T13:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="food" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184" lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="transportation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-08-20T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-08-20T13:00:00-05:00" n="618" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d618">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/8–2045:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-08-20T21:00:00+03:00">August 20, 1945—9 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received August 20—6:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>329. The Control Council held its third meeting in Berlin today. United States
                    proposals relating to the vesting and marshalling of German external assets and
                    to the removal of Allied and neutral property in Germany were both referred to
                    the Coordinating Committee for further study. On objection from Field Marshal
                    Montgomery no decision was reached on the proposal prohibiting the wearing of
                    uniforms by disbanded personnel of the former German Army. Under this proposal
                    from October 1, 1945, or 30 days after discharge, former members of the German
                    Army and other civilians living on German territory would be forbidden to wear
                    military uniform in its present color and all badges of rank whatever.
                    Montgomery stated that in the British zone this order would affect approximately
                    two million men many of whom would have no other civilian clothing. It would be
                    impossible to dye that number during the period indicated and he said that he
                    would be agreeable only to an order requiring this action to be taken “as soon
                    as possible” in the discretion of the commanding general of each zone. Marshal
                    Zhukov felt that Montgomery overestimates the difficulties stating that this
                    action has to a large extent already been undertaken in the Soviet zone of
                    occupation. Montgomery undertook to give a forecast date of when in his opinion
                    such an order could be made effective. The question was put over until the next
                    meeting of the Control Council.</p>
                <p>Marshal Montgomery invited the attention of the Control Council to the congestion
                    and housing difficulties existing in a number of German cities in the British
                    zone especially in the Ruhr area. He said that he was working out a scheme for
                    the shifting of some of this population preparatory for the winter months. In
                    the greater Berlin area Montgomery said that he was reducing the size of the
                    British occupational forces from 10,000–12,000 men to 6,000–7,000 men for <pb facs="0843" n="833" xml:id="pg_833"/> the purpose of making housing
                    available to the German civilian population. In his opinion the Council may have
                    to face up to the danger of outbreaks of diseases and epidemics due to appalling
                    housing conditions. The civilian population, he thought, must be better cared
                    for than is the case at present.</p>
                <p>General Eisenhower referred to the number of displaced persons from the east to
                    the western zones and the necessity of arriving at an equitable distribution in
                    this respect and pointed out that the American zone at present is extremely
                    crowded. He also referred to the Potsdam decision regarding the transfer of
                    population from certain eastern areas.<note n="74" xml:id="d618fn74">See chapter
                        XIII of the Report on the Tripartite Conference of Berlin, <ref target="frus1945Berlinv02#pg_1511">
                            <hi rend="italic">Conference of Berlin</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Potsdam</hi>), vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 1511</ref>.
                        For documentation on this subject, see <ref target="frus1945Berlinv02#pg_1227">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                            pp. 1227</ref> ff.</note> Zhukov in the discussion insisted that the
                    transfer of these populations must not be deferred for long. He also announced
                    that the Soviet forces in the Berlin sector had been reduced to patrol units. He
                    did not state the number.</p>
                <p>Montgomery also reported disturbing trouble in the British zone with displaced
                    persons who have been guilty of numerous acts of looting, murder, and rape. He
                    stated that orders were being given to suppress such malefactors using organized
                    force if necessary. Zhukov announced that similar difficulty had not been
                    experienced in the Soviet zone.</p>
                <p>In connection with the supply of food for Berlin, Montgomery again emphasized the
                    unsatisfactory rail facilities between the British zone and Berlin over which
                    must pass all of the imports from the western zone. This line had been double
                    tracked but apparently due to removal of rails it is now being converted to
                    single track line which of course creates congestion and delays supplies in
                    arriving in the Berlin area. The problem is now under study by the
                    transportation directorate.</p>
                <p>Sent to Dept as 329, repeated to Moscow as 25, London as 47, and Paris as 46.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
