<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by James W. Riddleberger, Chief of the Division
                    of Central European Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="674"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d674">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/12–545</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by James W. Riddleberger, Chief of
                        the Division of Central European Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-05">December 5,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Mr. Berard, Counselor of the French Embassy, came in this morning to discuss the
                    next steps with respect to the French proposals for the Rhineland–Ruhr. He said
                    that Mr. Alphand was now in Moscow to carry out the same mission which Mr. Couve
                    de Murville had done in London and Washington. The French Embassy here had no
                    information respecting the outcome of these discussions but would inform me when
                    anything was received. It was anticipated that the conversations in Moscow would
                    not take over a week.</p>
                <p>Mr. Berard then said that the French Government was of the opinion that when the
                    conversations in Moscow had been completed a four-power meeting should be held
                    to discuss this question in the light of all the information and explanations
                    that had now been provided The French Government did not envisage a meeting
                    necessarily on <pb facs="0926" n="916" xml:id="pg_916"/> the Foreign Minister
                    level but would very much like to have it held in Paris. It hoped that the
                    American Government would agree to this procedure and suggested that perhaps it
                    would be possible to designate the respective Ambassadors in Paris as
                    representatives to such a meeting. Experts on the various questions involved
                    could no doubt be attached to the representatives in such manner as each
                    government deemed appropriate.</p>
                <p>Mr. Berard said that the French Government would like to have this meeting as
                    soon as possible after the conclusion of the Moscow conversations and that
                    General de Gaulle hoped the American Government would give its sympathetic and
                    immediate consideration to this proposal.</p>
                <p>I told Mr. Berard that I thought Mr. Couve de Murville had suggested
                    approximately the same procedure to Mr. Dunn during the course of the
                    conversations here. Mr. Dunn had been called away rather suddenly and we
                    consequently had not as yet given consideration to the question of the possible
                    meeting. I said that we were also awaiting the outcome of the French discussions
                    in Moscow. Therefore, we had not as yet taken up the question of the meeting,
                    but in view of the French suggestions that I would bring it to the attention of
                    the Secretary at once. I told Mr. Berard that after discussions here we would
                    communicate with him again.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
