<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany
                        (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d696</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">696</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-03T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="696" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d696">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control (Germany)/6–345</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 456</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfurt</hi>
                        </placeName>?]<note n="48" xml:id="d696fn48">During the latter part of May
                            and the first part of June, the Political Division of U.S. Group C.C.
                            was moved in stages from Versailles to Hoechst, a district of
                            Frankfurt-am-Main. Mr. Murphy’s own office was moved to SHAEF in
                            Frankfurt. This move was necessitated by the gradual closing down of
                            SHAEF Headquarters in Versailles, and the transfer of the American
                            element to Frankfurt, where it became Headquarters, U.S. Forces in the
                            European Theater (USFET) after the dissolution of SHAEF on July
                            14.</note>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-03">June 3,
                        1945</date>.<lb/>[Received June 12.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit for the Department’s
                    information a copy of a directive from Headquarters, European Theater of
                    Operations, <pb facs="0953" n="943" xml:id="pg_943"/> United States Army, dated
                    May 24, 1945,<note n="49" xml:id="d696fn49">Copy of directive not printed; the
                        directive itself was dated May 13, and the covering memorandum transmitting
                        it to the Commanding General of the 12th Army Group was dated May 24.</note>
                    setting forth the organization for the Military Government of the United States
                    Zone and other areas in Germany in which United States forces are deployed.</p>
                <p>The purpose or mission is stated to be the establishment of an organization to
                    apply and administer efficiently approved policy to the Military Government of
                    Germany and to establish the allocation of responsibility within that
                    organization. The plan is to be made effective when Combined Command is
                    terminated and prior to that time it is to be developed as far as practicable
                    without violating existing SHAEF policies.</p>
                <p>Within the United States Zone in Germany it is the Theater Staff of the
                    Commanding General, USAF, ETO, which is charged with the execution,
                    implementation and supervision of approved United States and Allied control
                    authority policy. Specifically, within the Theater Staff, G–5 is directed to
                    develop basic policies for, to prepare directives and instructions for, and to
                    supervise for the General Staff, activities pertaining to Military Government
                    control in liberated countries and pertaining to Military Government control and
                    supervision generally over the German civil government within the United States
                    Zone in Germany. In the exercise of these controls and supervision, the fields
                    of activity are: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Local Government, German civil service, public safety, public health,
                            postal services, education and religious affairs.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Public finance, public and private financial institutions, foreign
                            exchange, accounting and auditing, currency and financial
                            intelligence.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>German courts, Military Government courts and prisons.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>United Nations displaced persons, German refugees and German welfare
                            agencies.</item>
                        <label>(5)</label>
                        <item>Economic affairs, including supplies for civilian needs, production of
                            food, trade, labor, local civilian road transport and, except as
                            assigned to G–4, production, transportation and communication.</item>
                        <label>(6)</label>
                        <item>Restorations and reparations, property and preservation and
                            restoration of monuments, fine arts and archives.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In view of the nature of the assignment of the Department’s personnel to US Group
                    CC, I wish to suggest that this directive be given only limited circulation
                    within the Department and that if its contents are discussed with any outside
                    department or agency, reference to source be avoided.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Donald</hi> R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Counselor</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
