<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The British Ambassador (
                        Halifax
                    ) to the Acting Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v03</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d874</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">874</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-03-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="874" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d874">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00116 E.W./3–645</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p>His Majesty’s Ambassador presents his compliments to the Secretary of State and
                    has the honour to refer to the Embassy’s <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                    dated October 30, 1944,<note n="51" xml:id="d874fn51">
                        <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_1389">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 1389</ref>.</note> which was left with
                    the Legal Adviser to the Department of State on that date, concerning various
                    proposals made by the United Nations War Crimes Commission in London and to the
                        <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoire</hi> dated December 27, 1944,<note n="52" xml:id="d874fn52">
                        <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_1409">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 1409</ref>.</note> concerning a draft
                    directive regarding the functions of theatre commanders in relation to war
                    criminals.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Since the delivery to the Department of State of above mentioned <hi rend="italic">Aide-Mémoires</hi>, officials of the Embassy have had the
                        advantage of informal discussions on the subject of war crimes and war
                        criminals with the Legal Adviser of the Department of State and with other
                        officials of the United States Government.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom believe that the time has
                        come when a general discussion of the subject between representatives of the
                        United States and of the United Kingdom would be mutually advantageous. Lord
                        Halifax, therefore, has pleasure on behalf of His Majesty’s Government, in
                        inviting to London Mr. Green H. Hackworth, Legal Adviser to the Department
                        of State, Brigadier General John Weir<note n="53" xml:id="d874fn53">Director
                            of War Department’s War Crimes Office.</note> of the United States War
                        Department, and such other officials as they or Mr. Grew may designate, for
                        the purpose of holding such discussions. His Majesty’s Government hope that
                        the meeting may, if possible, take place in London on or about March 15th
                        next.</item>
                    <pb facs="1163" n="1153" xml:id="pg_1153"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>His Majesty’s Government consider that the proposed discussions could
                        profitably include such matters as the trials of war criminals, the
                        suggested International Criminal Court, the proposed mixed military
                        tribunals, and the procedure to be adopted for dealing with lists of war
                        criminals produced by the Commission.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>As regards other matters concerning the pre-surrender period in Western
                        Europe, these appear for the most part to be covered in practice by action
                        taken by the Supreme Headquarters of the Allied Expeditionary Forces and by
                        Allied Force Headquarters, by the draft directive which it is hoped the
                        Combined Chiefs of Staff will issue very shortly,<note n="54" xml:id="d874fn54">For text of this draft directive, issued on June 26,
                            1945, see <ref target="frus1945Berlinv01#pg_580">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Conference of Berlin
                                (The Potsdam Conference), 1945, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                                580</ref>.</note> and by the existing liaison arrangements between
                            S.H.A.E.F.<note n="55" xml:id="d874fn55">Supreme Headquarters Allied
                            Expeditionary Force.</note> and A.F.H.Q.<note n="56" xml:id="d874fn56">Allied Force Headquarters.</note> and between other competent Allied
                        authorities. There seem few other questions relating to this period which
                        require discussions between the United States and the United Kingdom, but no
                        doubt such questions as the establishment of a channel for exchange, between
                        the United Kingdom and the United States, of information on war crimes and
                        war criminals could also be considered advantageously at such a
                        meeting.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>There is, however, one outstanding question, namely, whether the
                        Governments of the United States and of the United Kingdom should try to
                        establish some form of liaison with the Government of the Soviet Union in
                        the pre-surrender period for: <list>
                            <item>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the mutual collection and exchange of
                                information about war crimes; and</item>
                            <item>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the apprehension, and possibly the
                                exchange, of war criminals whose custody is desired by either
                                side.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label/>
                    <item>A case in point under (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) is the over-running by
                        Soviet forces of Stalag Luft III at Sagan where fifty British and Allied
                        air, force officers were murdered by the Germans in March of 1944. The
                        principal difficulty in connection with such arrangements is the manner in
                        which the other Allies would be brought into any such liaison arrangements.
                        The Government of the Soviet Union might feel disinclined to participate in
                        a wide arrangement embracing a number of the Allies, but, on the other hand,
                        if the United Kingdom and United States were to make arrangements with the
                        Government of the Soviet Union on their own account alone, the other Allies
                        who, as stated below, have suffered very severely in the matter of war
                        crimes, might be offended. This matter is being urgently considered in the
                        United Kingdom and Lord Halifax hopes to send to Mr. Grew shortly some
                        proposals in this regard. This matter could also be discussed <pb facs="1164" n="1154" xml:id="pg_1154"/> further by the representatives
                        of the United States and the United Kingdom at the proposed meeting in
                        London.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Some thought has been given to the advisability of inviting
                        representatives of the French Provisional Government and the Soviet
                        Government to participate in the proposed discussions in London, but His
                        Majesty’s Government see some difficulty in inviting the French Government
                        to participate without giving other Allies an opportunity also to take part.
                        A number of such other Allies have, in the view of His Majesty’s Government,
                        suffered in proportion, at least as heavily, if not more heavily, than have
                        the French, from the atrocities committed by war criminals, and it might
                        provoke great resentment among them if they were excluded, in favour of the
                        French alone, from conversations on proposals emanating from the United
                        Nations War Crimes Commission. His Majesty’s Government also feel that at
                        the present stage the Government of the Soviet Union would be unlikely to
                        accept any invitation to take part in talks at a technical level on war
                        criminals and therefore no invitation is, at the present time, being issued
                        to that Government to participate in the discussions. His Majesty’s
                        Government are of the opinion that if it is decided to try to establish such
                        liaison and mutual assistance with the Soviet Union, as is mentioned in
                        paragraph 6 above, the matter would best be taken up through ordinary
                        diplomatic channels and that there is no need for special discussion with
                        the Soviet Union about it. Therefore the invitation to the proposed
                        discussions is being limited to the Government of the United States. If it
                        appeared that the Government of the Soviet Union or the French Government
                        could assist at any stage in the discussions, appropriate representatives of
                        such Governments could, of course, be consulted separately.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The Government of the Soviet Union have asked that the requirements
                        concerning the handing over of war criminals should be discussed by the
                        European Advisory Commission and His Majesty’s Government are preparing a
                        draft directive<note n="57" xml:id="d874fn57">This was draft directive EAC
                            (45) 42 of April 20, 1945, entitled “Inclusion of Provision for the
                            Surrender of War Criminals in the Proposed Allied Declaration”, not
                            printed.</note> which it is hoped will shortly be discussed by the
                        Commission. It is understood that United States authorities are also at work
                        on a similar draft directive.<note n="58" xml:id="d874fn58">For text of the
                            EAC draft directive on United Nations’ renegades and quislings and the
                            changes recommended by SWNNC, see <ref target="frus1945Berlinv02#pg_422">
                                <hi rend="italic">Conference of Berlin</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Potsdam</hi>), vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 422</ref>,
                            footnote 6.</note> The discussions at the European Advisory Commission
                        on these two directives will enable the United States Government, His
                        Majesty’s Government, the French Government and the Government of the Soviet
                        Union to state their views on all matters relating to war criminals and
                        arising in the post-surrender period, except possibly the question <pb facs="1165" n="1155" xml:id="pg_1155"/> of the form of trials and such
                        matters as the proposed International Criminal Court and the proposed mixed
                        military tribunals.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>The question of major war criminals was, as Mr. Grew will be aware,
                        touched upon at the Crimean Conference and has been referred to the three
                        Foreign Secretaries for further consideration.<note n="59" xml:id="d874fn59">See <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_938">
                                <hi rend="italic">Conferences at Malta and Yalta</hi>, p.
                            938</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>In these circumstances, it does not seem possible to discuss at the
                        present stage any post-surrender matters relating to war criminals with the
                        Government of the Soviet Union other than the discussions which will take
                        place in the European Advisory Commission.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Lord Halifax will be glad to be informed, as soon as is conveniently
                        possible, whether Mr. Hackworth, General Weir and other representatives of
                        the United States Government will be able to visit London on or about March
                        15, 1945, for the purpose of the discussions above described.<note n="60" xml:id="d874fn60">In his reply of March 30, Mr. Hull informed Lord
                            Halifax, “that Judge Samuel I, Rosenman, special counsel to the
                            President, who is now in Europe, has been charged with the
                            responsibility of discussing with British officials in London the
                            questions raised in the Ambassador’s note. He will be joined by
                            Brigadier General Weir and Colonel R. Ammi Cutter of the War Department
                            … Mr. Hackworth will be unable to go to London …” (740.00116
                            EW/3–645)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-03-06">6 March
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
