<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-07-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-07-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="28" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                    <head>28. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1" type="from">Nixon</persName> to the Director of the Arms Control and Disarmament
                        Agency (<persName corresp="#p_SGC1" type="to">Smith</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d28fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 197, Agency Flies, ACDA,
                            1/20/69-12/31/69. Secret; Nodis. Drafted in the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff by Helmut Sonnenfeldt, and revised by <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-07-21">July 21, 1969</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Dear Gerry:</p>
                    <p>Following our discussion today, I wish to convey to you my thoughts on the
                        forthcoming talks with the Soviet Union on strategic arms. You and your
                        associates will be dealing with a subject of crucial significance to the
                        safety of this country. My purpose in these talks is to determine whether it
                        is feasible to make arrangements with the Soviet Government that will
                        contribute to the preservation and, if possible, the improvement of this
                        country’s security. Any arrangement with the Soviet Union, especially if it
                        is to be in the form of explicit and formal commitments, must meet this test
                        to my own full satisfaction.</p>
                    <p>When I speak of this country’s security, I fully realize that we cannot
                        expect to return to an era when our country was literally immune to physical
                        threat. Neither our military programs nor any negotiation with our potential
                        adversaries can achieve that. But I am speaking of a situation in which I,
                        as President and Commander-in-Chief, have at my disposal military forces
                        that will provide me with the best assurance attainable in present and
                        foreseeable circumstances that no opponent can rationally expect to derive
                        benefit from attacking, or threatening to attack us or our allies. I am
                        determined, moreover, to pass on to my successor that same sense of
                        assurance.</p>
                    <p>If the Soviet leaders operate on similar premises (which we do not know and
                        which their current military programs give some reason to doubt), there
                        could be, I believe, a prospect of reaching an understanding with them
                        whereby, in the first instance, limits would be placed on the quantitative
                        and qualitative growth of strategic forces. It will be your task to obtain
                        evidence that will assist me in making a determination whether such a
                        prospect is real and what the elements of such an understanding could
                        be.</p>
                    <p>Any understanding, whatever the form, that places limitations on Soviet
                        forces will obviously involve limitations on ours. I will judge the
                        resulting relationship of <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>-Soviet strategic
                        forces in terms of the criteria for strategic sufficiency that I have
                        established.</p>
                    <pb facs="0110" n="90" xml:id="pg_90"/>
                    <p>Moreover, I will accept limitations on our forces only after I have assured
                        myself of our ability to detect Soviet failure to implement limitations on
                        their own forces in sufficient time to protect our security interests. In
                        this latter connection, you should know that I am determined to avoid,
                        within the Government and in the country at large, divisive disputes
                        regarding Soviet compliance or non-compliance with an understanding or
                        agreement. Nor will I bequeath to a future President the seeds of such
                        disputes. In our open society and political system it is my duty to provide
                        persuasive public evidence not only of any Soviet non-compliance with an
                        agreement but also of Soviet compliance with it. Any agreed limitations must
                        therefore meet the test of verifiability. I recognize that this may not be
                        obtainable with 100 percent assurance; but the margin of uncertainty must be
                        reasonable. I will make this judgement.</p>
                    <p>I have carefully examined the possible alternative arrangements that might be
                        entered into with the Soviet Union, as developed through our National
                        Security Council process. In the absence of any indications from the Soviet
                        Union of the direction they propose to take, I do not find it possible to
                        make a clear selection among them. I do not, therefore, desire to propose to
                        the Soviet Government a specific set of measures corresponding to the five
                        alternatives analyzed in <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 62.<note n="2" xml:id="d28fn2">
                            <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 62 was addressed on July 2 to the
                            Secretaries of State and Defense, the Director of Central Intelligence,
                            the Director of the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, the Chairman of
                            the Atomic Energy Commission, and the President’s Science Adviser. In
                            this memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, on
                            behalf of the President, directed the preparation of negotiating
                            positions for the strategic arms control talks. (National Archives,
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 365, Subject Files,
                            National Security Study Memoranda (<gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>s), Nos. 43-103)</note> You should outline to the Soviet
                        representatives the various approaches we have studied, as reflected in
                        Alternatives I, II and III of <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 62 and
                        indicate our readiness to examine jointly with them these and any others
                        they might advance. You may state that we are prepared to consider
                        limitations on all strategic offensive and defensive weapons systems, that
                        our suggestions are not exhaustive but that we wish to hear their views
                        before advancing any additional ones ourselves. Upon completion of the work
                        of the <gloss target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss> verification panel, I may
                        authorize presenting aspects of Alternative IV.</p>
                    <p>In short, your task in the initial phases of the talks is to explore Soviet
                        intentions without yourself placing on the table the full range of
                        alternative arrangements that we might consider. In the light of the
                        progress of the explorations, and other relevant factors, I will determine
                        the timing and contents of any specific limitation proposal that we might
                        make to the Soviet Union.</p>
                    <p>Let me, in conclusion, outline my general approach to our relations with the
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> so that you and your associates
                        will be guided thereby in <pb facs="0111" n="91" xml:id="pg_91"/> your
                        talks. I have conveyed to the Soviet leaders my view that our relations
                        should be based on a recognition by each side of the legitimate security
                        interests of the other; I have conveyed to them also my readiness to engage
                        in bona fide negotiations on concrete issues. I have told them that I have
                        no interest either in polemical exchanges or in the mere atmospherics of
                        détente. Having propounded these principles and acted on them in practice
                        since entering office, I believe the seriousness of this Administration in
                        pursuing the path of equitable accommodation with the Soviet Union is being
                        demonstrated. I consider that the approach to the arms limitation talks
                        outlined above will serve to provide further such demonstration. The other
                        side has the opportunity to respond to the same spirit. If it does so,
                        arrangements to restrain the pace of competition in the field of strategic
                        armaments should be within our reach.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">
                                <hi rend="strong">Richard Nixon</hi>
                            </persName><note n="3" xml:id="d28fn3">Printed from a copy that
                                indicates <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> signed the
                                original.</note>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>