<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-01-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="49" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                    <head>49. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_WWM1" type="from">Marshall
                            Wright</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                        President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d49fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Secretariat Files, Box 1303, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard M. Nixon</persName> Annual Review
                            1970-1974, Annual Review 1970. Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-01-10">January 10, 1970</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Revised Drafts of African and <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> papers
                            for Annual Report<note n="2" xml:id="d49fn2">Attached are an 8-page
                                paper outlining the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                                administration’s policy toward Africa and a 7-page paper which
                                addressed the administration’s view of the United Nations. Neither
                                draft is dated nor is drafting information provided. Regarding the
                                annual report to Congress, see <ref target="#d60">Document
                                60</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Here are the latest versions of these two papers, revised to reflect your
                        comments as relayed by <persName>Dick Kennedy</persName>.</p>
                    <p>In connection with these drafts I want to remind you that both in Africa and
                        in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> our policy is essentially
                        defensive. Neither is central in any way to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> foreign policy operations or interests. We deal with them
                        because they are there, not because we hope to get great things out of our
                        participation. We aim at minimizing the attention and resources which must
                        be addressed to them. What we really want from both is no trouble. Our
                        policy is therefore directed at damage limiting, rather than at
                        accomplishing anything in particular.</p>
                    <p>That being true, there is (or at least, I can find) no broad and positive
                        conceptual base which can credibly be put forward to explain why we do what
                        we do in Africa and the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. The real base we
                        cannot mention. The task then is to put the best possible face upon
                        essentially negative roles, and to try to make them sound more positive and
                        more integrated than they actually are.</p>
                    <p>I call this to your attention so that you will be under no illusions that I
                        consider the attached drafts to be what you asked for.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>