<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-07-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="68" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d68">
                    <head>68. Press Conference by President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d68fn1">Source:
                            Public Papers of the Presidents of the United States: <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard Nixon</persName>, 1970, pp. 626-635. The
                            press conference was held at 8 p.m. in the Century Plaza Hotel and was
                            broadcast on television and radio.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Los Angeles, California</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-07-30">July 30,
                            1970</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>[Omitted here are the President’s introductory remarks and his responses to
                        questions dealing with the Middle East, Vietnam and the Paris peace talks,
                        arms control negotiations, price trends, and school desegregation.]</p>
                    <p>Q. To pursue the question of our military preparedness a bit further, twice
                        within the past week statements have been made by high ranking naval
                        officers, Admiral Rickover and Admiral U.S. Grant Sharp, to the effect that
                        our military preparedness is suspect. And they went further. Each gentleman
                        said that in his opinion it is doubtful that we could win a war with the
                        Soviet Union. Given the eminence of these gentlemen, as Commander in Chief,
                        how do you regard the validity of those statements?</p>
                    <p>The President. Well, I would first react by saying that if there is a war
                        between the Soviet Union and the United States, there will be no winners,
                        there will be only losers. The Soviet Union knows this and we know that.</p>
                    <p>That is the reason why it is vitally important that in areas like the Mideast
                        that we attempt to avoid to the greatest extent possible being dragged into
                        a confrontation by smaller powers, even though our interests in the area are
                        very, very great. That is why it is very much in our interests in the <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> talks to work out an arrangement if we
                        can, one which will provide for the interests of both and yet not be in
                        derogation of the necessity of our having sufficiency and their having
                        sufficiency.</p>
                    <p>One other point I would make briefly is this: What the Soviet Union needs in
                        terms of military preparedness is different from what we need. They are a
                        land power primarily, with a great potential enemy on the east. We are
                        primarily, of course, a sea power and our needs, therefore, are different.
                        But what is important now is to find a way to stop this escalation of arms
                        on both sides, and that is why we have hopes in the <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> talks which, I emphasize again, do not involve disarmament
                        for the United States or the Soviet Union, but do involve a limitation and
                        then eventually a mutual reduction.</p>
                    <p>[Omitted here are questions and answers on domestic issues and Vietnam.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>