<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-09-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-09-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="72" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                    <head>72. Background Press Briefing by the President’s Assistant for National
                        Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d72fn1">Source:
                            Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box CL 426, Subject File, Background
                            Briefings, September-October 1970. No classification marking. The
                            briefing took place from 7:10 to 7:45 p.m. local time.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Naples, Italy</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-09-29">September 29, 1970</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>[Omitted here are Press Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ZRL1">Ronald
                            Ziegler</persName>’s introduction of <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, his explanation of the rules governing a
                        background briefing, and the initial questions fielded by <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> in the briefing, relating largely
                        to the Yugoslav portion of the trip.]</p>
                    <p>Let me say a word about the general objective of the President in the last
                        two days and then fit the Springfield into it.<note n="2" xml:id="d72fn2">The question <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> was
                            responding to at this point was: “What did the President discuss in his
                            conference today with the military commanders on the Springfield?”
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> had met with the
                            commanders of the Sixth Fleet aboard the U.S.S. Springfield earlier in
                            the day. (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White House Special Files,
                            Staff Members and Office Files, Office of Presidential Papers and
                            Archives, Daily Diary)</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Many of you have heard me talk about the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine at perhaps exorbitant length. But one of the
                        problems that we have faced in connection with our foreign policy and with
                        the transition from a period in which the United States carried the almost
                        exclusive responsibility to one in which we are trying to share increasingly
                        our responsibility with others, is the fear of many countries, particularly
                        of many allies, that the United States might withdraw from its
                        responsibilities altogether.</p>
                    <p>Whenever we have met Europeans over recent months, European leaders over
                        recent months, this has been one of their principal concerns. It turned out
                        to be one of the important concerns of Italian leaders when we saw them
                        yesterday, one of whom pointed out to us that the first visit of the
                        President here in February was very important but the one this week was
                        really quite crucial in reassuring the Europeans, and particularly the
                        countries of the Mediterranean, that the United States was not withdrawing
                        into isolationism, but, rather, remained committed to its alliances.</p>
                    <p>I mention this because the President has reiterated wherever he has been that
                        the United States did not intend to make any unilateral reductions of its
                        forces; that we considered the problems of the Western Alliance a concern
                        for all the countries.</p>
                    <p>What we attempted to do this afternoon was to review with our commanders in
                        the Mediterranean two problems. One, the problems <pb facs="0279" n="259" xml:id="pg_259"/> posed for the southern flank of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> by the developments in the Mediterranean
                        over recent years and partly by the growth of the Soviet naval presence in
                        the Mediterranean, and, secondly, to draw some lessons from the experiences
                        of recent weeks, to review the experiences of recent weeks, and to see about
                        the relationship between our strength in this area and the prospect for
                        stability in this area.</p>
                    <p>We thought that this was particularly important, because, as I pointed out in
                        the backgrounder I gave before we left, we are not only interested,
                        obviously, in the aspect of how to protect the security of these countries,
                        or help to protect the security, but how we can contribute to a more stable
                        and more permanent peace, a problem which we want particularly to explore in
                        our next stop when we visit Yugoslavia.</p>
                    <p>So, what we had this afternoon was a full review of the various capabilities
                        in the Mediterranean, both as they affected <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and as they affected other areas.</p>
                    <p>[Omitted here is discussion of official U.S. attendance at the funeral of
                        United Arab Republic President Nasser.]</p>
                    <p>Q. Doctor, it seems at times that the relationship between the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine as enunciated at Guam was
                        not entirely clear in relationship to the President’s statements concerning
                        our role and our future role and our intentions in the Mediterranean.</p>
                    <p>Specifically, in his opening remarks with President Saragat,<note n="3" xml:id="d72fn3">Reference is to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s arrival statement in Rome on September 27. For
                            text, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of the
                                United States: <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Richard Nixon</persName>,
                                1970,</hi> p. 772.</note> I believe he was talking along the lines
                        that we intend to see to it that this will not become the place where future
                        wars will begin. Can you talk about this statement in connection with the
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine?</p>
                    <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: This is great for my
                        ego, but it is very dangerous. The question is that the relationship between
                        the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine and some of the
                        pronouncements on this trip did not seem self-evident to the questioner,
                        particularly the opening remarks to President Saragat where the President
                        said, “We will see to it”, or some words to that effect, “that peace in this
                        area will be maintained.”</p>
                    <p>Let me say two things about it. First, we have always brought out the fact
                        that there can never be a neat breakoff point between American foreign
                        policy in one place and another.</p>
                    <p>Secondly, it is clear that the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Doctrine had always envisaged a continuation of some significant American
                        presence in crucial areas of the world where that American presence was
                        necessary and was considered to be in the American interest.</p>
                    <pb facs="0280" n="260" xml:id="pg_260"/>
                    <p>Both of these conditions obtain in the Mediterranean. The objective of the
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine continues to be
                        one of the guidelines, or the guideline, of our foreign policy. We intend to
                        shift an increasing amount of responsibility to our allies. We intend to
                        cooperate with them more fully than has been the case in the past, and we do
                        look to them to make their contribution.</p>
                    <p>But we also recognize that the threat in the Mediterranean may have grown
                        larger than anyone assumed over, say, 10 years ago, and, therefore, we
                        recognize that some of the measures that are possible in other parts of the
                        world do not apply with equal force here. But the basic objectives
                        remain.</p>
                    <p>[Omitted here is the remainder of the briefing, devoted largely to questions
                        relating to the Middle East.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>