<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>104. Letter From Secretary of State Rusk to the Deputy Secretary of Defense (
                    to the Deputy Secretary of Defense (Gilpatric))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d104</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">104</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-08-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-08-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-08-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="104"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d104">
                <head>104. Letter From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="from"
                        >Rusk</persName> to the Deputy Secretary of Defense (<persName
                        corresp="#p_GRL1" type="to">Gilpatric</persName>)<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d104fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                        784A.5611/8–1461. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CWRJ1"
                            >Crawford</persName> and cleared by <persName corresp="#p_FPJ1"
                            >Farley</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KJC1"
                        >Kitchen</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-08-30">August 30, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Ros</hi>: We have read with interest your letter of
                    August 14 forwarding an analysis of the probable impact of the acquisition by
                    Israel of a nuclear weapons capability.<note n="1" xml:id="d104fn1">See <ref
                            target="#d95">Document 95</ref> and the source note thereto.</note>
                </p>
                <p>This is, as you are aware, a subject we have followed with the greatest
                    attention. We have indicated to Israel at a high level on several occasions our
                    opposition to proliferation of nuclear weapons capabilities. As you know, we
                    sought, and eventually gained, the opportunity to examine the Dimona
                    installation. This examination satisfied us that, for the present, the
                    Government of Israel is not actively engaged in programs aimed at nuclear
                    weapons production. We fully intend to press for future examinations of this
                    sort at appropriate intervals. In addition, the President has been assured by
                    Prime Minister Ben-Gurion that Israel agrees in principle to international
                    visits to its nuclear installations by reputable neutral scientists.
                    Arrangements for such visits are being discussed with the Government of
                    Israel.</p>
                <p>Should future developments make this appear desirable, we would not hesitate to
                    re-affirm to Israel in strong terms our belief that it is not in the interest of
                    Israel or of this country that Israel engage in programs aimed at nuclear
                    weapons production. [<hi rend="italic">2½ lines of source text not
                        declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>I am hopeful that our continued close attention to this problem along the lines
                    indicated above will prevent the development of a nuclear weapons capacity by
                    Israel.</p>
                <p>With warm personal regards,</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                            <hi rend="strong">Dean Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d104fn2">Printed from a copy that indicates <persName
                                corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> signed the original.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
