<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-02-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-02-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="188" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                    <head>188. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                        Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_GJP1" type="from">Grant</persName>) to the President’s Special Representative and Adviser
                        on African, Asian, and Latin American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BCB1" type="to">Bowles</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d188fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 611.86B/2–662. Secret.
                            Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SRC4">Strong</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BJR2">Barrow</persName>. Additional briefing material,
                            entitled “Suggested Points for Discussion by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName> with Senior Officials in the
                            United Arab Republic,” attached to the source text, is not printed. It
                            contained a series of papers on key trouble spots in other parts of the
                            world, disarmament, neutralism, Africa, U.S. policy toward the Middle
                            East, and U.S.-<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                        relations.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-02-06">February 6,
                            1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Objectives of your Visit to the United Arab Republic</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Pursuant to your request I submit the following as an addendum to the
                        briefing papers previously prepared regarding objectives to be sought and
                        particular points to be discussed in your conversations with President
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Essentially what we envisage is (a) progress toward the establishment of
                        mutual confidence; (b) the planting of certain of our ideas in <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s mind; (c) learning something of
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s feelings and intentions;
                        and (d) your recommendation whether the President should invite <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> for a state visit in April or delay
                        until after the election. Thus, we do not look for specific commitments but
                        rather for creation of a platform of mutual confidence from which further
                        discussions and, hopefully, a direct confrontation between <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> and President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> might be launched.</p>
                    <p>In this connection, we hope you can make <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> understand the following points: <pb facs="0526" n="466" xml:id="pg_466"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Our confidence in Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> (who will accompany you).</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Our desire for cooperation to the extent that the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> also desires it.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Our acceptance of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> neutrality
                                provided it is truly neutral.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Our world objectives and approaches to them.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>That we are quietly confident of our military posture.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The constancy and magnitude of our assistance despite pressures
                                against us.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s opportunity for
                                genuine statesmanship as a neutral and damage he does to his image
                                by extremism; he should realize the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> is independent and without challenge to its
                                independence.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>That his freedom to be neutral depends on the economic, cultural
                                and military strength of the West.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>That <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> interests in Middle East
                                are confined to Persian Gulf and South Arabian protectorates. No
                                internal support in <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> for another
                                Suez or other adventures in Middle East.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>Need for stability and development in Near East; West is not
                                pushing Fertile Crescent scheme and does not intend to.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>Strenuous efforts of US to maintain impartiality between Arabs and
                                Israelis and also as between Arab states.</item>
                            <label>12.</label>
                            <item>Mischief-making of Sino-Soviet Bloc keeping area upset; false
                                documents and rumors.</item>
                            <label>13.</label>
                            <item>Objectives of our African policy.</item>
                            <label>14.</label>
                            <item>Our support for concepts social reform and social justice, and
                                positive contributions of our system thereto.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The following are points upon which we would like <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s frank views: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Depth and source of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> jitters
                                over its security, means to alleviate.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s view of his
                                relations with the West, present and future; need for good relations
                                with Western Europe if <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                development needs are to be met.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> intentions versus Israel and
                                reasons for increasing its armaments; attitude toward Dimona Reactor
                                and Jordan Waters.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> objectives vis-à-vis Iran and
                                other Arab states.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> African policy.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> view of Kuwait impasse.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>We would suggest the following tactics be used in connection with <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> and others:<note n="1" xml:id="d188fn1">Subparagraph 1, which reads: “Utter frankness,” has
                            been crossed out.</note>
                        <list>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Care and deliberation in use of words; <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s English is not the best.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Care not to interfere in intra-Arab affairs.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Avoidance of serious concern at Soviet role in <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Avoidance of details of US aid and <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> desires.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Avoidance of proposals for Near East arms limitation (presently
                                not practicable for internal political reasons in <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>).</item>
                            <pb facs="0527" n="467" xml:id="pg_467"/>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Concentration on what we hope for the future, rather than on
                                troubles of past.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Full opportunity to <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                                and others to express their point of view.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>A relaxed approach since <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> will likely be prepared to spend several
                                hours with you.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>Engage in wide-range discussion of problems on first meeting;
                                attempt in second meeting to summarize and conclude bringing out
                                points of difference and points of agreement.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>As regards dealing with other personalities, we would attach considerable
                        importance to talks with Vice Presidents Baghdadi and Muhieddin, with whom
                        you can be frank. Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_FM5">Fawzi</persName> is reliable, though not influential. [<hi rend="italic">2½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>