<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>232. Telegram From the Embassy in Jordan to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d232</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">232</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-04-02T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-04-02T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-04-02T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-04-02T06:00:00-05:00" n="232"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d232">
                <head>232. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Jordan</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d232fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 783.00/4–262. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_Niact1">Niact</gloss>.
                        Received at 2:45 p.m. and relayed to <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss>, Army, Navy, and Air Force. Repeated
                        to Damascus, Tel Aviv, Jerusalem, Cairo, London, Beirut, Baghdad, and
                        Ankara.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Amman</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-04-02T13:00:00+02:00">April 2, 1962, 1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>463. Pass Defense. Reference: <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 462.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d232fn1">In telegram 462 from Amman, April 1, <persName
                            corresp="#p_MWBJ1">Macomber</persName> reported that King <persName
                            corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName> had summoned him to express his
                        concern over reports of serious disturbances in the cities of Aleppo, Homs,
                        and Hama in Syria, reportedly connected with efforts to restore <persName
                            corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s authority over Syria. <persName
                            corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName> also pointed to reports of Israeli
                        and <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> troop movements. (Ibid.,
                        783.00/4–162)</note> Prime Minister called me to his office 0900 April 2.
                    Said situation in Syria had become far more serious than at time my conversation
                    with King <persName corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName> yesterday afternoon
                    (reference telegram), and that he now convinced that issue was whether or not
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> power to be restored
                    there.</p>
                <p>I asked what new information he had which would support this conclusion. Prime
                    Minister said that trouble in Syria had now spread as far south as Dera where he
                    just received information <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> flag now flying.
                    He cited other alleged reports. These did not seem convincing to me and when I
                    pointed out he said real basis for his conclusion was “Arab intuition”. He then
                    repeated thesis that King <persName corresp="#p_HIT1">Hussein</persName> had
                    previously argued with me many times, i.e. that if Nasserism regains control of
                    Syria, moderate progressive capitalistic governments such as in Jordan, doomed
                    in this part of Arab world. He said that in view of this Jordan would prefer
                    face showdown in Syria rather than face issue later on when defeat
                    inevitable.</p>
                <p>When I questioned thesis that Jordan demise inevitable if <persName
                        corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> regained control of Syria, Prime
                    Minister held to his position but added that even if this not the case <persName
                        corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s reappearance in Syria would mean
                    re-establishment of iron-fist totalitarian control not only in Syria area but in
                    Jordanian area as well. Re latter said if <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                    regained control of Syria, Jordan would have to take extreme internal security
                    measures which in effect would mean establishment of rigid conservative military
                    dictatorship here which would be completely incompatible with progressive
                    objectives he and his government now pursuing in Jordan.</p>
                <p>Prime Minister next said that while <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                    threat in Syria very great, he believed that anti-<gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                        >UAR</gloss> forces could still prevail provided prompt action taken and he
                    made it clear that if necessary Jordanians prepared send troops to Syria to
                    bolster anti-<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> forces.</p>
                <p>I repeated all arguments cited reference telegram. I then made added strong
                    argument against Jordan taking precipitous action based <pb facs="0632" n="572"
                        xml:id="pg_572"/> on Arab “intuition” and noted that in fact <gloss
                        target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> had no more information this morning than it
                    had yesterday and actual situation in Syria remained very unclear. Said that any
                    Jordanian troop movement even within its own borders could greatly strengthen
                    propaganda hand of <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> and undercut
                        <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> objectives in Syria.</p>
                <p>Prime Minister said that if Jordan Arab Army (<gloss target="#t_JAA1"
                    >JAA</gloss>) troops moved they would not stop at border but would keep going
                    until they reached Damascus. At same time, <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss>
                    would make clear that purpose of troop movement to Syria would be to restore
                    recently deposed civilian government and would withdraw immediately following a
                    plebiscite which would give Syrians opportunity free choice type of government
                    and alignment they desired. If Syrian people freely chose associate with
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>,<gloss target="#t_GOJ1"
                        >GOJ</gloss> would regret this but would not oppose it. On other hand,
                        <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> could not tolerate Syrians being brought
                    back forcefully and against the majority will into <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                        >UAR</gloss>.</p>
                <p>I pointed out discrepancy between numbers of Jordanian and Syrian troops and
                    suggested Jordan troops would be swallowed up before they could carry out this
                    objective. Prime Minister disagreed saying that if <gloss target="#t_JAA1"
                        >JAA</gloss> moved quickly and decisively they would be supported by
                    elements Syrian army dedicated to same objectives.</p>
                <p>I noted that if Jordan troops entered Syria, Iraqi troops might also come in.
                    Prime Minister said that would not create problem as <gloss target="#t_JAA1"
                        >JAA</gloss> would not fight Iraqis and both could withdraw after plebiscite
                    and restoration of civilian government. I said I thought this great over
                    simplification of problem and that if Jordan troops went across border they
                    would be stepping into morass from which it would be most difficult extricate
                    themselves.</p>
                <p>After further discussion, Prime Minister stressed that he had not yet reached
                    firm conclusion that it would be necessary send Jordanian troops to Syria and
                    that he not yet prepared to make such a recommendation until situation further
                    clarified. Said, however, that if <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> decided to
                    move would move very quickly and Jordanian troops might be in Damascus by
                    tomorrow morning. I said I thought this not only unwise but impossible.</p>
                <p>Prime Minister then made two specific requests. First, he asked that USG make
                    immediate démarche to <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> urging that
                    he stay out of Syrian situation. Second, he requested that USG, through its
                    Embassy in Damascus, seek put backbone in military junta by assuring it of USG
                    support against “minority” forces seeking restore <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> control over Syria. At same time, suggested USG apply
                    pressure on junta to make its peace with previous civilian government so they
                    could work together against pro-<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> elements.
                    (After leaving Prime Minister’s office, and while dictating this telegram, Prime
                    Minister telephoned me adding <pb facs="0633" n="573" xml:id="pg_573"/> further
                    request that US Embassy in Damascus pass word to Zahr ad-Din that <gloss
                        target="#t_JAA1">JAA</gloss> stood ready to be of assistance if he should so
                    request.)</p>
                <p>Conversation concluded with my reiterating strong advice that <gloss
                        target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> remain calm and not take foolish or precipitous
                    action. I emphasized again that neither <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss>, nor
                    anyone else at moment, had any firm information re higher nature, or degree of
                    seriousness, current Syrian situation. Prime Minister replied he still not ready
                    recommend any major action unless further developments within Syria made this
                    absolutely essential and said he would keep in touch with me.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> While I believe <gloss target="#t_GOJ1"
                        >GOJ</gloss> is more concerned re Syrian situation this morning than
                    yesterday, I conclude that much of Prime Minister’s talk was designed to
                    emphasize to USG gravity <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> attaches to
                    situation. Absence of <gloss target="#t_JAA1">JAA</gloss> troop movement and
                    low-key nature of military alert remains as reported <gloss target="#t_reftel1"
                        >reftel</gloss>. I am, nevertheless, concerned that combination of Jordan
                    fear of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and prevalence of unsubstantiated
                    but alarming rumors, could lead to precipitous action on part of <gloss
                        target="#t_JAA1">JAA</gloss> particularly if <gloss target="#t_GOJ1"
                        >GOJ</gloss> authorities conclude that moment had been reached when they
                    must act or <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> triumph in Syria will be
                    assured.</p>
                <p>Embassy is keeping in close touch with situation and will continue to counsel
                    restraint. I will be seeing King later in day.</p>
                <p>With regard Prime Minister’s first two requests, I defer to Department and my
                    colleagues in Damascus and Cairo as to whether representations along these lines
                    would serve any useful purpose. With regard to his third (telephone) request,
                    assume Department will not wish USG channels be used for this type
                    communication. However, believe <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> will seek
                    use other channels including its own to get this message through to Zahr
                    ad-Din.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MWBJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Macomber</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
