<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-06-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-06-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="304" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d304">
                    <head>304. Memorandum From the Department of State Executive Secretary
                            (<persName corresp="#p_BWH2" type="from">Brubeck</persName>) to the
                        President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG2" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d304fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                            611.86B/6–2162. Confidential. Drafted by Thacher and cleared by
                                <persName corresp="#p_TPH2">Talbot</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-06-21">June 21,
                            1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Article in June 25 New Republic Re <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The article in the June 25 New Republic, “Courting <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>”, in which the President has
                        expressed an interest, is filled with distortions and <pb facs="0805" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> untruths. The policy it attacks is a mockery
                        of what in fact is our policy toward the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                        and the Near East generally.</p>
                    <p>Contrary to assertions in the article, all Presidential correspondence with
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> was fully staffed
                        throughout the government.<note n="1" xml:id="d304fn1">Attached but not
                            printed is a “Chronology of Substantive Correspondence and Oral Messages
                            Exchanged Between President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> and President <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>.”</note> We have never, of course, sought to
                        “humor <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s aspiration to be the
                        key figure in mid-eastern politics”. We consulted with <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> with regard to the Syrian crisis but
                        certainly did not seek his “go-ahead” before recognizing the Syrian regime.
                        Our timing and tactics paid handsome dividends in preserving our relations
                        with the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and getting us off on the right
                        foot with the new Syrian government.</p>
                    <p>United States assistance to the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> in food,
                        technical assistance and industrial loans has been tied closely to Embassy
                        Cairo’s recommendations although details of our recent loans in support of
                        the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>’s <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss>-backed stabilization program were worked out here with the
                            <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> Minister of Economy. Our policies
                        have been based on careful appraisal of our national interests and not the
                        inspiration of any single individual. <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s role in the Congo shifted to full support of the
                        Adoula government when he became convinced that it was an independent one.
                        We have no evidence of his playing a provocative role among the Mau-Mau
                        (dead as an organization for several years). The canard that he showed
                        willingness to deny the canal to Portuguese and Dutch ships in the Goan and
                        West Irian crises is based on wholly unsubstantiated press stories.
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> has gone in for
                        anti-Iranian propaganda but we are working on a plan whereby both the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and Iran would cease simultaneously their
                        mutually hostile radio broadcasts.<note n="2" xml:id="d304fn2">Documentation
                            is in Department of State, Central File 686B.88.</note></p>
                    <p>We have not expected our policies to put <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> at the end of a short string or induce him to abandon
                        his neutralist policy nor to give up all ideas of a prominent role in the
                        Arab world. Our objectives are not in this context.</p>
                    <p>We have expected, however, a number of things which are occurring—increased
                            <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> concentration on its internal
                        development with a growing inclination to leave aside touchy area problems,
                        or, as Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_FM5">Fawzi</persName> has put
                        it, “place in the icebox” the Arab-Israel dispute. We have been gratified by
                        the consistent tapering off of anti-U.S. material in the Cairo press, by
                            <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> endeavors to mend its fences with
                        the Western governments and by a gradual thaw in our whole range of contacts
                        with the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, from Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> down through our political officers
                        in Cairo. The <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> is developing a stake in
                        good relations with the United States and the West. The scope of the
                        dialogue between <pb facs="0806" n="746" xml:id="pg_746"/> us is expanding
                        and the fabric of our ties is being strengthened. We expect disagreements
                        may arise but we are convinced, too, that our present approach is gradually
                        expanding our influence in Cairo with a consistently moderating impact on
                            <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s whole outlook.</p>
                    <p>Several of our Near Eastern Ambassadors reported at the recent conference in
                        Athens nervousness among Near Eastern governments and leaders that we might
                        be making <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> our “chosen
                        instrument”. But after full discussion our Ambassadors agreed that our
                        present course toward the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> was the one
                        best calculated among available alternatives to serve the United States
                        interest.</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">J.T. Rogers</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d304fn3"><persName>Jordan T. Rogers</persName> (<gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>-S) signed for <persName corresp="#p_BWH2">Brubeck</persName> above Brubreck’s typed
                                signature.</note></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>