<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Eastern European Affairs (
                    (Kelley))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933-39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">146</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-09-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rechrPce7erABw7F0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067245"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Interest rate</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-09-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-09-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="146"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d146">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51W89 U.S.S.R./116½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of Eastern European
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_KRF1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kelley</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="63" xml:id="d146fn63">Photostatic copy obtained from the
                            <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> Library, Hyde Park, N.
                        Y.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-09-05">September 5,
                            1934</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Conversation:</cell>
                        <cell>The Ambassador of the Soviet Union,</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName>;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>The Assistant Secretary of State, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRW1"
                                >Moore</persName>;</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Robert F. Kelley</persName>.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRW1">Moore</persName> opened the conversation by
                    stating that, without standing on ceremony, he had taken the initiative in
                    proposing this conference, since he felt that both sides were anxious to reach a
                    settlement of the matter of debts and claims. He pointed out that when
                    recognition was accorded, it was hoped that it would contribute both to the
                    promotion of world peace and to the development of trade between the two
                    countries, and while we had no illusions as to the amount of trade which might
                    be developed, he thought that every effort should be made to realize the
                    objectives which had been had in view. He referred to Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName>’s last proposal and said that the
                    main point at issue was the loan demanded by the Soviet Government. He did not
                    think there would be great difficulty in reaching an agreement in respect to the
                    amount of indebtedness, interest rates, et cetera, but that it was hardly worth
                    while discussing these matters so long as the Soviet Government insisted upon
                    the granting of a loan as a condition of its paying the indebtedness which might
                    be agreed upon. Mr, <persName corresp="#p_MRW1">Moore</persName> emphasized that
                    it was out of question for the Government of the United States to extend a loan
                    to the Soviet Government, either as proposed by Mr.
                        <persName>Litvinoff</persName> or as proposed by Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName>. If <pb facs="0247" n="141"
                        xml:id="pg_141"/> the Soviet Government insisted on this requirement, there
                    was no possibility of reaching a settlement of the matter.</p>
                <p>It was stated to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName> that the
                    Bank had contemplated financing credits of varying lengths according to several
                    categories of goods—possibly a year to a year and a half for consumers’ goods,
                    two to three years for light capital goods, and four to five years for heavy
                    capital goods. It was pointed out to him that these terms were much more
                    favorable than the Soviet Government was receiving in other countries. It was
                    suggested that it was possible that the President might agree to grant special
                    terms in exceptional cases, say for equipment for large industrial projects; but
                    it was emphasized that the maximum terms even in such cases could not possibly
                    exceed six to seven years, and such terms would be granted only in very
                    extraordinary cases. It was made clear to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TAA1"
                        >Troyanovsky</persName> that this matter had never been discussed with the
                    President, and it was not known whether he would approve of any exceptions to
                    the five year maximum. The suggestion was set forth merely as a possibility.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName> argued at great length
                    that the main difficulty was the effect of any agreement with the United States
                    on the relations of the Soviet Union with other countries, and that what the
                    Soviet Government granted the United States would have to be accorded to other
                    countries. This was the reason, he said, that the Soviet Government desired a
                    loan. It was suggested to him that, since it was impossible for the United
                    States to grant a loan, some other device might be worked out which would serve
                    this purpose just as well. He was asked whether he could not give thought to
                    this and propose some other formula which would meet the difficulty in question,
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName> replied that he had
                    exhausted his powers of invention in his last proposal, but that he would be
                    glad to consider, of course, any proposal along this line which we might
                    suggest.</p>
                <p>There was a brief discussion of the rates of interest, and Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName> stated that his Government was
                    prepared to pay a total interest rate on credits of seven per cent, four and a
                    small fraction of which would cover the interest charges and expenses of the
                    Bank, two and a half per cent constitute a sinking fund to liquidate the agreed
                    indebtedness, and the remaining fraction would be sufficient to liquidate the
                    interest of one per cent which the Soviet Government proposed to pay on the
                    agreed indebtedness. He declared that we had been willing to accept a similar
                    low interest rate in the case of our debt agreements with other countries.</p>
                <p>In concluding, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName> said that
                    he would be very glad to have another meeting if any suggestions occurred to us,
                    but he did not hold out the slightest possibility of his Government yielding on
                    the question of a loan.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
