<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933-39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d151</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">151</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1934-09-13T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1934-09-13T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1934-09-13T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1934-09-13T03:00:00-05:00" n="151"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d151">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51W89 U.S.S.R./121: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BWC1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1934-09-13T11:00:00+03:00"
                            >September 13, 1934—11 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 1:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>298. <persName corresp="#p_SBE1">Skvirsky</persName> who is here on vacation
                    called on me obviously under orders from the Foreign Office. He described what
                    he alleged was the exact point of view of the Soviet Government with regard to
                    settlement of debts and claims. The main point of his argument was that the
                    Soviet Government could not make any settlement with us which would cause at
                    this time a revival of the claims of England and France. He argued that the
                    payment of extra interest on credits from American exporters even though our
                    Government should carry a large part of the credit risk would produce immediate
                    revival of the claims of other nations. He said he had advised his Government
                    that the President could obtain easily the support of public opinion for a
                    settlement along the lines of <persName corresp="#p_TAA1"
                    >Troyanovsky</persName>’s last proposal to you.</p>
                <p>I replied that I believed he was totally in error, that public opinion in the
                    United States had been so outraged by the defaults of France, Great Britain, <hi
                        rend="italic">et al.</hi>, that any direct loan or unrestricted credit to
                    any nation on earth was a political impossibility and that I hoped he would
                    inform his Government that this was the fact.</p>
                <p>He answered that I had been so long away from America that I was out of touch
                    with the present state of public opinion, that he was in close touch with
                    American public opinion and that if the President should accept <persName
                        corresp="#p_TAA1">Troyanovsky</persName>’s last proposal he would have the
                    almost unanimous approval of public opinion. I replied that I felt sure that
                    public opinion would approve only a sharing of the credit risks of American
                    industry and that I had no reason to believe that the President had deviated
                    from the position he had taken in his negotiations with <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMM1">Litvinov</persName> or that he would alter that position.
                    I should be obliged if you would inform me if my view of American public opinion
                    and that point of view of the President is a mistaken one.</p>
                <p>I was somewhat surprised by the vehemence with which <persName corresp="#p_SBE1"
                        >Skvirsky</persName> insisted that the Soviet Government was even more
                    anxious today to reach a settlement than it had been when <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMM1">Litvinov</persName> was in Washington.</p>
                <p>I see no reason to disbelieve <persName corresp="#p_SBE1">Skvirsky</persName>’s
                    assertion that the chief obstacle in the minds of the members of the Soviet
                    Government is the difficulty of devising a method of distinction between the
                    claims of our Government and of other governments at a moment when the Soviet
                    Government is making every effort to establish intimate relations with England
                    and France.</p>
                <pb facs="0251" n="145" xml:id="pg_145"/>
                <p>I venture to suggest that we should exercise whatever ingenuity we may possess in
                    attempting to devise a basis of settlement which while acceptable to us could
                    not be acceptable to France, Great Britain and other claimants.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BWC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
