<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-07-07T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-07-07T21:00:00-05:00" n="322" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d322">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.6131/408: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HLW1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-07-07T22:00:00-04:00">July 7,
                                    1936—10 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>98. Your 161, July 3, 4 p.m.</p>
                        <p>1. Your numbered paragraph 6. Department has no objection to your writing
                            the following informal letter to either <persName corresp="#p_NAF1">Neymann</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_RBD1">Rosenblum</persName>: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Referring to our conversations concerning the tax imposed on
                                    coal imported into the United States from the Soviet Union I may
                                    say informally and for your strictly confidential information
                                    that it is my understanding that the Department of State is
                                    considering at the present time the possibility of seeking the
                                    removal of at least the discriminatory features of the tax by
                                    legislative action at the next session of Congress. It is not
                                    possible, of course, to forecast what action Congress may
                                    take.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>This letter should be considered as part of the discussions leading up to
                            the agreement and accordingly should not be published under any
                            circumstances until further definite authorization.</p>
                        <p>2. Your numbered paragraphs 8 and 9, in respect to note B. Department
                            approves text of proposed note B with following changes: (1) the
                            substitution in two places of “next 12 months” for “forthcoming year”;
                            (2) the transposition of the phrase appearing towards the end of the
                            note “in the course of the next 12 months” to follow “America”; and
                            (this is important) (3) the insertion of the adjective “American” before
                            the word “goods.”</p>
                        <p>Department desires you to endeavor to have the words “at least” inserted
                            before “$30,000,000”. While the insertion of this phrase does not
                            increase the obligation assumed by the Soviet Government, it offers a
                            basis for the American Government pointing out, as suggested by
                                <persName corresp="#p_NAF1">Neymann</persName> (your numbered
                            paragraph 7), that Soviet purchases may exceed the amount for which
                            Soviet Government has obligated itself. If the Soviet Government is
                            strongly opposed to agreeing to this proposal you are authorized to drop
                            the matter.</p>
                        <p>While note B may be dated 2 days later than note A, it is desired that
                            your inquiry be dated several days prior to the date of note A. Your
                            inquiry should follow the phraseology of that of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BWC1">Bullitt</persName> of July 11, 1935,<note n="69" xml:id="d322fn69">See Embassy’s telegram No. 275, July 11, 1935, 5
                                p.m., <ref target="#pg_211">p. 211</ref>.</note> except that
                            reference should be made to recent conversations “in regard to the
                            prolongation of the agreement of July 13, 1935, concerning commercial
                            relations between” et cetera.</p>
                        <p>3. Your numbered paragraphs 8 and 9, in respect to note A. Department
                            would prefer the following phraseology which is more precise: <pb facs="0446" n="340" xml:id="pg_340"/>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In accordance with the conversations which have taken place I
                                    have the honor to confirm on behalf of my Government the
                                    agreement which has been reached between the Governments of our
                                    respective countries that the agreement regarding commercial
                                    relations between the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics and
                                    the United States of America recorded in the exchange of notes
                                    between the People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs and the
                                    American Ambassador on July 13, 1935, shall continue in force
                                    for another year, that is, until July 13, 1937.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>4. Department suggests that the identic notes be dated July 11 and that
                            they be released in Moscow to the press at 5 p.m., that day, Moscow time
                            (10 a.m., Washington time). Department will make available to the press
                            at the same time text of the notes together with an explanatory
                            statement. Department assumes that Soviet Government has no objection to
                            the Department pointing out in this statement that the Soviet Government
                            has given assurances that it intends to purchase during the next 12
                            months American goods to the value of $30,000,000.</p>
                        <p>Department will release to the press at 10 a.m., Washington time Monday,
                            July 13, and suggests that you do the same at 5 p.m., that day, Moscow
                            time, texts of your letter of inquiry with regard to Soviet purchases
                            and of reply of the Soviet Government which should be dated July 13.</p>
                        <p>Please telegraph as soon as possible full text of notes so that
                            Department will be able to make them available to the press.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HC1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>