<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1936-07-09T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1936-07-09T07:00:00-05:00" n="323" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d323">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.6131/409: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HLW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1936-07-09T15:00:00+03:00">July 9,
                                    1936—3 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received July 9—11:44 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>163. Your 98, July 7, 10 p.m.</p>
                        <p>1. The following is the full text of exchange of notes to be signed by
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNN1">Krestinski</persName> and myself on July
                            11, 1936, at 3 p.m. <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p rend="flushleft">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Note A.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>, July 11,
                                    1936.</p>
                                <p>Excellency: In accordance with the conversations which have taken
                                    place, I have the honor to confirm on behalf of my Government
                                    the agreement which has been reached between the Governments of
                                    our respective countries that the agreement regarding commercial
                                    relations between the United States of America and the Union of
                                    Soviet Socialist Republics recorded in the exchange of notes
                                    between the American Ambassador and the People’s Commissar for
                                    Foreign Affairs on July 13, 1935, shall continue in force for
                                    another year, that is, until July 13, 1937.</p>
                                <pb facs="0447" n="341" xml:id="pg_341"/>
                                <p>Accept, Excellency, the renewed assurances of my highest
                                    consideration. Signed <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Loy W.
                                        Henderson</persName>, Chargé d’Affaires ad interim of the
                                    United States of America.</p>
                                <p>His Excellency <persName corresp="#p_KNN1">N. N.
                                        Krestinski</persName>,<lb/>Assistant People’s Commissar for
                                    Foreign Affairs, Moscow.”</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Note B.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>, July 11th,
                                    1936.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Chargé d’Affaires: In accordance with the conversations which
                                    have taken place, I have the honor to confirm on behalf of my
                                    Government the agreement which has been reached between the
                                    Governments of our respective countries that the agreement
                                    regarding commercial relations between the Union of Soviet
                                    Socialist Republics and the United States of America recorded in
                                    the exchange of notes between the People’s Commissar for Foreign
                                    Affairs and the American Ambassador on July 13, 1935, shall
                                    continue in force for another year, that is, until July 13,
                                    1937.</p>
                                <p>Accept, Mr. Chargé d’Affaires, the renewed assurances of my
                                    highest consideration. Signed <persName corresp="#p_KNN1">N.
                                        Krestinski</persName> Assistant People’s Commissar for
                                    Foreign Affairs.</p>
                                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Loy W.
                                    Henderson</persName>,<lb/>Chargé d’Affaires ad interim of the
                                    United States of America, Moscow.”</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Note C.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>, July 9, 1936.</p>
                                <p>Excellency: I have the honor to refer to our recent conversations
                                    in regard to the prolongation of the agreement of July 13, 1935,
                                    concerning commercial relations between the United States of
                                    America and the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics and to ask
                                    you to let me know the value of articles the growth, produce, or
                                    manufacture of the United States of America which the Government
                                    of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics intends to purchase
                                    in the United States of America during the next 12 months for
                                    export to the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics.</p>
                                <p>Accept, Excellency, the renewed asurances of my highest
                                    consideration. Signed <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Loy W.
                                        Henderson</persName>, Chargé d’Affaires ad interim of the
                                    United States of America.</p>
                                <p>His Excellency <persName corresp="#p_KNN1">N. N.
                                        Krestinski</persName>,<lb/>Assistant People’s Commissar for
                                    Foreign Affairs, Moscow.”</p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Note D.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>, July 13,
                                    1936.</p>
                                <p>Mr. Chargé d’Affaires: In reply to your inquiry regarding the
                                    intended purchases by the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in
                                    the United States of America in the course of the next 12
                                    months, I have the honor to inform you that, according to
                                    information received by me from the People’s Commissariat for
                                    Foreign Trade, the economic organizations of the Union of Soviet
                                    Socialist Republics intend to buy in the United States of
                                    America in the course of the next 12 months American goods in
                                    the amount of at least $30,000,000.</p>
                                <pb facs="0448" n="342" xml:id="pg_342"/>
                                <p>Accept, Mr. Chargé d’Affaires, the renewed assurances of my
                                    highest consideration. Signed <persName corresp="#p_KNN1">N.
                                        Krestinski</persName>, Assistant People’s Commissar for
                                    Foreign Affairs.</p>
                                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Loy W.
                                    Henderson</persName>,<lb/>Chargé d’Affaires ad interim of the
                                    United States of America, Moscow.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. The Foreign Office has no objection to the notes being released as
                            suggested in your numbered paragraph 4.</p>
                        <p>3. I would appreciate it if the Department would find it possible to
                            prepare a short statement for me to give to the American journalists
                            here on July 11 immediately after the release of notes A and B. Although
                            they have realized that conversations have been taking place they have
                            been loyal in not endeavoring to obtain advance information and it would
                            be helpful if the Embassy in return could assist them in writing their
                            stories.</p>
                        <p>4. The Soviet Government desires that the reference in the Department’s
                            statement of July 11 to Soviet assurances be changed to read somewhat as
                            follows: “The Soviet Government has informed the American Government
                            that the appropriate Soviet economic organizations intend to purchase
                            during the next 12 months American goods to the value of at least
                            $30,000,000.”</p>
                        <p>5. I have written an informal letter as authorized in your numbered
                            paragraph 1 to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RBD1">Rosenblum</persName>
                            under date of July 8 and am to hand it to him on July 11 under the
                            conditions laid down by you.</p>
                        <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_KNN1">Krestinski</persName> is signing the notes
                            as Assistant People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs because <persName corresp="#p_LMM1">Litvinov</persName> may arrive in Moscow on July
                            12.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>