<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1937-09-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1937-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="349" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d349">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.3361/37</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_HLW1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 553</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1937-09-14">September 14,
                                1937</date>.<lb/>[Received September 27.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to this Embassy’s telegram
                            No. 197 of July 29, 1937,<note n="39" xml:id="d349fn39">Not
                                printed.</note> and its despatch No. 506 of August 20, 1937,
                            relating to the visit of Admiral <persName corresp="#p_YHE1">Yarnell</persName> and several vessels of the United States Asiatic
                            Fleet to Vladivostok during the period July 28 to August 1, 1937, I have
                            the honor to enclose a memorandum<note n="39" xml:id="d349fn42">Not
                                printed.</note> regarding the visit prepared by Lieutenant-Colonel
                                <persName corresp="#p_FPR1">Faymonville</persName>, the Military
                            Attaché of this Mission, who went to Vladivostok in order to participate
                            in the festivities attendant to the call. It is regretted that pressure
                            of other work rendered it impossible for one of the Secretaries of the
                            Mission also to be present. It is understood, however, that
                            Lieutenant-Colonel <persName corresp="#p_FPR1">Faymonville</persName>
                            was able to render the Admiral and his staff valuable assistance and
                            that he was particularly useful in helping them to orient themselves in
                            the surroundings peculiar to the Soviet <pb facs="0497" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/> Union and in giving them advice with respect to
                            Soviet currency conditions, manner of entertaining, and so forth.</p>
                        <p>As of possible interest both to the State and Navy Departments, I am also
                            submitting herewith translations of three articles which appeared in the
                            Soviet press relating to the visit.<note n="40" xml:id="d349fn40">None
                                printed.</note> These three articles were selected for translation
                            as being typical of numerous accounts of the visit published in various
                            Soviet newspapers.</p>
                        <p>At the request of Admiral <persName corresp="#p_YHE1">Yarnell</persName>,
                            I have addressed a letter to the Acting People’s Commissar for Foreign
                            Affairs expressing the appreciation of the Admiral and of the American
                            Government for the courtesies shown by Soviet officials during the
                            course of the visit.<note n="41" xml:id="d349fn41">With the passing of
                                time the good effects of this visit diminished, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">Henderson</persName>, when he was Assistant
                                Chief of the Division of European Affairs in the Department of
                                State, in a memorandum of January 16, 1939, advised against the
                                desirability of American warships paying a visit to Leningrad in
                                1939, because the Vladivostok visit of 1937 had not brought about
                                “an increase of understanding between the hosts and guests and did
                                not arouse feelings of mutual esteem.” (811.3361/41)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_HLW1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Loy W. Henderson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>