<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1933-12-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1933-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="51" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">702.6111/236</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">A. R. Feil</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1933-12-12">December 12,
                                1933</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In reply to your letter of November 25,
                            1933, requesting an official ruling with respect to the present status
                            of the former Russian Consulate General at New York, you are advised
                            that on November 17, 1933, the Department informed by telegraph the
                            Russian Consuls General and Consuls recognized by this Government that
                            in view of the recognition of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics by
                            the Government of the United States, their exequaturs had been revoked
                            effective as of November 16, 1933, and that consequently their status as
                            Russian consular officials was considered as terminated on that
                            date.</p>
                        <p>Such a telegram was not sent to Mr. <persName>Oustinoff</persName>,
                            formerly Russian Consul General at New York, who has been abroad since
                            July 1929, since he had already been dropped earlier in the present year
                            by the Department from the list of foreign consular officers recognized
                            by this Government, following the receipt of information to the effect
                            that he was not expected to return to the United States in the near
                            future.</p>
                        <p>In view of the foregoing and of the fact that this Government has
                            recognized the Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics,
                            your office should not hold itself out to be a Russian Consulate General
                            and should not undertake to perform consular functions.</p>
                        <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                        <closer>For the Acting Secretary of State: <lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MRW1">R. <hi rend="smallcaps">Walton
                                        Moore</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Assistant Secretary</hi>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>