<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Steinhardt) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1933-39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d600</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">600</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-11-01T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-11-01T14:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                    <term ref="recJqlMttIxR5nnOr" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Nonaggression</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recb140a4efc2e771d" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general">Warships</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recfec047f5431758f" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="property-claims" subject="contraband-of-war">Contraband of war</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-11-01T14:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-11-01T14:00:00-05:00" n="600"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d600">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">760d.61/384: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SLA1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-11-01T22:00:00+03:00"
                            >November 1, 1939—10 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received November 1—9:40 p.m.<note n="84" xml:id="d600fn84">Telegram
                            in two sections.</note>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>847. The press today publishes the text of <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName>’s speech to the Supreme Soviet last evening.</p>
                <p>The first portion dealing with the general international situation consists
                    largely of a repetition of views previously expressed in the Soviet press
                    relating to Soviet-German friendship, the collapse of <pb facs="0893" n="787"
                        xml:id="pg_787"/> the Polish State, support of German peace efforts, a
                    denunciation of England and France for continuing the war for “imperialist aims”
                    under cover of the slogan of democracy. He announced that in the light of recent
                    events the terms “aggression” and “aggressor” have acquired a new concrete
                    meaning and that the roles were now reversed with Germany striving for peace
                    and: England and France for war. He mentioned the necessity of a “strong”
                    Germany for an enduring peace in Europe and spoke with sympathy of Germany’s
                    efforts to throw off the Treaty of Versailles<note n="85" xml:id="d600fn85"
                        >Signed on June 28, 1919; for text, see <ref target="frus1919Parisv13#pg_55">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Paris Peace Conference,
                            1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, p. 55</ref>.</note> created
                    by France and England “with the active participation of the United States”.
                    After dwelling at length on Soviet-German friendship he mentioned especially the
                    successful progress of economic negotiations taking place here and in
                    Germany.</p>
                <p>After justifying Soviet “liberation” of Western Ukraine and White Russia,
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> discussed the recently
                    concluded treaties with Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania<note n="86"
                        xml:id="d600fn86">For the enforced conclusion of pacts of mutual assistance
                        between the Baltic States and the Soviet Union, see <ref target="#pg_934"
                            >pp. 934</ref> ff.</note> emphasizing the benefits conferred on those
                    countries and vigorously denying any intention on the part of the Soviet Union
                    to interfere in their internal affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> then dwelt at great length on the
                    negotiations with Finland.<note n="87" xml:id="d600fn87">See <hi rend="italic"
                            >supra.</hi>
                    </note> After stating that relations with Finland as compared to the other
                    Baltic States were in a special category primarily due to the fact that a
                    “variety of outside influences emanating from third countries were at work in
                    Finland”. He denounced the inventions and lies of the foreign press, concerning
                    the Soviet proposals which he said were extremely modest and the minimum
                    necessary for the protection of Soviet security. Turning to the actual
                    negotiations, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> stated that since
                    the Finnish Government had been unwilling to conclude a pact of mutual
                    assistance similar to the pacts concluded with other Baltic States, the Soviet
                    Government had not insisted on this point. He then outlined the concrete
                    proposals submitted by the Soviet Government, substantially along the lines
                    previously reported by the Embassy revealing that the two major points now at
                    issue concern the territory north of Leningrad and a Soviet base at the entrance
                    to the Gulf of Finland. He observed “the differences in regard to certain of our
                    proposals are not yet overcome and the concessions made by Finland in this
                    connection, for example, the partial cession of territory on the Karelian
                    Isthmus, clearly do not achieve their purpose”.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> then referred to the concessions
                    made to Finland, mentioning the withdrawal of the Soviet objections to the
                    fortification of the Aland Islands, provided it was done by Finland alone and
                        <pb facs="0894" n="788" xml:id="pg_788"/> without the participation of any
                    third power; the demilitarization of the Finnish-Soviet frontier on the Karelian
                    Isthmus; and the supplementing of the Soviet-Finnish pact of nonaggression<note
                        n="89" xml:id="d600fn89">Signed at Helsinki, January 21, 1932; for text, see
                        League of Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">clvii</hi>, p.
                        393. For protocol prolonging the validity of this treaty until December 31,
                        1945, signed at Moscow on April 7, 1934, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>,
                        vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">clv</hi>, p. 325.</note> by mutual guarantees and
                    development of economic relations between the two countries. He then stated
                    that, “After all this we do not think that Finland should begin to seek grounds
                    for a rupture of the proposed agreement. This would not be in conformity with
                    the policy of friendly Soviet-Finnish relations and would certainly cause
                    serious harm to Finland.” He added, “We are certain that the importance of the
                    strengthening of friendly Soviet relations will be correctly understood by the
                    ruling Finnish circles and that the Finnish statesmen will not give in to any
                    anti-Soviet pressure and incitement on the part of anyone.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> then observed: “I must, however,
                    report that even the President of the United States found it appropriate to
                    interfere in these questions, which is difficult to reconcile with the policy of
                    American neutrality. In his message of October 12, addressed to <persName
                        corresp="#p_KMI1">Kalinin</persName>,<note n="90" xml:id="d600fn90">The
                        President’s message was dated October 11, 1939, and delivered on October 12;
                        for text, see Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October
                        21, 1939, p. 395.</note> President of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of
                    the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, Mr. <persName>Roosevelt</persName>
                    expressed a hope for the preservation and development of friendly and peaceful
                    relations between the Soviet Union and Finland. It might be thought that insofar
                    as the United States is concerned matters are better let us say, with the
                    Philippines or Cuba which have long demanded from the United States their
                    freedom and independence and have been unable to receive them, than with the
                    Soviet Union and Finland which long ago received from the Soviet Union its
                    freedom and state independence.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> then quoted the text of <persName
                        corresp="#p_KMI1">Kalinin</persName>’s reply to the President,<note n="91"
                        xml:id="d600fn91">For text, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 395.</note>
                    omitting, however, the initial greeting, and beginning with the words, “I
                    consider it appropriate to remind you Mr. President”. He then continued, “After
                    such a clear answer from the President of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of
                    the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics it should be entirely obvious that with
                    good-will the Finnish Government will meet our minimum proposals which not only
                    do not contravene the national and state interests of Finland but strengthen its
                    external security and create a broad basis for the further broad development of
                    political and economic relations between our two countries.”</p>
                <pb facs="0895" n="789" xml:id="pg_789"/>
                <p>In respect of Turkey <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> stated that
                    despite the wildest comment abroad the Soviet-Turkish negotiations concerned
                    only the conclusion of a bilateral pact of mutual assistance limited to the
                    Black Sea area and the straits with the reservation that nothing thereunder
                    should involve the Soviet Union in armed conflict with Germany; and a guarantee
                    that Turkey would not permit the warships of a non-Black Sea power to pass
                    through the Bosphorus into the Black Sea. Both of these reservations <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> charged, Turkey had refused and thereby
                    rendered impossible the conclusion of the pact. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> then asserted that even though unsuccessful the
                    negotiations had been of value in that as a result the policy of Turkey was now
                    much clearer to the Soviet Union. After charging that Turkey had now abandoned a
                    policy of neutrality and had been drawn into the orbit of the war in the
                    interests of England and France, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    hinted Turkey might some day regret the step that it had taken.<note n="92"
                        xml:id="d600fn92">A treaty of mutual assistance was signed between Great
                        Britain, France, and Turkey at Ankara on October 19, 1939, following the
                        breaking off of the Turkish-Soviet negotiations in Moscow; for text, see
                        League of Nations Treaty Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cc</hi>, p. 167,
                        or Department of State, <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November 11, 1939,
                        p. 544.</note> In respect of the Soviet Union, however, he added that in
                    conformity with its general policy which consisted in retaining liberty of
                    action, the pursuance of a policy of neutrality and cooperation in the movement
                    for the reestablishment of peace, this policy would be equally applied in the
                    area of the Black Sea.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> then spoke of the improvement in
                    Soviet-Japanese relations which had resulted from the conclusion of a truce on
                    Japanese initiative on the Mongolian-Manchurian frontier.<note n="93"
                        xml:id="d600fn93">September 15, 1939.</note> He characterized this conflict
                    as entirely unnecessary, having been due to the attempts of the Japanese to
                    seize a portion of the territory of the Mongolian People’s Republic. The
                    liquidation of this conflict, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    stated, constituted the first step in the improvement of Soviet-Japanese
                    relations. He continued that if good-will were displayed in the work of the
                    mixed frontier commissions a successful solution of the frontier conflicts might
                    be expected. After referring to the possibility of trade negotiations between
                    the Soviet Union and Japan, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    concluded his reference to Soviet-Japanese relations with the statement that
                    while there had been a tendency towards improvement in these relations at the
                    present time it is difficult to judge to what extent it is possible to count on
                    rapid development of this tendency. [“]We have not yet succeeded in finding out
                    how seriously the ground has been prepared in Japanese circles. For our part it
                    must be said that we are favorably disposed to Japanese proposal of this nature
                    and will approach them from the point of view of our basic political position
                    and our interest in peace.[”]</p>
                <pb facs="0896" n="790" xml:id="pg_790"/>
                <p>(It is significant that <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> makes no
                    reference in his speech to Soviet relations with China).</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> then outlined in brief the Soviet
                    position in regard to contraband of war as set forth in the Soviet note to Great
                    Britain and concluded that from the point of view of the termination of the war
                    the decision of the American Senate in removing the embargo on arms<note n="94"
                        xml:id="d600fn94">The Neutrality Act of 1939, passed by the Senate on
                        October 27, 1939, was approved on November 4, 1939; 54 Stat. 4.</note>
                    arouses “legitimate doubts”. He added, indeed there can be no doubt that this
                    decision will have as its result neither a slowing down nor a curtailment of the
                    war; but on the contrary an increasing intensification and prolongation of the
                    war. Obviously such a decision will assure higher profits for the American
                    munitions industry. But the question is: “Can this circumstance serve the
                    justification for the repeal of the embargo on the export of arms from America?
                    It is clear that it cannot.”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SLA1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
