<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-10-07T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-10-07T13:00:00-05:00" n="772" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d772">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/726:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SLA1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-10-07T21:00:00+03:00">October 7,
                                    1939—9 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received October 7—6:05 p.m.<note n="43" xml:id="d772fn43">Telegram in three sections.</note>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>702. During the course of a long conversation yesterday evening with the
                            German Ambassador<note n="44" xml:id="d772fn44">
                                <persName corresp="#p_SFWCvd1">Friedrich Werner, Count von der
                                    Schulenburg</persName>.</note> he made the following
                            observations of interest.</p>
                        <p>1. Estonia and Latvia will occupy the same status vis-à-vis the Soviet
                            Union as Egypt occupies with Great Britain. Lithuania will conclude an
                            agreement with the Soviet Union giving the latter special transit
                            facilities and perhaps the right to maintain certain military air bases
                            in Lithuania. The question of Finland was not discussed in the
                            Soviet-German negotiations but it was the Ambassador’s belief that the
                            Soviet Government would be more careful in dealing with Finland and
                            would probably confine its demands to the return of the Finnish Islands
                            in the region of Cronstadt, as the Finns, for whom the Russians have a
                            wholesome respect, would probably resist any attempt to establish a
                            Soviet foothold on the Finnish mainland.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>In respect of Soviet-German relations in general, and particularly Soviet
                            penetration in the Baltic, the Ambassador stated that at the present
                            time, in view of their involvement in the west, Germany is in no
                            position to oppose legitimate Soviet interests in those regions. I also
                            received the impression that the Soviet Government is not fully
                            consulting with Germany in respect of action in areas which do not fall
                            within the character of mutual interest concerning which consultation
                            was provided for in the Soviet-German treaty of nonaggression. The
                            Ambassador expressed the greatest admiration for <persName corresp="#p_SIV1">Stalin</persName> who, he said, had shown himself
                            to be well-informed, astute and fully capable of taking advantage of the
                            present situation for the benefit of the Soviet Union. In general,
                            however, I gained the impression that <pb facs="1069" n="963" xml:id="pg_963"/> there has up to the present been no serious
                            friction between the German and Soviet Governments, due primarily to the
                            fact that the Russians have not yet encroached upon any areas which are
                            of primary interest to Germany, or which had not been recognized as of
                            greater interest to the Soviet Union at the time of the original
                            agreement in August.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SLA1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>