<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 129The Commander in Chief, Pacific (Stump), to the Chief of Naval
                    Operations (Fechteler)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-07-23T15:04:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-07-23T15:04:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-23T15:04:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-23T15:04:00-05:00" n="129"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of Defense files: Telegram</note>
                <note n="1" xml:id="d129fn1">The source text is not the transmission copy of the
                    telegram; it is labeled Enclosure “D” to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                    2118/57.</note>
                <head>No. 129<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander in Chief, Pacific (<persName corresp="#p_SAFB1"
                            type="from">Stump</persName>), to the Chief of Naval Operations
                            (<persName corresp="#p_FAWM1" type="to">Fechteler</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d129fn2">Also sent to the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Honolulu</hi>
                        </placeName>?,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-07-23T10:04:00-10:00"
                            >July 23, 1953—10:04 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>232004Z. CNO 222159Z of July.<note n="*" xml:id="d129fn3">On file in <gloss
                            target="#t_JCS1">J.C.S.</gloss> Secretariat. [Footnote in the source
                        text. Telegram CNO 222159Z is not printed.]</note> Consider my Formosa
                    directive should be modified to include assistance to ChiNats in defense or
                    recapture of those off-shore islands or island groups which they now hold and
                    which are determined by us to be essential for retention. Essential for
                    retention falls into 2 categories: <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>Essential for defense of Formosa and Pescadores.</item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>Essential for other US interests. Category “A” islands are
                                <persName>PaiSha</persName> (Kaoteng),
                                <persName>Pei-Kan-Tang</persName> (Tangki Tao),
                                <persName>Ma-Tsu</persName>, <persName>Pai-Chuan Tao</persName>
                            (White Dog), <persName>Chin-Men Tao</persName> (Quemoy) (Kinmen),
                                <persName>Lieh Hsu</persName> (Little Quemoy Island),
                                <persName>Ta-Tan Tao</persName> and <persName>Erh-Tan
                            Tao</persName>. These islands block the Foochow and Amoy approaches
                            which are possible staging areas for offensive action against Formosa
                            and Pescadores and can also be used to counter ChiCom invasion
                            operations. Retention of these islands is considered further essential
                            for <gloss target="#t_NGRC1">NGRC</gloss> morale, psychological warfare
                            purposes, <gloss target="#t_NGRC1">NGRC</gloss> pre-invasion mainland
                            operations, commando raiding, intelligence gathering, maritime
                            resistance development, sabotage and escape and evasion. Category “B”
                            islands likewise essential for retention are Shang-Ta-Chen-Shan and
                            Hsia-Ta-Chen which though not essential to defense of Formosa and
                            Pescadores do serve other purposes listed for category “A” islands.
                            There are other ChiNat islands which are desirable for retention as they
                            serve to facilitate the security of above essential islands. I do not
                            propose US assist in defense these islands but ChiNats should be
                            prevailed upon to defend and US should assist material wise as
                            practicable. If my directive is modified as above I propose to make
                            COM7THFLT operationally responsible in same manner as for defense of
                            Formosa and Pescadores. I would contemplate the use of US Naval and Air
                            Forces in defense of essential islands and no others. This would involve
                            destroyer and carrier air operations against the ChiComs together with
                            Air Force units if made available. This would vary according to island
                            groups as possibly only air operations could be conducted in defense of
                            Kinmen. I consider it essential that I be authorized to permit ChiNats
                            to attack unmistakable ChiCom concentrations on mainland when proximate
                            to and threatening an essential island or island group. I recognize that
                            forces would have to be made available to me by the <gloss
                                target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> upon my recommendation but propose to
                            predetermine force and timing requirements for each essential island
                            group based on <pb facs="0266" n="238" xml:id="pg_238"/> detailed
                            studies. Meanwhile every effort is being made for ChiNats to plan and
                            prepare proper defense islands determined to be essential or desirable
                            for retention.<note n="3" xml:id="d129fn4">The Joint Chiefs replied in
                                    <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> telegram 948918, Sept. 24,
                                that they did not wish to recommend an increase in U.S.
                                responsibility for defense of the off-shore islands at that time but
                                that, in case the decision was made in the future that the United
                                States should take an active part in the defense of the islands, and
                                to facilitate the development of a future <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                                    >JCS</gloss> position on the subject, <gloss
                                    target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> was instructed to submit a
                                plan for employment of U.S. forces in defense of each island or
                                island group concerned. (<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                                records, CCS 381 (1–24–42) Sec. 43)</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
