<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-13T14:08:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-13T14:08:00-05:00" n="189" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d189">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/5–554: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 189<lb/><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">United States
                                        Delegation at the Geneva Conference</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-13T15:08:00-04:00">May 13, 1954—3:08
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Tosec 151. Reference Secto 104.<note n="1" xml:id="d189fn1">Secto 104
                                        (<hi rend="italic">see</hi>
                                    <ref target="#d187fn3">footnote 3, Document 187</ref>) also
                                    commented that the Chinese would probably react to the proposed
                                        <gloss target="#t_IRC1">IRC</gloss> approach concerning U.S.
                                    civilians by raising the question of Chinese detained in the
                                    United States. Secto 88 from Geneva, May 4, reported that
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HHC1">Huang Hua</persName>, adviser
                                    and spokesman for the Chinese Delegation, had told a reporter
                                    that the Americans imprisoned in China “were being held hostage
                                    for the fifty Chinese students that the US would not allow to be
                                    returned to China.” (396.1 GE/5–454)</note> Interdepartmental
                                committee agreed Tuesday<note n="2" xml:id="d189fn2">May 11.</note>
                                recommend Attorney General reappraise all <pb facs="0445" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/> cases Chinese (now mostly teaching colleges or
                                working private labs) detained United States by individual
                                administrative orders, using criterion future detention only if
                                return to Communist China would substantially injure defense United
                                States. Recommendation predicated on assumption that release of
                                Chinese will obtain release American citizens held Communist China.
                                Appears likely Attorney General will agree and start necessary
                                procedures at once.</p>
                            <p>Preliminary survey indicates most detainees will be allowed return
                                after reappraisal, 8 to 10 repeatedly attempted obtain exit permits.
                                Sentiments others unknown. Canvass of their desires to start near
                                future.</p>
                            <p>Defense participating in procedures and asks that Vice Admiral
                                    <persName>Davis</persName><note n="3" xml:id="d189fn3"><persName>Davis</persName> was serving as a special adviser
                                    to the U.S. Delegation.</note> be informed of foregoing.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>