<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="239" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source"><persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> papers, “Telephone Conversations—White
                                House”</note>
                            <head>No. 239<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone
                                    Conversations, by the Secretary of State</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d239fn1">A note on the source text indicates that the
                                    conversations took place between 9:30 and 10:30
                                a.m.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-07-25">July 25, 1954</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>I called <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Admiral Radford</persName> to
                                inquire as to what the instructions were governing the aircraft
                                carriers that had been sent to the scene of the Chinese Communist
                                attack on the Cathay–Pacific airliner. He said that instructions
                                were to defend themselves, but not to engage in “hot pursuit” which
                                might take them into Chinese national air. I said that I thought
                                “hot pursuit” should be permitted even though it did carry into the
                                air above the Communist mainland or territorial waters. He said that
                                the instructions had been given by Sec. <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>, and that he could not vary them. He
                                suggested that I might call Sec. <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>.</p>
                            <p>I then called Sec. <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>, and
                                told him my views as earlier expressed to <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Adm. Radford</persName>, without however
                                mentioning my prior talk with <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Adm.
                                    Radford</persName>. Sec. <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> felt that he would not want to alter the
                                instructions without authority from the President.</p>
                            <p>I then called the President at Gettysburg. I expressed the view that
                                the air defense of our carriers should not be so strictly limited to
                                exclude “hot pursuit” into the air above Communist Chinese territory
                                or territorial waters.</p>
                            <p>The President said he was very much concerned about the situation and
                                had been thinking about it much during the night. He suggested that
                                since the plane was British, the primary responsibility laid upon
                                the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>. He asked what I thought they
                                would do. I said I thought that they would probably limit themselves
                                to the exchange of notes and that they would make every effort to
                                minimize the incident in line with their policy of recognition of
                                Communist China and promoting good relations with it. I said that I
                                planned to get in touch with the British Ambassador to find out what
                                their further plans were. So far, they have told us of the terms of
                                their instructions to <persName corresp="#p_TH1">Trevelyan</persName> at Peiping.</p>
                            <p>The President said he did not want us to get too far in front and
                                that he questioned the desirability of our planes flying into
                                Chinese Communist air in order to seek a fight. I said I did not
                                have this in mind, but did have in mind that if there were hostile
                                demonstrations against our aircraft carriers, they could be driven
                                off even <pb facs="0535" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/> though our planes
                                in so doing infringed on Chinese Communist air. The President said
                                that he agreed with this, and thought that our ships and planes in
                                that area could be instructed to take “all necessary measures to
                                protect themselves”, and that this would not exclude a pursuit into
                                Chinese air if the initial hostile demonstration occurred in
                                relation to our planes or ships on the high seas. He authorized me
                                to advise Sec. <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>
                                accordingly.</p>
                            <p>I next called Sec. <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> and
                                reported to him the conversation with the President. Sec. <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName> said that he would get in
                                touch with <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Adm. Radford</persName> to
                                discuss the possible desirability of modifying the existing
                                instructions.</p>
                            <p>I then called <persName corresp="#p_RAAW1">Adm. Radford</persName>
                                telling him that I had spoken to the President and to Sec. <persName corresp="#p_WCE1">Wilson</persName>, and that he would doubtless
                                hear from the latter.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DJF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">John
                                            Foster Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>