<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 255Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs
                    (Robertson) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d255</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">255</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-08-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-08-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="255"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d255">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">893.49/8–1754</note>
                <head>No. 255<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern
                        Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWS1" type="from">Robertson</persName>) to
                        the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d255fn1">Filed with a memorandum of Aug. 17 from <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_RWS1"
                            >Robertson</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-08-16">August 16,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Proposal to Assist Chinese National Government to Offer Food to Mainland
                        Flood Victims in Own Name</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Problem:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Embassy/<gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                    Taipei propose in Taipei’s <gloss target="#t_Tousfo1">Tousfo</gloss> 232 (Tab
                        A)<note n="2" xml:id="d255fn2">Not printed.</note> that this Government
                    assist the Chinese National Government in making a food offer to flood victims
                    in Communist China in its own name. I believe that this proposal, on the scale
                    of aid contemplated, would not involve most of the disadvantages of the proposal
                    discussed in my memorandum to you of August 11 (Tab B),<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d255fn3">Not printed. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1"
                            >Robertson</persName>’s Aug. 11 memorandum stated that it had been
                        tentatively decided that the United States should offer relief food to the
                        flood victims in China through the International Red Cross and urged that
                        the proposal should be rejected.</note> would produce similar psychological
                    advantages and would in addition enhance the prestige of the Government of
                    China, which is one of our policy objectives.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Embassy/<gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                        >CIA</gloss> proposal in Tab A recommends that <gloss target="#t_FOA1"
                        >FOA</gloss> agree to purchase 20,000 tons of rice to be shipped in the name
                    of the Government of China from Taiwan direct to mainland ports in Chinese
                    Government or neutral ships under a safe conduct guarantee. This amount is
                    designed to be neither so small as to indicate a purely propaganda move, nor so
                    large as to be obvious to all that Free China is incapable of making such an
                    offer on her own. In addition, it would not be so large as to permit the regime
                    to divert sizeable amounts for barter trade in strategic materials.</p>
                <p>I believe that the Nationalist Chinese origin of this food offer, despite
                    probable Communist attempts to hide or twist the facts, would become known to a
                    large number of Chinese on the mainland, who would be reminded that the Chinese
                    National Government is concerned about the needs of its compatriots under
                    Communist domination and that it recognizes its responsibility toward them,
                    consonant with its capabilities.</p>
                <p>The anticipated refusal would place the Chinese Communist regime on the
                    defensive. It would show that the regime places its <pb facs="0554" n="526"
                        xml:id="pg_526"/> political and prestige interests above the welfare of the
                    flood victims. The rejection could probably be exploited with great
                    effectiveness by U.S. and Chinese Nationalist propaganda organs.</p>
                <p>The offer would underscore the important fact (too often overlooked) that the
                    Chinese Nationalist Government asserts sovereignty over the Chinese mainland.
                    The stature of the Chinese Nationalist Government would be increased by the mere
                    making of the offer, and doubly so in the highly unlikely event of acceptance of
                    the offer.</p>
                <p>The offer could be convincingly held out as a bona fide one. If it is refused by
                    the Communists, the pressures on us to make a direct relief offer to the Chinese
                    Communists (which we believe to be full of dangers) would be appreciably
                    reduced. The unwillingness of the Chinese Communists to put the welfare of its
                    populace above extraneous considerations would be established.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>That the proposal in Tab A be approved.<note n="4" xml:id="d255fn4">
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>’ Aug. 17 memorandum to
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> (see <ref
                                target="#d255fn1">footnote 1</ref> above) reads as follows: <quote
                                rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“In view of the forceful and cogent objections raised by
                                        <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName> and <persName
                                        corresp="#p_HGJE1">Hull</persName> to U.S. flood relief aid
                                    to Mainland Chinese, I believe that this project should be
                                    definitely abandoned. However, I am intrigued by the idea of
                                    putting the Chinese Nationalist Government in a position to
                                    offer such aid. I do not want definitely to approve it until it
                                    has been submitted to <persName corresp="#p_AJM1"
                                        >Allison</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HGJE1"
                                        >Hull</persName> to be sure that it does not encounter the
                                    objections of the earlier budget. I think that it would not
                                    because there could be no possibility of misconstruing the
                                    motivation of the Chinese Nationalist Government. Unless
                                        <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName> and <persName
                                        corresp="#p_HGJE1">Hull</persName> have serious objections,
                                    I would favor proceeding with the project, as outlined in your
                                    memorandum to me of August 16.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>A memorandum of Aug. 25 from <persName corresp="#p_RWS1"
                                >Robertson</persName> to Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWB1"
                                >Smith</persName> stated that the matter was under consideration by
                            the Operations Coordinating Board; an <gloss target="#t_OCB1"
                                >OCB</gloss> working group had recommended adoption of the proposal
                            for U.S. support of a Chinese Nationalist food offer. (<gloss
                                target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> files, lot 62 D 430, “China
                            (Communist)”)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
