<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-08T23:10:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-08T23:10:00-05:00" n="284" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d284">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.00/9–1454</note>
                            <head>No. 284<lb/><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">President</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary
                                        of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d284fn1">Teletype
                                    message; filed with a memorandum of Sept. 14 from <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                        secret<lb/>priority</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Denver</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-08T21:10:00-07:00">September 8, 1954—9:10
                                        p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>In spite of all our current preoccupations in the European
                                difficulties, I think it most important that we have the assurance
                                that there is going to be no possibility of driving a wedge between
                                ourselves and our principal European allies, especially Britain, in
                                any action we may be forced to take. I cannot over-emphasize how
                                deeply I believe this to be true. The matter was brought to my mind
                                with special force because of the recent incident in the Sea of
                                Japan and <persName corresp="#p_KSWF1">Knowland</persName>’s public
                                statement with respect to it.<note n="2" xml:id="d284fn2">Reference
                                    is to a telegram of Sept. 5 from <persName corresp="#p_KSWF1">Knowland</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>, which <persName corresp="#p_KSWF1">Knowland</persName> released to the press on the same day,
                                    urging a break in diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union.
                                    For text of the telegram, see the <hi rend="italic">New York
                                        Times</hi>, Sept. 6, 1954.</note></p>
                            <p>The reading of <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>’s
                                summary of the convictions of the British Laborite<note n="3" xml:id="d284fn3">See <ref target="#d280fn3">footnote 3, Document
                                        280</ref>.</note> only serves to underscore this great need.
                                What <pb facs="0606" n="578" xml:id="pg_578"/> would you think of a
                                telegram to <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Winston
                                    [Churchill</persName>] somewhat along the following lines:
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Dear <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Winston</persName>:</p>
                                    <p>I think that when you seized the opportunity to send your
                                        recent message to Adenauer,<note n="4" xml:id="d284fn4">For
                                            text of the message from <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> to West German Chancellor
                                            Konrad Adenauer, see the letter from <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>, Sept. 3,
                                                <ref target="frus1952-54v05p2#pg_1144">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, Part 2, p. 1144</ref>.
                                            Adenauer’s response is not printed.</note> you took
                                        action that may yet save to us many of the advantages we
                                        hoped to gain in Europe through <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>. I was delighted also to see the reasonable
                                        and cooperative spirit that Adenauer showed in his
                                        reply.</p>
                                    <p>While all these things go on, we can not afford to forget
                                        that all along the Eastern edge of Asia, from the Bering Sea
                                        to Indonesia, there is a constantly boiling kettle of
                                        possible trouble. Incidents of small and large magnitude
                                        constantly occur, and at any moment one or both of us could
                                        be confronted with a situation that would require from us
                                        clear-cut and even decisive action. The presence of this
                                        kind of risk serves to emphasize again the great truth that
                                        the free world cannot possibly prosper should there be any
                                        major cleavage between yourselves and ourselves. Of course
                                        we should always like France, Germany and our other European
                                        friends and—indeed—all non-Iron Curtain countries to stand
                                        shoulder to shoulder with us in any conceivable crisis. But
                                        the foundation of multiple-lateral action must be the
                                        closest of understanding and purpose between Britain and
                                        America.</p>
                                    <p>An awkward situation arises out of the fact that some years
                                        ago your government recognized Red China while we clung, and
                                        still cling, to the theory that the Communist ruling clique
                                        there is a conspiracy and is not a government in the
                                        civilized meaning of the word. As a result of this
                                        divergence, we might conceivably have great difficulty in
                                        concerting our policies and actions in the event that there
                                        should begin an aggression out of continental China against
                                        Formosa. This matter troubles me much because I am certain
                                        that American public opinion overwhelmingly favors any
                                        necessary action on our part to make certain of the defeat
                                        of any such attempt. I must say also that I believe that
                                        America is morally bound to take such action under these
                                        circumstances and that it would be definitely in the
                                        interests of the whole free world to do so.</p>
                                    <p>Where do you think your government would stand in such a
                                        contingency? I assure you that I do not expect you to give
                                        me an answer that would be considered a commitment on the
                                        part of your government. But if you and I should find that
                                        our thinking ran somewhat parallel upon these momentous
                                        possibilities, then we might arrange to put some of our
                                        trusted advisers together to study the matter further—even
                                        to include the methods by which we could induce other allies
                                        to share our convictions and our attitudes. With warm
                                        personal regard, Signed Ike.”</p></quote></p>
                            <p>I am asking Mrs. <persName>Whitman</persName> to read this to you
                                over the White House phone this evening because I would like to know
                                whether you approve in general of the effort and the general tenor
                                of my <pb facs="0607" n="579" xml:id="pg_579"/> presentation. If you
                                so agree, she will send the whole thing to you by teletype—after
                                which you can edit it, and if you think necessary, call me back
                                before dispatching. I think it should go as a Top Secret telegram to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Winston</persName>. I thought at one
                                time of sending this as a Secret letter in the pouch so that no one
                                aside from yourself would know its contents, but I have since
                                decided that if it has any virtue at all, our own Ambassador in
                                London and <persName corresp="#p_ESA1">Anthony [Eden]</persName>
                                should both know of its contents. Signed <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName>.<note n="5" xml:id="d284fn5">A
                                    memorandum of Sept. 8 from <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_SWB1">Smith</persName> reported that <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> thought it would be inadvisable to
                                    send a message to <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> until the President had made a
                                    decision regarding the defense of the offshore islands. A
                                    memorandum of Sept. 14 from <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> reads: “I am inclined to think that
                                    it would be better to hold this up for the time being. If the
                                    inquiry were put, I think it might lead to a counter inquiry as
                                    to our intentions and that until we have explored further the
                                    suggestion which I made at the Denver <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting [on Sept. 12], it is better not to
                                    expose ourselves to this line of questioning.” (Both
                                    793.00/9–1454)</note></p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>