<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 362Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of Chinese
                    Affairs (McConaughy)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d362</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">362</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-10-27T10:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-10-27T10:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-10-27T10:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-10-27T10:30:00-05:00" n="362"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d362">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.5/10–2754</note>
                <head>No. 362<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the Office of
                        Chinese Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MWP1">McConaughy</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-10-27T10:30:00-05:00"
                            >October 27, 1954—10:30 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>1. New Zealand Resolution.</item>
                    <item>2. Mutual Defense Treaty.</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KDVKW1">V.K. Wellington Koo</persName>, Chinese
                        Ambassador</item>
                    <item>Foreign Minister, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">George Yeh</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Walter S. Robertson</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary for <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MWP1">Walter P. McConaughy</persName>, Director
                        for <gloss target="#t_CA1">CA</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Limited distribution. Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1"
                        >Yeh</persName> referred to the Chinese memorandum of October 23<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d362fn1">This memorandum, with a covering note from Ambassador
                            <persName corresp="#p_KDVKW1">Koo</persName>, was delivered to the
                        Department on Oct. 23. (793.00/10–2354)</note> setting forth the Chinese
                    position in regard to the New Zealand resolution. He said that he would be
                    grateful if the Department could reply informally in writing to the Chinese
                    memorandum, so that he could make appropriate recommendations to his Government
                    on the basis of the written U.S. reaction.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he would prefer to wait a day or so before expressing any
                    further views. There are certain aspects of the matter which are still under
                    consideration. He hoped that it might be possible to start serious talks with
                    the Chinese representatives about the 29th. He confirmed that the United States
                    wanted to work out a Mutual Security Treaty, as the Generalissimo had been
                    informed. The question of how to specify the area to be protected was causing
                    some difficulty. Obviously it could not be said that every little island dot off
                    the coast of China, if taken by the Chinese Communists, would represent a danger
                    to peace and security. There are good reasons for considering the defense of
                    Formosa and the Pescadores important to the security of the United States. But
                    the United States cannot commit itself to fight for the retention of the
                    off-shore islands by the Chinese Government. At the same time the U.S. does not
                    want to leave them vulnerable to Chinese <pb facs="0826" n="798" xml:id="pg_798"
                    /> Communist attack. The Department is wrestling with this problem at the
                    moment. Meetings are taking place with the responsible people from the Pentagon.
                    All are thinking hard about the problem, but a minimum of 48 hours is needed for
                    [all?] to think the problem through and obtain necessary clearances. It should
                    be possible to start serious talks early next week, if not during this week-end.
                    Insuperable obstacles might be encountered, but we hope not. He said he has been
                    exploring all the angles of the problem since his talk with the Generalissimo in
                    Taipei. He has worked hard on the difficult aspects. The question is very much
                    on his mind. The Foreign Minister might be needed back in Washington in a day or
                    so.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said that he had
                    to return to New York on the 28th. He could return to Washington any time after
                    the 29th. He hoped that the Chinese position was made clear in the memorandum of
                    October 23. He feared that the New Zealand Government might have under-estimated
                    the implications and connotations of its proposed resolution. The Chinese
                    Government would be willing to go along with the resolution if the undesirable
                    implications and connotations were eliminated. He observed that in the Chinese
                    view the resolution would not give actual protection to the off-shore islands.
                    If the resolution were rejected by the Communists, the aggressive Communist
                    attitude might help the moral position of the Chinese Government. But the
                    adverse factors must be weighed against the possible moral benefit.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said the Foreign Minister could be sure that the Department is
                    studying the whole question with a sympathetic understanding of the Chinese
                    Government’s point of view. He would prefer to wait about two days before saying
                    anything more specific. Any time after Friday would probably be suitable. The
                    Secretary added that the subject was very touchy politically. Of course, there
                    was a group of senators quite dedicated to anything which would help the Chinese
                    Government position. But actually this group constituted a minority of the
                    Senate. It might be important to know the result of the elections on November 2
                    before proceeding. If Republican control of the Senate were retained, the
                    Administration would be off to a good start and might get prompt action on a
                    Treaty. But if the Democrats won control of the Senate, there would be a change
                    in those to be consulted. Such a shift might delay action on Treaty matters. He
                    hoped to get action started at once on a rounded program, of which the proposed
                    Treaty would be a part. He hoped that the program would substantially meet the
                    Foreign Minister’s wishes and strengthen the position of his Government. He
                    recalled that he had told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KDVKW1"
                        >Koo</persName> that a Defense Treaty might tend to weaken the position of
                    the Chinese Government <pb facs="0827" n="799" xml:id="pg_799"/> in some
                    respects, since it could apply only to Formosa and the Pescadores. He remembered
                    that the Generalissimo had maintained that appropriate language could readily be
                    worked out to solve this problem. However, he had not received any concrete
                    suggestion along this line from the Generalissimo. He was studying the matter
                    closely anyway.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> asked if Treaty
                    talks should get under way before the election.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he thought it might be possible to start talks during the
                    coming weekend.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> pointed out that it would
                    not seem desirable to make any announcement regarding any prospective Treaty
                    before the election.</p>
                <p>The Secretary emphatically agreed, but he thought that private talks with the
                    Foreign Minister might start before the election. In any event it would take two
                    or three days to consult President <persName corresp="#p_CKSG1"
                        >Chiang</persName> in Taipei.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said that of
                    course he recognized that the application of the operative clause of the Treaty
                    would have to be limited to some extent. He suggested that the original draft
                    Treaty submitted by the Chinese Government last December<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d362fn2">See <ref target="#d161fn2">footnote 2, Document
                        161</ref>.</note> might be used as a tentative basis for the initial
                    discussions. He appreciated that changes must be made. He said that even his own
                    Government would not wish to stand pat on the language it proposed at that time.
                    He thought his Government would have some changes to suggest. The Chinese
                    position was by no means inflexible.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that both sides must be flexible and think in practical terms.
                    It would be impossible to obtain ratification of a Treaty which might
                    automatically draw the United States into war with Communist China.</p>
                <p>The Foreign Minister said that his Government did not want to force the United
                    States into war with Communist China and would not propose Treaty language
                    designed to embroil the United States with Communist China.</p>
                <p>The Secretary remarked that the problem of drafting appropriate Treaty language
                    could not be lightly brushed aside. It was extremely hard to solve.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said that the
                    Treaty could not stand by itself.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> agreed. The two
                    Governments must have an understanding on many things. This added to the
                    difficulty.</p>
                <pb facs="0828" n="800" xml:id="pg_800"/>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said the Treaty
                    would have the advantage of affording a more permanent relationship. But other
                    arrangements were needed also.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> noted that there was a
                    grave constitutional question as to how long the President could keep the order
                    to the 7th Fleet in force. The original order of President <persName
                        corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> could be justified under the “war
                    powers” of the President. But after the Korean Armistice there is a question as
                    to the President’s authority in the absence of a Joint Resolution of Congress,
                    or a Treaty ratified by the Senate. Legally the President acting independently
                    of Congress might not have the power to determine that the defense of Formosa
                    and the Pescadores is vital to the peace and security of the United States. The
                    legal right of the President to direct the 7th Fleet to defend Formosa without
                    Congressional sanction was being eroded with the lapse of time. The Attorney
                    General might find that the President lacks constitutional authority to continue
                    the order to the 7th Fleet. <persName corresp="#p_KSWF1">Senator
                        Knowland</persName> has expressed the view that Congress would be reluctant
                    to pass in advance a Joint Resolution giving this authority to the President.
                    Congress does not like to give “a blank check”. If the President waits until an
                    emergency arises and then seeks Congressional backing, the approval might come
                    too late. Emergency powers do not last forever. The question is how to replace
                    the 7th Fleet order with something not based on emergency powers. The United
                    States Government does not want any gap in its defense arrangements. The
                    off-shore island chain extends from the Aleutians through Japan and the Ryukyus,
                    Formosa and the Philippines to Australia and New Zealand. Formosa is the only
                    place in this chain not covered by defense provisions of undoubted validity. The
                    United States does not want a gap in the chain any more than the Chinese
                    Government does. The United States is working hard to find an answer along the
                    lines of a Treaty.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said that last
                    February he wrote down some thoughts on the matter. At that time he doubted the
                    constitutional position of the President. This was one of the reasons for a
                    Treaty which he listed in a letter to Vice President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >Nixon</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d362fn3">Presumably the letter
                        transmitted in telegram 360, <ref target="#d162">Document 162</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> then said that he
                    wished to make a statement which must be put most precisely: <list>
                        <label>a)</label>
                        <item>The Chinese Government does not have the slightest intention of making
                            a Treaty with the United States serve as a basis for action against the
                            mainland of China.</item>
                        <label>b)</label>
                        <item>There is no intention on the part of the Chinese Government to involve
                            the United States in war with Communist China.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0829" n="801" xml:id="pg_801"/>
                <p>The Foreign Minister said “I mean this Mr. Secretary, and I think you can trust
                    me”.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he did believe and accept the assurances of the Foreign
                    Minister.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said on the other
                    hand his Government wanted to be certain that the Treaty did not confine its
                    sovereignty to Formosa and the Pescadores. Such a limitation would be
                    unacceptable both politically and psychologically. The Chinese Government
                    position rests on two pillars: 1) its strength for defense, and 2) its hope for
                    return to the mainland. The reference to “hope” might sound far fetched,
                    but—</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> interrupted to say that
                    the reference was not at all far fetched. He recognized its importance. It was
                    his view that despotisms such as the one now ruling the mainland of China are
                    not permanent. They run counter to the nature and aspirations of humanity. They
                    often have a seemingly impregnable exterior but inside they are full of
                    rottenness. We did not fully realize the truth of this generalization as applied
                    to Nazi Germany until after the war we got into the secret wartime diaries and
                    letters of the Nazi leaders. When they seemed so invulnerable in the war years,
                    we know now they had already begun to crumble. Powerful leaders in a
                    dictatorship may be liquidated very abruptly, as happened in the case of Beria
                    last year. It is not unrealistic to envisage the possibility of a sudden
                    unexpected collapse of a ruthless dictatorial regime. We would want to be ready,
                    if the opportunity comes, to take immediate advantage of it. The opportunity
                    might come in one year or in 5 years. No one could tell. The Secretary said he
                    recognized that Formosa must not become an island prison for Free Chinese. On
                    the other hand it would be folly to kill the chances of success by moving
                    prematurely. He thought that if the Chinese Nationalists should try an invasion
                    today, they would probably be destroyed. He assumed that the Chinese Government
                    agreed that it did not have the capability at present for large-scale offensive
                    action.</p>
                <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_YGKCYK1">Yeh</persName> said that the
                    assumption was of course correct. He mentioned that the Chinese Government had
                    already given a firm commitment not to mount any attack—even a large-scale raid
                    or commando-type operation—without first obtaining U.S. consent. The Chinese
                    Government had scrupulously lived up to this commitment and would continue to do
                    so.</p>
                <p>The conversation ended at about 11:10 a.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
