<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-22T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-22T03:00:00-05:00" n="37" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d37">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.00/7–2252: Telegram</note>
                            <head>No. 37<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Republic of China
                                        (<persName corresp="#p_JHP1" type="from">Jones</persName>)
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Taipei</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-22T17:00:00+09:00">July 22, 1952—5
                                    p.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>77. Admiral <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName> had
                                private conversation with President <persName corresp="#p_CKSG1">Chiang</persName> Sunday July 20 at occasion of dinner given in
                                his honor by Generalissimo. I was present at invitation of
                                Generalissimo.</p>
                            <p>Conversation resulted in suggestion by Generalissimo “speaking as a
                                friend to friend” that Chinese troops be used to invade Chinese
                                mainland, with only matériel support from US, Generalissimo arguing
                                this would be mere civil war and would not precipitate world
                                conflict. Chinese military would need planes and ships and logistic
                                support but he insisted no US personnel need be involved in combat
                                operation which Generalissimo estimated could be conducted at
                                one-third dollar cost of Korea.</p>
                            <p>Fukien-Amoy coast is not yet well-defended, Generalissimo said,
                                although cities of Shanghai and Canton are. Plan has been worked out
                                in detail for assault on coast which he offered to have shown to
                                Admiral <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName>.</p>
                            <p>Implication in Generalissimo’s remarks on coastal defense was that
                                time was of essence but subsequent discussions by Admiral <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName> with [apparent omission]
                                action in near future could be contemplated in view equipment and
                                training required. Plans for assault on Amoy were shown last night
                                to Admiral <persName corresp="#p_FAWM1">Fechteler</persName> and
                                General <persName corresp="#p_CMGWC1">Chase</persName> both of whom
                                convinced tremendous amount preparatory work required before
                                operation could be considered feasible.</p>
                            <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CMGWC1">Chase</persName> further
                                considers totally impracticable large-scale amphibious assault with
                                present state equipment and training Chinese Armed Forces. Such
                                operation in his opinion would require in foreseeable future
                                substantial support from US Navy and Air Force and complete logistic
                                support in addition to assistance and advice in planning.</p>
                            <pb facs="0105" n="77" xml:id="pg_77"/>
                            <p>Evident Generalissimo letting loose trial balloon but possible one
                                meriting some consideration if sober analysis substantiates his
                                contention as to Chinese capabilities.</p>
                            <p>Generalissimo also expressed himself as strongly in favor blockade of
                                Chinese coast and bombing of Manchuria bases in event of failure
                                truce efforts Korea which he believes inevitable.</p>
                            <p>Despatch follows.<note n="1" xml:id="d37fn1">Despatch 35 from Taipei,
                                    July 25, not printed.</note></p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JHP1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Jones</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>