<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 413Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Economic
                    Affairs (Kalijarvi) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v14p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d413</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">413</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="413"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d413">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files,
                    lot 63 D 351, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5429 Series</note>
                <head>No. 413<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Economic Affairs (<persName type="from">Kalijarvi</persName>) to the <gloss
                            type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-11-29">November 29,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Current U.S. Policy in the Far East (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            5429/3)<note n="1" xml:id="d413fn1">
                            <ref target="#d397">Document 397</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Background:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The subject paper has been overtaken by recent events which raise major
                    international political problems and make it clear that <pb facs="0986" n="958"
                        xml:id="pg_958"/> no revision in or review of controls applicable to trade
                    with Communist China can be undertaken at present. The problem raised by the
                    higher level of controls applicable to Communist China as compared with the
                    European Soviet bloc remains a troublesome one which should, however, be dealt
                    with as soon as the general political situation permits. In this connection, you
                    will wish to know that at the recent Economic Defense Officers’ conference held
                    in Paris the week of November 15, the missions represented unanimously reported
                    that our insistence on holding to a multilateral level of control for Communist
                    China which is higher than that for Eastern Europe is driving us into a
                    negotiating position of increasing isolation and undermining our ability to
                    exert leadership in other matters. The mission representatives particularly
                    urged that the United States be careful to avoid a procedure, whenever the China
                    policy has been reviewed and a course set, of negotiating solely with the
                    British and French and coming then to the other participating countries with a
                    predetermined tripartite position.</p>
                <p>The following general conclusions of the Economic Defense Officers’ conference on
                    the subject of China trade controls may be of interest: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <list>
                            <item>“1. A review of the US policy regarding trade with China should be
                                undertaken urgently, but it is desirable that this be undertaken in
                                the light of a reappraisal of our overall China policy.</item>
                            <item>“2. The higher level and broader scope of the China trade controls
                                in the past have not been shown to have been of more than marginal
                                utility in impeding the industrial and military build up of
                                China.</item>
                            <item>“3. The pressure from our allies for the adjustment of the level
                                of trade controls with China stems more from political than economic
                                reasons, except in the case of Japan where acute economic problems
                                are involved.</item>
                            <item>“4. A completely isolated position from its allies by the United
                                States on the question of China trade controls will detract from the
                                effectiveness of its leadership in other matters.</item>
                            <item>“5. A dual level of trade controls for China and for the European
                                Soviet bloc countries can be simplified for smoother operation, but
                                practical measures for preventing frustration of the tighter China
                                controls have not yet been devised.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that there be no relaxation in trade controls applicable to
                    Communist China at this time in the light of recent events and in the interest
                    of maintaining maximum pressures on that area, and therefore that the National
                    Security Council should not consider the revision of trade controls toward
                    Communist China until the current situation becomes clarified.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
