<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-05-02T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-05-02T10:00:00-05:00" n="100" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">868.76/10: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Goold</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-05-02T17:00:00+02:00">May 2, 1929—5
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 5:55 p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>34. Your 20, April 29, 6 p.m. I am in receipt of a letter from Mr.
                            Venizelos in reply to mine transmitting greetings of Mr. Skinner. The
                            principal part states that the Minister of Communications informs him
                            that he has already decided to give the concession to Marconi and that
                            he cannot go back on his decision. As the decision must also be approved
                            by a technical commission he adds that it is only in the event that this
                            council has not approved the concession that the matter could be
                            examined again and the proposals of the American concern taken into
                            consideration.</p>
                        <pb facs="0229" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/>
                        <p>I learn from Akilloglou, Durham’s agent, that on Monday the Minister of
                            Communications referred question to technical board which is expected to
                            hand down decision in a few days. Today, however, fearing a few members
                            adverse to Marconi, Minister ordered case to be presented to technical
                            council of Ministry of Communications at six o’clock this afternoon.</p>
                        <p>I am sending note to Mr. Venizelos, who left Athens this morning for the
                            five Easter holidays, requesting him to postpone further hearings before
                            either commission until arrival of Mr. Durham. This letter will be
                            handed to Mr. Tsibidaros, chief of the Prime Minister’s political
                            bureau, who will be asked to communicate it to Mr. Venizelos.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Goold</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>