<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-12-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="221" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d221">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Message of the President of the United States to
                                Congress, December 7, 1929</hi><note n="27" type="source" xml:id="d221fn27">Reprinted from H. Rept. 39, 71st Cong., 2d sess.,
                                p. 1.</note></head>
                        <p>In my message to Congress of the 3d instant<note n="28" xml:id="d221fn28"><ref target="frus1929v01#pg_V">Vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi></ref>.</note> I
                            indicated my concern as to the future of our policies in Haiti. I stated
                            that we have there about 700 marines, and that we are confronted with a
                            difficult problem, the solution of which is still obscure. I further
                            stated that if Congress approves I shall dispatch a commission to Haiti
                            to review and study the matter in an endeavor to arrive at some more
                            definite policy than at present.</p>
                        <p>Our representatives in Haiti have shown great ability and devotion, and
                            have accomplished signal results in improvement of the material
                            condition of that people. Yet our experience has revealed more clearly
                            than was seen at first the difficulties of the problem, and the entire
                            situation should be reviewed in the light of this experience.</p>
                        <p>Since the dispatch of my message disturbances in Haiti emphasize the
                            importance of such an investigation and determination of national
                            policies in the immediate future.</p>
                        <p>The students at the agricultural school at Damien went on a strike on
                            October 31 as a protest against a new policy of the Haitian Government.
                            The Haitian Government has heretofore allotted $10,000 per annum to this
                            school for scholarships, but this year it withheld $2,000 of the
                            appropriation in order to make it possible for needy students to perform
                            practical school work on the grounds. Sympathetic strikes were
                            subsequently declared in the medical and law schools. President Borno
                            appointed a committee of Haitians to inquire into the matter and it
                            seemed probable at the time that recommendations presented by this
                            committee and accepted by the authorities would adjust the difficulty.
                            Unfortunately, advantage was taken of the situation by various agencies
                            to foment disturbances against the Haitian administration, and on
                            December 3 the American high commissioner reported that the strike
                            movement had spread <pb facs="0326" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/> throughout
                            the country and that it was feared that the Haitian employees of the
                            departments under American treaty officials might become involved.</p>
                        <p>On December 4 customhouse employees at Port au Prince abandoned their
                            work in a disorderly manner and crowds have gathered in Port au Prince.
                            At the same time there were reported demonstrations by crowds at Cape
                            Haitien in sympathy with the disturbance in Port au Prince. The American
                            high commissioner reported that on the morning of December 4 it was
                            feared that disorderly conditions would arise at Aux Cayes and similar
                            disturbances were possible at other places.</p>
                        <p>The high commissioner has asked that additional marines be in readiness
                            to make sure that if the situation becomes serious American lives will
                            be protected, and the force he has suggested has been ordered dispatched
                            for that purpose.</p>
                        <p>I feel that it is most desirable that the commission mentioned in my
                            message of December 3 be constituted and sent to Haiti without delay,
                            and I therefore request the Congress to authorize the immediate sending
                            of such a commission and to appropriate for this purpose $50,000. It is
                            my intention to include one or two members from each House of Congress
                            on this commission.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Herbert Hoover</hi></signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">The White
                                        House</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-12-07">December 7, 1929</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>