<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-08-14T16:44:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-08-14T16:44:00-05:00" n="316" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d316">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">882.5048/59: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Liberia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wharton</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Monrovia</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-08-14T21:00:00-00:44">August 14, 1929—9
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received August 14—2:34 p.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>40. Referring to Legation’s No. 39, August 9, 2 p.m.; and Department’s
                            No. 30 [<hi rend="italic">29</hi>], August 3, noon, particular reference
                            to paragraph (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) and numbered 2.</p>
                        <p>Secretary of State orally advises that the Liberian Government feels that
                            this paragraph should read: “To what extent compulsory labor exists as a
                            factor in the social and industrial economy of the state either for
                            public or private purposes.”</p>
                        <pb facs="0416" n="298" xml:id="pg_298"/>
                        <p>He states that second clause of Department’s emendation seems to carry
                            with it a conclusion of fact the existence of which is actually the
                            purpose of the Commission’s inquiry and that his Government believed
                            that paragraph (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) as quoted above with the words
                            “public or private purposes” is sufficiently broad in scope to enable
                            the Commission to inquire into all recruitment and employment of alleged
                            compulsory labor for public and private purposes. He adds that the other
                            emendation[s] are all right in principle and he made no comment.</p>
                        <p>Upon receiving Department’s reply, terms of reference will be concluded
                            and the Liberian Government will request Department recommend a member
                            and request to League of Nations by Liberia direct.</p>
                        <p>[Paraphrase.] I have heard of the Liberian Government’s endeavor to be
                            represented at the League of Nations by a Spaniard,<note n="21" xml:id="d316fn21">The arrangement contemplated was the naming of a
                                Spaniard by the League of Nations to serve on the Commission of
                                Inquiry.</note> and from a reliable source I learn that the Liberian
                            Government has authorized the payment of its fees to the League of
                            Nations, some $4000, which practically takes up all of the unassigned
                            revenues on hand. [End paraphrase.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wharton</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>