<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-03-06T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-03-06T20:00:00-05:00" n="383" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d383">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">812.00Sonora/103: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Morrow</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-03-06T19:00:00-06:00">March 6, 1929—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received March 7—7:27 a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                        <p>67. Minister Estrada informed Colonel MacNab that the Mexican Government
                            desired to purchase certain arms and ammunition from the American
                            Government and that he was sending two army officers to confer with
                            MacNab as to what request to make. These officers stated that the
                            Mexican Government desires to know if it can secure from the United
                            States Government ten thousand rifles preferably Springfields and if not
                            Springfields then Enfields and also ten million rounds of ammunition
                            preferably of recent manufacture for these rifles. This will be in
                            substitution of the seven millimeter rifles referred to in my 54, March
                            4, 10 p.m. The Mexican Government would be glad to know at once the
                            prices and conditions of payment. If purchase is made immediately,
                            delivery will be desired probably through Tampico.</p>
                        <p>The Mexican Government advises us that in addition to the nine airplanes,
                            all ordered from the Chance Vought Company and referred to in our 25,
                            February 18, 4 p.m., they will desire five additional pursuit planes and
                            that it will also desire bombs for these planes. They are making inquiry
                            of various airplane manufacturers in the United States but if more
                            prompt delivery can be secured from our Government they will probably
                            desire to arrange a purchase of these five planes directly from our
                            Government.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Morrow</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>