<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-07-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-07-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="48" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">867n.156/8</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Jerusalem</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Heizer</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Jerusalem</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-07-24">July 24, 1928</date>.<lb/>[Received August
                                15.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1814</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report to the
                            Department that according to information received from London the
                            construction of the Harbor Works at Haifa is not to be undertaken by the
                            Government of Palestine as originally intended, but is to be built by
                            contract. The Government expresses the hope that it will be possible to
                            have the tenders submitted by the end of November, 1928.</p>
                        <p>For the construction of this harbor at Haifa over five million dollars
                            have been set aside from the recent loan contracted by the Government of
                            Palestine.</p>
                        <p>It is believed that American contractors may wish to make tenders for the
                            work. Specifications have been asked for and as soon as obtained will be
                            forwarded to the Department.</p>
                        <p>The following particulars are published with regard to the harbor at
                            Haifa which it is now reported is to be built by contract.</p>
                        <pb facs="0180" n="62" xml:id="pg_62"/>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“The Harbor is to be formed by a breakwater 8000 feet in length,
                                running N. W. by S. E. from Ras el Krum point. The existing jetty
                                will be extended towards the end of the breakwater. The breakwater
                                is to be built of local stone quarried in the neighborhood of
                                Athlit.</p>
                            <p>Within the area of approximately 200 acres thus enclosed, vessels of
                                30 feet draught will be protected against gales and bad weather.
                                Berthing facilities will be provided along the inside of the
                                breakwater for about two thirds of its length, and, when the use of
                                the Harbor warrants it, the 6000 feet of shore frontage will also be
                                developed for quayage.</p>
                            <p>The ultimate development of the scheme will therefore give nearly
                                12,000 feet of berthage.</p>
                            <p>The task of determining the best alignment of the quays and
                                breakwaters is a difficult and lengthy operation. A large number of
                                borings are being made. Most of these borings have to be taken from
                                floating craft and owing to rough weather the work has been much
                                delayed.</p>
                            <p>Serious difficulties have also been met in finding a suitable site at
                                which to establish a quarry for the stone required in the
                                construction of the breakwaters. The whole country within twenty
                                miles of the harbor site has been explored and trial excavations
                                have been made at many places. The possible sites have now been
                                limited to two and the final choice depends on investigations which
                                are now proceeding into the comparative cost of quarrying and
                                transport of stone at the two sites.</p>
                            <p>Government will also consider in the light of all the facts that will
                                become available during the course of this summer what is the best
                                method of construction.</p>
                            <p>In spite of all difficulties it is expected that the final plans will
                                be ready by the autumn and it is hoped that the work of construction
                                will be put in hand before the end of this year.”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <p>File No. 815.6</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Oscar S. Heizer</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>