<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Mexico ( (Morrow) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d539</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">539</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-08-15T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-08-15T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-08-15T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-08-15T19:00:00-05:00" n="539"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d539">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">411.12/955: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Morrow</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-08-15T18:00:00-06:00"
                            >August 15, 1929—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received August 16—3:22 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>312. That the Department may be informed I have the honor to report as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>On Monday August 12 I saw Secretary Estrada and pointed out to him the
                    desirability of concluding the conventions extending the two claims commissions
                    before the present conventions expired. As I told you in my 307 of August
                        9th,<note n="15" xml:id="d539fn15">Not printed.</note> President Portes Gil
                    is out of the city. The Secretary again promised to consult the President as
                    soon as he should return.</p>
                <p>Not hearing from Estrada on Tuesday, August 13th, I again conferred with him on
                    Wednesday, August 14th, at which time I once more urged the necessity for a
                    prompt signature of the conventions extending the claims conventions. Estrada
                    expressed then a view which he has several times voiced to the effect that the
                    conventions would be extended and that the mere date of extending them was more
                    or less immaterial. Upon returning from this interview Clark telephoned Lane
                    advising him that Estrada had asked Tellez to raise three points concerning the
                    extension of the special claims commission.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>First, that he wished to have the extension of the special claims
                        convention signed here in Mexico City.</item>
                    <item>Second, that he desired an informal understanding that the future sessions
                        of the special claims commission should be held in Mexico City.</item>
                    <item>Third, an informal understanding that the presiding commissioner should be
                        chosen in accordance with the Pan-American arbitration agreement of last
                        January.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I understood Estrada’s position to be that the signing of the extending
                    convention was not conditioned upon our agreeing to these <pb facs="0564"
                        n="446" xml:id="pg_446"/> three matters but that he desired to present them
                    and if possible secure an understanding covering them.</p>
                <p>Lane later in the same afternoon, August 14th, telephoned Clark that he had
                    reached Tellez by telephone and that the Ambassador stated his instructions were
                    to sign both the general and special extension conventions in Washington and
                    that he had received a wire stating that his full powers were en route. Lane
                    also stated that the Department had already advised Tellez as set out in the
                    Department’s 437 of August 8, 6 p.m., that the Department felt it would be
                    advisable to defer making a decision as to a choice of the presiding
                    commissioner until the conventions were actually extended and that the
                    Undersecretary had told Tellez that the Undersecretary apprehended no difficulty
                    on this score. Lane also stated that Tellez had not presented to the Department
                    the matter of holding the sessions of the Special Claims Commission in Mexico
                    City.</p>
                <p>A memorandum was made of the foregoing conversation between Lane and Clark which
                        Dawson<note n="17" xml:id="d539fn17">Allan Dawson, Third Secretary of
                        Embassy.</note> took to Estrada later in the afternoon of the 14th and upon
                    which Estrada commented as follows: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>That he had that afternoon telephoned the President at Tehuacan on the
                            subject of the general claims convention and that it was possible
                            something might be done about this before the departure of the
                            Ambassador on Saturday.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>That in Estrada’s instructions to Tellez he had mentioned only the
                            signing of the general claims convention in Washington, it having always
                            been Estrada’s desire to have the special claims convention signed in
                            Mexico. Full powers to sign the general claims convention had been
                            forwarded to Tellez but he had no authorization to sign the special
                            claims convention.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>That, in a long telegram sent by Estrada to Tellez some time ago,
                            Tellez was instructed to take up among certain other subjects the
                            question of holding the meetings of the Special Claims Commission in
                            Mexico City. Estrada observed that in view of the length of the telegram
                            perhaps Tellez had overlooked this point.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Today, August 15, at 4 p.m. Lane telephoned Clark that Lane had seen Tellez and
                    had told Tellez that we were agreeable to holding the meetings of the special
                    claims commission in Mexico City and that Tellez had brought up the further
                    point with reference to the Special Claims Commission, namely, that the
                    jurisdiction of the existing Special Claims Commission should be modified to
                    accord with paragraph “a” of article 2 of the Pan American arbitration
                    convention, signed in Washington last January.</p>
                <p>Clark and Dawson saw Estrada at 5 p.m. today, August 15. They informed Estrada
                    that the United States was willing to hold the meetings of the Special Claims
                    Commission in Mexico City. After reading the report of a telephone conversation
                    between Sierra and Tellez of <pb facs="0565" n="447" xml:id="pg_447"/> today
                    Estrada dictated in the presence of Clark and Dawson a telegram the purport of
                    which is as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Accepting the offer of the American Government to discuss the details of
                            the convention relating to organization, functioning, etc., you, Tellez,
                            are authorized herewith to sign the extension of the special claims
                            convention.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>It would thus appear that whatever Tellez’s authority has heretofore been he now
                    has authority to sign both conventions at Washington. Estrada did not mention
                    and Clark and Dawson did not mention the point last raised by Tellez covering
                    the modification of the jurisdiction of the special claims convention.</p>
                <p>No answer has yet been received by Estrada from President Portes Gil regarding
                    the letter (see our 306 of August 6 as modified by your 435, August 7) that is
                    to accompany the signature of the extension of the general claims
                    convention.</p>
                <p>The President’s office telephoned at 6 p.m. that the President, Portes Gil, will
                    probably return to Mexico City on Saturday or Sunday.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Morrow</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
