<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of a Conference Held at 4 P.M., July 31, 1929, Regarding the
                    Turtle Islands Boundary Negotiations</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">56</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-07-31T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-07-31T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-07-31T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-07-31T15:00:00-05:00" n="56"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.4115A/60</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of a Conference Held at 4 P.M., July 31, 1929,
                        Regarding the Turtle Islands Boundary Negotiations</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1929-07-31T16:00:00-04:00">July
                        31, 1929, 4 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi>: <list>
                            <item>Mr. J. A. Metzger,</item>
                            <item>Mr. J. K. Caldwell</item>
                            <item>Mr. T. A. Shone, First Secretary of the British Embassy,</item>
                            <item>Mr. F. W. Fraser.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Shone submitted certain changes which he proposed be made in the American
                    draft treaty, and also submitted a draft of the proposed British note providing
                    for the continued administration of the Turtle and Mangsi Islands by the British
                    North Borneo Company. After some discussion, it was mutually agreed that certain
                    changes be made in the drafts submitted by Mr. Shone and that the treaty and the
                    note in the form finally agreed upon be typed up as soon as possible, in the
                    Department of State, and that copies would be sent to Mr. Shone for submission
                    to the British Ambassador. It was also agreed that copies would be submitted to
                    General McIntyre and to the Secretary and that a final meeting of the British
                    and American representatives should take place on Friday, August 2, at 10:00
                    o’clock.</p>
                <p>Mr. Shone also requested that he be given a copy of pages 4 and 5 of the
                    memorandum of the Geographer of the Department, dated July 26, 1929,<note n="80"
                        xml:id="d56fn80">Not printed.</note> dealing with possible changes which
                    might be necessitated by subsequent more accurate surveys, in order that he may
                    submit this matter to the British Ambassador for consideration of the
                    advisability of incorporating some such provision in the treaty.</p>
                <p>Copies of the treaty and of the British note as redrafted on the meeting on July
                    31 are attached hereto.<note n="81" xml:id="d56fn81">Neither printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It was proposed by Mr. Shone that the treaty be completed in final form, so far
                    as the negotiators can do so, at the meeting on Friday morning (tomorrow) August
                    2nd, after which the British would like to submit the text to the Foreign
                    Office, since there is no urgency about the signing in view of the arrangement
                    that the administration be continued by the British North Borneo Company. Mr.
                    Fraser would return home, and the treaty would be signed later.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. K. C[<hi rend="smallcaps">aldwell</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
