<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-06-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="579" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d579">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">452.11/222</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Diplomatic Agent and Consul General at
                                Tangier</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Blake</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tangier</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-06-19">June 19, 1929</date>.<lb/>[Received July
                                9.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 410</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In reference to my No. 392 of May 17th,
                            1929, reporting the <hi rend="italic">ad referendum</hi> agreement
                            between General Jordana and myself revising the total amount of the
                            American claims in the Spanish Zone, as originally provided for in the
                            joint report, I have the honor to inform the Department that there
                            occurred a slight misunderstanding with regard to the Raisuli indemnity,
                            as explained in a communication, dated June 17th, 1929, which I have
                            received from my Spanish Colleague. The Spanish Minister Plenipotentiary
                            and Consul-General, in transmitting to me General Jordana’s Memorandum
                            of the results of our interview, points out that the proposition of the
                            Spanish High Commissioner was, to increase Raisuli’s indemnification for
                            property destroyed by the military, from Pesetas: 6,944.45 to Pesetas:
                            12,000.00, whereas it had been my impression that Pesetas 12,000.00 was
                            to be added to the original amount of this item of Raisuli’s claim. It
                            would seem impossible to question the good faith of the Spanish
                            Commissioner in his statement as to his understanding of this agreement,
                            and I am accordingly prepared to accept same. Consequently, the amount
                            of the item in question of Raisuli’s claims, will be reduced from
                            Pesetas: 18,944.45 to Pesetas: 12,000.00. The grand total of the claims
                            will therefore be reduced in the sum of Pesetas: 6,944.45 and will stand
                            at Pesetas: 503,805.75.</p>
                        <p>I am informed in the same communication that on June 4th, 1929, General
                            Jordana transmitted our <hi rend="italic">ad referendum</hi> agreement
                            to the Presidency of the Council of Ministers, General Direction of
                            Morocco and Colonies, at Madrid.</p>
                        <p>From a trustworthy official source it has been intimated to me that the
                            matter, now being in the hands of General Primo de Rivera,<note n="31a" xml:id="d579fn31a">Marqués de Estella, President of the Spanish
                                Council of Ministers and Minister for Foreign Affairs.</note> is not
                            likely to receive any solution through subordinate authorities, in the
                            Spanish Foreign Office, and it therefore will remain in abeyance until
                            it receives the personal attention of the President of the Council.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Maxwell Blake</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>