<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Diplomatic Agent and Consul General at Tangier
                    ( (Blake))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d597</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">597</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-01-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-01-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="597"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d597">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">881.512/67</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Diplomatic Agent and Consul General at Tangier</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Blake</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-01-29">January 29,
                            1929</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 505</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to your despatches Nos. 343 and
                    350 of December 4 and December 31, 1928, respectively, concerning the request of
                    the French Resident General for the consent of this Government to the
                    application to American nationals and <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> of
                    the proposed “padlock law” and of the four specific taxation measures, and
                    supplementing the Department’s telegram No. 4 of January 22, 1929, 6 p.m., in
                    which you were authorized provisionally to assent to the four taxation measures,
                    the Department concurs in your views concerning the “padlock law” and authorizes
                    you to address a note to the French Resident General, in reply to his note of
                    November 23, 1928 concerning that law, in substance as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“This Government regrets that it does not see its way clear to giving the
                            consent requested by His Excellency, in his capacity as Minister of
                            Foreign Affairs of His Shereefian Majesty, to the application to its
                            nationals and <hi rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> of the proposed
                            measure providing that any draft law submitted by the Administration in
                            connection with an increase of consumption taxes shall be put into
                            immediate effect. While desirous of facilitating the task of the
                            Administration at Tangier in such manner as may be possible and
                            appropriate, this Government is unable to concur in a proposal such as
                            the contemplated law which would involve a radical departure from its
                            well-established practice in Morocco in conformity with its treaty
                            rights, and a substantial alteration of those rights. This Government
                            will continue to give the same careful consideration which it has
                            accorded in the past to requests made in accordance with existing treaty
                            provisions for its consent to the application to its nationals and <hi
                                rend="italic">ressortissants</hi> of new taxation measures which
                            shall have been definitely adopted by the competent legislative body in
                            Tangier. Furthermore, this Government, if given through the customary
                            channel an opportunity to examine proposed taxation measures, will issue
                            appropriate instructions in advance to the American Diplomatic Agent and
                            Consul General at Tangier so that, where possible, its consent to the
                            application of <pb facs="0640" n="522" xml:id="pg_522"/> these measures
                            may be given immediately after they have been duly adopted by the
                            competent legislative body in the form submitted to this
                            Government.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The Department requests you to inform it by telegram when you have transmitted
                    this note to the French Resident General in order that it may at that time make
                    appropriate reply to the representations of the British, French and Italian
                    Embassies concerning this matter.</p>
                <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Reuben Clark, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
