<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-04-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="63" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.512368 Shipping/5</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Greek Minister</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Simopoulos</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg></opener>
                        <p>The Secretary of State presents his compliments to the Greek Minister and
                            has the honor to refer to the Minister’s note of February 29, 1928,
                            setting forth the provisions of the Greek income tax law exempting from
                            taxation earnings made in Greece by ships flying a foreign flag.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary of State has the honor to inform the Greek Minister that
                            before it can be determined whether these exemptions are equivalent to
                            the exemptions that may be accorded by the United States under Section
                                213(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) (8) of the Revenue Acts of 1921 and
                            1924 it will be necessary for the appropriate authorities of the
                            Government to be informed as to whether: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>during the years 1921–1924, inclusive, taxes have been
                                    collected by the Greek Government from the revenues of American
                                    citizens not residing in Greece or of corporations organized
                                    under the laws of the United States, derived from the operation
                                    of ships documented under the laws of the United States;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>the exemption provided in Article 3, Paragraph 7 of the Law,
                                    No. 3338 applies to the profits derived by a citizen of the
                                    United States not residing in Greece, and to corporations
                                    organized under the laws of the United States, or whether in the
                                    case of such citizen the exemption only applies if he resides in
                                    the United States;</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>the exemption applies in cases where citizens of the United
                                    States or corporations organized under the laws of the United
                                    States maintain agencies, branch offices, or representatives in
                                    Greece, in connection with the operation of ships documented
                                    under the laws of the United States.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In this connection the Secretary of State has the honor to state that he
                            has been informed by the appropriate authorities of the <pb facs="0203" n="85" xml:id="pg_85"/> Government that if it is eventually
                            determined that the pertinent exemptions in the Greek income tax law are
                            equivalent to the exemption provision of Section 213(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) (8) of the Revenue Acts of 1921 and 1924 it will be
                            unnecessary for the United States to conclude any agreement with Greece
                            relative to the exemption of earnings derived from the operation of
                            ships documented under the laws of the two countries.</p>
                        <p>With reference to the Minister’s request that the collection of income
                            tax on the earnings in the United States of the National Steam
                            Navigation Company, Limited, of Greece, be delayed until the appropriate
                            authorities of the Government have determined whether the exemptions
                            provided for by Greek law are equivalent to those provided for by the
                            income tax legislation of the United States, the Secretary of State has
                            the honor to inform the Greek Minister that there is no provision in the
                            income tax law of the United States or in the regulations issued
                            thereunder which authorizes a collector of internal revenue to refrain
                            from collecting income tax properly due from a taxpayer. The Treasury
                            Department however has informed the Secretary of State that it will
                            suggest to the Collector in New York that he withhold for a reasonable
                            time the collection of income tax in the case of the National Steam
                            Navigation Company, Limited, of Greece, provided such action will not
                            jeopardize the ultimate collection of the tax due. In the meantime if
                            the Greek Minister will supply the additional information needed the
                            appropriate authorities of the Government will be able to arrive at a
                            definite decision with reference to the general question of the
                            exemption of earnings made in the United States by ships flying the
                            Greek flag.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-04-26">April 26,
                                    1928</date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>