<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-05-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="667" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d667">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">312.1722 Sandino/30</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Clark</hi>) <hi rend="italic">of a Conversation With
                                the Mexican Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Téllez</hi>), <hi rend="italic">May 17, 1929</hi></head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1929-05-17">May 17, 1929</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p>The Ambassador told me that Mr. Morgan had been around to see the Foreign
                            Office with reference to a communication which our Embassy in Mexico had
                            received regarding Sandino. (It would seem that the telegram in question
                            was probably ours of May 8.) The Ambassador assured me that the Mexican
                            Government was not interceding upon behalf of Sandino and were under no
                            obligations to him, but that he had applied for asylum and just as we
                            gave asylum to Mexican rebels, they had felt they could give asylum to
                            Sandino.</p>
                        <p>Upon his expressing some apprehension about Sandino’s safety, I told the
                            Ambassador that we would do what we could to prevent any injury to
                            Sandino from the regular Nicaraguan forces and from the Guardia, but
                            that I understood the northern part of Nicaragua was in a very disturbed
                            condition with the result that we were not in a position to guarantee
                            Sandino’s safety. I told him that we would, of course, request the
                            Guardia not to injure Sandino, but that I did not know how far any
                            request that we might make would go.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador left with the statement that so soon as they knew that
                            Sandino was ready to come out they would advise us in order that we
                            might advise the proper persons. I told him that we would leave the
                            matter in that shape.</p>
                        <closer><signed>J. R[<hi rend="smallcaps">euben</hi>] C[<hi rend="smallcaps">lark</hi>]</signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>