<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1928-09-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1928-09-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="887" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d887">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">702.0652/11</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Spain</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hammond</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">San
                                        Sebastian</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1928-09-20">September 20, 1928</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                October 6.]</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1031</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the Department’s instruction
                            No. 439 of August 16th, last (File No. 702.0652/8) and to previous
                            correspondence relative to taxation in Spain of motor vehicles owned by
                            American consular officers, I have the honor to transmit herewith for
                            the Department’s information a copy of the Embassy’s note No. 604 of
                            August 29th last to the Spanish Government,<note n="35" xml:id="d887fn35">Not printed.</note> sent in compliance with the
                            Department’s instruction under acknowledgement, together with a copy and
                            translation of the Spanish Government’s reply in the premises, No. 281
                            dated September 12th, last.<note n="35" xml:id="d887fn36">Not
                                printed.</note></p>
                        <p>As the Department will perceive, the Royal Spanish Foreign Office has
                            refused the Embassy’s request for the exemption of American consular
                            officers in Spain from taxation on their motor vehicles on the ground
                            that certain American States, notably: Wisconsin, Indiana, Minnesota and
                            Pennsylvania, as well as the Philippine Islands and Porto Rico, refuse a
                            like exemption to Spanish consular officers.</p>
                        <p>In view of the fact that the Spanish reply ignores the omission from the
                            pertinent section of the United States-Spanish Treaty of 1902 of any
                            provision for strict reciprocity, as well as the Department’s
                            undertaking to uphold the right of Spanish consular officers to be
                            exempt from taxation on automobiles owned by them in all States of the
                            Union, I have the honor to request the Department’s further instructions
                            in the premises.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Ogden H. Hammond</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>