<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Private Secretary to the British Prime Minister ( (Vansittart) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1929v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">9</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1929-10-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1929-10-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1929-10-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1929-10-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="9"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d9">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">033.4111MacDonald, Ramsay/113½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Private Secretary to the British Prime Minister</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Vansittart</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ottawa</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1929-10-19">October 19,
                            1929</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: As we were leaving you asked me to
                    send you a line on the Ottawa sequel to the Washington conversations. I take
                    this first opportunity of doing so. We have still one more day here, but I
                    expect you will be glad of early information since, owing to the fact that Mr.
                    MacDonald’s speech had to be delivered on the very day of his arrival it was not
                    possible to cover much ground. No doubt Campbell gave you my advance message to
                    this effect. I telephoned to ask him to do so. Since then there has been a
                    little more time, and Mr. MacDonald has been able to give Mr. Mackenzie King a
                    full account of the Washington proceedings, including of course the paragraphs
                    which the President wished to add in regard to ships laden exclusively with
                    foodstuffs. I may say that the idea of exempting foodships has been received
                    here with a great deal of interest and will be examined in Ottawa as we promised
                    it should be examined in London. You will have noticed also that Mr. MacDonald
                    in his speech went a step ahead in foreshadowing the joint examination provided
                    for in the first of the eliminated paragraphs.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister also discussed the question of the naval stations. It is, I
                    think, clear from further close examination that the plan for the division of
                    the world into two hemispheres will not be workable, and we shall have to think
                    out some other way of laying the ‘ghost’ of the so-called menace of the naval
                    stations.</p>
                <p>The Canadian Government are willing in principle to announce simultaneously and
                    jointly with us that their naval stations are not, and are not intended to be, a
                    menace to the United States. This, <pb facs="0155" n="37" xml:id="pg_37"/>
                    however, could only be done if the same statement were made reciprocally by the
                    United States. If this is, in your view, impossible, the agreement would then be
                    confined to the Caribbean area. The wording of this statement would as arranged
                    be settled between us. Mr. Ramsay MacDonald will go into this matter immediately
                    upon his return to London.</p>
                <p>The intentions of the Canadian Government in regard to the refusal of clearance
                    to vessels carrying liquor to the United States we found to agree with the last
                    paragraph of the President’s memorandum sent to me by Akerson on October 10th;
                    and an announcement will be made in due course by the Canadian Government of the
                    action it proposes to take.</p>
                <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Vansittart</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
