<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-06-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="13" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d13">
                    <head>13. Memorandum for the President’s File by <persName corresp="#p_JWJ_1">William J. Jorden</persName> of the National Security Council
                            Staff<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d13fn1">Source: National
                            Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                            Materials, Staff Member and Office Files, White House Special Files,
                            President’s Office Files, President’s Meeting File, 1969–1974, Box 92,
                            Memoranda for the President—Beginning June 3 [1973]. Confidential.
                            According to the President’s Daily Diary, the meeting took place in the
                            White House Cabinet Room from 11:33 a.m. until 12:31 p.m. (Ibid., White
                            House Central Files) A list of attendees is attached but not printed.
                            The Council of the Americas is a business organization founded by
                            financier <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">David Rockefeller</persName> to
                            promote hemispheric free trade and open markets.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-06-07">June 7, 1973</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Meeting with Board of Trustees of the Council of the Americas on
                            Thursday, June 7, 1973 at 11:35 a.m to 12:30 p.m.</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>The President</item>
                        <item>Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SBA_1">Brent Scowcroft</persName> (<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>)</item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_JWJ_1">William J. Jorden</persName> (<gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>)</item>
                        <item>Board of Trustees of the Council of the Americas (list
                            attached)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>[Omitted here are <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>’s remarks
                        concerning his Latin American mission, Council of the Americas Chairman Jose
                        de Cubas’s introductory points, and <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>’s comments on foreign investment.]</p>
                    <p>The President said a new wave of isolationism had surfaced—in Congress, in
                        labor, and even in some business circles. You men, with an international
                        mission, have to counteract this trend to isolationism. Otherwise our hopes
                        for a more open world will go down the drain. He agreed that we need more
                        flexibility in legislation on expropriation, flexibility for the President
                        and the Administration. But he noted that there were Congressional problems
                        that result from both domestic pressures and from public attitudes in Latin
                        America. The President said that the attitude of some countries in Latin
                        America is to play to the radical groups and to believe that the way to
                        success is to kick the U.S. around publicly. He quoted a politician in the
                        Philippines who once said: “Give the Americans hell—but don’t drive them
                        away.” It is important for Latin American leaders to understand that they
                        can only go so far before they drive us away. The Congress reacts to these
                        things. Many Americans are tired of being kicked around.</p>
                    <pb facs="0095" n="64" xml:id="pg_64"/>
                    <p>(He cited the example of Echeverria of Mexico who “goes around attacking us
                        but privately is friendly.”<note n="2" xml:id="d13fn2">On March 26 <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, Deputy Chief of Mission of
                            the Embassy in Mexico City Robert Dean, and <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staff member Jonathan Howe met with <persName corresp="#p_EL_1">Echeverría</persName> at the Presidential
                            residence at Las Pinos. According to a memorandum of conversation,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> commented: “We
                            have difficulty with Latin America because it is imperative for leaders
                            to make anti-U.S. statements in order to take pro-U.S. measures
                            (Echeverria laughs deeply). So, I understand. But if it goes beyond a
                            certain point, then it turns into a contest between the developed United
                            States and the underdeveloped world. It faces us with a dilemma. It
                            helps create a political structure which freezes a country into a
                            posture against us. And, as I say, this does create a real dilemma. We
                            want independence but also a structure in which we can get along
                            together.” (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 788, Country Files—Latin America, Mexico,
                            Vol. IV, 1973 [1 of 3]) The full memorandum of conversation is scheduled
                            for publication in <ref target="frus1969-76ve11p1">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume E–11,
                                Documents on American Republics, 1973–1976</ref>.</note> But the
                        real questions are: what do we do about Mexican tomatoes, what do we do
                        about salinity?)</p>
                    <p>A serious problem is those politicians who exploit the radical activists. We
                        must fight this to the extent we can. We must get our friends—in government,
                        in business—to know that this is a dangerous game.</p>
                    <p>(He quoted <persName corresp="#p_LHC2_1">Henry Cabot Lodge</persName> as
                        saying that Latin America was important in the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> and that without them the U.S. position would be weak.) We
                        realize that Latin America is important. But the truth is that they need us
                        more than we need them. He noted that government aid was a small proportion
                        of our total involvement ($16 billion invested). But when you go to Congress
                        to try to get more done, it is rough. And it is getting rougher.</p>
                    <p>The President then reminisced about how much different the situation was
                        today than when he last met with the Council of the Americas Trustees in
                        November 1969. Then, he said, there were 300,000 demonstrators around the
                        White House. We were losing 300 men a week in Vietnam. We were in
                        confrontation with the Russians. We had no contact with China. The situation
                        in Latin America was about the same, maybe a little better. When we see the
                        changes that have taken place, there is no reason for euphoria but there is
                        reason for hope. However, we live in a potentially dangerous world. A basic
                        fact is that with the advent of nuclear weapons, there will be no
                        conventional wars between major powers. Now it will all be done in 30
                        minutes.</p>
                    <p>It is important that we realize what we have done in the world despite the
                        threat of war. The people are pleased with the end of the Vietnam War. Far
                        more important is what we have done to change the world. That is what the
                        China initiative was all about. It was not just handshaking. As President, I
                        could not let one-fourth of the people of the world—with a future as a
                        nuclear power—not have relations with us. We must look down the road 15 to
                        20 years in terms of our commu<pb facs="0096" n="65" xml:id="pg_65"/>nications with them. Interestingly enough, the U.S. is China’s best
                        friend.</p>
                    <p>Another thing—the meetings with the Soviet Union in Moscow<note n="3" xml:id="d13fn3">See <ref target="#d7fn4">footnote 4, Document
                            7</ref>.</note> were important. A number of agreements were signed.
                        Overriding all of them was the first step in limiting nuclear arms. Far more
                        important is the fact that the U.S. and the Soviet Union are in a position
                        where we are negotiating. We have to find a way to avoid a nuclear
                        explosion. The important thing is the fact that there is communication. The
                        reason for that communication: the U.S. and Soviets are equal (in power) and
                        China will be equal in 15 years. If a President of the U.S. decides he has
                        to react, it means the death of 70 million Russians and 70 million
                        Americans. “Anyone who sits in this chair has to avoid that happening,” he
                        said.</p>
                    <p>There is a tendency in Congress toward increasing isolationism. They see the
                        end of the war in Vietnam and say “isn’t that nice—let’s cut $10 billion
                        from the Defense budget.” We should not cut the Defense budget at this time
                        because it means changing the game plan which is working. But that is what
                        Congress is doing when it says “regardless of what you do, we are going to
                        cut.” We have to recognize that nothing is done in this field (détente) from
                        love. It is done from respect, even fear. There must be mutual cuts.
                        Otherwise our bargaining position is incredibly weaker. Our allies will lose
                        trust. The Soviets will lose respect. And China will no longer feel that
                        agreements with us are important.</p>
                    <p>We face the stark fact that in a nuclear world we are the only free country
                        that counts. The British and French don’t have the power; the Germans are
                        not allowed to develop nuclear weapons; Japan must not be allowed to develop
                        them. In terms of security of our alliances the power is all right here.
                        Japan is keenly aware that without us, they will (1) have to make a deal
                        with the Soviets or (2) go nuclear.</p>
                    <p>As for Latin America, we care about our closest friends there. Our actions
                        (on other problems) should not be read as meaning we don’t care.</p>
                    <p>This is not true. What we are talking about has great importance for our
                        close friends and neighbors. They have a stake in a peaceful world. Latin
                        America is most important to us. Vitally important in terms of economics. We
                        must do everything we can to reinforce our interest. But we must also let
                        them know that it is to their advantage to work with us. However, we should
                        not infringe on their sensitivities.</p>
                    <p>The major danger spot is the Middle East. There are no easy answers. But we
                        are working on it. It is the most likely area of big power <pb facs="0097" n="66" xml:id="pg_66"/> conflict. The Vietnam war was not that important
                        to Soviet interests. The Middle East is that important. Europe gets 90% of
                        its fuel from the Middle East. Japan gets 80% of its fuel from there.</p>
                    <p>I raise these other parts of the world—not to downgrade Latin America, but to
                        put things in perspective. We must get along with the Soviet Union and with
                        China. We must get along with Europe. Latin America is still important to
                        us, even more important than it was. Your concerns will get our deepest
                        consideration. We need your support, in defense and in total policy. For our
                        friendship with Latin America will not be important if we become the second
                        most powerful nation.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">David Rockefeller</persName> said he agreed
                        with everything the President had said. He said that Latin Americans note
                        that we talk of the Five Major Power centers (the U.S., Europe, the Soviet
                        Union, China and Japan). They ask: where are we in that scheme? It is
                        important for us to find ways to assure them of our esteem.</p>
                    <p>Regarding investment, it is big—$16 billion is already at stake. However,
                        private enterprise is under fire there (in Latin America) and in our own
                        Congress. We have a defensive battle of our own. It is all the more
                        important for us to find ways for our role to be constructive. We need a
                        more organized role with the U.S. Government and Latin governments. The
                        Council’s proposed idea of an advisory council could contribute toward
                        this.</p>
                    <p>The President said he did not want to end the meeting on a downbeat note.
                        There are always many danger spots. The world, in terms of the long view, is
                        a safer place than it was four years ago. It is not in the nature of men to
                        love one another; but that doesn’t mean they need to fight one another. My
                        greatest goal in the next four years is to make the world even more safe
                        than it is now. </p>
                    <p>Toasts and speeches are all froth. “We need to get more body to this beer.”
                        We cannot bug out on our responsibilities.</p>
                    <p>The President concluded the meeting by thanking the members of the Council
                        for their advice and their time. He walked around the Cabinet table and
                        shook hands personally with each of the Trustees. The meeting concluded at
                        12:30 p.m.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>