<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>4. Memorandum for the President’s Files by the President’s Press Secretary
                    (Ziegler))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v38p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">4</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007242"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Defense budget</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="4"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d4">
                <head>4. Memorandum for the President’s Files by the President’s Press Secretary
                        (<persName corresp="#p_ZR_1">Ziegler</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d4fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1"
                            >Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, Staff Member and Office Files,
                        White House Special Files, President’s Office Files, President’s Meeting
                        File, 1969–1974, Box 91, Memoranda for the President—Beginning February 4
                        [1973]. No classification marking. <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1"
                            >Nixon</persName> attended a luncheon at the Department of State where
                        he met with <persName corresp="#p_RWD_1">Rogers</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RKW_1"
                            >Kenneth Rush</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PWJ_1">William
                            Porter</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CWJ_1">William
                        Casey</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TCW_1">Curtis Tarr</persName>,
                        William Macomber, <persName corresp="#p_PRF_1">Richard Pedersen</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_DJF_1">Joseph Donelan</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NDD_1">David Newsom</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_AWC_1"
                            >Willis Armstrong</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GM_1">Marshall
                            Green</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SWJJ_1">Walter
                            Stoessel</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WWM_1">Marshall
                            Wright</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_DS_1">Samuel
                        DePalma</persName>, William Hall, <persName corresp="#p_SJJ_1">Joseph
                            Sisco</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RJJ_2">John
                            Richardson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">U. Alexis
                            Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MAH_1">Armin Meyer</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRJ_1">Robert McCloskey</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_ETLJ_1">Theodore Eliot</persName>, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_ZR_1">Ziegler</persName>. (President’s Daily Diary; ibid.,
                        White House Central Files) <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>
                        also delivered remarks to Department of State personnel at an afternoon
                        memorial ceremony honoring Ambassador to the Sudan <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCAJ_1">Cleo Noel, Jr.</persName>, and Deputy Chief of
                        Mission <persName corresp="#p_MGC_1">George Curtis Moore</persName>. Members
                        of the Black September terrorist group had kidnapped and slain <persName
                            corresp="#p_NCAJ_1">Noel</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MGC_1"
                            >Moore</persName>, and Belgian Chargé d’Affaires Guy Eid on March 2. For
                        text of these remarks, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName
                                corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>, 1973</hi>, pp. 169–171.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-03-06">March 6, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Department of State Luncheon with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1"
                            >William P. Rogers</persName> and State Department Officials, Tuesday,
                        March 6, 1973 at 12:50 p.m.</item>
                </list>
                <p>[Omitted here is discussion of the murders of the diplomats in the Sudan by
                    terrorists.]</p>
                <p>Discussion then moved to the defense budget. There was comment that most people
                    don’t understand that the defense budget has already been cut. Discussion went
                    to the period immediately after World War II when our foreign policy did
                    accomplish great objectives in terms of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                    and the Greek-Turkish situation,<note n="2" xml:id="d4fn2">Reference is to the
                        founding of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization in 1949 and the events
                        leading to the promulgation of the <persName corresp="#p_THS_1"
                            >Truman</persName> Doctrine in 1947.</note> but at that point we went
                    too far down in our defense budget and helped create the conditions that lead to
                    Korea. The ability to get support for adequate foreign policy and foreign
                    assistance, the President said, is going to be quite a challenge. How do we
                    combat opposition to it? It means a united front for maintaining adequate
                    defense and foreign assistance. We must get across <pb facs="0045" n="14"
                        xml:id="pg_14"/> the point that to have the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> to turn inward would be dangerous. If the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> turns inward the China and Soviet initiatives
                    will go down the drain. The day the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> ceases to
                    be a formidable defense and diplomatic power, economics will not be enough to
                    hold it together. It is a dangerous situation, the President said. The old
                    isolationists and the new isolationists could be a majority. Our failure to
                    succeed could lead to a period when we could draw away from our responsibility.
                    We must inform the country that having ended the war and with our new
                    initiatives in China and the Soviet Union, this is the time for the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> to continue to play a forceful role in the
                    world—militarily, economically and diplomatically. The President recalled when
                    he left Washington in 1960, we had an 8 to 1 defense advantage. Today we are
                    behind in throw weight.</p>
                <p>With the Vietnam war over, we must inspire the American spirit and accept the
                    role of world leadership. The game is more difficult to play today than before.
                    If the Soviet Union and the <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> continue
                    fighting with one another, that adds to the complexities. Let’s not let the
                    impression get around that now that we have gotten out of Vietnam, let’s get out
                    of the world. The President then expressed his appreciation to all of those
                    present.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> said that he had spent two days
                    on the Hill and he didn’t detect opposition. The President said, “That’s combat
                    pay now,”—referring to a trip to the Hill.</p>
                <p>The President said that <persName corresp="#p_SHD_1">Scott</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d4fn3">Senate Minority Leader <persName corresp="#p_SHD_1"
                            >Hugh Scott</persName> (R–Pennsylvania).</note> had told him in the
                    morning that we would lose our Foreign Assistance Bill 65–34, and was talking
                    about how your leaders are supposed to come in and build you up when you’ve had
                    a hard day. And, referring to <persName corresp="#p_SHD_1">Scott</persName>’s
                    comment, the President said, “I’ve had a helluva hard day!”</p>
                <p>“The U.S. must play a world role but a different world role. We can’t call all
                    the shots; we can’t dominate; but, we can’t let the world be shaped in a way
                    that would be counter to our interests.”</p>
                <p>If we can get people in this country proud of their world role and the record in
                    Vietnam, then there is much to be accomplished. But if you tell them that it was
                    all in vain, we will never get them to try again. “This country needs a sense of
                    direction; this country needs a sense of pride; this country needs a positive
                    attitude,” the President said.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
