<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="177" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d177">
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi></head>
                    <p>Following preliminary hearings in the House of Representatives in March 1953
                        on extension of the Mutual Security program, President Eisenhower on May 5
                        recommended to Congress the passage of legislation extending the program.
                        The basic purpose of the program was characterized by the President as
                        “simply the long-term security of the United States living in the shadow of
                        the Soviet threat.” The President requested approximately $5,250 million for
                        military weapons and support to aid the defense efforts of friends and
                        allies, and approximately $550 million for technical, economic, and
                        developmental purposes. The total request represented a reduction of
                        approximately $1.8 billion from the Truman Administration’s <pb facs="0652" n="626" xml:id="pg_626"/> projected mutual security budget. For the text
                        of the President’s message, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the
                            Presidents of the United States: Dwight D. Eisenhower</hi>, 1953, pages
                        256–259.</p>
                    <p>Both Secretary Dulles and Mutual Security Director Harold Stassen testified
                        before a joint session of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee and the
                        House Foreign Affairs Committee on May 5. During the course of his remarks,
                        the Secretary stated that “A main objective of the program is to get the
                        most security for the least cost”. He also observed that a large part of the
                        total amount was being requested for defense of the European area within the
                        framework of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization, and that the most
                        careful planning had gone into the formulation of the request. “There is no
                        ‘water’ in this program to be squeezed out without taking greater risks than
                        we believe are acceptable at the present time”, he stated in connection with
                        the European portion of the proposed program.</p>
                    <p>Stassen, in his testimony, stated that the program before the two Committees
                        “represents the product of months of work by the National Security Council
                        where each of our security objectives was carefully studied and its
                        importance weighed in relation to the fiscal considerations” that so greatly
                        concerned Secretary of the Treasury George Humphrey. The testimony of
                        Secretary Dulles and Mutual Security Director Stassen is printed in the
                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, May 25, 1953, pages
                        736–742.</p>
                    <p>Senate hearings on the Mutual Security bill took place in the latter half of
                        May. Those hearings are printed in U.S. Senate, <hi rend="italic">Hearings
                            on a bill to amend the Mutual Security Act of 1951</hi>, May 15–29,
                        1953, 83d Cong., 1st sess. The earlier House hearings are printed in U.S.
                        House of Representatives, <hi rend="italic">Hearings … Mutual Security Act
                            Extension</hi>, March 1953, 83d Cong., 1st sess.</p>
                    <p>On May 27, President Eisenhower reduced his initial request by $354 million.
                        On June 16, the House Foreign Affairs Committee reported <gloss target="#t_HR1">H.R.</gloss> 5710 authorizing $5 billion. Subsequently,
                        the full House passed the bill after rejecting all amendments proposing
                        further reductions but agreeing to an amendment by Representative Fulton
                        (R.–Pa.) requiring disposal of surplus agricultural commodities wherever
                        possible. The Senate version of the Mutual Security bill, approved on July
                        1, authorized a grant of $5.3 billion. A conference report fixing the final
                        Mutual Security appropriation was approved July 13 by both Houses.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>