<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-03-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-03-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="197" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d197">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> files, lot 56 D 551, “1955 Congressional
                        Presentation MS Bill”</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Special Assistant to the
                            Secretary of State for Mutual Security Affairs (<persName type="from">Nolting</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d197fn1">Drafted by George S.
                            Newman, Special Assistant to the Secretary of State for Mutual Security
                            Affairs.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-03-12">March 12, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <item>Subject:</item>
                        <item><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1955 Mutual Security Program</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi></p>
                    <p>At your meeting today with Messrs. Stassen, Kyes and Dodge,<note n="2" xml:id="d197fn2">No record of such meeting has been found.</note> an
                        effort will be made to resolve certain questions relating to the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1955 Mutual Security Program. Among the
                        points which may be discussed are the following:</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The form of legislation</hi></p>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> has prepared consolidated legislation
                        repealing all existing statutes on foreign assistance and reenacting their
                        provisions, including those on organization, in a single organic statute.
                        The Secretary has indicated that he prefers the method of amending the
                        existing laws since this will not prejudice the long-term organizational
                        arrangements. However, it is possible to draft a bill which will meet the
                        objections of the Department by omitting any references to organizational
                        matters and the Act for International Development and simply consolidate the
                        substantive provisions of the statutes governing military and economic
                        aid.</p>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Appropriation of military aid funds and their merger
                            with Department of Defense appropriation</hi></p>
                    <p>The problem is whether military aid funds should be appropriated directly to
                        Defense or to the President. In the latter case they would be under Mr.
                        Stassen’s control. This question is not of direct concern to the Department.
                        However, it is absolutely essential from a foreign policy point of view that
                        regardless of where the funds are finally appropriated, arrangements be made
                        to assure (a) adequate foreign policy guidance and control in the
                        development and execution of military assistance programs, and (b)
                        satisfactory reporting to the Department on progress and status of these
                        programs.</p>
                    <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Administration and coordination of the foreign aid
                            programs</hi></p>
                    <p>It has generally been agreed that for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 1955
                        the existing arrangements, with <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss>
                        responsible for administration and coordination, subject to foreign policy
                        guidance from the Secretary, should be continued.</p>
                    <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Coverage of the Military Assistance
                        Appropriation</hi></p>
                    <p>The question here is whether the military aid appropriation should include
                        funds for support of the Navarre Plan in Indo-China and certain common-use
                        programs. We believe that funds for these programs should be sought as a
                        part of the military assistance programs since their justification is
                        directly related to military activities. <pb facs="0757" n="731" xml:id="pg_731"/> They should, however, be clearly identified from the
                        end-item program and probably be administered by <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> with assistance from Defense.</p>
                    <p>Another subject which you may wish to mention at the meeting is the problem
                        of improving the present arrangements for bringing to bear foreign policy
                        considerations on the military programs during their formulation and
                        implementation on a more continuing basis. While present arrangements have
                        functioned satisfactorily, they can be improved considerably to avoid the
                        difficulties and delays that frequently occur. Recent examples of this
                        problem are “Plan K”<note n="3" xml:id="d197fn3">For documentation on Plan
                            K, see <ref target="frus1952-54v06p1">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi></ref>.</note> and Defense policies and pricing criteria
                        on off-shore procurement. A move in this direction might be to provide for
                        State attending meetings of the Munitions Allocations Council (a Defense
                        committee on which <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss> sits as an
                        observer).</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>