<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Special Consultant to the President (Randall) to the
                    President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v01p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">28</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-12-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recEe8ikdAbvcrXbA" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067736"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Foreign investments</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2r0t2UkWjO2ZV1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004011274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Subsidies</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec1pn5YTx6GUWt03" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002261"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Agricultural program</term>
                    <term ref="rec0YIEoMSlyPKAGO" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="general-agreement-on-tariffs-and-trade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001009859"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">GATT</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-12-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="28"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d28">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Eisenhower Library, Eisenhower papers, Whitman
                    file</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Special Consultant to the President
                            (<persName type="from">Randall</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                            >President</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d28fn1">Distributed to members of the Cabinet as a Cabinet
                        Paper, designated <gloss target="#t_CP1">CP</gloss>–4, under cover of a
                        memorandum by Secretary to the Cabinet Maxwell M. Rabb, dated Dec. 8, 1954,
                        not printed.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-12-07">December 7,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The conclusions on foreign economic policy expressed here have been formed after
                    weeks of discussion with representatives from every department and with many
                    others who have been consulted.</p>
                <p>These conclusions are based squarely upon the Special Message of March 30, 1954
                    which was in turn based upon the conclusions of the Commission on Foreign
                    Economic Policy, but they were not arrived at by any pattern-mindedness. The
                    subject was reopened in every aspect in an endeavor to find weaknesses in that
                    program or important additions to it, but the end of the process has come to
                    substantially the same result.</p>
                <p>That there is serious distortion in the world economy is clear, and that the
                    United States should do something about it is equally clear. We are impelled to
                    that viewpoint by the short-term consideration of security, which requires
                    economic strength among our allies, by humanitarian impulses of improving the
                    lot of the underprivileged in the world, but most especially by the long-term
                    consideration that an increasing volume of world production and trade is the
                    best possible assurance for a rising standard of living for our own people.</p>
                <p>This program seeks to mitigate the distortions in the world economy by the
                    release of normal forces within the framework of free enterprise and competitive
                    markets, and is the antithesis of global spending. We have ahead of us the best
                    opportunity that has occurred in a generation to move the United States
                    intelligently toward a more liberal trade position.</p>
                <p>The whole approach to the subject should be non-partisan, and it is extremely
                    important that foreign economic policy be the first subject taken up in the new
                    Congress. It would seem imperative that a strong note on this subject be sounded
                    in the State of the Union Message, and that in the matter of just a few days
                    thereafter <pb facs="0132" n="106" xml:id="pg_106"/> a special message be sent
                    to the Congress outlining the specific legislative proposals. The program
                    recommended is now outlined step by step:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Tariffs</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Kean Bill should be reintroduced. It provides: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>That the President shall have the power by multilateral negotiations
                            to reduce tariffs on selected commodities by 5 percent per year for
                            three years.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>That where tariffs exceed 50 percent, they may be reduced through
                            multilateral negotiations to that limit over the three-year
                            period.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>That where no substantial amount of the commodity is imported, the
                            tariff may be reduced over the three-year period to 50 percent of the
                            rate existing on January 1, 1945, with or without receiving reciprocal
                            concessions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The present escape and peril point provisions would be preserved.</p>
                <p>The hearings on the Kean Bill, which should open the first week in January,
                    should be supported by the marshalling of the largest, most impressive number of
                    witnesses that can be gotten together.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Customs Simplification</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Jenkins Bill, revised, should be reintroduced to make intelligent
                        standards for the valuation of imports.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The President should say that he is awaiting with interest the report of
                        the Tariff Commission on simplification of the classification of imports for
                        which the Customs Simplification Act of 1954 provided. A preliminary report
                        is due by March 1st. Further recommendations for legislation may follow
                        receipt of this report.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Investments Abroad</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The whole world needs capital, and America is its largest source. It is important
                    that the flow of capital abroad from our country be stimulated and under such
                    auspices that it reach private hands as distinguished from
                    government-to-government.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The proposed new International Finance Corporation, which will be a medium
                        for providing capital to private enterprise, should receive full
                        Administration support.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The proposal that an incentive to cause private American capital to go
                        abroad might be created by a fourteen-percentage-point tax credit on income
                        earned from such foreign investments should be revised to meet the
                        criticisms in the last session and reintroduced in Congress.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Further study should be given to find new ways to enlarge the outward flow
                        of capital.</item>
                    <pb facs="0133" n="107" xml:id="pg_107"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The Executive Branch should continue to insist that our diplomatic
                        representatives abroad use every effort to strengthen the private enterprise
                        concept in investment as well as in other economic activity.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Technical Assistance</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Administration should continue to support the principle of technical
                    assistance to underdeveloped countries, meaning by this, “know-how” and not
                    capital. An immediate effort should be made in the new Congress to restore the
                    funds required to support the multilateral technical assistance programs of the
                    United Nations. The bilateral programs of the United States should be pressed
                    vigorously.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Travel</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Frelinghuysen Bill to increase the customs exemption for the incoming tourist
                    from $500 to $1,000 should be reintroduced in the Congress. The amount of money
                    involved here is not large, but the psychological effect would be important in
                    Europe.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Subsidies</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The President should again restate the principle that, in his judgment, all costs
                    required for our security should be directly borne to the greatest possible
                    extent and express his disapproval for this purpose of disguised subsidies to
                    American business.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Agriculture</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The President should once more make it clear that the necessities of our
                    agricultural program and of our foreign economic policy must be harmonized. We
                    cannot suspend natural economic laws in the field of agriculture without having
                    that cause distortion in our foreign trade.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>A medium for multilateral negotiation with other countries in the field of trade
                    is absolutely indispensable to an intelligent foreign economic policy. Without
                    that, an extension of the Trade Agreements Act for three years with an intention
                    to reduce tariffs gradually would be meaningless. The Administration should
                    therefore give its full support in the presentation of the renegotiated <gloss
                        target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> to the Congress.<note n="2" xml:id="d28fn2"
                        >The <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> was renegotiated at the Ninth
                        Session of the Contracting Parties; for additional documentation, see <ref
                            target="#pg_114">pp. 114</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Convertibility</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Convertibility of exchange, which is so urgently required for the development of
                    a steadily rising volume of world trade, cannot be <pb facs="0134" n="108"
                        xml:id="pg_108"/> achieved until the present imbalance in international
                    trade and payments has been corrected. No gold reserves in other countries will
                    stand against the drain if their international payments as a whole are not in
                    balance. That is why the foreign economic program proposed herein would make an
                    important contribution to convertibility.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Japan</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The economic plight of Japan is desperate. Unless she can find a way to live, she
                    may be driven into the camp of the enemy. This problem should be solved through
                    multilateral agreement among the free nations, by which each will do its part in
                    opening sufficient markets to Japan to help her to earn her way. The President
                    should fully support that concept.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Organization for the Development and Coordination of Foreign
                        Economic Policy</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The proposals on organization recommended to the President by Mr. Joseph Dodge in
                    conjunction with the Advisory Committee on Government Organization and the
                    Director of the Bureau of the Budget are heartily endorsed. Steps taken to
                    improve the development and coordination of foreign economic policy within the
                    Executive Branch would be a significant adjunct to this program.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Public Relations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In terms of public relations, it is important that the President early make clear
                    to our people the essentials of his program for the coming year, and it is
                    equally important that from time to time he re-emphasize the objectives and the
                    steps to be taken.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Buy American</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is important that the Buy American Order<note n="3" xml:id="d28fn3">Reference
                        is to a draft of Executive Order 10582 issued on Dec. 17, 1954, which
                        prescribed uniform procedures for certain determinations under the Buy
                        American Act; for text of the Executive Order, see 19 <hi rend="italic"
                            >Federal Register</hi> 8723.</note> be cleared at the Cabinet level as
                    soon as possible and be made public.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Clarence B. Randall</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
