<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-02-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-02-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="42" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d42">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">411.0031/2–2553</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Legal Adviser for Economic
                            Affairs (<persName type="from">Metzger</persName>) to the Deputy Legal
                            Adviser (<persName type="to">Tate</persName>)</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d42fn1">Drafted by Walter Hollis of the Office of the Assistant
                            Legal Adviser for Economic Affairs.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-02-25">February 25, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <item>Subject:</item>
                        <item>Renewal of Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act and Related Problems—A
                            Current Appraisal</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>During the past few months there has been a considerable amount of
                        re-examination within the Department of the policy of the United States with
                        respect to foreign trade. This re-examination has been stimulated by a
                        number of factors including the expiration on June 12, 1953 of the
                        President’s authority to enter into new trade agreements under the Trade
                        Agreements Act, the study of this subject by the Public Advisory Board set
                        up by President Truman, the continuation of balance of payments difficulties
                        of the major European trading countries at a time when various types of
                        financial assistance from the United States are being, or are likely to be,
                        reduced substantially and, since last November, the forthcoming change of
                        Administration.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">I. Reciprocal Trade Agreements
                            Extension</hi></p>
                    <p>Since the original enactment of the Trade Agreements Act on June 12,
                            1934<note n="2" xml:id="d42fn2">The Trade Agreements Act (Public Law
                            316), enacted June 12, 1934, was embodied in Section 350 of the revised
                            Tariff Act of 1930 and entitled “Promotion of Foreign Trade;” for text,
                            see 48 Stat. 943.</note> the policy of the United States with regard to
                        foreign trade has become largely centered around that act and the <pb facs="0165" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/> agreements concluded pursuant to
                        it. Under the act the President is authorized to proclaim limited reductions
                        in duties, and, in very general language, other regulations as to trade, in
                        order to carry out trade agreements. The authority to conclude new
                        agreements to be carried out under this Act expires periodically and has in
                        each case been renewed following examination by the Congress of action by
                        the Executive under the statute. Agreements in effect are not directly
                        affected by the time limitation upon the President’s authority to conclude
                        new agreements, although the statute requires that, following an initial
                        period of not more than three years, agreements must be terminable on not
                        more than six months’ notice.</p>
                    <p>Pursuant to rather general language in the original statute elaborate
                        procedures were gradually developed with respect to the negotiation of trade
                        agreements. The policy-making body with respect to trade agreement matters
                        is the Interdepartmental Trade Agreements Committee, now constituted by
                        Executive Order, the chairman of which is the Chief of the Commercial Policy
                        staff in the Department of State. Its membership consists of representatives
                        from the Departments of the Treasury, Defense, Interior, Agriculture, and
                        Commerce, Labor, and from the Mutual Security Administration, and of a
                        Commissioner of the Tariff Commission (acting in an individual capacity).
                        Operating through interdepartmental subcommittees when considering matters
                        requiring a large amount of research, this committee examines in detail
                        practically all questions relating to trade-agreement matters, and, where
                        appropriate, makes recommendations to the President as to action to be
                        taken.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Tariff Rates</hi></p>
                    <p>The original Trade Agreements Act authorized the President to increase or
                        decrease rates of duty by not more than 50% of the existing rate or to
                        provide for the continuation of existing customs treatment, that is, the
                        so-called binding of rates against increase or the binding of duty-free
                        treatment. As World War II was drawing to a close, trade agreements
                        legislation in 1945, extending for three years the President’s authority to
                        conclude agreements, authorized reductions in duty of 50% of the rate in
                        effect January 1, 1945, that is reductions to 25% of the 1934 rate in cases
                        in which the latter had been reduced by the full 50% permitted in the
                        original legislation. This authority has been utilized for the major trade
                        agreement negotiations in connection with a General Agreement on Tariffs and
                        Trade, at Geneva in 1947, at Annecy, France, in 1949, and at Torquay,
                        England, in 1950–51.</p>
                    <p>A major negotiating problem which is expected to arise in the near future
                        will be our first tariff negotiation under the Trade <pb facs="0166" n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/> Agreements Act with Japan, the application for the
                        accession of which to the General Agreement is now under preliminary
                        consideration by parties to that agreement These parties are also examining
                        in a preliminary manner various proposals for general schemes of tariff
                        reduction under which participating countries would make certain percentage
                        reductions in the average rates of their tariffs applicable to specified
                        categories of products. The extent of flexibility which a country would have
                        under these plans to retain high duties on particular products depends, to a
                        large extent, upon the number of products included within the various
                        categories to which the percentage of reduction would be applied.</p>
                    <p>These possible negotiations within the next few years, together with the
                        growing emphasis on the need for more exports from European countries to
                        dollar areas, particularly the United States, at a time when direct
                        financial assistance is being reduced, have led to examination of various
                        possibilities of including in the Trade Agreements Act additional authority
                        for the reduction of tariffs. Considerable authority still remains for the
                        reduction of duties on various imports of particular interest to Japan as a
                        result of the policy usually followed in the negotiation of trade agreements
                        of not granting concessions to one country covering products of which
                        another country is the principal supplier.</p>
                    <p>For example, in addition to the possibility of permitting rates to be cut by
                        50% of the rate in effect on some new base date, as January 1, 1953, thought
                        is being given to authorizing the reduction of duties between 30% ad valorem
                        and 40% ad valorem to 30% ad valorem, duties between 20% ad valorem and 30%
                        to 20% ad valorem, et cetera. Any such formula as the latter raises problems
                        as to specific duties, that is, duties imposed at so much per unit of
                        measure, and duties which are in part specific. Either the above formula
                        could be applied to the ad valorem equivalent of the specific duties on a
                        particular date, or some other formula, as that of authorizing 50%
                        reductions, would have to be applied to them.</p>
                    <p>The existing Trade Agreements Act, which was originally enacted during the
                        depression in 1934, gives as the one purpose for concluding the agreements
                        the expanding of markets for exports from the United States. In negotiating
                        trade agreements under this act an attempt has usually been made to strike a
                        fairly even balance between the concessions obtained for United States
                        exports and the concessions granted for exports from other countries. In
                        view of the particular need currently for exports to the United States from
                        other countries in balance of payments difficulties, it is believed by many
                        that this criteria of even balance and emphasizing only markets for United
                        States exports, is no longer adequate.</p>
                    <pb facs="0167" n="141" xml:id="pg_141"/>
                    <p>In addition to the consideration of much broader foreign policy objectives as
                        purposes for which trade agreements may be entered into under the Trade
                        Agreements Act, consideration is also being given to the possibility of
                        tariff reductions being made, either by Congress or the Executive other than
                        as a part of negotiated trade agreements. One proposal has been that
                        Congress reduce to 50% ad valorem, or the equivalent thereof, all rates in
                        excess of that rate and that the Executive be given authority thereafter to
                        reduce any tariff rate to 10% ad valorem (or to 12½ ad valorem which is
                        understood to be the approximate average level of our tariff) or to the ad
                        valorem equivalent of any such rate in the case of specific duties. At least
                        one-half of this reduction by the Executive would have to be pursuant to
                        trade agreements of the type heretofore concluded; the other half could be
                        reduced by the Executive without requiring the usual type of trade-agreement
                        commitment from the other country. Since some of the measures which the
                        United States may wish to try to persuade other countries to adopt, such as
                        reforms in their internal fiscal policies, are not the type of measures to
                        which they would be willing to bind themselves in formal agreements, it has
                        been proposed that the Executive be given this authority to make unilateral
                        reductions in particular cases, presumably where other countries adopt such
                        measures, without formal commitments on either side.</p>
                    <p>Another rather complicated proposal for unilateral action would be the
                        grouping of products into related classifications, and the determination of
                        the average rate now applicable to products in each group. Then the rate for
                        all products in the group would be fixed at 40% ad valorem if the average
                        were above 40%, at 30% ad valorem if the average were between 30% and 40%,
                        et cetera. Special treatment would be given to specific rates, to rates
                        which were wholly or partly specific, and to rates on products of particular
                        strategic significance.</p>
                    <p>In view of the talk of an early adjournment by Congress and in view of the
                        importance of some of the other trade problems which are discussed below,
                        there may, be considerable likelihood at this session of a simple extension
                        of the authority to conclude trade agreements, or at least of action without
                        increased authority to reduce tariffs. Some opportunity may be presented for
                        adding to the law in some form one or more of the following new bases for
                        tariff reduction: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Unilateral reduction by the Executive other than pursuant to
                                formal trade agreements;</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Authority to reduce particularly high rates to a specified level
                                without regard to limitations applicable to other reductions;</item>
                            <pb facs="0168" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Authority to make a series of relatively moderate reductions, each
                                successive reduction being permissible only after the next preceding
                                reduction has been in effect for a specified time; or</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>A broadening of the purposes for which trade agreements may be
                                entered into.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">II. Related Problems</hi></p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade</hi></p>
                    <p>Although the provisions of the Trade Agreements Act itself are directed
                        principally to authority to reduce duties, the Act also authorizes the
                        modification of import restrictions, the imposition of new restrictions and
                        the continuation of existing customs treatment. Most of the 30-odd bilateral
                        trade agreements which were concluded between 1934 and 1946 contain, in
                        addition to provisions putting into effect the reductions and bindings of
                        duties, rather extensive provisions relating to other trade controls, many
                        of them designed to protect the tariff concessions from impairment. The most
                        important of these were prohibitions, with specified exceptions, against the
                        imposition of quantitative restrictions on the importation of products on
                        which tariff concessions had been granted, most-favored-nation treatment
                        with respect to duties and restrictions on importation, and national
                        treatment as to the taxation of imported products. Occasionally various
                        provisions of this nature had been referred to with approval in the reports
                        of Congressional committees recommending extension of the President’s
                        authority to enter into new trade agreements.</p>
                    <p>During and after the second World War the United States took the leadership
                        in attempting to work out a multilateral code of international trade
                        practices to be administered by an organization. A preparatory committee, to
                        work out the charter of this organization for submission to a world
                        conference, was set up by the Economic and Social Council of the United
                        Nations in 1946. That preparatory committee decided at its first session in
                        1946 that, in addition to work on the draft charter for the International
                        Trade Organization, negotiations for reduction of tariffs should be
                        undertaken at its second session to be held at Geneva in 1947, without
                        waiting for completion of the charter. The report of a drafting committee
                        set up by this first session contained a preliminary draft of the agreement
                        which might be concluded at the end of such tariff negotiations, which would
                        provisionally contain most of the articles of the draft charter relating to
                        commercial policy. These were in general an elaboration, on a multilateral
                        basis, of the general rules and exceptions thereto contained in bilateral
                        trade agreements. The draft tariff agreement also provided for an interim
                        trade committee to carry on various administrative functions in many
                        respects parallel with the functions relating to commercial policy <pb facs="0169" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/> which it was envisaged would
                        subsequently be carried on by the organization under the draft charter.</p>
                    <p>On the eve of the Geneva Session of the preparatory committee, the Finance
                        Committee of the Republican 80th Congress held hearings on the draft of the
                        Charter to be considered at that meeting. In the course of such hearings
                        some attention was given by the committee to the draft tariff agreement. The
                        view was expressed by Senator Milliken, then and now Chairman of the Finance
                        Committee, that although it had been stated that the Charter of the
                        International Trade Organization would be brought back to Congress, as had
                        been the charters of numerous other organizations, the tariff agreement was
                        an attempt to set up a comparable organization without obtaining
                        Congressional approval. The Finance Committee was assured that this would
                        not be done, and that no provisions of the tariff agreement would purport to
                        override existing legislation.</p>
                    <p>The tariff agreement was negotiated in 1947 under the name of the General
                        Agreement on Tariffs and Trade and came into effect in January 1948. The
                        references in the draft to action by the interim trade committee were
                        changed to action by the contracting parties to the agreement acting
                        jointly, and provision was made that most of the general rules applicable to
                        trade, as distinguished from the tariff concessions for which there was more
                        specific authority in the Trade Agreements Act, would be applicable only to
                        the extent not inconsistent with existing legislation.</p>
                    <p>It had been anticipated that upon the entry into force of the Charter for the
                        International Trade Organization most of the general rules governing trade
                        contained in the General Agreement would be superseded by the comparable
                        provisions of the Charter, and that the General Agreement would remain
                        principally as an agreement applying the tariff concessions negotiated from
                        time to time. However, the International Trade Organization was never set
                        up, and these general rules have remained in the General Agreement. The
                        contracting parties to the General Agreement have held eight sessions to
                        consider various problems under the agreement relating both to the tariff
                        concessions and the general rules as to trade. They have also held two
                        longer sets of tariff negotiations for the addition of new contracting
                        parties and new tariff concessions, and now have a number of committees to
                        work on matters pending or arising between sessions.</p>
                    <p>Due to this early situation as to the relationship between the General
                        Agreement and the International Trade Organization Charter, to the scope and
                        complexity of the general trade provisions in the multilateral general
                        agreement, and to some extent to the wide imposition by other countries of
                        restrictions on exports from the United States, which are justified on
                        balance-of-payments <pb facs="0170" n="144" xml:id="pg_144"/> grounds under
                        terms of the agreement, many questions have been raised both in Congress and
                        in business groups, regarding the agreement. A number have related to the
                        legal authority for some of its provisions, while others are based on policy
                        considerations. The questions usually single out the General Agreement
                        itself, as distinguished from the trade agreements program as a whole.</p>
                    <p>This feeling was reflected in the statement in the Senate report in 1949
                        recommending extension of the President’s authority to conclude new
                        agreements, following a detailed examination of the General Agreement by
                        Senator Millikin<note n="3" xml:id="d42fn3">Eugene Millikin (R.-Colo.),
                            Chairman of the Senate Finance Committee.</note> and officers of this
                        Department, that the favorable report “is not intended to commit the
                        Congress on questions raised by the incorporation of general regulatory
                        provisions in the multilateral trade agreement recently concluded at Geneva
                        or on any other aspect of our foreign trade program”. This was followed by a
                        statement that full consideration of such matters would no doubt be
                        undertaken when the International Trade Organization Charter was submitted
                        to Congress.</p>
                    <p>The Trade Agreements Extension Act of 1951, extending, with amendments, the
                        President’s authority to conclude new agreements, contains a separate
                        article stating that “the enactment of this Act shall not be construed to
                        determine or indicate the approval or disapproval by the Congress of the
                        Executive Agreement known as the General Agreement on Tariffs and
                        Trade”.</p>
                    <p>In addition to these general questions, a problem exists with respect to the
                        financing of participation by the United States in the activities of the
                        contracting parties. Since there has been neither express Congressional
                        approval of the agreement nor authorization for any appropriation for this
                        purpose, participation has been financed through the general international
                        contingencies appropriation of the Department of State. If questions should
                        be raised with respect to a continuation of this practice during
                        consideration of the budget of the Department of State considerable
                        embarrassment might be caused to the participation by this country in the
                        activities of the contracting parties.</p>
                    <p>From the above it seems clearly evident that a meeting of the minds with
                        respect to the General Agreement, perhaps with various amendments, should be
                        reached between the Executive and the Congress. The Executive has felt that
                        the President has had ample authority under the Trade Agreements Act and his
                        general authority with respect to the conduct of foreign relations to enter
                        into the General Agreement and to modify its provisions from time to time as
                        amendments were considered appropriate. Consequently, it would seem
                        preferable to have Congress merely authorize appropriation <pb facs="0171" n="145" xml:id="pg_145"/> for participation by the United States in the
                        agreement, or to authorize participation in the contracting parties as an
                        organization. Any such authorization would of course entail a detailed
                        examination of the agreement by the Congress. It might, of course, be quite
                        difficult to obtain from the Congress approval in such a form leaving full
                        discretion with the Executive, even with more or less informal Congressional
                        proposals for amendment of the agreement.</p>
                    <p>It seems likely that, following a minute examination of the General
                        Agreement, Congress would want to express itself in a formal manner as to
                        the agreement as such, presumably approving it subject to its being amended
                        in important respects. Such action might cause considerable difficulty. In
                        the first place, very important parts of the agreement are the schedules of
                        tariff concessions, which on the part of the United States, are clearly
                        within the prior authorization given to the President in the Trade
                        Agreements Act. A basic purpose of that act has been to place tariff making
                        in the hands of the Executive rather than of Congress, and subsequently
                        approval of the whole General Agreement by the Congress would raise
                        important questions as to whether a review of Executive tariff making was
                        not being brought back into the Congress with its attendant dangers.
                        Moreover, such positive action by the Congress now approving the whole
                        agreement would appear to cast serious doubt as to the prior legality of at
                        least parts of the agreement, which has been considered by the Executive as
                        having been validly in effect since 1948.</p>
                    <p>Finally, if the exact text is approved it might be specifically required, or
                        argued by implication, that all protocols of amendment or modifications of
                        the agreement, of which there have been a considerable number (in many
                        instances the modifications have been either relatively minor or of little
                        concern to the United States), should themselves receive formal
                        Congressional approval before they could be accepted by the United States.
                        Such a procedure would greatly delay action by the United States on these
                        documents and appear to take up an unnecessary amount of the time of both
                        the Executive and the Congress.</p>
                    <p>An approach to this problem to which consideration is now being given, which
                        might be a compromise if it seems impossible to obtain simple authorization,
                        is to add to the Trade Agreements Act, either with some express reference to
                        the General Agreement or in a manner applying to all trade agreements,
                        relatively general standards covering general rules as to trade and some of
                        the more important exceptions thereto, which would have to be included in
                        the relevant agreements under that Act. At the same time authorization might
                        be obtained for an appropriation either for participation in the General
                        Agreement or, more generally, for participation <pb facs="0172" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/> in continuing administrative arrangements for carrying
                        out a trade agreement. It is hoped that the formulation of such standards by
                        Congress, which might well require the amendment of the General Agreement in
                        some respects, would be considered by the Congressional critics of the
                        agreement as sufficient participation by the Congress, and that the more
                        formal submission of the agreement as such for approval could be
                        avoided.</p>
                    <p>It is felt by some that the general rules as to trade in the General
                        Agreement, as well as in the International Trade Organization, are too
                        complicated, and it has been proposed that the General Agreement be reduced
                        to an agreement putting into effect the tariff concessions. It would then be
                        supplemented by a purely consultative organization with respect to trade
                        matters which could make recommendations as to the general rules but without
                        any binding rules and exceptions such as are now in the General Agreement.
                        The general feeling within the Department seems to be that this would be a
                        most unfortunate backward step. In the first place, many of the general
                        rules in the agreement are important to prevent, or at least limit, evasion
                        of the tariff concessions through the imposition of other trade controls.
                        Moreover, most of the detailed rules and procedures, including provisions
                        for action by the contracting parties acting jointly, relate not to the
                        laying down of additional obligations but are exceptions to relatively
                        simple general rules.</p>
                    <p>There are practically no instances in which the contracting parties acting
                        jointly could tell the United States that they must take certain action; on
                        the other hand, the United States has utilized in many instances provisions
                        of the agreement permitting flexibility, notably to obtain a complete
                        release from its obligations to Czechoslovakia under the agreement, in order
                        to put into effect Congressional desires. In practice the contracting
                        parties attempt to assist individual countries in working out their
                        difficulties with each other, frequently making recommendations as well as
                        interpretations of the General Agreement. Of course, as in the case of
                        participation in almost any multilateral agreement, the United States
                        becomes only a minority of one when questions of interpretation are
                        involved.</p>
                    <p>Although the authority of the contracting parties acting jointly is generally
                        limited to the interpretation of obligations which an individual party has
                        undertaken in the agreement, rather than to placing any new requirements
                        upon a party, there are a number of instances under which sanctions may be
                        applied in the form of retaliatory action by injured contracting parties
                        which would not otherwise be permitted under the agreement. In most cases
                        the retaliation must be approved by the contracting parties acting jointly.
                            <pb facs="0173" n="147" xml:id="pg_147"/> These retaliatory provisions
                        have been utilized very sparingly, but it is felt that their existence gives
                        a vitality to the conduct of business by the contracting parties which would
                        be absent if their meetings should be replaced by a purely consultative
                        body.</p>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Quantitative Restrictions</hi></p>
                    <p>In order to protect the concessions which had been granted on particular
                        products in the schedules annexed thereto, most of the bilateral trade
                        agreements contained prohibitions, subject to specified exceptions, against
                        the imposition of quantitative restrictions on the importation of such
                        products. The exceptions usually included permission to impose restrictions
                        in connection with various agricultural programs.</p>
                    <p>At the time the General Agreement was entered into Section 22 of the
                        Agricultural Adjustment Act, as amended,<note n="4" xml:id="d42fn4">Section
                            22 was enacted into law on Aug. 24, 1935, as one provision of the
                            amended Agricultural Adjustment Act (Public Law 318) and was reenacted
                            on June 3, 1937, as part of the Agricultural Marketing Agreement Act of
                            1937 (Public Law 137). For texts, see 49 Stat. 773 and 50 Stat.
                            246.</note> required the President to impose restrictions on imports of
                        agricultural products when he found such restrictions necessary to prevent
                        imports from materially interfering with certain agricultural programs,
                        including programs in which domestic production or marketing was restricted.
                        The General Agreement contains a broad prohibition against quantitative
                        restrictions on imports of any product, whether or not included in the
                        schedules to the agreement, but subject to various exceptions. Among these
                        is an exception for agricultural products in cases in which domestic
                        production or marketing is also restricted. However, in such cases the
                        import restrictions may not under the Agreement reduce the proportion of
                        domestic consumption that may be supplied by imports below the proportion
                        thereof during a previous representative period.</p>
                    <p>Shortly after the General Agreement went into effect Section 22 of the
                        Agricultural Adjustment Act was further amended<note n="5" xml:id="d42fn5">Section 22 of the Agricultural Act of 1948 (Public Law 897), enacted
                            July 3, 1948; for text, see 62 Stat. 1249.</note> to require the
                        imposition of quantitative restrictions if imports were likely to interfere
                        with any price support program, in many of which there are now no provisions
                        for the restriction of domestic production or marketing. At the same time a
                        new subsection was added to the effect that Section 22 should not be applied
                        in any manner which would conflict with an international obligation of the
                        United States. The latter provision, protecting international obligations,
                        has subsequently been practically reversed by Congress so that now it
                        provides, in effect, that no international obligations shall prevent the
                        application of Section 22. Although there have <pb facs="0174" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/> been no proclamations issued under this new Section 22
                        in order to prevent imports from interfering with a price support program
                        under which there is no restriction of domestic production or marketing, the
                        Tariff Commission now has under consideration a proposed application of
                        Section 22 with respect to wool which would raise problems of this nature if
                        it should lead to Presidential action putting into effect quantitative
                        restrictions on imported wool.</p>
                    <p>It is recognized that action by the Government which has the effect of
                        maintaining a relatively high price for agricultural commodities tends to
                        make this market a particularly attractive one for imports, and therefore to
                        attract imports which add to the cost to the Government of maintaining its
                        price support program. Recognizing the validity of the arguments for the
                        imposition of some quantitative restrictions in this type of situation,
                        consideration is being given to a change in our policy, which would involve
                        a change in the General Agreement, to permit restrictions in such a case
                        provided they do not reduce the proportion of the American market supplied
                        by imports below that proportion which they would normally have supplied. In
                        other words imports may not come in merely to replace domestic production,
                        but may come in to maintain their proportionate share of any increase in
                        domestic consumption. This new approach would also require a modification of
                        Section 22, which now permits the limitation of imports to 50% of the
                        quantity imported during a previous representative period rather than to
                        100% of the proportion of domestic consumption supplied by imports during
                        such a period, as would be the limit under the new proposal.</p>
                    <p>Another important exception in the General Agreement for agricultural
                        interests is that relating to commodity agreements, which covers other raw
                        materials as well. Before World War II the United States was a party to
                        commodity agreements designed to assist in maintaining fair prices for sugar
                        and coffee. Although the substantive provisions of these agreements have
                        lapsed, a conference is scheduled for next summer to consider a new sugar
                        agreement, and the wheat agreement, which has been in effect for about four
                        years, is currently under renegotiation. Some consideration has also been
                        given since the war to agreements on tin and cotton.</p>
                    <p>In 1947 the Economic and Social Council of the United Nations laid down
                        principles that should be applied in the conclusion of commodity agreements,
                        including the representation therein of both producing and consuming
                        interests. These principles, together with procedures for studies which
                        might lead to commodity agreements, were embodied in a commodity chapter of
                        the International Trade Organization Charter. The General Agreement contains
                        no express statement of the principles, but excepts from the general <pb facs="0175" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> prohibitions against restrictions
                        on importation and exportation, measures undertaken pursuant to an agreement
                        conforming to the principles laid down by the Economic and Social
                        Council.</p>
                    <p>The policy of the United States has been to limit commodity agreements to
                        cases in which there was an actual threat of a burdensome surplus. The
                        current thinking, however, is that such agreements may be justified for
                        commodities the general history as to the production of which shows a
                        likelihood that a burdensome surplus might develop at some time in the
                        future, even though there is no present threat of such a surplus.</p>
                    <p>The basic economic difficulty between the United States and Europe since the
                        War—the serious dollar balance-of-payments deficits of most European
                        countries—has left its mark on the General Agreement and on the operations
                        under it. The Agreement permits the imposition of quantitative restrictions
                        by a country to protect its reserve position, and, in rather vague language,
                        permits countries imposing such restrictions for balance-of-payments reasons
                        to discriminate in their application. These provisions are quite detailed,
                        more as to the procedures which they set up than as to the substantive rules
                        to be applied. They have been the subject of considerable domestic criticism
                        because of the extent to which they permit countries to impose restrictions,
                        even discriminatory restrictions, against the United States.</p>
                    <p>In connection with the European Recovery Program<note n="6" xml:id="d42fn6">For documentation concerning the formulation and early operation of the
                                <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss>, or Marshall Plan, see <ref target="frus1947v03#pg_197"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations,</hi> 1947, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp.
                                197</ref> ff.</note> the United States has encouraged the relaxation
                        by European countries of their restrictions among themselves while
                        recognizing their right to retain them against the dollar area. There is no
                        doubt that the continuance in effect over a long period of restrictions for
                        balance-of-payments reasons creates a considerable amount of protection for
                        domestic industry and that there are numerous opportunities for abuse of the
                        exceptions. This and other problems relating to these restrictions have been
                        the subject of rather close examination during the more recent meetings of
                        the contracting parties, in a general exploratory fashion rather than
                        through the bringing of particular complaints.</p>
                    <p>The exceptions permitting the balance-of-payments restrictions require their
                        relaxation or removal when the reserve position has been strengthened
                        sufficiently to warrant such a removal. This provision has led to one
                        particular difficult problem with respect principally to the sterling area
                        discussion of which among the Contracting Parties has been seriously
                        avoided. This is the question whether when the trade position of a
                        particular member of the area, as <pb facs="0176" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/>
                        Ceylon, has improved so that when viewed alone it might be considered as
                        being in a position to relax or eliminate its restrictions on the dollar
                        area it should be required to do so without recognizing its obligations
                        under the sterling area arrangement to make available to the sterling area
                        dollar pool a substantial proportion of its dollar earnings. Although this
                        Government has attempted to reserve its rights with respect to this point,
                        its continued failures to press for relaxation or elimination of
                        restrictions in such cases because of the political implications involved
                        seem to weaken its position considerably. Operations under the European
                        Payments Union may lead to comparable conflicts of policy.</p>
                    <p>It was envisaged, at the time the General Agreement was drafted, that the
                        balance-of-payments difficulties following the War would in most cases not
                        continue beyond 1951 and many of the complicated provisions of the agreement
                        relating to the application of restrictions to protect reserves were drafted
                        with such a relatively transitional period in mind. Although this situation
                        has not been cleared up as quickly as had been anticipated, the current
                        feeling is that we should continue to consider such restrictions, and the
                        discriminations in their application, as transitional and operate under them
                        in the expectation that the time will come when they are unnecessary on the
                        return of the general convertibility of currencies. Moreover, there is
                        considerable feeling that these balance-of-payments provisions of the
                        General Agreement are unnecessarily detailed and complicated, principally as
                        to procedures for considering the balance-of-payments problems, and that
                        consequently it would be desirable to replace them by more simplified
                        provisions.</p>
                    <p>Formation of the European Coal and Steel Community, which was supported by
                        the United States for reasons of broad political and military policy,
                        presented particular problems with respect to the discriminatory application
                        of both quantitative restrictions and tariffs. The plan envisages the
                        substantial elimination of trade barriers among the six participating
                        countries with respect to the coal and steel products. Rather broad waiver
                        provisions in the General Agreement were utilized to permit the
                        participating countries to put the community into operation.</p>
                    <p>A particular problem with respect to quantitative restrictions for the United
                        States has been the conflict between the General Agreement and Section 104
                        of the Defense Production Act, first enacted in the summer of 1951. This
                        section requires the imposition of quantitative restrictions on the
                        importation of dairy products and certain other specified imports when it is
                        found that certain situations exist for which there is no exception in the
                        General Agreement. Notwithstanding the fact that Congress, in enacting the
                        legislation, stated that it was necessary for the security interest of the
                            <pb facs="0177" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/> United States in language
                        following that of the security exception to the General Agreement, the
                        Executive has not considered that there is sufficient relationship between
                        the controls and our security to justify the restrictions which the
                        Secretary of Agriculture has found necessary under this legislation.</p>
                    <p>In the case of most of the restrictions which have been imposed under this
                        legislation, the more important of which have been on cheese, the United
                        States has admitted a violation of the General Agreement, and one injured
                        contracting party has been permitted by the contracting parties jointly
                        under the agreement to retaliate against United States exports of flour.</p>
                    <p>The Executive opposed an enactment of the section, which was inserted in the
                        legislation rather hurriedly at an advanced stage in consideration of the
                        bill. Promptly upon its enactment legislation for its repeal was introduced,
                        but was never passed. In extending the Defense Production Act in the summer
                        of 1952 Congress liberalized the provision somewhat, but without removing
                        the violations of the General Agreement. At that time the Executive had been
                        willing to accept as a compromise language of an earlier act which permitted
                        the imposition of restrictions under situations of surplus or short supply
                        of the products involved. This proposed language follows an exception in the
                        General Agreement applicable originally only to the transitional period
                        prior to 1951, but the application of which is being currently extended by
                        action of the contracting parties jointly.</p>
                    <p>3. <hi rend="italic">No-injury Test</hi></p>
                    <p>Some of the early bilateral Trade Agreements contained variously worded
                        provisions under which concessions could be withdrawn if imports under them
                        were causing serious injuries to a domestic industry. These culminated in
                        the so-called “escape clause” in the Mexican trade agreement of 1942,<note n="7" xml:id="d42fn7">Article XI, “Agreement Between the United States
                            of America and Mexico Respecting Reciprocal Trade,” signed on Dec. 23,
                            1942; for text, see 57 Stat. 845.</note> under which concessions could
                        be withdrawn in case of serious injury or threat thereof to a domestic
                        industry resulting from increased imports under the concession. Moreover,
                        during various discussions regarding trade agreement legislation with
                        Congress statements had also been made that the trade agreements program
                        would not be carried out in such a manner as to cause serious injury. In
                        1945 President Truman wrote to Congress that his administration would follow
                        this policy which had been followed by the Roosevelt administration.</p>
                    <p>Early in 1947, as a result of discussions between an official of the State
                        Department and Senate leaders in the Republican 80th Congress, an Executive
                        Order was issued providing that all new trade <pb facs="0178" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/> agreements should contain an escape clause along the
                        lines of that in the Mexican trade agreement. It also set up a procedure
                        whereby Tariff Commission would make investigations in cases in which it was
                        claimed that serious injury might be caused or threatened as a result of a
                        concession in an agreement having such a clause and make recommendations to
                        the President regarding the claim. An escape clause of this type is included
                        in the General Agreement.<note n="8" xml:id="d42fn8">Article XIX, “Emergency
                            Action on Imports of Particular Products,” General Agreement on Tariffs
                            and Trade.</note></p>
                    <p>The Trade Agreement Extension Act of 1948,<note n="9" xml:id="d42fn9">Public
                            Law 792, enacted June 26, 1948; for text, see 62 Stat. 1053.</note>
                        passed by the 80th Congress, added a new phase to the no-serious injury
                        approach. In substance it provided that, before a trade agreement should be
                        entered into, the President should submit to the Tariff Commission a list of
                        the products on which tariff concessions might be granted. The Commission
                        should report the extent to which it considered a concession could be
                        granted on each product in the list without causing or threatening serious
                        injury to an American industry. If the President granted a concession on any
                        product greater than that which the Tariff Commission found could be granted
                        without such injury or threat, he should report his action to Congress and
                        the Tariff Commission should transmit its peril point finding to Congress.
                        These provisions were followed in preparation for the trade agreement
                        negotiations at Annecy in 1949, but were repealed by the Trade Agreement
                        Extension Act of 1949,<note n="10" xml:id="d42fn10">Public Law 307, enacted
                            Sept. 26, 1949; for text, see 63 Stat. 597.</note> enacted by the 81st
                        Congress before the conclusion of the agreement embodying such
                        negotiations.</p>
                    <p>The Trade Agreement Extension Act of 1951<note n="11" xml:id="d42fn11">Public
                            Law 50, enacted June 16, 1951; for text, see 65 Stat. 72.</note>
                        reenacted the peril point provisions with relatively little change, and also
                        added to the trade agreements legislation provisions regarding escape
                        clauses and action thereunder. In rather ambiguous language it laid down the
                        escape clause principles and required the inclusion of such escape clauses
                        in all such future trade agreements. In addition, it directed action toward
                        the inclusion of escape clauses in existing trade agreements and set up a
                        new procedure for Tariff Commission investigations and recommendations to
                        the President under escape clauses. As in the case of peril point findings,
                        the President is not required to put into effect recommendations of the
                        Tariff Commission for the withdrawal of modification of concessions but if
                        he fails to do so he is required to report his reasons to Congress.</p>
                    <p>Enactment of this legislation was followed by a flood of applications for
                        escape clause action, upon which the Tariff Commission is <pb facs="0179" n="153" xml:id="pg_153"/> required to report within one year. In several
                        cases the Commission had failed to recommend action, in three cases (one
                        preceding the 1951 act) escape clause modifications have been put into
                        effect, and in two cases the President had rejected recommendations,
                        questioning and finding of serious injury or threat thereof. President
                        Eisenhower has deferred action, and requested further information from the
                        Commission, in the only case that has come to him for decision.</p>
                    <p>The reaction abroad, principally in Italy and other Western European
                        countries, to the escape clause actions that have been put into effect has
                        been quite strong. Not only has it been felt that the particular actions
                        interfere with the program for an expansion of exports to the United States
                        by countries so badly in need of dollar earnings, but it is pointed out that
                        the possibility that a future expansion of exports of any product may result
                        in escape clause action has a generally deadening effect upon attempts to
                        stimulate this much needed trade expansion.</p>
                    <p>In view of the unfortunate effect of these escape clause actions,
                        consideration has been given to various means of alleviating the situation.
                        Some would relate to detailed questions of interpreting such terms as
                        “serious injury” under certain circumstances, or to the scope of the concept
                        of an “industry” which might suffer injury. Another approach has been to
                        have a body composed differently from the Tariff Commission take into
                        consideration both the questions of injury and of the broader public
                        interest which may be involved in escape clause actions. A third approach
                        would be only to permit escape clause action when the economy of the United
                        States as a whole, rather than an individual industry, is suffering injury
                        from the imports.</p>
                    <p>Finally, some thought has been given to replacing the “no-injury” concept by
                        provision for making payments by the Government to enterprises injured by
                        tariff reductions. These might include various types of assistance to labor,
                        in the form of dismissal wages or retraining programs, and of assistance to
                        capital either through direct compensation for loss suffered by the
                        enterprise or through a low interest loan (on possibly a grant) to help
                        enterprises to readjust themselves in other lines of activity.</p>
                    <p>In view of the development of the no-injury concept, as previously embodied
                        in the escape clause provision of the 1947 Executive Order and the peril
                        point provision of the 1948 Act, it might be considered doubtful whether
                        substantial change could be gotten. However, realization of the extent to
                        which other countries, particularly in Western Europe, need to increase
                        their exports to the United States would seem to justify the continuing
                        examination of this aspect of the trade agreement program. It might be
                        possible to <pb facs="0180" n="154" xml:id="pg_154"/> obtain at least some
                        substantial relaxation in the criteria to be applied under the escape
                        clause.</p>
                    <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Buy American Provisions</hi></p>
                    <p>In 1933 legislation<note n="12" xml:id="d42fn12">Title III of the
                            Appropriations Act of 1933 (Public Law 428), approved Mar. 3, 1933; for
                            text of Act, see 47 Stat. 1489.</note> was enacted requiring, in quite
                        general language, that Government purchases of goods for use in the United
                        States should be of United States products except where the public interest
                        required otherwise or the cost of such products was unreasonably high. For
                        some time the cost of American goods have been considered as unreasonably
                        high if their prices were more than 25% above the prices of available
                        foreign products.</p>
                    <p>Recently, there have been a number of requests by Western European countries,
                        notably the United Kingdom and Italy, with respect to the rejection of bids
                        by producers in those countries at a time when we have encouraged the
                        countries to increase their dollar exports. A bill was introduced during the
                        last session of Congress to repeal this buy-American legislation, and the
                        prevailing thinking in the Department is that this would be the best way of
                        taking care of the problem.</p>
                    <p>Thought is also being given to the possibility of increasing the use of
                        foreign goods through an interpretation that, under existing circumstances,
                        purchase of such foreign products is in the public interest within the
                        meaning of the statute. It has also been suggested that the percentage by
                        which the American price must exceed the foreign price before the American
                        price will be considered unreasonably high might, by interpretation, be
                        reduced below 25%.</p>
                    <p>The Defense Department Appropriation Act for the present fiscal year has a
                        particular provision which in effect requires not only that American
                        textiles be purchased but textiles manufactured from American raw
                        material.</p>
                    <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Custom Simplification</hi></p>
                    <p>The Executive introduced into the 81st Congress a Custom Simplification Bill
                        which had been worked out on an interdepartmental basis to include
                        recommendations made by a firm of efficient experts which had investigated
                        the Customs Bureau, and modifications in customs and internal revenue
                        legislation which would be necessary to put the General Agreement into
                        effect definitively (as distinguished from the present application of some
                        ports only to the extent not inconsistent with existing legislation). No
                        action was taken on the bill in the 81st Congress, but it was re-introduced
                        in the 82nd Congress where it passed the House, with important amendments,
                        and hearings were held in the Senate.</p>
                    <pb facs="0181" n="155" xml:id="pg_155"/>
                    <p>It is felt both that provisions deleted by the House were of considerable
                        importance, that there are numerous other modifications which might be added
                        to the earlier bills, some of them proposed during the Senate hearings and
                        considered quite uncontroversial. Consideration is now being given in
                        consultation with the Treasury to pressing for the passage of a broad bill
                        at this session, although it is recognized that another approach would be to
                        have two bills one with the more uncontroversial provisions with a view to
                        having it passed as quickly as possible, and the other containing additional
                        more controversial provisions.</p>
                    <p>Considerable interest has been expressed by some countries, particularly
                        Canada, in these bills, but it is feared that they may overestimate the
                        effect of such a bill, especially if it should be limited to the less
                        controversial provisions.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>