<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 664Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                    International Security Affairs (Davis) to the Director of the Foreign Operations
                    Administration (Stassen)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v06p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d664</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">664</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-10-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-10-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recwtK4pWGzcpfduJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">USCINCEUR</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rec8f8ab487d399bce" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="mutual-defense-assistance-program">Mutual Defense Assistance Program</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-10-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-10-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="664"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d664">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_DMS1">DMS</gloss> files, lot W–1444, “France”</note>
                <head>No. 664<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                        International Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_DAVISVAAC1"
                            type="from">Davis</persName>) to the Director of the Foreign Operations
                        Administration (<persName corresp="#p_STASSENHE1" type="to"
                            >Stassen</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d664fn1">Copies of this memorandum were sent to Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1">Dulles</persName> and Director of the
                        Budget <persName corresp="#p_HUGHESRR1">Hughes</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-10-20">October 20,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject: Aid to France</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Reference is made to your memorandum to the Secretary of Defense, dated 29
                        September 1954,<note n="2" xml:id="d664fn2">
                            <ref target="#d662">Document 662</ref>.</note> subject as above, which
                        was referred to this office for reply.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The National Security Council in their paper 5433/1, dated 25 September
                            1954,<note n="3" xml:id="d664fn3">For text, see <ref
                                target="frus1952-54v05p2#pg_1268">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>,
                                Part 2, p. 1268</ref>.</note> established a policy that “under
                        present circumstances and until the situation has been further clarified,
                        slow down U.S. aid to France and make no new financial commitments to
                        France.” In implementing this policy, Department of Defense has forwarded
                        memoranda to the Secretaries of the three Military Departments requesting
                        that until further notice no new financial commitments be made to France and
                        implementing action be taken without delay to slow down Mutual Defense
                        Assistance Program shipments to France.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Based on a request by American Embassy, Paris, Department of Defense
                        dispatched instructions to <gloss target="#t_USCINCEUR1">USCINCEUR</gloss>
                        on 27 July 1954 stopping all proposed awards on Mutual Defense Assistance
                        Program/Offshore Procurement contracts to the Government of France or
                        private contractors in France. These instructions also requested that
                        current negotiations, if any, would be suspended and no new discussions of
                        negotiations with French contractors would be instituted.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Thus, part of the action suggested in your memorandum of 29 September has
                        already been accomplished. However, your suggestion that during the months
                        of October and November 1954 legitimate payments due the French under our
                        Defense contracts be purposely delayed is not favorably considered by the
                        Department of Defense.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Serious objections have been raised by the three Military Departments
                        concerning the implementation of this suggestion. Primarily these objections
                        are: <pb facs="0365" n="1455" xml:id="pg_1455"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>(a)</label>
                            <item>Increased administrative burden in administering offshore
                                contracts.</item>
                            <label>(b)</label>
                            <item>The integrity of our military contracting officers and the
                                services they represent may be open to serious question by the
                                French.</item>
                            <label>(c)</label>
                            <item>Retaliatory action by the French, such as slowing down
                                deliveries.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>One of our compelling bargaining tools to obtain low prices and
                        satisfactory delivery schedules from the French on existing contracts was
                        every assurance by our contracting officers to the manufacturers that
                        payments would be accomplished promptly to offset their short working
                        capital position. To date prompt payments have been effected to the maximum
                        extent practicable. Implementation of the proposed action would place our
                        contracting personnel in a most undesirable position of being justly accused
                        of breach of faith. The effect of this on our future contracting in Western
                        Europe not only for Mutual Defense Assistance Program end items, but also
                        logistical support of United States units deployed there, is readily
                        apparent.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Retaliatory action by the French to perhaps hold back deliveries could be
                        expected. We would then be confronted with the late receipt of urgently
                        needed items as well as concurrent contracting problems generated by
                        contract delinquencies.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>For the above reasons, therefore, we would prefer not to delay payments
                        under our existing French contracts. We are in agreement with your other
                        suggestions and, as previously indicated, implementing action has already
                        been initiated.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAVISVAAC1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. C. Davis</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
