<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 674United States Minutes of the Third Plenary Meeting Between United
                    States and French Representatives, at the Department of State, November 19,
                    1954, 3:30 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v06p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-11-19T15:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-11-19T15:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recQvPtoqiukOAmlM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="receiqhGHZGpcOok4" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">SACEUR</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-11-19T15:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-11-19T15:30:00-05:00" n="674"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d674">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 398</note>
                <head>No. 674<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Minutes of the Third Plenary Meeting Between
                        United States and French Representatives, at the Department of State,
                        November 19, 1954, 3:30 p.m.</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d674fn1">Drafted on Nov. 23. These minutes, along with a
                        cover sheet and a brief index, were circulated as document <gloss
                            target="#t_MFT1">MFT</gloss> Plenary Min 3.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1954-11-19T15:30:00-05:00">November 19, 1954, 3:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>
                        <list type="simple">
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">US</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">State</hi>
                            </item>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MACARTHURDII1">MacArthur</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DILLONCD1">Dillon</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ROBERTSONWS1">Robertson</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>McCardle</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NOLTINGFE1">Nolting</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Utter</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BEIGELEJ1">Beigel</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_FISHERWD1">Fisher</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MOOREBT1">Moore</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Jones</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName>Young</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <list type="simple">
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Defense</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>Asst. Secy. <persName corresp="#p_HENSELHS1">Hensel</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Admiral <persName corresp="#p_DAVISVAAC1">Davis</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss>
                            </item>
                            <item>General <persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1">Porter</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <list type="simple">
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">France</hi>
                            </head>
                            <item>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                                    >Mendès-France</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BONNETH1">Bonnet</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Roux</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_BORISG1">Boris</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Juniac</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_SEYDOUXDECLAUSSONNER1">Seydoux</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>de La Grandville</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_SOUTOUJ1">Soutou</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Cheysson</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName corresp="#p_MARTINEM1">Martin</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Vimont</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Tine</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Andronikof</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Froment-Meurice</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>M. <persName>Ruffin</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0398" n="1488" xml:id="pg_1488"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Indochina—Joint Instructions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary opened the meeting by suggesting that agreement be reached on the
                    text of the joint instructions to US and French representatives in
                        Indochina.<note n="2" xml:id="d674fn2">For the text of this joint
                        instruction, sent to Saigon in telegram 2055 of Nov. 20, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v13p2#pg_2274">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>,
                            Part 2, p. 2274</ref>.</note> He proposed the several drafting
                    modifications which were accepted by Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName>. The most significant
                    one of which involved the elimination of a statement to the effect that the US
                    has primary responsibility for Western policy in the Far East. The Secretary
                    also stated that he wished to make clear that he did not interpret anything in
                    the instructions as requiring the establishment of a fixed tripartite
                    committees, saying that he did not wish to make this matter a rigid thing.</p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that
                    he understood the Secretary’s interpretation. He then proposed several minor
                    modifications which were accepted and the text of the instructions were
                    agreed.</p>
                <p>The Secretary stated that after the Manila Pact was in force it might then be
                    appropriate to modify the principles outlined in the joint instructions. He said
                    that the Indochina area in a sense was under the Treaty and he said he thought
                    it might be covered by the paragraph concerning subversion which calls for
                    consultation. Under the Treaty there would be certain obligations to the other
                    signatories, and once treaty procedures were developed, new procedures regarding
                    consultation on Indochinese problems might be necessary. Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that he thought
                    there were two different things involved. He said that Paragraph 4 of the joint
                    instructions alluded to Paragraph 3 of the September 29 US-French minute of
                    understanding, that this all concerned not only military dangers but lots of
                    additional questions concerning consultation between the US and France, many
                    problems not connected with internal or external dangers. The Secretary thought
                    that this would present no problem, that he only wished not to put the US and
                    French in a position where they would not be taking into account the legitimate
                    interests of other signatories of the Manila Pact.</p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that
                    perhaps he had not expressed his view clear enough. He said there were
                    essentially two kinds of problems, first, problems such as the US and French
                    were discussing <pb facs="0399" n="1489" xml:id="pg_1489"/> at the moment which
                    included many things not included in the Manila Pact, and Paragraph 4 says that
                    there will be consultation and he believed this consultation would continue even
                    if the Manila Pact were enforced. Second, there were other special problems
                    which would come under the Pact. He proposed that there be a clear distinction
                    between the two and that it be understood that Paragraph 4 of the instruction be
                    operating even when the Manila Pact is in force. The Secretary said that the US
                    and French might wish to report to the Manila Pact signatories. Premier
                        <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> again stated
                    he thought the Paragraph 4 would still be valid even after the Manila Pact went
                    into effect. The Secretary said that he did not mean to suggest that the Manila
                    Pact might automatically change Paragraph 4, but that there were many members in
                    the Pact and he did not know what might be called for at that time. Premier
                        <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that if
                    the Manila Pact were in force, there would still be a need for such talks as the
                    present ones. The Secretary said yes, but it was conceivable the situation might
                    change and that he did not want the US bound for all eternity by the joint
                    instructions, although he did not anticipate that it would be necessary to
                    depart from the principles contained therein. Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that any change
                    would have to be discussed between the US and French to which the Secretary
                    indicated agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Pierre Mendès-France</persName> then
                    inquired as to what should be said to the Associated States about the joint
                    instructions. The Secretary said that he thought advice should be obtained from
                    the representatives in Indochina, but that in any event he did not believe there
                    should be any formal notification. This would give undue importance to the joint
                    instructions. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> indicated general agreement and proposed that
                    experts meet perhaps that evening to see what might be said Saturday by a
                    representative of the Secretary and by Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_BONNETH1">Bonnet</persName> to the three Ambassadors of the
                    Associated States.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he thought that the actual principles in the draft instruction
                    would be developed gradually on a working basis. He said that there was the
                    bigger problem of informing the representatives of the Associated States,
                    concerning the present talks, to satisfy their curiosity and dispell their
                    suspicions. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ROBERTSONWS1">Robertson</persName> said
                    that he thought the present instructions were merely in implementation of the
                    September agreement and did not represent any new agreement requiring formal
                    notification to the Indochinese. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> indicated his concurrence and the Secretary said
                    that he agreed to the proposal that the experts get together to determine what
                    should be told to the three Ambassadors.</p>
                <pb facs="0400" n="1490" xml:id="pg_1490"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Relationship with the Viet Minh</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> asked if
                    there was any other Indochina business. The Secretary replied that there were
                    plenty of problems: one of which might be brought up at this time was that of
                    the recognition of the Viet Minh which the US wished to avoid. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_ROBERTSONWS1">Robertson</persName> asked what was the
                    relationship of the Sainteny mission<note n="3" xml:id="d674fn3">
                        <persName>Jean Sainteny</persName>, former French official in Indochina was
                        dispatched to Hanoi by the French Government in August 1954 to arrange for
                        the protection of French economic and cultural interests. For information on
                        his activities, see <ref target="frus1952-54v13p2#pg_1936">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, Part 2, pp. 1936</ref> ff.</note> to the
                    Viet Minh. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName>
                    replied that there was an ambiguous situation, that the text of his letter had
                    been worded as carefully as possible to avoid the appearance of recognition.
                    They were not particularly happy with the paper but they felt obliged to give
                    Sainteny some kind of paper of this type. He read the letter again which
                    referred to Sainteny as being charged with the defense of French interests in
                    the north zone, and being named delegate of the French Government “Auprès de
                    vous”. He said he wasn’t proud of the wording but he hadn’t been able to find
                    another one. He said that the Viet Minh had not said anything about a reciprocal
                    representative, but it was believed they would most likely send one, and that
                    one in Saigon would be dangerous but it would be very hard to refuse one for
                    Paris.</p>
                <p>The Secretary suggested that he ask his experts again whether there might be some
                    substitute for the phrase “Auprès de vous” saying he personally would prefer,
                    “to negotiate with you to that effect”, but he did not want to put his views in
                    this matter ahead of those of the French. Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that unfortunately
                    at Geneva a letter was written addressed to the Democratic Republic of Vietnam
                    but he would see if some change could be made in the Sainteny letter.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">French Citizens in North Vietnam</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that
                    there was still the problem of the French concern that the French citizens
                    remaining in the North not be discriminated against by the United States, and M.
                    Cheysson said that in September four written questions were addressed to the US,
                    two of which had been answered, but the one pertaining to the matter of
                    discrimination had not been answered. Mr. <persName>Young</persName> said that
                    this matter was being worked on but that it involved a number of US Government
                    agencies and it took a little time. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> said he understood that the preliminary reply was
                    favorable and this was generally confirmed by the Secretary.</p>
                <pb facs="0401" n="1491" xml:id="pg_1491"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Training Vietnamese Forces</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary read from the telegram 2027<note n="4" xml:id="d674fn4">Telegram
                        2027 to Saigon, Nov. 18, stated that preliminary discussions indicated that
                            <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> was
                        opposed to eventual exclusive U.S. training responsibility in Vietnam.
                        (751G.5 <gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/11–1854)</note> which the
                    Department had sent to General <persName corresp="#p_COLLINSJL1"
                        >Collins</persName> Thursday evening and Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> indicated his
                    concurrence.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Diem Government</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> referred to
                    the previous discussion concerning a program of action for the Diem government
                    and inquired as to whether it was agreed to go ahead on this basis. The
                    Secretary stated no objection and suggested that the experts get together first
                    to define the specific proposals that might be suggested to Diem and the timing
                    and manner of the presentation plus the arrangements for speaking together to
                    see how the program was developing. General <persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1"
                        >Porter</persName> said that he thought it would be necessary to go into the
                    program carefully and the Secretary said but not so carefully that Diem will be
                    gone before the program is ready to be presented to him. Mr.
                        <persName>Young</persName> said that there were a number of pending
                    proposals regarding agrarian reform which could be considered and General
                        <persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1">Porter</persName> said that he believed
                    that Mr. <persName>Barrows</persName>, the head of the <gloss target="#t_FOA1"
                        >FOA</gloss> Mission, would have something to contribute.</p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> inquired as
                    to whether messages should not be sent to the two Generals in Saigon proposing
                    that they work out precise measures. The Secretary said that he wished to make
                    clear that he wouldn’t want to agree always to present the proposals on a
                    strictly joint basis but that the efforts and timing should be concerted.
                    Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that
                    the only way to impress Diem’s associates was to show that the US and France
                    agree; if not, they feel there may be disagreement and are inclined to play off
                    one against the other. The Secretary said we do not want to be committed that
                    the US would never talk alone to the Diem government. Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that he was
                    speaking only of the present decision and program that was under consideration
                    and not all things in general. The Secretary said that the US would want to
                    check first with its representatives on this specific program. He said he agreed
                    that while he was in favor of working together, he didn’t like to adopt a
                    general principle as being absolute for every case. Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that what is
                    important is that the Generals make the survey and keep in contact to judge on
                    the execution of the program.</p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that
                    it was difficult for the French to come to a decision on the problem of Bao Dai,
                    and he wished the US views. He said that Bao Dai wants to go back to Viet-Nam
                    and <pb facs="0402" n="1492" xml:id="pg_1492"/> so far the French had been
                    successful in avoiding that, but he is insisting. The Secretary said that while
                    he was not in a position to give advice on the matter in general the US was
                    against Bao Dai’s returning. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> said that even if Bao Dai was not a very
                    interesting person, he did provide legitimacy; he was now for Diem but if he
                    went back what would be his position in a matter of months is another question.
                    He said that it was hard to forbid him from going back and it was a delicate
                    matter. He said he was afraid Bao Dai might make some public statement to the
                    effect that the French were keeping him from returning, and again inquired if
                    the US had any new ideas on this subject. The Secretary referred to Ambassador
                    Heath’s return and said that he relied a lot on the Ambassador’s advice but at
                    the moment he had no views to offer on this subject.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_WEU1">WEU</gloss> Arms Agency</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that
                    on the question which had been discussed in London and Paris<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d674fn5">For documentation concerning the Nine-Power Conferences at
                        London and Paris, Sept. 28–Oct. 3, and Oct. 20–23, including records of
                        meetings concerning the matter of the <gloss target="#t_WEU1">WEU</gloss>
                        Arms Agency, see <ref target="frus1952-54v05p2#pg_1294">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, Part 2, pp. 1294</ref> ff. and <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v05p2#pg_1404">1404</ref> ff.</note> concerning the
                    distribution of US arms via the <gloss target="#t_WEU1">WEU</gloss> Arms Agency
                    the French still desire something in this matter. He said that in London the
                    Secretary had stated that the US would notify the Agency so it could take US
                    arms aid into account in its own work. In Paris there was thought given to
                    consultation but the Secretary had said he was not prepared to agree. He said he
                    would like the Secretary to think the matter over because it was a matter of
                    importance for the efficiency of the Agency and for public opinion.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he had no doubt that means can be arrived at to help the
                    Agency deal with its program but that the US did not want to duplicate
                    machinery. He said that the US has missions in various countries which together
                    with <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> mechanisms seem to work very well. He
                    said that the US was anxious to see the Agency develop satisfactorily. He said
                    the US would be glad to keep in touch with the Agency and see how, consistent
                    with basic US principles, the US can help the Agency carry out its task, but the
                    US cannot proceed very far until it sees how the Agency plans to work. He said
                    that perhaps a good deal may depend upon the January 17 talks concerning the
                    arms pool.</p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said he was
                    not seeking a commitment but only an indication from the US. He inquired whether
                    the Secretary did not think that something could be developed on the same basis
                    as had been done under the Marshall Plan with the <gloss target="#t_OEEC1"
                        >OEEC</gloss>. The Secretary said that he was concerned about there being
                        <pb facs="0403" n="1493" xml:id="pg_1493"/> duplication and delays in
                    practical operations. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HENSELHS1">Hensel</persName>
                    said that the US would consider the matter sympathetically but it was difficult
                    to agree in advance particularly as there was a responsibility to Congress. The
                    Secretary said that France had not questioned US control of distribution of aid
                    but desired consultation. He said it depended upon what kind of a positive or
                    negative role the Agency developed. He said he did not want to pile machinery
                    upon machinery. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> said he was not sure concerning the procedures
                    with <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> but that he thought that each country
                    only indicated what program it could conduct and <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> is not directly included in the kind of consultation he had in
                    mind. The Secretary said he didn’t fully understand the <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> procedure but as all the Brussels Treaty people were also
                    sitting in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> perhaps something could be
                    arranged in that way. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> said that in the <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                        >EDC</gloss> it was foreseen that aid would be distributed by the <gloss
                        target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> organs and there was a consistent system with
                    the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> being responsible for supplying all
                    arms. He said he couldn’t understand why what was planned for <gloss
                        target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> would not work now. The Secretary said that
                    like <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> he himself
                    had nothing to do with developing the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss>.
                    However, he said there were no national armies in the <gloss target="#t_EDC1"
                        >EDC</gloss>, only one common army and this made a difference. But he said
                    he had not taken the position concerning US aid distribution through the <gloss
                        target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> and he did not take that position now, that the
                    matter was subject to the same objections in his mind.</p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> inquired as
                    to whether it would be possible to have at this time some declaration of
                    intention regarding sympathy for the French idea and stated that such a
                    declaration would be a great help for the debate and ratification. The Secretary
                    said he could take what he had previously said at London and Paris and perhaps
                    tie it up in a ribbon, that might be of assistance. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that it would be of
                    particular assistance if the ribbon would be a bit more tight and the Secretary
                    said he would try to help. He inquired why the deputies were worried and
                    sensitive about this matter. <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> said that frankly they were afraid that the US
                    would give more and better arms quicker to Germany than to France, that as a
                    result Germany will have a newly equipped army and the French will have old
                    fashioned type of equipment.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">North Africa</hi>
                    <note n="6" xml:id="d674fn6">For documentation on the subjects mentioned in the
                        conversation concerning North Africa, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v11p1#pg_127">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xi</hi>, Part
                            1, pp. 127</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Secretary said that our people were sensitive also when the French used the
                    material we gave them to fight against the natives <pb facs="0404" n="1494"
                        xml:id="pg_1494"/> in North Africa, and that there was a feeling here that
                    material should be given to those who keep it in Europe. He said he felt we may
                    have considerable difficulties over this. <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> said that the French were doing this in the common
                    interest for it was a situation that was bad for all. The Secretary said he did
                    not wish to speak on the substance of this problem but wished to point out that
                    the US had parliamentary difficulties too. Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that under Article
                    4 of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Algeria was covered and a threat to
                    the peace was a matter of common concern and the signatories would have to
                    concert action. He said he had been instructed by the National Assembly last
                    week to have a formal consultation on Article 4. He said that before leaving the
                    Arms Agency matter he wished to stress that although he was not in a great hurry
                    the matter was very important.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> then referred to
                    the Spanish, Egyptian, and Hungarian radio broadcasts in North Africa. He said
                    that while the US perhaps could do little in Budapest he hoped the US could help
                    in Cairo and Madrid. The Secretary said that the US had already spoken to the
                    Egyptians and that additional instructions will be drawn up to Ambassador
                    Caffery since the effect of the steps that were taken recently apparently had
                    worn off. He inquired whether the French thought it was correct that the line
                    Caffery should take was that the US was satisfied that <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> was making an early and
                    determined effort in the Tunisian matter. <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> indicated his concurrence. The Secretary said that
                    as he understood the matter, <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> intended to deal first with Tunisia and then apply
                    similar policies to Morocco. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> said that for the immediate future political and
                    economic measures were being undertaken although they realized this was not
                    enough to resolve the crisis which was based on the dynastic problem. He said
                    there is no speedy solution to the problem there. He said that with regard to
                    Egypt could not some reference be made in the communiqué to the problem. He said
                    this would be good for public opinion. The Secretary said he did not believe
                    there should be anything in the communiqué that the US would be taking up with
                    other countries. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> asked that even if mention wasn’t made of the name
                    of any country perhaps in the communiqué it could be indicated the matter had
                    been discussed. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MERCHANTLT1">Merchant</persName> said
                    he was afraid if something were in the communiqué there might be a reaction
                    which would make it more difficult for an effective approach by Ambassador
                    Caffery. Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName>
                    said that unless something of this nature could be said in the communiqué from
                    the French standpoint it would be better to say nothing.</p>
                <pb facs="0405" n="1495" xml:id="pg_1495"/>
                <p>The Secretary inquired as to whether <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> was going to address himself to the North African
                    matter in his speech before the United Nations. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> replied that was not his
                    intention because he did not want to give the impression of defending the French
                    position although his speech was not final as yet. He referred to his reply to a
                    Press Club luncheon question which he had discussed the matter of arms coming in
                    from outside North Africa, and added that if he touched on North Africa in his
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> speech it would be in this connection.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BYROADEHA1">Byroade</persName> said that a study had
                    indicated there had been a change in the output of radio Cairo during the week
                    and he said that the matter had been discussed with the Egyptian Ambassador who
                    had telephoned Nassar who had promised to tone down the output. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that his reports
                    were that the opposite was the case for on November 18 and November 19, the
                    anniversary of the former Sultan, the Egyptians had repeated many times a day a
                    call for manifestations on the streets in Morocco.</p>
                <p>Premier <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> inquired as
                    to whether in the communiqué something could not be said to the effect that the
                    problems had been examined in the spirit of Article 4 of the North Atlantic
                    Treaty and it had been decided to have consultation to resolve these problems.
                    He asked that the matter be thought over. The Secretary said that Article 4 was
                    not a bilateral matter but required a meeting of all the members of the North
                    Atlantic Council. <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName>
                    said that is why he had suggested the words “in the spirit of” Article 4.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that a meeting would be held at 10:00 Saturday, November 20, to
                    reach an agreement on the communiqué.<note n="7" xml:id="d674fn7">For a record
                        of this meeting, see <ref target="#d681">Document 681</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HENSELHS1">Hensel</persName> said that the US was
                    disturbed over the reduction in French M to M plus 30 day divisions from 14 to
                    12. This taken with the transfer of divisions to North Africa weakens <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SACEUR1">SACEUR</gloss>
                    is disturbed. This development would have an effect upon other countries tending
                    towards a progressive reduction of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    strength. He said also that US regulations did not permit furnishing <gloss
                        target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> equipment to divisions less ready than at M
                    plus 30. He said that the US was mindful of the security problem in North Africa
                    but that the US Congress insisted that <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>
                    equipment remain in Europe and even Algeria was not on the European continent.
                    He said that the US hopes that France will return the divisions and equipment as
                    soon as the danger is passed. In the meantime it would be difficult to replace
                    in Europe any of the <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> equipment taken to
                    North Africa.</p>
                <pb facs="0406" n="1496" xml:id="pg_1496"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said that Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HENSELHS1">Hensel</persName>’s remarks caused no
                    difficulty and it was the French intention to return the equipment as soon as
                    possible as it was only sent as a temporary measure to deal with an acute
                    situation. He said that France hoped, if it got results in Africa on the
                    political side, to reduce the forces in North Africa by the end of 1955. He said
                    that as this is connected with the evolution of the political situation it was
                    hard to be precise concerning the date. He said that the French efforts were for
                    the common defense and North Africa was not far away so that the troops could be
                    brought back soon in an emergency. He said that the reduction of the M plus 30
                    divisions from 14 to 12 was a realistic measure for some of these 14 divisions
                    had not been in full strength and had many gaps. He said that frankly, however,
                    the situation derived from the North African problem and that part of the former
                    M plus 30 divisions had been taken to make new divisions for North Africa. The
                    French action gave only an appearance of a weakening for the manpower and the
                    money was the same and the situation was on a more honest basis. He said that by
                    the end of next year when forces could be returned from North Africa and
                    Indochina he hoped this would allow an increase in the French <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> contribution in the course of 1955.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HENSELHS1">Hensel</persName> said that the US was
                    disappointed in the reduction in planning for <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> strength and that the French decisions while involving the
                    same amount of money resulted in less strength. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said France was not
                    decreasing its manpower or its expenditures although it was not enlarging its
                    forces this year as it had been hoped due to the North African situation. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HENSELHS1">Hensel</persName> said he appreciated the
                    French difficulties and hoped <persName corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1"
                        >Mendès-France</persName> also appreciated the US worries. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said he did but that if
                    the North African situation deteriorates it involves danger for all. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HENSELHS1">Hensel</persName> said he hoped the US will
                    be given time to talk to the French before any further <gloss target="#t_MDAP1"
                        >MDAP</gloss> equipment is moved to North Africa. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MENDSFRANCEP1">Mendès-France</persName> said he understood and
                    that the French would get in touch with the US in such event. He said he hoped
                    there was an understanding that the North African forces were for the common
                    defense.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
