<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 825The Ambassador in Norway (Bay) to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v06p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d825</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">825</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recNuUP5FwVBYX7g7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic policies</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="tariffs" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132405" lcsh-match="good_close">Tariff</term>
                    <term ref="congressional-relations" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="congressional-relations" subject="relations-with-congress">relations with Congress</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="825"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d825">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.57/7–3153: Despatch</note>
                <head>No. 825<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Norway (<persName corresp="#p_BAYCU1"
                            type="from">Bay</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>No. 85</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Oslo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-07-31">July 31,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="references">
                    <item>Reference: Oslo despatch No. 1121, June 26, 1953;<note n="1"
                            xml:id="d825fn1">Despatch 1121, similar in many ways to this despatch,
                            focused primarily on Norway’s attitude toward Chinese representation in
                            the United Nations. (795.00/6–2653)</note> and Department’s circular
                        telegram No. 53, July 23, 1953<note n="2" xml:id="d825fn2">See <ref
                                target="#d824fn1">footnote 1, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                            </ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject: Norwegian Attitudes Towards the United States</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Department’s telegram under reference was received just one week ago, which
                    is to say seven days before the effective date of my resignation as
                        Ambassador.<note n="3" xml:id="d825fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BAYCU1">Bay</persName>’s appointment was terminated on
                        July 31; <persName corresp="#p_STRONGLC1">L. Corrin Strong</persName>, who
                        was appointed to replace him on June 24, presented his credentials on Aug.
                        10.</note> However, I feel it important that I should submit a reply before
                    leaving office rather than turn such a problem over to my successor, for he will
                    not have had opportunity to be familiar with Norwegian official and public
                    attitudes over the past months. In my despatch no. 1121 of June 26, I covered
                    much of the ground involved, based primarily upon an evening of full and frank
                    discussion with the Foreign Minister himself and several other key figures in
                    the Labor Government and Labor Party, but which also included broader background
                    coverage from other sources. In fact, my previous despatch is practically a
                    complete reply to the Department’s telegram, but as my last official act I think
                    it well to take up the Department’s questions specifically in an effort to give
                    direct answers.</p>
                <pb facs="0679" n="1769" xml:id="pg_1769"/>
                <p>The Department’s first question is whether there is mistrust among Norwegians of
                    United States motives underlying our policy towards the USSR. In my view the
                    Norwegians do not distrust our motives, but they are more inclined than they
                    have previously been to question the soundness and stability of our judgment.
                    There is a general feeling that too many Americans have an unduly emotional and
                    alarmist attitude towards Communism which makes it difficult for us to form
                    objective judgments as a basis for wise and moderate policies. We must remember
                    that the Norwegians are accustomed to Communists in their midst, and some of the
                    soundest present Labor Party leaders were not far from being Communists
                    themselves in pre-war days. They feel that they have the internal Communist
                    situation under sufficient control even when, as at present, about 6% of the
                    national vote goes Communist, which is to say about 100,000 votes. It seems to
                    be their impression that Communists are relatively far less numerous in the
                    United States, and hence their concept that we have allowed ourselves to become
                    unduly alarmed, especially concerning the internal dangers of Communism. Some
                    ranking officials also have doubts concerning our estimate of the Communist
                    danger in Europe and lean to the reported British view that Russia is hardly
                    likely to initiate a military sweep across Western Europe in the immediate years
                    ahead. While they appreciate fully, of course, that such could happen and that
                    it is likely the Russians have the strength with which to mount such an
                    aggression, yet in gauging the probabilities they feel we may be too much
                    influenced by strictly military considerations set in a background of alarmism
                    and without due respect to seasoned political considerations.</p>
                <p>The Department’s second question whether there has been a lessening of confidence
                    in U.S. intentions adequately to support its allies, both individually and
                    collectively, in measures designed to strengthen free world security, raises the
                    question of isolationism. Norwegian officials are watching carefully to see
                    whether isolationist pressures within Congress and also upon Congress are
                    gaining headway. Completely confident of President <persName
                        corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName>’s basic position and guiding
                    principles, there exists an undeniable feeling of uncertainty of his ability to
                    gain the necessary support from Congress. Strictly in terms of United States
                    military and economic aid for Norway, there has been no indication whatsoever of
                    criticism on the part of the Government or the public. They know we do not
                    expect to provide further direct economic aid, but realize we have aided them
                    most generously over the past five years, and that such contributions had to end
                    sooner or later. As for military equipment and supplies, those at all familiar
                    with the situation understand that we have already programmed enough equipment
                    to make possible <pb facs="0680" n="1770" xml:id="pg_1770"/> the planned
                    build-up of their forces. Just how they will maintain the ultimate level of
                    strength and equipment is a problem to which they are, perhaps naively or just
                    politicially, rather shutting their eyes.</p>
                <p>The Government has not yet obtained foreign financing to cover its anticipated
                    1953 foreign exchange deficit, which will probably be a large one. (Minister of
                    Commerce Brofoss recently estimated that after capital transfers the balance of
                    payments deficit this year will total about 500 million kroner.) Norway may be
                    faced with a very serious problem if foreign loans and credits are not
                    forthcoming and the terms of trade and shipping do not improve. As already
                    stated, however, I do not find that even the most apprehensive Norwegian blames
                    this situation upon us, or expects us to write blank checks indefinitely for
                    future deficits. On the other hand, the Government, together with both labor
                    unions and trade circles, is far from confident of U.S. intentions to direct its
                    own domestic and foreign economic policies so as to contribute to economic and
                    political stability in Western Europe and, by the same token, to free world
                    security. Government officials express to us their fear that the present U.S.
                    restrictive monetary and fiscal policies may lead to a recession and that the
                    “Republican” Administration may not be prepared to take effective remedial
                    measures. They feel that such a development would have drastic consequences for
                    Western Europe. Not only have Norwegians been not too sanguine about
                    possiblities for U.S. tariff liberalization, but indicate grave concern lest
                    protectionist pressures in Congress may force the adoption of a more restrictive
                    trade policy.</p>
                <p>The Department’s third question concerns the possibility that the United States
                    is not living up to its leadership responsibilities. I believe there is such a
                    feeling here which I shall endeavor to define. The Government has been much
                    disturbed in recent months over what it has considered a failure by the United
                    States to assume the initiative and to adopt the flexibility called for in the
                    fluid situation brought about by Stalin’s death, and a period in which many read
                    signs of a receptive attitude on the part of the new Soviet regime. Perhaps it
                    could be said they have held with Sir <persName corresp="#p_CHURCHILLWS1"
                        >Winston Churchill</persName> in believing the time has come for
                    face-to-face discussions of a general nature between the top officals of East
                    and West. They feel we have adhered too rigidly to policy lines adopted long ago
                    to cope with an entirely different situation. There is evidence, however, that
                    this attitude has been modified somewhat by the US–UK–French proposal for a
                    four-power foreign minister’s conference <pb facs="0681" n="1771"
                        xml:id="pg_1771"/> which a key Labor Party leader has described as a “great
                    forward step.”<note n="4" xml:id="d825fn4">The reference here is to a proposal
                        made at the Tripartite Foreign Ministers meetings in Washington, July 10–14,
                        1953. For documentation concerning these meetings and the note to the Soviet
                        Union, dated July 15, which resulted from it, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v05p2#pg_1607">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, Part
                            2, pp. 1607</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>On specific issues I might say that our continued insistence on the vital
                    necessity of the <gloss target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> and our position on
                    Communist China seem too inflexible to Norwegians. They believe that <gloss
                        target="#t_EDC1">EDC</gloss> cannot possibly be accepted by France and
                    Germany so long as there is hope for settlement with Russia on German
                    unification. The Department already knows Norway’s position on the Chinese
                    situation as last reported in my despatch 1121 of June 26.</p>
                <p>I believe that the recognition of the leadership which we have exercised for so
                    long will suffer in some degree here in Norway unless, in the establishment of
                    our own policies, we are willing to sympathetically give fullest consideration
                    to the viewpoint of the Europeans themselves on such issues as those mentioned
                    above. The issue goes more deeply than the question of economic aid or its
                    possible withdrawal on the part of the United States.</p>
                <p>The fourth question is whether United States domestic political events have
                    influenced Norway’s attitude toward United States leadership. Norwegian answers
                    to this question vary somewhat, though the preponderant view seems clearly to be
                    that the names “<persName>McCarthy</persName>” and “<persName
                        corresp="#p_MCCARRANPA1">McCarran</persName>” symbolize a disconcerting
                    development of undemocratic and irresponsible forces within our country.
                    Norwegians of every hue traditonally resent any assault against civil liberties.
                    A long chapter could be written on this, but it hardly seems necessary,
                    especially in view of what I have previously reported. Suffice it to say that
                    many Norwegians feel that the emotional anti-Communist forces have exercised too
                    great an influence on the foreign policies of the present Administration. They
                    see the President so far as conciliating the opposing and recalcitrant factions
                    within Congress whose positions are thus allowed to loom so large that the
                    foreign policy of the U.S. at times seems difficult to understand. They regard
                    some of the more “extreme” statements made by Administration spokesmen to
                    “appease” such factions as threat to Western unity. I have just been told of the
                    “shocked reaction” expressed by a key Labor Party leader to an Embassy officer
                    regarding the “categorical” nature of the Secretary’s latest statements on the
                    question of Communist China’s admission into the United Nations and its
                    irrelevance to the forthcoming political conference on Korea.</p>
                <pb facs="0682" n="1772" xml:id="pg_1772"/>
                <p>During my farewell call on Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_TORPO1"
                        >Torp</persName>, occasioned by my departure from this post, we discussed
                    several aspects of American foreign policy which relate directly to the
                    questions set forth in the Department’s referenced telegram. Making allowance
                    for a certain politeness and reserve in Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TORPO1"
                        >Torp</persName>’s remarks on delicate questions, I may say that his
                    observations reflected the attitudes which I have described above. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_TORPO1">Torp</persName> indicated that while Norwegian
                    Government officials still have faith in President <persName
                        corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName>, they feel that conflicting
                    forces within the Republican Party are seriously impeding his program and that
                    they have so far dimmed the force and clarity of the President’s views. He
                    observed that Norwegian officials are not acquainted with leaders of our
                    administration, aside from President <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>, and do not know what to expect from them. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_TORPO1">Torp</persName>’s only response to my question
                    as to his reaction to American political developments was that he felt less sure
                    about the current situation than during the latest previous years and hoped
                    “that the President would show in American politics the same spirit he showed as
                    Commander in Europe.” With reference to the strength of isolationism in the
                    United States, he expressed the hope also that American sentiment would permit
                    the new Administration to continue to demonstrate a positive willingness to
                    cooperate fully with the nations of Western Europe. The Prime Minister expressed
                    understanding of the attitudes of the American people on the future of foreign
                    aid, but said that he hoped personally that aid would continue in such
                    reasonable amounts as would achieve the broad aspects of <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> defense objectives. He added that “we do not
                    feel so sure today as previously about the extent of aid.” Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_TORPO1">Torp</persName> strongly emphasized that no opportunity
                    should be lost to explore any reasonable possibility looking toward the
                    development of new and better relations with the Soviet Union, and hoped that
                    the United States would enter four-power discussions with the view of reaching
                    the highest degree of understanding and agreement.</p>
                <p>In concluding our discussion, I asked the Prime Minister whether he believes that
                    the Government and people feel as much faith as ever in United States purposes
                    and leadership toward the goal of political unity. He stumbled a bit on this and
                    then came back to his previous remark that he is less sure of the soundness of
                    our policy today than he has been previously. He ended with the remark that
                    certainly all the free world today must rest its hope largely in our
                    country.</p>
                <p>The Department’s telegram closes by requesting the views of Chiefs of Mission as
                    to major factors which should be borne in mind during coming months in
                    determining U. S. lines of action. It is somewhat difficult to make definitive
                    recommendations in this <pb facs="0683" n="1773" xml:id="pg_1773"/> sense, since
                    much of the problem seems to result from the fluid state of American politics.
                    When the President is able to stabilize his relations with Congress and
                    establish a coherent set of policies in line with his own expressed views, a
                    greater degree of confidence will in all likelihood develop toward the United
                    States among Norwegian officials. In developing our foreign policy tactics, I
                    would place great emphasis on the principle recently expressed to us by the
                    Chairman of the Foreign Affairs Committee of the Norwegian Storting—namely, that
                    far more important than any particular line of action towards the Soviet bloc is
                    the development and maintenance of understanding and unity on major foreign
                    policy issues among the nations of the Atlantic Community.</p>
                <p>In conclusion it is my personal view that no great damage has been done to United
                    State prestige and leadership, but that our future course calls for study of
                    ways and means to achieve the above-mentioned European unity without which any
                    nation’s leadership becomes futile. In so far as unity between our country and
                    Norway is concerned, it is certain that the Norwegian Government and all the
                    Norwegian people hold our Government and people to be sincere and determined in
                    our efforts to make every possible contribution toward this end. The only
                    question is the degree to which we may be achieving or failing to achieve this
                    in our present course of action. I believe further that the Norwegian Government
                    and people view with realism the fact that all freedom-loving nations may seek
                    the same goal and yet pursue somewhat different courses as reflected in their
                    foreign policies. A forthright and positive United States foreign policy would
                    do much to clear the atmosphere in so far as Norway is concerned, and
                    particularly so if that policy is directed toward unity among the Western
                    European nations.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">C. Ulrick Bay</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
