<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-01-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-01-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="833" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d833">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">611.52/1–552</note>
                        <head>No. 833<lb/><hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in Spain
                                    (<persName type="from">Jones</persName>) to <persName corresp="#p_DUNHAMWB1" type="to">William B. Dunham</persName> of
                                the Office of Western European Affairs</hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-01-09">January 9, 1952</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName>Bill</persName></hi>: Your letter of
                            December 14<note n="1" xml:id="d833fn1">Not found in Department of State
                                files.</note> arrived shortly before the Christmas holidays and I
                            have not had an opportunity to acknowledge <pb facs="0693" n="1783" xml:id="pg_1783"/> it earlier. We took advantage of the long weekend
                            over New Year’s to go south (Ubeda, near Jaén) for four days’ rest and
                            sunshine. It was very pleasant and we missed the <persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1">Porter</persName> visit<note n="2" xml:id="d833fn2"><persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1">Porter</persName>
                                was in Madrid from Dec. 30, 1951, to Jan. 2, 1952, while en route
                                from Lisbon to Paris.</note> with all of the work and social
                            activity involved. Meanwhile, the subject of your letter has developed
                            into an open issue with the <persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1">Porter</persName> press conference<note n="3" xml:id="d833fn3">Brief accounts of the <persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1">Porter</persName> news conference, given for American reporters
                                while in Madrid, are in despatches 637 and 639 from Madrid, Jan. 4.
                                (752.00(W)/1–452)</note> and subsequent publicity on both sides of
                            the Atlantic.</p>
                        <p>While the Embassy has been guided by the policy referred to in <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 463 of December 12,<note n="4" xml:id="d833fn4">For the text of telegram 463, see <ref target="frus1951v04p1#pg_856"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1951, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>,
                                    Part 1, p. 856</ref>.</note> there has been a feeling here that
                            plans for economic aid, as provided in the <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> Appropriations Act of 1952,<note n="5" xml:id="d833fn5">Mutual Security Appropriations Act of 1952, P.L. 82–249 (62 Stat.
                                137), Oct. 31, 1951.</note> should not be neglected while waiting
                            termination of the military negotiations which have not even yet begun.
                            This attitude was explained in the last paragraph of <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 592 of December 8<note n="6" xml:id="d833fn6">For the text of telegram 592, see <ref target="frus1951v04p1#pg_855"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1951, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>,
                                    Part 1, p. 855</ref>.</note> to which you referred. Our feeling
                            is rather that the United States Government should be ready to move
                            ahead on economic aid simultaneously with negotations in the military
                            field since the success of our military objectives, we feel, are closely
                            bound up with an intelligent economic aid program. Regardless of whether
                            the Spaniards will grant us military facilities without economic
                            concessions, I think that most of us here are in agreement with
                                <persName corresp="#p_SUFRINSC1">Sufrin</persName>’s thesis that a
                            thoughtful economic aid program is essential in support of our military
                            objectives and that this support should be simultaneous with and not
                            subsequent to initiation of the military program.</p>
                        <p>The phrase in <gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 604<note n="7" xml:id="d833fn7">Telegram 604 advocated the recall of the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> (<persName corresp="#p_SUFRINSC1">Sufrin</persName>) group immediately upon completion of the
                                survey of the Spanish economy in order not to leave the impression
                                that aid was forthcoming regardless of what military concessions
                                were granted to the United States by the Spanish. (752.5 <gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/12–1151)</note>—“position the
                            Department is taking”—was, unconsciously perhaps, a reflection of our
                            feeling that this position was not necessarily that of the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> (now <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss>) and an indication of our concern over a possible
                            conflict of tactical policies in Washington. If I may express my
                            personal concern, it was that the Department would lose control of
                            foreign policy in their particular phase of Spanish–American relations
                            by adhering too rigidly to a pat formula, “limited economic aid for
                            Spain only as a concession to the achievement of specific military
                            objectives”, with the implied timetable of no economic aid until after
                            the successful conclusion of military negotiations. Congress has
                            earmarked <pb facs="0694" n="1784" xml:id="pg_1784"/> a substantial sum
                            for Spain and in my opinion it is only realistic to assume that the
                            Spaniards consider this figure a floor for their aspirations in the
                            economic field rather than a ceiling. In other words, Senator <persName corresp="#p_MCCARRANPA1">McCarran</persName> tipped your hand to the
                            Spaniards when he wrote his amendment into the appropriations bill.<note n="8" xml:id="d833fn8">Reference is to the Mutual Security
                                Appropriations Act of 1952, P.L. 82–249 (65 Stat. 730), Oct. 31,
                                1951. The clause inserted by Senator <persName corresp="#p_MCCARRANPA1">McCarran</persName>, a member of the
                                Appropriations Committee, reads as follows: “Assistance to Spain:
                                For economic, technical, and military assistance, in the discretion
                                of the President under the general objectives set forth in the
                                declaration of policy contained in the titles of the Economic
                                Cooperation Act of 1948 and the Mutual Security Act of 1951, for
                                Spain, $100,000,000”.</note> Furthermore, <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> will undoubtedly feel a responsibility to Congress to
                            proceed as soon as possible with an aid program, specifically authorized
                            by the legislative branch of the Government, before the fiscal year runs
                            its course—and it is more than half gone now. I agree that the original
                            tactics were sound but they have been weakened—probably beyond
                            usefulness—by time and a series of events, such as the assignment of an
                                <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> group to Spain in August, the
                                <persName corresp="#p_MCCARRANPA1">McCarran</persName> amendment to
                            the <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> Appropriations Act, the delay in
                            the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> to make decisions on the
                                <persName corresp="#p_SPRYJW1">Spry</persName> report,<note n="9" xml:id="d833fn9">The <persName corresp="#p_SPRYJW1">Spry</persName>
                                Report was the product of the survey of Spanish military facilities
                                conducted between Aug. 22 and Nov. 1, 1951, by the Joint Military
                                Survey Team under the leadership of Maj. Gen. <persName corresp="#p_SPRYJW1">James W. Spry</persName>. (For the origin
                                and purposes of this team and its mission, see <ref target="frus1951v04p1#pg_838"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1951, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>,
                                    Part 1, p. 838</ref>.) The <persName corresp="#p_SPRYJW1">Spry</persName> Report was transmitted in despatch 425 from
                                Madrid, Nov. 2, 1951. (752.5/11–251) Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GRIFFISS1">Griffis</persName> expressed in his
                                covering note to the report his and <persName corresp="#p_SPRYJW1">Spry</persName>’s opinion “that the Spaniards will be willing
                                to negotiate a military agreement, including basing and overflight
                                rights, physical developments of military facilities and munitions
                                factories (with their obvious economic correlation), prior to and
                                without any final and definite assurance of substantial direct
                                economic aid.” The report, which consisted of a summary of the
                                findings of the Survey Team and seven annexes, began by proposing
                                the initiation of “immediate negotiations with a view to developing
                                facilities for the support of the foreseeable U.S. military
                                requirements.” It continued by noting that the Spanish Government
                                was not at that time “favorably inclined toward membership in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>,” preferring instead a bilateral
                                agreement with the United States, and that Spain, “under existing
                                political conditions,” did not want to send troops beyond its
                                borders into Europe in the event of war. After presenting a brief
                                evaluation of currently existing Spanish military facilities, the
                                report suggested a list of eight desirable U.S. military
                                requirements. While most of these concerned Air Force and Navy
                                facilities, the final one (h) provided for “development, equipping,
                                manning and utilization of facilities as required for any projected
                                United States Army operations.” The <persName corresp="#p_SPRYJW1">Spry</persName> Report was submitted immediately upon
                                completion to the Joint Chiefs of Staff for approval or modification
                                of its recommendations.</note> and the recent publicity on the
                                <persName corresp="#p_SUFRINSC1">Sufrin</persName> report and the
                            anticipated establishment of an <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss>
                            representation in Spain.</p>
                        <p>We have just seen a copy of a joint mesage from <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss>, Defense and State to <persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1">Porter</persName> dated January 3<note n="10" xml:id="d833fn10">Reference is to telegram 528 to Madrid, Jan. 3, sent originally to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PORTERPR1">Porter</persName> through the
                                Embassy in France as telegram 3792. It reported the Department of
                                State plan to undertake negotiations with Spain for economic,
                                technical, and military agreements on a coordinated basis as soon as
                                the Joint Chiefs of Staff had passed judgment on the <persName corresp="#p_SPRYJW1">Spry</persName> Report. (752.5 <gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/1–352)</note> which seems to
                            establish a <pb facs="0695" n="1785" xml:id="pg_1785"/> realistic and
                            workable program for future negotiations. If we can begin negotiations
                            for a bilateral agreement of economic assistance at the same time we
                            undertake negotiations for military facilities, we will have the
                            advantage of a well-coordinated policy during the period of the
                            negotiations with one ready to support the other at the appropriate
                            time.</p>
                        <p>The sooner the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> decisions on the
                                <gloss target="#t_JMST1">JMST</gloss> report are forthcoming, the
                            easier it will be to keep all this on the track. Your 528 of January 3
                            is good policy now but it may not be in three months.</p>
                        <p>All our sincere best wishes for 1952. May it be as good to all of us as
                            the one just past.</p>
                        <p>Yours ever,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="smallcaps">Johnny</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>