<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="860" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d860">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">752.5/7–552</note>
                        <head>No. 860<lb/><hi rend="italic">Record of a Meeting Between United
                                States and Spanish Representatives, Madrid, July 5, 1952</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d860fn1">The participants in this meeting, which took
                                place at 11 a.m. in <persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Arguelles</persName>’ office, were <persName corresp="#p_TRAINGF1">George F. Train</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WHITEIB1">Ivan B. White</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_MCCAFFERYRSJ1">Richard S. McCaffery, Jr.</persName>,
                                for the United States, and <persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Jaime Arguelles</persName> and <persName>Francisco Javier
                                    Elorza</persName> for Spain. No indication of authorship was
                                found on the source text.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-07-05">July 5, 1952</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Arguelles</persName> said that
                            he had called us together because the Spanish Government on the
                            military, economic and political sides had been doing a good deal of
                            soul searching during the last few days and had decided that it would be
                            useful to give us as clearly as possible the essence of the conclusions
                            the Spanish had come to. It was obvious that these derived from a
                            cabinet meeting on July 4, 1952.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Arguelles</persName> spoke in
                            English throughout (something he has never done heretofore). He made it
                            clear that although talking only to the economic side of the U.S.
                            negotiating team, he had been instructed to talk officially and express
                            the views of the Spanish Government.</p>
                        <p>He said they considered that the negotiations had come to a “standstill”;
                            that <persName corresp="#p_ARBURUADLMM1">Arburua</persName> had had
                            lengthy discussions all week with General <persName corresp="#p_VIGONJ1">Vigon</persName> from which it was apparent that General <persName corresp="#p_VIGONJ1">Vigon</persName> was not satisfied that the
                            amount of military aid thus far suggested ($12 million<note n="2" xml:id="d860fn2">This figure was the sum allocated for military aid
                                in <gloss target="#t_DMS1">DMS</gloss> D–7, <ref target="#d846">Document 846</ref>, and proposed in <persName corresp="#p_TRAINGF1">Train</persName>’s <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire,</hi><ref target="#d851">Document
                                851</ref>.</note> plus the entire $25 million<note n="3" xml:id="d860fn3">This figure was the sum appropriated for Spain in
                                the Mutual Security Act of 1952, P.L. 82–400 (66 Stat. 141), June
                                20, 1952. No restrictions were placed by Congress on its use within
                                Spain.</note>) would permit him to provide adequately for the
                            defense of the national territory in the light of the increased
                            vulnerability of Spain which would result from an agreement now to
                            permit the U.S. to construct and utilize air bases under the terms and
                            conditions we have outlined; that realizing that the U.S. position was
                            such that a total of $125 million is all that will be available in
                            Fiscal ’53, the Spanish Government had considered how far it would be
                            willing to go within the limitation of the sums available and had
                            decided to suggest the following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Negotiate and sign an Economic Aid Agreement</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Negotiate and sign an <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>
                                    Agreement</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Negotiate and sign an agreement providing for the construction
                                    of air bases (here he parenthetically added that the Spanish
                                    Government would pay peseta costs from counterpart)</item>
                                <pb facs="0771" n="1861" xml:id="pg_1861"/>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Negotiate and sign a conditional agreement covering the
                                    utilization of the bases. In this connection, he said that a
                                    final agreement regarding use of the bases cannot be a <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo</hi> for the agreements suggested
                                    in 1, 2, and 3 above and expressed the opinion that progressive
                                    negotiations for the use of the bases should be developed “au
                                    fur y mésure” as Spain’s economic and military capability
                                    developed as the result of implementation of the <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> and Economic
                                    Agreements.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>In reply to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TRAINGF1">Train</persName>’s
                            question as to whether a conditional time-phased agreement for
                            progressive utilization of the bases would be possible of execution
                            together with the other three agreements, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Arguelles</persName> was somewhat
                            doubtful but agreed to explore the matter further in the light of the
                            consideration that the U.S. could hardly use appropriated dollar funds
                            for the equipment of bases with respect to the use of which, in given
                            circumstances, the position was unclear. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TRAINGF1">Train</persName> suggested consideration of
                            conditions begin from an unconditional commitment by Spain for immediate
                            utilization of the bases in the event of war. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Arguelles</persName> said that he
                            would provide Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TRAINGF1">Train</persName> with
                            a written memorandum<note n="4" xml:id="d860fn4">Transmitted in telegram
                                41 from Madrid, <ref target="#d861"><hi rend="italic">infra</hi></ref>.</note> of the Spanish government proposal
                            within two or three days and that the present discussion was intended to
                            explain and clarify the thinking behind this memorandum. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Arguelles</persName> made several
                            interesting statements and gave the impression of speaking with unusual
                            frankness—always on a personal and friendly basis—in the course of the
                            conversation. For example, he said that in the matter of increased
                            vulnerability, the opinion of the Spanish army and its officers had to
                            be taken into account. In fact, he said that in a country where public
                            opinion does not exist, the responsibility of a government for making
                            decisions affecting the nation was even more grave than would be the
                            case if there was such a thing as public opinion. He certainly intimated
                            that (a) the position of the Spanish Government depends on the support
                            of the army and (b) that the army would not be satisfied to see a base
                            agreement executed unless it was given sufficient equipment to permit
                            its officers to become more actively operational, presently or
                            prospectively, than would be the case with the amount of funds now
                            proposed for military assistance. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TRAINGF1">Train</persName> explained the difficulty of supplying equipment to
                            a Spanish army which would have a purely defensive role, stating that
                            unsatisfied prior commitments to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            countries for scarce equipment precluded, in his opinion, the
                            immobilization of such equipment in Spain or anywhere else. Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_TRAINGF1">Train</persName> also stated that
                            there was a strong impression, whether well founded or not, among many
                            officials in the U.S. Government that General <persName corresp="#p_FRANCOYBAHAMONDEF1">Franco</persName>
                            <pb facs="0772" n="1862" xml:id="pg_1862"/> would never permit Spanish
                            ground forces to fight outside Spain, to which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Arguelles</persName> replied that
                            there were elements in Spain which did not wish to see any agreements
                            with the United States.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TRAINGF1">Train</persName> repeatedly urged Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_ARGUELLESYARMADAJ1">Arguelles</persName> to
                            use every effort to persuade General <persName corresp="#p_VIGONJ1">Vigon</persName> to permit the staff level discussions requested by
                            General <persName corresp="#p_KISSNERAW1">Kissner</persName> to commence
                            immediately and intimated that this was the “next step” indispensable to
                            consideration of the Spanish suggestions.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>It is not possible to obtain a base agreement in the form we now
                                propose in consideration of $125 million military and economic aid,
                                no matter how we slice this figure. We have convinced the Spanish
                                that this is all we are prepared to offer at this time. It is
                                possible to get an agreement to begin base construction at once, an
                                    <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> agreement and an Economic
                                Aid Agreement based on $125 million.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>If General <persName corresp="#p_KISSNERAW1">Kissner</persName>’s
                                staff level discussions result in conclusions that the Spanish army
                                can be satisfied with equipment to be delivered at some future date
                                costing say $150 million over a period of three years or $50 million
                                annually in addition to the military component of the $125 million
                                presently authorized, it is my opinion that we can get a base
                                agreement on the terms we want.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>