<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 952Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the Personal Secretary to the
                    Secretary of State (Evans)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v06p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d952</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">952</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-11-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-11-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="952"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d952">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.42321 SL/11–352</note>
                <head>No. 952<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the <gloss
                            type="from">Personal Secretary</gloss> to the Secretary of State
                            (<persName type="to">Evans</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1952-11-03">November 3,
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESOND1">Acheson</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The Secretary returned a telephone call which Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> had made to the Secretary
                    yesterday but which had not gone through to the Secretary who was out at the
                    farm. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> said he
                    wanted to discuss with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ACHESOND1">Acheson</persName>
                    the letter which the Prime Minister had sent to the President on Saturday<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d952fn1">
                        <ref target="#d951">
                            <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                    <pb facs="0954" n="2044" xml:id="pg_2044"/> and the note which the Canadians
                    proposed to present on November 4 to this Government in regard to canceling the
                    1941 agreement on the St. <persName corresp="#p_VASSLC1">Lawrence</persName>.
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> said that the
                    Prime Minister had explained that Canada proposed to take this action in view of
                    the International Joint Commission’s recent action. He had said that it would be
                    very embarrassing for the Canadian Government to go back before Parliament on
                    the basis of the 1941 agreement in view of the Joint Commission’s action and
                    that the Canadian Government was very anxious to state its position at this
                    time.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> had said to the
                    Prime Minister that he would get this information to the President and
                    subsequently telephoned Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MURPHYCS1">Murphy</persName>
                    and gave him the substance of the Prime Minister’s letter. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MURPHYCS1">Murphy</persName> thought that this action on the
                    part of the Canadian Government was precipitant in that it was being delivered
                    on election day. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> had
                    explained the Canadian reasons for wanting to deliver it on election day, i.e.,
                    by delivering it on election day they could not be accused of influencing the
                    American election one way or the other, nor could there be ascribed to the
                    Canadian Government any reaction on its part to whichever candidate won. Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MURPHYCS1">Murphy</persName> said he could see no
                    urgency from our point of view for having the Canadian Government take such
                    immediate action.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> said that he
                    reported to the Secretary of the Privy Council the fact that he had talked with
                    one of the President’s assistants and had passed on the substance of the Prime
                    Minister’s letter; that he did not feel that he could get in touch with the
                    President personally because of the pressure of his trip. The Secretary of the
                    Privy Council had reaffirmed that the farthest thought from Canadians minds was
                    to embarrass the President. It had been exactly the opposite and that was why
                    they had picked November 4 as the best day to deliver the note.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> pointed out to
                    the Secretary that his opinion was that the Canadians should be deferred from
                    delivering the note tomorrow, which would freeze their position. He thought the
                    President had gone very far in supporting the Canadian position and he felt that
                    this new proposed action would be difficult for the President.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he had had some talk with Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PEARSONLBM1">Pearson</persName> about the St. <persName
                        corresp="#p_VASSLC1">Lawrence</persName> project but that he had not been
                    told about the proposed letter to the President and the note. He had not talked
                    the matter over with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WRONGH1">Wrong</persName>, when
                    he saw him on Saturday night, because he did not know what the President’s
                    position <pb facs="0955" n="2045" xml:id="pg_2045"/> would be. Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> said that it had been
                    his understanding from the Prime Minister that the latter was going to ask Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_PEARSONLBM1">Pearson</persName> to tell the Secretary
                    about the note. The Secretary said that all Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_PEARSONLBM1">Pearson</persName> had spoken to him about was what
                    had been reported in the memorandum of conversation<note n="2" xml:id="d952fn2"
                        >No record of this meeting between the Ambassador and the Prime Minister,
                        presumably held in late October, has been found in Department of State
                        files.</note> which he had dictated in New York.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> said the more he
                    thought about it, the more important it seemed to him that the Canadians should
                    not take this position without further consultation with us and possibly some
                    talk with the President. The Secretary said he was inclined to agree and that,
                    if there should be any communication at this time, it would probably be better
                    not to have a written one. He said he would consult further in the Department
                    and would get in touch with the President.</p>
                <p>After talking with the President, which conversation is reported in a separate
                        memorandum,<note n="3" xml:id="d952fn3">
                        <ref target="#d953">
                            <hi rend="italic">Infra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> the Secretary telephoned Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> again and reported the
                    President’s views as set forth in the memorandum of conversation. The Secretary
                    said that he had told the President that he had a recommendation from Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> and from Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MURPHYCS1">Murphy</persName> that an effort should be made to
                    get the Canadians to defer the delivery of the note. The President had been firm
                    in his decision to let the note be delivered.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WOODWARDS1">Woodward</persName> said that he
                    would call the Secretary of the Privy Council and tell him that there was no
                    objection to delivering the note.<note n="4" xml:id="d952fn4">The note was
                        released to the press in Washington and Ottawa after delivery to <persName
                            corresp="#p_ACHESOND1">Acheson</persName> by <persName
                            corresp="#p_WRONGH1">Wrong</persName> on the afternoon of Nov. 4.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
