<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 965The Chairman, U.S. Section, Permanent Joint Board on Defense (Henry)
                    to the President</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v06p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d965</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">965</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-04-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-04-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec6XfF2Oe1IjakB2" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005823"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Electronic equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recOYjNCDlfiZUjKY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nickel</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="rec0NGmogdkmVrqib" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022963"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemicals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-04-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-04-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="965"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d965">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, <persName
                        corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName> papers, <persName
                        corresp="#p_WHITMANAC1">Whitman</persName> file, Admin series</note>
                <head>No. 965<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman, U.S. Section, Permanent Joint Board on Defense
                            (<persName corresp="#p_HENRYGV1" type="from">Henry</persName>) to the
                            <gloss type="to">President</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-04-23">April 23,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. President</hi>: In view of the impending visit
                    of the Prime Minister of Canada, I wish to inform you that at the last <pb
                        facs="0986" n="2076" xml:id="pg_2076"/> meeting of the Board, the Chairman
                    of the Canadian section made a strong plea on behalf of his Government that the
                    Board reaffirm its position, taken in 1948 and 1951, that completion of the St.
                        <persName corresp="#p_VASSLC1">Lawrence</persName> waterway and power
                    projects had a direct bearing on the defense of North America. I assured General
                        <persName corresp="#p_MCNAUGHTONAGL1">McNaughton</persName>, Canadian
                    Chairman, that this view, summarized in the attached memorandum, would be
                    brought to the attention of United States authorities.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HENRYGV1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Guy V. Henry</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Major General, U.S.A. (Ret.)</hi>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Enclosure]</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>At the meeting April 13–17, 1953, of the Permanent Joint Board on Defense,
                        Canada–United States, the Chairman of the Canadian Section presented a
                        submission containing views of the Government of Canada regarding the St.
                            <persName corresp="#p_VASSLC1">Lawrence</persName> Seaway and Power
                        Project (enclosure no. 1).<note n="1" xml:id="d965fn1">Agenda memorandum for
                            the members of the <gloss target="#t_PJBD1">PJBD</gloss>, Apr. 2, 1953,
                            not printed. (<persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName>
                            Library, <persName corresp="#p_EISENHOWER1">Eisenhower</persName>
                            papers, <persName corresp="#p_WHITMANAC1">Whitman</persName> file, Admin
                            series)</note> It was suggested that the Board reaffirm its previous
                        recommendations regarding the seaway and power developments.</p>
                    <p>The Chairman of the United States Section expressed belief that the Board’s
                        action in December 1948 and February 1951 already placed it on record as
                        favoring early development of the St. <persName corresp="#p_VASSLC1"
                            >Lawrence</persName> waterway and power projects as in the “best
                        interests” and “vital” for joint defense of Canada and the United States. He
                        agreed, however, to bring the views of the Canadian Section to the proper
                        authorities in the United States.</p>
                    <p>The submission, after providing familiar background regarding unsuccessful
                        earlier attempts to obtain Congressional approval for joint construction of
                        the power, Ontario is ready to undertake development of its share of the
                        power and navigation phases of the St. <persName corresp="#p_VASSLC1"
                            >Lawrence</persName> project, sets forth the present position: The
                        International Joint Commission having approved proposals for the
                        construction of power, Ontario is ready to undertake development of its
                        share of the power and the Canadian authorities are awaiting early and
                        favorable action by the Federal Power Commission on an <pb facs="0987"
                            n="2077" xml:id="pg_2077"/> application to construct power facilities on
                        the New York State side.</p>
                    <p>The project is considered urgent in Canada, from the standpoint of
                        preparedness, because the Ontario area to be served by power from the St.
                            <persName corresp="#p_VASSLC1">Lawrence</persName> provides nearly half
                        of Canada’s current production of defense goods. The proportions range from
                        100% of jet engines to 80% of mechanical transport and 60% of electronic
                        equipment. The area accounts for all Canadian-produced synthetic rubber, a
                        large proportion of explosives, ammunition, ships; large percentages of
                        nickel, copper, cobalt, and strategic non-ferrous metals, as well as major
                        fabricating capacity for specified metals and industrial chemicals.
                        Secondarily, it is asserted, with reference to the reciprocal procurement of
                        defense materials which the Board has fostered, that the more limited but
                        nonetheless real defense needs of the United States are dependent upon
                        industrial plants in Ontario where activity and expansion may be jeopardized
                        failing an early start in the development of power from the St. <persName
                            corresp="#p_VASSLC1">Lawrence</persName>.</p>
                    <p>The stated Canadian view is that early completion of the St. <persName
                            corresp="#p_VASSLC1">Lawrence</persName> navigation and power project
                        has, with the passing of time, become an urgent requirement in the defense
                        of the North American Continent.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
