<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-05-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-05-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="969" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d969">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">742.13/5–453</note>
                        <head>No. 969<lb/><hi rend="italic">Memorandum for the President by the
                                Secretary of State</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d969fn1">Drafted by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PETERSONAF1">Peterson</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-05-06">May 6, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <item>Subject: Visit of Canadian Prime Minister</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>This official visit of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STLAURENTLS1">St.
                                Laurent</persName> is partly for prestige purposes but mainly to
                            establish personal contact with you in keeping with past practice and
                            our special relationships with Canada. No specific subjects requiring
                            decision or leading to future negotiations are expected.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister will seek an exchange of views regarding <hi rend="italic">foreign policy and defense</hi>, probably taking your
                            April 16 speech<note n="2" xml:id="d969fn2">The “Chance for Peace”
                                address delivered before the American Society of Newspaper Editors
                                and broadcast to the nation over radio and television networks, is
                                printed in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, Apr.
                                27, 1953, p. 599.</note> as point of departure: your estimate of
                            Soviet intentions, the threat in South East Asia, prospects in Korea and
                            the future of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. The Canadians are
                            fearful we will become overextended in Asia at the cost of Europe and
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and will want to discuss <hi rend="italic">priorities in Defense.</hi> We should let them know we
                            count on their continued and enlarged support of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and in Korea.</p>
                        <p>The defense of North America will probably be discussed, with an estimate
                            of the <hi rend="italic">threat of Air Attack from the North</hi>, and
                            need for radar installations. For political reasons the Prime Minister
                            does not relish a large build-up of U.S. installations in Canada, will
                            want Canadians to do more in defense of Canada, and will be worried
                            about costs. You could <hi rend="italic">reassure him of our respect for
                                Canadian sovereignty</hi> and the fact that our mutual defense
                            arrangements are always jointly agreed. From our viewpoint principles
                            underlying our continental defense cooperation are satisfactory.</p>
                        <pb facs="0996" n="2086" xml:id="pg_2086"/>
                        <p>Views of the Canadian Government regarding the need to remove or lessen
                                <hi rend="italic">obstacles to trade</hi> will be discussed,
                            probably with some fears voiced lest U.S. trade policy may be developing
                            contrary to the interests of the free world in having international
                            trade liberalized. Canada is heavily dependent upon U.S. trade.</p>
                        <p>The Prime Minister will underline the importance to Canada of making a
                                <hi rend="italic">quick start on the power phase of the St.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_VASSLC1">Lawrence</persName></hi>. You
                            could mention the National Security Council’s conclusion that, on the
                            seaway phase, it would be desirable for the U.S. to participate, which
                            we hope continues to be agreeable to Canada, provided our participation
                            in the seaway does not delay the power works.</p>
                        <p>I have papers on subjects mentioned above should details be required in
                            the discussions.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DULLESJF1"><hi rend="smallcaps">John
                                        Foster Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>