<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-11T10:03:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-11T10:03:00-05:00" n="1024" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1024">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">357.AD/12–1150: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United
                            Nations</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Austin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-11T10:03:00-05:00">December 11,
                                1950—10:03 a. m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received December 11—10:21 a. m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 413. Re Korea—views of LA
                        delegations. During evening December 10 US <gloss target="#t_Gadel1">GADel</gloss> officer spoke separately with representatives of Brazil,
                        Chile, Cuba and Ecuador describing current developments re cease fire and
                        outlining US position as set forth by Gross and reported <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 400.<note n="1" xml:id="d1024fn1">Received at 9:55 p. m. on December 9, <ref target="#pg_1492">p.
                                1492</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>All 4 Latin Americans were pleased with developments and indicated approval
                        US position. At the same time all expressed in varied degree considerable
                        skepticism over possibility that PRC would accept cease fire agreement
                        without requiring political concessions on our part which we would be unable
                        to make. Gutierrez (Cuba) and Santa Cruz (Chile) emphasized importance of
                        thinking now of next step in event cease fire negotiations fail. They also
                        expressed view that situation is made more serious by failure of US and UK
                        to agree to broad issues in Far East and by what they sense as lowered
                        prestige of US among Asian and European countries because of military
                        reverses.</p>
                    <p>It appears that the Latin Americans as represented by the above 4 delegations
                        continue to be ready to support the US position in the Korean situation as
                        part of the larger world conflict and await our lead.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>