<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-21T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-21T04:00:00-05:00" n="1082" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1082">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/12–2150: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Korea</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Muccio</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Seoul</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-21T18:00:00+09:00">December 21,
                                1950—6 p. m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received December 21—1:54 p. m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>602. Korean Army has instituted inquiry into conduct of executions in British
                        area yesterday, has given assurances to British Chargé will be no further
                        executions in British area, and that lieutenant in charge firing party is
                        being held for court martial proceedings. Embassy officer examined court
                        martial records yesterday’s executions.</p>
                    <p>58 persons condemned to death by Military Court (57 for espionage and 1 for
                        murder) were to be shot yesterday; 20 were shot before British stopped
                        proceedings, remainder were returned to West Gate Prison. Of total 4 were
                        women, youngest being 29; youngest man was 20. All executions now suspended
                        pending investigation procedure and review of cases.</p>
                    <p>President issuing proclamation tomorrow announcing extensive amnesty
                        effective December 23, is expected reduce prison population by between
                        30–50%. Wiring separately.</p>
                    <p>Minister Justice and Home Minister appeared before <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss> this afternoon, made oral statements similar to that in
                        Justice Ministry release (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 600,
                        December 20 [<hi rend="italic">21</hi>]<note n="1" xml:id="d1082fn1">Telegram 600 not printed; the text of the public statement issued by
                            the Minister of Justice is in U.N. document A/1881, pp. 20–22.</note>)
                        and announcing details amnesty program. <gloss target="#t_UNCURK1">UNCURK</gloss> will make press release shortly describing same.<note n="2" xml:id="d1082fn2">Text <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 22.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Justice Ministry arranging with <gloss target="#t_EUSAK1">EUSAK</gloss> for
                        transportation for 2900 major criminals from Seoul to Taejon and Taegu
                        prisons within next few days. Will leave approximately 2,000 ordinary
                        criminals in prison here.</p>
                    <p>Repeated info Tokyo unnumbered.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Muccio</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>