<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-06-25T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-06-25T23:00:00-05:00" n="112" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">330/6–2650: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United
                            Nations</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Austin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-06-26T00:00:00-04:00">June 26,
                                1950—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received June 27—1:35 a. m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>546. Reports from <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> re Korea: The
                        following telegram reports conversations by <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> officers with other delegations and <pb facs="0209" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/> Secretariat personnel and is substituted for
                        usual <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> daily classified summary and
                        separate documents of these conversations.<note n="1" xml:id="d112fn1">The
                            names of the members of the U.S. Delegation involved in the
                            conversations are given parenthetically at the end of each
                            section.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Views of Security Council Members:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>UK—In exploratory talk on possible courses of action which SC might take in
                        event North Koreans ignored resolution, Laskey (UK) indicated he had no
                        instructions. He gave personal estimate of type of action which Council
                        might be willing to take. It might make findings in more detail regarding
                        invasion and determine it was unprovoked act of aggression, violation of
                        Charter, et cetera. He also thought SC would be willing to authorize or give
                        blessing to action which any member might take in support of south Koreans
                        with respect to military aid.</p>
                    <p>Laskey doubted Council’s willingness to give blessing to direct military
                        support, or to lay aggression at door of USSR. In any case, he felt Council
                        would be swayed by events. If South Korea had fallen or was obviously about
                        to fall, there would be no inclination to take strong action. If South Korea
                        appeared able to hold out, chances for strong action would greatly increase.
                        However, he felt there would be difficulty in assuming full moral
                        responsibility for action which might result in third world war.</p>
                    <p>In confidence, Laskey indicated British Embassy Moscow had suggested SC take
                        advantage of Russian absence to request USSR formally to support Council’s
                        June 26 [<hi rend="italic">25</hi>] action. UK delegation reaction, he
                        indicated, was that it would be inappropriate to direct resolution to
                        Russians but that this general line might be developed in speeches. He had
                        no question in his mind that Russians were fully responsible. He seemed to
                        hold view it might be advantageous not to lay attack at door of Russians in
                        hope that if South Koreans proved strong enough to defend themselves, the
                        Russians might conceivably ditch North Koreans since Russians had not
                        committed their own prestige publicly. (Noyes, J. Hyde.)</p>
                    <p>Ecuador—at end of SC meeting June 25, Correa (Ecuador) said he had just been
                        on telephone to Quito and had been instructed to keep in closest touch with
                            <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> and to support US moves in dealing
                        with problem. He added that continuing and strong Ecuadoran support in SC
                        could be counted upon. (J. Hyde.)</p>
                    <p>Cuba—During the meeting, Ribas (Cuba) stated there was no question of their
                        continuing support in handling problem. (J Hyde.)</p>
                    <p>China—Tsiang (China) telephoned and recalled that US Chargé in Formosa had
                        been in touch with former’s government and that understanding was that US
                        and China would keep in close touch on <pb facs="0210" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/> Korean ease. In light of this, he asked what last word
                        on US thinking was. (J. Hyde.)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Views of Members not Represented on Security Council:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Australia (<gloss target="#t_UNCOK1">UNCOK</gloss> member)—Indicating no
                        reactions had yet been received from his government but that they were
                        expected June 27, Shann’s personal view was that Australia would be prepared
                        to support SC action calling for armed intervention and that its position
                        would be as strong as that of any UN member. His conversations with other
                        members had given him impression that most would gladly support a resolution
                        which meant US would fight their battles. He thought UN might be prepared to
                        support action placing responsibility on Soviet Union but he did not feel
                        this would be of much value even though it resulted in their ouster from the
                        UN.</p>
                    <p>Considering this action on part of Russians a clear indication that they did
                        not intend to return to UN, and having thought for a long time that
                        reorganization of UN without them would be advantageous, Shann now felt it
                        was far preferable to oust them over an issue of this kind rather than for
                        them to leave over an issue such as Chinese representation. In his opinion,
                        events in Korea made it impossible to seat Chinese Communists at GA.</p>
                    <p>Shann thought there would be little advantage in a GA special session unless
                        it were called to work out strong measures to save the situation. It might
                        provide an opportunity for the small powers who feared starting a world war
                        to exercise influence in the direction of mediation, half measures, et
                        cetera, but he thought they might prefer to be faced with a SC decision
                        binding upon them.</p>
                    <p>The UN had no alternative but to stand up to this test, in Shann’s view, for
                        if it failed to do so, it would go way of League and situation in South East
                        Asia would be worse than disastrous.</p>
                    <p>In earlier conversation, Shann indicated that although the June 25 resolution
                        was vital, it was obvious to him that no attention would be paid it by North
                        Koreans. He wanted to know what US could do in why of meeting force with
                        force and thought perhaps the Australians were in position to help if UN
                        decided to take strong action. (Noyes.)</p>
                    <p>Philippines (<gloss target="#t_UNCOK1">UNCOK</gloss> member)—Ingles
                        (Philippines) as usual had nothing to say in Romulo’s absence. Romulo
                        apparently told him before departing for Manila that he would telephone or
                        telegraph “some thoughts” to delegation here. (Maflitt.)</p>
                    <p>Canada—Although he had no word from his government on Korean developments,
                        Holmes (Canada) expressed view that SC might conceivably give its blessing
                        to any military action which US was willing to take. He agreed some action
                        would be necessary June 27 or 28. (Noyes, J. Hyde.)</p>
                    <pb facs="0211" n="191" xml:id="pg_191"/>
                    <p>Dominican Republic—During SC meeting, De Marchena (Dominican Republic) said
                        he had been on telephone to his Foreign Office and his government was firmly
                        behind vigorous US approach to problem. In subsequent conversation,
                        Henriquez-Urena did not appear unduly alarmed, seeing present situation as
                        simply another provocative act in series occurring in past few months. He
                        felt June 25 resolution was sufficient first step but next one should be
                        stronger. He suggested possibility of Council calling on any country able to
                        do so to go all out to Korea’s assistance. He felt SC vote had shown
                        unanimity in free areas of world. (J. Hyde, Maffitt.)</p>
                    <p>Uruguay—Fabregat (Uruguay) was very much alarmed, said concept of aggression
                        could not be tolerated and thought strongest measures should be taken. He
                        had no specific suggestion but felt Henriquez-Urena’s idea should be tried.
                        (Maffitt.)</p>
                    <p>Argentina—Situation was most serious and required energetic measures, Munoz
                        (Argentina) stated. He thought it time to call things by their right names
                        and therefore USSR should be named as source of this aggression. He greatly
                        feared results in rest of Asia from successful aggression in Korea,
                        (Maffitt.)</p>
                    <p>Pakistan—Chhatari (Pakistan) said formally that Pakistanis deplored this
                        resort to arms and any government striking at foundations of UN through
                        aggression should be dealt with very strongly. He thought June 25 resolution
                        childish but seemed to be referring more to fact that only UN action so far
                        had been a resolution. If all an aggressor had to fear from SC was paper
                        resolution, he said aggression would not be deterred. He was worried at
                        possibility an aggressor might get away with his act and present world with
                            <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> of most illegal nature.
                        (Maffitt.)</p>
                    <p>Netherlands—Luns had been instructed to impress on all members he saw how
                        seriously Netherlands Government considered this crisis in UN. Discussing
                        next SC step, Luns felt it necessary to go farther and probably attempt a
                        resolution condemning North Koreans action, and making it possible not only
                        for US but all members to supply at least material assistance to South
                        Korea. He found President’s statement strong and very helpful.</p>
                    <p>Speaking personally, Luns felt if Council adopted resolution calling on
                        members to assist Korean Republic with military supplies, Netherlands would
                        be prepared to do so at least in token manner. He referred to strong Dutch
                        forces now in Pacific and thought it possible that his government, if asked
                        on basis of such resolution, would supply perhaps two destroyers. He
                        stressed Dutch still had interests in Pacific and took very basic view as UN
                        member.</p>
                    <p>Luns was critical of France, feeling they did not see clearly enough the
                        implications of this attack on over-all Asian situation/Indochina <pb facs="0212" n="192" xml:id="pg_192"/> and Korea were all part of Asia
                        problem. He offered make preliminary check with his government as to what
                        military assistance it would be prepared to give. He referred with some
                        bitterness to statement by Indonesian spokesman that this was US-Russian
                        fight in which Indonesians should be absolutely neutral. Commenting on
                        immediate SC activities, Luns gave personal view, as was all of above, that
                        escape hatch should be allowed for Russians to disassociate selves from what
                        may prove to be unsuccessful adventure. (J. Hyde.)</p>
                    <p>Brazil—Ouro Preto fully supported resolution adopted by SC but, in absence of
                        his ambassador, indicated he would have to ask for instructions as to
                        general line to follow if cease-fire order ignored. Commenting on desire of
                        number of members to admit Chinese Communists, he implied there would be
                        considerable sentiment among such nations against taking strong action. He
                        gave impression his attitude was one of extreme caution rather than that he
                        had strong views against UN taking strong action. (Noyes.)</p>
                    <p>Sweden—Grafstrom (Sweden) felt this was most serious crisis that UN has faced
                        in two years. He agreed that if North Koreans disregarded SC order, Council
                        must take further action if UN was to survive. He was thinking in terms of
                        resolution condemnatory of North Korean regime and permitting US and others
                        to give military assistance to Republic. There was no implication that his
                        government would be party to such undertaking, but Grafstrom stressed that
                        further action should be taken. He was clearly thinking of sanctions. He
                        felt strongly that handling of case should not point finger inevitably to
                        Russians as responsible. He thought to attempt to underline Russian
                        liability and supply military assistance to the Republic of Korea on that
                        basis meant war. (J. Hyde.)</p>
                    <p>Thailand—Amatayakul (Thailand) had no instructions and said he did not expect
                        any. He seemed most concerned to report to his government on (1) whether US
                        at June 27 meeting would ask aid be given by members to Korea; and (2) what
                        validity should be given to Pyongyang allegation that June 25 resolution was
                        illegal because Nationalist Chinese participated. (Maffitt.)</p>
                    <p>Turkey—During SC meeting, Kural (Turkey) advocated a strong line in
                        conversation with <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> and said he was
                        sorry SC resolution had been watered down. It was first time in his view
                        that Communists had undertaken direct military aggression without attempt to
                        cover it up. He thought this was important test which must be met with
                        strong action. He wondered what US was prepared to do when it was clear that
                        resolution was being ignored. (Noyes.)</p>
                    <p>Indonesia—Palar (Indonesia) who was also interviewed at SC meeting, fully
                        supported US resolution and course of action it contemplated. However, he
                        was somewhat concerned that his people did not <pb facs="0213" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/> have full information necessary to convince them of
                        serious significance of this attack. At outset, he expressed anxiety that
                        Indonesians might think SC acted without full information in finding South
                        Korea had been invaded. He was convinced SC resolution would be ignored by
                        North Koreans and wondered what US was prepared to do in that case. Palar
                        was most anxious to keep in close touch with <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> and planned to get in touch immediately with his
                        government. (Noyes.)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Other Comments:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Mascia, Italian observer, stated his government was not only deeply
                        interested but concerned because it saw in this case the future of the UN
                        directly involved. He liked the US approach. (J. Hyde.)</p>
                    <p>Feller and Cordier (Secretariat) were both delighted at Lie’s strong
                        statement in SC. Cordier was quite frank in pressing view this would help
                        SYG in light of his current troubles with American public opinion. They felt
                        this event helped Lie to prove he was a UN man right down the line
                        regardless of which way the chips fell.</p>
                    <p>Both UN officials advanced idea that Council’s resolution would not be
                        effective and indicated their understanding that major decision had to be
                        made whether to meet force with force. They seemed to favor a strong line.
                        Cordier indicated this development would completely upset all UN plans,
                        including especially question of seating Chinese Communists. He considered
                        it out of question that they would be seated either at <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> session July 3 or at GA. (Noyes.)</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>