<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-06-27T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-06-27T05:00:00-05:00" n="114" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d114">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/6–2750: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                            the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-06-27T13:00:00+03:00">June 27,
                                1950—1 p. m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received June 27—8:55 a. m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>1743. Indian counselor Kapur called at Embassy June 26 to obtain information
                        re US position on Korean situation, saying his Embassy had received urgent
                        instructions to find out how far US prepared to go both within and without
                        UN to assist <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> in throwing back North
                        Korean invaders. Embassy officer said he was not in position to give
                        authoritative answer to such a broad question and asked whether it was
                        correct to assume that Ambassador Pandit<note n="1" xml:id="d114fn1">Madame
                            Pandit was Indian Ambassador in the United States.</note> would be
                        keeping in close touch with responsible US officials in Washington on this
                        important question. Kapur answered that Pandit had received same
                        instructions as Indian Ambassador Moscow but that frankly she had proved
                        such a “bust” in Washington that he doubted she would ascertain what <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> wanted to know, i.e., “whether US was
                        prepared risk World War III over Korea”.</p>
                    <pb facs="0216" n="196" xml:id="pg_196"/>
                    <p>Kapur then proceeded expound in similarly frank vein views which he said
                        reflect present <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> outlook on situation
                        Asia in light Soviet military move Korea: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>He said that Indian estimate has been that US not prepared follow
                                firm line in Asia if possible risk of war with Soviets
                                involved.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Soviets are not themselves prepared for full-scale war but being
                                aware underlying lack of firmness in US position will continue
                                extend their power by indirect means with minimum risks until such
                                time as they have developed necessary military and economic
                                potential to engage in all-out war if latter at that time necessary
                                achieve their final objectives.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>When Ambassador Radhakrishnan<note n="2" xml:id="d114fn2">Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan was Indian Ambassador in the Soviet
                                    Union.</note> asked Stalin<note n="3" xml:id="d114fn3">Iosif V.
                                    Stalin, Chairman of the Council of Ministers of the Soviet
                                    Union.</note> last January, whether US intervention in Indochina
                                would not make a difference, Stalin replied “the people will decide
                                first,” this being interpreted by Kapur to mean that Soviets would
                                not be deterred by kind of aid US now contemplating furnish
                                Indochina.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Indians believe that US action or inaction re Korea will be key to
                                our subsequent policy (and thus also to Soviet policy) in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>If US takes a firm stand on Korea, doubtful that war with Soviets
                                will occur, but if it should materalize over that issue, India will
                                come into US camp.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> very skeptical efficacy UN
                                action if confined to vague restraining moves and not accompanied by
                                clear-cut and forceful application of US military power.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>India’s reluctance thus far place itself squarely in anti-Soviet
                                camp not based on lack realistic appreciation of threat to India
                                arsing from link between Soviet power and Indian Communists but
                                rather on peculiar domestic and regional considerations which US has
                                so far failed utterly to understand, most important being that for
                                India to adhere unequivocally to US camp would almost certainly
                                drive Pakistan into Soviet bloc, and Soviet “Communism would quickly
                                entrench itself only an overnight’s journey from Delhi, i.e. at
                                Lahore”.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>If US makes firm and successful display its military power in
                                Korea, not only will this have heartening effects in Japan, <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> and India but it will also impress
                                Communist China.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Reports just received from Indian representative Tokyo do not,
                                however, indicate that such application US military power
                                forthcoming in Korea.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Kapur was told at end conversation that his frank expression of views
                        appreciated and that since US particularly interested in Indian attitude on
                        such Asian questions as Korea, it was hoped that at this critical juncture
                        Indian representatives at Washington and New York, not to mention <gloss target="#t_MEA1">MEA</gloss> Delhi, would not fail to transmit to
                        responsible US officials candid expressions of <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> views on this latest flagrant Soviet threat to peace.</p>
                    <pb facs="0217" n="197" xml:id="pg_197"/>
                    <p>Though Kapur purported be taking official line, his remarks probably mixture
                        personal and official opinion. Nevertheless, Embassy believes that views
                        expressed by him sufficiently authoritative to warrant conclusion that
                            <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> policy on Korea will be shaped to
                        considerable extent by their estimates as to firmness US counter-moves.</p>
                    <p>View nature Kapur’s approach, Embassy would appreciate receiving any
                        appropriate information on US position Korea which can be passed on to
                        Indian Embassy here. Also please protect source.</p>
                    <p>Department pass New Delhi, <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>; repeated
                        info New Delhi 28. <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> 41.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>