<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-06-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-06-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/8–2550</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Charles P. Noyes,
                            Adviser on Security Council Affairs, United States Mission at the United
                            Nations</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d180fn1">The source text is a copy of a
                            document in the <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files, Department of
                            State, bearing the designation US/S/1269 and the date June 30,
                            1950.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">New
                                York</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-06-30">June 30, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Korea</p>
                    <p>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top">Participants:</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Andrew W. Cordier, Executive
                                    Assistant to the Secretary-General</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. A. H. Feller, Legal Office of the
                                    Assistant Secretary-General</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. C. P. Noyes, United States
                                    Mission</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>Cordier expressed disappointment that, as he understood, we were not in a
                        position to make any move today in the Security Council in <pb facs="0284" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/> implementation of the Council’s decision. He
                        indicated that he thought there were three problems:</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">first</hi> involved the problem of coordination of
                        offers of assistance and the organization of a channel of communication
                        between Lake Success and Korea. I asked him how he thought this problem
                        should be solved. He said that he had had many expressions of opinion from
                        various government Representatives with whom he had spoken in the last two
                        or three days and mentioned in particular Foreign Minister Pearson.<note n="2" xml:id="d180fn2">Lester B. Pearson, Canadian Secretary of State
                            for External Affairs.</note> The general consensus seemed to be that it
                        is important that there should be some official machinery with the United
                        Nations label which could coordinate these offers of military assistance and
                        take any other action in implementation of the Council’s decision. He
                        thought the simplest device would be a Security Council Committee made up of
                        a number of the Members of the Security Council. This Committee could meet
                        in private. It would be able to consider offers of assistance and make
                        arrangements to decide whether offers could be accepted. It could establish
                        a channel of communications via the United States Mission to MacArthur’s
                        command, and another channel of communications direct to the Government of
                        Korea through a Representative of Korea. It would be an excellent umbrella
                        for all activities in this field and would have important public relations
                        aspects. In this respect he mentioned that its Reports to the Security
                        Council would be useful. The Committee would also be in a position to meet
                        with Representatives of States who were not Members of the Security Council
                        and who had offered aid. I told Cordier I would let him know as soon as we
                        got any reactions.</p>
                    <p>As to the <hi rend="italic">second</hi> point, Cordier said that there had
                        been a number of expressions of opinion, both from Representatives and the
                        Press, in support of the designation in some way of a United Nations
                        Commander in Chief. The title was not important but there was a strong
                        feeling on the part of many Delegations that there should be some
                        acknowledgment of the fact that the combined forces were acting on behalf of
                        the United Nations; since in fact most nations who had offered substantial
                        contributions had already made private arrangements to place these units
                        under General MacArthur’s command, it was obvious that the easiest device
                        would be to arrange for General MacArthur to be given some title. He thought
                        this could be done in several ways. It could be handled through appointment
                        being made by the Security Council. It could be made by the Government of
                        South Korea, or could be made, formally or informally, by the States who
                        were contributing and later acknowledged or confirmed in some way by the
                        Security Council. We discussed some of the difficulties. Cordier <pb facs="0285" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/> seemed to favor the third
                        alternative. He thought it would be quite adequate. I told him we had no
                        instructions on this point as yet but were still discussing the matter with
                        the Department. I told him I would let him know as soon as we got any
                        reaction.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">third</hi> point: the United Nations Flag. Cordier said
                        that they considered the question of the combined forces flying the United
                        Nations Flag. Feller came up and indicated he had already given us a copy of
                        a legal memorandum.<note n="3" xml:id="d180fn3">Not printed.</note> His view
                        is that it would be entirely legal for this to be done. I told them that
                        Ambassador Austin’s reaction had been that it is wrong to fly a flag of
                        peace over troops. Feller pointed out that the philosophy behind the
                        regulations which the Secretary-General had already approved was based on a
                        different principle, namely, that the United Nations flag should fly over
                        all United Nations activities of whatever nature. He pointed out that our
                        purpose in the present crisis is peace and that the Charter itself
                        contemplated that peace could best be served by enforcing collective
                        security.</p>
                    <p>Cordier indicated that the Secretad-General was enthusiastic about the idea.
                        He thought it would have excellent public-relations value and that something
                        of this kind was badly needed. If the United States was willing to accept
                        this suggestion, he was quite certain that the Secretary-General would be
                        prepared to contact the other Members of the Security Council, as well as
                        all nations whose forces were fighting under MacArthur’s command, to
                        determine whether they would agree to this proposal. If the consensus is
                        favorable, he thought the Secretary-General would himself be prepared to
                        propose to the Security Council that this be done.</p>
                    <p>Cordier suggested it might be done by a short resolution authorizing the
                        combined forces to fly the United Nations Flag. It was conceivable that it
                        might be done by the Secretary-General on his own responsibility if he had
                        determined in advance that the nations primarily involved were
                        agreeable.</p>
                    <p>Cordier urged that we move as rapidly as possible on these questions. He
                        though that this coming long weekend provided an excellent opportunity to
                        give the matter careful thought and to come up with a good solution by next
                            Wednesday.<note n="4" xml:id="d180fn4">July 5, 1950.</note> He said he
                        would be available Monday for any consultations.</p>
                    <p>In the meantime I told Cordier that if he had any problems, we should be very
                        glad to work closely with him and act as a channel of communication between
                        his office and our authorities in Washington. I thought such a channel would
                        serve for the moment.</p>
                    <pb facs="0286" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Egyptian Position on Korea</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Cordier and Lie indicated they were very much upset about the Egyptian
                        position. Cordier thought Egypt’s position with the Membership of the United
                        Nations had suffered terribly. He commented that it was particularly bad in
                        the light of the situation at the time of Egypt’s election two years
                            ago.<note n="5" xml:id="d180fn5">Egypt was elected to a seat on the
                            Security Council in 1948; for related documentation, see <ref target="frus1948v01p1#pg_98">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, part 1, pp. 98</ref> ff.</note>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>C. P. <hi rend="smallcaps">Noyes</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>