<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Douglas) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d240</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">240</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-07-08T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-07-08T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-08T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-08T08:00:00-05:00" n="240"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d240">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">330/7–850: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Douglas</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-08T14:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 8, 1950—2 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received July 8—9:50 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>156. Eyes only for the Secretary.</p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>I called at Foreign Office this morning reDeptel 83<note n="1"
                                xml:id="d240fn1">Transmitted at 12 noon on July 7, <ref
                                    target="#pg_327">p. 327</ref>.</note> and had preliminary
                            conversation with Younger and later with Prime Minister who called at
                            Foreign Office. As British had full text of Reftel detailed repetition
                            of contents was unnecessary. Prime Minister stated that British thinking
                            was consistent with ours; that they would despatch a holding telegram to
                            Kelley at once informing him that instructions would follow; that
                            instructions would be along lines of following paragraph; that text
                            would be furnished you in Washington and to me here and that Kelley
                            would be told not to take action for 48 hours to give you time to
                            comment.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Kelley would be instructed to confine himself to general terms and to
                            the resolutions of SC. He would be told to endeavor to draw Gromyko out
                            in order to determine insofar as possible the Soviet’s position and what
                            they are prepared to do. Kelley will make it clear that UK is acting
                            wholly within the framework of UN resolutions and that UK as a member of
                            SC would be glad to listen to any proposals Soviets may have in
                            mind.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Speaking entirely off the record and personally I suggested to Prime
                            Minister that very probably one of the prices which Soviets would demand
                            for using their influence to cause withdrawal North Korean forces would
                            be agreement that Communist China be seated in SC. If Communist China
                            became member SC its claim to Formosa would be difficult to refute and
                            the US position would be made extremely difficult. Thus price of
                            Communist representative in SC might result in a real estate swap of
                            South Korea for Formosa. Prime Minister replied that British had been
                            thinking along this same line and that the position of <gloss
                                target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> would be that the question of Korea and
                            admittance of Communist China to SC were wholly separate.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0352" n="332" xml:id="pg_332"/>
                <p>Department pass Moscow; repeated info Moscow 9 eyes only for the Ambassador.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Douglas</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
