<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The President of the Republic of Korea ( (Rhee) ) to President Truman</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d326</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">326</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-07-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-07-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="326"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d326">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/7–1950</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The President of the Republic of Korea</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Rhee</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to"
                            >Truman</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d326fn1">The source text is the original of this letter as
                        transmitted by Ambassador Muccio to Mr. Acheson tinder a covering note, not
                        printed, on July 19; a copy of the text was also sent in telegram 60 from
                        Taegu (not printed), July 19, which, however, was delayed in transmission
                        and not received in the Department of State until July 23.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Taegu</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-19">July 19,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: I can not find words to express,
                    for myself and for all the people and Government of Korea, our profound
                    gratitude for your prompt and continued actions in bringing aid to Korea in
                    these desperate days. While we deeply appreciate the support of so many free
                    nations, through the United Nations, to the cause of Korea, which also is the
                    cause of freedom, we know full well that without your courageous leadership in a
                    time of bewildering crisis there would have been no support and no aid.</p>
                <p>I am deeply moved as I learn of increasing American battle casualties here. It is
                    a tragic thing that so many men should have had to give their lives for liberty
                    in this land so far from their own. It is easier for me to accept word of our
                    own battle casualties than of yours, cruel as ours have been, since our forces
                    are fighting in and for their native land. I wish I could convey to every mother
                    and father and wife and child, and sister and brother of an American soldier
                    killed or wounded here in Korea even some slight comfort through the knowledge
                    that no Korean can ever forget the courage and sacrifice of these men who in the
                    great traditions of the United States of America have come to the defense of the
                    weak against the cruel aggressor, and have fought and given their life’s blood
                    that liberty and freedom should not perish from the earth. These soldiers of
                    your great country, Mr. President, have lived and died as Americans, but they
                    have given their lives even beyond love of country as citizens of the world,
                    knowing that to permit the further destruction of the independence of free
                    nations by the Comminazis is to clear the way to assault upon every nation, even
                    the United States itself.</p>
                <pb facs="0449" n="429" xml:id="pg_429"/>
                <p>As you know, the Korean people were divided against their will: as a result of
                    military decisions in 1945 regarding the 38th Parallel, to which no Korean was a
                    party. This division permitted the development in the north, under Soviet
                    direction and leadership, of a communist regime wholly alien to Korean
                    traditions and feelings. With absolute control of the military, police and
                    fiscal powers in that region of Korea, the communists, with Soviet direction,
                    were able to create the formidable force which has caused such cruel damage not
                    only to Korea but also to the United States and most members of the United
                    Nations. When the Soviet sponsored regime in North Korea simultaneously attacked
                    the defense forces of the Republic of Korea in the early morning of June 25,
                    they ended any possible claim to the maintenance of the 38th Parallel as a
                    political or military dividing line between free and slave Korea.</p>
                <p>It would be utter folly to attempt to restore the <hi rend="italic">status quo
                        ante</hi>, and then to await the enemy’s pleasure for further attack when he
                    had had time to regroup, retrain and reequip. The time has come to cut out once
                    and for all the cancer of imperialist aggression, the malignant growth
                    artificially grown within the bosom of our country by the world communists.</p>
                <p>The people of North Korea are the same as the people of South Korea. All are
                    loyal to the land of their birth with the very few minor exceptions of foreign
                    trained and foreign directed communists. This war is not a conflict between
                    North and South; it is a conflict between the few who are communists, who by an
                    accident got control of half of our country, and the overwhelming mass of the
                    citizens of Korea, wherever they may live.</p>
                <p>The Government and the people of the Republic of Korea consider this is the time
                    to unify Korea, and for anything less than unification to come out of these
                    great sacrifices of Koreans and their powerful allies would be unthinkable. I am
                    sure, Mr. President, that you have come to the same conclusion yourself, but I
                    wish to make clear to you the position of this Government. The Korean Government
                    would consider as without binding effect any future agreement or understanding
                    made regarding Korea by other states or groups of states without the consent and
                    approval of the Government of the Republic of Korea. From statements which you
                    have made recently I believe that this also is the position of the Government of
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>Daily I pray for the joint success of our arms, for clear skies so that the
                    planes of the United States Airforce may search out and destroy the enemy, and
                    for the earliest possible arrival of sufficient men and material so that we can
                    turn to the offensive, break through the hard <pb facs="0450" n="430"
                        xml:id="pg_430"/> crust of enemy forces and start the victorious march
                    north. I have no slightest doubt in the ultimate victory of our cause; I know
                    that both right and might are on our side.<note n="2" xml:id="d326fn2">For
                        President Truman’s reply, see telegram 68 to Taegu, August 10, <ref
                            target="#pg_553">p. 553</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>With ever continued warm personal regards,</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Syngman Rhee</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
