<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in India ( (Henderson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d345</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">345</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-07-23T12:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-07-23T12:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rectswnul2C5uzE9Y" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092233"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Non-alignment</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-23T12:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-23T12:30:00-05:00" n="345"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d345">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">330/7–2350: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-23T23:00:00+05:30"
                            >July 23, 1950—11 p. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received July 23—6:36 p. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>180. Deptel 106, July 22.</p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>It is somewhat difficult decide whether or not we should engage in
                            further correspondence on this subject. Among factors this end are: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Nehru and Bajpai who in effect is <gloss target="#t_FonMin1"
                                        >FonMin</gloss> appear to be considerably irritated at our
                                    reply. Bajpai particularly seems to have taken reply as personal
                                    affront and has made number of sarcastically critical remarks to
                                    other chiefs of mission. For instance, immediately following
                                    receipt our reply British Chargé asked him if Indian press might
                                    not start campaign against US. Bajpai’s answer was “They won’t
                                    like the American reply any better than I”. To another diplomat
                                    he said “The US has made its decision and the worse for US”. To
                                    another he said US had completely failed understand spirit in
                                    which approach was made. Bajpai’s anger due in part personal
                                    pique. Although idea of sending messages was it seems first
                                    suggested by Krishna Menon <gloss target="#t_HC1">HC</gloss> to
                                    UK most effective foe of US among Nehru’s trusted inner circle,
                                    Bajpai assumed role master strategist. He personally drafted
                                    messages after presenting arguments to me re importance seating
                                    of Peiping in SC, after working on British, etc. With his
                                    supersensitive mind he apparently has interpreted second
                                    paragraph our reply in which we state our policies re
                                    maintenance peace and of strengthening UN as veiled insinuations
                                    that our policies this respect were in contrast those of India.
                                    He apparently failed note that this paragraph had been inspired
                                    by mention these points in Nehru’s original message to us. This
                                    misconception Bajpai’s part responsible for third paragraph
                                    Nehru’s second published note.<note n="1" xml:id="d345fn1">See
                                        telegram 148, from New Delhi, received on July 19 at 9:27 a.
                                        m., <ref target="#pg_425">p. 425</ref>. Reference is to the
                                        third and fourth sentences of Mr. Nehru’s message.</note>
                                    Neither Nehru nor Bajpai has made move discuss exchange with me
                                    subsequent receipt our reply. I have considered it wise not to
                                    approach them on subject for present. Bajpai has taken occasion
                                    twice to tell me over telephone <pb facs="0475" n="455"
                                        xml:id="pg_455"/> that <gloss target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss>
                                    considers correspondence on this subject as “terminated” and
                                    both times I have indicated my belief US Government has similar
                                    views.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Indian press in general has denounced what it considers as
                                    thwarting by US of Nehru’s efforts for peace. Nehru by this move
                                    has won back favor of those sections Indian press which most
                                    enthusiastically support India’s policy of “non-alignment with
                                    either power bloc.” Nehru and Bajpai are undoubtedly encouraging
                                    to some extent criticism in Indian press our response to Nehru’s
                                    approach.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>There is no indication our reply has irritated such Indian
                                    political leaders as Patel<note n="2" xml:id="d345fn2">Deputy
                                        Prime Minister Sardar Vallabhai Patel.</note> and
                                    Rajagopalachari who seem to understand our position.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Nehru and Bajpai are further annoyed by leak in Washington of
                                    Nehru’s second message.<note n="3" xml:id="d345fn3">See
                                        enclosure 1 to the note from Madame Pandit to Mr. Acheson,
                                        July 17, <ref target="#pg_408">p. 408</ref>.</note> Bajpai
                                    telephoned me about <hi rend="italic">NY Times</hi> article
                                    expressing surprise Nehru and self and complaining same time re
                                        <hi rend="italic">NY Times</hi> unfortunate editorial on
                                    Kashmir.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>I am inclined believe that in spite Bajpai’s intimations <gloss
                                target="#t_GOI1">GOI</gloss> would prefer correspondence closed we
                            should send immediately another note along lines suggested. Following my
                            reasons: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>By outlining with such frankness our reasons for turning down
                                    Nehru approach to us we would indicate that we consider his
                                    cooperation important and desire take him into our
                                    confidence.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Delivery of note would furnish Nehru and Bajpai
                                    self-satisfying opportunity give vent to their resentment
                                    arising from injured pride. It would also give me chance to
                                    point out their misinterpretation spirit of our formal
                                    reply.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Note contains convincing exposition our position which must
                                    have certain effect on Nehru and much more so on other members
                                    his new Cabinet Committee on Korea—Patel, Rajagopalachari,
                                    Ayyangar.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Delivery should be soon in order prevent resentment Nehru and
                                    Bajpai from hardening and to influence them to curtail their
                                    critical comments of us to Indian leaders and press and foreign
                                    diplomats and from taking other steps which might be
                                    injurious.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Following represent certain suggestions re Department’s draft: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>First sentence fourth paragraph. It might be helpful instead
                                    merely of referring to reasons given Nehru orally last autumn
                                    for our failure to recognize Peiping, to list most cogent
                                    reasons as we did in recent message to Bevin (Deptel 40, July
                                        10<note n="4" xml:id="d345fn4">See telegram 132, July 10, 5
                                        p. m. to London, <ref target="#pg_347">p. 347</ref>,
                                        repeated to New Delhi as 40</note> section 2 first seven
                                    numbered points). Foreign Relations Committee Cabinet might thus
                                    be in better position understand our policy toward
                                    Peiping.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Change next last sentence paragraph 5 to read: <quote
                                        rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“We are hoping that in the present critical phase of the
                                            development of the UN as an effective mechanism to
                                            prevent aggression <pb facs="0476" n="456"
                                                xml:id="pg_456"/> those nations sharing the common
                                            objective of stopping aggression in Korea will not
                                            permit differences of opinion over such questions as
                                            Chinese representation to divert their attention and
                                            energies from the attainment of this objective.”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Second sentence penultimate paragraph. Substitute words
                                    “continue to endeavor” for “make every effort”.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Any leak Washington this message after previous leaks would be most
                            unfortunate. It is difficult us believe leaks have been US sources. We
                            are wondering whether member some foreign diplomatic mission in
                            Washington might not have been indiscreet.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
