<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Executive Secretary of the National Security Council (
                    (Lay))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">356</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-07-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-07-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-07-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="356"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d356">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Executive Secretariat Files: <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76/1</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Executive Secretary of the National Security
                        Council</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lay</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76/1</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-07-25">July 25,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Note by the Executive Secretary to the National Security
                        Council on</hi> U.S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Courses of Action in the Event
                        Soviet Forces Enter Korean Hostilities</hi>
                </p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>References:</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 308–<hi rend="italic"
                                >c</hi>
                            <note n="1" xml:id="d356fn1">The text of the record of action, taken at
                                the 58th <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting on June 28,
                                read as follows: “Agreed that the Council should prepare for
                                consideration by the President recommendations as to the courses of
                                action to be followed in the event that Soviet forces enter Korean
                                hostilities.” (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files) See also
                                footnote 1 to the note from Acheson to Johnson, June 28, <ref
                                    target="#pg_217">p. 217</ref>.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76<note n="2" xml:id="d356fn2">See
                                footnote 2 to the memorandum, July 10, from the JCS to the Secretary
                                of Defense, <ref target="#pg_346">p. 346</ref>.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The enclosed comments on <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76, prepared by the
                    Department of State and the National Security Resources Board Consultants,<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d356fn3">The comments of the NSRB Consultant are not
                        printed.</note> respectively, are submitted herewith for consideration by
                    the National Security Council in connection with its consideration of <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76 as Item 2 on the Agenda of the Meeting
                    scheduled for Thursday, July 27, 1950.</p>
                <p>The National Security Council Consultants recommend that after discussion by the
                    Council, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76 together with the enclosures be
                    referred to the Consultants for preparation of a report on the subject in the
                    light of the discussion by the Council.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> S. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lay, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure]</head>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">State Department Consultant’s Comments With Respect
                            to</hi>
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76</p>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The State Department agrees completely that full-scale
                                mobilization should be initiated immediately it is determined that
                                major Soviet combat units have entered Korean hostilities or have
                                indicated their intention of engaging. The further decisions set
                                forth in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76 relate to the most
                                basic national policies and should not be taken except at the
                                highest level in the light of all relevant circumstances at the
                                time.</item>
                            <pb facs="0496" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The determination whether major Soviet combat units have entered
                                Korean hostilities or have clearly indicated their intention of
                                engaging in hostilities, and the decision to initiate the actions
                                contemplated by <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 76 should be
                                made only by the President. It is difficult at this time to foresee
                                clearly the various possible ways in which the engagement of Soviet
                                combat units might be indicated or occur. It would be of the utmost
                                importance that a course of action not be touched off by an
                                incorrect evaluation of the actual situation which had arisen.<note
                                    n="4" xml:id="d356fn4">
                                    <p>At its 62nd meeting on July 27, the <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                            >NSC</gloss> recorded the following decision taken as
                                        Action No. 324 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>):</p>
                                    <p>“Agreed with the recommendation by the Secretary of State
                                        that, in order to establish the fact of support to the North
                                        Koreans by the USSR or the Chinese Communists, aerial
                                        reconnaissance over all Korean territory, including Korean
                                        coastal waters, up to the Yalu River on the west and up to
                                        but short of the Korean-Soviet International boundary on the
                                        east should be authorized, subject to the understanding that
                                        such operations will be conducted from as far south of the
                                        frontiers of Manchuria or the Soviet Union as practicable,
                                        and that in no case will these frontiers be overflown.</p>
                                    <p>“<hi rend="italic">Note:</hi> The action in <hi rend="italic"
                                            >b</hi> above subsequently transmitted to the Secretary
                                        of Defense for appropriate action.” (<gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                            >NSC</gloss> files)</p>
                                    <p>Appropriate instructions were sent out by the JCS to General
                                        MacArthur in telegram JCS 88051, August 5, for text, see
                                            <ref target="frus1950v06#pg_424">vol. <hi
                                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, p. 424</ref>.</p>
                                </note>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The phrases “prepare to minimize its commitment in Korea” and
                                “prepare to execute war plans” appear to require clarification. The
                                State Department assumes that the phrase “prepare to minimize its
                                commitment” means that the evacuation of Korea would be prepared and
                                undertaken. The State Department is not clear as to what, in
                                addition to the initiation of full-scale mobilization, is
                                contemplated by the phrase “prepare to execute war plans”. In any
                                event, it is the opinion of the State Department that the actual
                                decision should be made by the President in the light of all the
                                circumstances at the time. It is the State Department’s opinion
                                that, prior to the actual execution of war plans, careful
                                consideration should be given to the following points, among others: <list>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>Appropriate action in the United Nations.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The effect on our relations with our principal allies. The
                                        Atlantic Pact does not by its terms cover hostilities
                                        breaking out in Korea.</item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The advisability of the immediate execution of war plans
                                        under the particular state of facts which had occurred. In
                                        this connection it would be important to determine: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Whether the nature of the commitment of Soviet
                                                forces had been such as to secure the clear support
                                                of world opinion for the execution of war plans by
                                                us.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>What would be the effect upon our allies, in
                                                particular our European allies, of an immediate
                                                generalization of hostilities.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>Whether the country was sufficiently mobilized to
                                                carry out its war plans with maximum effectiveness
                                                in the light not <pb facs="0497" n="477"
                                                  xml:id="pg_477"/> only of the immediate military
                                                situation but also of the total campaign to be
                                                waged, or whether additional time for mobilization
                                                would improve the prospects of ultimate
                                                victory.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </item>
                                    <label>
                                        <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                    <item>The type of action to be taken by the Congress before the
                                        initiation of war plans. A decision as to what action the
                                        Congress should take would have to be made by the
                                            President.<note n="5" xml:id="d356fn5">According to
                                            Action No. 323 taken at the 62nd meeting of the <gloss
                                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> on July 27, the <gloss
                                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> “noted and discussed
                                            the reference reports [<gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                                >NSC</gloss> 76 and 76/1] and referred them to the
                                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Consultants and
                                            Staff for the preparation of recommendations for Council
                                            action thereon”. (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                                            files) Subsequently, this action was cancelled in the
                                            light of action taken on <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                                >NSC</gloss> 73/4 of August 25, scheduled for
                                            publication in volume <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, and
                                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 81/1, September
                                            9, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_712">p.
                                                712</ref>.</note>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
