<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-08-03T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-08-03T17:00:00-05:00" n="394" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d394">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">611.91/8–350: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                                <gloss type="to">Embassy in India</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-08-03T18:00:00-04:00">August 3,
                                1950—6 p. m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>169. Text msg from <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> for delivery Nehru
                        thru Bajpai fols:</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“My dear Mr. PriMin: Thank you very much for ur gracious ltr, delivered
                            to me by ur Amb on July 30. I am grateful to you for discussing so fully
                            and frankly ur views on current developments in China, and I am
                            confident that as a result of our exchange of ideas we now have a better
                            understanding of each other’s views.</p>
                        <p>“I very much appreciate ur kindness in forwarding to ur Amb in Peiping
                            the Pres’s statement re Formosa. I am likewise grateful for ur efforts
                            to impress upon the auths in Peiping the desirability, in the interest
                            of world peace, of avoiding action that might extend the area of
                            hostilities.</p>
                        <p>“I was informed July 31 of India’s offer of a medical unit for the UN
                            effort in Korea. I shld like to express my personal gratification that
                            ur Govt found it possible to take this step which further evidences
                            India’s solidarity with those members of the UN” who oppose
                            aggression.</p>
                        <p>“With warm personal regards. Sincerely yours.”</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>You may wish to remark to Bajpai that the <gloss target="#t_Secy1">Secy</gloss> and other top officials of <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> were gratified by the frank and friendly tone of Nehru’s
                        note and found it very helpful in clarifying our understanding of India’s
                        position. Such expressions of opinion are bound to increase mutual
                        understanding between our two Govts.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>