<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Planning Adviser, Bureau of Far Eastern Affairs (
                    (Emmerson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d686</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">686</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-10-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-10-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="686"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d686">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/10–1650</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Planning Adviser, Bureau of Far Eastern
                        Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Emmerson</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-10-16">October 16,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Korean Security Problems</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The problem of Korean security divides itself into three parts, as follows: (1)
                    the maintenance of UN forces in Korea, pursuant to the <pb facs="0993" n="973"
                        xml:id="pg_973"/> General Assembly resolution of October 7, 1950; (2) the
                    establishment of Korean military forces; and (3) the permanent neutralization of
                    Korea.</p>
                <p>The General Assembly resolution provides that UN forces should not remain in any
                    part of Korea “otherwise than so far as necessary” for achieving the objectives
                    of (1) insuring conditions of stability throughout Korea and (2) of taking all
                    constituent acts, including the holding of elections, for the establishment of a
                    unified, independent and democratic government in the sovereign state of Korea.
                    It should therefore be the task of the UN Commission for Unification to
                    recommend the withdrawal of UN forces when it has determined, after consultation
                    with the Unified Command, that the objectives specified in the resolution have
                    been achieved to the extent that UN forces are no longer required. If, in the
                    meantime, a General Assembly resolution should be passed providing for the
                    maintenance of national armed forces elements for service as United Nations
                    units, the forces in Korea could be considered as such units and would provide
                    the precedent for their employment in other areas by the United Nations.</p>
                <p>With regard to the establishment and maintenance of military and internal
                    security forces for the Republic of Korea, the UN Commission for Unification,
                    pursuant to its authority to “represent the UN in bringing about the
                    establishment of a unified, independent and democratic government of all Korea”
                    should make recommendations to the Unified Commander for the establishment, in
                    agreement with the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>, of a UN Advisory
                    Military Group in Korea. This group would in fact represent a continuation of
                        <gloss target="#t_KMAG1">KMAG</gloss> but should be reconstituted to include
                    personnel from UN member states. To effect this, the UN Commission on
                    Unification should resolve that, in order to maintain its independence, Korea
                    should be encouraged to establish a defensive military force under UN auspices
                    and that, upon agreement between the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and the
                    Unified Command, a UN Advisory Military Group would be made available to advise
                    and assist the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> in maintaining a defense
                    force.</p>
                <p>The problem of neutralization would apparently require further action by the
                    General Assembly. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 81/1,<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d686fn1">Dated September 9, <ref target="#pg_712">p.
                        712</ref>.</note> paragraph 30, provides that “the U.S. should recommend
                    that the UN Commission should consider the desirability of permanent
                    neutralization of Korea accompanied by political undertakings by the <gloss
                        target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and by other states separately, including the
                    U.S.S.R., to refrain from any aggression. The question of a UN guarantee should
                    be studied but no U.S. commitment on this point should be made at this
                    stage”.</p>
                <pb facs="0994" n="974" xml:id="pg_974"/>
                <p>It may be that if a “uniting for peace” resolution, is passed by the General
                        Assembly,<note n="2" xml:id="d686fn2">The “Uniting for Peace” resolution was
                        approved by the U.N. General Assembly on November 3 as Resolution 377 (V);
                        for related documentation, see <ref target="frus1950v02#pg_303">vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 303</ref> ff.</note> and if the
                    Republic of Korea is admitted to the United Nations, the obligations thereby
                    assumed might be considered as making unnecessary special international
                    commitments with regard to Korea. It would be unlikely that either Communist
                    China or the U.S.S.R. would participate in political undertakings to guarantee
                    the neutrality of Korea and therefore an attempt to obtain such guarantee from
                    Korea’s neighbors would accomplish little more than a propaganda objective.</p>
                <p>Since Mr. Santa Cruz of Chile has raised the question of a UN guarantee it seems
                    that we might indicate our sympathy with a general discussion of this problem by
                    the Interim Committee. However we might take the position that this is a
                    question which will merit careful consideration and must be thought of in
                    connection with other action which may be taken by the UN, such as the “uniting
                    for peace” resolution, and the progress of the Commission’s work in bringing
                    about the unification of Korea.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
