<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Ray L. Thurston, Adviser to the United
                    States Delegation to the United Nations General Assembly</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d876</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">876</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-11-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-11-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-11-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="876"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d876">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">795.00/11–2450</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. <persName type="from">Ray
                            L. Thurston</persName>, Adviser to the United States Delegation to the
                            <gloss type="to">United Nations General Assembly</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-11-24">November 24,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">US/S/1585</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Indian Proposal for a Security Council Subcommittee to
                    Deal with the Chinese Communist Delegation.</p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#top">Participants:</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Dayal, Indian Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. D. L. Sharma, Indian Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Ray Thurston, United States
                                Delegation</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>I told the Indians today that after some discussion we were not favorably
                    disposed towards their idea that a subcommittee of the non-permanent members of
                    the Security Council be established to handle <pb facs="1240" n="1220"
                        xml:id="pg_1220"/> the various Far Eastern items which will shortly be
                    discussed in the Security Council with the participation of the Chinese
                    Communists. I alluded to the fact that one of the most important reasons that
                    have been adduced in support of the Indian suggestion was that it would
                    eliminate long propaganda speeches having a tendency to exacerbate the situation
                    and pointed out that even should the SC subcommittee partly meet this problem,
                    we were now going to have the Chinese Communists in Committee I of the General
                    Assembly, and it was almost certain that speeches of the kind in question would
                    be made.</p>
                <p>I asked the Indians whether they were going ahead with their scheme and whether
                    they intended formally to present it in the SC when it meets. They answered that
                    they did not intend to take such action and that their approach to us had been
                    merely of a sounding out nature. I gathered that their soundings have produced
                    negative replies generally and that they have lost their enthusiasm on this
                    particular project.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
