<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the United Nations ( (Austin) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v07</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d925</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">925</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-12-01T11:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-12-01T11:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-01T11:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-01T11:15:00-05:00" n="925"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d925">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">691.93/12–150: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-01T11:15:00-05:00"
                            >December 1, 1950—11:15 a. m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received December 1—11:47 a. m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>921. For Hickerson from Gross. At Bebler’s Security Council dinner last night Rau
                    took me aside to tell me that the initiative for his <pb facs="1309" n="1289"
                        xml:id="pg_1289"/> meeting this morning with Wu “this time came from them”.
                    Rau said Wu sent him a message at the Security Council table yesterday afternoon
                    suggesting they meet at 10:30 Friday a. m. Because of Rau’s tendency to leap out
                    of the water at flies, I undertook to sound some warnings. I expressed view that
                    on basis Wu’s performance in Security Council it was clear he had a long way to
                    go before showing up at Tito’s headquarters. Rau nodded agreement.</p>
                <p>Following this up, I asked Rau if he would forgive a tactless question and when
                    he replied that I should feel free to ask him anything, I said suddenly “what is
                    your appraisal of Panikkar?” Rau was startled by the question, and after a
                    slight pause, he grinned and said “you have something of an answer in my delay
                    in formulating a reply”. Rau then proceeded with the frank comment that Panikkar
                    was a fine person and great scholar, but that “the people in Delhi know how to
                    evaluate him and give the proper discount”. I then explained that I had asked
                    the question because several months ago Rau had told me of Panikkar’s conviction
                    that Communist China was pursuing its own course, that it was not a Soviet
                    satellite, and that it was more Chinese than Communist. I said we had always
                    been skeptical of this appraisal, and that Wu’s performance appeared to me to
                    show up Panikkar’s analysis.</p>
                <p>I thought it was difficult to say how much of Wu’s manner was due to political
                    immaturity and how much to planned terror tactics. In any event, it seemed to me
                    important to avoid entrapment in a situation which would affect momentum in UN
                    and especially important to prevent the fact of his meeting with Wu creating
                    false hopes among UN members.</p>
                <p>I reminded Rau that Soviets had often tried to obstruct and divert free world
                    efforts to concert their policies by propaganda trick of pretending to want
                    “discussions”. I expressed hope Rau would be wary of efforts on part of Wu to
                    build up a climate of so-called discussions and that in any statement Rau might
                    make after the meeting he would avoid falling into this familiar trap. Rau
                    listened intently and throughout nodded his agreement. Referring to earlier
                    discussions relating to our willingness to talk with Wu, I said Rau would
                    forgive me if I again stressed that while we were not eager to talk with Wu, and
                    indeed had nothing to offer him or to suggest to him, that if Wu had anything on
                    his mind we were prepared to listen. Rau professed understanding.</p>
                <p>He said he would like to see me this afternoon, to tell me of his talk with Wu
                    and also to discuss our notions of what happens next.</p>
                <p>Rau referred to news of Attlee’s visit to Washington. He said it had occurred to
                    him after hearing this news that it might be a good idea for Nehru to come for a
                    talk with the President, if Nehru could arrange to do so. Rau stressed this was
                    his own idea, just born, and <pb facs="1310" n="1290" xml:id="pg_1290"/> he did
                    not know if it was practical. He thought I might pass it on the Department as
                    Rau’s personal and tentative idea.</p>
                <p>Reverting to conversation earlier in day in which I had urged him not to launch
                    in Security Council his plan to suggest including in resolution an offer to
                    withdraw 7th fleet from Formosa Straits in return for Chinese withdrawal from
                    Korea, I thanked him for acceding to my request. I explained in some detail the
                    political and military dangers implicit in such a proposal, net effect of which
                    might be to put UN and us under a commitment which we would honor but Communists
                    would disregard at will and which moreover might well result in merely shifting
                    the offensive to Formosa with Chinese troops released from their Korean
                    adventure. Rau did not press his idea and acceded to my request that he talk
                    with me before doing anything more with the plan. [Gross.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
