<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-04-18T23:52:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-04-18T21:05:00-05:00" n="123" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                    <head>123. Memorandum of Conversation, Beijing, April 19, 1972, 10:05 a.m.-12:52
                            p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d123fn1">Source: National
                            Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                            Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 1038, Files
                            for the President-China Material, <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>
                            Trip to China [April-May 1972]. The precise location of the meeting is
                            not indicated on the memorandum. <persName corresp="#p_LW2">Lord</persName> transferred the memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> under a May 12 covering
                            memorandum that was sent for information. No classification marking
                            appears on the memorandum of conversation. The covering memorandum is
                            classified Secret; Sensitive. Attached but not published at Tabs A and B
                            are <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>’s reports. Attached at Tab C of
                            the covering memorandum are the memoranda of their conversations with
                                <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou En-lai</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Ch’iao Kuan-hua</persName>. The text of the first
                            conversation is published herein and is presumably drafted by Norvil
                            Jones, a staff member of the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations.
                            Texts of the subsequent conversations are published as <ref target="#d124">Documents 124</ref>–<ref target="#d26">26</ref>. Tabs
                            D and E are attached but not published.</note>
                        <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d123fn2">
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff member <persName corresp="#p_LW2">Lord</persName> provided President’s Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> with a brief summary of Senators <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>’s trip to China.</note>
                    </head>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Beijing</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1972-04-19T10:05:00+08:00" to="1972-04-19T12:52:00+08:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">April 19, 1972, 10:05 a.m.–12:52
                            p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p>INFORMATION</p>
                    <p>May 12, 1972</p>
                    <list type="to">
                        <head>MEMORANDUM FOR:</head>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">HENRY A. KISSINGER</persName>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <list>
                        <head>FROM:</head>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_LW2">WINSTON LORD</persName>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName> Reports on Their China
                            Trip</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Attached are the materials that Senators <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>
                        left personally with the President when they saw him earlier this week
                        concerning their China trip: <list>
                            <item>— Tab A - Senator <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName>’s Report</item>
                            <item>— Tab B - Senator <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>’s
                                Report</item>
                            <item>— Tab C - Memoranda of Conversations with <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou En-lai</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_QG1">CHIAO KUAN-HUA</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>— Tab D - the Senators’ public statement in Hong Kong about their
                                trip</item>
                            <item>— Tab E - a short piece by Senator <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>, apparently given to Roscoe Drummond</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>There is nothing in these materials that is particularly sensitive or
                        startling. <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">John Holdridge</persName> is staffing
                        this package for the President, but you may wish to leaf through it in
                        advance.</p>
                    <p>A few quick impressions from a fast reading: <list>
                            <item>— Senator <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName>’s
                                report, which is a genuine effort to be thoughtful, basically
                                confirms the Senator’s prior perspective of China, as well as his
                                great concern over our Indochina policy and its possible impact on
                                    U.S./<gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> relations.</item>
                            <item>— Senator <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>’s report is
                                very thin gruel. One interesting fact is Chou receptivity to the
                                Senator’s inquiry on Senator <pb facs="d123-02" n="2" xml:id="d123-02"/> Magnuson and some members of the Commerce
                                Committee visiting China to discuss trade and commerce. Also
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou</persName>’s generally
                                positive attitude on exchanges in general.</item>
                            <item>— The reception for the Senators and their party was very cordial
                                and very efficient. This was reconfirmed to me by a debriefing of
                                the trip that I got from Ken Calloway, our contact in State who was
                                personally tremendously impressed by <persName corresp="#p_MZMT1">Mao</persName>’s China.</item>
                            <item>— The conversations with <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao</persName>
                                did not reach great philosophic heights. The bulk of the time was
                                spent on Indochina, with the Chinese repeating familiar positions
                                and the Senators displaying their own divergent views.</item>
                            <item>— <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou</persName> specifically ruled
                                out discussions on Taiwan, on the grounds of his confidential
                                exchanges with the President.</item>
                            <item>— I don’t see anything in the attached that bears out <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName>’s emphasis in the Senate
                                yesterday that no further progress in U.S./<gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> relations is possible until Indochina is settled.
                                The current situation since the President’s speech may be a new
                                factor, but in the context of the Senator’s discussions in China in
                                April, the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> line seems to be
                                similar to the one we have always heard, i.e. that Indochina is the
                                “most urgent” issue for reducing tensions in the Far East.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="d123-03" n="3" xml:id="d123-03"/>
                    <p>FIRST MEETING</p>
                    <p>Peking, China - April 19, 1972</p>
                    <p>CHINESE DELEGATION</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao Kuan-Hua</persName>, Vice-President of
                        the Chinese People’s Institute of Foreign Affairs, Vice-Minister of the
                        Chinese Foreign Ministry</p>
                    <p>Prof. Chau Pei-yuan, Vice-President of the Chinese People’s Institute of
                        Foreign Affairs, Vice-Chairman of the Revolutionary Committee of Peking
                        University</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CW2">Chang Wen-chin</persName>, Director of
                        Department of American and Western European and Australasian Affairs of the
                        Foreign Ministry</p>
                    <p>Mr. Chau Ch’iu-yeh, Secretary-General of the Chinese People’s Institute of
                        Foreign Affairs</p>
                    <p>Mr. Hu Hung-fan, Council Member of the Chinese People’s Institute of Foreign
                        Affairs</p>
                    <p>Miss Tang Wen-sheng, Interpreter</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Tzu Chung-yun, Interpreter</p>
                    <p>Mr. Chao Chi-hua, Interpreter</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lian Cheng-pao, Stenographer</p>
                    <p>AMERICAN DELEGATION</p>
                    <p>Sen. <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mike Mansfield</persName> (D., Mont.),
                        Majority Leader, U.S. Senate</p>
                    <p>Sen. <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Hugh Scott</persName> (R., Penn.),
                        Republican Leader, U.S. Senate</p>
                    <p>Mr. Frank Valeo, Secretary of U.S. Senate</p>
                    <p>Mr. Bill Hildenbrand, Admin. Asst. Republican Leader, U.S. Senate</p>
                    <p>Mr. Norvil Jones, Staff Member - Senate Committee on Foreign Relations</p>
                    <p>Meeting lasted 2 hrs. 47 mins. (10:05 a.m.-12:52 p.m.)</p>
                    <pb facs="d123-04" n="4" xml:id="d123-04"/>
                    <p>April 19, 1972</p>
                    <p>The Vice-Minister opened by saying that contacts between the two peoples has
                        increased since President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s
                        visit. American businessmen (30) will be attending Canton Trade Fair and the
                        pandas have arrived in Washington and President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> has received the Chinese ping pong team and
                        understands that they were well received in U.S. cities. The Vice-Minister
                        is very glad to see these visits occurring and feels a frank exchange of
                        views despite differences in two systems is most beneficial. Both leaders
                            (<persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName>) desire to exchange views on Asia
                        and the world as well as visit various Chinese cities. The Vice-Minister
                        welcomes the opportunity to have a frank discussion of views. 20 years of
                        non-communication has brought many changes in the world that need
                        discussion.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> - We have been apart too
                        long - China cannot be ignored - China has many problems and the sooner we
                        arrive at communication between the two countries the better both countries
                        will be. Hope the Chinese understand the system of Democratic majority in
                        Congress and a Republican Administration. Will do our best to answer any
                        question and will try and be frank.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName> - Following President’s visit
                        there was almost a miracle. There has existed for 22 years a feeling among
                        the American people for better relations with China, though politicians of
                        both parties were not fully aware of the peoples’ desire - the high regard
                        for both peoples was there all the time. Both parties endorse President’s
                        visit and visit of the two leaders we would like to say that we laid the
                        groundwork for other visits and exchanges, i.e., House Members, governors,
                        mayors, cultural and athletic. Meetings such as this must not be squandered
                        with small talk but must be meaningful and frank discussions.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao Kuan-Hua</persName> - Believe differences
                        exist but believe differences need not obstruct our coming together. We
                        understand the system <pb facs="d123-05" n="5" xml:id="d123-05"/> of two
                        parties, this is natural, we respect your differences between parties—how
                        you resolve them is an internal matter. <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName>
                        can give views of their two parties. In our party we cannot say we agree on
                        specific issues but we are all in agreement on direction.
                            <persName>Frank</persName> exchange of views is not to cover up but to
                        discuss differences openly - debate of differences will be helpful - natural
                        to have differences. I understand President has just indicated a desire to
                        come to China in the spring - you are lucky because you are seeing China in
                        the spring before your President.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> - Spring is the time for
                        new life, new awakening and better understanding.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName> - Would you comment on
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine long range aspects
                        despite present unfortunate South Viet-Nam situation?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao Kuan-Hua</persName> - As for <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine, have read it and have had
                        it explained. At present, under existing circumstances, not in accord with
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine. Of course, when I
                        say this I am not necessarily in opposition to all President does - agree to
                        his visit - it was good.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> - As a Democrat I agree
                        with the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine call for
                        withdrawal of U.S. troops or sizeable reduction from many parts of the world
                        where they now exist. Due in part to vacuum created after great war, U.S.
                        overextended, too far, too wide, too thinly. Bring about gradual withdrawal,
                        facing up to recognition that U.S. has limited number of people and limited
                        resources. Purpose is to make possible more people in all parts of the world
                        to be dependent on themselves and less on others. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine to take in all the world.
                        (Mentioned <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.) It means in Asia that the
                        U.S. is basically a Pacific power and not an Asian power - our interest is
                        off the mainland of Asia, not in Asia. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine cannot be put in action overnight you must
                        recognize we are facing up to political realities and economic realities ot
                        today. Keep in mind we have much to learn compared to China - we are still
                        in swaddling clothes - you have had much time, you have made great
                        contributions. We will develop policies in accord with today, not yesterday.
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        <pb facs="d123-06" n="6" xml:id="d123-06"/> Doctrine has tremendous
                        possibilities not only to the U.S. but to the rest of the world if the rest
                        of the world will join in that understanding. We recognize the problems but
                        do not have all the solutions - need all countries to join in to find those
                        solutions.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao Kuan-Hua</persName> - Believe many points
                        in Mansfield statement we agree with.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName> - <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine as I view it is directed toward Asia. I agree
                        with <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> that what is
                        contemplated but not active is an extension. <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> and I disagree with numbers of withdrawal in
                        Europe. Desire never again to be involved in Asia. Our wish to avoid through
                        American power or presence so that Asian countries will not call upon us to
                        get involved. American public will more quickly approve gradual withdrawal.
                        We speak of trends of withdrawal—your view is our commitment should be
                        complete. Is that a fair statement?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao Kuan-Hua</persName> - Believe exchange
                        should be frank - we would like to be frank. I would like to enlarge my
                        comments on the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine. It is
                        nearly 27 years since end of World War II and as for our view since 2nd
                        World War U.S. has been reaching its hands out too far. And in those 27
                        years both Administrations in America have put forth various doctrines to
                        cope with these situations. Preceding from personal experience - shortly
                        after World War II I met Dulles and at that time it was the Truman Doctrine
                        during Korean War and then Eisenhower put forth his doctrine and then in the
                        60’s the <persName>Kennedy</persName> Administration also had a strategy to
                        go any place to meet any challenge. After that <persName>Johnson</persName>
                        and during that Administration there was an expansion of war in Viet-Nam.
                        This question is of great concern to China. Then came <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Administration. I would also like to
                        say frankly our attitude has been consistent in listening to their words but
                        watching their deeds. Would not want to dwell on past matters—although no
                        opportunity to have friendly exchanges—many times we met as enemies. For
                        instance, Korea - 1st Geneva Conference - 2nd Geneva Conference—during “54”
                        Geneva Conference American representative refused to shake hands with
                        Premier. While this belongs in the past, it is in our memory. From what the
                        two Senators just said you have common feeling that world has changed <pb facs="d123-07" n="7" xml:id="d123-07"/> and old policies cannot meet
                        these changes. Should be said that we have noted and attached great
                        importance that <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> has courage to
                        face the fact that old policies cannot meet today’s problems. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> also expressed desire to improve
                        relations with China. This admittance of a changed world reflects desire to
                        have better relations with China and have found common points in this sense.
                        As for <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine, Scott asked
                        whether we wished speedy and complete withdrawal from this area - of course,
                        that is true - one point of difference between two Senators - once military
                        presence is withdrawn from area that area becomes a vacuum—not so. For
                        instance China - I have discussed with Harriman before in Geneva - he took
                        part in Yalta Conference—what we are having now is not diplomatic but
                        friendly—China partly in sphere of influence of U.S. and partly in sphere of
                        influence of U.S.S.R. but more closely to U.S. But later on could also be
                        said the U.S. had to loosen hold on China and what was the result - we both
                        can see China did not become a vacuum. There are two super-powers—U.S. and
                        Russia—China belongs to neither. That is one example and therefore we do not
                        agree to the idea that once American presence is withdrawn that area becomes
                        a vacuum - that when one super-power leaves the other one must enter. Our
                        philosophies different, therefore there is no need to debate at great
                        length. We also take analysis when we discuss <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine. Another question not ready to debate at
                        great length, American involvement in Viet-Nam. Should be ended and we see
                        unfortunately that this has not happened - am not prepared to debate at
                        length - to ease tensions in Far East basic issue is Viet-Nam and the rest
                        of Indo-China. Also in Shanghai Communique crucial question is Taiwan that
                        obstructs normal relationship but Viet-Nam is still overriding and without
                        settlement there can be no normalization of relationship. We believe there
                        has been change since <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> took
                        office - big change. It is not to say that we agree that the present way the
                        U.S. is handling Viet-Nam government is the way to bring results - I am not
                        prepared to deal at great length because of differences between two
                        Senators. As for aspect of <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Doctrine fixing first objective and then gradual approach to that objective
                        - we cannot say there is not merit to that approach. Question <pb facs="d123-08" n="8" xml:id="d123-08"/> of Taiwan not settled - only
                        found some common points of view on this issue - and if on basis of these
                        common points able to reach solution we Chinese are patient and able to wait
                        a while. General view of <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        Doctrine is analytical, not one monolithic piece.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> - Don’t intend to engage in
                        debate or make public statement here - will confine to my own country. _You
                        mentioned many doctrines - Truman Doctrine separate from Eisenhower
                        Doctrine—any blame both parties responsible. During Truman became involved
                        in Viet-Nam before “54” Accord. Continued under Eisenhower - maintained
                        military advisor group in Viet-Nam. Continued under
                            <persName>Kennedy</persName> and 16,000 troops at time of assassination
                        - still advisors. <persName>Kennedy</persName> statement, “Be prepared to
                        meet any challenge at any time at any place” was spoken in defense of U.S.
                        and not foreign adventures. Under <persName>Johnson</persName> increased to
                        548,000 in Viet-Nam. Under <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                        reduced to 85,000 today. As we all know build-up in air and sea power
                        because of increased activity. Deed of reduction fits into desires of
                        President.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName> - Further reduction by end of
                        this month to 69,000.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> - Disagree with statement
                        that we met as enemies numerous times - I say only a few times - Korea and
                        Geneva Conference - not even active participant when Dulles refused to shake
                        hands.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName> - In 1956 at Yugoslavia
                        reception in New Delhi did not agree with American policy but was not
                        permitted to get close enough to Premier <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou</persName> to shake his hand.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> - Also mentioned Guam
                        declaration - <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> has courage to
                        change - goes to disprove the French saying, “The more things change, the
                        more they remain the same.” Most respectfully disagree that we should
                        withdraw completely from this area - no actual interest in Asian mainland -
                        must maintain peace in Pacific - not alone but hopefully with China and
                        Japan - all have common responsibility. I dislike the word “super-power” -
                        any sovereign nation is a power - completely surprised by your reference to
                        Harriman and dividing China as <pb facs="d123-09" n="9" xml:id="d123-09"/>
                        spheres of influence between U.S. and Russia - never heard of it.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao Kuan-Hua</persName> - One misunderstanding:
                        that was my opinion, not that Harriman said this.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> - Unthinkable position. I
                        was in Chungking in 1945-46 - Russia helping Kuomindong, not <persName corresp="#p_MZMT1">Mao</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou</persName>. Is this correct?</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao Kuan-Hua</persName> - I say again - spirit
                        of discussion - major issues - was reviewing history - if I didn’t express
                        my view would not be frank - don’t think advisable to have misunderstanding
                        in a friendly discussion - this is friendly. We on our side should proceed
                        frankly and sometimes bluntly and give our views and you yours even bluntly
                        - no help to mutual understanding otherwise.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName> - This is a new experience for
                        me since Sen. <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> is regarded
                        as laconic - I revert to statement regarding present American view toward
                        North Viet-Nam is not way to bring results it is our clear intent to
                        withdraw subject to <gloss target="#t_POW1">POW</gloss> issue particularly.
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> desires to be known as a
                        peacemaker - time is right towards step to peace in Korea time has come -
                        good offices of <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> and U.S. bringing about
                        withdrawal of forces around the world as well as Korea.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_QG1">Chiao Kuan-Hua</persName> - Maybe we can discuss
                        that next time - mention one point - appreciate <persName corresp="#p_MMJ1">Mansfield</persName> statement that these talks are off record and not
                        for public consumption. So it is important no misunderstanding - also like
                        to mention I did not want to review past 22 years only went into historical
                        significance in answer to question - relations between two countries has not
                        been good and we should look forward. Like to thank both Senators very much
                        for views although we differ, appreciate opportunity to exchange views. This
                        is our first meeting and we do not know each other very well. Just as
                            <persName corresp="#p_SHD2">Scott</persName> said, not engage in small
                        talk but discuss major issues - that is spirit of discussions - have great
                        respect for both Senators and will not try and impose our views on you or
                        your views on us. Am surprised by some of your views but glad to have them.
                        Will meet again tomorrow same time.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>