<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>34. Memorandum for the Record, Paris, October 15, 1971, 11 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-10-15T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-10-15T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-10-15T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-10-15T05:00:00-05:00" n="34"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                <head>34. Memorandum for the Record, Paris, October 15, 1971, 11 a.m.<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d34fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 849, President’s File-China
                        Trip, China Exchanges, July 1971-Oct 20, 1971. No classification marking.
                        Ellipses in the source text. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WLGVA1"
                            >Walters</persName> on October 15.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d34fn2">After Military Attaché <persName
                            corresp="#p_WLGVA1">Walters</persName> relayed information about
                        President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s communications operations for
                        his upcoming trip to China, interpreters Tsao and <persName>Wei</persName>
                        asked about the role of the military and the racial question in U.S.
                        politics.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1971-10-15T11:00:00+01:00">October 15, 1971, 11 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>MEMORANDUM OF CONVERSATION:</p>
                <p>MEETING WITH CHINESE ON OCTOBER 15th 1971</p>
                <p>Late at night on October 14th I had a call from Tsao saying that they would like
                    to see me the next morning. I agreed and they set 1100 as the appropriate time.
                    At that time I went there and was received as always by them in the usual
                    sequence and with the usual rites. Amb. Huang was not present.</p>
                <p>They then read me a message indicating that they wished to know data concerning
                    the transmitter we would use while Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>’s aircraft was on the ground in Peking. They read me
                    the following message.</p>
                <p>The Chinese side agrees to the use of a communicator/engineer for purposes of
                    direct communication with Washington during Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>’s visit to Peking. The transmitter will be used every
                    two hours on even days. The Chinese side would like to know the power, call
                    sign, frequencies and method of operation and type of radio transmission.</p>
                <p>I said that I would pass this on to Washington and would try an get the answers
                    before 18 October as they had requested.</p>
                <p>We then passed on to Chit chat. They asked me about the role of U.S. Military in
                    politics. I pointed out that we had none, had to resign to run for office, could
                    not make political statements or attend any political meeting in Uniform. We
                    could vote but a law prohibited any military person from being Secretary of
                    Defense or of the Army Navy and Airforce. They looked at me in bewilderment and
                    asked me to repeat this to make sure that they had heard right. I repeated. They
                    then said what about General Eisenhower. I assured them that he had resigned
                    from his five stars before he ran for President and they wanted to know why. I
                    said that this was the way the U.S. operated.</p>
                <p>We then spoke about the racial question in the United States. I pointed out that
                    we had a Japanese, a Chinese, a Black and a Spanish Speaking Senator. That the
                    Chief of Personnel of the U.S. Army in Europe was a black Major General, that
                    the Ambassador to Sweden was black, so was the Under Secretary of
                    Transportation. That Senator Brooke was elected in a state that had only 5% of
                    blacks among its population. All of this was done somewhat less abruptly than
                    recorded here, adding that there were still injustices but we were aware of them
                    and trying to correct them. They appeared surprised at the foregoing and some
                    statistics concerning the income of black families in the U.S. I then mentioned
                    that the Chinese ethnic community was perhaps the most law abiding in the United
                    States. <persName>Wei</persName> laughed and said that they had plenty of crime
                    in China (!!!) I felt it better not to ask whether it was political… They then
                    asked about intermarriage with Vietnamese. I said that there had been some but
                    perhaps less than in Japan.</p>
                <p>Both said that a great effort to learn English was afoot in China, they realized
                    that they needed this to communicate with the world. Tsao added that Chairman
                        <persName corresp="#p_MZMT1">Mao</persName> was personally studying English.
                    He could not really speak if but could understood it to some degree. Tsao added
                    that Edgar Snow had met Ambassador <persName>Huang</persName> in Yenan.</p>
                <p>Tsao and <persName>Wei</persName> chuckled over the fact that nearly everyone
                    thought that the contacts between the U.S. and China were being handled in
                    Ottawa. <pb facs="d34-02" n="2" xml:id="d34-02"/>
                    <persName>Wei</persName> said that he had read in the paper that many
                    journalists were watching the Chinese and American Embassies there to see if
                    they could detect how the connection was made. They said that it was well to be
                    discreet in the delicate stage of Chinese American relations. They knew that the
                    opening of the dialogue with China kad not been easy for Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> because of internal opposition in the
                    United States. I said that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> was
                    a courageous man who would not be deterred from doing what he thought was right
                    by opposition. They nodded agreement.</p>
                <p>I said that returning to the question of the role of the U.S. Military in U.S.
                    Politics. I must tell them a story of a conversation I had had with one of my
                    Russian colleagues. He had told me that I did not really live in a democracy and
                    when I asked him why he had replied “You are an officer in the Army but you
                    cannot hold political office, whereas I am an officer in the Soviet Navy but I
                    can be a member of the Supreme Soviet”. To which I had replied “But I still have
                    an advantage over you, I can join the opposition and you cannot.” Both Tsao and
                        <persName>Wei</persName> threw back their heads and roared with
                    laughter.</p>
                <p>Both shovelled out soft soap to me. How frank I was, how much they enjoyed
                    talking to me etc. By this time the jasmine tea was almost coming out of my
                    ears, and one more preserved apple and I would start growing blossoms. Great
                    cordiality and many apologies for the absence of the Ambassador.</p>
                <p>They then asked me what I had thoght about China before I had met them. I said
                    that I had met few (relatively) Chinese before them but that those I had met had
                    lived up to their reputation as a cultured, industrious, hard working people,
                    who had given the world some of its greatest discoveries. I added “You gave us
                    some good things like the compass and printing and some bad things like
                    gunpowder and rockets.” They laughed and obviously enjoyed the exchange. They
                    expressed the hope that I would visit China. I said it was important that as
                    people we get to know one another. One always dislikes what is unknown. They
                    agreed rather solemnly.</p>
                <p>With further expressions of mutual goodwill and esteem I made my way out in
                    accordance with the usual ceremonial.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
