<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>43. Memorandum of Conversation, Beijing, October 22, 1971, 4:10-5:37
                    p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve13</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">43</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-10-22T03:10:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-10-22T04:37:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="receuSgBSWw1dxuqH" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Cultural affairs</term>
                    <term ref="east-asia-and-pacific" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="east-asia-and-pacific">East Asia and Pacific</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-10-22T04:37:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-10-22T03:10:00-05:00" n="43"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d43">
                <head>43. Memorandum of Conversation, Beijing, October 22, 1971, 4:10-5:37 p.m.<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d43fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 1035, Files for the
                        President-China Material, <gloss target="#t_HAK1">HAK</gloss> visit to
                            <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>, October 1971, Memcons-originals.
                        Top Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. No drafting information
                        appears on the memorandum. An unknown hand crossed out a portion of the date
                        on the memorandum, changing the year from 1972 to 1971. The meeting was held
                        in the Great Hall of the People.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d43fn2">Topics discussed among Prime
                        Minister’s Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung Hsiang-hu</persName>
                        and U.S. officials <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> and
                            <persName>Jenkins</persName> included the establishment of liason
                        offices, President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s proposed
                        visit, possible scientific, technical, and cultural exchanges, and the issue
                        of American organizations inviting Taiwanese athletes to tour the United
                        States.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Beijing</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        from="1971-10-22T16:10:00+08:00" to="1971-10-22T17:37:00+08:00"
                        type="conversation-or-meeting-date">October 22, 1971, 4:10–5:37 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <pb facs="d43-01" n="1" xml:id="d43-01"/>
                <p>MEMORANDUM OF CONVERSATION</p>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">John Holdridge</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_JAS1">Alfred LeS. Jenkins</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung Hsiang-hui</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>TIME AND PLACE</p>
                <p>Friday, October 22, 1971; 4:10 - 5:37 p.m.</p>
                <p>Great Hall of the People</p>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>Exchanges and Trade</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Yesterday morning we had a meeting
                    which has been carried out in accordance with procedures agreed upon by Premier
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou En-lai</persName> and Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>. And to speak frankly, I didn’t
                    expect what kind of questions the United States side put forward before the
                    meeting. But you have made very good preparations.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: All very tentative.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: And only during the course of our
                    exchanges of views have I come to realize the nature and contents of the
                    questions you have put forward. That is why yesterday morning I mainly listened
                    to what you have got to say. And in the course of our talk I made a very brief
                    clarification. That is to say both Mr. <persName>Jenkins</persName> and Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> must be very familiar with
                    the whole process of the Sino-United States talks so far as the consistent stand
                    of China. And there is much content in this sentence. I think both of you will
                    understand it. And after the meeting I joined another meeting in the afternoon
                    and in the evening we also attended the performances and in the morning we went
                    on an excursion to the Great Wall. So to speak frankly I haven’t read over the
                    list you handed over to us. Because we haven’t got enough time.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: We fully understand. You have been so gracious in
                    affording us so pleasant and profitable a time, we fully understand.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: So we are not in the same
                    circumstances. So I would like to say a few words about my preliminary ideas. Of
                    course, we will report our respective preliminary ideas to our respective
                    leaders.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-02" n="2" xml:id="d43-02"/>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Certainly.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: And of course eventually it will
                    be solved by Premier <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou En-lai</persName> and Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: this is just for exchange
                    of views.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I think that would be very useful.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: It’s not a decision, just an
                    exchange of ideas.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I understand.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Yesterday, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> had raised some points on the
                    contacts between China and the United States. I haven’t got a note here; this is
                    a translation of your proposals.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: It looks far more concrete in
                    the form that you have it there than in the way that I presented it.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: That’s the Chinese characters. The
                    way they print it gives you the impression.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: You must assume that the way
                    we talked about it yesterday was very informal.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Just an exchange of views.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: So what I am going to touch on is
                    first of all the questions of the contacts between China and the United States
                    as was mentioned yesterday by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HJH1"
                        >Holdridge</persName>. And yesterday Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HJH1"
                        >Holdridge</persName> also mentioned that there had already been established
                    effective contacts between Premier <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou
                        En-lai</persName> and President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                    so I am not going to talk at length on this point. Of course, it goes without
                    saying such contacts will go on. And in addition to that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> had made three suggestions for the
                    consideration of the Chinese side. Because I haven’t brought the note with me,
                    if I don’t speak very accurately please correct me. The first point is to
                    establish, on the basis of reciprocity, a liaison office by both sides.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: May I make one statement here?
                    We said reciprocity if the Chinese government is interested in reciprocity.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-03" n="3" xml:id="d43-03"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Of course I mentioned just now
                    your suggestions are for the consideration of the Chinese side. So it’s all
                    right if I didn’t mention that point. We think this is not realistic. It is
                    quite obvious there is a so-called embassy of the <persName corresp="#p_JJ3"
                        >Chiang Kai-shek</persName> clique in Washington. And as regards this, we
                    haven’t ___________ to the United States. If any situation of two Chinas occurs
                    then it is utterly unacceptable to us. That is if there is a so-called
                    Kuomintang Embassy in Washington and at the same time there is a so-called kind
                    of liaison organization whether official or non-official of the Peoples Republic
                    of China in Washington. And it goes without saying it is not appropriate. And we
                    are not willing to put the United States side in an embarrassing state and wish
                    the United States side will also not put us in an embarrassing state. That is
                    why I say that as for the first point, it is not feasible.</p>
                <p>As for the second suggestion, it is to establish a section in a friendly embassy
                    on both sides. And on this there is some sort of similarity between this point
                    and the last suggestion. We are used to doing things in a frank and open
                    way.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: That we welcome.</p>
                <p>Hsiang: I don’t mean to make any criticism of U.S. representation at missions in
                    the Middle East, but that’s not our practice. That’s why the second suggestion
                    is also not feasible. As for the sort of suggestion about the sending of sort of
                    technical personnel to deal with administrative questions before or during or
                    after the visits of senior representatives of President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> or Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> either from Hong Kong or from Washington. As for this
                    point, we think it can be considered. ________________ in July Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> came here to China and this time he
                    has come again and with even a larger party. And the period for your stay is for
                    you to decide. Of course, it is impossible for you to stay for a longer time.
                    Because Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> has told me that he
                    is going to leave on the 25th. So shall we put this question on a more realistic
                    basis. So from the 25th of this month when Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> and his colleagues are leaving China to the date of
                    President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s visit to China there is
                    still quite a few months, about four or five months. Plus, the final date is not
                    yet known, for during this period of time the United States side thinks it is
                    necessary to send some people here to China we think it can be taken into
                    consideration. If there is some other preparatory work to be done in that case,
                    this can be realized through the channels mentioned by Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName> yesterday. As to who will come or how
                    many of them will come, and how long they are going to stay, it can be consulted
                    and agreed upon through the channels which already exist. But we think it is
                    better and more effective to send a representative right from Washington. As for
                    the function of the personnel and Hong Kong, I am sure that both you and they in
                    Hong Kong are very clear about the function of them. It’s a very big consulate.
                    If they came here, it will affect their <pb facs="d43-04" n="4" xml:id="d43-04"
                    /> function in Hong Kong. So we think in that case it will be more effective to
                    send representatives right from Washington although they only deal with
                    administrative work, but it is more effective to send them right from
                    Washington, the personnel, not the senior representatives, but the personnel. It
                    is more realistic to have them during the period after Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s interim visit and before President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s visit to China. As for the
                    contacts after President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s visit to
                    China, we can leave it to them to decide. What would you think of such an
                    idea?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: Certainly this is something we
                    want to consider and discuss with Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>, and we appreciate the receptivity of the Peoples
                    Republic of China.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: What is your opinion?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: I think that certainly my
                    contacts … I think this will be beneficial and be helpful to others who come of
                    higher rank, to have this assistance on the groundwork so to speak. This of
                    course is my personal opinion.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: What I was referring to is the
                    period after Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s interim
                    visit to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s visit to
                    China.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: I don’t believe Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> has yet formed any particular idea on
                    what type of contact or further conversations we should have in that period. At
                    this point I am not in a position to comment any further. At this point it will
                    depend on what Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou En-lai</persName> should discuss.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Because this is the third
                    suggestion you made yesterday, so that’s what I have considered because I have
                    put it on a more realistic basis.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: I do recall offering to
                    receive any suggestions from the People’s Republic of China and wonder if your
                    side has any suggestions to make going beyond what I said yesterday.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: I think as for this point it is in
                    conformity with the point put forward by Premier <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1"
                        >Chou En-lai</persName> last July.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: Fine, I have nothing further
                    to say then.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Now, the second question. That is
                    the question put forward by Mr. <persName>Jenkins</persName>. That is the
                    proposal on the exchanges of scientific, technical and cultural and so forth. I
                    think altogether there are 25 proposals.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-05" n="5" xml:id="d43-05"/>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: May I say these were very illustrative, and we
                    didn’t have any idea we’d want to consider them as a package, but simply to
                    start our thinking going.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Last time you mentioned three
                    proposals orally; as for the written list, it consists of 25. Of course last
                    time you did mention the three suggestions were just illustrative. My idea is
                    like this: The Chinese and the American peoples have long been friendly to each
                    other, and owing to reasons not because of the Chinese side, for the last 2-1/2
                    years, and more, the exchanges between the two countries have been cut off. A
                    new page has been opened after the visits of the American table tennis team to
                    China in last April. Of course, before that there were a few American friends
                    who have come to China, say Mr. ___________. And after the visit of the table
                    tennis team from the United States there has been an increasing number of the
                    American friends who have come to China for visits and many of them include
                    correspondents. Of course, there were also correspondents who came with the
                    table tennis players and after their visit there have been a number of
                    correspondents who have come and also tourists and scientists and so on. That’s
                    why in his toast at the banquet Premier <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou
                        En-lai</persName> also mentioned that the contacts between the Chinese and
                    American people are bound to develop. I think you are also clear on this point.
                    But so far, it’s American friends and American people who have come to China.
                    And from April up to now it’s one-way traffic. And of course, the American Table
                    Tennis Association also has invited the Chinese Table Tennis Association to
                    visit the United States. And our Chinese Table Tennis Association is most
                    thankful to the American Table Tennis Association. And we have also noticed that
                    in last August the <persName corresp="#p_JJ3">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> clique
                    had also sent its table tennis team to the United States and they visited many
                    cities. They visited more than 20 cities and finally they arrived in Washington.
                    And we are very thankful to the American Table Tennis Association who refused to
                    play with them. They refused to have any matches with the Chiang Kai-shek table
                    tennis team.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I recall that.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: There were still people who,
                    although not members of the Table Tennis Association, they did play with the
                        <persName corresp="#p_JJ3">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> table tennis team. I
                    cite this question just to illustrate that there is a political factor to the
                    question of contacts.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: May I say something here? This
                    brings up precisely the point we were making yesterday. There are those in the
                    United States who are very critical of the policy established by President
                        <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, doing their best to interfere
                    with the normalization of relations and this is an illustration. <pb
                        facs="d43-06" n="6" xml:id="d43-06"/> This visit of the table tennis team
                    from Taiwan was arranged by the groups critical of the President’s policy, and
                    the United States Government had nothing to do with the visit of the group from
                    Taiwan.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: I would like to make two points of
                    comment on this. Firstly, we would not like to put the United States in an
                    embarrassing state, nor do we wish that the United States will put us in an
                    embarrassing state. If we have to take into consideration that aspect of the
                    picture, why didn’t you take into consideration this side of the picture? And
                    the second point is to say the United States Government has nothing to do with
                    the invitation of the <persName corresp="#p_JJ3">Chiang Kai-shek</persName>
                    table tennis team is only to speak of the picture. We have all engaged in
                    diplomatic work. First of all, you have to give them a visa, and a visa doesn’t
                    come from non-governmental organizations, and prior to that it is clearly
                    written in United States passports they are not permitted to come to the
                    People’s Republic of China.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: I don’t understand.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: In your American passports.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: That’s incorrect. Since 15
                    March, there are not more restrictions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Prior to that.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: What we should talk about now
                    is not the past but the future.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: I was just making comments on the
                    fact that you mention your government has nothing to do with invitation of the
                    Chiang Kai-shek table tennis clique to the United States. Because prior to that
                    your government has laid down rules to which countries they are allowed to issue
                    passports for U.S. citizens. And for the people of other countries to go b the
                    United States, they have got to get visas from the U.S. side. Without visas, how
                    could they go to the United States? Who would issue the visas, and also as to
                    when to issue the visas, it is up to the United States government organizations
                    to decide. If the Chinese Table Tennis Team also went to the United States in
                    August then in that way they would have been put in a more embarrassing
                    position. The State Department ______________ refused to issue visas to the
                        <persName corresp="#p_JJ3">Chiang Kai-shek</persName> team.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: But this was apprivate
                    arrangement, and for the government to do that would have been a distinct
                    political act.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: This is a political act?</p>
                <pb facs="d43-07" n="7" xml:id="d43-07"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: Not to act is a political
                    act.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: This is a political question.
                    Whether you issue the visa or not is a political question. You can’t ignore this
                    point. Whether this side or that side, it is always a political consideration.
                    That’s why I said in these circumstances as for your suggestions as to exchange
                    between the two countries it would be impossible to be conducted on a
                    governmental basis. That is to say, subsidiary questions have to be subordinated
                    to the fundamental questions. This is our consistent fundamental stand in the
                    Sino-U.S. ambassadorial talks in Warsaw.</p>
                <p>Of course, after the publication of the announcement, after Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s July visit to China, it is clearly
                    stated in the announcement that we are seeking the normalization of the
                    relations between the two countries. President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >Nixon</persName>’s visit is to seek the normalization of the relations
                    between the two countries. So in these circumstances it can be considered that
                    the cultural, scientific and technical exchanges can be conducted on a private
                    basis, but it can’t be too much because up to now the relations between our two
                    countries have not been normalized. There is still the Taiwan question. So it
                    can be considered to conduct exchanges on a non-governmental basis, but there
                    cannot be too much of this. What I referred to as exchanges, as for exchanges ov
                    visits between the two peoples, as Premier <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou
                        En-lai</persName> has mentioned, this is bound to develop. As to which
                    proposals out of these 25 proposals can be conducted in either the present or
                    the near future, these can be discussed. And generally speaking, this kind of
                    exchanges will be put on a non-governmental basis and there can be not too many
                    of them. That is my preliminary idea.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: It is perfectly agreeable to us that these
                    exchanges be on a non-governmental basis, and we think that it is reasonable
                    that progress in this area be step-by-step. I think that our leaders have both
                    expressed the idea that an eventual increase in such things is virtually
                    inevitable, and this is something we can look forward to in the future if things
                    go well in the interim. I think it is acceptable for there to be a somewhat
                    modest beginning, but the important thing is that there be a beginning.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Such exchanges can be realized,
                    but as for whether it will be mentioned in the joint communique after the visit
                    made by President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, that is the
                    joint communique issued during President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >Nixon</persName>’s visit this is not up to me (if there is any communique).
                    This is another matter. It is up to Premier <persName corresp="#p_ZECE1">Chou
                        En-lai</persName> and Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>
                    to consider it.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Yes, we agree.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: So what I have mentioned and
                    whether the joint communique should refer to this is two matters.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-08" n="8" xml:id="d43-08"/>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Yes, I understand that. We agree. I want to
                    emphasize that this rather large package of illustrative suggestions is by no
                    means exclusive. Any idea you have that is not in this we would, of course, be
                    very interested in considering also.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: What I have said just now, when
                    you handed over this list I haven’t thought it over before that. I don’t know
                    whether our comrade from the Foreign Ministry has thought it over or not.</p>
                <p>___________: Then I will consider it.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: But when our Foreign Ministry is
                    going to explain this to the departments concerned, they have to provide some
                    sort of information to them to ___________ further exploration.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I think the proposals as we gave them are about as
                    detailed as we can go into now, because they cover so many fields that none of
                    us are real specialists in these fields, and I think we need to come to some
                    general agreement as to where we are going in the field and then we can prepare
                    more detailed studies on any of these items which we find to be of mutual
                    interest. I think when you have time and an opportunity to study what we have
                    given you that you will find we have indicated fairly clearly what types of
                    steps we are prepared to take in general and in most instances we have indicated
                    the type of organization in the United States which we think would be primarily
                    concerned with them. But that is not fixed either. We can describe to you the
                    facilities and types of experience which these organizations have which might be
                    of interest to you and then move on from there on which _____ you might wish to
                    follow up on.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: According to your concept, your
                    ideas, would such kind of contacts be carried out by the method of direct
                    contact between non-government organizations on our side and in your country, or
                    by the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Either way is satisfactory to us. I think it would
                    be a little easier if the government were in the picture, because as I mentioned
                    earlier of the multi-faceted nature of this many types of atheletic, cultural
                    and ecientific associations we have. But it is also perfectly acceptable to us
                    to ______________________________________. If that is done you may wish to
                    consult with us concerning the facilities, reputation, etc. of these
                    organizations to better understand what they would be able to do and perhaps
                    what they would not be able to do.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-09" n="9" xml:id="d43-09"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Because these proposals were put
                    forward by your side, that is why I think I would like to clarify some points.
                    To make clear some of the points which I can conceive at the moment. So it’s not
                    a matter of suggestions put forward by our side which are satisfactory to you. I
                    just want to make clear on certain points. Just now you said it would be better
                    to have the government in the picture. What organizations do you refer to?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I am saying it would probably be easier for us if,
                    for instance, at least as sort of a clearing house the Communist Affairs Office
                    of our State Department were involved. However, if you don’t wish it that way it
                    is agreeable to us. It might facilitate matters, but if for political reasons
                    you prefer to have it not that way, that is agreeable. Or similarly, our United
                    States Information Agency would be a normal clearing house for journalists or
                    things of that nature, but we would not insist upon it. As a matter of fact, we
                    can furnish you a list of names of any number of organizations in the United
                    States which would be entirely non-governmental and if you prefer you can make
                    your arrangements with these organizations without governmental activity on our
                    part.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: Other than to facilitate the
                    issuance of visas.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: What do you think of the prestige
                    of the United States Information Agency in other countries?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I think I would rather not address that question
                    today if you don’t mind.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: To increase our mutual
                    understanding, I would like to ask how many sections are under your State
                    Department.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: In the State Department we have several bureaus.
                    There must be six geographical bureaus in the world.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Bureaus?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: And secretaries?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: There’s a secretary, an under secretary, an under
                    secretary for political affairs.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-10" n="10" xml:id="d43-10"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>:</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: That’s right. Then Assistant Secretaries who head
                    bureaus. There are six geographic bureaus.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Would the assistant secretary also
                    be the head of the geographic bureau?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: That is correct. Also several functional bureaus
                    at the same level as geographic bureaus. For instance, the Bureau of Economic
                    Affairs, the Bureau of International Organizational Affairs which handles U.S.
                    affairs …</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Cultural affairs?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Bureau of Cultural Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: How many bureaus are there
                    altogether?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I would guess ten, maybe twelve, but I would say
                    ten.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: We would have to count up.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Approximately ten.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Including the functional
                    bureaus?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Six geographic bureaus?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Which bureau are you in?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: East Asia and Pacific Affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: How many areas are included?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: From Japan all the way down through Indochina,
                    Southeast Asia, China through Burma. It stops there.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Australia?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Yes, Australia and New Zealand. (Lists
                    countries)</p>
                <pb facs="d43-11" n="11" xml:id="d43-11"/>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: East Asia and Pacific Affairs?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: There is such a bureau called Asia
                    and Communist Affairs?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: Not a bureau.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Not a bureau, it’s an office. I have 11 people in
                    my office.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: And a desk in the office?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: There are several officers within one office. It
                    varies. Some officers are large; some are smaller in number of personnel. An
                    office includes several offices.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: That means for instance if you
                    want to contact an Asian country aside from regional bureaus you make contacts
                    through the cultural bureau if it is in cultural affairs and contact the
                    economic affairs bureau if it is in economic affairs. Is this world wide?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Yes, but the normal point of contact for official
                    representatives in Washington would be the geographical bureau usually. The
                    geographical bureau then works closely with those functional bureaus.</p>
                <p>Hisung: I am not very familiar with this. That is why I asked. Which bureau is in
                    charge of issuing visas? Is there a special bureau in charge of it?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I don’t think it’s called a bureau; it’s an
                    office.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: Security and consular
                    affairs.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: And in that is the passport office and the visa
                    office. I do have one other topic I would like briefly to mention before the
                    break if that is agreeable, and Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> said if we finished here before the other meeting has
                    finished he would be glad if Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HJH1"
                        >Holdridge</persName> and I joined them in the other meeting, and we want to
                    know if that’s agreeable.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: We can do it according to Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s wish.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Thank you.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-12" n="12" xml:id="d43-12"/>
                <p>Hsiuing: When shall we stop?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Whenever we have finished what we need to do. It’s
                    not specific.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: If that’s the case then we can
                    take some refreshments.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I mentioned very briefly at our previous meeting
                    the subject of trade. I don’t know to what extent you want to discuss that
                    subject now. We are prepared to discuss it if you wish. I would like to mention
                    one matter which Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> has asked
                    me to say and that is that we are prepared to enlarge our general list of trade
                    items to the limit of our present laws before the President’s visit to China and
                    we are prepared to do that without any conditions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Personally, I am not interested in
                    this question. This morning on the way back from the Ming Tombs as our Acting
                    Foreign Minister was preoccupied with some other work, he said goodbye to Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> early so I was in the same
                    car with Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and he also
                    mentioned that the withdrawal of the Soviet exports greatly affected China. I
                    said that we are most grateful to Khrushchev. Because in acting that way he had
                    enabled us to carry out Chairman Mao’s policy of self-reliance even more
                    rapidly. But first of all, we must give thanks to the United States policy of
                    embargo. First _______ it was the United States who imposed embargo on China and
                    then it was Khrushchev who removed Soviet exports and _________ the agreements,
                    and it was a good thing because we don’t care for such things. In this way we
                    have developed even more rapidly.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: We certainly respect self-reliance, and we
                    understand your feelings on that score. We feel that even though the United
                    States too is able to be self-reliant, we would profit too from mutual trade
                    with others quite apart from the ability to be self-reliant. And we feel this
                    area also leads to increased understanding between peoples, and to the further
                    inhancing of their economic status and the livelihood of their people. But we
                    fully understand your justifiable pride in self-reliance and we respect that
                    attitude.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: While saying self-reliant, we also
                    have trade relations with many countries on the basis of ______ and mutual
                    benefit and supplying each other what it needs. But as for Sino-U.S. trade, at
                    present conditions are not yet right. That is my opinion; that is why I am not
                    interested in this question.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-13" n="13" xml:id="d43-13"/>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: We will not press it. I had mentioned it as
                    another possible area to supplement exchanges we have spoken of and I would like
                    to say again that we consider whatever you are ready to discuss in these areas
                    as contributing to making movement possible in the fundamental issues. We would
                    not want to use these terms “subsidiary” questions as any diversion from facing
                    the fundamental questions, but it makes it easier for us to approach
                    normalization of relations if we can show our detractors from our present policy
                    that tangible progress is possible without conditions attached to it.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: But the normalization of the
                    Sino-American relations is conditional.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Would Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HH3"
                        >Hsiung</persName> enlarge on that comment?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: That means the normalization of
                    relations between the countries cannot be carried out without conditions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I understand what you mean, and our principals are
                    talking about the fundamental issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: That is why before the
                    normalization of relations between the two countries is realized many matters
                    have to be handled in the circumstances when our relations have not yet been
                    normalized.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: We understand that.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: Out of courteous reasons we are
                    ready to listen to whatever ideas you would like to put forward, but as to the
                    question of trade, I am not interested. But you can put forward your ideas.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: Of course it makes it difficult to express any
                    specific proposals if we are told there is no interest. I would not like to
                    press this matter.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: What I mean is if you have any
                    ideas you can put them forward and if not then it is not necessary for you to
                    speak.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: We could offer ideas if there were interest
                    expressed in them but I am not sure it would be fruitful if there is no interest
                    in the subject.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: It is not necessary that
                    everything will be fruitful. We can exchange views and exchange our ideas. I am
                    willing to listen.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: I think perhaps we can address this letter.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: We will break now then.</p>
                <pb facs="d43-14" n="14" xml:id="d43-14"/>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jenkins</persName>: (To <persName corresp="#p_HJH1"
                        >Holdridge</persName>) Break or end?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HJH1">Holdridge</persName>: If Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName> has nothing further to bring up, we don’t
                    either.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_HH3">Hsiung</persName>: You are going to join in the other
                    talks? He is going to contact them.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
