<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="111" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d111">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/3–2248</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director of the Office of United
                                Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-22">March 22, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>In dealing with questions on Palestine, the following points are
                            fundamental:</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">1. The United Nations itself reached a complete
                                impasse on Palestine.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">a. <hi rend="italic">The Security Council</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>On March 5, 1948, the Security Council refused to pass an American
                            resolution which would have accepted the General Assembly resolution as
                            a basis for Security Council action. Our resolution got only 5 of the
                            necessary 7 votes. During Big Five consultations over the past two
                            weeks, no agreement was reached on a basis for further Security Council
                            action on Palestine. In addition, informal consultations among the
                            non-permanent members of the Security Council indicated very clearly
                            that partition could never get 7 votes in the Security Council.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">b. <hi rend="italic">The Trusteeship Council</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>On March 16, 1948, there were only 4 affirmative votes for the Draft
                            Statute for the City of Jerusalem, an essential part of the partition
                            plan. There were 5 votes in opposition. The only way in which partition
                            was saved this defeat was by postponing action in the Trusteeship
                            Council until April.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">c. <hi rend="italic">The Palestine Commission</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Palestine Commission will not be able to proceed to Palestine without
                            armed forces to support it, will not be able to establish an <pb facs="0241" n="751" xml:id="pg_751"/> Arab Government in the
                            proposed Arab state, will not be able to establish an economic union,
                            and will not be able to place in operation the international territory
                            of the City of Jerusalem. Thus it is clear that the only part of the
                            plan which the Palestine Commission might possibly carry out would be
                            the announcement of a provisional council of government for the Jewish
                            state itself.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">2. Unless emergency action is taken, large-scale
                                fighting will break out in Palestine on May 16.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The United Kingdom seems determined to terminate the mandate on May 15.
                            There is no prospect that the partition scheme can now be made effective
                            by that date. Any effort to establish a Jewish state by self-help on the
                            part of the Jews would inevitably result in large-scale fighting between
                            the Jews and the Arabs. The Arabs will insist that the termination of
                            the mandate leaves Palestine as a single independent country, of course
                            under Arab control.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">3. The United States proposal for a temporary
                                trusteeship is emergency action directed solely to the maintenance
                                of peace pending a political settlement.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>In discussing the nature of the proposed trusteeship, it is important to
                            emphasize that it is a means for obtaining a truce. The military truce
                            must be accompanied by a political truce, but the political truce
                            requires governmental machinery to take over when the British leave. The
                            proposal is without prejudice to the eventual political settlement. It
                            is a conservatory effort.</p>
                        <p>4. In the trusteeship field, the United Nations is empowered to act as a
                                <hi rend="italic">government</hi> and is not making recommendations.
                            There is therefore no Charter problem about enforcing law and order in
                            Palestine in connection with trusteeship.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>