<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Dr. Chaim Weizmann to President Truman</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="139"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Truman Papers, Official File</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName type="from">Chaim Weizmann</persName> to
                        President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-04-09">April 9,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: I had intended to take the liberty
                    of addressing you in writing immediately after the interview which you kindly
                    accorded me on March 18th. The events which followed, however, impelled me to
                    wait until I could formulate some clearer impressions on the new situation which
                    has developed. In inviting your consideration of my views at this time, I wish
                    to thank you, Mr. President, for the personal kindness which you have so often
                    shown me, and for the sympathetic interest which you have constantly devoted to
                    the cause of our people in its grave ordeal.</p>
                <p>I noted with satisfaction that in your statement of March 25 you indicated that
                    the United States had not abandoned Partition as the ultimate political
                    settlement in Palestine. I welcome this assurance because my long experience of
                    this problem has convinced me beyond doubt that no more realistic solution
                    exists. Palestine is inhabited by two peoples. These peoples have separate
                    political aspirations and common economic interests. The settlement by Partition
                    and economic union recognizes this logic. Partition is further reinforced by the
                    support of two distinguished investigating Commissions (in 1937 and 1947), by
                    the binding force of the General Assembly’s Resolution and by the fact that a
                    virtual Partition is now crystallising in Palestine. Jews and Arabs are both
                    mature for independence and are already obedient in a large degree to their own
                    institutions, while the central British Administration is in virtual collapse.
                    In large areas Jews and Arabs are virtually in control of their own lives and
                    interests. The clock cannot be put back to the situation which existed before
                    November 29. I would also draw attention to the psychological effects of
                    promising Jewish independence in November and attempting to cancel it in
                    March.</p>
                <p>It is the logic of partition and of the present situation in Palestine which
                    compelled me to go on record against the idea of trusteeship. <pb facs="0298"
                        n="808" xml:id="pg_808"/> One fails to see how any of the admitted
                    difficulties of Partition are avoided by Trusteeship. The problem of enforcement
                    becomes even more acute, as neither the Arabs nor the Jews of Palestine have
                    accepted Trusteeship which appears likely to deprive each of them of Statehood.
                    It is proposed to institute a Trusteeship in a country threatened by foreign
                    Arab aggression, torn by internal warfare, and already moving inexorably towards
                    Partition under a valid international resolution. The proposal is made without
                    any assurance that a trustee is available, that Arabs or Jews will cooperate,
                    that the General Assembly will approve an agreement or that any effective
                    measures can be improvised by May 15th.</p>
                <p>The difficult but clear course of implementing Partition is thus replaced by a
                    leap into the unknown, and I am forced to regret, Mr. President, the great
                    increase of trouble, danger and responsibility which must ensue for the United
                    States from the unfortunate reversal on March 19th, with its inauguration of new
                    uncertainty and new political conflict.</p>
                <p>If I may venture to leave you, Mr. President, with one or two reflections on the
                    major aspects of the problem, I would sound a note of solemn warning against any
                    prolongation of British rule in Palestine. As you may know, I have cherished the
                    British-Jewish relationship all my life. I have upheld it in difficult times. I
                    have been grieviously disappointed by its recent decline. It is because I hope
                    for its renewal that I tremble to think of the wave of violence and repression
                    which would sweep Palestine if the conditions and auspices of the recent unhappy
                    years were to be continued under British, or indeed any foreign rule. I also
                    know how passionately the British people desire the end of this troubled
                    chapter. Should your administration, despite all this, press for any
                    prolongation of British tenure, it would incur a responsibility for terrible
                    events and, almost certainly, the equal resentment of the British and Jewish
                    peoples.</p>
                <p>I recall that it is exactly two years since the Anglo-American Committee so
                    emphatically endorsed your moving plea for the immediate admission of 100,000
                    Jews from the Displaced Persons Camps to Palestine. They are still in those
                    camps. Reports have reached me of the grave effect produced on their dwindling
                    resources of hope and morale by the United States declaration of March 19th. I
                    cannot for a moment believe, Mr. President, that you would be a party to the
                    further disappointment of pathetic hopes, which you yourself have raised so
                    high. Their hope is solely for personal and national integration in a Jewish
                    State in Palestine.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, I am convinced that the present situation in Palestine is making a
                    profound impact on the conscience of the American people. Having recognized the
                    right of our people to independence last November, <pb facs="0299" n="809"
                        xml:id="pg_809"/> the great powers now expose them to the risk of
                    extermination and do not even grant them the arms to provide for their own
                    defense. Arab aggression is now more confident than ever. Arabs believe that an
                    international decision has been revised in their favour purely because they
                    dared to use force against it. Mr. President, I cannot see how this belief can
                    honestly be refuted. The practical question now is whether your Administration
                    will proceed to leave our people unarmed in the face of an attack which it
                    apparently feels it is unable to stop; and whether it can allow us to come
                    directly or indirectly under Arab domination which is sworn to our
                    destruction.</p>
                <p>The choice for our people, Mr. President, is between Statehood and extermination.
                    History and providence have placed this issue in your hands, and I am confident
                    that you will yet decide it in the spirit of the moral law.<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d139fn1">A marginal notation on the source text by Rose A. Conway,
                        Administrative Assistant in the President’s office, indicates that the
                        letter was not answered. <p>Dr. Weizmann transmitted a copy of the letter to
                            the Secretary of State on April 9; it was acknowledged by Acting
                            Secretary Lovett in a letter of April 24 which concluded as follows:</p>
                        <p>“I sincerely hope that action which has been and will be taken in the
                            United Nations will lead to the restoration of peaceful conditions in
                            Palestine and to agreement between Arabs and Jews resident there on
                            their future government.” (501.BB Palestine/4–948)</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Chaim Weizmann</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
