<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-04-22T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-04-22T07:00:00-05:00" n="171" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d171">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/4–2248: Circular
                            telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to <gloss type="to">Certain Diplomatic and
                                    Consular Offices</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-04-22T07:00:00-05:00">April 22,
                                    1948—7 a. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Reference is made to Dept Radio Bulletin No. 94 of April 20 quoting
                            statement regarding Palestine by Ambassador Austin in the First
                            Committee of the General Assembly on that date.</p>
                        <p>Particular attention is directed toward those paragraphs dealing with
                            efforts which US has made in concert with other members of UN since
                            Special Session of May 1947 to achieve solution of Palestine problem
                            which would be acceptable to Jews and Arabs of Palestine.</p>
                        <p>Particular attention is also directed to conclusion informally reached by
                            members of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> on March 19 that “it was
                            impossible to find the necessary agreement, either among the peoples of
                            Palestine or among the members of the Security Council, to permit the
                            peaceful implementation of the Assembly Resolution” of November 29, 1947
                            which provided for partition with Economic Union. It was for this
                            primary reason that US thereafter suggested necessity for immediate
                            truce in Palestine, early convocation of Special Session of <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> and temporary trusteeship for Palestine
                            which would provide interim governmental machinery in Palestine
                            following termination British Mandate on May 15.</p>
                        <p>Call for truce was issued by <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> April 17;
                            Special Session <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> was convoked April 16;
                            US submitted draft trusteeship agreement April 20 <pb facs="0334" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/> as working paper to members UN for their
                            consideration as feasible form interim governmental machinery for
                            Palestine following termination British Mandate May 15. It is hoped
                            other members UN will have suggestions to make concerning this draft,
                            that it will be debated shortly and that if any members have alternative
                            suggestions as to other forms interim governmental machinery they will
                            make them as soon as possible.</p>
                        <p>You are instructed to discuss question of Palestine along foregoing lines
                            immediately with Prime Min, For Min or Chief of State or if you deem it
                            helpful with all of them. You should make it clear during your talks
                            that unless way can be found at once to prevent situation in Palestine
                            from developing into open warfare security of whole <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> will be seriously threatened and economic
                            situation of Arab world is certain to deteriorate with result that its
                            economic development will be retarded for many years to come. You should
                            also make it clear that so long as Palestine situation continues to
                            remain serious threat to peace of <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> it
                            would seem to be pointless for US to endeavor to enter into any
                            arrangements of political or economic nature looking forward to
                            promotion of security or economic improvement of <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss>.<note n="1" xml:id="d171fn1">The Office of Financial and
                                Development Policy called a meeting on May 7 to discuss the economic
                                implications of the political situation in the Middle East. The
                                meeting was attended by nine economic officers and two <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> representatives. The memorandum
                                covering the conversation was prepared by Samuel J. Gorlitz of the
                                Division of Investment and Economic Development. It stated that
                                “after general discussion, it was agreed that the circular telegram
                                of April 22 to Middle East missions should be interpreted to mean
                                that despite our long-range policy of positive economic assistance
                                to the Middle East states, execution of specific projects should be
                                delayed until the Palestine situation has been clarified, but that
                                planning activities should continue.” (890.50/5–748)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>You should impress upon officials with whom you are talking that no
                            matter how deep an interest US may have in maintenance of security of
                                <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> and in development of <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> prosperity it feels that there are no
                            effective measures which it can take in this direction until way is
                            found out of Palestine impasse.<note n="2" xml:id="d171fn2">Ambassador
                                Tuck conveyed the purport of the circular telegram of April 22 to
                                Egyptian Prime Minister Nokrashy on April 24. He advised that
                                “Nokrashy Pasha listened attentively, then remarked that message
                                which I had delivered was very serious. While he did not say so in
                                as many words, I had the inescapable impression that my statement to
                                him—with reference to pointlessness for US to endeavor to enter into
                                any arrangement of a political or economic nature looking forward to
                                promotion of security or economic improvement of the <gloss target="#t_ME1">ME</gloss> pending solution Palestine
                                impasse—was, in fact, an attempt by our government to force Arab
                                states to modify their present policy toward defense of Palestine.”
                                (Telegram 410, April 24, 5 p. m., 501.BB Palestine/4–2248)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sent to Baghdad, Beirut, Damascus, Jidda and Cairo for action; repeated
                            to Jerusalem, London, Paris and New York for info.</p>
                        <p>Baghdad, Beirut and Jidda please await immediately following
                                telegram<note n="3" xml:id="d171fn3">See telegram 117 to Baghdad,
                                April 22, <ref target="#pg_850">p. 850</ref>.</note> before taking
                            action.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Lovett</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>