<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-01-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="2" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d2">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/1–648</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Fraser Wilkins of
                                the Division of Near Eastern Affairs</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-01-06">January 6, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Epstein, Jewish Agency<note n="1" xml:id="d2fn1">Eliahu Epstein, Director of the Washington
                                        Office of the Jewish Agency for Palestine.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Eban, Jewish Agency</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Henderson, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Rusk, <gloss target="#t_SPA1">SPA</gloss><note n="2" xml:id="d2fn2">Dean Rusk, Director
                                        of the Office of Special Political Affairs.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Merriam, <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss><note n="3" xml:id="d2fn3">Gordon P. Merriam,
                                        Chief of the Division of Near Eastern Affairs.</note>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Mr. Wilkins, <gloss target="#t_NE1">NE</gloss> Mr. Epstein and Mr. Eban
                            called on Mr. Henderson, Mr. Rusk and Mr. Merriam separately today for
                            the purpose of reporting current developments with regard to Palestine
                            and eliciting the further support of the United States Government in
                            implementation of the recent UN recommendation to partition
                            Palestine.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Eban said that he had accompanied <gloss target="#t_UNSCOP1">UNSCOP</gloss> during its investigation last summer and that more
                            recently had been acting as a liaison officer for the Jewish Agency with
                            the UN in New York. Mr. Eban pointed out that the Jewish Agency was
                            particularly concerned with two aspects of the UN recommendation at the
                            present time: (1) immigration; (2) security. Mr. Eban said that the
                            Jewish Agency hoped that the British authorities would be able to
                            provide a seaport by February 1<note n="4" xml:id="d2fn4">The partition
                                resolution of the General Assembly had provided that “The mandatory
                                Power shall use its best endeavours to ensure that an area situated
                                in the territory of the Jewish State, including a seaport and
                                hinterland adequate to provide facilities for a substantial
                                immigration, shall be evacuated at the earliest possible date and in
                                any event not later than 1 February 1948.” (Appendix, <ref target="#pg_1711">p. 1711</ref>.)</note> in order that
                            immigration might commence at once but that unless the UN Commission was
                            able successfully to negotiate with British authorities, it did not
                            appear that immigration would take place as soon as hoped.</p>
                        <p>With regard to security, Mr. Eban expressed the view that two matters
                            might be considered under this heading: (1) action by the Security
                            Council; (2) action by the militia authorized in the UN recommendation.
                            With regard to the first, Mr. Eban recalled that the American
                            representatives at the UN had remarked during recent UN consideration of
                            the Palestine problem that the U.S. would play its part. For this
                            reason, Major Eban hoped that the United States would support such
                            action relating to security as the Security Council might deem it
                            appropriate to take. Mr. Eban said that he understood the <pb facs="0028" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/> Syrian representative and the
                            Polish representative on the Security Council might raise the Palestine
                            question as a threat to international peace and security and observed
                            that this might be appropriate time for the U.S. Government to make
                            known its views. With regard to militia forces in each of the proposed
                            states in Palestine, Mr. Eban said that he hoped that the members of he
                            UN including the United States would be in a position to arm and equip
                            these forces. Major Eban said that at the present time, the Haganah,
                            which would be the armed militia in the proposed Jewish State, was
                            adequately manned but poorly equipped and that it was essential that
                            supplies be obtained.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Eban expressed the view that current newspaper reports and
                            information being received from Palestine indicated that the Arabs hoped
                            the UN recommendation to partition Palestine would not be implemented
                            and that the Jews feared no action would be taken to put it into effect.
                            Mr. Eban thought that this basic approach to the problem on the part of
                            the Arabs and Jews was one of the major factors in the present situation
                            and expressed the belief that strong support by the U.S. for partition
                            in the Security Council and the provision of equipment for the Jewish
                            militia would indicate American determination and would thus have a
                            stabilizing effect on the situation in Palestine.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Henderson said that he had been following recent developments in
                            Palestine closely and was very much concerned with the type of incidents
                            which were now taking place in Palestine. Mr. Henderson recalled the
                            recent attack at the Consolidated Refinery in Haifa in which Jews bombed
                            Arabs and Arabs in reprisal killed some 30 to 40 Jews in spite of the
                            fact that both Jews and Arabs had worked in harmony previously. Mr.
                            Henderson pointed out that a continuation of terroristic activities
                            which resulted in the killing of innocent people would have a
                            brutalizing effect and would cause many to have serious doubts as to
                            whether either the Arabs or the Jews were sufficiently mature to govern
                            themselves. Mr. Henderson asked Mr. Epstein and Mr. Eban whether they
                            thought the issuance of a statement by the UN or possibly by the US
                            deploring such activities and pointing out the inevitable consequences
                            would have a salutary effect. Both Mr. Epstein and Mr. Eban were of the
                            opinion that the issuance of a statement of this type would be helpful
                            and said that, as far as the Jews were concerned, they were making every
                            effort to conduct themselves with restraint. Mr. Epstein stressed the
                            fact that the Jews were desirous of acting in accordance with the UN
                            recommendation and hoped that the UN would support their activities.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Rusk remarked in reply to Mr. Eban’s statements regarding immigration
                            and security that he believed the establishment of a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi> between the Jews and the Arabs was the most
                            important question for consideration at this time since all other
                            matters <pb facs="0029" n="539" xml:id="pg_539"/> were of necessity
                            corollary to it. Mr. Eban said that he agreed but that it was essential
                            that actual steps be taken regarding the commencement of immigration and
                            the establishment of security forces in advance of the departure of the
                            British from Palestine. Mr. Rusk said he understood the members of the
                            UN Commission had now been appointed and that it would meet on January 9
                            or 10, and that he hoped that the Jews would shortly initiate
                            conversation with the Commission, the British authorities and the Arabs.
                            Mr. Rusk said the successful implementation of the UN recommendation
                            hinged on the working out of details with these three groups. Mr. Rusk
                            said that he stressed this aspect of the situation because he believed
                            that Mr. Epstein and Mr. Eban were well aware of the many legal
                            difficulties attendant on further consideration of the Palestine problem
                            in the Security Council. Mr. Rusk said that, for this reason, it was
                            extremely important that both the Jews and the Arabs should attempt to
                            settle the problems with regard to Palestine as well as they could by
                            themselves and should only fall back on UN action as a last resort.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Epstein and Mr. Eban expressed their appreciation for the various
                            views expressed and said that Mr. Shertok<note n="5" xml:id="d2fn5">Moshe Shertok, Head of the Political Department of the Jewish
                                Agency.</note> was returning to the US from Palestine via London
                            toward the end of this week and that he would undoubtedly call at the
                            Department for the purpose of presenting further information with regard
                            to current developments in Palestine.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>