<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-05-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="284" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d284">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/5–1748</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-05-17">May 17, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>At my meeting with the President at 12:30 today we first took up the
                            question of the position paper for our representatives at the Security
                            Council for the meeting this afternoon. I read the draft to him, <pb facs="0498" n="1008" xml:id="pg_1008"/> and Rusk and I explained
                            some of the details to all of which he agreed and formally approved the
                                paper.<note n="1" xml:id="d284fn1">For Ambassador Austin’s statement
                                before the Security Council on May 17, see <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Following this I had Mr. Rusk explain to him the present situation
                            regarding the arms embargo and following that I stated that I was not
                            certain that Mr. Rusk had made the facts clear enough. The President
                            then said “I will recite how I understand it” and did so reflecting
                            correct understanding of our point of view.</p>
                        <p>After Mr. Rusk’s departure I again referred to the arms embargo and read
                            the section of the Resolution of April 17 that referred to it and made a
                            particular point of the fact that we must proceed in this matter with
                            extreme care or we will give a final kick to the UN. The President
                            agreed to that view of the matter. I went on to say that we had to see
                            what happened and he said he agreed, that we have to see who does what
                            to whom and quoted my language to the press. I added some other
                            explanations of possibilities in the case all of which he agreed
                            with.</p>
                        <p>Incidentally he did not know up to that time what had occurred at the
                            Security Council in the absence of Ambassador Austin and the fact that
                                Sayre<note n="2" xml:id="d284fn2">Francis B. Sayre, a member of the
                                United States Delegation at the United Nations.</note> was unaware
                            of what was coming, and treated it somewhat as a joke as I had done but
                            I think we both privately thought it was a hell of a mess. I went on to
                            say that we felt that the United States had hit its all-time low before
                            the UN and that we must be most careful what we do in relation to this
                            arms embargo.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow two paragraphs of discussion on candidates to head the
                            United Nations program of relief for Palestine refugees.]</p>
                        <p>There were no other matters discussed.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>G. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>