<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Vice Consul at Jerusalem (
                        Burdett
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p2</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d380</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">380</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-06-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="380" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d380">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/6–1348: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Vice Consul at Jerusalem</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Burdett</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Jerusalem</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-06-13">June 13,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>908. Following message was communicated at 2100 hours local tonight to Jewish
                    authorities in Jerusalem by Truce Commission and Count Bernadotte’s special
                    representative in Jerusalem.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“The Truce Commission and Colonel Brunsson,<note n="1" xml:id="d380fn1">Nils
                            Brunsson, Personal Representative of Count Bernadotte at Jerusalem and
                            Chief Military Observer in that city.</note> special representative of
                        Count Bernadotte, have carefully considered the question of Jewish convoys
                        to Jerusalem, They feel such convoys must be checked at Bab el Wad in order
                        to insure effective control. Until further notice the Jewish authorities are
                        requested to stop all vehicles before they reach Bab el Wad. If any vehicles
                        pass Bab el Wad before clearance by representatives of the mediator, the
                        Truce Commission and Colonel Brunsson consider that the Jewish authorities
                        will bear full responsibility for any resulting breach of the cease-fire
                            agreement.”<note n="2" xml:id="d380fn2">The Truce Commission, on June
                            14, sent a further communication to Dr. Bernard Joseph, the Israeli head
                            of the Jerusalem Emergency Committee, fixing a deadline of 8 p. m. that
                            night for accepting establishment of the checkpoint. Mr. Burdett
                            reported that “Five minutes before deadline Joseph notified Commission
                            he agreed on own responsibility and in absence instructions from Tel
                            Aviv to establishment Bab El Wad check post Added he assumed no
                            responsibility for safety observers and that in event his decision
                            countermanded by Tel Aviv, check point would have to be evacuated.”
                            (Telegram 918, June 14, from Jerusalem, 501.BB Palestine/6–1448)</note>
                    </p>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Burdett</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
