<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-06-30T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-06-30T07:00:00-05:00" n="424" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d424">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/6–3048: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Jerusalem</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Macdonald</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Jerusalem</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-06-30T16:00:00+04:00">June 30,
                                    1948—4 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1009. During official call today on Commander Shaltiel, Jewish military
                            commander Jerusalem, possibility of extending truce was mentioned. He
                            said Israel does not desire extension for political and military
                            reasons. He accused Arabs of constant violations truce stressing chiefly
                            their refusal supply water Jerusalem. He also stated <gloss target="#t_HMG1">HMG</gloss> is advising Transjordan ruler not to
                            agree to renewal of truce and encouraging Arab Legion to resume
                            hostilities.</p>
                        <p>Bernard Joseph, chairman Jewish Jerusalem Emergency Command liaison
                            officer Truce Commission, claims Jews should not have agreed to truce as
                            they were on verge of military victory. He does not think truce will be
                            extended and judging from his remarks he is not in favor of
                            extension.</p>
                        <p>Consensus Jews Jerusalem is that truce will not be extended. Jewish
                            leaders give impression of feeling confident of military victory. If
                            truce not extended they will undoubtedly try place entire blame on Arabs
                            in hope of increasing pro-Jewish sympathy in US and repeal of arms
                            embargo.</p>
                        <pb facs="0649" n="1159" xml:id="pg_1159"/>
                        <p>Arab attitude re truce extension will be reported after calls on Arab
                            leaders tomorrow.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Macdonald</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>