<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-07-07T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-07-07T07:00:00-05:00" n="441" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d441">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/7–748: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Patterson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">most immediate</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                                </gloss>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-07-07T14:00:00+02:00">July 7,
                                    1948—2 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>922. On informing Count Bernadotte at 9:30 this morning of content <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 929, July 6,<note n="1" xml:id="d441fn1">Not printed; it requested that Count Bernadotte be
                                apprised of press and other reports concerning termination of the
                                truce in Palestine and of the United States “hope that he will issue
                                necessary orders to assure safe withdrawal of observers and
                                equipment to ports where they may be safely embarked if and when he
                                is convinced such action should be taken.” (501.BB
                                Palestine/7–648)</note> he stated that Arab League had not rejected
                            his proposals for continuation of truce. Bernadotte, however, apparently
                            expected truce to lapse. He viewed Arab counter-proposals (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 920, July 6<note n="2" xml:id="d441fn2">Not printed, but see editorial note, <ref target="#pg_1192">p. 1192</ref>.</note>) as hardly more than
                            repetition of year-old arguments for unitary state. He could not,
                            accordingly, consider them as bases for discussion. The Jews had made no
                            counter-proposals whatever. Bernadotte was hopeful that Arabs would
                            accept demilitarization of Jerusalem as proposed by him. He fancied,
                            however, that they would not assent to demilitarization of Haifa.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, he had proposed and was hopeful that both Arabs and Jews
                            would at least concede a request which he had just made for a three-day
                            prolongation of the truce which would enable observers and other
                            personnel and materiel to be evacuated to ports. Colonel Bonde had
                            already elaborated a plan whereby observers and other Mediator personnel
                            would be evacuated to Haifa, Amman, and Cairo with eventual
                            concentration at Beirut for transportation to Athens.<note n="3" xml:id="d441fn3">The Department, on July 7, told Jerusalem that
                                Count Bernadotte had formally requested removal of UN personnel and
                                equipment from the Near East by the United States Navy (telegram
                                710, 501.BB Palestine/7–748). In a letter of July 9, to Secretary
                                Forrestal, Acting Secretary Lovett requested that the evacuated
                                personnel and equipment remain in the immediate vicinity until it
                                became certain that the truce would not be extended (501.BB
                                Palestine/7–948).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Bernadotte felt neither side would care to reject this modest extension
                            of truce and that indeed each would be reluctant to assume
                            responsibility for resumption of hostilities, truce or no truce. He felt
                            that the four-weeks truce had entered into effect too soon since the
                            Arabs, at least, were still “feeling their oats” and had not, through
                            continuation of hostilities, had enough of the fight knocked out of
                            them.</p>
                        <p>Sent Department 922, repeated Jerusalem 107, Haifa 74.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Patterson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>