<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-02-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-02-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="46" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d46">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/2–1948</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-02-19">February 19, 1948</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>In my conversation with the President today I followed the understanding
                            you and I had this morning.<note n="1" xml:id="d46fn1">The editors have
                                found no record of the nature of this understanding in the
                                Department of State files.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The President assured me whatever course we considered the right one we
                            could disregard all political factors. I told him that Sunday
                                night,<note n="2" xml:id="d46fn2">February 22.</note> but more
                            probably sometime Monday morning, we would send to his ship the proposed
                            statement for Austin. He said he would be in St. Croix<note n="3" xml:id="d46fn3">President Truman departed from Washington on
                                February 20 for a trip to the Caribbean and vacation in Florida. The
                                Presidential yacht <hi rend="italic">Williamsburg</hi> was waiting
                                for the President in San Juan, Puerto Rico when he arrived there by
                                air on February 21. He visited St. Thomas on February 22 and St.
                                Croix on February 23.</note> getting there about 5 in the morning,
                            but not going ashore until 9 or 10; that he would give instructions that
                            whenever a message came in it be delivered to him immediately wherever
                            he was; that the arrangement I suggested was most satisfactory. I gave
                            him no idea of what our solution might be but I did tell him of the
                            careful approach you were making toward the reaching of a conclusion,
                            particularly as to the San Francisco and Senate discussions and also the
                            consultations with men of some international legal understanding.<note n="4" xml:id="d46fn4">These allusions were not identifiable by the
                                editors.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>G. C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>