<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Special Representative of the United States in Israel
                        (
                        McDonald
                    ) to President Truman
                    
                    Transmitted to the Department by Tel Aviv in
                        telegram 104 for “personal attention President and Secretary.”</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p2</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d596</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">596</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-09-12T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-09-12T11:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="refugees" subject="refugees" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585" lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-12T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-12T11:00:00-05:00" n="596" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d596">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/9–1248: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Special Representative of the United States in Israel</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">McDonald</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <gloss type="to">Truman</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d596fn1">Transmitted to the Department by Tel Aviv in
                        telegram 104 for “personal attention President and Secretary.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tel Aviv</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-12T19:00:00+03:00">September 12, 1948—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In your letter July 21,<note n="2" xml:id="d596fn2">The text of the letter is
                        incorporated in Mr. (Lovett’s memorandum of conversation of July 21, <ref target="#pg_1232">p. 1232</ref>.</note> Mr. President, among other
                    points you instructed <pb facs="0885" n="1393" xml:id="pg_1393"/> me to report
                    to you on “appropriate time for full recognition” <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss>. That time has, I believe, now come.</p>
                <p>After more than four weeks intensive study here and further to my telegram to you
                    (70, August 24<note n="3" xml:id="d596fn3">See footnote 1, <ref target="#pg_1337">p. 1337</ref>.</note>) that indefinite truce cannot
                    lead to peace without positive action to clarify situation, I am convinced that
                    full recognition by the US now of <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> would
                    accomplish four major US objectives: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Strengthen <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> moderates who want if
                            humanly possible avoid renewal warfare.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Give Arab moderates, especially Abdullah (who knew past months
                            decision battlefield was gravely adverse and who fear renewed warfare
                            might result personal and national debacle), additional reason
                            accelerate move towards settlement.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Remove major obstacle to peace negotiations by demonstrating to Arab
                            intransigents fact that Israel’s existence cannot longer be denied or
                            ignored.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Encourage British relax its non-recognition policy.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Unless US makes up own mind as in original recognition without waiting on British
                    corresponding or related action, I see delay dangerous and possibly fatal to
                    peace hopes. British present procrastination is continuation of His Majesty’s
                    Government’s non-cooperation policy since <gloss target="#t_UNSCOP1">UNSCOP</gloss> partition recommendation and reflects same stubborn
                    miscalculation of basic elements in this area. Judged by present results,
                    British experts—except General D’Arcy and General Gort who warned that Jews
                    would defeat Arabs—gravely misled their government and are still doing so.
                    Hence, to wait on British is to invite failure.</p>
                <p>Grounds justifying full recognition are found in <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss>’s—(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) plans early election constituent
                    assembly, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) its control of state, (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) its repeated public and official expressed willingness negotiate
                    peace settlement with Arabs.</p>
                <p>In urging full recognition now I am aware of possible repercussions in Arab
                    countries, including possible danger to Americans. However, I believe that clear
                    statement to Arab governments given in advance through neighboring missions that
                    such US action be not unfriendly but acceptance of Israel as <hi rend="italic">fait accompli;</hi> and notification that US expects fullest protection its
                    citizens would remove or greatly minimize danger. Furthermore, in this
                    connection I wish observe that several other nations have accorded full
                    recognition Israel without suffering danger or damage their missions or citizens
                    in Arab countries.</p>
                <p>I have also kept in mind fact that there are important unanswered questions about
                        <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss>’s attitude towards (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Jerusalem, (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) November 29 frontiers, (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Arab refugees. Despite these questions, I am convinced
                    that <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> recognition in advance UN assembly would
                    increase <pb facs="0886" n="1394" xml:id="pg_1394"/> chances satisfactory
                    settlement these and related issues during peace negotiations.</p>
                <p>Bernadotte and staff’s urgent recommendation peace effort at UN and their
                    conviction that otherwise truce must lead to war within few weeks (<gloss target="#t_remytel1">refmytel</gloss> 101, September 10<note n="4" xml:id="d596fn4">Not printed.</note>) are additional reasons immediate full
                    recognition. There can be no fruitful peace negotiations until Arab states see
                    that Israel is definitely established.</p>
                <p>Although legal differences between <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> and <hi rend="italic">de jure</hi> recognition are regarded by some distinguished
                    lawyers as slight, it would be difficult exaggerate practical value US decision
                    full recognition advance UN Assembly.</p>
                <p>Mr. President, your and Secretary’s action May 15[<hi rend="italic">14</hi>]<note n="5" xml:id="d596fn5">See Secretary Marshall’s letter of May 14 to Mr.
                        Epstein, <ref target="#pg_992">p. 992</ref>.</note> was highest
                    statesmanship because it courageously Set constructive example. Completion now
                    of what you both then began might be decisive for peace in Palestine and Middle
                    East</p>
                <p>Department please reply direct to Tel Aviv.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">McDonald</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
