<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Editorial Note</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p2</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d6</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">6</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-01-03T17:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-03T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="6" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d6">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The Legal Adviser (Gross), in a memorandum of January 15, to Mr. Rusk, commented
                    on a recommendation drafted by Mr. Rusk for the Under Secretary. The editors are
                    unable to find Mr. Rusk’s recommendation in the Department of State files. Mr.
                    Gross’ memorandum, however, summarized the recommendation as follows: “In your
                    draft memorandum the problem was considered of what position the United States
                    should take in the Security Council of the United Nations in the event that a
                    member of the Council should move ‘to request an advisory opinion from the
                    International Court of Justice on the legality of the action recently
                    recommended by the General Assembly with respect to Palestine. The memorandum
                    recommended that the United States should support such a motion.’”</p>
                <p>After analyzing the advantages and disadvantages of the recommendation, the Legal
                    Adviser concluded:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>“(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The United States should not <hi rend="italic">support</hi> a motion in Security Council to refer any question on
                        Palestine to the International Court;</item>
                    <item>“(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The United States should oppose reference to
                        the Court of <hi rend="italic">any</hi> question on Palestine as a
                        pre-condition to action by the Security Council in carrying out its
                        responsibilities for the maintenance of international peace and security;
                        the United States should be prepared to vote against a reference under such
                        circumstances, after consultation with other Security Council members to
                        ascertain that such negative vote would not constitute a unilateral United
                        States veto;</item>
                    <item>“(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) The United States should oppose reference to
                        the Court, by the Security Council, of any question not pertinent to a
                        matter before the Council (e.g., the general question whether the General
                        Assembly had power to recommend a Palestine solution that did not have the
                        consent of the inhabitants of Palestine); again, the United States should be
                        prepared to vote against such a reference provided the negative vote did not
                        result in a unilateral United States veto;</item>
                    <item>“(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) In other cases of a motion in the Security
                        Council to refer questions on Palestine to the Court the United States
                        should not support a reference and should abstain from voting.” (501.BB
                        Palestine/1–1548)</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
