<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Draft Telegram to the Special Representative of the United
                        States in Israel (McDonald)Drafted on September 30 by Mr. McClintock for Mr. Lovett’s
                        signature. This message was not sent.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p2</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d630</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">630</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-09-30T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="international-relations" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-09-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-09-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="630" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d630">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/9–3048</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Draft Telegram to the Special Representative of the United
                        States in Israel</hi> (<hi rend="italic">McDonald</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d630fn1">Drafted on September 30 by Mr. McClintock for Mr. Lovett’s
                        signature. This message was not sent.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   us urgent</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, [<date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1948-09-30">undated</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Please call on Ben Gurion and leave memorandum in following terms: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <list>
                            <item>“1. The US Govt, which as events have shown, has proved a sincere
                                friend of <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss>, desires in spirit of
                                friendly counsel to urge that <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss>
                                accept or acquiesce in conclusions of Bernadotte Plan in their
                                entirety. US Govt is gratified to be informed by its Representative
                                in Tel Aviv (your 151, Sept 28) that Israeli Foreign Minister
                                departed for Paris prepared to acknowledge Bernadotte’s report as
                                basis for discussion and in spirit of hope for a reasonable
                                settlement.</item>
                            <item>“2. Although conclusions of Mediator may not in all respects meet
                                with Jewish desires this Govt is convinced after careful analysis of
                                Bernadotte’s recommendations that his plan affords a common
                                denominator for present acquiescence as between Israel and Arab
                                States and eventual formal acceptance of a peaceful and permanent
                                solution of Palestine problem.</item>
                            <item>“3. This Govt is fully cognizant of value attached by <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> to the Negev but cannot agree that
                                relinquishment of this desert area is in fact a basic loss to the
                                new Jewish State. Territorial proposals of the dead Mediator were
                                not based on the number of square miles accruing to one side or the
                                other but on terms of real value. Mediator’s proposals were
                                motivated by Count Bernadotte’s firm determination to <pb facs="0928" n="1436" xml:id="pg_1436"/> accord even-handed
                                justice to both Jews and Arabs. While admittedly neither side will
                                receive under Bernadotte plan all that it desires, Jewish statesmen
                                must realize that in any viable political settlement concessions
                                must be made by both sides, To US Govt it would accordingly seem to
                                be the course of wisdom for <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> to
                                accept or acquiesce in Bernadotte’s territorial recommendations,
                                confident that once a basis for peaceful development has thus been
                                established Jewish State will achieve its additional objectives such
                                as a trade route to the Orient or peaceful commercial access to the
                                Dead Sea by only sure means to make possible attainment of these
                                goals: friendly agreement between neighboring peoples, both Arab and
                                Jewish, founded on mutual accommodation and interest. In
                                consequence, this Govt believes that, taking Bernadotte plan as a
                                whole, Israel stands materially to benefit.</item>
                            <item>“4. As for pretensions of <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> to
                                extension of its authority to include the greater part of Jerusalem,
                                US Govt is convinced that recommendations of Mediator which are in
                                effect identical to those recommended by UN <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> in its resolution of Nov 29, 1947, afford most
                                equitable settlement of Jerusalem problem. This Govt, while
                                sympathetic to views of both Arab and Jewish Govts regarding their
                                respective communities in the Holy City, nevertheless must look to
                                worldwide interest in preservation of Jerusalem and its ready access
                                to persons of all three religious faiths who regard Jerusalem as a
                                central and symbolic point. Accordingly this govt does not believe
                                that <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> should control part of
                                Jerusalem or that it should have a corridor to that city.
                                Conclusions in Bernadotte Plan specifically providing for right of
                                unimpaired access to Jerusalem by rail, road and air would seem in
                                our opinion to obviate any need for a Jewish corridor.</item>
                            <item>“5. <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> should be prompt to
                                recognize advantages to it of Bernadotte’s conclusion in 4(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) which provides for special assurance that
                                new frontiers of Israel shall remain inviolate. These assurances
                                should be of particular value to the small Jewish State as affording
                                a bulwark against possible pressure from the vast Arab world. This
                                govt believes that under UN charter not only shall all members of UN
                                settle their international disputes by peaceful means and shall
                                refrain in their international relations from threat or use of force
                                against territorial integrity or political independence of any State
                                (Art. 2, Para. 3 and 4), but the organization shall ensure that
                                States which are not members of UN act in accordance with these
                                principles. There is therefore a Charter obligation to respect
                                territorial integrity of existing States. If new frontier in
                                Palestine can be demarcated on <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                                recommendation and with acquiescence of the parties this frontier
                                will automatically be protected by Charter articles cited above.
                                Furthermore this Govt has many times made clear its unequivocal view
                                that <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> has responsibility to prevent
                                recourse to force to settle international differences. US in future
                                will insist in <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> that any recourse
                                to hostilities from either side in Palestine situation be opposed if
                                necessary by action under Chapter VII.</item>
                            <item>“6. Although we are cognizant of fact that <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> would prefer direct peace negotiations with Arab
                                Govts, Arab experts of <gloss target="#t_PGI1">PGI</gloss> will
                                undoubtedly have themselves informed their Govt that under present
                                    <pb facs="0929" n="1437" xml:id="pg_1437"/> emotional stress it
                                is most unlikely that Arab leaders will agree to enter into such
                                negotiations. Accordingly it seems to us that Bernadotte plan with
                                backing of UN Assembly and <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> affords
                                a ready instrument for achieving those conditions of peace and tacit
                                agreement which are indispensable to peaceful development of Jewish
                                State.”</item>
                        </list>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>You should in your contacts with them leave no doubt in minds of any responsible
                    statesmen in Israel that US Govt and people believe that Mediator has left a
                    legacy to the world of a workable solution of Palestine problem. In consequence
                    this govt has a duty to use its utmost endeavor as member of UN and as loyal
                    friend of Israel to see that Bernadotte plan is placed into effect.</p>
                <p>Sent Tel Aviv for action as ________, repeated for info to Paris for <gloss target="#t_GADel1">Gadel</gloss> as _________, London as ______, Cairo as
                    ________.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
