<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The United States Representative at the United Nations ( (Austin) ) to the
                    Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d676</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">676</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-10-18T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-10-18T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHjbB9I2rxR2aku" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092807"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Notification</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-10-18T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-10-18T17:00:00-05:00" n="676"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d676">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/10–1848: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Representative at the United Nations</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Austin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                        </gloss>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-10-18T23:00:00+01:00"
                            >October 18, 1948—11 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 387. Fawzi Bey approached us urgently
                    this afternoon on the following matter and said he considered it important
                    enough to take <pb facs="0984" n="1492" xml:id="pg_1492"/> up with the Secretary
                    or acting head of our delegation. He requested a prompt expression of our
                    view.</p>
                <p>Fawzi said it was clear to the Egyptian Government that the Jews had unlawfully,
                    in violation of the truce, taken the initiative in military activity in the
                    Negev during the past few days.<note n="1" xml:id="d676fn1">For cablegrams of
                        October 15 and 16 from Acting Egyptian Foreign Minister Ibrahim Dessuky
                        Abaza to Secretary-General Lie concerning alleged violations of the truce by
                        Israeli forces, see <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">3rd
                            yr., Supplement for October 1948</hi>, p. 54. For the texts of the
                        letters of October 8 and October 18 from Mr. Eban to the President of the
                        Security Council concerning alleged violations of the truce by Arab forces,
                        see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 50, 63.</note> He explained that
                    whether it was a convoy or not it was certainly not a convoy in the UN sense
                    because there had been no notification of any such convoy to UN authorities and
                    UN authorities had certainly not accompanied such convoy. He also said that the
                    Israelis had in any event bombed Egyptian installations.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d676fn2">Foreign Minister Abaza in discussing with an officer of the
                        American Embassy on October 18, the alleged Egyptian refusal to permit
                        Israeli convoys to traverse lines to beleaguered settlements in Negev, “did
                        not deny Egyptian halting of convoy but stated that Egyptians had offered to
                        discuss problem of re-victualing the settlements. The Jews had, however,
                        answered by armed attack.” (Telegram 1504, October 20, 10 a. m., from Cairo,
                        867N.01/10–2048)</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the circumstances, Fawzi wanted to know what action the Government of the US
                    would take. We asked if he intended to imply unilateral action by the US. He
                    replied that the questions for us to decide were whether we would take any
                    action and if we were prepared to take action whether it would be unilateral or
                    in support of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> action.</p>
                <p>Fawzi went on to say that paper resolutions were turning out to serve very little
                    purpose. It would not be enough for the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> merely
                    to pass another such resolution. He recalled that the July 15 resolution
                    provided for consideration of further action by the <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss> under Chapter VII in the event either party violated the truce
                    laid down in that resolution.</p>
                <p>It is essential for us to make at least some interim reply to Fawzi, particularly
                    since <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> is meeting Tuesday morning at urgent
                    suggestion of Acting Mediator to consider report from him on last days events in
                    Negev area, including his request to both parties for an immediate
                        cease-fire.<note n="3" xml:id="d676fn3">For the text of Mr. Bunche’s report
                        of October 18, see <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, <hi rend="italic">3rd
                            yr., Supplement for October 1948</hi>, p. 55.</note> In this connection,
                    Bunche has talked with Egyptian and Israeli foreign ministers here, but at late
                    hour this afternoon they had not received replies from their governments.</p>
                <p>We planned to say to Fawzi that we have reported his inquiry to the Department
                    and that we feel this inquiry must be considered in the light of the Acting
                    Mediator’s report and consideration of this report by the <gloss target="#t_SC1"
                        >SC</gloss>.<note n="4" xml:id="d676fn4">The Department, in reply on October
                        19, stated: “You should tell Fawzi Bey US will of course continue to act
                        within framework UN and will not take unilateral action re present military
                        activity in Negev (<gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 387). Dept
                        approves action outlined last para <gloss target="#t_urtel1">urtel</gloss>.”
                        (Telegram <gloss target="#t_GADel1">Gadel</gloss> 247, 501.BB
                        Palestine/10–1848)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Austin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
