<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-12-08T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-12-08T19:00:00-05:00" n="820" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d820">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/12–948: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Acting Chairman of the United States Delegation at
                                Paris</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dulles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret   urgent</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <gloss target="#t_niact1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">niact</hi>
                                </gloss>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-12-09T01:00:00+01:00">December
                                    9, 1948—1 a. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_Delga1">Delga</gloss> 1122. Following is situation
                            regarding plenary <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> action on Palestine
                            resolution: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>A group of members including Australia, New Zealand, Canada,
                                    China and possibly others will introduce certain amendments in
                                    plenary session to Committee I Palestine resolution to make it
                                    possible to obtain broadest possible support for such
                                    resolution. These amendments, which will be supported by US and
                                    UK, are as follows: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Delete all of the preamble of the present Committee I
                                            resolution and substitute therefor the following:
                                            “Having considered further the situation in
                                            Palestine”</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Delete sub-paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) which
                                            contains a specific reference to the State of
                                            Israel.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Delete paragraph 3 containing an unpopular formula for
                                            selection of conciliation commission.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Delete last clause of paragraph 10 beginning “in this
                                            connection”; Arabs insist upon this deletion because of
                                            its reference to Bernadotte report despite fact content
                                            is in Arab interest.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Delete first clause paragraph 11 for same
                                            reason.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Arabs are expected to insist that reference to
                                            November 29 resolution contained in paragraph 8 be
                                            deleted and boundaries be indicated by reference to
                                            geographical localities.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Our best available information is that these amendments will
                                    make it possible for Arab States to abstain rather than vote
                                    against and that Middle East and Far East friends of Arabs will
                                    vote affirmalively <pb facs="1149" n="1657" xml:id="pg_1657"/>
                                    for resulting resolution. These changes are also believed to be
                                    acceptable to Israel.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Department’s attention is invited to fact that course of
                                    discussions on Palestine resolution has clearly indicated that
                                    both Arabs and Jews seek straightforward conciliation effort and
                                    object to any effort by present assembly to be specific about
                                    the details of final settlement. Although Jews and Arabs differ
                                    widely in their ultimate objectives, they now appear to agree
                                    upon conciliation as method of settling such
                                    difficulties.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>We do not expect strong Jewish reaction in Paris against
                                    deletion of sub-paragraph 2 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)
                                    containing specific reference to State of Israel, but some
                                    ill-informed press sources in US may give such deletion wrong
                                    interpretation. <gloss target="#t_USGADel1">USGADel</gloss> has
                                    told Committee I that we do not seek an. Assembly resolution
                                    which represents in every respect US policy on Palestine but
                                    rather a resolution which we believe will contribute most to a
                                    peaceful settlement of outstanding differences. In this sense,
                                    we have specifically discouraged introduction into resolution of
                                    question of recognition of Israel or of approval of Israel
                                    membership, while at same time reaffirming US policy these
                                    points both in <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Deletion of present provision for election of conciliation
                                    commission by Big Five is necessary to overcome objections on
                                    part of middle and small powers against “undemocratic”
                                    procedure. Commission will probably be selected by ordinary
                                    election by Assembly (simple majority) following adoption
                                    Palestine resolution. Since US is being treated as a candidate,
                                        <gloss target="#t_USGADel1">USGADel</gloss> is not taking
                                    active part in selection of commission but we have indicated
                                    that commission consisting of Australia, Turkey, and US, or
                                    alternatively France, Turkey and US, would be acceptable to us.
                                    There appears to be overwhelming sentiment in Assembly, shared
                                    both by Jews and Arabs, that US must be member of conciliation
                                    commission.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dulles</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>