<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Chairman of the
                        Delegation at Paris (Dulles)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p2</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d828</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">828</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-12-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="828" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d828">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/12–1348</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Acting Chairman of the
                        Delegation at Paris</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dulles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-12-13">December 13,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top #nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Riad Bey Solh, Prime Minister of
                            Lebanon</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. Malik</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Dulles</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>On Monday, December 13th, the Prime Minister of Lebanon and Dr. Malik came to
                    call upon me at the Hotel Crillon. I expressed to him my satisfaction that the
                    Palestine Resolution had been adopted. I said I realized that the Arab States
                    could, if they had wanted, have prevented the adoption of the Resolution by the
                    necessary two-thirds. Of course, the Arab States themselves had voted against
                    the Resolution, but I knew that states friendly to the Arabs had voted for the
                    Resolution. I interpreted this as indicative of a spirit of conciliation on the
                    part of the Arab States, which I thought augured well for the future. I did not,
                    however, ask that the Prime Minister should comment on this aspect of the matter
                    unless he so desired.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister said that he was quite glad to discuss this aspect of the
                    matter. It was true that the Arab States could have defeated the Palestine
                    Resolution at any time up to five minutes before the vote. They had decided not
                    to do so and their decision had in considerable part been influenced by the talk
                    which I had with him and by the hope I had held out that if once the Israel
                    matter could be settled, that would mean an era of good relations, rather than
                    increasingly bad relations, with the Arab States.</p>
                <p>I said that the result of the vote had made me feel under a greater obligation
                    than ever to try to assure the result that I had forecast as possible and that I
                    would, upon my return, report our conversation to the President.</p>
                <pb facs="1157" n="1665" xml:id="pg_1665"/>
                <p>The Prime Minister said that he hoped that the matter of Palestine would be
                    disposed of first and the question of relations between the United States and
                    Arab States dealt with only subsequently, not combining the two ideas.</p>
                <p>There followed an exchange of courtesies.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
