<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by Mr. Robert M.
                            McClintock to the Under Secretary of State (
                        Lovett
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1948v05p2</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d83</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">83</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1948-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1948-03-09T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1948-03-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-03-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="83" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">501.BB Palestine/3–948</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Robert M.
                            McClintock</persName> to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lovett</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1948-03-09">March 9,
                            1948</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>Three telegrams<note n="1" xml:id="d83fn1">Presumably telegrams 122, 125, and
                        172, immediately following.</note> are attached for your signature pursuant
                    to our conversation this morning.</p>
                <p>I talked to Mr. Rusk at 11:25 a. m., by telephone. Fortunately <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> had arrived at the same conclusions as we,
                    and Mr. Rusk has already had conversations with Mr. Tsiang of China and M. de
                    Rose of France in which general agreement was reached on the need for
                    interrogating the parties. The French and Chinese were pleased with our proposed
                    questions and Tsiang expressed the opinion that they went to the core of the
                    problem.</p>
                <p>I suggested to Mr. Rusk that for the record an effort should be made again to
                    invite Gromyko to participate and that we hoped that the <pb facs="0191" n="701" xml:id="pg_701"/> interrogatories would be conducted by the Big Three as a
                    group and not separately.</p>
                <p>I drew to Mr. Rusk’s attention the article on Page 3 of this morning’s <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, in which the legal experts of the UN
                    Secretariat are quoted as affirming the legal authority of the Security Council
                    to partition Palestine by force, as well as establishing the opinion that the UN
                    Palestine Commission “will become the legally constituted government of
                    Palestine after Britain surrenders the mandate on May 15.” Mr. Rusk said that
                    this was a working paper which had been asked for by the Palestine Commission
                    and that it was dated February 3. Secretary-General Lie had, however, submitted
                    it informally to members of the Security Council yesterday.</p>
                <p>I commented that it was most unfortunate for the public impression to get around
                    that the UN Secretariat had prepared a refutation of Senator Austin’s statement
                    of February 24, to say nothing of rendering an opinion on the question of who
                    had responsibility for Palestine after May 15. I suggested that Mr. Lie had
                    better set the record straight as to the date and origin of this paper and that
                    we might wish to inform Mr. Lie, since he had comunicated to us as a member of
                    the Council, that we did not concur in his legal opinion.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rusk said we should not be surprised to see press accounts quoting “a Russian
                    spokesman” to the effect that the Soviet Union will advocate that the Security
                    Council implement by force, if necessary, the partition plan. The “Russian
                    spokesman” is Mr. Gromyko.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
