<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-11-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="150" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Executive Order No. 3360–A, November 29, 1920,
                                    Canceling Cable Permit Issued to the Deutsch-Atlantische
                                    Telegraphengesellschaft</hi><note n="20" xml:id="d150fn20">Copies of this order were communicated, Nov. 29, to the
                                    delegations to the Conference.</note></head>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1920-11-29">November 29, 1920</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi> the Deutsch-Atlantische
                                Telegraphengesellschaft, a German corporation having its principal
                                office and place of business at Cologne, Germany, was granted a
                                permit by the President of the United States, dated May 27, 1899,
                                whereby said Company was granted permission to lay, construct, land,
                                maintain and operate telegraphic lines or cables on the Atlantic
                                coast of the United States to connect Borkum-Emden, Germany, and the
                                City of New York, touching at the Azores, upon certain conditions
                                which had been accepted by the Company in a letter dated May 13,
                                    1899;<note n="21" xml:id="d150fn21">For correspondence regarding
                                    the issuance of the cable permit to the Deutsch-Atlantische
                                    Telegraphengesellschaft, see <ref target="frus1899#pg_310"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1899, pp.
                                        310</ref> ff.</note> and</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi> the said Deutsch-Atlantische
                                Telegraphengesellschaft thereafter laid two cables as aforesaid,
                                upon the conditions set forth in said permit; and</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi> the said cables were cut in May,
                                1915, between the United States and the Azores, and were thereby
                                rendered useless for communication purposes, and a portion of one of
                                said cables was thereafter removed and transferred to Halifax,
                                Canada, by the British authorities, and the other cable is
                                temporarily in the possession of the French Government, and a permit
                                issued on August 23, 1917, authorized a change in the landing point
                                of this cable so that it lands at Manhattan Beach, Long Island, New
                                York; and</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi> it is desirable to cancel the
                                permit issued to the Deutsch-Atlantische Telegraphengesellschaft on
                                May 27, 1899, since operation of cables laid under it has ceased;
                                and</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi> said permit of May 27, 1899,
                                provided in Article XI for its revocation and termination in the
                                following terms: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“That the consent hereby granted shall be subject to any
                                        future action by the Congress or by the President,
                                        affirming, revoking or modifying, wholly or in part, the
                                        said conditions and terms on which said permission is
                                        given.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>Now, <hi rend="smallcaps">therefore</hi>, I, Woodrow Wilson, by
                                virtue of the authority vested in me as President of the United
                                States, and in accordance with the provision contained in Article XI
                                of the said permit of May 27, 1899, hereby revoke, cancel, annul and
                                terminate the said permit issued to the Deutsch-Atlantische
                                Telegraphengesellschaft on May 27, 1899, and declare that hereafter
                                it is null and void and of no effect whatsoever.</p>
                            <pb facs="0240" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/>
                            <p>This Order is made without prejudice to applications that may
                                hereafter be filed by German concerns. The permit issued by me on
                                August 23, 1917, to the French Government shall not be affected by
                                this order.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Woodrow
                                Wilson</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>