<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-06-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-06-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="411" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d411">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">711.428/597</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Geddes</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-06-19"><hi rend="italic">June 19,
                                        1920</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                                the receipt of your note No. 354, of June 10, 1920, relative to the
                                signature of the proposed treaty between the United States and Great
                                Britain concerning port privileges of foreign vessels, lobster
                                fishing, halibut fishing, and the tariff on fresh fish, and to
                                inform you that a communication dated June 11, 1920,<note n="8" xml:id="d411fn8">Not printed.</note> has been received from
                                Senator W. L. Jones, of the State of Washington, in which it is
                                stated that he expects to forward a communication within a few days
                                giving his position with reference to this treaty.</p>
                            <p>As it appears desirable to meet, if possible, any objections which
                                may be advanced by Senator Jones, it seems advisable to postpone the
                                signing of the proposed treaty until these objections can be given
                                careful consideration.</p>
                            <p>As regards the matter of the publication of the report of the
                                International Fisheries Commission, I have the honor to state that
                                this matter has been referred to the appropriate authority of this
                                Government, with a request for a statement of his views concerning
                                it. Upon receipt of a reply I shall not fail to communicate with you
                                again.</p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Bainbridge
                                Colby</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>