<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Quarterly Report of the Legation in China for the Period July 1–September 30,
                    1920</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d470</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">470</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-09-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081635"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Martial law</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041551"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Election law</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recBTfVgprHsl1J9K" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85047074"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Famine</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-09-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="470"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d470">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">693.00/3787</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Report of the Legation in China for the Period July
                        1–September 30, 1920</hi>
                    <note n="41" xml:id="d470fn41">Enclosure to despatch no. 778, Jan. 26, 1921,
                        from the Minister in China; received Mar. 9, 1921.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        from="1920-07-01" to="1920-09-30" type="content-date">undated</date>
                </dateline>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Political—Domestic</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The events which led up to the most important political change in this
                    quarter—the downfall of the Anfu clique in Peking—may be said to have had their
                    actual beginning in the withdrawal of General Wu Pei Fu together with his Third
                    Division from their station at Hengchow in Hunan to return to Chihli, their home
                    station, the latter part of May. The motives leading to General Wu’s withdrawal
                    to Chihli Province are many and complicated but a <hi rend="italic">résumé</hi>
                    of some of the more important will throw some light upon the general political
                    situation, as well as upon the character of General Wu who has stood out in
                    striking contrast to the majority of Chinese military officials. In the spring
                    of 1918 General Wu, acting under orders <pb facs="0559" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"
                    /> from his superior Tsao Kun, Tuchun of Chihli Province, had gone to Hunan and
                    recaptured Yochow and Changsha from the South and established himself in the
                    province. Instead of receiving appointment as Tuchun of Hunan to which it would
                    seem he was entitled, this position was given to General Chang Ching-yao, an
                    adherent of Tuan Chi-jui, and a notoriously corrupt and vicious official, who
                    had rendered no aid in recapturing Hunan for the North, and who administered his
                    position in such a manner as to best enrich himself at the expense of the
                    province, particularly the northern portion where he was established. General Wu
                    had conducted himself in a way to gain the admiration of the natives in the
                    southern portion of the province, where he was established and actually held
                    Hunan against the South. For ten months prior to his withdrawal to Chihli,
                    General Wu had received no funds from the Central Government for payment of his
                    Third Division troops. The Anfu Club which controlled the administration of the
                    central government in Peking was indulging in a saturnalia of corruption
                    unequaled since the establishment of the Republic and perhaps seeing their star
                    declining were engaged in a most energetic absorption of loans and government
                    revenues, and no funds were available for any except their actual adherents of
                    which Wu Pei-fu was not one. What funds were given by the central government for
                    troops in Hunan were sent to the corrupt Anfu adherent, Chang Ching-yao. The
                    latter also allowed no more of the provincial revenues to be utilized by General
                    Wu than those received from the territory in which General Wu was actually in
                    control. In the meantime a movement had arisen in Hunan directed against Chang
                    Ching-yao and his regime of despoliation. The cry was “Hunan for the Hunanese”.
                    General Tan Yen-kai, classed as an adherent of the South, was the military
                    leader of the movement. General Wu, disgusted with the attitude of the central
                    government and sympathizing with the desire of the natives of Hunan to rid
                    themselves of Chang Ching-yao had secured the permission of his chief Tsao Kun
                    to withdraw to Chihli, the ostensible reason at first given being the
                    non-payment of the troops by the Central government. It is also asserted on good
                    authority that General Wu had privately negotiated with General Tan Yen-kai,
                    sympathized with his aims of driving out General Chang, and arrived at an
                    understanding with the Southern general. It is stated that General Wu received
                    $600,000 from the South for his withdrawal, and while this is undoubtedly true,
                    his friends point out that it was disbursed to his troops whose pay was months
                    in arrears, and [for] whom according to Chinese custom, the provincial revenues
                    were looked [to] to provide a large share of payment.</p>
                <p>On May 25 General Wu started the withdrawal of his troops from Hangchow, and
                    distributed them at strategic points on the Peking-Hankow <pb facs="0560"
                        n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/> line, thus rendering impossible any probable aid
                    reaching Chang Ching Yao from the North. Meantime General Wu openly announced
                    his intention of checking and destroying the Anfu activities in Peking [and] in
                    view of subsequent events it must be said in fairness to General Wu in this move
                    he was actuated chiefly by patriotic motives and that the destruction of the
                    Anfu party in Peking was the leading object of his withdrawal to Chihli. As had
                    been expected, as soon as General Wu had retired from Hunan, Tuchun Chang was
                    attacked from the south by General Tan Yen Kai. The troops of General Chang
                    Ching-yao, a large portion of which existed only on paper for pay-roll purposes,
                    rapidly gave way. By the middle of June Changsha had fallen to the Southern
                    troops, Chang Ching-yao had withdrawn to Yochow, and a mandate was issued
                    sternly ordering him to defend the province against the advances of the southern
                    forces, and stripping him of his titles of Tuchun and Acting Civil Governor, but
                    allowing him to remain in charge to direct the battle. It was on June 13th,
                    1920, during this occupation of Yochow by Chang Ching-yao, that Wm. A. Reimert,
                    an American missionary of the Reformed Church Mission at Yochow, was shot down
                    in cold blood on the mission premises, by an officer and squad of soldiers
                    belonging to Chang Ching-yao’s forces. This occurred after repeated and
                    unavailing requests for protection had been addressed to General Chang by the
                    mission, Chang admitted his personal responsibility for the murder of Reimert,
                    and personally paid a solatium of $45,000 to the family of the deceased, but up
                    to the present has not been further punished, the Central Government holding
                    that the Mandate of June 13th, 1920 stripping Chang of official rank is
                    inclusive in its nature and a punishment for all his crimes as Tuchun of Hunan.
                    This view is being strongly opposed by the Legation, which is pressing for
                    adequate punishment of Chang Ching-yao.</p>
                <p>By the end of June Yochow had fallen, and Chang Ching-yao’s troops had withdrawn
                    and fled from Hunan, and the latter had fled to foreign concession in Hankow,
                    though ordered to Peking by mandate for an accounting. Hunan was again in the
                    hands of the South, or rather of the Hunanese.</p>
                <p>By this time it was realized in Peking that the Anfuites must either submit to
                    being curbed or come into conflict with Wu Pei-fu, who had established his
                    headquarters at Paotingfu where he was conferring with his chief, Tsao Kun, whom
                    he had apparently won over to his beliefs.</p>
                <p>Near the end of June Chang Tso-lin, Governor General of Manchuria, had come to
                    Peking with a bodyguard of troops, to act as mediator between the Anfu group and
                    the Chihli party. He conferred <pb facs="0561" n="463" xml:id="pg_463"/> with
                    the President, Tuan Chi-jui and “Little” Hsu (General Hsu Shu-cheng, the
                    powerful leader of the Anfu clique), and then went to Paotingfu for a conference
                    with Tsao Kun and Wu Pei-fu, where he apparently entered into an agreement to
                    support them in the event of an open conflict with the Anfu group, led by Tuan
                    Chi-jui and “Little” Hsu. On his return to Peking he again conferred with the
                    President and Tuan, presenting the demands of the Chihli Party for the removal
                    of “Little” Hsu and the reorganization of the government, consisting of the
                    elimination of the Anfu members of the cabinet, and the dismissal of both
                    Parliaments (northern and southern) and the settlement of the parliamentary
                    question as well as of unification and other national questions by a popular
                    convention. On July 4 a presidential mandate was issued relieving General Hsu
                    Shu-cheng of his post as Commissioner for Frontier Development in the
                    Northwestern Regions (Mongolia), as well as abolishing the post of commandant of
                    the Frontier Defense Force, removing the latter from Tuan’s control and placing
                    it under the direct authority of the Ministry of War. For the moment it looked
                    as if the Anfu Club were routed, and that in the new cabinet, whose organization
                    was mooted, it would strive to retain only the most lucrative posts of Minister
                    of Communications and Minister of Finance for its members, in order to insure to
                    itself adequate revenues. However, it was reported that Tuan was insisting that
                    Wu Pei-fu should be punished for his interference in politics, and it was not to
                    be expected that the astute, ambitious and courageous “Little” Hsu, than whom no
                    man was more feared in Peking, would calmly submit to being stripped of his
                    power, although he had been given the honorary rank of Generalissimo, or
                    Marshal, which carried no office but a salary.</p>
                <p>Finding Tuan in no mood for compromise, Chang Tso-lin, left Peking in the
                    direction of Mukden, it being understood that he had ordered two of his
                    divisions from Mukden and Fengtien to entrain for Shanhaikwan. Tuan Chi-jui was
                    concentrating his troops at Nanyuan near Peking, and trying to induce the
                    President to dismiss Wu Pei-fu. Then troops were thrown about the President’s
                    palace to “protect” him and, acting under coercion from Tuan and “Little” Hsu,
                    the President placed his seal on a mandate on July 9th cashiering General Wu
                    Pei-fu, stripping him of his offices and decorations and also depriving General
                    Tsao Kun of his rank but allowing him to retain his office and command. From
                    that time until the routing of the Anfu forces the President remained a prisoner
                    in his palace, subject to the demands of Tuan and “Little” Hsu. On July 8th, the
                    Diplomatic Corps handed a note to the Chinese Government<note n="42"
                        xml:id="d470fn42">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_456">p. 456</ref>.</note>
                    expressing their confidence in the President and trusting in <pb facs="0562"
                        n="464" xml:id="pg_464"/> him to protect foreigners and their property and
                    deprecating fighting in Peking or the bombing of the city by aeroplane, which
                    had been threatened by the Anfuites. Both sides began threatening movements of
                    troops—Tuan and “Little” Hsu toward Paotingfu and Wu Pei-fu and Tsao Kun toward
                    Peking. Chang Tso-lin had moved some of his troops within the wall at
                    Shanhaikwan, and was threatening Tuan with “armed” mediation if he did not come
                    to terms, but until the last moment it remained doubtful if Chang would remain
                    neutral or would really throw his troops into armed conflict on the side of Tsao
                    Kun and Wu Pei-fu. It may be seriously questioned if Chang Tso-lin was actuated
                    in his final decision by any high patriotic motives, but rather it was to his
                    own personal advantage and ambition to join the Chihli party. In the first place
                    he was fighting on the side enjoying popular approval because of its avowed
                    intention of removing the Anfu power, with its pro-Japanese activities, from
                    Peking; but his real motive no doubt was that by joining the Chihli party it
                    offered an opportunity to eliminate from power his envied and feared rival
                    “Little” Hsu, and to add the latter’s sphere of influence Mongolia to his own
                    extensive Manchurian kingdom, as a field for the development and increase of
                    power.</p>
                <p>On July 12th Tsao Kun, Military Governor of Chihli, Chang Tsolin, High Military
                    Commissioner of the Three Eastern Provinces of Fengtien, Wang Chan-yuan,
                    Military Governor of Hupeh, Li Shun, Military Governor of Kiangsu, Ch’en
                    Kuang-yuan, Military Governor of Kiangsi, Chao T’i, Military Governor of Honan,
                    Tsai Cheng-hsun, Tartar General of Suiyuan, Ma Fu-hsiang, Defence Commissioner
                    of Ninghsia, Kansu, issued a public statement denouncing “Little” Hsu, Tuan
                    Chi-jui, the Anfu party and parliament, and declaring their intention of
                    upholding the President to exterminate the traitors and strengthen the country,
                    and appealing for public support of the above officials. Only Chang Tso-lin, and
                    Tsao Kun actually furnished troops for the fighting, and General Wu Pei-fu,
                    being a subordinate of Tsao Kun was not mentioned, but to him must be given the
                    credit of having the initiative and the courage of his convictions to throw down
                    the gauntlet to forces superior to his own and to be ready to actually fight for
                    his conviction of what was right. … As it was, attempts were made at compromise
                    and mediation, but Tsao Kun and Wu Pei-fu remained firm and prepared to contest
                    the troops of the Anfuites. Public opinion as expressed by native commercial and
                    educational bodies was opposed to armed conflict, but after the fight started
                    public sympathy was within Wu Pei-fu and his adherents.</p>
                <p>A mandate forbidding hostilities issued on July 14th was followed by the
                    proclamation of martial law in Peking, the seizure of the <pb facs="0563"
                        n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/> telegraph offices in the city by the Anfuites, the
                    closing of hostile newspapers, and the establishment of a strict censorship
                    favorably inclined toward Anfu. Marshal Tuan issued [a] manifesto putting a
                    price on [the] heads of Tsao Kun and Wu Pei-fu. Railway communication was cut
                    and Peking was isolated. Meantime desultory encounters between the troops of
                    Marshal Tuan and “Little” Hsu and those of Tsao Kun and General Wu were
                    occurring in the vicinity of Chochow and Paotingfu, with at first gains reported
                    for the Anfuites, but it soon became apparent that the troops of General Wu
                    though less well equipped than those of the opposition, who possessed liberal
                    quantities of arms and ammunitions, some of Japanese and Italian origin, had
                    greater efficiency in action and morale and in addition more aggressive
                    leadership. Under Tuan were the two mixed brigades of the Frontier Defense
                    Force, totalling about 30,000 and in addition the 9th, 13th and 15th divisions,
                    the loyalty of the latter being doubtful. Under Wu Pei-fu were his Third
                    Division and two brigades brought from Hunan, and Tsao Kun had two brigades in
                    and around Paotingfu. Tuan had moved his 13th and 15th divisions toward Chochow,
                    about 50 miles south of Peking, where a portion of them came into conflict with
                    the troops of General Wu.</p>
                <p>Inspired reports of overwhelming victory for the Anfu forces were circulated in
                    Peking, and a mandate was issued by the President ordering the troops to cease
                    fighting and withdraw to their former stations. At first this was interpreted as
                    a move to allow the Chihli party gracefully to withdraw without loss of face
                    after their defeat, but the real news soon leaked through that Tuan’s forces had
                    been outmaneuvered and defeated by General Wu, and the mandate then appeared in
                    the light of a cover for Tuan to retire. Toward the east the mixed Brigades of
                    the Frontier Defence Force had been employed, and had gained a small victory by
                    capturing Yangtsun from an inferior Chihli force, but with the advent of Chang
                    Tsolin’s two divisions from the north, well-equipped with Japanese arms and
                    munitions, the Anfu forces after several skirmishes began to withdraw and
                    desert, fleeing toward Peking.</p>
                <p>During this encounter on the Peking-Mukden Railway, train service between Peking
                    and Tientsin had been interrupted by the military, but was re-established by an
                    allied military expedition from Tientsin, who repaired the torn track, and the
                    opposing parties promised to abide by the provisions of the Boxer protocol and
                    to refrain from interrupting rail communication between Peking and Tientsin.</p>
                <p>Lacking effective leadership in the field, with a broken-down commissariat, and
                    with little stomach for fighting for their pro-Japanese superiors, the Anfu
                    troops were rapidly withdrawn toward Peking; <pb facs="0564" n="466"
                        xml:id="pg_466"/> the city gates were closed to prevent their entry, and
                    there was a cessation of actual fighting. The troops of Chang Tso-lin and Wu
                    Pei-fu moved forward to encircle Peking, to disband the enemy, and to await for
                    negotiations with the vanquished Tuan, and his party. There was a disposition on
                    the Chihli side not to exact any penalty from Tuan who was looked upon as the
                    venerable old man and teacher of most of the Chihli generals, and the blame for
                    the Anfu activities was placed largely upon his subordinates, particularly
                    “Little” Hsu.</p>
                <p>On July 27th a mandate was issued cancelling the order to degrade and punish
                    Generals Tsao Kun and Wu Pei-fu, owing to “extenuating circumstances”
                    conflicting with the previous mandate. On the 28th followed three mandates—one
                    accepting the resignation of Tuan Chi-jui, another placing all the troops of the
                    Frontier Defence Force under the control of the Ministry of War, and a third
                    instructing the Ministry of War immediately to disband the Frontier Defense
                    Force, including General Hsu Shu-Cheng’s four brigades of Northwest Frontier
                    (Mongolia) Defence troops. It was known that a fourth mandate had been prepared
                    ordering the arrest of the leaders of the Anfu group, but this had been
                    anticipated by these leaders who were now engaged in a mad scramble seeking the
                    safety of the hotels, homes and Legations of the Legation quarter, the Anfu
                    members of the cabinet having despatched their resignations. The Diplomatic Body
                    had met on the 28th to consider the right of asylum in the Legation quarter, at
                    which the British, French and American Minister[s] announced their intention of
                    notifying their nations not to harbor Chinese fugitives, but in this the
                    Japanese Minister refused to concur.</p>
                <p>The issue of the mandate for the arrest of ten of the Anfu leaders the seizure of
                    the Anfu Club, the search of members’ houses, and the closing of their
                    propaganda organs, marked the final downfall of this pro-Japanese clique, who
                    during their regime had borrowed between Y. 300,000,000 and $400,000,000
                    bartering many available resources or sovereign rights of the country. Some of
                    this money was spent in furthering the private aims of the Anfuites and their
                    masters, but large quantities adhered to the fingers of the various members of
                    the Anfu Club. …</p>
                <p>It is an interesting commentary on the workings of the central government that
                    after the downfall of the Anfu Club the Waichiaopu issued a public statement
                    washing its hands of any loans made during the past few years, asserting that
                    most of those concluded had been negotiated and signed without its knowledge and
                    approval.</p>
                <p>Although the troops of Li Shun, Tuchun of Kiangsu, took no active part in the
                    conflict between the Anfu-Chihli parties, and his soldiers <pb facs="0565"
                        n="467" xml:id="pg_467"/> were not sent out of the province, the important
                    part that he played in this conflict must be mentioned. Animated by a desire to
                    destroy the “traitors” at Peking and to attain a real unification of the country
                    followed by the establishment of a stable central government, his
                    representatives from the first had been in touch with Generals Tsao Kun and Wu
                    Pei-fu. Occupying as he did a strategic position in the Yangtze Valley and
                    having at his command seasoned and loyal troops, he was able to preserve peace
                    in the entire Valley and prevent any assistance being rendered to the Anfuites
                    from Central or South China, Anhui Province, whose Tuchun Ni Ssu-chung had left
                    the province just before the Anfu-Chihli embroglio to recuperate at Pehtaiho and
                    Tientsin from illness, was a stronghold of Anfuism, many of the members of the
                    Anfu Club coming from Anhui. Military headquarters for Anhui had been
                    established at Pengpu, a strategic point on the Tientsin-Pukow Railway line, and
                    from there it would have been possible to despatch troops to attack Wu Pei-fu in
                    the rear, but as the troops of Li Shun commanded a portion of the line above
                    Pengpu (Anhui) and his attitude was well known no attempt was made to render aid
                    to Anfu from this quarter. Li Shun was also in a position to attack Shantung
                    from the rear if any serious attempt should have been made by Ma Liang (Defense
                    Commissioner in Shantung and pro-Anfu) to render aid to his group. To the south
                    was Chekiang, in which Lu Yung-hsiang a Tuan-Chi-jui adherent, was Tuchun.</p>
                <p>It is not believed that he had any serious intention of aiding the Anfu group in
                    the conflict, but Ho Feng-lin, who was Defense Commissioner of Shanghai and in
                    charge of the Arsenal there had just before the conflict been transferred by
                    mandate from the authority of General Lu of Chekiang under the direct authority
                    of Li Shun, by which the latter hoped to gain control of the Arsenal. This was
                    resented by Ho Feng-lin, as well as General Lu, and at the beginning of the
                    trouble in the North, both sides advanced troops along the Shanghai-Nanking
                    Railway, cutting the line and holding up traffic, and for a few days it looked
                    as though a conflict would result, but as the movements of troops seem to have
                    been ordered by subordinates without the direct knowledge of either General, and
                    as neither had inclination or any good reason for fighting, the troops along the
                    railway were withdrawn by mutual agreement.</p>
                <p>Li Shun had also obtained evidence that Wang I-tang the Northern Peace Delegate
                    at Shanghai and an Anfu appointee, was sending agents <hi rend="italic"
                        >provocateurs</hi> into the province to stir up trouble, and issued an order
                    for his arrest. Wang denied the charge but with the downfall of Anfu his name
                    was among the supplementary “traitors” ordered to be arrested by Presidential
                    mandate, and he fled to Japan, leaving the North without a peace delegate for
                    the time being.</p>
                <pb facs="0566" n="468" xml:id="pg_468"/>
                <p>The Peking Government having been purged of the Anfu clique it remained to be
                    seen what sort of a settlement would be made by the victorious generals who were
                    in a position to dictate terms, and to see what attitude would be adopted toward
                    the popular program which General Wu Pei-fu had championed, viz., the calling of
                    a representative citizens’ convention to solve such problems as the drafting of
                    a Constitution, the organization of a new parliament, together with the
                    unification of the North and South, abrogation of the Sino-Japanese Military
                    Pact, and the disbandment of troops. It soon became apparent that Chang Tso-lin
                    intended to claim chief credit for the victory and to impose such a settlement
                    as would meet with his wishes without regard for those of General Wu. In a
                    statement to foreign correspondents on July 26th at his headquarters he stated
                    when asked his opinion of General Wu:</p>
                <p>“I deal with Tsao Kun only. General Wu is only chief of a division. Men of that
                    rank can hardly deal in politics, for there are many divisional commanders in
                    the land.”</p>
                <p>A Presidential Mandate appeared appointing the new acting cabinet composed as
                    follows: Chin Yun-peng as Premier and Minister of War; Chang Chih-tan, Interior;
                    Wang Nai-pin, Agriculture, Admiral Sah, Navy (non-party); W. W. Yen, Foreign
                    Office (nonparty); Tung Keng, Justice, Fan Yuan-lien, Education (said to be
                    Chinputang); Chow Tze-chi, Finance; Yeh Kung-cho, Communications (Chiaotung).
                    The most important portfolios, War, Interior, Finance and Communications were
                    regarded as going to men who were the choice of Chang Tso-lin, and the Premier
                    was known to be a close friend and adherent. For this cabinet it may be said
                    that in ability it surpassed any since the establishment of the Republic and for
                    this reason much was [<hi rend="italic">has</hi>] been expected from it in
                    different quarters; but it must be pointed out that however able may be the men
                    composing it, its existence is largely dependent upon the will of the two
                    powerful militarists of the north, Chang Tso-lin, and Tsao Kun; the central
                    government has no troops under its direct authority and so must depend in the
                    last resort upon the will and wishes of those able and willing to underwrite the
                    Central government. The government was in urgent need of funds for
                    administrative purposes, while on the other hand the militarists showed no
                    disposition to disband troops but called instead for increasing amounts of money
                    for military purposes. Therefore, it was not to be expected that much positive
                    progress in reform of administration, or in settling the internal troubles of
                    China would [be] made by the present cabinet. Furthermore, its members were only
                    acting and could be considered to lack any legal basis for holding their
                    portfolios, inasmuch as the northern parliament, which was largely composed of
                    Anfu adherents, was dispersed at the fall of the Anfu clique, and no quorum <pb
                        facs="0567" n="469" xml:id="pg_469"/> was available at least to give the
                    form of legality to the cabinet by approval of its appointment by presidential
                    mandate.</p>
                <p>Although a People’s Convention or Assembly was one of the chief points in General
                    Wu Pei-fu’s program, and was favorably discussed throughout the country by
                    native educational and commercial bodies as well as being recommended by Dr.
                    Reinsch in a memorandum to the central government it received little
                    consideration at the hands of Chang Tso-lin or the Peking government. The matter
                    was referred for consideration to the Ministry of the Interior where as far as
                    can be ascertained at the end of the quarter it was still being “considered”. No
                    doubt the central government felt that the calling of such an Assembly, unless
                    the election of representatives were properly manipulated, would finally call
                    into doubt the legal basis of its own existence. The President was elected by
                    the Parliament called after Tuan Chi-jui came into power, the legality of which
                    would no doubt be questioned by a popular or representative assembly, and thus
                    the legality of the office of the President appointed by this “illegal”
                    parliament. To call for the election of a new parliament under the old election
                    law would have been tacitly to admit that the Tuan parliament was illegal. The
                    government therefore found itself in a quandary as far as any legal or
                    constitutional basis was concerned and adopted a dilatory attitude on the
                    settlement of such questions. Popular opinion on the other hand was convinced
                    that any election arranged for by the present government would only result in an
                    assembly of persons representing the various tuchuns and would consequently not
                    be expected to accomplish more than was already being done by these authorities
                    toward the solution of internal problems.</p>
                <p>In the settlement at Peking, after the July conflict it soon became apparent that
                    Chang Tso-lin was to dictate the terms as far as possible, though naturally Tsao
                    Kun’s wishes had to be deferred to. The settlement became a rivalry between
                    these two military chiefs to strengthen their own personal power rather than to
                    establish a strong stable central government. Chang Tso-lin seized most of the
                    surplus military supplies, aeroplanes, and other military equipment and
                    transported them to Manchuria. Both he and Tsao Kun recruited soldiers from the
                    defeated Anfu troops and Chang Tso-lin stationed some of his own troops near
                    Peking, in order to “protect” the President and the Peking government. In order
                    to be on a parity with Chang Tso-lin, Tsao Kun was given appointment as
                    Inspector General of Chihli, Shantung and Honan. Li Shun, who had wanted the
                    Inspectorate General of Kiangsu, Kiangsi, and Anhui, was instead given the
                    meaningless appointment of Inspector General of the Yangtze, which he refused.
                    He was also urged to become Chief <pb facs="0568" n="470" xml:id="pg_470"/>
                    Peace Delegate for the North, but this he also declined at first, though it was
                    known that he was unofficially negotiating between the North and South as to
                    unification terms. It was known that he was greatly disappointed over the
                    outcome of the routing of the Anfu clique, which he had hoped to see followed by
                    measures looking toward the establishment of a more representative and stable
                    government in Peking, but which instead was followed by the substitution of the
                    power of Chang Tso-lin and Tsao Kun, for that of Tuan Chi-jui and “Little” Hsu,
                    and by the practical ignoring of the liberal views of Wu Pei-fu and himself (Li
                    Shun).</p>
                <p>In the settlement Wu Pei-fu was appointed deputy Inspector General of Chihli,
                    Shantung and Honan under Tsao Kun, and it was believed that he would have charge
                    of the greater portion of his superior’s troops. It must be pointed out that Wu
                    Pei-fu was lacking a Tuchunship from which he could obtain provincial revenues
                    for his troops and for increasing his power and must depend upon his superior,
                    Tsao Kun, for this. It is claimed for General Wu that he is a poor man after
                    years in government service, which is in itself exceptional in China, that he is
                    a strict disciplinarian, a man of few words, modest, and with no claim to being
                    a politician. It is believed that he is actuated by truly patriotic motives, and
                    in popular opinion he is looked upon as the Hero of China. It was thought that
                    he would undoubtedly devote himself to the strengthening of his position and the
                    increase of his army, for it was apparent that he and Chang Tso-lin held
                    opposing views which might some day result in a clash. General Wu, however,
                    realized that any attempt at present to try conclusions with Chang Tso-lin would
                    only prove abortive, the latter having at his command some 200,000 troops, well
                    armed and equipped, and the three rich Manchurian provinces from which to draw
                    revenues.</p>
                <p>During the struggle in the North events were far from peaceful in the South. The
                    Yunnan-Kweichow offensive instituted by Tang Chi-yao (Military Governor of
                    Yunnan) in May against Szechuan finally resulted in the defeat of the Szechuan
                    Tuchun Hsiung K’o-wu, largely because of disloyalty in his own ranks. Although
                    Tang Chiyao by no means gained control of the entire province and his position
                    there remained to be consolidated and strengthened, it represented an additional
                    gain to his already large sphere of influence in the south. During this time
                    Tang aligned himself with the former directors of the Canton Military
                    Government, Tang Shao-yi, Sun Yat-sen and Wu Ting-fang (in Shanghai) and
                    announced his adherence to the constitutional cause, and invited the old
                    Parliament to come to Yunnan, and later to Chungking.</p>
                <p>Another movement was that of General Chen Chiung-ming, commander of the southern
                    (Kwangtung) forces stationed in Fukien, <pb facs="0569" n="471" xml:id="pg_471"
                    /> directed against the Tuchun of Kwangtung, Mo Yung-hsing, a lieutenant of
                    General Lu Yung-ting of Kwangsi, whose subordinates were in control of Kwangtung
                    province. On August 20th Swatow had fallen to the forces of General Chen, and
                    his forces were advancing on Waichow, near Canton. His avowed purpose was to
                    capture Canton and relieve his native province of the burden of the Kwangsi
                    militarists, who with the aid of Tsen Chun-hsuan and Wen Tsung-yao were still
                    maintaining the skeleton of the old Canton Military Government, and wielding
                    their power chiefly for their own benefit. Toward the end of the quarter it
                    looked as though General Chen would meet with success, in driving out the
                    Kwangsi militarists from Kwangtung.</p>
                <p>During this period the Central Government adopted a two-fold policy toward the
                    question of internal peace. Measures were taken to treat directly with the
                    military powers in control in the various provinces, meanwhile attempting to
                    deal also with the south, using Li Shun, Tuchun of Kiangsu as intermediary, the
                    latter finally assuming the office of Chief Peace Delegate for the North, and
                    sending delegates to treat with Tang Chi-yao and other southern leaders. So far
                    little progress toward any real understanding had been made. It was known that
                    Sun Yat-sen was asking [<hi rend="italic">aiding</hi>] General Chen in his
                    efforts against the Kwangsi militarists in Kwangtung and if the latter’s efforts
                    should prove successful the re-establishment of the Constitutional Party at
                    Canton under the leadership of Sun Yat-sen, whose influence in the south is
                    considerable, might be expected. Tang Chi-yao insisted upon his position being
                    recognized in the southwest as co-equal with that of Chang Tso-lin and Tsao Kun
                    in the north, and consequently would demand some voice in the Peking government
                    under any plan of unification. Also if disbandment of troops was to take place,
                    the southern military leaders, jealous of the increasing power of their northern
                    rivals insisted that for each division disbanded in the south, one must also be
                    disbanded in the north. It was doubtful if Chang Tso-lin and Tsao Kun had any
                    idea of disbanding any of their troops, and the possibility of any agreement
                    between the north and south seemed far distant, and little could be expected
                    from the militarists in the final solution of China’s problems. Rather would it
                    come from the people themselves.</p>
                <p>In general it may be said that Competent observers who have traveled about the
                    provinces in the past few years state that the people are going ahead making
                    progress, and getting very definite ideas as to what they want. They want to see
                    the country united, having little interest in the rivalry between the northern
                    and southern militarists. They are becoming weary of the reign of the Tuchuns
                        <pb facs="0570" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/> and want to see them abolished,
                    and the people of each province are becoming daily more insistent upon the
                    running of their own affairs within the province without interference from
                    outside sources. They are adopting such slogans as “Hunan for the Hunanese” and
                    “Home Rule for the provinces.” Recently the gentry and citizens of Kiangsu and
                    Hupeh province[s] have opposed the appointees of the central government to the
                    Civil Governorships of those provinces, insisting upon their own candidates,
                    some demanding that they be elected by the province and have met with some
                    success in their opposition. This movement is spreading throughout central and
                    southern China, and is making some headway in the north. It is the opinion of
                    some well-informed persons that within the course of two years China will
                    experience a real revolution which will rid her of the military, and the form of
                    government then sought will be a federation of States or provinces.</p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Political—Foreign Relations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On August 9th the Japanese Minister handed a note to the Chinese Foreign Office
                    announcing what had already been suspected for some time, that the Anfu leaders
                    had been given refuge in the Japanese Legation; the following men were named as
                    being in the Japanese Legation Guard compound: Hsu Shu-cheng (Little Hsu), Tseng
                    Yu-chun (ex-Minister of Communications), Tuan Chih-kuei (Commander Peking
                    garrison), Ting Shi-yuan (Director Kin-Han-Suiyuan Railways), Chu Shen
                    (ex-Minister of Justice) Wang Chilung (Financial agent of the Anfu Club) Liang
                    Hung-chih (Chief Secretary of the Senate); Yao Tseng [<hi rend="italic">Yao
                        Chen?</hi>] (Chief Justice); and Yao Kuo-chen (Vice-Minister of
                    Communications). Li Ssu-hao (ex-Minister of Finance) is also said to be in
                    hiding in the Legation Quarter. After the downfall of the Anfu Club Peking had
                    been placarded with photographs of these “traitors” and large rewards offered
                    for their capture. The entrances to the Legation Quarter were guarded by
                    Metropolitan police to prevent the escape of these men. However, it was an open
                    question whether their capture was sincerely desired by the President or the
                    Premier. But the notice from the Japanese minister that these men had been given
                    an asylum in his Legation gave the opportunity for a protest from the Foreign
                    Office and the request for the handing over of these men to be tried on civil
                    and criminal charges, which was of course refused by the Japanese Minister. His
                    action was the subject of criticism in the foreign and native press and of
                    protests from native commercial and educational organizations. The action of the
                    Christian Chinese in refusing to send delegates to the World Sunday School
                    Convention in Tokyo may be taken as an indication of the popular feeling against
                    Japan.</p>
                <pb facs="0571" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/>
                <p>The arrest in August of George Shaw, a British merchant in Antung, by the
                    Japanese authorities while he was in Korea and his detention without trial
                    because of alleged conspiracy with the Koreans on Chinese soil also created a
                    wave of resentment throughout China among all foreigners and was! the subject of
                    protest from British Chambers of Commerce, who believed that the motive of
                    arrest was to destroy the profitable trade in which Mr. Shaw was engaged in
                    Antung, of which the Japanese were envious. It has been looked upon as another
                    incident showing the real attitude of Japan toward the “Open Door” in China,
                    especially in Manchuria.</p>
                <p>The last of August the mission from the Verkhne Udinsk government, headed by M.
                    Yourin, arrived in Peking to enter into unofficial negotiations with the Chinese
                    government relative to the resumption of commercial relations between China and
                    that part of Russia represented by the Far Eastern Republic with headquarters at
                    Verkhne Udinsk. This delegation had been held up at Kiakhta, its entry into
                    China having been protested by the French and Japanese Ministers. Then
                    intervened the conflict between the Anfu and Chihli factions; but after the
                    formation of the new cabinet it was decided to allow the delegation to proceed
                    to Peking but not to receive them formally. Delegates were appointed by the
                    Foreign Office to treat with M. Yourin informally.</p>
                <p>The last of September a mandate was issued cancelling the recognition of the
                    Russian Legation and consulates in China, the officials in charge being
                    appointees of the old regime in Russia. Official denial was made that this
                    withdrawal of recognition was in any way connected with the mission of M.
                    Yourin. The Bureaus of Foreign Affairs in the various cities were ordered to
                    take over and administer the Russian concessions. This action brought a protest
                    from the Legations, as well as from the foreign communities in China, involving
                    as it did questions of extraterritoriality and the regulation by Chinese
                    authorities of foreign interests in the Russian concessions. The Foreign Office
                    issued a statement shortly after the mandate explaining that the Russian
                    concessions would merely be taken under trust by the Chinese government and
                    would be returned to a future Russian government when recognized by China and
                    that the rights of the Russian citizens in China would be safeguarded. At the
                    end of the quarter this matter was still in nebulous state being the subject of
                    discussion between the Legations and Consulates and the Chinese Government. It
                    had been admitted informally by some Chinese officials that this move was a
                    mistake, or at least that it was premature as no adequate machinery was
                    available for taking over and administering the Russian concessions, or for
                    looking after the judicial rights of Russians before the promulgation of the
                    mandate, <pb facs="0572" n="474" xml:id="pg_474"/> and therefore its issuance
                    might result in difficulties rendering modifications necessary in carrying out
                    the mandate. However, the Chinese Government may well have realized the
                    possibility of these difficulties, but wished to face the foreign powers with a
                        <hi rend="italic">fait accompli.</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Financial—The Consortium</hi>
                </p>
                <p>After the organization of the new cabinet the attitude of the Consortium towards
                    making loans was again discussed. The new cabinet found that large sums had been
                    misappropriated by the Anfu club from the revenues of the Ministries of Finance
                    and Communications, and then were also faced with the usual monthly excess of
                    administrative expenses over revenues. Various plans for disbandment of troops
                    and the reorganization of departments were brought forward as well as measures
                    for increasing revenue, but at the end of the quarter no real improvement was to
                    be noted. Mr. Lamont’s open letter to various publications in China correcting
                    the misapprehension arising from the propaganda of misinformation regarding the
                    aims of the Consortium and the reservations conceded to Japan in Manchuria and
                    Inner Mongolia were given wide publicity. The announcement of the appointment of
                    Mr. Frederick W. Stevens as the representative in Peking of the American Group
                    was also received. The liberal elements among the Chinese continued to oppose
                    any loan to the present central government, believing that it would only prolong
                    Chinese internal ills. On the other hand it was argued by the Chinese that if
                    supervision of expenditure of loans and of the revenues furnishing the security
                    for loans was to be carried out so as to insure that the money would be spent
                    for non-political purposes, it would amount to international control of China’s
                    finances and consequently of China herself, to which they were naturally
                    strongly opposed. Other Chinese deprecated our association with England, France
                    and Japan in this undertaking, pointing out that the policy of these three
                    countries was not in accord with ours; they pointed to the attempts of England
                    to make Tibet a dependency, to the expenditure by British interests of some
                    three and a half million dollars in Szechwan, ostensibly for the development of
                    oil fields but chiefly for political purposes, to the attempts of France to
                    increase her sphere in Yunnan and Kwangsi, and the Japanese in Manchuria,
                    Shantung and Fukien. They argued that they did not doubt the good will and
                    intentions of the United States but that the practical operation of the
                    Consortium would either be rendered impossible by our associates, or that if it
                    did come into operation it would not be along the lines laid down by the United
                    States. They pointed to instances in the past where our announced intentions and
                    policies in the East had been rendered nugatory by other powers with only a
                    formal protest from the <pb facs="0573" n="475" xml:id="pg_475"/> United States,
                    which the Chinese did not feel to be of much value as opposed to the aggressive
                    policy of the other powers. They stated that if a loan was to be made, they
                    would prefer to have America make it alone. They believed that if the United
                    States adhered to the announced aims of the Consortium, the final result will be
                    that America and American interests would be excluded from participation in
                    large undertakings in China, but that the reverse would be true so far as the
                    other powers were concerned.</p>
                <p>The meeting of the Consortium Groups in New York in October would undoubtedly be
                    watched with keen interest by the Chinese government and people, and it was
                    thought no doubt the Consortium would be approached by representatives of the
                    Chinese Government for a loan, as the central government was hard pressed for
                    funds.</p>
                <p>On September 15th the Cabinet announced the flotation by the Ministry of Finance
                    of the Ninth Year short term domestic loan, amounting to $60,000,000, of which
                    $36,000,000 was to be used to buy back the depreciated Peking notes of the Bank
                    of China and the Bank of Communications during the period of November 1, 1920 to
                    January 31, 1921. The balance was to be used to discharge mortgages held by
                    these two banks. Interest on the bonds was at 6%; the depreciated notes of the
                    two banks mentioned to be accepted at par value in the purchase of bonds. These
                    notes now sell for about 63¢ on the dollar. The bonds are secured on the Customs
                    Surplus. After their withdrawal the depreciated notes are to be destroyed. It is
                    hoped that this operation will re-establish the credit of these two government
                    banks.</p>
                <p>On August 5th an unofficial party of Congressmen, and their wives, daughters and
                    mothers accompanied by Dr. Reinsch and Mr. Arnold, Commercial Attaché to the
                    Legation, arrived at Shanghai, where they were lavishly entertained both by
                    Chinese and foreign officials and organizations. From Shanghai the party went to
                    Hangchow, thence to Nanking, Tsinanfu, Peking, Tientsin and Mukden, being
                    extended every possible courtesy by the Chinese provincial and government
                    officials, as well as by the Chinese citizens and the American officials and
                    residents in China. It is hoped that the trip will result in a better
                    understanding of the needs of American business interests in China, as well as
                    the strengthening of our friendly relations with China and the Chinese.</p>
                <p>Toward the end of September reports were received of the prevalence of a
                    wide-spread famine area throughout the provinces of Chihli, Honan, Shantung and
                    Shansi, estimated as affecting some twenty millions of people, and assuming the
                    proportions of a national calamity. Steps were taken by the various Legations
                    and foreign communities to organize International Relief Committees to work in
                    cooperation with the Chinese in mitigating the famine.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
