<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-03-08T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-03-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="487" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d487">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">893.51/2703: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Morris</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-03-08T14:00:00+09:00"><hi rend="italic">March 8,
                                            1920—2 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[Received March 9—3:13
                                    a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>84. Supplementing my number 82 March 8 [<hi rend="italic">7</hi>], 4
                                p.m. and in reply to your number 68, March 5, 8 p.m.<note n="66" xml:id="d487fn66">Not printed.</note> just received. Mr.
                                    Alston,<note n="67" xml:id="d487fn67">Sir Beilby Francis Alston,
                                    British Minister in China.</note> Mr. Lamont and I after
                                separate study of the memorandum and formula find ourselves in full
                                agreement and after conference have drafted the following summary of
                                our views which my British colleague is also forwarding to his
                                Government.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The memorandum was apparently prepared and (waiting?) to meet
                                    Mr. Lamont’s arrival not as final expression of Japanese views
                                    but as an effort to establish an advance position from which to
                                    recede if necessary.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Since his arrival Mr. Lamont has had private conversations
                                    with Government officials as well as influential representatives
                                    of the banking group here and he has derived the distinct
                                    impression that we should hold our ground in the belief that
                                    eventually the Japanese Government will come to adopt
                                    substantially our viewpoint inasmuch as the financial interests
                                    here, which are all in favor of the consortium, are insistent in
                                    bringing strong pressure to bear.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>In view of these considerations we are all of the opinion that
                                    our respective Governments should, without further loss of time,
                                    send an immediate acknowledgment to the Japanese Government
                                    expressing grave disappointment that the formula proffered is so
                                    exceedingly ambiguous and so irrevocable in character that it
                                    might indicate on the part of the Japanese Government a
                                    continued desire to exclude the cooperation of the American,
                                    British and French banking groups from participation in the
                                    development for China’s benefit of important parts of the
                                    Republic, and therefore confirms the impression that the
                                    Japanese formula cannot be received on the principle of the
                                    independence and the territorial integrity of China; that our
                                    Government[s] clearly recognize the Japanese nation’s legitimate
                                    desire to obtain supplies of food and raw materials necessary to
                                    her economic life and also her desire to protect the Korean
                                    frontier, but our Governments find it quite impossible to
                                    believe that in order to meet such needs it is essential for
                                    example for Japan alone to construct and control so
                                    distinctively [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] a railway line as the
                                    one projected from Taonanfu to Jehol and thence to the coast.
                                    Finally, we venture to suggest that the acknowledgment should
                                    emphatically express the opinion that in the judgment of our
                                    respective <pb facs="0605" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/> Governments
                                    the only method by which any speedy solution of the present
                                    difficulty in the formation of the consortium can be found is to
                                    request the banking groups to undertake a prompt review of the
                                    whole question in the hope that these groups may reach a
                                    solution which can be approved by all the Governments concerned.
                                    The presence in Tokyo of Mr. Lamont, the representative of the
                                    American banking group, who is fully conversant with the view of
                                    the British and French groups, renders such a review with the
                                    Japanese group particularly hopeful.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>If our suggestions as above are approved, and while the
                                    Japanese Government are reconsidering their position in the
                                    light of our reply, Mr. Lamont will continue his private
                                    conversations and endeavor to pave the way for a reasonable
                                    solution which he is confident the financial elements in Japan
                                    earnestly desire.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>If Mr. Lamont should be disappointed in his hope of reaching a
                                    solution by such a review, we are still free to fall back upon
                                    the formation of a three power consortium in order to meet the
                                    essential economic needs of China.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>Repeated to Peking.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Morris</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>