<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-07-22T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-07-22T18:00:00-05:00" n="60" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">760c.60f/34a: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Wallace</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Paraphrase]</seg></opener>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-07-22T19:00:00-04:00"><hi rend="italic">July 22,
                                            1920—7 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>1284. The Department feels that some ill feeling may be caused if
                                Italy and Japan are not included among the Governments to choose the
                                Commission that I proposed in telegram 1278, as we now understand
                                that they were represented on the Teschen Commission. … You may
                                therefore suggest as indicated that the Commission be composed of
                                five members, who will select as president of the Commission one of
                                themselves. You may suggest that the Commission be also the
                                commission to delimit the frontier on the spot, but that, in view of
                                the nature of the territory to be delimited, it have larger
                                discretionary powers than such a body is usually allowed.</p>
                            <p>To separate the Teschen question from the solution of the general
                                coal question in Central Europe is extremely difficult, especially
                                as regards Upper Silesia. The amount of coal that the Poles should
                                be granted from Teschen would be influenced by the amount that they
                                receive from Upper Silesia; until the determination of the
                                plebiscite in Upper Silesia, no final definition of coal deliveries
                                to Poland should be reached.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Colby</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>