<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Ambassador ( (Spring Rice) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1914Supp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1016</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1016</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1914-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1914-11-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-11-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="1016"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1016">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72111/736</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SRSCA1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Spring Rice</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">British Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                    <placeName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-11-23">
                        <hi rend="italic">November 23, 1914</hi>.</date>
                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received November 24</hi>.] </dateline>
                <p rend="flushleft">No 397]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to my immediately preceding note
                    of yesterday’s date on the subject of the <persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Sacramento’s</hi>
                    </persName> voyage,<note n="1" xml:id="d1016fn1">Not printed.</note> I have the
                    honour to state, under instructions from <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Sir Edward
                        Grey</persName>, that the systematic continuance of ships sailing from
                    United States ports with the object of supplying and cooperating with German
                    cruisers is a matter of gravest anxiety to His Majesty’s Government. They fully
                    recognise the absolute sincerity of the United States authorities in
                    endeavouring to satisfy themselves as to the innocence of shipments made by
                    these German supply ships under neutral flags, but the fact remains that the
                    confidence of the authorities is systematically abused by the German agents and
                    shippers. It is feared that the instructions recently issued prohibiting the
                    disclosure of any information in regard to merchant vessels and their cargoes
                    leaving the United States ports play directly into the hands of agents of the
                    German Government who direct in United States territory the operations of these
                    supply ships under neutral flags. If the supply ships, which act as auxiliaries
                    to the German fleet, continue to carry on freely their operations from United
                    States ports, His Majesty’s <pb facs="0951" n="637" xml:id="pg_637"/> Government
                    feel unable to admit that the United States Government can repudiate all
                    responsibility for the damage and depredations caused by German cruisers.</p>
                <p>His Majesty’s Government have reliable information that some of the persons
                    connected in the dealings of the <hi rend="italic">Sacramento</hi> are now
                    concerned in the <hi rend="italic">Olson and Mahony vessel</hi> under the United
                    States flag, which is due to sail on November 24 from San Francisco with
                    Valparaiso as ostensible destination. These facts make it more than probable
                    that this vessel, like the <hi rend="italic">Sacramento</hi>, is also engaged in
                    supplying German cruisers.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances of gravest suspicion I have the honour to request that
                    the <hi rend="italic">Olson and Mahony</hi> may not be allowed to sail without a
                    most careful and searching investigation on the part of the United States
                    Government.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SRSCA1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cecil Spring Rice</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
