<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-10-24T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-10-24T13:00:00-05:00" n="227" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d227">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/1124</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Morgenthau</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <lb/>
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-10-24T20:00:00+02:00">
                                <hi rend="italic">October 24, 1914, 8 p.m.</hi>
                            </date>
                            <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received 12 p.m.</hi>] </dateline>
                        <p rend="center">[Telegram]</p>
                        <p>Yesterday French Ambassador sent nine cases and to-day British Ambassador
                            and Russian Counselor requested permission to send <pb facs="0435" n="121" xml:id="pg_121"/> some cases to the Embassy for
                            safe-keeping. The cases contain documents, silver, and other valuables.
                            The British and Russian Ambassadors claim to have secret information
                            that the Germans are now exerting extraordinary pressure to force the
                            Ottoman Government into the general war and they, as well as French
                            Ambassador, are, therefore, preparing for possible early departure.
                            Secretary or War, while dining with me Thursday, said that Turkey does
                            not contemplate attacking any country but intends to keep strengthening
                            its army so as to be prepared for any emergency and is not considering
                            partial demobilization as rumored. At my suggestion Minister of Public
                            Instruction accompanied me to luncheon at Girls College and reception
                            and concert at Robert College to-day. Both faculties appreciated his
                            coming as it was the first time that any Minister of Public Instruction
                            visited either institution. Minister of Public Instruction expressed
                            great satisfaction with both institutions.</p>
                        <p>Please inform me if <hi rend="italic">Tennessee</hi> is also to remain in
                            Ottoman waters and comply with my requests.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Ambassador</hi>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>