<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-11-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="263" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d263">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72119/38</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé d’Affaires in the Netherlands</hi>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_LM1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Langhorne</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Legation</hi>, <lb/>
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Hague</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-11-19">
                                <hi rend="italic">November 19, 1914</hi>.</date>
                            <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received December 7</hi>.] </dateline>
                        <p rend="flushleft">No. 170]</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose herewith an
                            article published in the <hi rend="italic">Gazette de Hollande</hi>,
                            containing a translation of an editorial which appeared in the Amsterdam
                                <hi rend="italic">Algemeen Handelsblad</hi>, one of the leading
                            papers in Holland, on the 16th instant.</p>
                        <p>This article has been widely copied in European papers and has caused
                            much discussion here. The prevailing opinion in The Hague is that it is
                            a very good piece of journalism, but that such action at present would
                            be premature.</p>
                        <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LM1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Marshall Langhorne</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <pb facs="0460" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/>
                        <postscript>
                            <p rend="center">[Enclosure]</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="italic">Article from the “Gazette de Hollande” November
                                    17, 1914</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>An eloquent appeal for mediation in the great world struggle is made
                                by the <hi rend="italic">Algemeen Handelsblad</hi>, in the course of
                                which our contemporary writes:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Nation after nation is being drawn into a struggle whose
                                    continuance can serve no ideal end, whilst it is slaying or
                                    destroying the noblest youthful powers of Europe and leaving
                                    only the names of some famous towns on the map. The sufferings
                                    of hundreds of thousands are becoming unbearable. Human woe is
                                    rising to heaven, witnessing against religion and
                                    civilization.</p>
                                <p>Is not the moment come to attempt to save what there is yet to
                                    save? Two countries are indicated for this task, the Kingdom of
                                    the Netherlands and the Republic of the United States of North
                                    America . . . and now is a favourable moment to offer their
                                    mediation. The Minister of the United States here is now on his
                                    way to Washington, where he enjoys the full confidence of the
                                    American Government. Our Queen is honoured, is popular in
                                    America. Our Minister for Foreign Affairs is generally known and
                                    esteemed in the Republic. Cannot both Governments now, under
                                    these favourable circumstances, together prepare for the task of
                                    offering their mediation? A like opportunity to that now
                                    offering will certainly not easily recur. A powerful word can be
                                    spoken, and it would prove to the great honour of our country if
                                    coming generations were able to testify that it was Holland’s
                                    Queen who had had the high courage to first speak the word that
                                    showed the peoples of Europe the way to a lasting peace. . .
                                    .</p>
                            </quote>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>