<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1914-09-03T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1914-09-03T14:00:00-05:00" n="474" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d474">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 300.115/165</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at London</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SRP1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Skinner</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <dateline>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Consulate General</hi>, <lb/>
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="italic">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1914-09-03T19:00:00+00:00">
                                    <hi rend="italic">September 3, 1914, 7 p.m.</hi>
                                </date>
                                <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received 7:30 p.m.</hi>] </dateline>
                            <p rend="center">[Telegram]</p>
                            <p>President Admiralty division prize court writes:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Writs are issued when it is shown that ship or goods should be
                                    condemned as lawful prize. Prize court will sit only in London
                                    for [the] United Kingdom. Owners of cargo alleged to be property
                                    neutrals, if they satisfy procurator general by the shipping,
                                    documents that such cargo is neutral property, will obtain his
                                    consent to cargo being released and marshal will at once act on
                                    such consent. In compliance with your request American owners of
                                    cargo shall have one month further time in which to enter
                                    appearance and court should be prepared on special grounds to
                                    enlarge this time. The procurator general has already in many
                                    cases consented to release before an appearance has been
                                    entered.</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>Procurator general has agreed with me to note my informal protests as
                                to vessels taken to ports in British Isles and give me opportunity
                                to appoint solicitor for absent owners if such have not entered
                                appearance within tune limit agreed. Following courts authorized act
                                as prize courts under Prize Courts Act 1894:</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Supreme Court in Gibraltar; Colombo for Ceylon; Mauritius;
                                    Singapore for Straits Settlements; Hongkong; Sydney for New
                                    South Wales; Melbourne for Victoria; Adelaide for South
                                    Australia; Perth or Albany for Western Australia; Hobart for
                                    Tasmania; Dunedin, Wellington, Auckland and Christchurch for New
                                    Zealand; St. John’s for Newfoundland; Stanley for Falkland
                                    Islands; Brisbane for Queensland; Kingston or Port Royal for
                                    Jamaica; Simon’s Bay or Cape Town for Cape of Good Hope; Sierre
                                    Leone; Bombay; Durban for Natal; Suva for Fiji; Nassau for
                                    Bahamas; Georgetown for British Guiana; Belize for Honduras;
                                    Port of Spain for Trinidad; Antigua for Leeward Islands;
                                    commercial court in Malta; exchequer court or local judges in
                                    Admiralty in Halifax, Victoria, Quebec, Charlottetown and St.
                                    John for Canada; court of general assizes for Bermuda; royal
                                    court of St. Lucia for Windward Islands; residents court for
                                    Aden; high court of judicature, Fort William, for Calcutta; and
                                    chief court for Lower Burma.</p>
                                <p>The towns named indicate places at which it would be convenient
                                    court sit and colonies have been so informed but decision as to
                                    place of sitting rests with colony.</p>
                            </quote>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SRP1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Skinner</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>