<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Pakistan ( (Warren) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v06p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d191</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">191</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-08-01T02:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-08-01T02:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recrT0TBgNbKJyC3W" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006005376"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Extremist</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recxByt4hmF6omKym" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018002867"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Demilitarization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-01T02:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-01T02:30:00-05:00" n="191"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d191">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">690D. 91/8–151: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Pakistan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Warren</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Karachi</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-01T13:00:00+05:30"
                            >August 1, 1951—1 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>114. UK acting <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d191fn1">R. R. Burnett.</note> discussed with me yesterday
                    his call on Zafrulla under instrs from London re <gloss target="#t_Deptel1"
                        >Deptel</gloss> 19, July 30<note n="2" xml:id="d191fn2">Reference is
                        presumably to London’s telegram 19 to Karachi, same as London’s 590 to
                        Washington, July 30, <ref target="#pg_1800">p. 1800</ref>.</note> and <gloss
                        target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss>’s comments.</p>
                <p>He said both <gloss target="#t_FonMin1">FonMin</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_FonSecy1">FonSecy</gloss> appeared relaxed in their attitude to
                        <gloss target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>
                    relations, the only good sign he sees in present sitn. <gloss
                        target="#t_FonSecy1">FonSecy</gloss> confirmed that Mohd Ali has been
                    responsible for drafting of Liaquat’s notes to Nehru in past two weeks. Burnett
                    feels Mohd Ali is so bitter against India because of his own personal losses
                    resulting from partition that his attitude colors Liaquat’s correspondence with
                    Nehru. I feel same way and expressed myself guardedly to Finance Min and <gloss
                        target="#t_FonSecy1">FonSecy</gloss> to effect that Liaquat’s peace
                    proposals as addressed to Nehru might have been more effective had they not been
                    packaged in extraneous and bitter preamble.</p>
                <p>Acting UK <gloss target="#t_HICOM1">HICOM</gloss> is depressed and apprehensive
                    over the outlook and said yesterday he was informing his govt to that effect. My
                    own feeling is that the press campaign is inflammatory and invitations to the
                    provincial populations and frontier tribesmen to express their adherence to
                    Liaquat’s govt by mass demonstrations is dangerous. In my opinion two areas of
                    most acute friction are tribal areas and Azad Kashmir in West <gloss
                        target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> and villages <gloss target="#t_Pak1"
                        >Pak</gloss> adjacent to Bengal. Provincial Governor Noon’s appeal in Dacca
                    to East <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> population to rally behind <gloss
                        target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> might easily be utilized by extremist elements
                    to provoke communal disturbances in that area. Shld this occur there is almost
                    certain risk of war.</p>
                <p>I visited the frontier tribal area bordering on Azad Kashmir two weeks ago immed
                    before the announcement of Ind troop concentrations and found the population
                    there preoccupied with campaign for <pb facs="0340" n="1804" xml:id="pg_1804"/>
                    December elections in the frontier province and expressing little concern over
                    the Kashmir question at that time. But with campaigns now under way to arouse
                    public feeling I feel that attitudes may change almost over night.</p>
                <p>With Amb Henderson’s approval I have sent Metcalf ,<note n="3" xml:id="d191fn3"
                        >Lee E. Metcalf, Second Secretary and Vice Consul of the Embassy in
                        Pakistan.</note> Polit Secy, to consult with Emb staff in Delhi and Consul
                    Gen in Calcutta en route to a week’s observation in East <gloss target="#t_Pak1"
                        >Pak</gloss>. If the tension eases I propose to make another visit to the
                    northern frontier the last week in Aug to observe attitudes, not only with
                    respect to Kashmir, but also with respect to Afghan ref Kabul’s 68 to Dept.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d191fn4">Telegram 68, from Kabul, July 27, suggested that
                        there was a close connection between the Kashmir issue and the dispute
                        between Pakistan and Afghanistan with respect to jurisdiction over the
                        North-West Frontier Province and Tribal Areas. For text, see <ref
                            target="#pg_1987">p. 1987</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Shld Nehru be successful in delaying Graham’s work through Aug by vague proposal
                    on Kashmir demilitarization, I feel boiling point may be reached in <gloss
                        target="#t_Indo1">Indo</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> relations
                    no later than mid-Sept. In view of this depressing outlook I recommend that US
                    and UK suggest to their <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> reps the desirability
                    of having <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> informally ask Graham for an interim
                    report not later than mid-Aug, provided he has not already submitted his views
                    on the probable success of his task, in order that thought may be given in the
                    latter part of the month to an <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> reminder to
                    both govts that present tensions if not curbed are a threat to the peace.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Warren</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
