<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-01-30T03:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-01-30T03:30:00-05:00" n="305" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d305">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">689.90D/1–3051: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Pakistan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Warren</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Karachi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-01-30T14:00:00+05:30">January 30, 1951—2 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>685. For McGhee. Ikramullah<note n="1" xml:id="d305fn1">Mohammad
                                    Ikramullah, Secretary, Ministry of Foreign Affairs and
                                    Commonwealth Relations, Government of Pakistan.</note> showed me
                                this morning Bevin’s top secret letter of December 4, 1950 to the
                                Pakistan High Commissioner in London<note n="2" xml:id="d305fn2">Habib Ibrahim Rahimtoola.</note> defining the UK position on
                                the Durand line. While I cannot quote from memory, the substance of
                                the communication is that His Majesty’s Government in the UK
                                considers that Pakistan at the time of the formation of its
                                government became the inheritor of the Durand Line as the boundary
                                with Afghanistan. In the view of the UK Government, Afghanistan’s
                                expressed willingness to enter into direct negotiations with
                                Pakistan on the problems of mutual concern without including
                                Pushtoonistan specifically in the conversations shows a more
                                conciliatory attitude. It is the hope of the UK Government that
                                Pakistan for the reason cited above may find it possible to accept
                                the good offices of the US Government and enter into direct
                                conversations with Afghanistan.</p>
                            <p>I urgently recommend you present to the Secretary from the point of
                                view of timing and effect the desirability that he give assurances
                                similar to Bevin’s to the Pakistan Ambassador in Washington. The
                                Pakistanis are prepared to go ahead immediately and have already
                                drafted, and Ikramullah tells me, have cabled approval for the notes
                                inviting the Afghans to enter into conversations.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Warren</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>