<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="329" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">789.13/4–2351</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of
                                    State</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-23">April 23,
                                    1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Interview with Afghan Prime Minister</p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Sardar Shah Mahmud Khan—Prime
                                        Minister of Afghanistan</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Abdul Hamid Aziz—Chargé d’Affaires,
                                        Embassy of Afghanistan</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">The Secretary</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. McGhee—Assistant Secretary</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Mathews—Director, Office of South
                                        Asian Affairs</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>After appropriate remarks of courtesy, the Prime Minister referred to
                                this Government’s proposal of November 6, 1950 to the Governments
                                    <pb facs="0502" n="1966" xml:id="pg_1966"/> of Afghanistan and
                                Pakistan looking toward an improvement of relations between them. He
                                pointed out that his Government was deeply grateful for the interest
                                which the United States had shown and had accepted our proposal
                                promptly. There has, unhappily, been no reply from Pakistan. I said
                                that we had just received Pakistan’s answer. The Government of
                                Pakistan accepted the first three points of our proposal relating to
                                the prevention of propaganda, the prevention of incidents among the
                                tribes, and the exchange of Ambassadors. With respect to the fourth
                                point, which proposed a meeting of representatives of the two
                                governments without an agenda or preconditions, Pakistan had
                                indicated that it would be prepared to participate in such a meeting
                                if prior discussions through the newly appointed Ambassadors showed
                                that the meeting would be fruitful. Mr. McGhee commented that as
                                this departed to some extent from our original proposal, we could
                                not consider the Pakistan reply an acceptance of our proposal unless
                                the Afghan Government were disposed to accept the Pakistan
                                counter-suggestion.</p>
                            <p>The Prime Minister remarked that his Government had exchanged
                                Ambassadors with Pakistan before but that discussions through these
                                regular diplomatic channels had been without avail. He feared,
                                therefore, that the Pakistan counter-proposal would lead to the same
                                unsatisfactory situation with the result that the Ambassadors would
                                have to be withdrawn and that there would be no lasting improvement
                                in Afghan-Pakistan relations. He stated that although he was Prime
                                Minister, he could not by himself indicate whether his Government
                                would or would not find the Pakistan counter-proposal acceptable. It
                                would have to be carefully considered by the Afghan Cabinet. I said
                                that the Department was transmitting the Pakistan reply to Kabul in
                                order that our Embassy might transmit it to his Government.</p>
                            <p>Mr. McGhee urged that the Afghan Government give very careful
                                consideration to the Pakistan counter-proposal. It was not too far
                                removed from our original suggestion and since both governments were
                                in agreement as to the first three points of that suggestion, it
                                would be unfortunate if this measure of progress were lost. The
                                Prime Minister indicated that he would pass these comments on to his
                                colleague, the Acting Prime Minister and Foreign Minister, and
                                remarked that we might now be embarking upon a period of bargaining
                                between Kabul and Karachi which could be time-consuming.</p>
                            <p>In more general discussion of the Pushtoonistan issue, the Prime
                                Minister emphasized that he was speaking not only for himself and
                                his government, but for all the people of Afghanistan. They felt
                                very strongly that their 4 to 4½ million Pathan brethren in Pakistan
                                should have the right to determine their own future. He warned me
                                that <pb facs="0503" n="1967" xml:id="pg_1967"/> Pakistan could
                                never be strong as long as these unwilling people were kept within
                                its borders. On the other hand, if there were a free Pushtoonistan
                                the peoples of that nation and of Afghanistan would be a solid
                                bulwark against the threat from the north. He urged that I think on
                                these things and I said that I would do so.</p>
                            <p>The Prime Minister expressed the gratitude of his Government and his
                                people for the loan extended to Afghanistan by the Export–Import
                                    Bank.<note n="1" xml:id="d329fn1">Reference is to a recent loan
                                    of $21,000,000.</note> He went on to say that Afghanistan looked
                                to the United States as a stronger and richer brother which would
                                help his poor country along the road to self-reliance. The Afghan
                                people were strong and his country had many resources, but it needed
                                outside help to develop itself. He hoped that the United States
                                would provide the necessary assistance; if it did, it could rely
                                upon the loyal support of Afghanistan. I assured the Prime Minister
                                that we were interested in the progress of his country.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>