<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-29T02:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-29T02:30:00-05:00" n="369" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">689.90D/11–2951: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Afghanistan</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Merrell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kabul</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-11-29T12:00:00+04:30">November 29, 1951—noon.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>260. Dept pass DeptAr <gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>–2. <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss> Chargé wishing discuss
                                “Hussain-Majid agreement” (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>
                                to Dept 254, Nov 26)<note n="1" xml:id="d369fn1">Telegram 254, from
                                    Kabul, November 26, not printed, reported that the Hussain–Majid
                                    “agreement” outlined in Karachi’s telegram 44 to Kabul, November
                                    15 (same as telegram 525 to Washington, <ref target="#pg_1999">p. 1999</ref>) had been reposing in the Prime Minister’s
                                    desk and that the Minister of Foreign Affairs had been summoned
                                    from vacation to Kabul to consider it. The acting Minister of
                                    Foreign Affairs had stated that while the agreement might not
                                    lead to a solution it was “encouraging.”
                                    (689.90D/11–2651)</note> called on Horner yesterday. Horner
                                attempted impress upon Abdur Rahman advantages of positive <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> response to <gloss target="#t_GOA1">GOA</gloss>’s evident desire to achieve face-saving compromise
                                to Pash question. Abdur Rahman said he wld call on AF Amb to London
                                Shah Wali (who has been visiting Kabul, and is brother <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss> and uncle of King) with
                                object inciting him to travel back via Karachi (Emb had understood
                                previously that Shah Wali wished to go thru <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>, but was uncertain of his reception). He also said,
                                if response was favorable, he wld ask <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> to extend formal invitation and to urge warm
                                reception calculated to improve polit atmosphere.</p>
                            <p>Abdur Rahman agreed that essential feature of any agreement is
                                face-saving formula. In that regard, Horner indicated Emb’s strong
                                belief that gradual cessation propaganda on both sides was crux of
                                situation without which no agreement was possible. Horner also
                                suggested that during period in which propaganda being diminished it
                                wld be most helpful if <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> cld make
                                some unsolicited offer to improve transit Afghan goods, even to
                                point of suggesting possibility of free port arrangement and
                                extension of rail line from Chaman into <pb facs="0538" n="2002" xml:id="pg_2002"/> Kandahar. Chargé promised bring these views
                                to attention <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> with positive
                                recommendation.</p>
                            <p>As previously indicated, Emb considers that atmosphere conducive to
                                satisfactory settlement <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>–Af
                                dispute, if on no more than temporary basis, is being rapidly
                                generated Emb feels this result, in large measure, <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss>’s own earnest wish for
                                opportunity for peaceful development Afghan industry and economy.
                                Emb therefore believes it wld be important if face-saving formula
                                (largely intended to strengthen <gloss target="#t_PriMin1">PriMin</gloss>’s hand against more nationalistic elements)
                                could be accompanied by economic advantages to <gloss target="#t_GOA1">GOA</gloss>. These wld not be essentially
                                bribe, but rather wld be intended rationalize Afghan’s land locked
                                position, and to replace archaic Brit system of refundable customs
                                duties, which has led to great delays in Afghan imports and exports,
                                and very considerable increase in costs thereof. Emb hopes that
                                ultimately <gloss target="#t_GOA1">GOA</gloss> can be offered free
                                port arrangement in Karachi, and that rail line shld be extended
                                into Kandahar, thereby making possible exemption Afghan goods from
                                customs examination and duty within <gloss target="#t_Pak1">Pak</gloss>. At same time, Emb wld like to envisage substantial
                                improvement Kabul–Kandahar road (partially paid for by US grant
                                aid).</p>
                            <p>These improvements in communications not only wld bolster Afghan
                                econ, but wld be of ultimate military value in event Sov aggression
                                in this area. For that reason, if for no other, Emb wld recommend
                                strong support by Dept and Emb Karachi along those lines. Army
                                Attaché concurs.</p>
                            <p>Dept pass Karachi. Sent Dept 260, rptd info Karachi 45, pouched
                                London unn, Delhi unn, Moscow unn.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Merrell</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>