<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-09-06T05:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-06T05:30:00-05:00" n="483" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d483">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">611.91/9–651: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in India</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Henderson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">priority</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">New Delhi</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-09-06T16:00:00+05:30">September 6, 1951—4 p. m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>868. No distribution outside Dept.</p>
                            <p>1. In view apparent surprise in wide US circles at rejection by Nehru
                                of Jap treaty and consequent speculation re status Amer-Ind
                                relations, we venture submit herewith some our ideas re likely
                                future <pb facs="0716" n="2180" xml:id="pg_2180"/> attitude Nehru
                                towards Jap in framework his general fon policies as we presently
                                assess them.</p>
                            <p>2. Rejection Jap treaty your opinion not mere reflection of current
                                status US relations with Ind. We believe it represents logical step
                                on part Nehru in his efforts attain one his primary fon policy
                                objectives, that is, eventual exclusion from mainland and waters
                                Asia all Western milit power and what he wld consider as Western
                                polit and econ pressures.</p>
                            <p>3. By rejection treaty for reasons given by him Nehru has laid basis
                                which will enable him carry on subsequent campaign stimulate and
                                gain influence over nationalistic and anti-white elements in Jap. He
                                believes these elements if discreetly encouraged and skillfully
                                guided by such experienced Asian nationalist leaders as himself will
                                eventually take over power in Jap, denounce Jap alliance with US,
                                and insist on evacuation all Amer armed forces from Jap and return
                                to Jap control such islands as US might be occupying.</p>
                            <p>4. Thus far Nehru has made little progress in persuading Commie Chi
                                abandon its ties with Russia and form partnership with India
                                carrying out campaign to unite Asia under slogan “Asian
                                nationalism.” (content of “Asian nationalism” as this expression
                                used by Nehru is for most part combination of desire for an “Asia
                                for Asians” and of “anti-Westernism.”) If he can succeed in drawing
                                Commie Chi away from Russia and Jap away from US and can work them
                                into common front with Ind he will feel he has made substantial
                                progress in direction attainment united Asia in which he can play
                                important role (in referring to Asia herein we not including Russian
                                Asia) and which he wld like use in pursuing further objectives.</p>
                            <p>5. Nehru will probably work not only thru Ind dipl and cons offices’
                                in Jap and on Jap dipl and cons reps in Ind but also in numerous
                                other ways to gain in Jap reputation disinterested and idealistic
                                defender of Jap polit and territorial integrity against US
                                imperialism. It is believed he will use channels press and radio,
                                encourage exchange goodwill visits, instruct Ind dipls take
                                appropriate attitudes in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and
                                elsewhere, and employ usual tricks modern propaganda.</p>
                            <p>6. In carrying on his campaign to attain his objectives in Asia Nehru
                                not likely move too openly or rapidly. He will, not wish arouse too
                                much hostility or indignation in US. He realizes for some time to
                                come Ind will sorely need certain capital and consumption goods
                                which only US can furnish. He not likely disclose his real
                                objectives. He will probably continue try appear as democratic
                                idealist primarily interested in welware downtrodden masses of Asia;
                                as David who regretfully faces materialistic and clumsy Goliath of
                                militarism and imperialism. He will continue endeavor gain support
                                in Western <pb facs="0717" n="2181" xml:id="pg_2181"/> world,
                                particularly in US and UK, of various non-Commie left wing elements
                                and well-intentioned idealists with progressive view as well as
                                professional “liberals.” He will continue make special effort charm
                                and flatter naive Amer and Brit, who he thinks might be useful in
                                helping mold public opinion in his favor or in supporting policies
                                in their countries which wld facilitate gaining of his fon policy
                                objectives. He will continue make minor concessions and friendly
                                gestures from time to time to US in order keep down tide resentment
                                and and make US officials think, “He will come to our side
                                eventually if we are patient and handle him properly.” He not
                                likely, however, change his basic policies unless Commie Chi by acts
                                makes clear once for all that his dreams for partnership with it
                                cannot be realized. It wld be foolish for Commie Chi commit such
                                acts just now because potential value of Nehru in helping stimulate
                                hatred in Asia against peoples of Eur stock, particularly of US,
                                shld not be underestimated.</p>
                            <p>7. In presenting our ideas above with minimum of reservations and
                                qualifications we have probably made Nehru’s objectives and plans
                                for obtaining them more clear-cut than they really are. Nehru
                                frequently “plays by ear” and permits his emotions of moment
                                influence his actions. Nevertheless we believe what we have said
                                above portrays Nehru’s present approach to problem of Jap future and
                                to related problems.</p>
                            <p>8. Discussions measures we might take meet Nehru’s probable campaign
                                against us in Jap not in scope this tel. We wish stress, however,
                                that in determining and carrying out such measures we shld be
                                careful differentiate between him and India. Altho Nehru at present
                                conducts Ind fon policies to suit himself many thoughtful Ind polit
                                and econ leaders disagree with these policies and believe friendly
                                coop with US more important than close ties with unreliable Commie
                                Chi. We shld be playing into hands our enemies if in endeavoring
                                meet Nehru’s campaign against US in Asia we shld “write India off”
                                or take measures likely wound sensibilities of Ind people.<note n="1" xml:id="d483fn1">
                                    <p>In telegram 441 from Moscow, September 13, Ambassador Kirk
                                        sent the following comment to the Secretary of State:</p>
                                    <p>“Amb Henderson’s tel 868, September 6 of great interest this
                                        Emb providing clearest exposition Nehru character and
                                        program to date.</p>
                                    <p>“Obviously we shld continue concentrate on steering Nehru
                                        away from collaboration with Commie China and Soviet Union
                                        which bound end disastrously for India and West. Presumably
                                        we in better position counteract his attempts wean away
                                        Japan.</p>
                                    <p>“India as future great world power is of utmost importance US
                                        and world security. In implementing recommendation last para
                                            <gloss target="#t_reftel1">reftel</gloss> we must not
                                        neglect fact that possibility adroit Soviet exploitation of
                                        any situation which might be construed as indication lack US
                                        faith and interest in India and its people, is main danger.”
                                        (611.91/9–1351)</p>
                                </note>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Henderson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>