<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-11-25T10:46:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-11-25T10:46:00-05:00" n="159" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d159">
                    <head>159. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Egypt<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d159fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                            P850002–2321. Secret; Flash; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>
                            Distribute as <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_Cherokee_1">Cherokee</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SM_2">Sterner</persName>; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_QWB_1">Quandt</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>,
                            and Robert Perito; and approved by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>. Sent immediate for information to Tel Aviv and
                            the White House.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-11-25T15:46:00+00:00">November 25, 1977, 1546Z</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>282008. <gloss target="#t_WH_1">WH</gloss> for <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>. Subject: Instructions to Ambassador for Meeting
                        With Sadat. For the Ambassador From the Secretary. Ref: Cairo 19466.<note n="2" xml:id="d159fn2">See <ref target="#d155">Document
                            155</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>1. Please try to see Sadat as soon as possible to convey the following
                        comments to him in response to his report to you.</p>
                    <p>2. Tell Sadat we are, first, very grateful to him for the full and timely
                        report of his conversations in Israel. President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> is personally appreciative. It is
                        now clear that Sadat’s visit to Israel will be regarded as a momentous event
                        in the history of the Arab-Israel conflict. Negotiations he and Israelis are
                        proposing to set in motion, together with the impact his visit has had in
                        psychological terms, open up dramatic and hopeful new prospects for a peace
                        settlement.</p>
                    <p>3. We want to assure Sadat that the United States is fully in support of him
                        in this bold new venture, and that we remain ready to be of whatever
                        assistance we can. Objective of U.S. policy throughout this long conflict
                        has been to promote the most direct, expeditious process of negotiations
                        among the parties.</p>
                    <pb facs="0811" n="784" xml:id="pg_784"/>
                    <p>4. We do not know what the Soviet feelings are about this but their ability
                        to interfere, once the Middle Eastern parties themselves establish
                        negotiating momentum, is in our opinion limited. We ourselves have no
                        problem in the parties proceeding in this manner, and, in answer to Sadat’s
                        specific question in paragraph 9 of your telegram, we would have no problem
                        with his stating in his Peoples Assembly address that peace treaties should
                        be reached through direct negotiations among all the parties. This coincides
                        not only with our view but also with Israeli policy as we understand it.</p>
                    <p>5. We would like for Sadat to be as specific as possible concerning the
                        relationship between his bilaterals with Israel and the comprehensive
                        settlement among all the parties which both he and <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> have stressed remains the overall
                        objective. Sadat has emphasized that “careful preparation” is
                        needed—presumably to be accomplished in the bilateral talks he is launching
                        with Israel—leading to the convening of a multilateral peace conference. How
                        far does he believe the process of bilateral Egypt-Israel exploration can go
                        before negotiations must involve the other parties? In the meanwhile,
                        assuming the bilateral talks with the Israelis are productive but take some
                        time, how does he propose that the rest of the Arabs be kept from mobilizing
                        against him and withdrawing from peace talks because of their suspicions
                        that a private Egyptian-Israeli deal is in the making?</p>
                    <p>6. As we see it, while Sadat could proceed without support from some of the
                        other Arab states, one important key to his strategy will be retaining Saudi
                        support. How far has he taken Saudis into his confidence about his coming
                        program for negotiations? We take his point about our not attempting to
                        carry his brief in Saudi Arabia but we will continue on-going dialogue with
                        Saudis on this and other subjects and we need to know what Sadat would
                        prefer us to say to them in connection with his initiative. We would also
                        like to hear his view as to what line we can best take with the Syrians and
                        Jordanians, with whom we will continue close consultations.</p>
                    <p>7. While we recognize that it will not be possible to allay all suspicions in
                        Arab world, or to bring all the Arabs along with Sadat in his strategy, we
                        consider it important that Sadat stress in his public statements his
                        continuing commitment to comprehensiveness of a peace settlement and to
                        early convening of a Middle East Peace Conference in which Palestinians and
                        other parties would participate. Whatever he chooses to say publicly about
                        his continuing talks with the Israelis can best be projected as exploration
                        of substantive issues preparatory to, and a logical and necessary step
                        toward, the convening of a Middle East Peace Conference. In this respect it
                        is worth recalling that Sadat himself insisted that Sinai I and II
                        agreements be cast in terms of step toward overall peace settlement—indeed,
                        Sadat will recall that the <pb facs="0812" n="785" xml:id="pg_785"/>
                        Egyptians drafted the title to these agreements which stressed this point.
                        It seems to us that the “Geneva Middle East Peace Conference” has by now
                        become a symbol of very important progress that has been made since 1973 in
                        Arab-Israel negotiations, and that its preservation as an umbrella,
                        particularly in terms of public pronouncements, will strengthen Egypt’s
                        ability to pursue its bilateral explorations with Israel. The Geneva venue
                        for such negotiations is of course not crucial in itself but the continuing
                        objective of a “Middle East Peace Conference” remains valid and
                        necessary.</p>
                    <p>8. For this reason we believe Sadat’s proposal that he in effect bury the
                        Geneva conference in his speech to the Peoples Assembly Saturday<note n="3" xml:id="d159fn3">November 26.</note> could be understood as an
                        abandonment of a comprehensive peace and therefore would have adverse
                        repercussions. The Israelis would no doubt accept the proposal for a Cairo
                        conference instead, but we doubt if the Syrians, or main body of
                        Palestinians would, and even the Jordanians might be a problem. If Sadat
                        were to make such a proposal on Saturday, it might only serve to depict
                        Egypt as violating a commitment made to other involved parties and isolated
                        in its search for peace. While a conference other than at Geneva might
                        become a good idea at some stage in the future, provided it includes
                        Palestinians and others, we think it would be a mistake for him to propose
                        it in public speech on Saturday as an alternative to Geneva. We believe
                        Sadat would be better served, for the reasons set forth above, to restate
                        his commitment to a reconvening of the Geneva Conference as the ultimate
                        objective, even if, in practical terms, the immediate focus of Egypt’s
                        diplomatic activity will no longer be directed towards an early reconvening.
                        Such a restatement would also be entirely consistent with the line both
                        Sadat and <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> took at the
                        conclusion of their talks.</p>
                    <p>9. With respect to Sadat’s idea of having an Israeli diplomat stationed
                        clandestinely at the U.S. Embassy in Cairo, you should say that we see some
                        problems and would wish to explore other alternatives with Sadat and
                            <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> which might serve equally
                        well.</p>
                    <p>10. We see no reason why direct, continuing discussions leading to a
                        comprehensive peace settlement should not continue at the ministerial level
                        between Egypt and Israel.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"><hi rend="strong">Vance</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>