<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>170. Telegram From Secretary of State Vance to the White House and the
                    Department of State to the White House and the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">170</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-12-10T20:01:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-12-10T20:01:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008008484"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Public affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3U9TKkW5rS0s3i" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">Freedom of navigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-12-10T20:01:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-12-10T20:01:00-05:00" n="170"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                <head>170. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"
                        >Vance</persName> to the White House and the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d170fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        P840072–1437. Secret; Flash; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>
                        (Handle as <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>); <gloss
                            target="#t_Cherokee_1">Cherokee</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-12-11T01:01:00+00:00">December 11, 1977, 0101Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Secto_1">Secto</gloss> 12059. White House for President and
                    Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> Only. Department for the
                    Acting Secretary Only. Subject: Message to the President—Meeting With Sadat.</p>
                <p>1. We met this morning for about 3 hours with President <persName
                        corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> and other senior advisors, including Vice
                    President <persName corresp="#p_MH_1">Mubarak</persName>, Prime Minister Salim,
                    General Gamasy and others.<note n="2" xml:id="d170fn2">A reference to the
                        meeting on December 10; see <ref target="#d167">Document 167</ref>.</note>
                    At the outset, President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> and I
                    spent almost two hours in a private conversation. The reason for this is the
                    fact that only Vice President <persName corresp="#p_MH_1">Mubarak</persName> is
                    privy to Sadat’s thinking, and Sadat does not want to inform the others at this
                    time. During our tete-a-tete we covered the following matters.</p>
                <pb facs="0848" n="821" xml:id="pg_821"/>
                <p>2. I opened our meeting by delivering to him your letter<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d170fn3">The letter has not been found.</note> and conveying your
                    admiration and warmest best wishes. He was most appreciative and sent his
                    highest regards to you. He repeated that the inspiration for his dramatic
                    initiative had been his conversations with you and your request that bold action
                    be taken to break through the procedural tangle which was delaying the convening
                    of the Geneva Conference.</p>
                <p>3. He then turned to substance, saying that he had made a fundamental and
                    dramatic move when he went to Jerusalem and that there was now a crying need for
                    an appropriate response. He said that response should take the form of a
                    declaration by <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>: (1) That Israel is
                    willing in principle to withdraw from the Arab lands occupied in 1967, with
                    minor rectifications with respect to the West Bank; and (2) that Israel is ready
                    in principle to resolve the Palestinian question in all of its aspects. He said
                    that although it would not be necessary, he would like President <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> to join in the declaration, which could
                    be made at a meeting in Cairo at which there would be present Prime Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>, President <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1"
                        >Sadat</persName>, Secretary General <persName corresp="#p_WK_1"
                        >Waldheim</persName> and perhaps others.</p>
                <p>4. He then added that you might wish to invite <persName corresp="#p_BL_2"
                        >Brezhnev</persName> to Cairo. He said that he was sure that <persName
                        corresp="#p_BL_2">Brezhnev</persName> would not come, but that if you
                    thought it would be a good idea, it would be fine with him. He said that he
                    believed this would present the declaration in the most dramatic and effective
                    context and would accomplish his purpose of demonstrating to the Arab world that
                    he had achieved the goal which all of the Arab world sought. He added that he
                    would hope that the declaration would make some reference to his initiative.</p>
                <p>5. He stressed to me several times the importance to him that <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> make this declaration, and the need for
                    the United States to put its weight behind persuading <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> to do so. He said that he hoped the
                    declaration could be made promptly, i.e., within a week or two, as this would
                    strengthen his position in the Arab world.</p>
                <p>6. He then digressed to say that Assad had been touring various Arab capitals
                    attacking Sadat and telling the various leaders with whom he was meeting that
                    Assad was prepared to make available nuclear bases to the Soviets in the Middle
                    East, and made other threatening statements. Sadat said that such statements had
                    frightened one or two of the Mid-East leaders, particularly King Khalid. He said
                    that Prince Fahd had sent a message to him yesterday urging me to put pressure
                    on King Khalid when I came to Riyadh to support Sadat. He urged that we
                    underscore our desire for reaching a peaceful, compre<pb facs="0849" n="822"
                        xml:id="pg_822"/>hensive solution and state that we intended to stay with
                    the matter until that objective was achieved.</p>
                <p>7. Sadat then digressed again to talk about his proposal for the West Bank. He
                    said that he believed the West Bank should be put under <gloss target="#t_UN_1"
                        >UN</gloss> oversight for a transition period of five years, at the end of
                    which there would be self-determination. I asked him what he meant by
                    self-determination in light of the fact that he had stated on several occasions
                    that any Palestinian entity should be linked with Jordan. He responded initially
                    that was still his position, and that self-determination merely meant a
                    plebiscite on the question of federation or confederation with Jordan. After
                    further reflection, he said that the West Bankers should also be given the
                    option of independence. He said that this, however, was not a real option, as he
                    believed that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> was losing ground and
                    that within one year after the transition period started, the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> would no longer be a factor to be feared. He
                    said that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> had hurt its position by its
                    recent actions, and that Sadat’s own actions had further weakened their
                    influence.</p>
                <p>8. In response to my question, he indicated, however, that the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> would have to be dealt with in connection with
                    the Cairo meetings, should they ultimately decide to participate, and certainly
                    in any Geneva Conference. I asked him how this could best be done and whether or
                    not the arrangements which we had talked to <persName corresp="#p_FI_1"
                        >Fahmy</persName> about were still in the picture. He replied affirmatively,
                    saying that he was still in touch with <persName corresp="#p_AY_2"
                        >Arafat</persName> and that <persName corresp="#p_AY_2">Arafat</persName>
                    would be coming to Cairo within the next two days. He said that Palestinian
                    representation would be taken care of by the designation of a few Palestinians
                    who would be either non-<gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> or non-well-known
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>, and who had been cleared in advance
                    with the Israelis.</p>
                <p>9. Returning to the subject of an Israeli declaration, he said that after such a
                    declaration he would wish to raise participation in the Cairo meetings to the
                    Foreign Minister level. He would then want to move away from secret meetings and
                    have the Foreign Ministers working “in the daylight.” I told him that that
                    coincided with our thinking.</p>
                <p>10. Sadat went on to say that once the declaration is made he will call on all
                    the other invitees to join the Cairo meeting. I asked him whether he would also
                    call an Arab summit. He said he had not made up his mind on that point, but that
                    he would send the declara-tion to heads of the other Arab nations through an
                    Arab League representative.</p>
                <p>11. I asked Sadat what he believed should be done if it was impossible to
                    persuade the Israelis to make the declaration he had requested. He said that if
                    the declaration cannot be made as requested, it is better that no declaration be
                    made, he said that a weak declaration would <pb facs="0850" n="823"
                        xml:id="pg_823"/> hurt him, whereas he could live with no declaration, even
                    though that would, in his judgment, set back severely the peace process.</p>
                <p>12. I then asked him what he expected to come out of the initial Cairo meeting
                    and how he proposed that we should deal with the public affairs aspects of the
                    meetings. He replied that the meetings should open with the normal speeches
                    about peace and the desire of all the parties for a comprehensive solution. He
                    said that we should stress that 242 is the basis for a just and lasting peace in
                    the Middle East and therefore for this informal preparatory meeting. In terms of
                    public statements, Sadat said we should emphasize the fact that Geneva cannot
                    convene without further preparation. He said we should stress the necessity of
                    resolving the remaining procedural questions and the other necessary preparatory
                    steps in looking forward toward a comprehensive settlement in Geneva. He further
                    stated that we should emphasize that the Cairo meeting is open and that there is
                    no fixed time schedule for its completion. I said that although we would not be
                    stressing it at the outset, I assumed we would be working on basic principles to
                    convene a Geneva Conference and the preparation of an agenda and other
                    guidelines.</p>
                <p>13. I indicated to him that I thought that the Conference might ultimately
                    produce: (A) a set of principles; (B) resolution of the remaining procedural
                    problems; (C) a skeletal draft of an Egyptian-Israeli treaty; (D) perhaps a
                    draft on arrangements for the Palestinian area, i.e., the West Bank and Gaza;
                    and (E) a draft agenda.</p>
                <p>14. With respect to Gaza, he said that he wanted you to know that he is in touch
                    with the leading figures in Gaza who will be coming to see him soon, and that
                    they are backing him wholeheartedly. He added that he was prepared to give
                    additional land to Gaza in order to provide adequate port facilities and
                    additional territory.</p>
                <p>15. I then asked what message he would like us to convey to President Assad. He
                    said that we should indicate to Assad that Sadat was not seeking a partial
                    agreement and is committed to reaching a comprehensive settlement. Sadat said
                    that I should also tell Assad that Sadat is prepared to go to Geneva, or any
                    other place, to complete the peace process, and that Cairo is merely a method of
                    clearing away the procedural problems which remain and taking other steps to
                    pave the way for an ultimate Geneva Conference. In response to my question, he
                    said that he wholeheartedly supported our urging Assad to return to the peace
                    process.</p>
                <p>16. With respect to Saudi Arabia, he repeated the suggestion that I press King
                    Khalid hard to support Sadat and the peace process taking place in Cairo. He
                    suggested further that I stress that Sadat was not seeking a bilateral
                    settlement, and is committed to a comprehensive settlement.</p>
                <pb facs="0851" n="824" xml:id="pg_824"/>
                <p>17. With respect to King <persName corresp="#p_HT_1">Hussein</persName>, Sadat
                    reported on the latter’s visit to Cairo, which has just ended. He said that they
                    had reached general agreement on all items and that Hussein was backing Sadat’s
                    peace efforts. He said further that Hussein would join the Cairo meeting at the
                    appropriate time—which Sadat said would be following the Israeli declaration.
                    Sadat said they had also talked about the West Bank and that the two were in
                    agreement that the West Bank must be linked to Jordan. He said that he was
                    confident that during the transition period Hussein’s influence would increase
                    steadily and there was no question but that the West Bank would eventually be
                    linked to Jordan, rather than become an independent state.</p>
                <p>18. Sadat then told me that he planned to continue secret meetings between
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> and Touhami for the time being.
                    He said that quite frankly he would prefer to deal with <persName
                        corresp="#p_WE_1">Weizman</persName>, whom he particularly liked, but that
                    he realized that <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> was important
                    because of the unique position that he held in the Israeli picture. Sadat said
                    that he believed that there would be no problem in reaching an agreement on
                    Sinai, and this was merely a question of sitting down with <persName
                        corresp="#p_WE_1">Weizman</persName> and his experts to complete the
                    necessary work on security measures. Sadat said he did not foresee any real
                    problems in bringing this to fruition. He repeated again, however, his strong
                    preference for a comprehensive settlement.</p>
                <p>19. Sadat then expanded on what he had meant by saying that once the Israeli
                    declaration was made and the Cairo meeting was held, all those who wanted Geneva
                    should go to Geneva to complete their respective negotiations. He said that as
                    far as he was concerned he didn’t need to go to Geneva because there was no
                    problem in working out his bilateral agreement, but that he would do so because
                    of the great importance which you attached to Geneva. He then repeated his great
                    admiration for you and for the part that you had played in bringing this new
                    momentum to the peace process. He also mentioned again that if you should come
                    to Cairo at the time of the declaration, he would like to ask the United States
                    to become a party to the 1888 Constantinople Convention which provides for
                    freedom of navigation in the Suez Canal,<note n="4" xml:id="d170fn4">The United
                        States was not an signatory of the Constantinople Convention of 1888, which
                        guaranteed the right of free passage for all ships through the Suez Canal in
                        peace and war.</note> as he had previously suggested at the time of my
                    August meeting with him.</p>
                <p>20. I also discussed the question of F–5’s. Sadat said he would prefer to deal
                    with this in January by putting it in a package with <gloss target="#t_F16_1"
                        >F–16</gloss>’s for Israel and perhaps <gloss target="#t_F15_1"
                    >F–15</gloss>’s for Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <pb facs="0852" n="825" xml:id="pg_825"/>
                <p>21. In sum, we had a good talk. The most urgent thing that came out of the
                    meeting was his proposal for a two-part declaration by <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>. I am passing this on to <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> as requested and will communicate the
                    results later.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Vance</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
