<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-12-14T16:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-12-14T16:45:00-05:00" n="176" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                    <head>176. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> to the Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d176fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, P840072–1466. Secret;
                            Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss> Handle as <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>; <gloss target="#t_Cherokee_1">Cherokee</gloss>. Sent immediate for information to Cairo.
                                <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> visited Riyadh from
                            December 14 to December 15.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Riyadh</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-12-14T21:45:00+00:00">December 14, 1977, 2145Z</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_Secto_1">Secto</gloss> 12130. White House for the
                        President and <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>. Department
                        for <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Warren Christopher</persName> only. Cairo
                        for Ambassador and <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName> only.
                        Subj: Meetings With the Saudi Leadership.</p>
                    <p>1. I had a very full and good day of talks today with the Saudi leadership. I
                        met first with Foreign Minister Saud for approximately one hour and then for
                        approximately forty-five minutes with King Khaled in presence of Crown
                        Prince Fahd and Princes Abdullah, Sultan and Saud. Finished with a meeting
                        of almost two hours with Fahd at which Abdullah, Sultan and Saud were also
                            present.<note n="2" xml:id="d176fn2">Memoranda of conversation of
                                <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>’s meetings with the
                            Saudi leaders are in the Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                            Staff Material, Middle East File, Trips/Visits File, Box 108, 12/7–17/77
                                <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> Trip to the Middle
                            East: Meeting Minutes, 12/77.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>2. I gave the Saudis a full rundown on my talks with Sadat, <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>, Hussein and Assad. I underscored our
                        determination to keep up the momentum of negotiations begun by Sadat and
                            <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> and the dedication of all
                        concerned—ourselves, the Egyptians, and the Israelis—to the principle of a
                        comprehensive settlement. I filled Saudis in on <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>’s visit to Washington and on his understanding of the
                        need for steps to match those taken by Sadat. They were interested to hear
                        about the changes that Sadat’s visit to Israel has brought about in Israeli
                        thinking on the Arabs in general and the Palestinian issue in particular.
                        They emphasized that specific steps are needed soon and made clear that they
                        look to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> to bring the Israelis along.
                        They were obviously gratified and reassured by our pledge to work for a
                        comprehensive settlement. In this regard, Fahd said he thought Assad would
                        join the negotiations if Sadat were successful in getting the Israelis to
                        take the steps he has asked of them.</p>
                    <p>3. Khaled and Fahd both expressed strong support for our peace efforts. They
                        said they realized that <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> success is in
                        their own interests. They said our failure would be damaging to them as well
                        as to us and would benefit only the Communists and their friends. Khaled and
                        Fahd repeatedly made the pont that Communists are working against <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> peace efforts. Khaled gave a long
                        explanation of the initially reticent Saudi reaction to Sadat’s visit to
                        Jerusalem, indicating that it was mainly due to surprise and to Sadat’s
                        having ignored their request, <pb facs="0886" n="859" xml:id="pg_859"/> once
                        Sadat had announced the visit, to delay it. But Fahd said “We support what
                        is happening”, and he, Khaled and Saud all urged us to use our influence
                        with the Israelis to bring about the sort of Israeli reciprocal move that
                        Sadat needs.</p>
                    <p>4. Saud spoke at length about, and Fahd also stressed, Saudi concern that the
                        Israelis might try to use Sadat’s visit to Jerusalem to legitimize their
                        presence there. He warned that this would be a grave mistake. He said he
                        hoped the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> would not take Sadat’s visit to
                        Jerusalem as a reason to move our Embassy there. I assured him that we had
                        no plans to move our Embassy from Tel Aviv. Fahd also mentioned the
                        importance of a just settlement of the Palestinian question, but did not
                        dwell on it and seemed to be raising it more out of duty than anything
                        else.</p>
                    <p>5. I conveyed your appreciation for Saudi Arabia’s leadership in the move for
                        a freeze on oil prices. Khaled said <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> is
                        vigorously pursuing its efforts for a freeze and thinks they will be
                        successful. Khaled noted that in addition to Iran, Kuwait, Qatar and Abu
                        Dhabi are now with Saudis on this issue, and he said the President of
                        Venezuela had sent him a message saying Venezuela would vote with the
                        majority. Khaled pointed out that the main advocates of a price increase,
                        Libya and Algeria, are also the states that are stirring up trouble. “We
                        don’t want to help them” he said.</p>
                    <p>6. In our subsequent conversation, Fahd expressed concern that the drop in
                        the value of the dollar would impede Saudi efforts to secure an oil price
                        freeze. Those in <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> who want a price
                        increase would use the downward trend of the dollar to butress their
                        arguments. He noted that it was also a matter of concern to the Saudi
                        Government because it affected the value of Saudi holdings in the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>. I assured Fahd that the problem of the
                        value of the dollar is a matter of highest priority for the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> Government.</p>
                    <p>7. Fahd also raised the question of Saudi Arabia’s request for <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> arms, stressing the <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss>’s need to show the Saudi people and the military that the
                        country has weapons to defend itself and pointing to the danger from Iraq
                        and South Yemen, both of which receive Soviet arms. Fahd said it was urgent
                        now that the Saudis see something done soon. I said I had already begun
                        talks with key members of Congress regarding the Saudi request for <gloss target="#t_F15_1">F–15</gloss>s, that the response was generally good
                        and that we would go forward in January with a proposal to Congress.</p>
                    <p>8. We also discussed the Horn and Aden. The Saudis clearly would like us to
                        do more for Somalia but did not raise request that we provide arms. Fahd
                        said that, in response to Saudi intercession, the Somalis had assured Kenya
                        that they have no territorial ambitions in Kenya. I stressed the need for
                        Somalia to take advantage of the current situation <pb facs="0887" n="860" xml:id="pg_860"/> to move for a negotiated settlement, and Fahd agreed.
                        They will wish to raise the question of Somalia during your visit as they
                        consider the Horn to be the most pressing problem after that of a Middle
                        East settlement. On Aden, the Saudis share our concern over the possibility
                        that the Soviets will be given facilities there to replace those they lost
                        at Berbera. [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines not declassified</hi>] Fahd said
                        they would keep the Aden regime under close scrutiny. He asked that we
                        continue to hold up on sending diplomatic representation to Aden and I
                        agreed to do so.</p>
                    <p>9. To sum up, it is clear that now that their initial shock is past—Saud said
                        people in Saudi Arabia wept in grief at the sight of Sadat in Jerusalem—the
                        Saudis very much want Sadat to succeed and are counting heavily on us to use
                        our influence with the Israelis. They themselves will undoubtedly do
                        everything they can to help Sadat short of publicly taking his side in his
                        polemic with the other Arabs. They see their role as one of working to heal
                        the rift in Arab ranks and quietly bring the Syrians and Palestinians into
                        the peace effort, and this undoubtedly is where they can be most effective.
                        Their remarks on Jerusalem are a reminder of the importance that they attach
                        to that issue and their sensitivity about it. They confirm that while the
                        Saudis may be expected to accept anything agreeable to the other Arabs on
                        most aspects of a settlement, they will want to be consulted closely on
                        Jerusalem and will probably have very specific views about it.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"><hi rend="strong">Vance</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>