<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>271. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d271</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">271</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-07-19T03:20:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-07-19T03:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recd7021a58b486ded" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="suez-canal" subject="suez-canal">Suez Canal</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-07-19T03:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-07-19T03:20:00-05:00" n="271"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d271">
                <head>271. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d271fn1"
                        >Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Staff Material, Middle
                        East Subject File, Box 2, Arab-Israeli Peace Negotiations 1978: Volume II
                        [II]. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_LSW_1">Lewis</persName>. The meeting took place at Leeds
                        Castle.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Kent, England</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1978-07-19T09:20:00+01:00"
                            >July 19, 1978, 9:20 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Talks—Middle East Peace Negotiations</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">U.S.</hi>:</item>
                    <item>Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LSW_1">Lewis</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Israel</hi>:</item>
                    <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_BA_1">Barak</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>The Secretary opened the discussion by making a few introductory comments about
                    the progress of the first day’s meetings, stressing that he thought that they
                    had been useful although by no means represented any breakthroughs. He asked
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> what he thought would be the
                    most useful way to approach the next phase of discussions.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said he did not know whether the
                    Egyptians would agree to any further meetings. The Secretary said that <persName
                        corresp="#p_KM_1">Kamel</persName> is not authorized at present to do so,
                    but that he would push him further. He intended to say he would come to the area
                    in about two weeks, and he would press Sadat to agree that a meeting be held
                    during that period. <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said that any
                    place convenient to the Secretary is all right with the Israelis. The Secretary
                    said the same was true for the United States, but that it <pb facs="1253"
                        n="1226" xml:id="pg_1226"/> would be best to be an expanded format with
                    defense ministers and foreign ministers both participating.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> then went through a long series of
                    comments about how he saw the present state of negotiations. First, he said,
                    it’s clear there is no chance to get the Israeli government to commit itself in
                    advance to full withdrawal from the West Bank and Gaza. “I’ve explained what is
                    feasible. Had I been the Egyptians, I would have compromised, taken at this
                    point what they can get from the Israeli cabinet for the Palestinians, that is,
                    a great degree of self rule. And, ultimately they would, therefore, be able to
                    show the Palestinians that they had achieved a great deal of progress for them,
                    on the way toward independence. They won’t get a precommitment from this
                    government for total withdrawal, and I’m afraid that Jordan won’t come into the
                    negotiations”. The Secretary agreed with <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Dayan</persName>’s observation about Jordan.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> went on to say that he doubted very
                    much whether Egypt will be able to sign any peace treaty for the West Bank, even
                    with some Palestinians sitting with them, since Jordan will hang back. At
                    present, he said, Egypt could make some sort of agreement but not a full peace
                    treaty. And in any case, they would do it in stages, even if Jordan were
                    participating. So, therefore, the Israelis would have to live with this kind of
                    procedure “if we can’t get anything better.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> then said he would like to outline
                    his assessment of what he thought might be done. He stressed that the ideas were
                    extremely sensitive and should have no further distribution “beyond the four of
                    us.” He recalled that in Sadat’s recent meeting with <persName corresp="#p_WE_1"
                        >Weizman</persName>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d271fn2">For a report on Sadat’s meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_WE_1">Weizman</persName>, see <ref target="#d265">Document
                            265</ref>.</note> he had brought up the idea of a unilateral Israeli
                    withdrawal in Sinai to the line connecting Al-Arish and Ras Mohammed. “If we
                    can’t get a full agreement, maybe this is a possibility, but not as a unilateral
                    gesture by Israel. Rather it would have to be the result of a real negotiation.”
                    It might be easier for Sadat to make such an agreement than full peace, since he
                    would have most of the real assets in Sinai (the Gulf of Suez, the oil fields,
                    Al-Arish, the major Israeli air bases, Rafadim, and so forth), but could still
                    say credibly to the other Arabs that he had not gotten all of his land back nor
                    made a “separate peace.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> stressed that the Israeli cabinet
                    has not agreed to any such ideas, and would not propose itself such a
                    negotiation for a partial withdrawal. However, he said, if Sadat proposes that,
                    it is a real possibility and Gamasy would see real military advantages in it.
                    “We shall certainly ask for quid pro quos, such as something with respect to
                    pledges of no more war and some of the elements of full peace.” Obvi<pb
                        facs="1254" n="1227" xml:id="pg_1227"/>ously, he said, he would prefer total
                    peace, but something is better than nothing.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> then continued: “So if we combine
                    the two conclusions that Jordan is not likely to join, and yet Egypt wants to go
                    ahead, then perhaps Egypt would wish to go ahead on such a partial step.” He
                    would not rule out the possibility that Sadat might make full peace just over
                    Gaza, but he doubted it.</p>
                <p>The Secretary responded that these ideas of <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Dayan</persName>’s were well worth thinking further about, but that he
                    would like to come back for a moment to the larger issue. If, he said, Sadat
                    could achieve a broad commitment on principle, then the Secretary thought he
                    would sign an agreement on the West Bank and Gaza without Hussein. “He’s said as
                    much to me. That then takes us back to what happens after the first five year
                    period. You said yesterday with regard to your security requirements on the West
                    Bank that they did depend in part upon the territory—that security cannot be
                    separated from land and borders. But what about substituting well-defined rights
                    and land, for example, the right to maintain your security forces idefinitely in
                    the West Bank as required and agreed upon?”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> responded that if the sovereignty
                    lodges elsewhere, the government could throw out Israeli forces at any time.</p>
                <p>The Secretary argued that with a binding agreement, and the forces themselves
                    present to protect that agreement, there would be no danger.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said that unfortunately it is in
                    the essence of the concept of sovereignty that any sovereign power can abrogate
                    an agreement if it chooses to do so, and “there are many precedents.” <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said he knows his position was not the
                    one which the Secretary wanted to hear; therefore, why not check it with the
                    Israeli cabinet when the Secretary came to the area? “Maybe I’m wrong.” The
                    Secretary said he would do so.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> then described a conversation he
                    had had with <persName corresp="#p_QWB_1">Bill Quandt</persName> at dinner about
                    an idea concerning the Israeli right to purchase land.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d271fn3">No record of this discussion was found.</note> He said he
                    knew that a dinner conversation had no official status, but he would be
                    interested in discussing <persName corresp="#p_QWB_1">Quandt</persName>’s idea
                    further. The idea would be, he said, that Israelis would have permanent rights
                    to purchase land in the West Bank and Gaza from private individuals, while all
                    of the state-owned lands would be under control of the Arab administrative
                    authorities who might refuse to sell any of it to Israelis. If this concept were
                    combined with free access for the Palestinian residents to both Jordan and
                    Israel, it could be an important concept. “And if we <pb facs="1255" n="1228"
                        xml:id="pg_1228"/> could overcome the key obstacles of security arrangements
                    and the rights for Israelis to purchase land there to settle, we would be going
                    a long way toward a solution.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said he thought that the real
                    obstacle now is not “in the actual concept but in the Egyptian demand for a
                    precommitment about the ultimate outcome.”</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that Sadat has to be able to say convincingly to his Arab
                    brethren that the Israeli occupancy is ended. “Yet he knows that your security
                    must be protected, and that the problem of protecting it is different in the
                    West Bank than in Sinai. How can you help to put him in the position to deal
                    with both these requirements?”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said that hearing this point, he
                    felt a little better about the possibility of finding a relative formula to
                    achieve Sadat’s goal. “Let’s define what the Israeli occupation really consists
                    of. Let’s see what has to be done to put an end to it, in particular to the
                    various elements of it. You agree that we need some Israeli forces at particular
                    points for our security—this is not the same as an occupation force. For
                    Israelis to purchase land from an individual in the West Bank just as they can
                    purchase land from individuals in the United States or in Europe is surely not
                    occupation.” I agree personally, he said, that the formula should be that we
                    have no occupation forces in the territories, and then we must agree exactly on
                    what is needed to end that occupation as it has been more precisely defined.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that this was why we had posed the first question to the
                    Israelis about making a definite decision on sovereignty in the way we had
                    framed it. “The way things look at present, with your answer to our question
                    about what happens after five years, the Arabs believe that not only are you an
                    occupying power but that the occupancy will be permanent since you have no idea
                    of ever relinquishing your sovereignty claim.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said, “Without the sovereignty,
                    we’re in trouble with <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>. If we were
                    to give up our claim to sovereignty, that inevitably means that eventually there
                    will be some form of Arab sovereignty. Then the issue will become how binding
                    any agreements might be if an Arab sovereign government will be able to
                    repudiate them. Any sovereign state can abolish an agreement, just look at the
                    Constantinople agreement concerning the Suez Canal<note n="4" xml:id="d271fn4">A
                        reference to the Constantinople Convention of 1888, which declared the free
                        navigation of the Suez Canal at all times and defined the regulations
                        related to its security and neutrality.</note> as only one of many
                    examples.”</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that he could, however, conceive of an agreement involving
                    Israel, Jordan, and the Palestinians which included an <pb facs="1256" n="1229"
                        xml:id="pg_1229"/> Israeli renunciation of its sovereign claim in exchange
                    for perpetual rights to have security forces in the West Bank, guaranteed free
                    access and open borders, rights for Israelis to purchase lands in the West Bank,
                    and so forth—all ratified in some fashion by the Palestinian residents of the
                    territories. He said such an agreement would indeed be binding.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said, “I don’t think <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> would agree.”</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he understood, but that if only the Israelis’ answer to our
                    first question had been positive, the Egyptians, the Saudis, the Jordanians, and
                    all of the moderate Arabs would have seen the situation totally differently.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> then returned to his basic thesis:
                    that for the Egyptians the best thing is to get <persName corresp="#p_BM_2"
                        >Begin</persName> and the Israeli cabinet to go as far on the West Bank as
                    is possible now. He said that the United States could assure the Arabs that a
                    great deal more would be possible after five years, obviously our influence with
                    Israel would continue to be very great. “If I were an Arab, I would think that
                    gives us a very good chance.” But in any event, that’s all you can get from a
                        <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> government. If you press
                        <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> for more, you won’t get it. But
                    if you want to try for more with him, you should certainly do so.
                    “Realistically, however, the best thing to do is to convince Sadat that he can’t
                    get everything he wants now; he can get some now, more later during the five
                    years, and a good chance for a decision about ultimate sovereignty after five
                    years. But he can get no commitment on that point at this stage. And I don’t
                    exclude the idea of some sharing of sovereignty after five years, beginning with
                    Jerusalem. When Sadat told <persName corresp="#p_WE_1">Weizman</persName> in
                    talking about Jerusalem that he would not care which faction was over the city,
                    so long as it was an Islamic flag, that was what I had proposed unsuccessfully
                    in 1967—though <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> opposed me.”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> insisted that what the Palestinians
                    want is some form of autonomy and independence within the Arab world, but a way
                    to maintain contacts with Israel. “Let’s work it out that way.” But if you ask
                        <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> today for a commitment to a
                    discussion about sovereignty in the future, he won’t give it—he knows that there
                    is no ralistic possibility of Israeli sovereignty’s being chosen—and that means
                    that in practice he is committing himself to turn over sovereignty to the
                    Arabs.</p>
                <p>The Secretary then said he would like to ask about the idea about a limited right
                    of self-determination excluding independence as an option. “What’s wrong with
                    that from the Israeli standpoint?”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> responded that what bothered him is
                    not a question of options, but rather that the suggested system of a referendum
                    or plebiscite would subject the process to intolerable <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> intimidation. He reminded the Secretary that the Israelis try
                    to distinguish between the people in the territories and the territories
                    themselves. “I have no <pb facs="1257" n="1230" xml:id="pg_1230"/> problem with
                    the Palestinians’ deciding what relationship they want individually or
                    collectively with Jordan or other neighbors. But they cannot make alone the
                    decision about the land, where some Israelis will also be living. If the
                    Palestinian Arabs determine themselves alone the future of the land, then
                    whoever holds sovereignty could restrict the rights and security of the Israelis
                    resident in the land.” Now in some areas, he said, particularly in Gaza, the
                    Arab population is such that there is no practical possibility for Israeli
                    settlement. In such areas, the practical distinction between decisions about the
                    population’s relationship with others and decisions about the land would be
                    practically meaningless, but where there is a possibility of future Israeli
                    settlement, as in much of the West Bank, the distinction is important.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> pointed out that if the phraseology
                    about self-determination contained in the Egyptian proposals were augmented by a
                    phrase “through talks among . . .” then you would have a very similar concept,
                    so long as it is clear that the Palestinians involved in the discussion were the
                    people living there rather than all Palestinians in other parts of the Arab
                    world.</p>
                <p>The Secretary then pointed out that there was one positive area in the
                    discussions the day before: you reached general agreement on how to deal with
                    the terrorist problem.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> agreed though he said it would be
                    difficult to reach an understanding on how to handle “public order.” The
                    definition of roles between local police and the Israeli security forces would
                    have to be carefully hammered out, and it would be difficult. However, this kind
                    of detailed discussion is covered in the Egyptian proposal and he liked that
                    aspect of it.</p>
                <p>The Secretary again returned to the problem of “withdrawal”. He said that the
                    biggest problem for the Egyptians and the Arabs are these two concepts:
                    “sovereignty” and “withdrawal”.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> said he saw three sticking points:
                    sovereignty, withdrawal, and occupation. With respect to these three concepts:
                    “Maybe we could reach agreement, as we discussed earlier, on how to deal with
                    the problem of Israeli occupation; on sovereignty, the most we can do is to
                    agree to discuss the subject after five years, as we have done; and as to
                    withdrawal, perhaps we could agree on your formula under which Israeli security
                    forces would stay but Israeli occupation forces would be withdrawn, clearly
                    distinguishing between the two kinds of forces.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said that Sadat understands this latter distinction with regard to
                    types of forces, and is prepared to have forces for security purposes remain in
                    the West Bank, certainly for five years, “and, I believe, for beyond five years
                    as well.” He said that the Egyptians stress the need to abolish the military
                    government and to allow the Palestinians to take over responsibility for their
                    own self-government. He <pb facs="1258" n="1231" xml:id="pg_1231"/> said he saw
                    a number of parallels in some of the phrases in the Egyptian plan to the
                    comments <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> had just made.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> agreed, read some sections from the
                    Israeli base plan and stressed the Israeli intention to abolish the military
                    government. Both he and <persName corresp="#p_BA_1">Barak</persName> mentioned
                    the fact that he had not succeeded the previous day in getting clearly across to
                        <persName corresp="#p_KM_1">Kamel</persName> this distinction between
                    occupying forces and security forces.</p>
                <p>The conversation concluded with some discussion about how to deal with the press
                    after the conference ended.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
