<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-06-30T08:52:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-06-30T08:52:00-05:00" n="45" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d45">
                    <head>45. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Egypt<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d45fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                            P850052–2006. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Niact_1">Niact</gloss>
                            Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by
                                <persName corresp="#p_VNA_1">Veliotes</persName>; cleared by
                                <persName corresp="#p_QWB_1">Quandt</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VRD_1">Robert Vine</persName> (<gloss target="#t_EUR_1">EUR</gloss>), <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>,
                            Larry MacFarlane (<gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>), <persName corresp="#p_ST_1">Talcott Seelye</persName> (AF), and <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName>; and approved by Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-06-30T13:52:00+00:00">June 30, 1977, 1352Z</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <p>152347. For Ambassador. Subject: <persName corresp="#p_FI_1">Fahmy</persName>’s Talks in Moscow. Ref: Cairo 10380.<note n="2" xml:id="d45fn2">In telegram 10380 from Cairo, June 21, the Embassy
                            reported Sadat’s detailed summary of Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_FI_1">Fahmy</persName>’s talks with Soviet Premier
                                <persName corresp="#p_BL_2">Brezhnev</persName> and Soviet Foreign
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA_1">Gromyko</persName>. (National
                            Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                            File, P850052–2101)</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>1. Please pass to Sadat as soon as possible following oral message from
                        President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> in response to
                        Sadat’s request for his views reported in <gloss target="#t_reftel_1">reftel</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> text: President very much
                        appreciates Sadat’s frankness in sharing such detailed account of <persName corresp="#p_FI_1">Fahmy</persName>’s discussions in Moscow. In general,
                        President believes Sadat’s analysis concerning Soviet motivations and
                        intentions is accurate. In this respect, the Soviets clearly want to find
                        ways to reestablish their position in the Mideast, which they lost in large
                        measure through President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>’s
                        farsighted and statesmanlike actions, and are obviously very nervous about
                        their prospects for success in the Horn of Africa.</p>
                    <p>—President believes heavy-handed Soviet tactics indicate that they clearly
                        continue to underestimate President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>’s determination <pb facs="0350" n="323" xml:id="pg_323"/> and commitment to pursuit of an independent national
                        policy for Egypt. President also concludes that current Soviet efforts are
                        obvious attempt to drive wedge between U.S. and Egypt with respect both to
                        Middle East and Africa. We believe that this can only be interpreted as
                        Soviet reaction to success of Sadat’s policies in the area which have the
                        support of other important African and Middle East countries as well as U.S.
                        This strongly suggests that the Soviets are worried that their strategies
                        may not succeed.</p>
                    <p>—President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> knows that Sadat
                        requires no advice on how to deal with such Soviet maneuvers and pressure
                        tactics. He would, however, wish to reaffirm his own deep respect for
                        President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>’s judgment in these
                        matters.</p>
                    <p>3. As concerns <persName corresp="#p_BL_2">Brezhnev</persName>’s comments on
                        the Middle East, we cannot exclude the possibility that the Soviets are
                        trying to exploit the uncertainties which some parties in the area, that are
                        hostile to both the U.S. and Egypt, are trying to foment with respect to the
                        U.S. commitment to the peace process in the aftermath of the <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> victory.</p>
                    <p>—The <persName corresp="#p_BL_2">Brezhnev</persName> statements on U.S.
                        policy are, to say the least, contradictory and, in any event, not to be
                        taken seriously. We hesitate to dignify them by attempting to address them
                        in any detail. It should suffice to note that U.S. interests (clearly more
                        so than Soviet interests) require a peace settlement and our mutual goal is
                        a comprehensive settlement. Neither the President nor Sadat has ever
                        underestimated the difficulties involved.</p>
                    <p>—In this respect, President <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>
                        knows he can count on President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s commitment to the peace process which he conveyed
                        during Sadat’s visit to Washington. President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> is very grateful for Sadat’s confirmation of their
                        agreements in their private talks during his visit to Washington.</p>
                    <p>—We are now preparing for very frank talks with <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> to impress on his government the need for early
                        progress towards Geneva. We will of course keep in close touch and President
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> expects Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> to be back in the area in
                        late July–early August.</p>
                    <p>—President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> wants to reassure
                        Sadat that we are being as responsive as possible concerning the military
                        requirements of our friends. In this respect, the President has again
                        reviewed the situation concerning military equipment for Egypt on the basis
                        of initial soundings with the Congress. As a result, the President has
                        decided to move ahead with efforts to obtain early Congressional approval
                        for the items Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EHF_1">Eilts</persName>
                        discussed with Sadat, despite the difficulties we anticipate.</p>
                    <p>—Although this is not fully responsive to Egypt’s needs, if Congress approves
                        we hope it will have a political and psychological significance beyond the
                        actual items involved. The President wishes <pb facs="0351" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/> Sadat to know that he is keeping this general subject
                        under continuing review.</p>
                    <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to the Middle East dispute.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"><hi rend="strong">Vance</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>