<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>80. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d80</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">80</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-08-09T10:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-08-09T10:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        withdrawal</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-08-09T10:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-08-09T10:40:00-05:00" n="80"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d80">
                <head>80. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d80fn1"
                        >Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName> Material, Country File, Box 50,
                        Middle East: 7–9/77. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. The
                        meeting took place at the Prime Ministry. All brackets are in the
                        original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Jerusalem</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1977-08-09T17:40:00+02:00"
                            >August 9, 1977, 5:40 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Israelis</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Menahem Begin</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Moshe Dayan</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Finance Minister Simcha Ehrlich</item>
                    <item>Interior Minister Yosef Burg</item>
                    <item>Defense Minister <persName corresp="#p_WE_1">Ezer Weizman</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Agriculture Minister <persName corresp="#p_SA_3">Ariel Sharon</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DS_1">Simcha Dinitz</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_EE_1">Ephraim Evron</persName>, Director General,
                        Ministry of Foreign Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KS_1">Shmuel Katz</persName>, Advisor to the Prime
                        Minister</item>
                    <item>General <persName corresp="#p_PE_1">Ephraim Poran</persName>, Military
                        Secretary to the Prime Minister</item>
                    <item>Attorney General <persName corresp="#p_BA_1">Barak</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Americans</hi>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Cyrus Vance</persName>, Secretary of
                        State</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Philip Habib</persName>, Under Secretary for
                        Political Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Alfred L. Atherton, Jr.</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary of State for Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs</item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LSW_1">Samuel Lewis</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1">Harold Saunders</persName>, Director <gloss
                            target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_QWB_1">William B. Quandt</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staff</item>
                    <item>Arthur Day, Deputy Assistant Secretary</item>
                    <item>John Crump, Political Counselor, <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                        Embassy</item>
                    <item>Hodding <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary of State (<gloss target="#t_PA_1">PA</gloss>)</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>
                    </hi> welcomed Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> to Israel
                    for continuation of talks between the two countries. He asked the Secretary to
                    begin with a report on the results of his trip. <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>
                    </hi> expressed his appreciation for the opportunity to meet with the Prime
                    Minister and to report on his visit in the Arab countries. He stated that he
                    would cover the responses of the Arab leaders to the Israeli peace proposals,
                    which he raised as the first item of business in each country. Then he <pb
                        facs="0454" n="427" xml:id="pg_427"/> would cover procedural issues, and
                    finally substantive points, with reference to the five principles previously
                    discussed with the Prime Minister. He would then suggest some possibilities for
                    proceeding in the future.</p>
                <p>Concerning Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>’s
                        proposal,<note n="2" xml:id="d80fn2">See the Attachment to <ref
                            target="#d52">Document 52</ref>.</note> the Arabs had no objections to
                    the first and second parts. On the third part, all of the leaders objected
                    because the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> was not included. On the fourth
                    point, they argued that Israel is setting conditions on borders, the Palestinian
                    question, and Jerusalem, and this is inconsistent with the statement concerning
                    negotiations without preconditions. They have no objection to the fifth point,
                    but on the proposal for mixed commissions they have a variety of objections. One
                    said that there should be no national mixed commissions, but rather there should
                    be functional groups dealing with questions such as the Palestinians,
                    guarantees, and military withdrawal. Another said that the Palestinian question
                    must be resolved first and that the question of mixed commissions is premature.
                    These were the two principal areas of disagreement. On the seventh point
                    concerning peace treaties, all accepted the word “peace treaties” instead of
                    “peace agreements.” The <hi rend="italic">Prime Minister</hi> said that he was
                    pleased to hear this. He asked if Syria had also accepted this. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Secretary</hi> said they had. They had, however, objected to
                    the mixed commission idea contained in that paragraph. On the eighth point,
                    involving chairmanship by rotation, there were a variety of objections. The Arab
                    leaders felt that the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> or one of the
                    co-chairmen of the conference should chair the committees. Another leader
                    objected to the principle of rotation entirely, but accepted the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> or the co-chairmen. On paragraph nine, the Arabs
                    only objected to the reference to diplomatic relations. On the alternatives
                    suggested by Israel, on the first alternative relying on Rhodes procedures for
                    talks, the Arabs would not exclude this as a possibility if the Palestinians
                    were included, but if the Palestinians are excluded, then they would object.
                    Concerning proximity talks, the problem was again the noninclusion of
                    Palestinians in the framework. They did not, however, exclude bilateral
                    conversations through an intermediary; but they do not accept mixed commissions
                    which exclude the Palestinians. That in brief is the response of the Arabs to
                    the Israeli proposals.</p>
                <p>On the question of procedures, the <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi> raised the
                    issue of how to proceed to Geneva. The first question was how to deal with the
                    structure of delegations. We went through the four alternatives that we
                    discussed in Washington:<note n="3" xml:id="d80fn3">See <ref target="#d52"
                            >Documents 52</ref> and <ref target="#d57">57</ref>.</note> the
                    inclusion of Palestinians in a national Arab delegation such as Jordan;
                    inclusion of Palestinians in a unified <pb facs="0455" n="428" xml:id="pg_428"/>
                    Arab delegation; agreement in advance that the Palestinian issue would be on the
                    agenda and that Palestinians would participate when the issue came to the fore;
                    agreement in advance that the Palestinian issue would be on the agenda and that
                    modalities for Palestinian participation would be discussed at the conference.
                    Each of the Arab leaders indicated that the latter two alternatives were not
                    acceptable. The discussion therefore focused on the first two alternatives—the
                    inclusion of Palestinians in a Jordanian delegation and in a united Arab
                    delegation. The Secretary reported the Prime Minister’s ideas on the Jordanian
                    delegation—Israel would consider accepting Palestinians in a Jordanian
                    delegation, and their credentials would not be examined, but no known <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> member could participate. Each Arab leader
                    said this was unacceptable. The <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> would not
                    agree and they could not agree either. The inclusion of the Palestinians in an
                    Arab delegation was accepted by all but one of the leaders as the best solution.
                    One leader believed that there should be national delegations at Geneva, plus
                    one other delegation for Palestine headed by the Assistant Secretary General of
                    the Arab League, who happens to be the Chief of Staff of the Egyptian Army. In
                    that delegation there would be other individuals from Arab countries and
                    Palestinians, including some Palestinian mayors from the West Bank, for example.
                    When this was discussed with other Arab leaders, it was viewed as interesting,
                    but not realistic. In brief, four Arab leaders favor a unified Arab delegation
                    including Palestinians, and one has a reservation about that alternative.
                    Foreign Minister <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>
                    </hi> asked whether the Secretary could inform the Israeli side if the
                    objections on some points came from the front-line countries or only from Saudi
                    Arabia. The <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi> replied that the one country
                    opposed to a unified Arab delegation was one of the confrontation states. He
                    also expressed his view that if the other Arab countries favor a unified Arab
                    delegation, all of the parties on the Arab side would agree. This is a
                    prediction, since one party still has not formally accepted the idea of a
                    unified delegation.</p>
                <p>On the Palestinian question, the <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi> stated that the
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> has asked to establish contact with the
                    United States and that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> has refused
                    because of its commitment under Sinai II. When we arrived in Egypt, the question
                    was raised of whether we were prepared to talk with the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> and the Secretary gave the Egyptians the answer that the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> must accept 242 first. We would, however,
                    understand the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> stating a reservation to the
                    effect that Resolution 242 does not adequately deal with the Palestinian
                    question, because it refers only to refugees and not to a homeland. If 242 is
                    otherwise clearly accepted, this would satisfy us. Some language was shown to us
                    in Egypt, but it did not meet these requirements. The same question was raised
                    in Damascus, although no language was proposed. But the Syrians did urge that we
                    make contact with the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>. In Amman, the same
                    discussion <pb facs="0456" n="429" xml:id="pg_429"/> took place. In Taif, the
                    question was raised again, and two variations of language that the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> might be ready to issue were presented. Again,
                    neither was acceptable to meet our needs on this issue. The Secretary stressed
                    that the key point was Israel’s right to exist as a state. Until this was
                    acknowledged, we could not talk to the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>.
                    Whether the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> would be forthcoming, the
                    Secretary could not say. There were indications in each capital that a
                    satisfactory formulation would emerge, but none as yet has been received. <hi
                        rend="italic">Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>
                    </hi> asked whether we had amended any of the drafts we saw. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Secretary</hi> said that we presented our view that the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> would have to accept Resolution 242, although
                    we would understand their reserving their position on the refugee clause. That
                    would meet our criteria. It is clear that Resolution 242 means that each state
                    has a right to exist and live in peace within secure and recognized boundaries.
                    In Taif, we were asked if talking to the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>
                    would mean that they could go to Geneva. The Secretary replied that the question
                    of who participates at Geneva has to be settled by the parties. He would not be
                    able to answer that question. That is where the situation stands. <hi
                        rend="italic">Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>
                    </hi> thanked the Secretary for his review of the issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>
                    </hi> continued with a review of the reactions to the five principles that were
                    discussed in each stop. [The Secretary read the full text of each of the
                    principles before describing the reactions of the various parties.] On principle
                    one, there was no disagreement. On principle two, there were also no objections.
                    On principle three, no one objected to the first clause on the termination of
                    the state of war. Objections were raised by two of the parties on the phrase
                    “normal peaceful relations.” One of the parties would accept the language as
                    written. One would accept it if the language expressed the development of
                    peaceful relations over time. One objected to the language without suggesting
                    any alternative. One wanted to modify the language somewhat. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Prime Minister</hi> asked if we could give details on the
                    positions of each country. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>
                    </hi> replied that he thought it would not be inconsistent with what he had said
                    to the parties to reveal their positions, provided that such information not
                    leave this room. Jordan, he said, accepts the principle as it is now written.
                    Saudi Arabia would suggest minor modifications. Egypt believes that it should be
                    changed, but offered no suggestions. The same was true for Syria. <hi
                        rend="italic">The Prime Minister</hi> asked if the normalization of
                    relations over time had come from the Egyptians. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Secretary</hi> said they had not suggested that wording, but had merely
                    stated that they could not accept the point as it was written. The Secretary did
                    say, however, that he thought they could accept the phrase “over time.” Nor
                    would he rule out Syrian acceptance of that language. There is a beginning of
                    movement on this issue, and we are seeing the effects of the American insistence
                    on real peace.</p>
                <pb facs="0457" n="430" xml:id="pg_430"/>
                <p>On point four, Israel had objected to the phrase “on all fronts.” We presented
                    the point as our view, noting that Israel did not accept the principle. On point
                    four, Sadat called for withdrawal to the 1967 lines in Sinai and Golan, and
                    would only accept minor modifications on the West Bank. Assad’s view was the
                    same. King <persName corresp="#p_HT_1">Hussein</persName> called for full
                    withdrawal to the 1967 lines, with minor reciprocal modifications on the West
                    Bank. He also raised the question of Jerusalem. Fahd supported return to the
                    1967 lines, with minor modifications on the West Bank. He also raised the
                    question of Jerusalem. He and Hussein took the position that east Jerusalem
                    should return to Arab sovereignty, there should be a unified city, with Arab
                    sovereignty in the east and Israeli sovereignty in the west. They support open
                    access to the holy places. On the phrasing in point four of implementation of
                    withdrawal over a period of years, some felt that the timing should be shorter.
                    On the final sentence, there was no objection. The <hi rend="italic">Prime
                        Minister</hi> asked if there was any question of external guarantees. The
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi> said that it was not raised in this
                    context, but that it had been mentioned elsewhere. <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>
                    </hi> asked if when the Arabs spoke of east Jerusalem under Arab sovereignty,
                    whether they meant the 1967 lines. The <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi>
                    confirmed that they did, including all of the old city.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> then read the fifth principle. All of the
                    Arab parties agree with the first sentence concerning the need for a Palestinian
                    entity. They all accept the need for self-determination. Assad objected to the
                    sentence of no militarization of the entity. He thought that such a provision
                    would be unacceptable and that it should not be included. The Secretary argued
                    this with President Assad, telling him that his position did not make sense,
                    that it would have to be demilitarized, and that it was not feasible or
                    realistic for the entity to have its own arms. Sadat emphasized that he favors a
                    link to Jordan, and that this should be announced before Geneva. <hi
                        rend="italic">Minister Burg</hi> asked whether the question of a corridor
                    had been raised. <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> said that this was not
                    Sadat’s idea, but that he was talking rather about a political link to Jordan.
                    Sadat agreed to the need for a Palestinian entity, but wanted a political link
                    to Jordan before Geneva. The others all felt that such a link should not be
                    determined before Geneva, but should result from the negotiations at Geneva. <hi
                        rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> noted that he had made it clear that Israel
                    objected to the fifth principle in its entirety.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary</hi> added that he believed it was possible to
                    make progress toward Geneva despite the differences. He and the President both
                    believe that if momentum is not continued, an opportunity may be lost and a
                    period of stagnation may begin. Then we might slip back from the present
                    positions. The Secretary said that he believed that efforts should be
                    intensified to narrow differences on procedure and substance and this should be
                    done soon. He noted that he had asked each <pb facs="0458" n="431"
                        xml:id="pg_431"/> of the leaders to prepare, if they were willing, a draft
                    of a peace treaty. This would be transmitted to him. He would not give it to
                    anyone else. He asked for concrete language describing their positions on each
                    of the issues. <hi rend="italic">The Prime Minister</hi> asked if he had
                    suggested that the drafts be provided only to him. <hi rend="italic">The
                        Secretary</hi> said that he had. Egypt would send a draft of an
                    Egyptian-Israeli treaty to the United States; Syria and Jordan would be asked to
                    do the same. The question was also raised in Lebanon. The Lebanese want to go to
                    Geneva, and the Secretary told them that the Israelis do not object, and he
                    therefore asked them also for a draft. They did not commit themselves to deliver
                    a draft, but they took a positive attitude toward the idea. The Secretary told
                    them that they might send in their ideas in any form, but that it was important
                    to provide detail on the central issues. The Secretary suggested that at the
                    time of the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> General Assembly that all of the
                    foreign ministers should be in New York so that the Secretary could move between
                    the parties to narrow differences. In general, there was a positive reaction to
                    the suggestion. These would be bilateral talks with each foreign minister,
                    although the Secretary said that he would not exclude that there might be
                    opportunities for them to talk with one another.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>
                    </hi> asked if the idea of trusteeship had been raised. <hi rend="italic">The
                        Secretary</hi> said the idea arose in the context of self-determination. The
                    Arabs, he said, think in terms of an international administrative regime for a
                    transitional period. At the end, they would consider a plebiscite under
                    international supervision. There were some suggestions on what a plebiscite
                    would cover. One idea was that a plebiscite would select a constituent assembly
                    to determine the future structure of the entity and its relations with its
                    neighbors.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>
                    </hi> expressed his gratitude to the Secretary for bringing Israel’s ideas to
                    the attention of the Arab rulers. He noted that he was very glad that there had
                    been one major achievement in gaining Arab acceptance of a comprehensive peace
                    settlement embodied in peace treaties. This was “an important achievement.”
                    Peace treaties, in his view, are very clear in international law. He expressed
                    his pleasure that the conflict should be resolved in the ordinary way through
                    peace treaties. Diplomatic relations are inseparable from peace treaties. A
                    treaty should have a special chapter on diplomatic relations. The Prime Minister
                    said that he felt Israel was on solid ground to think that diplomatic relations
                    should be mentioned explicitly. He hoped that the Arabs will agree that
                    diplomatic relations are part of peace treaties. A peace treaty would not be a
                    treaty without diplomatic relations. Even in the Soviet-Japanese peace
                    agreement, diplomatic relations were enumerated. On the problem of the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>, Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2"
                        >Begin</persName> said that this has become an issue of international
                    interest. According to the State Department spokesman, if the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> accepts Resolutions 242 and 338, <pb
                        facs="0459" n="432" xml:id="pg_432"/> with their own interpretation, and if
                    the Palestinian Charter continues in effect, this will be all right with the
                    United States.<note n="4" xml:id="d80fn4">See <ref target="#d44fn3">footnote 3,
                            Document 44</ref>.</note> This is what has been published. It is a very
                    serious problem. To understand the Israeli position, Prime Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> quoted from the Palestinian National
                    Covenant. He emphasized those articles which negated Israel’s right to exist and
                    which called for the expulsion of Israelis who arrived after 1917. Prime
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>, after reading several
                    articles from the Covenant, expressed his amazement that this could continue to
                    be in force, while the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> would merely accept
                    Resolution 242 with its own interpretation of the Resolution. Israel could not
                    accept such a procedure, and it was “one of the most regrettable developments
                    from the moral point of view” that Israel’s great friend was ready to accept
                    such an approach. The United States would be recognizing an organization that
                    has carried out 90 attacks in 1977, killing two people and maiming 120. The
                    victims have not been military personnel, but rather civilians. Only today, a
                    grenade was found in a supermarket. The Prime Minister unhesitatingly called the
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> a genocidal organization which wants to
                    destroy Israel, its people, and to destroy its civilization. If the Americans
                    allow the Covenant to stay in force, while only asking them to accept Resolution
                    242 with their own interpretation, that would be “a sorrowful day” for Israel
                    and for all free men.</p>
                <p>The Prime Minister referred to two agreements between the United States and
                    Israel: the Memorandum of Understanding of December 1973,<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d80fn5">The U.S.-Israeli memorandum of understanding of December 20,
                        1973, provided that the original participants in the December 1973 Geneva
                        Conference had to agree on any invitations to future participants to the
                        conference. See <ref target="frus1969-76v25#d410">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. XXV,
                            Arab-Israeli Crisis and War, 1973, Document 410</ref>.</note> and the
                    Sinai II Agreement. In the 1973 agreement, paragraph seven stated that
                    subsequent participation in the Geneva Conference would require the agreement of
                    all the initial participants. In <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>’s
                    view, this article could not be interpreted in more than one way. Israel would
                    agree that Lebanon might participate, but the organization referred to as the
                    so-called <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> will not be accepted. By mutual
                    agreement, only all of the initial participants can change the composition of
                    the Geneva Conference. As Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2"
                        >Begin</persName> had told the President, Israel can under no circumstances
                    agree to an organization such as the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>
                    participating. Only Palestinian Arabs in a Jordanian delegation would be
                    accepted. And Israel will not search their pockets for credentials. But at his
                    press conference the Prime Minister had added that if known <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> members tried to participate, Israel’s answer
                    would be unequivocally negative.<note n="6" xml:id="d80fn6">See <ref
                            target="#d56fn3">footnote 3, Document 56</ref>.</note> This is not
                    because Israel is intransigent, but stems from simple logic. Israel has its
                    attitude on the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> and <pb facs="0460" n="433"
                        xml:id="pg_433"/> cannot mislead its people. The <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> is excluded forever. Israel will not discuss its self
                    destruction. The Israeli people would not understand, it would be a complete
                    contradiction for Israel to talk to the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>.
                    This must be clarified and there can be no doubt about Israel’s position. In
                    view of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>-Israeli mutual agreement, it does
                    not even occur to Israel that the United States will not honor this agreement,
                    since the United States has always honored its commitments. Only with Israel’s
                    agreement can a change in the composition of the Geneva Conference take place.
                    Let it be clear: “We will not, we cannot, give our acceptance. We can’t and we
                    shan’t.” In September 1975, the Prime Minister noted, the language of the 1973
                    agreement was repeated with only a slight change. Thus the United States has
                    twice given Israel a clear commitment. Israel has been very disturbed by the
                    State Department’s statement. Israel is concerned on moral grounds, and in light
                    of the possible effect on the Arabs. If the Arabs insist upon the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> at Geneva and if the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> accepts the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> as a partner to
                    talks, this would imply a consensus in favor of the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> at Geneva, which would be contrary to the agreement between the
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and Israel.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Prime Minister</hi> pointed to another article in the
                    September 1975 agreement, article four. This states that the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> will oppose any change in the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Resolutions. Any attempt to add reference to a
                    Palestinian entity in Resolution 242 should be vetoed by the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>. Resolution 242 refers simply to a just
                    settlement of the refugee problem. Israel cannot be asked to accept Resolution
                    242 and then allow the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> to amend it. Israel
                    accepts the letter of Resolution 242. There are various interpretations, but
                    there is only one text, and it makes no reference to the Palestinian question, a
                    Palestinian entity, or anything else. If post facto, Israel is asked to accept
                    Resolution 242 with changes as proposed by the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss>, this would be completely impossible and Israel would not
                    agree. The Prime Minister asked that the Secretary bring to the knowledge of the
                    President these two documents so that he would know the wording of the specific
                    commitments. <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"
                            >Vance</persName>
                    </hi> asked to reply. He stated that the President is familiar with the
                    commitments. The Prime Minister’s reference to Resolution 242 with the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>’s interpretation was not an accurate
                    statement. What the United States has talked about is Resolution 242, with a
                    reservation by the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> to the effect that
                    Resolution 242 does not adequately cover the Palestinian question. A distinction
                    must be made among three points: the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>–<gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> contact; the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> at Geneva; and any change in 242. On the third point, we should
                    be clear that the United States does not support any change in Resolution 242.
                    The French may be considering this, but we are opposed to any amendment. <hi
                        rend="italic">The Prime Minister</hi> said he was glad to hear that. On
                    participation at Geneva, the <hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi> said,
                    participation requires the agreement of all the initial parties. The United
                    States cannot determine who will participate at Geneva. That is up to the
                    parties. Concerning a <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> dialogue <pb
                        facs="0461" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/> with the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss>, the United States has stated its policy of no talks unless the
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> accepts Resolution 242. That Resolution
                    calls for the sovereignty, territorial integrity, and political independence of
                    every state in the area and their right to live in peace within secure and
                    recognized borders. If the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> were to accept
                    this, it would negate, in the Secretary’s view, their Covenant. That would meet
                    our requirement for talking to the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>. <hi
                        rend="italic">The Prime Minister</hi> referred to the last point. If the
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> accepts Resolution 242, that would not
                    necessarily negate their Covenant. The State Department’s spokesman has said
                    that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> will not ask for a change in the
                    Covenant. This means that the Covenant can remain in force. He stated that if
                    the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> were to accept 242, they would not have
                    to change the Covenant. The <hi rend="italic">press spokesman</hi> noted that
                    this was not an accurate statement. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>
                    </hi> said he would be glad to learn that such a statement had not been made.
                    But the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> would accept <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> recognition of 242 with a reservation or an interpretation. <hi
                        rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>
                    </hi> said there was an important difference between the two. <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Prime Minister</hi> said that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    spokesman had gone on to say that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> would
                    not be asked to change any articles of the Covenant, and therefore one has to
                    assume that the Covenant would remain in force and would not be negated. In
                    March, some expected the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> to change its
                    Covenant, but nothing happened.<note n="7" xml:id="d80fn7">A reference to the
                        March 1977 Palestinian National Council meeting in Cairo.</note> Israel does
                    not accept the idea that the Covenant would be negated by the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>’s acceptance of Resolution 242. <hi
                        rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName>
                    </hi> stated that when he was in Taif he was asked about Resolution 242 and the
                    Palestinian Covenant.<note n="8" xml:id="d80fn8">See <ref target="#d75">Document
                            75</ref>.</note> He said that the United States would not insist on a
                    change in the Covenant, because if Resolution 242 were accepted, that would
                    constitute a change in the Covenant itself because of the reference to all
                    states having the right to exist in peace. <hi rend="italic">The Prime
                        Minister</hi> stated that this was a very important interpretation by the
                    representative of the United States, but it did not reflect the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>’s position. From their point of view,
                    accepting Resolution 242 would not negate the Palestinian Covenant. <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> acceptance of 242 would not negate that
                    genocidal document. <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KS_1"
                            >Katz</persName>
                    </hi> said that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>’s reservations might in
                    effect nullify their acceptance of Resolution 242 in any case. <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Secretary</hi> said that if the statement of the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> was not acceptable, the United States would
                    not talk to them.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>
                    </hi> said that he would like to comment on the idea of a unified Arab
                    delegation. This had been discussed in Washington and the Israeli position was
                    explained. Israel wants peace treaties with states, not with the Arab League or
                    with a unified delegation. Negotiations must be state to state. Israel does not
                    accept at all the idea of a unified Arab delegation. If peace treaties are the
                    goal, negotia<pb facs="0462" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/>tions must take place
                    between states. Otherwise, how in a general Arab delegation, with the Secretary
                    General of the Arab League, could negotiations take place. Now there are 21 or
                    22 Arab states. Israel is not going to sign peace treaties with all of them.
                    Israel’s position, he stated, is reasonable and logical. In concluding, the
                    Prime Minister said that these first talks had been very fruitful and had
                    clarified a number of issues. The United States had rendered a service to the
                    cause of peace by getting Arab agreement to peace treaties. There are still
                    obstacles, but efforts should still be made. Foreign Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName> will go to the United States in
                    September, and Israel is pleased that the President has agreed to see him. All
                    options can be discussed. The meeting ended at 7:00 p.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
