<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>97. Central Intelligence Agency Intelligence Information Cable</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v08</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d97</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">97</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1977-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1977-08-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recXeh96O09nMK0r1" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-08-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="97"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                <head>97. Central Intelligence Agency Intelligence Information Cable<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d97fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Staff Material, Middle East File, Subject File, Box 74,
                        Palestinians: 8/77. Secret; Priority; No Foreign Dissem/No Contractor
                        Dissem/Controlled Dissem and Extraction.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1977-08-20">August 20, 1977</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list>
                    <head>COUNTRY</head>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">name not declassified</hi>]</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <head>DOI</head>
                    <item>19 August 1977</item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>(1) Current <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> position on 242</item>
                    <item>(2) Soviet and Arab advice to <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> on
                        242</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <head>ACQ</head>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">date not declassified</hi>]</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <head>SOURCE</head>
                    <item>[<hi rend="italic">4 lines not declassified</hi>]</item>
                </list>
                <p>Summary: The Palestine Liberation Organization (<gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss>) has not finally rejected the idea of announcing acceptance of
                    United Nations Security Council Resolution 242 which would open an official
                    dialogue with the United States. The prevailing mood within the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> leadership, however, is increasingly against
                    such an announcement. The Saudis, Egyptians and the Soviets have urged the
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> leadership to make a reserved
                    announcement of acceptance of Resolution 242. The Syrians have advised the
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> not to announce acceptance of the
                    Resolution unless the United States offers a more tangible quid pro quo than
                    just a <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    dialogue. The 18 August communique issued by the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> Executive Committee was the result of Syrian pressure and made
                    to please the Syrian regime.</p>
                <p>1. As of late 19 August, the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> leadership was
                    still discussing a possible announcement of acceptance of Resolution 242. The
                    mood of the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> leadership, however, is
                    increasingly against such a statement. Despite efforts by Fatah moderates to
                    convince the rest of the leadership that a dialogue with the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> entails sufficient long range benefits to
                    justify making the required statement on 242, the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> leadership remains largely convinced that it must demand more
                    than just talks with the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> before giving up
                    what it considers to be its only major “card” in the negotiating process.</p>
                <pb facs="0513" n="486" xml:id="pg_486"/>
                <p>2. On 17 August, officials of the Soviet Embassy in Beirut met with <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> officials. The Soviets told the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> officials that they had received a message
                    from Moscow, instructing them to meet with the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> and to deliver the following message: “The Soviet leadership
                    considers it important that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> accept
                        <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Resolution 242, with the reservations
                    proposed by the United States. Such an announcement of acceptance would deny the
                    Israelis and the United States the justification that they have so far used to
                    keep the Palestinians out of the negotiations toward a settlement of the Middle
                    East question.” The <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> officials noted the
                    significant escalation of Soviet pressure from that of urging “flexibility” to
                    that of specifically urging the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> to accept
                    the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> position on 242.</p>
                <p>3. The Syrians on the other hand have urged the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> not to accept Resolution 242 unless more than a dialogue with
                    the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> would result. On 17 August, Syrian
                    President Hafiz al-Asad met with Ahmad Dajjani, a member of the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> Executive Committee, in Damascus. Asad
                    reiterated his position that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> should
                    hold out for more than just a dialogue with the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>. Asad told Dajjani that, during <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VC_1"
                    >Vance</persName>’s visit to Damascus, Asad had asked <persName
                        corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> specifically whether the Palestinians
                    would obtain more than just a dialogue with the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> in exchange for a statement of acceptance of 242. Asad said that
                        <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Vance</persName> was emphatic in his statement
                    that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> was not offering anything more than
                    an agreement to talk with the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>.</p>
                <p>4. The announcement, on 18 August, that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>
                    continued to oppose the acceptance of Resolution 242 was made to please the
                    Syrians. The selection of <persName corresp="#p_MMA_1">Muhammad Abu
                        Mayzar</persName> to make this announcement was made because <persName
                        corresp="#p_MMA_1">Abu Mayzar</persName> has close ties with the
                    Syrians.</p>
                <p>5. The Saudis and Egyptians continue to urge <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>
                    acceptance of Resolution 242. The <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> has
                    attempted to handle its major moves regarding this resolution with the Saudis.
                    On 3 August 1977 <persName corresp="#p_AY_2">Yasir Arafat</persName>, the
                    Chairman of the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> Executive Committee,
                    formally agreed with Saudi Crown Prince Fahd Ibn ’Abd al-Aziz and Saudi Foreign
                    Minister Prince Saud Ibn Faysal that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>
                    would agree to make the announcement proposed by the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss>, in exchange for <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> agreement to
                    three conditions: (1) <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> recognition of the
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> as “the legal representative of the
                    Palestinian people,” (2) the official dialogue between the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>, and
                    (3) a <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> commitment to invite the <gloss
                        target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> to the Geneva Middle East Peace Conference, on
                    the basis of the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>’s reserved position on
                    Resolution 242. On 9 August Prince Saud met with <gloss target="#t_PLO_1"
                        >PLO</gloss> Central Committee member <persName corresp="#p_AM_1">Mahmud
                        Abbas</persName> (Abu Mazin) and <persName corresp="#p_MMA_1">Muhammad Abu
                        Mayzar</persName>. He told them that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    could not accept the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> conditions and had
                    added the following “clarifications” to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    position: (1) acceptance of the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> as a
                    partner in a dialogue would not mean <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    recognition of the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> as the representative of
                    the Palestinian people, (2) the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> would
                    continue to speak of the need for a “Pales<pb facs="0514" n="487"
                        xml:id="pg_487"/>tinian entity” and would not use language calling for an
                    independent Palestinian state, and (3) the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    could not invite the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> to Geneva unless all
                    original parties to the conference, including Israel, agreed. Prince Saud urged
                    the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> to accept the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >US</gloss> position, even with these clarifications.</p>
                <p>6. On 11 August Abu Mazin met with Syrian Foreign Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAH_1">’Abd al-Halim Khaddam</persName> and discussed the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and Saudi positions with him. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAH_1">Khaddam</persName> reacted negatively to the idea of
                    acceptance of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> position. He asked the
                        <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> official rhetorically whether the
                    Palestinians would sell themselves so cheaply.</p>
                <p>7. Israeli moves to extend social services to residents of the occupied
                    territories and to establish new settlements in occupied territories greatly
                    strengthened the hands of hard liners on the question of Resolution 242. Fatah
                    moderates have tried to argue that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    condemnation of Israel for these actions is far stronger than usual <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> language on the subject of Israeli actions. The
                    hard liners, however, argue that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> has not
                    taken any action to prevent or reverse these actions and that the situation
                    calls for actions rather than just statements.</p>
                <p>8. Field dissem: [<hi rend="italic">1½ lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
