<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-01-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="174" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                        <head>174. Report by the Under Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_KNB1" type="from">Katzenbach</persName>), the Under
                            Secretary of the Treasury for Monetary Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_DFL2">Deming</persName>), and the Special Representative
                            for Trade Negotiations (<persName corresp="#p_RWM2">Roth</persName>) to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1" type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d174fn1">Source: Johnson Library,
                                National Security File, Subject File, Balance of Payments, Vol. V [2
                                of 2], Box 3. Secret. No drafting information appears on the source
                                text. The text of this report was sent to the LBJ Ranch in telegram
                                    <gloss target="#t_CAP1">CAP</gloss> 80173, January 7. (Ibid.,
                                1968 Balance of Payments Programs, Memos and Miscellaneous [2 of 2],
                                Box 4) <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> also
                                prepared a country-by-country summary of his European meetings,
                                which was derived from his telegraphic messages. This summary was
                                transmitted under cover of a letter from <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName> to Representative <persName corresp="#p_MWD1">Mills</persName>, January 16. (Department of
                                State, Central Files, ORG 7 U)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1968-01-07">January 7, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Report on Our European Balance of Payments Trip</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This report contains the principal findings of our European trip. (We
                            have also taken into account <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil
                                Trezise</persName>’s talks in Scandinavia and Luxembourg.) Our
                            conclusions are based on the preliminary reactions of the people with
                            whom we talked. Obviously, the President’s <gloss target="#t_BP1">B/P</gloss> program cannot be easily or quickly comprehended, nor
                            could the effects of the measures on individual countries be thoroughly
                            analyzed in the short time between the announcement and our visits.</p>
                        <pb facs="0526" n="496" xml:id="pg_496"/>
                        <p>The purpose of our trip was to convey at the highest possible political
                            level the rationale behind the program, and seek whatever cooperation
                            was appropriate and possible. We put particular emphasis on the
                            President’s desire to maintain our commitments to European security and
                            to a liberal trade policy. We emphasized that European leaders must not
                            judge our measures on the basis of narrow technical considerations, but
                            rather in terms of the high political stakes involved in maintaining a
                            healthy and strong American economy.</p>
                        <p>As an over-all impression, we feel that the President’s program is
                            regarded as necessary and desirable. The central bankers approved in
                            general of the total program and its parts—a domestic tax increase,
                            reduction of expenditures and <gloss target="#t_BP1">B/P</gloss>
                            measures. They seemed prepared to see their reserves fall somewhat and
                            agreed that activation of the new special drawing rights in the <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> would have to come more quickly. The
                            government people, while approving the strength of the total program,
                            and specifically its domestic parts, were more critical about the <gloss target="#t_BP1">B/P</gloss> aspects—with the criticism varying from
                            country to country.</p>
                        <p>We sought both understanding and, to the extent feasible, undertakings
                            not to retaliate against our measures. Nobody, however, was prepared to
                            give us a firm commitment until they had studied the program and weighed
                            the possible consequences. We sought, therefore, to set a favorable
                            political climate for the decisions they will have to make.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">U.S. Domestic Policies</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>We were met with one common response—although with varying
                            emphasis—everywhere we went, i.e., <hi rend="italic">a successful
                                program depends on our ability to get additional taxes and to cut
                                Government expenditures.</hi> European reactions clearly will be
                            strongly influenced—and tempered—if we can demonstrate that we can carry
                            through tough measures to bring our own house in order. If we are to get
                            European cooperation and understanding—and we must make the Hill
                            understand this—we will have to move ahead on the domestic front.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Border Taxes</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>There was no immediate indication that a modest border tax—if it could be
                            justified under the <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>—would face
                            retaliation. There are, however, risks. The overwhelming size of our
                            economy places a special responsibility on us for maintaining the health
                            of the world economy. Thus, whether we like it or not, our conduct is
                            judged by a set of standards substantially different than those applied
                            to others. While European political leaders recognize and understand our
                            domestic problems, what we do is likely to set the tone for the entire
                            world trading community.</p>
                        <p>We must, therefore, weigh the domestic political and economic benefits of
                            introducing a modest border tax against the reactions of others. <pb facs="0527" n="497" xml:id="pg_497"/> One thing is certain—we must
                            justify the border tax within existing <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> rules. If we keep the rate at something between
                            2–2–1/2% we can, we believe, stay generally, although not necessarily
                            strictly, within the rules. Then the Europeans, who understand the
                            political nature of our domestic problem, will probably be able to
                            overcome the doubts of their technicians and, at least in the Common
                            Market and in Switzerland, will be able to avoid counter measures. This
                            is predicated on the assumption that our tax will be announced as a <hi rend="italic">temporary</hi> measure pending further discussions in
                            the <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> on the general questions of
                            border taxes and of the <gloss target="#t_BP1">B/P</gloss> adjustment
                            process. It also assumes that legislation can be controlled and that it
                            will dampen rather than enlarge protectionists’ fires.</p>
                        <p>In Bonn, Brussels and The Hague, we raised the possibility of a
                            suspension of recent or contemplated actions in the tax field. While
                            some effort might be made to explore compensating measures for the
                            border tax effect of the new <gloss target="#t_TVA1">TVA</gloss> tax
                            system, the legislative problem is so great that we do not feel this is
                            a realistic possibility in our time frame.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Harold Wilson</persName> clearly indicated
                            that he could not suspend the British export rebate at a time when the
                            United States was introducing a similar system.<note n="2" xml:id="d174fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName>’s report of his
                                conversation with <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Wilson</persName> is
                                in telegram 5279 from London, January 7. (Department of State,
                                Central Files, ORG 7 U)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Both the Swiss<note n="3" xml:id="d174fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName>’s account of his
                                conversation with Swiss Government officials and bankers on January
                                3 is in telegram 3831 from Brussels, January 3. (Johnson Library,
                                National Security File, Subject File, 1968 Balance of Payments
                                Programs, Cables [1 of 2], Box 4)</note> and the British made the
                            point that the imposition of a border tax implies that a currency is
                            overvalued and warned us that this might be a conclusion drawn in
                            certain business and banking circles. None of the Common Market
                            countries made this point.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Tourism</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The uniform European reaction—although everyone agreed that the President
                            could not ignore such a large element in our <gloss target="#t_BP1">B/P</gloss> deficit—is that any U.S. action to restrict tourism
                            would hit unfairly at airlines and hotels and probably would not achieve
                            the desired purpose. They were happy to learn we were not contemplating
                            exchange controls. Again they will probably accept some modest
                            limitations—particularly if they are part of a broader <gloss target="#t_BP1">B/P</gloss> program.</p>
                        <p>There is real substance to the European view that we should do much more
                            to encourage tourism in the U.S. Greater emphasis, for example, on
                            package tours, which give the middle income traveler a better idea
                            exactly how much he will have to spend, would do a lot of good. We
                            should also urgently examine the feasibility of persuading airlines to
                            give lower preferential air fares to round trips originating in
                            Europe.</p>
                        <pb facs="0528" n="498" xml:id="pg_498"/>
                        <p>Two other suggestions are worth studying: <list>
                                <item>—If we decide to put a small tax on passports, impose a ticket
                                    tax or a head tax, we might earmark the income to promote
                                    foreign travel to the U.S. (this would do much to make the tax
                                    more politically acceptable at home);</item>
                                <item>—We should take a very hard look at ways to simplify or
                                    eliminate our tourist visa requirements.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Investment</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>There was almost uniform (if at times grudging) approval of our decision
                            to control U.S. investment outflows, but several countries expressed
                            concern. Belgium, in particular, was quite worried; Holland was
                            concerned about its North Sea oil and gas; Italy by its problems in the
                            south. The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> also had some worries but
                            accepted the program as necessary. The Commerce Department should be
                            prepared to exercise some flexibility in administering the program.
                            Obviously we cannot grant so many exceptions that we fail to reach our
                            target. But we should at least encourage American business overseas to
                            attempt, as far as possible, to meet this highly political need as they
                            make their investment decisions.</p>
                        <p>While in Paris we met with a group of American businessmen, who raised an
                            issue that deserves Commerce’s urgent attention. They pointed out that
                            U.S. business has found it indispensable, when raising money in Europe,
                            to offer a parent company guarantee. In some cases they have gone so far
                            as to incorporate in Delaware simply to make their issues more appealing
                            to European investors. These guarantees very rarely come into play, but
                            their existence apparently is important.</p>
                        <p>We asked the businessmen to get their comments and suggestions about the
                            particular effects of these measures into Washington quickly. It will be
                            of the utmost importance to work closely with the business community in
                            order to meet their legitimate concerns, while at the same time assuring
                            that the program is not frustrated by their ingenuity.</p>
                        <p>Finally, we are all a bit concerned by <persName corresp="#p_DM4">Debre</persName>’s remarks that he wondered how the U.S. could
                            regulate American affiliates and still want them to receive equal
                            treatment “in countries such as France” (see Secun 30).<note n="4" xml:id="d174fn4">Another series indicator and number for telegram
                                5277 from London, January 6, sent to the President in <ref target="#d173">Document 173</ref>.</note> He may well be
                            preparing the ground for later <gloss target="#t_GOF1">GOF</gloss> moves
                            against U.S. affiliates in France—where and when it suits the French.
                            But such action will be difficult technically to devise.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Export Expansion</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>All of us—and <persName corresp="#p_TPH1">Phil Trezise</persName> on his
                            swing through Scandinavia—reassured the Europeans that the President’s
                            proposed export expansion measures would not set off a credit race. It
                            is important that we explain <pb facs="0529" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/>
                            publicly and repeatedly that we want to increase the efficiency of Ex-Im
                            in the credit field—not to move toward a system of subsidized interest
                            rates.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Neutralization of Military Expenditures Abroad</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Every <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> partner we talked with was
                            grateful for the President’s determination not to play into the hands of
                            those in the U.S. who want, for other reasons, to see substantial
                            American troop cuts in Europe. For bargaining purposes (particularly in
                            Bonn)—and despite the fact that we realized it would probably not be
                            possible—we emphasized the need for <hi rend="italic">full</hi>
                            neutralization of our foreign exchange costs. The trilateral talks last
                            year bought us some time, but it is important that we begin discussions
                            with the <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> as soon as we can on
                            arrangements for the next two years.</p>
                        <p>During each visit we mentioned the need for future multilateral
                            arrangements. Everyone expressed interest, but recognized that we would
                            probably have to proceed on a bilateral basis for the next two years.
                            State and Treasury have already begun consideration of a multilateral
                            system which we might propose in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>;
                            we will now make it a priority <gloss target="#t_SIG1">SIG</gloss>
                            agenda item.</p>
                        <p>The importance of the British problem must not be underestimated. If the
                                <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> fails to get a 100 million pound
                            off-set agreement (or very close to it) and, as a result, cuts the
                                <gloss target="#t_BAOR1">BAOR</gloss>, pressure for cuts of our own
                            may well reach intolerable proportions. <persName corresp="#p_WJH2">Harold Wilson</persName> made very clear that he would withdraw
                            troops without the off-set.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Gold</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Everywhere we went the question of the 25 percent gold cover was
                            raised—not nervously, but with a question as to why we had not yet acted
                            on it. We explained the Federal Reserve powers to suspend—a point
                            already known to the central bankers—and said any legislative action
                            would in any event have to await a propitious time.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>At a time when both the U.S. and British Governments are trying to
                            improve their payments positions by an aggregate figure of over $4
                            billion, we cannot ignore the possible cumulative effects of the
                            measures taken by the two countries on our own economies and the
                            economic fortunes of the world at large.</p>
                        <p>We must put our best economic brains to work on this problem—and soon.
                                <hi rend="italic">We recommend</hi> that the President appoint an
                            advisory committee, or perhaps use the existing <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> Committee (which includes people
                            such as Walter Heller, <persName corresp="#p_BFM1">Francis
                                Bator</persName>, Bob Roosa and <persName corresp="#p_GK3">Kermit
                                Gordon</persName>), to undertake an immediate examination of the
                            measures we have taken or are likely to take. If these experts conclude
                            that the US/<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> program may cause serious
                            economic problems, the U.S. should call for a <pb facs="0530" n="500" xml:id="pg_500"/> conference—perhaps sponsored by the Economic
                            Policy Committee of the <gloss target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss>—to propose
                            ways of ameliorating conditions arising from <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>/US balance of payments measures. We must, for
                            psychological reasons even more than technical ones, demonstrate our
                            determination to create conditions for an expanding world economy—with
                            deficit countries assuming their responsibilities, surplus countries
                            playing their proper role, and both responsive to the needs to <gloss target="#t_LDC1">LDC</gloss>s.</p>
                        <p>Also, as many of our European friends seem to recognize, the reduction or
                            elimination of our deficit makes it even more important that we proceed
                            as quickly as possible to approve and implement the special drawing
                            rights mechanism. While this may be a modest step, it will have an
                            important bearing on developing a sense of purpose and
                            responsibility.</p>
                        <p>It is important that we continue to analyze the domestic and
                            international consequences of various legislative proposals—particularly
                            their net effect on the <gloss target="#t_BP1">B/P</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>How we handle ourselves in dealing with our partners abroad is almost as
                            important as the measures themselves. It is extremely important that the
                                <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> speak with one voice, and that
                            we handle our negotiations with the utmost skill. There will naturally
                            be differences of view between the various Washington agencies concerned
                            with specific aspects of the program, but the political stakes are high
                            and we must find some way to settle our differences quickly and
                            constructively.</p>
                        <p>We were heartened, but at the same time sobered, by the recognition
                            abroad of the importance of US leadership and responsibility. Without
                            exception, the people we talked to are aware of the tremendous burdens
                            the President carries, and all (except France) spoke with admiration
                            that forceful and positive action had been taken.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>