<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-02-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="275" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d275">
                        <head>275. Memorandum From the Deputy Special Representative for Trade
                            Negotiations (<persName corresp="#p_RWM2" type="from">Roth</persName>)
                            to the President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs
                                (<persName corresp="#p_BMG2" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d275fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName> Papers, <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName>, Box 7. No
                                classification marking. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RWM2">Roth</persName>. The source text bears <persName corresp="#p_HCAJ1">Herter</persName>’s handwritten
                                initials.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1965-02-09">February 9, 1965</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Secretary Freeman had breakfast with Mansholt this morning. He said he
                            was quite sharp with him, indicating that there was a deep concern here
                            over the delay in agricultural negotiations and in the rigid insistence
                            of the Community on the montant de soutien formula.</p>
                        <p>He said there was real danger particularly in the grains that a price war
                            could come about and that this would have serious consequences for <pb facs="0733" n="703" xml:id="pg_703"/> world agriculture. U.S.
                            supports and farmer returns were going down, whereas the opposite trend
                            was apparent within the Community.</p>
                        <p>He urged three things on Mansholt: (1) that he review the September date
                            and attempt to establish an earlier one, (2) that grains negotiations
                            begin immediately and that the Community proceed with their offers
                            unequivocally, (3) that the tabling of agricultural offers in all
                            sectors not be conditional on additional discussions between now and the
                            date of tabling.</p>
                        <p>Freeman said he thought the talk was a good one and that an impression
                            had been made on Mansholt.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWM2">
                                    <hi rend="strong">William M. Roth</hi>
                                </persName><note n="2" xml:id="d275fn2">Printed from a copy that
                                    bears this typed signature.</note>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>