<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Great Britain ( (Page) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1916Supp</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1281</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1281</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1916-07-28T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1916-07-28T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005773"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Medical supplies</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-07-28T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-07-28T10:00:00-05:00" n="1281"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1281">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72112/2764</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName
                        corresp="#p_PWH1" type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Page</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-07-28T16:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 28, 1916, 4 p. m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received July 29, 8.30 p. m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4625. Your 3527, July 17, 6 p. m. I have to-day received the following memorandum
                    from the Foreign Office:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>The position of the Allied Governments in regard to the importation of
                        medical supplies into enemy countries is that they cannot be called upon to
                        admit a practice which has been forbidden in the case of every blockade
                        established in the past.</p>
                    <p>They consider, moreover, that the Geneva convention obviously does not
                        apply.</p>
                    <p>These questions of principle having been settled, frequent appeals have been
                        made to the Allied Governments to make some concession as a matter of grace.
                        His Majesty’s Government are always ready to mitigate the application of
                        principles, but this can only be done if it is possible to draw and maintain
                        some line beyond which the concession shall not apply. This is apparently
                        recognized as reasonable, and various attempts have been made by the
                        Department of State and by private persons in America to draw such a
                        line.</p>
                    <p>One suggestion is that a neutral commission should be appointed in Germany to
                        receive imported medical supplies and distribute them to enemy hospital
                        organizations, but this suggestion offers no means of restricting in any way
                        the amount of supplies imported. To meet this objection it has frequently
                        been suggested that the Allied Governments should specify the kinds and
                        amounts of medical supplies the importation of which into enemy countries
                        they will be prepared to allow. But it is impossible to fix amounts in this
                        way. One <pb facs="1242" n="956" xml:id="pg_956"/> cannot ration the whole
                        population of Germany and Austria in drugs and bandages. No ingenuity could
                        estimate what might reasonably be needed by the population. It is equally
                        difficult to lay down the kinds of goods which may be allowed. Even if such
                        rations could be fixed, it would be practically impossible to enforce them
                        without an amount of friction in the United States quite as great as that
                        caused by the present total prohibition. The American Red Cross draws its
                        supplies from an enormous number of small societies, sewing parties, etc.,
                        throughout the United States. These organizations send goods to the central
                        Red Cross warehouses. Can the Red Cross allot a ration of goods of each
                        class to each local society or club so that the total sent in will not
                        exceed the ration allowed by the Allied Governments? Surely it is obvious
                        that this is impossible. What would as a matter of fact happen would be that
                        gifts would flow into the Red Cross warehouses in the United States just as
                        they formerly did and that the Red Cross would be unable consistently to do
                        anything else than forward applications to the Allied Governments for
                        permission to ship the amounts collected, regardless of whether these
                        amounts did or did not exceed the ration, thus putting the onus of refusal
                        on the Allied Governments. There would follow refusals and consequent
                        agitation. This was what occurred before and what the total prohibition was
                        intended to stop.</p>
                    <p>His Majesty’s Government have given close consideration to the question and
                        they have found themselves utterly unable to evolve any system by which
                        general shipments of medical supplies, once permitted, could be kept within
                        limits at all. Their reasons for not allowing unlimited supplies to go in
                        have been frequently stated, viz., that the materials sent in would replace
                        materials existing in enemy countries which could and undoubtedly would then
                        be applied to other, and in many cases directly belligerent, purposes. It is
                        impossible to evolve any scheme by which the free importation of cotton
                        goods, rubber goods, clothing, etc., for hospital purposes can be reconciled
                        with a blockade, and it is to be observed that it is such hospital supplies
                        and not drugs or surgical instruments which form the bulk of the
                        applications received in the past from the American Red Cross.</p>
                    <p>His Majesty’s Government on their part have therefore laid down the only
                        workable distinction they could think of: namely, that American Red Cross
                        supplies may be sent to American Red Cross units, wherever such units may
                        be. They feel that no juster test could probably be found of the strength of
                        humanitarian claims and the interest taken by the people of the United
                        States in the needs of the Central Empires, than the extent to which the
                        people of the United States are prepared to subscribe money or send doctors
                        and nurses for hospital work in Germany and Austria. Wherever the sympathies
                        and energy of Americans are manifested by the presence of Americans engaged
                        in the relief of suffering, there American supplies can be freely imported
                        and used. This is a very definite concession and opens a wide door to
                        American philanthropy, and His Majesty’s Government can not understand why,
                        if feeling in the United States is strong on this subject, this door should
                        be allowed to remain closed.</p>
                </quote>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PWH1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Page</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
