<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-03-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-03-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="1305" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1305">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 600.001/12</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SWG1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Sharp</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-03-29">
                                    <hi rend="italic">March 29, 1916</hi>
                                </date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received March 30, 8 a.
                                m.</hi>]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1336. Conference of Allies held at Paris 27th and 28th, at which were
                            present representatives from Belgium, England, France, Italy, Japan,
                            Portugal, Russia, and Serbia, adopted following resolutions:<list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The representatives of the Allied Governments, at their
                                    meeting in Paris on March 27 and 28, 1916, affirm the complete
                                    community of views and solidarity of the Allies; they confirm
                                    all the steps taken to insure unity of action on the front as a
                                    unit. This is to be understood to mean the unity of military
                                    action, brought about by the understanding concluded between the
                                    staffs; the unity of economic action, the organization of which
                                    has been regulated by the present conference; and the unity of
                                    diplomatic action, guaranteed by their firm determination to
                                    carry on the struggle until the victory of the common
                                    cause.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The Allied Governments resolve to put their solidarity of
                                    views and interests into practice in the economic domain. They
                                    will instruct the economic conference, to be held shortly in
                                    Paris, to lay before them such measures as may be calculated to
                                    give effect to this solidarity.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>With the object of strengthening, coordinating, and unifying
                                    economic action, to be exercised for the purpose of preventing
                                    supplies from reaching the enemy, the conference decides to
                                    constitute in Paris a permanent committee in which all Allies
                                    shall be represented.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The conference decides: to carry on the organization, begun in
                                    London, of an international central freight bureau; to proceed
                                    jointly as soon as possible <pb facs="1259" n="973" xml:id="pg_973"/> to the investigation of such measures as
                                    may be practicable to bring about an equitable distribution,
                                    among the Allied nations, of the burdens arising out of maritime
                                    transports, and to check the rise in freights.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SWG1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sharp</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>