<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-01-25T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-01-25T18:00:00-05:00" n="201" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d201">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72/2355½</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PWH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Page</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-01-25T23:00:00+00:00">
                                        <hi rend="italic">January 25, 1916, 11 p. m.</hi>
                                    </date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received January 26, 7.30 a.
                                    m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>3648. <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Sir Edward Grey</persName> sent for
                                me this afternoon to talk about the Administration’s proposals about
                                submarine warfare and about forbidding any merchantman from carrying
                                a gun astern for defensive use. I was obliged to tell him that I
                                knew nothing about such proposals. He seemed disappointed [and] he
                                showed me a telegram on the subject from <persName corresp="#p_SRSCA1">Spring Rice</persName>, not omitting
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Sir Edward</persName>’s telegram of
                                to-day in reply.</p>
                            <p>I have only once before seen <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Sir
                                    Edward</persName> so grave and disappointed, and that was when
                                he informed me that the British had sent the German Government an
                                ultimatum. After he discovered that I had not been informed of the
                                subject he seemed disposed to say little. He did say, however, that
                                he indulged the hope that the Department had not foreseen the
                                results of the proposal which was wholly in favor of the Germans
                                theoretically and practically [and] wholly against the Allies. Then
                                he asked me for House’s address because, as I gathered, he had
                                talked with him at my table so frankly and freely about the
                                relations of our two Governments that he thought he ought to inform
                                House that he [did not] then know that this proposal would come. He
                                spoke as one speaks of a great calamity. He said that he would not
                                mention the subject in his speech in the House of Commons to-morrow
                                because the announcement that such a proposal had been made by the
                                United States would cause a storm that would drive every other
                                subject out of the mind of the House and of the country. He is the
                                best friend that we have in the Government and his surprise and
                                dismay are overwhelming.</p>
                            <p>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Sir Edward</persName> is too courteous
                                to expose himself, but the Government and British opinion will
                                regard this change by us of an accepted practice made while the war
                                is in progress as a complete German <pb facs="0438" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/> victory over us in the submarine controversy.
                                [The] engendered bitterness against us will be intense in the Allied
                                countries and such influence as we might have had with the Allied
                                Governments will be lost. If this proposal be persisted in, the
                                Administration will forfeit the confidence [and] good will of
                                England and France. Can we gain enormously by it to offset this
                                loss? [Hope you] will reread my confidential telegram of the 22d
                                    instant.<note n="1" xml:id="d201fn1">Not located in the files of
                                    the Department.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>It has been rumored here in well-informed circles for several weeks,
                                and I believe it is true, that the British Government have been
                                constructing extra munition works in England and Canada which can on
                                short notice be manned and used to make as many munitions as the
                                United States now supplies. The reason given for this expensive
                                preparation is the fear of <persName corresp="#p_BJHACV1">Bernstorff</persName>’s success in his efforts to cause the
                                Administration to embarrass the Allies. If necessary, orders placed
                                in the United States could now be stopped within a month without
                                diminishing the total supply. If no merchantman may carry a
                                defensive gun into an American port, [this] change may precipitate a
                                cutting off of American orders, not from any wish to cut them off,
                                but from fear that other embarrassing acts by us may follow.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PWH1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Page</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>