<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-05-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-05-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="491" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d491">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72112/2552</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PWH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Page</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 3702</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-05-03">
                                        <hi rend="italic">May 3, 1916</hi>
                                    </date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received May
                                    15</hi>.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose herewith
                                for the information of the Department, a copy of a communication
                                which I received from the Consul General at London, under date of
                                April 5, in reference to the complaint of various shippers of goods
                                from the United States to Holland relative to the seizure of such
                                consignments by the British authorities, irrespective of the fact
                                that the goods were shipped under permits issued by the Netherlands
                                Oversea Trust.<note n="1" xml:id="d491fn1">Not printed.</note> I
                                also transmit herein a copy of the <hi rend="italic">aide
                                    mémoire</hi> which I presented to <persName corresp="#p_GSE1">Sir Edward Grey</persName> on April 12, together with a copy of
                                his reply thereto under date of May 2, in reference to this
                                matter.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PWH1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Walter Hines Page</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                            <pb facs="0677" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The American Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PWH1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Page</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the British
                                        Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_GSE1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grey</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <p rend="center">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide Mémoire</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>The American Embassy has been informed that great anxiety has
                                    been caused amongst various American shippers of goods to
                                    Holland by the fact that large seizures have been reported
                                    within the last three months of various classes of goods shipped
                                    under Netherlands Oversea Trust permits, after the shippers had
                                    complied with every requirement of His Majesty’s Government
                                    known to the commercial community.</p>
                                <p>Many protests have been made by well-known and reputable
                                    forwarders of American staple commodities, and the burden of the
                                    complaint in each case is that they forwarded goods without
                                    hesitancy, relying upon the statement of His Majesty’s
                                    Government that while His Majesty’s authorities did not require
                                    American shippers to forward their goods in care of the
                                    Netherlands Oversea Trust, they would regard consignment to the
                                    Trust as proof of a <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> Dutch
                                    destination.</p>
                                <p>The matter has now become one of great seriousness as it affects
                                    not merely the particular consignments under consideration, but
                                    has destroyed confidence in the efficacy of the arrangements
                                    which have been made for the shipment of goods from the United
                                    States to the Netherlands.</p>
                                <p>It is hoped that some solution may be found in the
                                    misunderstanding which would appear now to prevail amongst
                                    American exporters, and that such shippers who have taken the
                                    precaution to comply with the regulations of His Majesty’s
                                    authorities and obtain a permit from the Netherlands Oversea
                                    Trust, may be permitted to ship their goods to Holland without
                                    interference.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-04-12">
                                            <hi rend="italic">April 12, 1916</hi>
                                        </date>.</dateline>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The British Secretary of State for Foreign
                                        Affairs</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_GSE1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grey</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                        the American Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_PWH1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Page</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 70508/X</seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-05-02">
                                            <hi rend="italic">May 2, 1916</hi>
                                        </date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Excellency</hi>: Careful consideration
                                    has been given to the <hi rend="italic">aide mémoire</hi> which
                                    your excellency was so good as to communicate to me on the 12th
                                    April regarding the detention of various classes of goods
                                    shipped from the United States to Holland under consignment to
                                    the Netherlands Oversea Trust.</p>
                                <p>I have the honour to state in reply that as a general rule His
                                    Majesty’s Government do regard consignment to the Trust as an
                                    adequate guarantee of the ultimate disposal of imports into
                                    Holland so consigned. Such consignment cannot, however, preclude
                                    and does not, under the specific provisions of the agreement
                                    with the Trust, preclude His Majesty’s Government from
                                    requesting the Trust to withhold delivery of goods in special
                                    cases pending enquiry, and even in certain circumstances to
                                    return cargoes to this country for prize court proceedings.</p>
                                <p>I need hardly assure your excellency that His Majesty’s
                                    Government, while compelled to take the utmost precautions to
                                    prevent the passage of goods to the enemy and any possible
                                    evasion of existing arrangements, are sincerely desirous to
                                    reduce delays and interference to a minimum, and would consider
                                    sympathetically any concrete cases of detention or seizure which
                                    your excellency may consider as falling outside the exceptional
                                    circumstances referred to.</p>
                                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                                <closer>For the Secretary of State: <lb/>
                                    <signed>
                                        <persName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Langley</hi>
                                        </persName>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>