<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1916-09-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1916-09-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="554" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d554">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 600.419/142</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at London</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SRP1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Skinner</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1916-09-11">
                                        <hi rend="italic">September 11, 1916</hi>
                                    </date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received 1.20 p.
                                    m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>Announcement made that no further export licenses or other facilities
                                will be given until October 1 or further notice by British
                                Government for shipment of following goods to countries named:</p>
                            <p>Denmark: Animal oils and fats, apricot kernels, borate of lime, borax
                                and boron compounds, bristles, egg yolk and albumen, grass seeds,
                                hair, meat, sago, starches, sulphur, talc (powdered), tapioca, tea,
                                vegetable fibres, vegetable oils and oil seeds (excluding soya
                                beans).</p>
                            <p>Norway: Beef casings, borax and boron compounds, cocoa, coffee,
                                nickel, pitch, sheepskins, talc (powdered), tar, tar oil.</p>
                            <p>Sweden: Antimony, apricot kernels, binder twine, bristles, carnauba
                                wax, casein, casings, cocoa, corkwood, coffee, dried fruit, gums
                                (except shellac), hair, honey, leather, margarine (raw materials
                                used in manufacture of), meat, peach kernels, plum kernels, rice,
                                rosin, spices, starches, sisal, steel (high speed), tea, turpentine,
                                turpentine oil.</p>
                            <p>Holland: Biscuits, bristles, eggs, egg yolk and egg albumen, fish
                                oil, fruit, nuts and kernels, gums, hair, honey, matches, pitch,
                                preserved and canned goods, sulphur, spirits, spices, starches,
                                rubber and balata, talc (powdered), tar, vegetable fibres,
                                    yeast.<note n="1" xml:id="d554fn1">Reports of later lists and
                                    removals not printed.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Holders of unexhausted licenses for shipment of goods named are told
                                to communicate with War Trade Department. Foregoing restrictions
                                agreed to by Allies and apply to shipments from United States.
                                Articles are those which have been supplied to countries concerned
                                in quantities alleged to be over normal requirements. As stocks
                                decline articles will be removed from list. Netherlands Oversea
                                Trust has been advised to issue no further permits for goods covered
                                by this notice. It is presumed that American goods already covered
                                by letters of assurance will not be stopped.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SRP1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Skinner</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>