<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Charles P. O’Donnell of the
                        Division of Commercial Policy</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v10</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d1109</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">1109</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="international-trade" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890" lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-04-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="1109" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1109">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">693.1111/4–3046</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Charles P. O’Donnell of the
                        Division of Commercial Policy</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-04-30">April 30,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. Ta-Chung Liu, Assistant Commercial
                            Counsellor, Chinese Embassy</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. S. C. Wang, Chairman, Chinese Supply
                            Commission</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Brown, CP<note n="2" xml:id="d1109fn2">Winthrop G. Brown, Chief of the Division of Commercial
                                Policy.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Gay, CP<note n="3" xml:id="d1109fn3">Merrill
                                C. Gay, Assistant Chief of the Division of Commercial Policy.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. White, CP<note n="4" xml:id="d1109fn4">Cecil
                                Thayer White.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Woodard, FE<note n="5" xml:id="d1109fn5">Granville O. Woodard, of the Division of Chinese Affairs, Office of
                                Far Eastern Affairs.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. O’Donnell, CP</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>At our request, Dr. Liu and Dr. Wang came to the Department to discuss questions
                    of policy concerning the operation of the Chinese Supply Commission.</p>
                <p>Mr. Brown explained that the Department is asking the representatives of
                    countries having purchasing missions in this country to discuss the present
                    operations of their missions and their future plans for them. Mr. Brown
                    explained that this Government believes that international trade should be
                    returned to private channels as soon as practicable. He pointed out that we were
                    fully appreciative of the enormous difficulties confronting China in the work of
                    rehabilitation and that the policy statement we presented to the Chinese
                    representatives in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> on purchasing
                    missions had taken this consideration into account.</p>
                <p>Mr. Wang said that the Chinese position was unique and that there was nothing in
                    China which made it possible to go back to individualistic purchases
                    immediately. He thought that some sort of plan somewhere between Amtorg<note n="6" xml:id="d1109fn6">Soviet Government trading organization in the United
                        States.</note> and <hi rend="italic">laissez-faire</hi> might have to be
                    worked out to deal with Chinese trade problems. He expressed the belief that it
                    would be disastrous to do away with the Chinese Purchasing Mission at once. He
                    said it would be first necessary to build up Chinese economy <pb facs="1407" n="1397" xml:id="pg_1397"/> and then unfreeze controls in the same way
                        OPA<note n="7" xml:id="d1109fn7">Office of Price Administration.</note>
                    controls might be demobilized in the United States. Mr. Wang said that if the
                    restoration of private trade in certain commodities resulted in only a slight
                    increase in the price for that commodity, there might be no objection to such
                    trade. However, there were many other products where the savings made by the
                    purchasing commission were substantial. He thought that two or three years of
                    purchasing mission activity might be necessary to accomplish the objective of
                    building up China’s economy.</p>
                <p>In reply to a question, Dr. Wang said that if importers telegraphed him money to
                    buy for them, he would be glad to arrange for such purchases, but this had never
                    been done. Dr. Liu asked Dr. Wang if it were not true that the purpose of the
                    Purchasing Mission was to purchase for government account and that there had
                    never been occasion to determine whether the Mission had the authority to
                    purchase for private business. Dr. Wang’s reply was non-committal.</p>
                <p>Mr. Brown asked the Chinese representatives to present their views on our
                    purchasing mission policy in writing and to indicate their future plans for
                    operation as soon as it is convenient.</p>
                <p>This meeting was held in Mr. Brown’s office, April 9, 1946, at 9:30 a.m.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
