<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="151" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d151">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Marshall</persName> to
                                President <persName type="to">Truman</persName>
                            </hi><note n="71" xml:id="d151fn71">Copy transmitted to the Acting
                                Secretary of State by the War Department on October 7.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-05">October 5, 1946</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1600. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: Since my message of
                            October 2nd to Secretary of State (1587) the following has transpired.
                            While I have not yet received a reply from Chou En Lai in Shanghai to
                            the Generalissimo’s proposal, Wednesday, October 2nd, his
                            representatives did spend 2 hours with me Friday morning explaining that
                            they had sent the message both to Yenan and Chou but no answers had been
                                <pb facs="0300" n="290" xml:id="pg_290"/> received. As the message
                            made no reference to Chou’s demand for cessation of advance on Kalgan
                            they pressed me to obtain some answer to that specific point. I told
                            them to put their query in writing and I would transmit it but would no
                            longer be a messenger for oral communications. They wished to know if
                            the Generalissimo would abide by the agreement of January 10th which
                            would require all troops to withdraw to their point of location on
                            January 13th. I replied that while I had no positive information on this
                            point my impression was—actually I am certain—that the Generalissimo
                            will insist on maintaining military occupation of the various places or
                            regions recently occupied. While the interview was lengthy it consisted
                            mostly of repetition of past contentions or events.</p>
                        <p>Last night, Friday, the Generalissimo called Doctor Stuart and me into
                            dinner. We had a conference of about 3 hours. He made a lengthy
                            statement to the effect that my memorandum to him of Tuesday, October
                            1st (1589)<note n="72" xml:id="d151fn72">Telegram not printed.</note>
                            had caused him more distress than anything that had happened in years;
                            that he had searched his thoughts and actions and could not find
                            anything that might have given the impression of ulterior motives or
                            deception; that such would be intolerable for him personally and he felt
                            that we should jointly endeavor to clear up any misunderstandings. He
                            stated that it was unthinkable that I should cease my efforts at
                            mediation and leave China; that this was he thought the most important
                            issue before the world and my mission was of great historical
                            importance. He recited the actions of the Communists which justified his
                            mistrust and which demanded of him, as President, that the security of
                            the country be a first consideration. He referred to the strategical
                            importance of Kalgan as a Communist threat to Peiping as well as a
                            barrier on one rail line south, and for the National Government a point
                            of separation of North China Communists from Manchuria. He said that
                            once Kalgan had been occupied—it may take about 10 days or so—he would
                            be ready to cease hostilities.</p>
                        <p>In reply I summarized the lengthy negotiations of May and June, pointed
                            out the fact that then, when the Government was in a far weaker North
                            China position than today, he had conceded to me that he would agree to
                            the Communists holding Kalgan but insisted that they must evacuate
                            Chengteh—northeast of Peiping. Today with the Government in possession
                            of Chengteh and the surrounding region, he now asserted that the
                            possession of Kalgan was of vital importance to the Government. I was
                            not disputing the importance of Kalgan, that was a matter for the
                            Government to decide, but the course of events and statements made
                            convince me that while the Communists were demanding a cessation of the
                            fighting, the Government was <pb facs="0301" n="291" xml:id="pg_291"/>
                            actually pursuing a policy of force. I was also convinced that any
                            negotiations not only specifically included complicated questions which
                            would be time consuming while military operations progressed, but also
                            that the Government’s proposal for negotiations now were definitely made
                            at the point of a gun. I could not serve as a mediator under such
                            conditions. I based my discussion on the grounds that there must be no
                            question regarding the integrity of my position or actions, that I could
                            not place the United States Government in a position where the integrity
                            of its actions as represented by me could be successfully
                            questioned.</p>
                        <p>There was a lengthy discussion back and forth with frequent references by
                            him to the bad faith or unjustified actions by the Communists and my
                            counter examples of questionable action by the Government
                            representatives. He insisted that a solution must be found and that he
                            could not accept my withdrawal. But he did not concede an inch regarding
                            the continuation of the campaign against Kalgan. I think his leaders
                            have carefully played their cards to create this situation believing
                            that, because of Soviet considerations, we would be forced to [go] along
                            with protracted negotiations while the campaign progressed as they
                            desired.</p>
                        <p>Despite the present vicious Communist propaganda of misrepresentation and
                            bitter attacks, and their stupid failure to agree to the proposal of
                            Doctor Stuart and me for the 5-man group to settle the State Council
                            issue—actuated, we think, through fear of exactly the delays their
                            refusal has led to with its attendant military crisis for them—my view
                            is that the United States Government cannot afford before the world to
                            have me continue as a mediator and should confidentially notify the
                            Generalissimo accordingly.<note n="73" xml:id="d151fn73">Remainder of
                                message canceled by General Marshall’s telegram No. 1605, October 6,
                                    <ref target="#pg_298">p. 298</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>I believe that this is the only way to halt this military campaign and
                            dispel the evident belief of the Government generals that they can drag
                            us along while they carry through an actual campaign of force. If I am
                            recalled, Doctor Stuart will be here in a position to negotiate if so
                            desired when the two sides reach an impasse as they undoubtedly will,
                            but just when I cannot estimate with any prospect of accuracy.</p>
                        <p>I therefore recommend that the procedure indicated by the following
                            suggested message from our President to the Generalissimo be considered,
                            it being understood that if the time involved in deciding on, and in
                            sending, the message and in awaiting a reply exceeds a week the prospect
                            is that the Government will have achieved its purpose in capturing
                            Kalgan. Just what the Communists’ reaction to that would be,
                            particularly regarding any degree of genuine cooperation <pb facs="0302" n="292" xml:id="pg_292"/> in National Assembly or reorganization of
                            the Government, I can only guess. You at home can judge of Soviet
                            reactions. Should you feel that our Government can accept the situation
                            I have outlined until the fall of Kalgan, I will go ahead gladly in my
                            endeavors to bring about a cessation of hostilities.</p>
                        <p>Suggested message: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Your Excellency: General Marshall has advised me of the
                                    situation regarding his efforts in mediation and of his
                                    discussions with you. He has recommended that his special
                                    mission be terminated and that he be recalled. He has explained
                                    to me, as he informs me he has explained to you, that he feels
                                    his continuance in the role of mediation under present
                                    circumstances of extensive and aggressive military operations
                                    would place the United States Government in a position where the
                                    integrity of its action, as represented by him, would be open to
                                    serious question.</p>
                                <p>“I deplore and I know the people of the United States will deeply
                                    regret that his efforts to assist in bringing peace and
                                    political unity to China have proved unsuccessful, but there
                                    must not be any question regarding the integrity of his position
                                    and actions which represent the intentions and high purpose of
                                    the United States Government. I therefore with great regret have
                                    concluded that he should be immediately recalled, and I do so
                                    with a full realization of the great consideration and
                                    distinguished courtesy with which you and your people have
                                    welcomed and received him.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>If I am recalled for consultation as suggested in Mr. Acheson’s message
                            of October 4 (82325), or otherwise, I think a declaration of policy and
                            directions regarding United States personnel in Executive Headquarters
                            and the Military Advisory Group can await my arrival home, leaving
                            Doctor Stuart possibly to profit by the effect of my withdrawal.
                            Naturally the contents of this paragraph should not be made known to the
                            Generalissimo.</p>
                        <p>The message should be sent through our Embassy here for delivery by
                            Doctor Stuart in order to save time involved in Chinese Washington
                            Embassy use of commercial communications. While there is still time for
                            the Generalissimo to reverse himself, I think it of the greatest
                            importance that no intimation of this action leak into the press where
                            it would do irreparable injury to the Chinese Government in favor of the
                            Communists. Finally I believe that while the Communists would welcome my
                            action from the viewpoint of possibly forcing the Government to
                            terminate hostilities they actually would be much worried to have me
                            leave.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>