<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="185" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/10–1446</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-14">October 14,
                                1946</date>.<lb/>[Received October 14—5:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1659. Press reports published October 13, Nanking, report Liang Shu Ming,
                            Secretary General of the Democratic League, who went to Shanghai October
                            12 in attempt to persuade General Chou En Lai to accept a compromise
                            plan, as stating that “the possibility of the resumption of peace
                            negotiations between the Government and the Communists is now a thing of
                            the past”. He further stated following his talks with Chou that “now
                            everything is changed. There is no use talking of peace negotiations any
                            longer.” Kiang Yung, member of the presidium of the PCC who accompanied
                            Liang, also declared that Liang’s statement represented his opinion too
                            since the Government had issued a mandate calling for National Assembly
                            and Communists will not send their delegates.</p>
                        <p>Coincidentally Dr. Sun Fo, President of Legislative Yuan, in an interview
                            with Central News urged that military operations be halted immediately,
                            peace negotiations resumed and Government reorganized in accordance with
                            PCC resolutions. Dr. Sun further urged all parties to submit immediately
                            lists of their delegates to National Assembly.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Stuart</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>