<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-21T02:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-21T02:00:00-05:00" n="206" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d206">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Notes on Meeting Between General Marshall and General
                                Yu Ta-wei at No. 5 Ning Hai Road, Nanking, October 21, 1946, 3
                                p.m.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Nanking</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-21T15:00:00+08:00">October 21, 1946, 3 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <table rend="width:50%" rendition="#center-block">
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap">Also present:</cell>
                                <cell>Colonel Caughey</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>General Yu Ta-wei opened the meeting by asking whether General Marshall
                            had heard anything official from the Communists. General Marshall
                            indicated that he had received no reply to the letter<note n="7" xml:id="d206fn7">October 17, <ref target="#pg_380">p.
                                380</ref>.</note> containing the Government’s 8 proposals which he
                            had relayed to General Chou En-lai, but that he would let General Yu
                            Ta-wei know when he had received an official reply.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall continued by stating there was a possibility that the
                            Communists might object to his (General Marshall’s) sitting on the
                            Committee of Three, and that this might be the reason for their recent
                            propaganda directed against him. General Marshall added that this
                            propaganda might be the Communists’ idea of how to obtain, in the United
                            States, a popular reaction against U. S. attitude in relation to the
                            Generalissimo. General Marshall stated that he had asked the
                            Generalissimo not to rise in his defense on this matter. It was a matter
                            for General Marshall to handle or the U. S. Government.</p>
                        <p>General Yu Ta-wei stated that negotiations (i. e., meeting of the Five
                            Man and Three Man Committees) would probably have to wait until the
                            Communists had agreed to the 8 points issued by the Government. To this,
                            General Marshall indicated agreement and further stated that it would
                            probably be best to let the third party members come to the fore in an
                            effort to bring the two major parties together. <pb facs="0407" n="397" xml:id="pg_397"/> This procedure would operate toward establishing a
                            firmer basis for subsequent negotiations.</p>
                        <p>To this, General Yu Ta-wei assented and told General Marshall he would
                            keep him informed of any development and requested that General Marshall
                            do the same.</p>
                        <p>General Yu Ta-wei said that General Hsu Yung Chang’s sickness would
                            preclude his being able to serve on the Committee of Three and that
                            General Chen Cheng<note n="8" xml:id="d206fn8">Chief of the Chinese
                                General Staff.</note> would take his place. He added that he
                            (General Yu Tai-wei) would assist General Chen Cheng.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>