<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-23T21:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-23T21:30:00-05:00" n="216" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Minutes of Meeting Between General Marshall, General
                                Chen Cheng, and General Yu Ta-wei at No. 5 Ning Hai Road, Nanking,
                                October 24, 1946, 10:30 a.m.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Nanking</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-24T10:30:00+08:00">October 24, 1946, 10:30 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <table rend="width:50%" rendition="#center-block">
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap">Also present:</cell>
                                <cell>Col. Caughey</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>General Chen Cheng opened the meeting by asking General Marshall if he
                            had heard from General Chou En-lai concerning the Government’s eight
                            proposals. General Marshall replied that he had not but, through Dr.
                            Stuart, he had received a copy of what were supposed to be the 11
                            points, or questions, raised by the Communists.<note n="15" xml:id="d216fn15">Communist counterproposals of October 22, <ref target="#pg_412">p. 412</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>General Marshall stated that he had been more or less forced to withdraw
                            from negotiations since the Communist Party is of the <pb facs="0425" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/> firm belief that he is backing the
                            National Government. This is not so in Dr. Stuart’s case, nonetheless
                            both he and Dr. Stuart are sitting on the sidelines at the moment. The
                            third party group in the meantime is attempting to seek, as a neutral
                            buffer element between the Communists and Nationalists, a solution from
                            the existing confusing situation. General Marshall continued by stating
                            that he gathered from the talk he had had with the third party members
                            that the Communists’ real reason for objecting to the fact that certain
                            of the tentative June agreements were brought forth in the Government’s
                            eight proposals, whereas certain other of the tentative June agreements
                            were omitted (such as adhering to military positions as of 13 January
                            and 7 June), was based on the fact that the Communists probably would
                            not now agree to establishing in Harbin a symbolic force of 5,000 troops
                            and, at the same time, permit the Government to retain Kalgan which,
                            according to the tentative June agreements, was to have been retained by
                            the Communists. In other words, the real issue concerns an adjustment
                            with respect to Harbin and Kalgan. General Marshall reiterated that the
                            great hope in the present negotiations is the participation of the third
                            party, and he hoped that the National Government representatives would
                            receive this group wholeheartedly and graciously in an effort to find
                            some peaceful solution.</p>
                        <p>General Chen Cheng agreed that the third party group was the big hope at
                            the moment but he stated that its effectiveness had not yet been proven.
                            On top of this, his study of recent Yenan broadcasts would indicate that
                            the Communist Party was not in a frame of mind conducive for a peaceful
                            settlement. He added that this attitude had continued for several
                            months. At the outset of negotiations the Communists had initially
                            refused to submit the list of troops, which they desired to be retained
                            in the reorganized army, in accordance with the 25 February
                            reorganization agreement. He stated that, if that agreement could not be
                            put into force, discussion on all other issues, whether it be political
                            or military, is so much idle talk.</p>
                        <p>General Chen Cheng stated that he had gone to Peiping not long ago for
                            the purpose of issuing the necessary instructions to the various
                            military commanders to put into effect the 10-day Kalgan truce. He
                            stated that he had with him a 19-page confidential letter from the
                            Generalissimo which indicated specific instructions that were to be
                            followed. The major points of this letter were that all efforts would be
                            made to abide by a temporary truce; that the attitude on the part of the
                            Nationalist forces would be purely defensive; and that advances on
                            Kalgan would cease, with the exception of taking over by the Nationalist
                            forces of the northern section of the Peiping-Hankow <pb facs="0426" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> railroad. General Chen Cheng said that
                            this conference came to naught in view of the Communists’ refusal to
                            accept the 10–day truce.</p>
                        <p>General Chen Cheng stated that the third party was going to have
                            difficulty in resolving the major issues as is evidenced by the letter
                            containing the seven political and four military points issued by the
                            Communists. (General Yu Ta Wei submitted a Chinese text of the 11 points
                            which is attached hereto.) General Chen Cheng then informed General
                            Marshall that the Generalissimo probably would not be back from Formosa
                            until the 31st of October since that was the date upon which he is to
                            officially celebrate his birthday.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall told General Chen Cheng that the Generalissimo had told
                            him he would be back from Formosa in a few days or would return upon
                            four hours notice from General Marshall. General Marshall stated that a
                            protracted stay in Formosa on the part of the Generalissimo would have a
                            direct bearing on the negotiations and would appear to the outside world
                            that the Generalissimo was deliberately avoiding negotiations.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall stated that the reorganization of the armed forces was
                            the basic factor in the present negotiations. General Marshall remarked
                            that the present Government attitude regarding the February 25th
                            agreement was unrealistic wherein it attempted to locate only Communist
                            forces whereas the 25 February agreement required the location of both
                            Nationalist and Communist forces. To do otherwise would lead to fear on
                            the part of the Communists that their forces would be to [<hi rend="italic">so?</hi>] isolated to facilitate subsequent
                            liquidation by Government forces.</p>
                        <p>General Chen Cheng stated that he had not had much experience in
                            negotiating but did believe that the reorganization of the armed forces
                            was the crux of the present situation. He stated that, based on the 25
                            February agreement, 59 Government armies had already been reduced to a
                            division status. Thirty-one armies had yet to be reorganized into
                            divisions, but these armies were the ones in North China and Manchuria
                            which the Government could not reduce due to the present military
                            situation in those areas. Aside from the fact that this demobilization
                            was contemplated in the 25 February agreement, it was also an economic
                            measure in order to try to avoid a financial situation which the
                            Government could not support.</p>
                        <p>At this point Dr. Stuart entered the meeting.</p>
                        <p>General Yu Ta Wei stated that he had received a telegram from the
                            Generalissimo in which the Generalissimo firmly holds to the third of
                            the eight points in the Government’s proposal which concerns the
                            adjustment of her military situation in Manchuria in accordance with
                            tentative agreements reached in June. The Generalissimo also insisted
                            that the Communist troops in Antung and Tunghua be withdrawn <pb facs="0427" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/> within 15 days after a cease
                            fire order is issued and move north of the Sungari River within one
                            month, and that redeployment of Communist troops in accordance with the
                            tentatively agreed plan in June be completed by the end of one year.
                            General Marshall asked if the Government thought it was logistically
                            possible for the Communists to meet this schedule and General Chen Cheng
                            answered that he thought so. General Marshall then asked whether the
                            Generalissimo meant “all” Communist troops in Manchuria were to move
                            north of the Sungari River or whether he meant just Communist forces in
                            Antung and Tunghua. General Chen Cheng was not certain but said that he
                            would check.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall then asked Dr. Stuart to recite the results of his
                            meeting with General Chou (Dr. Stuart did so in Chinese at the request
                            of General Yu Ta Wei. The gist of Dr. Stuart’s comments however
                            pertained to the fact that the Communists could not accept the
                            Government’s eight points). General Marshall stated that at the present
                            time neither the Three Man Committee or the Five Man Committee could
                            meet until the third party had an opportunity to try to work out some of
                            the differences between the Government and the Communist Party.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall again mentioned, and Dr. Stuart agreed, that a
                            protracted delay by the Generalissimo would be construed as a definite
                            action to prevent successful culmination of present negotiations.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall asked General Chen Cheng what harm would result if the
                            Marines were withdrawn. General Chen Cheng replied that the immediate
                            reaction probably would be insignificant but that the overall effect,
                            from a world security viewpoint, would have great implications since it
                            would be a signal for Russian participation in Chinese affairs.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>