<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Notes on Meeting Between General Marshall and General C. P.
                        Lee
                    Chen-pien Lee, Director of the Serum Institute of
                        the Chinese Ministry of National Defense.
                    at General Marshall’s Residence, Nanking, November 18, 1946,
                        10 a.m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v10</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d283</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">283</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-11-17T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-11-17T21:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="united-nations" subject="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="self-determination" subject="coalition-government" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420" lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-17T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-17T21:00:00-05:00" n="283" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d283">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Notes on Meeting Between General Marshall and General C. P.
                        Lee</hi>
                    <note n="36" xml:id="d283fn36">Chen-pien Lee, Director of the Serum Institute of
                        the Chinese Ministry of National Defense.</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">at General Marshall’s Residence, Nanking, November 18, 1946,
                        10 a.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Nanking</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-18T10:00:00+08:00">November 18, 1946, 10 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <table rend="width:50%" rendition="#center-block">
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap">Also present:</cell>
                        <cell>Captain Soong<note n="37" xml:id="d283fn37">John L. Soong, U. S. Army,
                                language aide to General Marshall.</note>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>General Lee stated that the situation today is extremely critical. There seem to
                    be two possibilities. One is an open bloody revolution at the end of which the
                    Government would be totally destroyed. The other one is renewed hope for a
                    peaceful settlement if action would be taken by the United States Government or
                    the United Nations Organization, or if the Generalissimo would resign his post.
                    He further stated that public opinion regarding the present government is
                    rapidly deteriorating and that the situation today offers the Communist Party
                    its best opportunity to win over the Chinese people. General Lee then said that
                    third party members, such as Mr. Hu Lin,<note n="38" xml:id="d283fn38">Editor of
                        the newspaper, <hi rend="italic">Ta Kung Pao.</hi>
                    </note> have lost considerable stature through the present tragic situation
                    because of failure to speak to the Generalissimo in a most frank manner. The
                    present Government policy has thrown all the monetary resources into war. Such a
                    policy has driven many good and capable persons to the Communists’ side.</p>
                <p>General Marshall then said that there are two things apparent to him. One is that
                    the military leaders are now in the saddle and are thoroughly convinced that the
                    Communist Party will not go through with any agreement reached. The other is,
                    the strong political clique in the Kuomintang is firmly convinced that a
                    coalition government is not possible because the Communists would merely disrupt
                    such a government. With these two forces working together, they have produced
                    the tragic situation of today. General Marshall also mentioned that it is clear
                    to him that the Government is merely using the negotiations to prove its point
                    of view regarding the Communist Party.</p>
                <p>General Lee then said that the hope for settlement now rests largely on General
                    Marshall and the American Government because they can <pb facs="0561" n="551" xml:id="pg_551"/> force the Government to take a different course by openly
                    announcing the discontinuance of support to the present Government. However,
                    General Marshall stated that the U. S. Government cannot pursue a course of
                    action that will destroy the foundation of the Chinese Government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
