<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-12-15T21:45:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-12-15T21:45:00-05:00" n="332" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d332">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Notes on Meeting Between General Marshall and Mr. Hon
                                Yeh-chun at No. 5 Ning Hai Road, Nanking, December 16, 1946, 10:45
                                a.m.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Nanking</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1946-12-16T10:45:00+08:00">December 16, 1946, 10:45
                                a.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <table rend="width:50%" rendition="#center-block">
                            <row>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap">Also present:</cell>
                                <cell>Mr. Effenberg</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Yang Lien</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Captain Soong</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>General Marshall read the memorandum submitted by Mr. Hou of the Chinese
                            Democratic Party.<note n="28" xml:id="d332fn28">Not found in Department
                                files.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Mr. Hou told General Marshall that the objective of the Chinese
                            Democratic Party is to achieve unity, peace and democracy for China. He
                            related that during the war he served under General Tang En-po as the
                            Director of Political Affairs. Later, he realized the need of organizing
                            a new political party. This proposal was submitted to the Generalissimo
                            through Mr. Chang Wen-po, Minister of Political Affairs of the National
                            Military Council, and was approved. Now, the Chinese Democratic Party
                            has a total membership of 630,000 in Yunnan and Szechuan provinces. He
                            also pointed out that about 27% of these members are industrialists and
                            businessmen, and 40% are from the educational field. He further stated
                            that the majority are between the ages of 35 to 50.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Hou then said that he would like to represent the entire membership
                            of his party to pay their respects to General Marshall in his mission to
                            achieve peace, unity and democracy for China. Mr. Hou stated that his
                            party would devote itself to unification of the country and application
                            of the Three People’s Principles.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall said that the policy outlined in this memorandum would
                            be most difficult to attain. He expressed his belief that the <pb facs="0641" n="631" xml:id="pg_631"/> major hope for China at the
                            present time lay in the combined action of all the minority parties.
                            General Marshall stated that during the past year, he had become
                            familiar with the Democratic League and its branch under Mr. Carsun
                            Chang, the Youth Party, the Farmers’ League and the non-partisans who
                            almost functioned as a formal party. Ever since General Marshall arrived
                            in Nanking, he had exerted his best efforts to persuade the numerous
                            minority parties to organize into a third group to balance the situation
                            between the Kuomintang and the Communist Party. General Marshall said
                            that the representatives of the Democratic League, the Youth Party and
                            the non-partisans had joined together for a very brief period when they
                            came to Nanking shortly before the convening of the National Assembly,
                            and were for a time able to exert an important influence. Then they were
                            split apart under pressure from both the Kuomintang and Communist
                            Parties, as he had warned them would be the case. Now their influence
                            was negligible. They cancelled each other.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall stated that the most important thing at the present time
                            is to organize all the liberals into one party and select some outsider
                            to be the leader. He believed that the time had come for each of the
                            minority parties to make genuine sacrifices so that they can agree on
                            the formation of a strong and influential group to mediate between the
                            Kuomintang and the Communist Party. He emphasized that without
                            organization, the minority parties would be powerless. General Marshall
                            further stated that throughout his past year’s experience, he had found
                            many liberals both in the Kuomintang and among the younger members of
                            the Communist Party. He felt that many of the educated people joined the
                            Communists out of sheer disgust with the local Kuomintang governments.
                            General Marshall also believed that the Democratic League allied itself
                            with the Communists because they felt that the only way they could bring
                            about reform in the Government was by utilizing the power of the
                            Communist Party.</p>
                        <p>General Marshall said that great confusion had resulted from the evil
                            propaganda of both sides. This confusion had influenced many people
                            erroneously and had rendered negotiations more difficult.</p>
                        <p>In conclusion, General Marshall reiterated that the most important thing
                            at present is the unification of the minority parties. These minority
                            parties must make individual sacrifices in order to form an effective
                            organization to deal with the current situation. Mr. Hou said he would
                            endeavor to conduct his party in accordance with General Marshall’s
                            suggestion.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>