<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="612" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d612">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">Marshall Mission Files, Lot 54–D270:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">General <persName type="from">Marshall</persName> to
                                the Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Smith</hi></persName>)<note n="21" xml:id="d612fn21">Sent through the War Department.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Nanking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-14">14 May
                                1946</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>687. I quote below two letters addressed by me to the Russian Ambassador
                            in China Petrov. To date no acknowledgement of either has been received
                            although in my US absence my staff made two additional written
                            inquiries. The first letter was written in agreement with Mr. Byrnes as
                            an effort to save the State Department the necessity of bringing up the
                            question in the midst of other more pressing negotiation. I tried to
                            make my inquiries purely business communications devoid of diplomatic
                            implications except, of course, as to Soviet intentions regarding
                            Japanese military prisoners in their hands. In effect I was not
                            interested in this. It was only a question of how many of total of
                            MacArthur’s ships should be prepared to stand by.</p>
                        <p>His fleet of Japanese ships, large, small, LSTs etc, are bound by allied
                            agreement to be employed by him to evacuate Japanese, first from China,
                            Manchuria, Korea and then from Indo China, Neth East Indies, Malayas,
                            Burma, New Guinea, etc. Americans have had to process individuals
                            preparatory to embarkation as Chinese had not the trained personnel
                            available for the purpose of the Commanding General of US in China as to
                            coordinate this with MacArthur’s requirements.</p>
                        <p>I appear in the matter as the individual to contact Soviets if that is
                            necessary. Hence, the two letters quoted below. I doubt if you can help
                            but it might be that you could dispel any idea of a deep diplomatic plot
                            in my action and get them to treat it as it is: as purely business to
                            utilize shipping without delays. As to Japanese military prisoners, they
                            could merely remain silent as to that.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow texts of letters dated April 27 and March 9 printed on <ref target="#pg_892">pages 892</ref> and <ref target="#pg_890">890</ref>.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>