<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-20T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-20T09:00:00-05:00" n="834" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d834">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.60 Manchuria/2–2046: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-02-20T14:00:00+00:00">February 20,
                                1946—2 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received 3:17 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>2101. During course of general conversation this morning, Sterndale
                            Bennett<note n="24" xml:id="d834fn24">John Cecil Sterndale Bennett, head
                            of the Far Eastern Department of the British Foreign Office.</note>
                        mentioned account in today’s <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> of Secretary
                        Byrnes’ press conference where it was reported the Secretary had requested
                        China and Russia for information regarding Sino-Russian <pb facs="1119" n="1109" xml:id="pg_1109"/> negotiations about Manchuria. British press
                        has recently carried numerous stories of alleged Russian actions in
                        Manchuria most of them taken from American press and Sterndale Bennett
                        expressed considerable concern over what the true situation might be. He
                        stated he would appreciate receiving information of any formal approaches
                        which U. S. may have made to China or Russia as British are seriously
                        considering what their policy in this area should be.</p>
                    <p>Sterndale Bennett said it was difficult to decide on the basis of present
                        information whether the Russians intended to stay in Manchuria only until
                        they had managed to get from that territory all they wanted in the way of
                        industrial equipment or whether they intended to stay permanently there. In
                        either case he said it was a matter of concern and would necessitate
                            HMG<note n="25" xml:id="d834fn25">His Majesty’s Government.</note>
                        giving thought on a high level as to what its policy should be and whether
                        it might not be necessary “to show our teeth”. Sterndale Bennett said he did
                        not know what Mr. Bevin<note n="26" xml:id="d834fn26">Ernest Bevin, British
                            Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.</note> had in mind on this
                        problem but he did know that it was a source of worry particularly when
                        viewed in the light of Russian action in other areas of the globe. Embassy
                        would appreciate any detailed information on this subject which Department
                        may have and which could appropriately be communicated to the Foreign
                        Office.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>