<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-03-06T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-03-06T05:00:00-05:00" n="840" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d840">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 PW/3–646: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Counselor of Embassy in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Smyth</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-03-06T17:00:00+07:00">March 6,
                                1946—5 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received March 6—12:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>437. During a conversation this afternoon with Foreign Minister Wang
                        Shih-chieh, he referred to a Central News report from Washington dated March
                        5 and published here today concerning release by State Department<note n="34" xml:id="d840fn34">Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, March 17, 1946, p. 448.</note> of Secretary’s notes
                        to Chungking and Moscow on Manchuria and excerpts from Chinese reply; the
                        news report stated that “Russia has also replied to Byrnes’ note.” Dr. Wang
                        said that he would appreciate very much receiving any information Department
                        might wish to make available concerning Russian reply in question.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Wang then remarked that on three occasions he had inquired of Soviet
                        Ambassador Petrov as to date on which Russian troops would leave Manchuria
                        but that each time Petrov replied he had no information. Dr. Wang said that
                        Chinese Government was now considering sending a note to Soviet Government,
                        formally requesting that Russian troops leave Manchuria immediately. He said
                        he would keep us informed of developments.</p>
                    <p>Dr. Wang appeared considerably heartened by recent attitude of Soviet
                        Government.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Smyth</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>