<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="925" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d925">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">893.00/11–1446</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at Dairen</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Benninghoff</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                            the Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Stuart</hi></persName>)<note n="46" xml:id="d925fn46">Copy
                            transmitted to the Department without covering despatch; received
                            January 8, 1947.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 46</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dairen</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-14">November 14,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Sino-Soviet Relations in the Dairen Area and
                        Vicinity.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Consulate
                        General’s telegrams to the Department Nos. 14, 17 and 18 of October 31,
                        November 6 and November 12, 1946,<note n="47" xml:id="d925fn47">None
                            printed.</note> respectively, concerning the subject of the approach of
                        Chinese Government troops toward this area, the attitude of the Russians,
                        the movement of Chinese Communist forces, and allied subjects.</p>
                    <p>(<hi rend="smallcaps">Note</hi>: If these telegrams reached the Department,
                        they should have been repeated to the Embassy. True copies are enclosed,
                        however, for use if the telegraphic facilities of the USSR failed to get the
                        messages through.)</p>
                    <p>In sending these telegrams, the Consulate General desired to transmit
                        information gained in Dairen, from the scanty sources at its disposal,
                        concerning Chinese and American radio reports to the effect that
                        conversations regarding the early entry of Central Government officials into
                        Dairen were being held, and that Chinese Communist forces “from the Dairen
                        area” were being sent south across the Yellow Sea to Chefoo and elsewhere in
                        Shantung to reinforce Communist troops there.</p>
                    <p>To take the last point first; as of this date, there is no evidence which the
                        Consulate General has been able to unearth which would lead to a belief that
                        the Soviet military are permitting the Chinese Communists to use Dairen or
                        “The Port Arthur Naval Base Area” <pb facs="1201" n="1191" xml:id="pg_1191"/> for the embarcation of Chinese Communist forces for Shantung. Chinese
                        merchants are constantly traveling back and forth between Dairen and
                        Communist held areas, and not once has even a rumor to that effect been
                        received. It should be pointed out that most if not all the merchants of
                        this type are by nature anti-Communist and anti-Soviet, and they would be
                        only too glad to pass on information to the detriment of either. The
                        Consulate General feels that, as of today, the Russians have not permitted
                        the Chinese Communists to use this Area for any military purpose. If any
                        such activity is taking place, it must be on a very reduced scale, for any
                        large movement of troops could hardly pass unnoticed in a region where the
                        population would on the whole be hostile to such a movement.</p>
                    <p>When questioned on the subject, the Soviet Acting Consul General, Mr.
                        Petroff, appeared to resent the suggestion that the <hi rend="italic">bona
                            fides</hi> of this Government were being impugned, for he said that any
                        use of the Area by Communist troops would be contrary to the Sino-Soviet
                        Treaty. He did not specify the clause of the Treaty which would be violated,
                        but he probably had reference to the agreement that this Area was to be <del rend="strikethrough">jointly</del> solely<note n="*" xml:id="d925fn48">Correction per directions contained in Dairen’s despatch No. 40, Dec.
                            18, 1946. [Footnote in copy as received from the Embassy in
                            China.]</note> defended by Soviet and Central Government troops.</p>
                    <p>With reference to a broadcast from Nanking in which a Chinese Government
                        spokesman was quoted as stating that conversations looking toward the early
                        entry of Chinese Government officials into Dairen were being held, neither
                        the Soviet Consulate General nor the Soviet military command would profess
                        to any knowledge of the subject. Needless to say, most unthinking Chinese
                        took this broadcast to mean that Nanking officials could be expected any
                        day. More serious observers, however, hold the opinion that although the
                        entry of Nanking officials cannot be long delayed, an interval of two or
                        three months may elapse before negotiations can result in a satisfactory
                        agreement on details between the Chinese and Soviet Governments.</p>
                    <p>It is reasonable to suppose that the Chinese Government has approached the
                        Russians concerning the entry of their officials into Dairen. Such an
                        approach would almost inevitably have to be in Moscow, and therefore the
                        ignorance of local Soviet officials on the subject is not surprising. The
                        Russian reaction to such an approach at the present time, even though
                        Nationalist troops are on or at least near the “border” of the Area, would
                        probably be one of delay and obstruction. The political future of the North
                        East is not yet clear; the railroad is not in operation and no agreement
                        concerning it, as provided for in the Treaty, has been negotiated; the
                        status of Soviet <pb facs="1202" n="1192" xml:id="pg_1192"/> commercial and
                        trading trusts lias not been agreed upon; the Russians probably desire to
                        retain as much as possible of the present pro-Communist regime in this Area;
                        no decision has been made in regard to the difficult problem of foreign
                        exchange. These and similar problems, it is felt, will be dealt with in any
                        Sino-Soviet negotiations looking toward the entry of Central Government
                        officials into this Area.</p>
                    <p>In studying these questions, the Embassy should also bear in mind the fact
                        that the arrival of Nanking officials and the opening of the port to
                        international trade are synonymous in the minds of most Chinese, and
                        probably in the minds of the Russians as well. The Consulate General feels
                        that the Russians are no more prepared to open the port now than they were
                        five months ago (see despatch No. 16 dated June 20, 1946<note n="48" xml:id="d925fn49">Not printed.</note> entitled “The Soviet Position in
                        Dairen”), as the presence of Nationalist troops to the north of Dairen has
                        not materially altered the general picture <hi rend="italic">as viewed from
                            the Soviet angle</hi>. The national interests which the Russians
                        probably consider as vital in this region would be jeopardized by the
                        installation of a non-Communist local government which might attempt to open
                        the port, establish foreign exchange banks, and otherwise endanger the
                        monopoly now held and permanently desired by the Soviet Union. If the
                        Chinese Government is willing to make concessions to safeguard these
                        national interests, including the retention in the area of a Chinese regime
                        with a strong Communist flavor, the Russians might be disposed to abide by
                        their obligations under the Treaty.</p>
                    <p>Another factor which must not be lost sight of is that the Chinese Communists
                        have not yet been eliminated from the North East, or from Shantung, which is
                        economically and politically tied to the North East. It would therefore
                        appear reasonable for the Russians to play for time in the hope that out of
                        the current politico-military turmoil there will emerge a compromise which
                        will place in power in Changchun Chinese elements favorable to the U. S. S.
                        R. Such a development would make easier for the Russians the solution of the
                        problems mentioned above, and the safeguarding of their national
                        interests.</p>
                    <p>If this analysis is valid, the observer would normally expect to see cordial
                        relations established between Soviet and Communist troops along the “border”
                        of this Area, and the offer of military assistance of various kinds by the
                        Russians. But such has not been the case in the seven months which have
                        elapsed from the opening of this office. As far as can be learned from
                        inquiries made of Japanese, Chinese and even Russians who crossed from one
                        area into the other, there is almost no interchange of any kind between the
                        two forces. <pb facs="1203" n="1193" xml:id="pg_1193"/> The Russians in
                        Manchuria appeared just as determined to isolate their troops from “foreign”
                        influences as were their comrades in Germany when they met American and
                        British forces along the Elbe. Nor were reports received of any assistance
                        in military supplies or equipment, although rumors were current that the
                        Russians turned over to the Chinese Communists some captured Japanese
                        equipment. Foreign Service Officers in Mukden or elsewhere may have more
                        accurate estimates of the amount of assistance given the Communists by the
                        Russians.</p>
                    <p>In the commercial field as well, there does not appear to have been any great
                        cooperation between the two. Although the Chinese Communists for a number of
                        months were in control of large agricultural areas in Manchuria, there is
                        nothing to indicate that they cooperated to any great extent in furnishing
                        supplies to the Russians. It is true that a large quantity of beans and
                        grains was sent to Vladivostok and elsewhere in Soviet bottoms, but all
                        evidence available indicates that this was collected by the Russians
                        themselves during their occupation of a large part of Manchuria. This
                        Consulate General recently learned on very reliable authority that the
                        manager of the local branch of the Soviet grain trust sent agents into
                        Communist territory with a view to purchasing beans, wheat and other
                        cereals. The Communist officials in charge said that all crops had been
                        “Nationalized” and were for the use of the people and were not for sale.
                        This example, the Consulate General was informed, is illustrative of the
                        type of commercial “cooperation” between the Russians and the Chinese
                        Communists.</p>
                    <p>In the political field, however, the situation is quite different; there is
                        close cooperation. This Consulate General has little information concerning
                        the manner in which Russian political agents operate, but it is believed
                        that they are completely independent of the Red Army or any other normal
                        agency of the U. S. S. R. They are doubtless in close liaison with the
                        Chinese Communist Party. In any event, the Russians have permitted to
                        develop (or, some say, brought about) a situation in Dairen wherein the
                        Communist Party is the only one with a legal existence; the only newspaper
                        quotes only Yenan for its foreign news, and most of the officials other than
                        local figureheads are avowed Communists from places other than Dairen. There
                        has been built up in this Area a Chinese administration which is sympathetic
                        to the Russians, and over which they exercise a controlling voice. It is
                        difficult to believe that they would discard such a regime for one from
                        Nanking, without a substantial <hi rend="italic">quid pro quo.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>This office, accordingly, does not believe that the Russians have assisted
                        the Chinese Communists in sending troops to Shantung, or have given them any
                        other substantial military assistance. Furthermore—and this is admittedly
                        speculation—there would appear to be <pb facs="1204" n="1194" xml:id="pg_1194"/> no reason for the Russians to permit the early entry
                        of Nanking officials into Dairen unless in the negotiations leading to that
                        event they are able to protect and advance their own interests not only in
                        this Area but also in the whole North East.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Merrell Benninghoff</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>