<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-11-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="117" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72119/2676</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Swedish Minister</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Ekengren</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 5582</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-16">November
                                    16, 1918</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to request Your
                            Excellency to kindly transmit the following message of the Austrian
                            Government, which 1 have received today through my Government, to the
                            President of the United States:<note n="7" xml:id="d117fn7">The
                                following is a translation of the German text quoted by the
                                Minister; the file translation has been revised. A translation of
                                this note was sent to Colonel House in Department’s telegram No. 83,
                                Nov. 27, 1918, 4 p.m.</note>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Mr. President: The Provisional National Assembly of German
                                    Austria on November 12, 1918, unanimously resolved to constitute
                                    German Austria into a democratic Republic which is to form part
                                        <pb facs="0278" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/> of the Great
                                    German Republic. The German people of Austria, in the exercise
                                    of their right of self-determination, have thus made it known
                                    that they will not henceforth be subjected to any executive
                                    power other than that set up by themselves and that they want to
                                    restore the close political connection with Germany which,
                                    fifty-two years ago, was rent asunder by the sword. We hope, Mr.
                                    President, that you will give your support to these endeavors of
                                    the German people of Austria, in accordance with the principles
                                    so often proclaimed by you. You, Mr. President, have championed
                                    the right of the Poles, Italians and Jugo-Slavs who hitherto
                                    belonged to the Austrian State to unite with their National
                                    States outside of Austria. We are convinced that you will also
                                    concede the same right to the German people of Austria. We beg
                                    you, Mr. President, to offer us the earliest opportunity to
                                    enter upon preliminary peace negotiations. The Council of State
                                    of the German Austrian Republic is exclusively empowered to
                                    conduct those negotiations in our name; the powers of the former
                                    Austro-Hungarian Ministry of Foreign Affairs have expired. The
                                    Austro-Hungarian Missions abroad are provisionally empowered to
                                    represent the Council of State until the German Austrian
                                    Republic organizes a representative corps of its own. We have
                                    read with special attention the warning given by you, Mr.
                                    President, to the liberated peoples of Austria to be firm and
                                        cautious.<note n="8" xml:id="d117fn8">See telegram No. 3275,
                                        Nov. 5, 1918, 4 p.m., to the Minister in Switzerland, <ref target="frus1918Supp01v01#pg_470">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1918, supp. 1,
                                            vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 470</ref>.</note>
                                    Our Government, which consists of representatives of all the
                                    parties in German Austria, has thus far fully succeeded in its
                                    efforts to maintain order and liberty in our land. These efforts
                                    however are at present hampered by the severe lack of food which
                                    prevails in our country. The continuance of the blockade
                                    threatens the German people of Austria with a danger all the
                                    more serious as the Slav National States which grew out of the
                                    soil of Austria also lock out the German Austrian Republic and
                                    refuse to deliver to the German Austrian industrials the surplus
                                    of their agricultural products. Under those circumstances a
                                    hunger catastrophe hangs over the German Austrian Republic. We
                                    therefore take note with the greatest satisfaction of your
                                    willingness, Mr. President, to come to the relief of German
                                    Austria by sending food products and beg you kindly to afford
                                    that relief with the utmost dispatch. Accept, Mr. President, the
                                    expression of our most distinguished consideration.</p>
                                <p>The Foreign Office of the German Austrian Republic. Dr.
                                    Bauer”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">W. A. F. Ekengren</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>