<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Professor A. C. Coolidge to Professor Clive Day, of the Commission to
                    Negotiate Peace</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">150</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-01-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-01-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-01-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="150"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d150">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 184.01102/3½</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Professor <persName type="from">A. C. Coolidge</persName> to
                        Professor <persName type="to">Clive Day</persName>, of the Commission to
                        Negotiate Peace</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-01-01">January 1,
                            1919</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Day</hi>: I have just had a long and interesting
                    interview with Gueshov.<note n="2" xml:id="d150fn2">T. E. Gueshov, former Prime
                        Minister of Bulgaria.</note> As Bulgaria is perhaps out of the bounds of my
                    vague bailie-wick, I am writing to you directly instead of reporting to the
                    Commission. Gueshov, as you know, has been out of his country for some months
                    and finds it difficult to keep in touch with it. He has almost no direct news
                    from Bulgaria and not much from elsewhere except what appears in the papers. His
                    main point was that according to the eleventh of the Fourteen Articles the
                    Balkan questions will be settled according to principles of justice and that
                    justice is all <pb facs="0310" n="222" xml:id="pg_222"/> that Bulgaria asks for.
                    I gently suggested to him that everybody else said the same thing, but he of
                    course has no doubt in the justice of his own claims. He regards Macedonia as
                    incontrovertibly Bulgarian and took the line that one ought to disregard all
                    that was said by Bulgarians and Serbians, (he naturally has no use for
                        Cvjich<note n="3" xml:id="d150fn3">Jovan Cvjich, Serbian author, professor
                        at the University of Belgrade.</note>), and confine oneself to the testimony
                    of competent neutrals who were in a position to know. He instanced the Carnegie
                        Report,<note n="4" xml:id="d150fn4">
                        <hi rend="italic">Report of the International Commission to Inquire into the
                            Causes and Conduct of the Balkan Wars</hi> (Carnegie Endowment for
                        International Peace, Washington, 1914).</note> the Encyclopedia Britannica
                    (Bourchier), and the American Missionaries in the Balkans. I hinted that some of
                    these authorities if neutral were not exactly impartial. A thing he laid
                    particular stress upon, as do naturally the Austrians, Magyars and others here,
                    was the unfairness of having their fate decided upon without their being
                    consulted. Gueshov asserted that as Bulgaria had not been at war with the United
                    States it would be unjust to her to have her destiny settled on the base of the
                    Eleventh Article without her voice being heard. Incidentally he made the rather
                    amusing point that if the Serbian view was accepted that the Macedonians were
                    Serbians, why then so were the Slavs within the Greek boundaries, in which case
                    the cry of a Serbia Irredenta would be soon be raised in a country much larger
                    and more powerful than Greece.</p>
                <p>I told Gueshov a little about the Division of Information in Paris and said that
                    the Legation here could send to it any literature that he wished to furnish it,
                    but advised him to spare you common or garden propaganda. He spoke bitterly of
                    the Greek charges of Bulgarian atrocities, stating that it was just what the
                    Greeks had done five years ago. They had cut off the Bulgarians from any
                    communication with the outside world, and had then accused them of atrocities
                    which were afterwards proved to be false. Here he referred to the Carnegie
                    Report. He asked if I included anti-atrocity literature in the material it was
                    useless to send. I said that the contradiction of any story was always worth
                    while.</p>
                <p>Gueshov took up the question of Bulgaria’s part in the present war. He declared
                    she had been forced into it by the king and by her geographical position against
                    the will of the great majority of the population and that the Bulgarian soldiers
                    had been no more willing combatants against the Allies than had the
                    Czecho-Slovaks and the Croatians. He adverted to the point that one of the three
                    Yugo-Slav commissioners in Paris, the Slovenian Zolger, had been one of the
                    chief aides of Seidler in Austria and contrasted this with the Bulgarian lack of
                    representation. He said that he and the opposition had done everything they
                    could to prevent the king from taking the fateful step, but unlike Venizelos
                    they had had no Allied support to bring pressure, <pb facs="0311" n="223"
                        xml:id="pg_223"/> that they had asked for a landing at Saloniki, Dedeagatch
                    or Varna, but they had been refused, that if Rumania had gone into the war when
                    Italy did, as was expected, Ferdinand would never have dared to stir. He said
                    that from Switzerland last summer he had implored the Malinov Ministry to
                    prevent the king from going on his last visit to Germany, but that he supposed
                    that Malinov had felt if he should do so, it would merely mean the recall of
                    Radoslavov. He said that Ferdinand would never have come to Bulgaria if
                    Alexander III had not refused to allow Prince Waldemar of Denmark to accept the
                    crown offered to him, (in those days England was Ferdinand’s chief friend and
                    supporter), that this foreign prince has brought untold evil on his people, and
                    that it was most unjust that they should have to suffer for all the things he
                    had done.</p>
                <p>Finally he expressed the hope that if it was impossible for any Bulgarian
                    representative to get to Paris, someone of you familiar with Balkan subjects
                    might come to confer with him and others here.</p>
                <p>I have also had an interview with Professor Constantine Stephanov, a professor in
                    the University of Sofia. He is a Macedonian by birth and feeling. He declares
                    that the Macedonians were largely responsible for the fact that Bulgaria joined
                    the Central Powers in 1915 because their ill-treatment at the hands of the
                    Serbians was such and their desire for the reunion of the different parts of
                    their territory was so great that they did much to influence Bulgarian opinion.
                    Professor Stephanov regards Macedonia as one and indivisible and also as
                    overwhelmingly Bulgarian, though this last was not the line of argument he
                    pursued. He declared that the only just thing to do as had already been
                    indicated in the usual inevitable telegram to President Wilson was to have the
                    whole of Macedonia occupied by impartial Allied troops and then a plebiscite
                    taken of the wishes of the inhabitants. I asked him if that plebiscite were in
                    favor of Serbia whether he would be willing to accept it for the whole of the
                    country including even the most eastern and Bulgarian portion of it. He wriggled
                    a little, but in general said yes, evidently not regarding the contingency as
                    possible. I asked him how he should feel about the same plan being tried in
                    Thrace. He expressed a willingness to which I do not believe Gueshov would
                    agree. He repeated that the Macedonians had a strong local sentiment of their
                    own and that they would prove practically impossible to govern against their own
                    consent. We skirmished a little as to just what was Macedonia. He seemed to me
                    not very practical, but sincere and interesting as expressing the Macedonian
                    point of view.</p>
                <p>We are delayed here by the length of the holiday but hope to get off Friday.
                    Happy New Year.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Archibald Cary Coolidge</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
