<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commander of United States Naval Forces in the Eastern Mediterranean (
                    (Bullard) ) to Admiral W. S. Benson</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d250</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">250</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-12-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-12-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037040"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Deportation</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-12-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="250"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d250">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 186.3411/98</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Commander of United States Naval Forces in the Eastern
                        Mediterranean</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullard</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to Admiral <persName type="to">W. S.
                            Benson</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">U. S. S. “Gregory,” Fiume</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-12-15">15 December,
                            1918</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Report activities Eastern Adriatic.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Captain Gherardi, U. S. Navy, arrived on board on Tuesday, December 10,
                        while the <hi rend="italic">Birmingham</hi> was at Spalato, bringing certain
                        verbal instructions and memorandum notes from Admiral Benson regarding
                        policy to be followed by the United States Representative in Adriatic
                        affairs.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Stribling</hi> left Spalato on Tuesday December 10,
                        carrying the different representatives of the United States at Pola in
                        connection with the terms of the Austro-Hungarian armistice. On receiving
                        notice of her arrival, I was able to report that arrangements for executing
                        the terms of the armistice on the part of the United States, as far as it
                        related to former Austro-Hungarian Men of War, naval equipment, etc., were
                        completed.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>There being no further immediate need of my presence at Spalato, and
                        desiring to get in closer touch with the Allied representatives of the Naval
                        Committee for the Adriatic, I left Spalato in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Birmingham</hi> on Wednesday December 11 for Venice, arriving off
                        harbor at daylight Thursday December 12. The weather was very foggy and
                        entrance into the harbor could not be effected until late in afternoon. I
                        found that the French Admiral Fatou, a member of the Naval Committee for the
                        Adriatic was seriously ill and would have to go to a <pb facs="0416" n="328"
                            xml:id="pg_328"/> hospital. British Admiral Kiddle had left earlier in
                        the week for Fiume. On Friday afternoon I received despatch from Admiral
                        Sims appointing me United States representative on a commission to hold an
                        inquiry and make a report to the Allied Governments showing clearly what is
                        the existing situation, and what measures it is necessary to take to watch
                        against disagreement or trouble in any territory of the Adriatic occupied
                        by, or to be occupied by, Allied Forces outside of those mentioned in
                        Article 3 of the Austrian armistice terms, such as Corfu, Spalato, Fiume,
                        etc. I was directed to report to senior representative of the commission
                        without delay. Accordingly, at once made plans for going to Fiume where I
                        was informed the Italian admiral was, as he was the Senior representative of
                        the Commission. I left Venice at daylight Saturday December 14 in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Gregory</hi>, leaving the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Birmingham</hi> at Venice as it was necessary she should coal. Captain
                        Gherardi accompanied me, as it was my desire to retain him until the return
                        of Captain Hussey, as the latter might bring further points on which
                        uncertainty might exist, and Captain Gherardi could return with full
                        information.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I had some time previously received word from the Admiral Cagni at Pola
                        that new mine fields had been discovered in the ordinarily used route to
                        Fiume, and therefore it was necessary to go to Pola to obtain a pilot and
                        first hand information. Arrived at Pola at 11:30 a.m. and had conferences
                        with Admiral Cagni and our senior representative Commander G. C. Logan. The
                        latter reported that everything was progressing smoothly and he had every
                        assistance offered him and courtesies shown by the Italian authorities. He
                        reported that they had not started to make inventories as yet, but would
                        soon begin. Left Pola at 1:30 with pilot and arrived at Fiume at sunset and
                        made fast to wharf. I found the senior representative of the New Commission
                        to be Rear Admiral Mola, temporarily quartered in an Italian Battleship and
                        I reported to him in person. Rear Admiral Kiddle of the English Navy, the
                        British representative, was quartered in an English Gunboat. I informed
                        Admiral Mola of Admiral Fatou’s illness and of his inability to attend any
                        meeting until all four representatives were present, and telegraphed the
                        Italian Naval Ministry with request to forward to French Naval Ministry to
                        appoint another representative.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Rear Admiral Kiddle called on me and detailed the serious situation that
                        had arisen involving the French and the Italians. The French had not
                        recognized the right of the Naval Committee for the Adriatic to allow only
                        Italian authorities to requisition Austro-Hungarian merchant ships, and
                        accordingly the French representative, Commodore Dumesnil, acting under
                        orders of the French Commander in Chief, Admiral Gauchet, hoisted the French
                        flag in six merchant ships and announced his intention of requisitioning
                        them <pb facs="0417" n="329" xml:id="pg_329"/> for the French navy.
                        Meanwhile the Italians said if they put to sea without an escort and a safe
                        passport issued by the Italian authorities they would be arrested for
                        breaking the blockade. Admiral Kiddle appreciating the grave consequences of
                        such an act persuaded the French Commodore to wait a reasonable time,
                        explaining that the action of the Naval Committee of the Adriatic required
                        the requisitioning by Italian authorities and the trade routes were to be
                        determined by the Allied Maritime Transport Committee of London. In the
                        meantime the French Commodore was called away hurriedly and while he was
                        gone, a subordinate French officer was persuaded their projected course was
                        not justified, and hauled down the French flags. Immediately the Italian
                        authorities stepped in and removed four of the ships to Pola for
                        requisitioning. On return of the French Commodore, who had received positive
                        orders to hoist the French flag and take the ships to sea, he hoisted the
                        French flag on the remaining two and one put to sea with a French
                        representative on board, and was not molested, and announced his intention
                        of sending the other one the next morning, Sunday December 15. The Italian
                        authorities by this time, firmly believing in their right to arrest these
                        ships, repeated their intentions to arrest this second ship if attempt was
                        made to go to sea. Such were the conditions when I arrived on the scene.
                        Admiral Kiddle suggested an informal meeting to discuss the affair and I
                        attended, expecting to do what was within my power to prevent the Italians
                        from carrying out their purpose of making this arrest. Fortunately, I had
                        seen the Chief of Staff of Admiral Fatou in Venice just before sailing and
                        he told me of a visit he made to Rome to see Admiral Revel, Chief of Staff
                        of Italian Navy and President of the Naval Committee for the Adriatic, and
                        how he had arranged that the French should requisition certain ships, fly
                        the French flag, and have a French representative on board. This was quite
                        at variance with the decision of the Naval Committee of the Adriatic, and
                        changed in principle, the Committee’s action without in any way informing
                        the Committee or even the Italian Representatives themselves. Recognizing
                        here was a way out of the difficulty, I presented the memorandum copy which
                        I had obtained from the Chief of Staff to Admiral Fatou, and as it had his
                        signature the Italian representatives consented to receive it as an official
                        document, and Admiral Kiddle and myself directed a letter to the Italian
                        Admiral recommending that he play no part in carrying out the threatened
                        arrest, and he accordingly informed the French Commodore that having
                        received later information, the sailing of the ship would not be contested,
                        and thus the incident passed without the probable grave consequences that
                        might have accompanied it. I explained this condition in a despatch and
                        explained that as the threatened state of affairs would take place in <pb
                            facs="0418" n="330" xml:id="pg_330"/> a few hours and I could not refer
                        the matter further, requested approval of my action.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>While at Pola I learned that orders had been given by the Italian C-in-C
                        that certain persons would be deported from that place. I do not know where
                        the authority comes for such an order, but apparently the Italians are
                        proceeding on the assumption they are never to be moved. Their action
                        certainly cannot be based on any terms of the Armistice. This might be a
                        fruitful source of inquiry by the new Commission, but this Commission is
                        barred from considering anything included in the area described in Article 3
                        of the Austrian Armistice terms. I made the report of this deportation in a
                        special despatch, Adriatic Nine,<note n="27" xml:id="d250fn27">Not found in
                            Department files.</note> and the full text of the proclamation is
                        contained in a written report from the U. S. Naval Representative at Pola,
                        copy of which is forwarded herewith together with other proclamations and
                        information of interest collected there.<note n="28" xml:id="d250fn28">No
                            enclosures with file copy of this document.</note> This report came to
                        me at Pola which explains the delay in forwarding. There are no means of
                        sending mail between ships of my forces except by destroyers, and as their
                        presence is needed as station ships and for communication purposes, mail
                        communication is practically at a standstill.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Owing to the presence of so many ships at Fiume, the air is constantly
                        filled with radio messages making the reception of messages sent from here
                        extremely difficult, and an attempt is being made to arrange a sending
                        schedule for ships of various Navies. There is a telegraph line from Fiume
                        connecting with the lines of other countries, but at the best telegraph
                        communication is bad and subject to severe delays … Messages are repeated by
                        radio whenever possible to the station ship at Venice, there to connect with
                        the telegraph line, but the same conditions exist there and I never feel
                        confident that my despatches go through. Some despatches from London and
                        Paris have taken five days.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>I feel the need of a small ship to carry stores, supplies, etc., and act
                        as general tender to the disarmed ships at Spalato, but have refrained from
                        asking for a special government ship, hoping I could get one of the small
                        Austrian coasting vessels now at Spalato. I have sent despatches concerning
                        the same, both to London and Rome and trust to have some measure of success.
                        This may involve the regular requisitioning of the ship, but I think there
                        will be no complications in the details concerning this, as whatever expense
                        is incurred will be well repaid by the services rendered. With only such
                        boats that the destroyer station ship carries in addition <pb facs="0419"
                            n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/> to a few boats on the battleships, there is
                        not much in the way of communication involving long distances or carrying
                        capacity.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Conditions at Fiume are generally quiet with now and then a local outbreak
                        due to temper or exasperation on the part of the populace. It has the air of
                        a purely Italian permanent occupation, and Italian flags fly everywhere and
                        I was informed that there was a soldier wherever an Italian flag was flying
                        to see that it was not disturbed. There are constant forms of different
                        propaganda: parades with flags flying, the issuing of a special class of
                        literature, and public utterances. There are only a few Jugo-Slav flags
                        seen. Nearly every person wears some sort of a national emblem to show his
                        nationality and sympathies. Sometimes this leads to street fighting among
                        the disorderly element. I understand an Italian governor has been appointed
                        and most of the business of the city is in the hands of the Italians.
                        Wherever they have entered along the Adriatic, they have entered in force
                        and entrenched themselves in every possible way. There seems thousands of
                        Italian troops, certainly 12,000 and soldiers are met everywhere. There is
                        also a battalion of English soldiers and a battalion of American soldiers. I
                        saw a French General on shore but no troops. Later learned there was one
                        battalion. The condition here will be thoroughly examined into by the new
                        Commission. I saw the Commanding Officer of the American Forces, Colonel
                        Wallace, and he said he expected to call on me. The American Officers are
                        quartered in an Austrian-Hungarian steamer and have every comfort and even
                        luxury. It is the part of the Italians to keep them under obligation in
                        every way. I have repeatedly expressed the opinion there was no necessity
                        for troops in this city, as I could not see it was provided for in the
                        Armistice, except in the general clause which allows troops to be landed to
                        quell disorder and preserve peace, but this does not require the landing of
                        thousands of troops as the Italians have done. Without definite instructions
                        I shall use my best endeavors in persuading my colleagues that if any troops
                        are needed at all, they should be but a small representation, certainly not
                        more than a battalion, and trust this may meet with approval. The fact that
                        the French wish to make this a port for evacuation of troops from the
                        interior and from the east, and that supplies will be forwarded from here to
                        the permanent Army of Occupation will probably lead them to wish for a much
                        larger force.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>The <hi rend="italic">Leonidas, Mazont</hi>, fuel ship, and chasers have
                        left for Corfu. One unit of these boats had arrived in Greece and another
                        was on its way.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">W. H. G. Bullard</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
