<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Commission to Negotiate Peace</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">252</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-12-17T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-12-17T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-12-17T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-17T20:00:00-05:00" n="252"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d252">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 186.3411/105: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-12-17T20:00:00-05:00"
                            >December 17, 1918—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received December 19—10:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>40. Following from Italian Embassy December 11th: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Commander of the Italian forces in Dalmatia has received, on
                            November 21st ultimo, a telegram from the provincial government <pb
                                facs="0422" n="334" xml:id="pg_334"/> of Zagabria asking that the
                            orders of the Italian command to the local authorities be imparted
                            through the central committee of Zagabria. In this telegram the
                            provincial government also protested against Admiral Millo haying
                            prevented officials residing in the territory occupied by the Italians,
                            to take the oath of allegiance to Jugoslavia. To this protest Admiral
                            Millo replied that while he, according to the terms of the Armistice,
                            has control of the local authorities, no reference is made in the
                            Armistice to other authorities residing beyond the territory of
                            occupation. He could not grant the request made him but had to continue
                            in dealing only with the local authorities. It is also reported that the
                            same committee has forced officials in Spalato to take the allegiance
                            oath, justifying such action with the authority derived by the fact that
                            it was recognized by the powers. Magistrates and other employees of
                            Italian nationality who, deferring to the decisions of the Peace
                            Conference, refused until then to submit to take the oath, have been
                            because of this resistance declared deposed and a disadvantageous
                            settlement of their rights to pensions has been imposed upon them. It is
                            expected that arbitrary measures of the same kind will be taken against
                            local officials of other classes. Your Excellency cannot fail to see the
                            illegality of such actions on the part of the Jugo-Slav Committee which
                            cannot, not even when it is question of zones lying beyond the line of
                            Armistice, perform acts in contrast with the manifest situation there
                            existent as Spalato is occupied by the Allies and America. It behooves
                            the Associated Governments to cause a conduct to prevail there based on
                            the principle that the occupying military authority has not the right
                            (excepting for all essential exigencies of military character or of
                            public order) to consent to any modification to the instructions and
                            laws in force. While asking me to bring what precedes to Your
                            Excellency’s knowledge the Royal Government expresses the desire that
                            instructions inspired by the same principles be also imparted by the
                            United States Government to their military and naval authorities in the
                            Adriatic.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Italian Chargé d’Affaires added orally that French officer in command at Albania
                    had reported that Italian delegates had been called to establish government, and
                    intimated that the Italians were parties to it. The Italians said they had never
                    called such a meeting and feared trouble would result. Baron Sonnino was anxious
                    the United States should know they were not at fault in case of trouble. Chargé
                    also said there was trouble in Southern Albania. He wanted to know what we knew
                    about the Serbs occupying Banat. He was informed that all those questions should
                    be settled in Paris.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Polk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
