<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-12-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="307" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d307">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72119/3263</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Swedish Minister</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Ekengren</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-12-23">December
                                    23, 1918</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: By order of my Government I
                            have the honor to transmit to You the following communication from the
                            Austro-German Government which communication has been simultaneously
                            transmitted to all of the allied powers:<note n="10" xml:id="d307fn10">The following is a translation of the French text quoted by the
                                Minister. A translation was sent to the Commission to Negotiate
                                Peace in Department’s telegram No. 126, Jan. 7, 1919, 3 p.m.</note>
                            <pb facs="0472" n="384" xml:id="pg_384"/>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Council of State finds itself under the necessity of taking
                                    the most formal exception to the military occupation by the
                                    Czechoslovak State of German Bohemia and of several parts of the
                                    Sudetes region and the Znaim district in Moravia. The armistice
                                    terms left the German Austrian Government powerless to resist
                                    the above mentioned invasion by force. The aforesaid occupation
                                    by Czechoslovak troops cannot however in any way impair the
                                    right of the German people concerned to shape out their own
                                    destinies. The German Austrian Republic insisting on the
                                    principle that no nation can be forcibly subjected to a foreign
                                    State again appeals to all the civilized States urging them to
                                    recognize the right of the aforesaid people to choose the State
                                    to which the territory shall hereafter belong by means of a
                                    plebiscite superintended by neutral authorities and protected by
                                    neutral troops. Neither the Government of the Republic nor the
                                    two local Governments can under those conditions accept
                                    responsibility for the proper conduct of public
                                    administration.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>With renewed assurances [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">W. A. F. Ekengren</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>