<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Denmark ( (Osborne) ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d361</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">361</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-01-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recu3GH1ojKcJBA1c" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="recfABRQvTqVuIjoA" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-01-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-01-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="361"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d361">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72119/3897</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Denmark</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Osborne</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="10" xml:id="d361fn10">A copy of this despatch, with its enclosure, was
                        sent to the Commission to Negotiate Peace, Jan. 18, 1919, by the American
                        Embassy in Paris.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1995</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-01-03">January 3,
                            1919</date>.<lb/>[Received February 25.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Adverting to my telegram No. 3385,<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d361fn11">Not printed.</note> of yesterday’s date, with regard to
                    the visit of M. Paderewski to Posen, I have the honor to enclose herewith the
                    memorandum on which that telegram was based.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lithgow Osborne</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chargé in Denmark</hi> (<hi
                            rend="italic">Osborne</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-01-01">January 1,
                                1919</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The British Chargé d’Affaires to-day showed me an original despatch from
                        Colonel H. H. Wade, British Military Attaché in Copenhagen, dated from Posen
                        December 28 (?), 1918, relative to M. Paderewski’s visit to Poland.</p>
                    <p>The despatch stated that upon his arrival in Danzig, together with Monsieur
                        and Madame Paderewski, he was visited by a German official who requested
                        that no demonstrations be organized in Danzig. Colonel Wade replied that he
                        could not prevent M. Paderewski’s friends from meeting him at the station.
                        The German official endeavored to induce Colonel Wade and M. Paderewski to
                        proceed to Warsaw via Thorn, but Colonel Wade insisted on going to
                        Posen.</p>
                    <p>The party was given a saloon car from Danzig. On the way to Posen a
                        representative of the German General Staff in civilian clothes boarded the
                        train and informed Colonel Wade that his safe-conduct called for his transit
                        through Germany to Warsaw and requested that he should not proceed to Posen.
                        Colonel Wade replied that he had received orders to proceed to Posen, where
                        he was to meet the rest of his mission, and that the German Foreign Office
                        must be cognizant of this fact. In consequence of this statement by Colonel
                        Wade, the representative of the German General Staff withdrew, saying that
                        in that case he only wished to enter a formal protest, which Colonel Wade
                        reported that he took note of.</p>
                    <p>Colonel Wade further reported that upon their arrival in Posen they were
                        greeted with great enthusiasm by the populace; their carriage was escorted
                        by Polish soldiers from the railway station to the <pb facs="0511" n="423"
                            xml:id="pg_423"/> hotel; the soldiers finally ended by carrying the
                        mission into the hotel. The following day shots were heard, and it was soon
                        reported that German soldiers had stormed the offices of the Polish National
                        Council and had torn down the Polish and Allied flags and stamped them into
                        the gutter. These German soldiers were supposedly “reactionaries.” At the
                        time of writing the despatch, Colonel Wade stated that the hotel was being
                        besieged by these German troops and defended by Polish soldiery.</p>
                    <p>Colonel Wade further reported that agitation was under way by the Germans for
                        the organization of forces of defense in the province of Posen, and that
                        these German forces were following a policy of repression against the Poles,
                        suppressing the language, etc. He had despatched Lieutenant Commander
                        Rawlings, R. N., who was attached to him, to the Commander of the Fifth Army
                        Corps, with the message that the British Government would hold him
                        responsible for the consequences of the attitude of the German troops. The
                        Commander of the Fifth Army Corps replied that he had no official knowledge
                        of Colonel Wade’s mission.</p>
                    <p>Colonel Wade further stated that the German forces in the province of Posen
                        were removing valuable material of all kinds and in general treating the
                        territory as if they were forces of occupation and in a manner contrary to
                        the terms of the armistice. He recommended that Allied or neutral
                        commissioners be despatched to exercise surveillance.</p>
                    <p>Enclosed with Colonel Wade’s despatch were the following: <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>An American flag torn to shreds, stated to have been one of those
                                pulled down by the German troops from the offices of the Polish
                                National Council.</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>A proclamation signed by the Commander of the Fifth Army Corps,
                                the Workmen’s and Soldiers’ Council, the Jewish Council, and other
                                city organizations, promulgating a state of siege for the
                                city.</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>A hand-bill printed by some German organization setting forth the
                                consequences of Posen’s becoming Polish and calling upon the German
                                population to “vote German” for the National Assembly.</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>A copy of the same manifesto republished by the German
                                organization in question with notations by a Pole made on the
                                original hand-bill.</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>An official order issued by the Commander of the Fifth Army Corps
                                and countersigned by the “Schlichtungskommission” stating that
                                disorders had broken out in the city, that it was still too soon to
                                determine the guilt in the matter, but calling upon all troops to
                                maintain order, in view of the hardships which they had undergone
                                together during the war.</item>
                            <label>(6)</label>
                            <item>An official order signed by the Commander of the Fifth Army Corps
                                and countersigned by the “Schlichtungskommission” stating that a
                                British commission had arrived and that, as it was under the
                                protection of international law, it was not to be interfered with.
                                The order further stated that the commission would carry the British
                                flag.</item>
                            <pb facs="0512" n="424" xml:id="pg_424"/>
                            <label>(7)</label>
                            <item>A clipping from a German newspaper in Posen calling for the
                                formation of voluntary militia for the protection of German
                                interests in the province of Posen.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>In a letter to his wife, Colonel Wade stated that field-guns had been drawn
                        up in front of the hotel, which was being fired on by machineguns from the
                        neighboring buildings. Bullets had entered Mr. Paderewski’s room.</p>
                    <p>Colonel Wade also indicated that he was not in complete accord with M.
                        Paderewski’s ideas as to the territorial extent of Poland, which he seemed
                        to regard as exaggerated.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
