<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Commission to Negotiate Peace</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919Parisv02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-12-13T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-12-13T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recabc45112c903455" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="armistices" subject="armistice">Armistice</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-12-13T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-13T19:00:00-05:00" n="39"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d39">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.711/854a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-12-13T19:00:00-05:00"
                            >December 13, 1918—7 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>25. For the President from McCormick. A serious movement is on foot here to
                    abolish forthwith all censorship insofar as the United States is concerned.
                    While fully appreciating that there should be a material and progressive
                    relaxation in censorship administration, I am equally clear that, prior to the
                    abolition of censorship as a war measure, this whole problem should be made the
                    subject of interallied discussion, presumably at Paris. The censorship has been
                    one of the effective weapons for weakening Germany economically. Without
                    censorship it would have been and would now be impracticable to prevent the
                    strong commercial and financial groups in Germany from undertaking active and
                    profitable operations through their branches in neutral countries at the expense
                    of Allies and weaker neutral nations. With the abolition of censorship, we would
                    remove a most potent influence for paralyzing German efforts at economic
                    rehabilitation through financial and commercial operations abroad before the
                    conclusion of peace. The censorship is thus one of the recognized blockade
                    measures which all of the associated governments have been administering and
                    which still constitutes a most important influence, particularly on the
                    wealthier classes in Germany, the foreign connections of which are extensive and
                    still maintained in large part. The elimination of censorship might appreciably
                    lessen the importance particularly to this class in Germany of the speedy
                    conclusion of a definitive peace. The terms of the armistice provide that
                    blockade conditions shall remain unchanged, and it was certainly not
                    contemplated that any one of the associated governments should during the period
                    of the armistice abruptly and by independent action totally abandon an important
                    blockade measure <pb facs="0140" n="52" xml:id="pg_52"/> such as censorship.
                    Were we to do so, it would in my opinion place us in an unfavorable light before
                    our associates and we would lay ourselves open to the charge of hastening to
                    secure a trade advantage through permitting the revival of enemy trade in our
                    interest, and we would further be charged with desiring to shift to our
                    associates the odium of maintaining an unpopular measure. If you concur in the
                    view that the abolition of censorship should first be made the subject of
                    interallied discussion in order that a common understanding may, if possible, be
                    arrived at, I should appreciate your cabling me to this effect, as there is
                    considerable doubt here as to your views, and I should like an expression
                    thereof to show, if it seems necessary, to congressmen and other officials who
                    would welcome an expression of your opinion.</p>
                <p>Mr. Polk fully concurs with the foregoing view as to the unfortunate effect which
                    independent action on our part at this time would have on our international
                    relations.</p>
                <p>While in my judgment the most important aspect of our proposed abolition of
                    censorship is the effect which it would have on our international relations, it
                    may be noted from a domestic standpoint that the Trading with the Enemy Act,
                    which remains law, cannot be enforced without the aid of censorship and that the
                    Alien Property Custodian is almost daily obtaining through censorship important
                    information as to enemy-owned property not heretofore reported to him.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Polk</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
