<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-12-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="396" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d396">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">759.6214/14</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Sharp</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 2415</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-12-13">December
                                    13, 1918</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department encloses, for the
                            information of Colonel House, copies of the following despatches from
                            the American Legation at Copenhagen, with reference to the cession of
                            the Province of North Slesvig:</p>
                        <p>No. 1889, dated November 8, 1918; No. 1890, dated November 8, 1918, with
                            enclosure; No. 1895, dated November 12, 1918, with enclosure.</p>
                        <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                        <closer>For the Acting Secretary of State: <lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Breckinridge Long</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Denmark</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grant-Smith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="4" xml:id="d396fn4">Filed separately under
                                    759.6214/12.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1889</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-08">November 8, 1918</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Adverting to my telegram No. 2946, of
                                October 14th,<note n="5" xml:id="d396fn5">Not printed.</note> last,
                                informing the Department of my interview with the King of Denmark
                                regarding the matter of Slesvig I have the honor to report that
                                after H. M. subsequently sent for M. Scavenius, Minister for Foreign
                                Affairs, and that the interview which followed was anything but of
                                an amiable character.</p>
                            <p>The King is said to have reproached M. Scavenius for having assured
                                me that no conversations were being had with Germany in regard to
                                the cession of North Slesvig, when he knew the contrary to be the
                                case. The Foreign Minister is reported thereupon to have reminded
                                the King that diplomatic representatives should be called into
                                audience only through the intermediary of the Ministry of Foreign
                                Affairs.</p>
                            <p>I have not been able to learn the details of the negotiations but the
                                fact that they actually occurred, with the full knowledge of the
                                Minister for Foreign Affairs, has been satisfactorily established
                                and his denial, reported in my telegram No. 2940, of October 14th
                                    last,<note n="5" xml:id="d396fn1">Not printed.</note> was based
                                on purely technical grounds. I am inclined to think that he realized
                                at the time that he was not deceiving me.</p>
                            <p>The forces which have been consistently opposed to Germany and
                                friendly to the cause of the Allies, headed by the King, and
                                composed chiefly of the shipping interests, are throwing their
                                weight against the policy of the present Government which, from the
                                beginning of the war, has been based on the presumption, if not of
                                German victory, at least a draw between the belligerents whereby
                                Germany would continue to be an ever present menace to the
                                independence. Now that <pb facs="0541" n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/>
                                Germany has gone under and the Associated Governments are victorious
                                they charge the Government with a lack of elasticity in adapting
                                itself to the new conditions. The early retirement of M. Scavenius
                                from the Foreign Office is prophesied but they do not seem inclined
                                to seek the overthrow of the entire Cabinet. The feeling is that the
                                more socialistic the complexion of the Government, the better chance
                                it will have in dealing with the situation which is upon it.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">U. Grant-Smith</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Denmark</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grant-Smith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="6" xml:id="d396fn6">Filed separately under
                                    759.6214/13.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1890</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-08">November 8, 1918</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Adverting to my telegram No. 3028, of
                                October 25th last,<note n="7" xml:id="d396fn7">Not printed.</note> I
                                have the honor to enclose herewith a memorandum<note n="7" xml:id="d396fn2">Not printed.</note> handed me by Lieutenant
                                Commander John A. Gade, Naval Attaché to this Legation, which was
                                given to him by the Chief of the Danish Admiralty, Admiral Jøhnke,
                                with reference to the hoped for recovery of a portion of the
                                Province of Slesvig, which was annexed by Prussia after the war of
                                1864, together with a revised version prepared by Lieutenant
                                Commander Gade, in which he has attempted to make the meaning more
                                clear. According to Admiral Jøhnke the memorandum in question was
                                prepared by M. Munch, Minister for Defence, (a well known pacifist)
                                and was revised by M. Scavenius, Minister for Foreign Affairs, as
                                well as by a Committee of the Rigsdag.</p>
                            <p>On handing the note, accompanied by the charts, to the American and
                                British Naval Attachés, Admiral Jøhnke is reported to have said that
                                since it was the consensus of opinion of the present Danish
                                Government, he hoped that it would be forwarded to their respective
                                Governments; and that, owing to the fact that the Danish Government
                                did not desire to take any official steps in the matter they took
                                the unusual method of bringing it to the attention of the American
                                and British Governments through their Naval Attachés because of the
                                interest which they had personally shown in the matter.</p>
                            <p>The charts in question are being sent as an accompaniment.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">U. Grant-Smith</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Subenclosure]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum on the North Slesvig Question</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>Denmark ceded the Duchy of Slesvig in 1864 and has later disclaimed
                                all rights to the Duchy as provided by paragraph 5 of the peace of
                                    <pb facs="0542" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/> Prague.<note n="8" xml:id="d396fn8">Treaty of Aug. 23, 1866, between Austria and
                                    Prussia, <hi rend="italic">British and Foreign State
                                    Papers</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">lvi</hi>, p. 1050.</note>
                                This paragraph provided for the return to Denmark of the Danish
                                speaking portion of the province in case a plebiscite should decide
                                in favor of such a return. Denmark herself has thus no further
                                rights in the matter, nor can well bring it forward, this devolves
                                upon the Danish speaking inhabitants of Slesvig themselves.</p>
                            <p>It is stated that they are now most anxious to return to Denmark.
                                They desire a new boundary line permitting the incorporation in
                                Denmark of all who speak and feel Danish, but only of such.</p>
                            <p>It is feared, in case the German portions of the Duchy are also
                                returned to Denmark, that endless controversies will ensue, making
                                affairs unbearable for the Danish portions and a union which might
                                not prove lasting. It is further feared that Germany once again
                                having regained its strength might take occasion to interfere in the
                                affairs of Slesvig, should the incorporation of a discontented
                                German portion prove unsatisfactory and troublesome. This fear on
                                the part of the Danish Slesvigers is shared by an overwhelming
                                majority of the Danish people. The Danish people further hope that
                                the matter may be so decided that the entire Danish population of
                                Slesvig may be rejoined to Denmark, but none of the German
                                inhabitants. Should Germans come under Danish rule, it is then
                                feared that the troubles of centuries will be reverted to. The
                                population of Northern Slesvig is essentially farmers, of similar
                                manners and customs to those of North Jutland. The rural population
                                of Southern Slesvig consists on the other hand principally of large
                                owners of estates, thoroughly German in names and sympathies.
                                Returning the German speaking portion of Slesvig to Denmark would
                                thus in reality bring about a reversal of the state of affairs since
                                1864, instead of a Danish speaking population under German rule,
                                there would be a German speaking one under Danish. The position
                                Denmark has up to now taken in the matter would have been absolutely
                                inconsistent—it would be following a course which it has for years
                                reproached Germany with.</p>
                            <p>With the principles of today of the self determination of
                                nations—principles which have been supported by leading Germans it
                                seems beyond doubt that Germany will consider it its duty to cede to
                                Denmark the Northern portion of Slesvig. Germany could decidedly
                                oppose the ceding of any territory to Denmark which has a German
                                population. Should such territory be ceded by outside powers,
                                Germany would constantly be considering the recovery, with the
                                resulting dangers to Denmark. Should the Allies now determine that
                                entire Slesvig should revert to Denmark, such a determination would
                                probably in time be regretted by them. The Allies will probably
                                remain hostile to Germany for some time to come. Such a feeling
                                cannot <pb facs="0543" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> naturally be
                                participated in by Denmark. Any future Slesvig trouble would thus
                                mean diplomatic and military difficulties to be met by the Allies
                                who had caused the return of the Entire Duchy including its German
                                source of trouble.</p>
                            <p>We have but to revert to the first Slesvig war of 1848–50 to see what
                                might happen. The fruits of it were denied Denmark by the great
                                powers who were guarantors of the peace which concluded it. In 1852
                                the same powers deemed it in the interest of Europe that the whole
                                of the Danish Monarchy be kept intact. A few years later Denmark was
                                advised by them to give way to Prussia’s demands, and when she
                                preferred to fight was left absolutely isolated.</p>
                            <p>It may be urged that one of the many reasons of the present war was
                                the error committed by Prussia, permitting her to seize Slesvig in
                                1864. The maritime and military results of the seizure, including
                                the Kiel Canal have been far reaching.</p>
                            <p>The powers were however not unaware of what might happen. As early as
                                the first Slesvig war, they fully understood the change of status
                                which would take place in regard to the Baltic if Prussia were
                                permitted to procure the harbor of Kiel and develop its naval
                                power.</p>
                            <p>In judging the Slesvig question, at this present moment, Denmark
                                cannot merely consider the political situation of today, nor the
                                possibility that this way will do away with “might being right”. She
                                must look ahead. Whatever political developments may ensure [<hi rend="italic">ensue?</hi>], the fact remains that Denmark and
                                Germany will remain next-door neighbors. If Denmark is forced into a
                                position which is beyond her and one opposed to Germany, the latter
                                will surely, even without exerting military pressure, force Denmark
                                into a corner. Owing to Denmark’s geographical position she must out
                                of economic reasons, remain on friendly terms with Germany, whatever
                                the latter’s position may be after the present war. Added to this,
                                should Denmark have numbers of Germans within her borders, she might
                                be subjected to considerable German intellectual, economic and
                                political pressure. Germans within Danish borders will not assist
                                Denmark in her effort to maintain her national characteristics nor
                                her economic and political independence. They would on the contrary
                                weaken them and bring with them the danger of German influence, up
                                to now so successfully withstood.</p>
                            <p>It is thus desirable from a Danish point of view that the question of
                                Northern Slesvig be solved by the claims of nationality. If such
                                claims are abandoned, conditions will only arise claiming future
                                readjustment Those that have been wronged will claim redress.</p>
                            <p>Such is the opinion of practically the entire Danish nation. A small
                                minority, not worth considering, claim that the new Slesvig frontier
                                should be the old historical frontier of the Eyder river. None <pb facs="0544" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/> desire a more southerly
                                line. All Danish parties are agreed in hoping that the coming peace
                                conference may give Denmark back such territory as is genuinely
                                Danish, and nothing more, and that Denmark may thus receive national
                                justice.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 3]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Denmark</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grant-Smith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 1895</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-12">November 12, 1918</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Adverting to my despatches Nos. 1889
                                and 1890, of the 8th instant,<note n="10" xml:id="d396fn10">Enclosures 1 and 2 <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi>
                                </note> I have the honor to transmit herewith, for the information
                                of the Department, copies and translations of two newspaper articles
                                on the Slesvig question, the first from the Copenhagen <hi rend="italic">Nationaltidende</hi> of October 2nd last and the
                                second from the <hi rend="italic">Hamburgischer Correspondent</hi>
                                of the 3rd instant.<note n="11" xml:id="d396fn11">Neither
                                    printed.</note> Both these articles indicate that the Germans
                                resident in Slesvig expect to meet with stubborn resistance any
                                attempt to return the territory to Denmark.</p>
                            <p>In this connection, I learn through the British Legation that the
                                proposed German condition for a franchise in any plebiscite which
                                may be held to decide the Slesvig national question is residence in
                                Slesvig for at least five years ending not less than five years ago,
                                and that the German Government have offered pecuniary assistance,
                                including all expenses, to persons in other parts of Germany who
                                have fulfilled these conditions if they are willing to return and
                                vote.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">U. Grant-Smith</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>