<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-01-04T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-01-04T20:00:00-05:00" n="585" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d585">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 871.51/3: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-01-04T20:00:00-05:00">January 4, 1919—8 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received January 6—8:10 a.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>103. For Secretary of State. Your 48 regarding loan to Roumania received
                        through Navy.<note n="58" xml:id="d585fn58">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_695">p. 695</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Only legal difficulties are: [1] Whether Roumania is as matter of fact at war
                        at the present time so as to be regarded as belligerent within meaning of
                        the act of Congress; (2) whether representative of Roumania here has
                        authority from duly constituted government to sign obligations for advances;
                        (3) whether the loan is to be used for the purpose contemplated by the act
                        of Congress. We have no information on first point other than following:
                        Telegram from Minister Vopicka, dated November 9th, delayed 6 weeks in
                        transmission states King was prepared to demand surrender of Germans and
                        thus re-enter the war.<note n="59" xml:id="d585fn59">See telegrams No. 133
                            and No. 134, Nov. 9 and 10, 1918, from the Minister in Roumania, <ref target="#pg_385">pp. 385</ref>–<ref target="#pg_387">387</ref>.</note> Cable from Ambassador Sharp, 6244, dated December 12,
                        5 p.m.,<note n="60" xml:id="d585fn60">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_397">p. 397</ref>.</note>
                        quotes Mr. Pichon as saying that he understands no declaration of war could
                        be made by the present government as now constituted, but he looks upon
                        Roumania as to all intent and purposes an ally although not formerly [<hi rend="italic">formally?</hi>] so recognized. Department has heretofore
                        held Roumania not at war since Bucharest treaties were signed. Department
                        assumes you have information showing that Roumania is in fact now in a state
                        of war with Germany. If this assumption is correct first legal difficulty
                        would be satisfied. Roumania no doubt would make a declaration of war upon
                        suggestion of American representative who can now be communicated with by
                        telegraph.</p>
                    <p>As to second difficulty there is no representative here who has authority of
                        any kind to sign obligations. When former advance was made Roumanian
                        Minister here signed obligations, but he has now left. The Treasury says it
                        has no information as to whether the advances formerly made by it have been
                        used or for what purpose they have been. Department is not advised as to
                        whether Roumanian <pb facs="0789" n="701" xml:id="pg_701"/> Government as at
                        present constituted can give valid constitutional authorization to
                        representative here to sign obligations any more than Servian or Belgian
                        Government could in the past.</p>
                    <p>As to third difficulty, act of Congress under which loans are made provides
                        that they be made “For the purpose of more effectually providing for the
                        national security and defense and prosecuting the war.” The Government has
                        recently refused to make loans to Montenegro for purchase of agricultural
                        machinery, cattle, relief of war desolation, army expense, care of disabled
                        soldiers, and to San Marino for railways, hospitals and schools.</p>
                    <p>Treasury Department unable to make loan proposed by you unless this
                        Department will say it is satisfied as to all points; viz., all three points
                        mentioned (which as indicated above it is not in position to do) or unless
                        the President will direct the Treasury to make the loan proposed.</p>
                    <p>It is suggested that if you have the facts showing that Roumania is at war
                        and that loan is to be used for purposes within act of Congress, Roumanian
                        Government should instruct its representative here in its name and on its
                        behalf to negotiate a loan agreeing to sign obligations thereunder and to
                        perform any other necessary acts in the premises. If the President will
                        then, on account of the uncertainty as to legal authority of the present
                        Roumanian Government to make foreign loans or delegate authority to its
                        representatives here, approve the loan, as a matter of policy, the Treasury
                        can act. This is the procedure followed in the doubtful cases of Servia and
                        Belgium.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Polk</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>