<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-01-09T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-01-09T12:00:00-05:00" n="601" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d601">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Paris Peace Conf. 871.48/3a: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Commission to Negotiate
                                Peace</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-01-09T17:00:00+00:00">January 9, 1919—5 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>215. For the Secretary of the Treasury from the President. Referring to cable
                        from Davis to you relative to an advance of $5,000,000 to Roumania<note n="69" xml:id="d601fn69">See telegram No. 132, Jan. 2, 1919, from the
                            Commission to Negotiate Peace, <ref target="#pg_693">p.
                            693</ref>.</note> and the various communications to the State Department
                        and Food Administration on Roumanian situation. The information from our
                        authorities indicates an extremely dangerous situation which must be
                        relieved in the next few days and one which, if cumulative, with others, may
                        necessitate increased military effort on our part. In my opinion this would
                        be in interest of National Defense and I strongly approve giving this
                        advance so as to allow the shipment of urgent food pending the appropriation
                        for relief now in Congress. The British are sending cargo of wheat and we
                        must assist by forwarding cargoes now in the Mediterranean. I also wish to
                        urge the desirability of the Treasury aiding in every way in the disposal of
                        our surplus food products in order to prevent losses to our producers and to
                        prevent consequent difficulties at home and disorder in Europe. Unless there
                        is some legal obstacle I regard this of the highest importance.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Am</hi>[<hi rend="smallcaps">erican</hi>] <hi rend="smallcaps">Mission</hi>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>