<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-11-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-11-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="84" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">862.00/788a</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                President <persName type="to">Wilson</persName>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-25">November
                                    25, 1918</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: The political situations
                            in Germany and Austria disturb me greatly, and from the reports which we
                            are receiving it seems probable that the Spartacus group of the
                            Bolsheviks is gaining headway. Kiel, Bremen and Düsseldorf are already
                            in the hands of the Bolsheviks according to press reports; while other
                            reports indicate that the Russian Bolsheviks are supplying Liebknecht
                            and his followers with unlimited funds and materials for the
                            dissemination of propaganda. Liebknecht’s meetings in Berlin are
                            becoming more and more popular.</p>
                        <p>From all information received the governments of Prussia and Bavaria are
                            in the hands of good men—moderate social democrats—and there are many
                            advantages, it seems to me, in doing what we can <pb facs="0190" n="102" xml:id="pg_102"/> at the present time to strengthen these two
                            governments. The possibility has occurred to me that we might ask Mr.
                            Hoover, who has already completed his visit in England and is now in
                            Paris, to proceed immediately to Berlin to get in touch there with the
                            actual situation, both political and economic, and report to you at the
                            earliest possible moment. I should think that Mr. Hoover could make this
                            trip in a very brief period of time.</p>
                        <p>I should be grateful for an expression of your judgment.</p>
                        <p>Faithfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>