<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-11-26T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-11-26T13:00:00-05:00" n="87" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d87">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">862.00/350: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Denmark</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grant-Smith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Copenhagen</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-11-26T19:00:00+01:00">November 26, 1918—7 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received November 27—1:28 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3205. Uncensored and confidential message received from …<note n="9" xml:id="d87fn9">A newspaper correspondent.</note> in Berlin reads as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Scheidemann said to me but not for publication: ‘Opposition to
                                    the Constituent Assembly would disappear if Wilson were to say
                                    that peace could be made only with the Constituent Assembly or
                                    Government supported by it.’ So far I can make the following
                                    positive statements: First. The Government must stand or fall by
                                    the Constituent Assembly. Second. The Spartacus group and
                                    other[s] of Bolshevik tendency can grow in power only if famine
                                    and rumor [of?] retreat to the Rhine throw the army into
                                    disorder. The Bolshevik centers are Berlin, Hamburg, and Bremen
                                    and they can only be successfully fought with immediate food.
                                    The food situation is really desperate and inspires the Radicals
                                    to plan to prevent the Constituent Assembly to force the Allies
                                    to come to Berlin and so threaten the Allied armies with
                                    Bolshevikism. Also our move is to announce loudly that food is
                                    coming to a democratic Germany, followed quickly by at least a
                                    few shiploads and at the same time to try [to] delay the
                                    fulfillment of the armistice terms especially regarding the
                                    delivery of the railroad so that it can be used in transporting
                                    coal and food.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Copenhagen to London.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Grant-Smith</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>