<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Van Limburg to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d388</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">388</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1864-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1864-10-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-10-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="388"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d388">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Van Limburg</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-10-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 27, 1864.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Among the questions which at present interest
                    those governments whose geographical position imposes on them the desire to
                    organize a fleet <pb facs="0349" n="329" xml:id="pg_329"/> which may at need
                    defend their coast, there is found in the front rank that of the construction of
                    iron-clads. The government of his Majesty would attach much importance to a
                    knowledge of the results which the naval authorities of the United States have
                    obtained in this matter, and the construction finally which the government of
                    the United States, enlightened by experience, judges to be preferable for this
                    class of vessels.</p>
                <p>If I do not deceive myself, the two American monitors, Mahopac and Dictator,
                    which have lately been launched, both represent, the last in a larger scale than
                    the first, the system which appears to be of the latest adoption. It is only the
                    great obligingness of the government of the United States, and your extreme
                    kindness, sir, which give me hope not to hazard in vain the respectful
                    application to obtain some information that will enable me to give the royal
                    government the advantage of the experience so gloriously obtained here, and I
                    shall be very happy if your kind intromission should enable me to obtain the
                    plans on which these steamers were constructed, as well as the data which give
                    exactly their dimensions, the mode of armament, their equipment, interior
                    arrangement, and the machinery which serves to manœuvre them. * *</p>
                <p>I avail of this fresh occasion, sir, to reiterate to you the assurances of my
                    very high consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>ROEST VAN LIMBURG.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
