<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Burlingame to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">393</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recuY33deeMLOZJV6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85123713"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Smuggling</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-11-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="393"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d393">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 54.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 5, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The accompanying enclosures relate to a
                    proposition on the part of the Chinese government to modify Art. XIV of the
                    American treaty, which they think bears hardly on our citizens in some of its
                    applications; and I have the honor to bring the subject to your notice, with one
                    or two remarks.</p>
                <p>It grew out of a complaint made to this government by its officers at Shanghai,
                    (enclosure A,) that it was a common practice of American shipmasters to present
                    false manifests of their cargoes, and that the consuls were unable or <pb
                        facs="0353" n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/> unwilling to remedy it. I replied to
                    this allegation, (enclosure B,) that it was necessary to state particulars; but
                    deemed it pertinent to their despatch to mention the judgment given in two cases
                    of violations of regulations, in order to show them that our consuls did what
                    they could to maintain the laws over American citizens.</p>
                <p>To this Prince Kung replied (enclosure C) with a suggestion to modify the XIVth
                    article of the American treaty, so as to conform the penalty for presenting
                    false manifests to that laid down in the British treaty. His reasoning seemed to
                    me just, and the proposal indicated more thoughtfulness than I had looked for,
                    and a desire to harmonize the diversities found in the treaties. I accordingly
                    agreed to the suggestion (enclosure D) until a reference could be made to the
                    government at Washington, and have already issued a notice to the consuls to
                    this effect, (enclosure E.)</p>
                <p>I submit the question for your consideration, with the respectful request that
                    instructions may be furnished me, so that I may inform the Chinese
                    officials.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your most obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">A.</note>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Prince Kung</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Burlingame</persName>
                    </head>
                    <p>Prince Kung, chief secretary of state for foreign affairs, herewith sends a
                        communication.</p>
                    <p>A despatch has been received from his excellency Li, superintendent of
                        commerce at Shanghai, as follows:</p>
                    <p>“I have been informed by the intendent of circuit at Shanghai that Mr.
                        Macpherson, acting collector at that port, has written to him, stating that
                        it is the common practice of masters of American ships at that port to
                        present false manifests of cargo, nor will the United States consul pay any
                        attention to this fraudulent conduct of the shipmasters. If they continue to
                        act thus, measures should be taken to deal strictly with them in order to
                        put a stop to this loss and injury, and I request you to inform the United
                        States consul, that he may attend to the matter.</p>
                    <p>“The intendent thereupon wrote to Mr. Consul Seward respecting it, who
                        replied, ‘the presentation of false manifests is a great evil, and is
                        practiced to some extent, but until I have reported the question to the
                        United States minister at Peking I cannot levy any fines.’ I accordingly
                        refer the whole subject to the foreign office for instructions how to act in
                        such cases.”</p>
                    <p>On receiving the above despatch I examined the treaty, and find that the
                        XIVth article provides: “That any citizen of the United States who shall
                        trade in any contraband article of merchandise shall be subject to be dealt
                        with by the Chinese government, without being entitled to any countenance or
                        protection from that of the United States.” The XXIst article further
                        stipulates: “That if the superintendent of customs, on examination, shall
                        detect any fraud on the revenue in the case, then the goods shall be subject
                        to forfeiture and confiscation to the Chinese government.”</p>
                    <p>Now, it is both a fraud and a loss of revenue to present a false manifest;
                        and as the consul knew that the detriment was great he ought to have aided
                        the collector and carried out treaty stipulations, and by inflicting the
                        punishment to have deterred others from like practices. Moreover, his excuse
                        that he could <pb facs="0354" n="334" xml:id="pg_334"/> not punish the
                        delinquent because he had not yet reported the matter to the United States
                        minister was an evasion of duty far from an honorable and straightforward
                        course.</p>
                    <p>In addition to sending this despatch to your excellency and orders to Li, the
                        superintendent of commerce, that he may inquire into the matter and settle
                        it, I likewise request that you will enjoin on all the American consuls that
                        whenever a case of presenting false manifests comes before them they will
                        strictly carry out the full stipulations of article XIV of the treaty about
                        clandestine trade, and also of article XXI respecting frauds on the
                        revenue.</p>
                    <p>It is to this end that I write, and in the hope of receiving a reply.</p>
                    <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Anson Burlingame,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States Minister.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <date
                                calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar                         gregorian"
                                when="1863-09-22">September 22, 1863, Tungchi 2d year, 8th moon,
                                10th day</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">B.</note>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to"
                            >Prince Kung</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-10-05">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 5, 1863.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the despatch
                        of your imperial highness of September 22, in which you inform me of the
                        practice of masters of American ships presenting false manifests, and that
                        the consuls would not interfere to remedy the evil, &amp;c., &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>As this despatch indicates no names, nor specifies the dates or kind of
                        property, I have no data on which to instruct the consuls to act, nor have I
                        heard before of this practice of rendering false manifests. But in respect
                        to the suggestion to enjoin United States consuls to observe treaty
                        stipulations I beg to enclose a copy of a correspondence with the consul at
                        Shanghai respecting a case of infringing the Tangtsze regulations, from
                        which you will perceive the desire on our part to strictly enforce the
                        rules.</p>
                    <p>In August last he wrote as follows: “The firm of Frazar &amp; Co. had bought
                        two native boats which were sent up the Yangtsze river with cargo to the
                        open ports, but at the end of the three months, which the regulations
                        require as the limit at which the shipping permit is to be returned, they
                        did not present the one for these boats, but said that if required they
                        could bring evidence that the goods had entered the customs.</p>
                    <p>“The firm of Leighton &amp; Co. seat a vessel up the Yangtsze with cargo,
                        whose permit was in like manner not returned in time, but was handed in at
                        the Shanghai custom-house after the three months. Now, both of these were
                        cases of infringement of the regulations, though one returned the permit and
                        the other did not. They have stated their cases to me, and, so far as I can
                        see, the one overpassed the time and the other lost the permit; they were
                        not engaged in smuggling, and might be released from the fine.</p>
                    <p>“The customs officers said the merchants were not smuggling, but still had
                        broken the regulations, and should be fined fifty taels each for their
                        offence instead of five hundred. This was reported to me and I confirmed the
                        decision, but it appears that the two firms resist this judgment, and refuse
                        to pay the fine because they had not been smuggling. The customs officers
                        maintained, however, that this infraction of the regulations caused them
                        much inconvenience; I have, therefore, deemed it best to report the two
                        cases for your decision, for this violation of the regulations and refusal
                        to pay the fines are against all order.”</p>
                    <p>On receiving this report and perceiving that the conduct of the two firms, in
                            <pb facs="0355" n="335" xml:id="pg_335"/> refusing to pay the mitigated
                        fine of the customs officers, indicated great disregard of the Yangtsze
                        regulations, I immediately directed the consul at Shanghai to adjudicate the
                        cases according to the strict letter of the regulations, and levy the fines
                        as therein stated. From this statement your imperial highness will perceive
                        that the United States consuls are zealous in carrying out all the
                        regulations respecting the trade on the Yangtsze river.</p>
                    <p>As to what is said in the despatch under reply about rendering false
                        manifests, and the indifference of the consuls about attending to the
                        matter, you will perceive from this that all the officers of the United
                        States regard the treaty as of the highest importance. There is not,
                        therefore, at present any need of enjoining this matter upon them, as they
                        already know their duties and desire to fulfil them.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Imperial Highness Prince <hi rend="smallcaps">Kung,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">C.</note>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Prince Kung</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Burlingame</persName>
                    </head>
                    <p>Prince Kung, chief secretary of state for foreign affairs, herewith sends a
                        communication.</p>
                    <p>On the 2d instant I received your excellency’s reply to my previous despatch
                        respecting the common practice of American merchants presenting false
                        manifests, and my request that instructions might be sent to the United
                        States consuls to carry out the provisions of the XIVth article of the
                        treaty respecting smuggling, in which you say that as no names are
                        mentioned, or the time or sort of goods indicated, there are no data to act
                        on, and it is difficult to send specific orders to remedy it. In this reply
                        a letter from the consul is copied, and particulars are given respecting the
                        violation by the firms of Frazar &amp; Co. and Leighton &amp; Co. of the
                        limit allowed for returning a permit, and of the fine imposed on them, all
                        of which I fully understand.</p>
                    <p>I have ascertained that the injurious practice of rendering false manifests
                        is not confined to one port or one nation. If an English ship does it her
                        master is fined five hundred taels, according to the XXXVIIth article of the
                        English treaty; but if the offender be an American the provisions of article
                        XIV of his treaty must apply to the case, and the Chinese officers be
                        allowed to deal with it without his being entitled to any protection from
                        the officers of the United States. Therefore, in all such cases, when the
                        offender is an American, the penalty is not one of a fine at all, and yet it
                        is an offence deserving of punishment. If, however, it is only lightly
                        fined, it will be dealt with differently from what the English treaty
                        requires, and the merchants of the two nations will not then be treated
                        alike. Furthermore, the laws of China are strict, and if an American
                        merchant merely smuggles, and no other crime is involved in the act, there
                        is no mode of arriving at an equitable decision in the case, while the
                        penalty [of his own treaty] seems to be too severe.</p>
                    <p>While I desire to observe all the provisions of the treaty most carefully, I
                        still think that a more equitable law respecting this matter might be
                        settled, so that the American merchants be not fined too heavily, and it is
                        for this purpose that I now address another communication to your excellency
                        upon this matter.</p>
                    <p>I propose the question for you to consider, when tie American merchants
                        present false manifests of cargo they shall be punished according to article
                        XIV of their own treaty, and be dealt with by the Chinese officers alone, or
                        be fined five hundred taels, according to the provision of the English
                        treaty, and <pb facs="0356" n="336" xml:id="pg_336"/> thus all parties be
                        placed upon the same footing. I hope that you will examine this proposal and
                        decide on the point, so that orders may be sent to the several consuls
                        directing them how to act in such cases.</p>
                    <p>As to the cases of Messrs. Frazar &amp; Co. and H. Leighton &amp; Co., let
                        them be punished by fine, according to the Yangtsze regulations, as their
                        vessels and property may have been valued.</p>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Anson Burlingame,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Minister.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <date
                                calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar                         gregorian"
                                when="1863-10-16">October 16, 1863, Tungchi 2d year, 9th moon, 3d
                                day</date>,</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">D.</note>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to"
                            >Prince Kung</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-10-21">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 21, 1863.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your
                        imperial highness’s despatch of the 16th instant, in which you remark that
                        the presentation of false manifests is not confined to any nation, nor to
                        any one of the ports. If an Englishman is convicted of this offence, the
                        thirty-seventh article of the British treaty provides that it be punished by
                        a fine; but in case of an American committing it, his treaty brings it under
                        article fourteen, wherein it is stipulated that all such cases shall be
                        punished by the Chinese government, &amp;c. It appears, therefore, that
                        offences of this description are decided by a different rule from the
                        English; and I wish to express my thanks for the thoughtfulness herein
                        exhibited in that, while desirous of carefully observing all treaty
                        stipulations, you still think that a more equitable rule can be made whereby
                        American merchants shall not be mulcted more heavily than others. It is
                        clearly the most equitable mode of disposing of such cases.</p>
                    <p>The consuls of the United States in China will, therefore, for the present,
                        decide all cases of presenting false manifests of cargo in conformity to the
                        provisions of article thirty-seven of the British treaty; but in respect to
                        adopting this as a permanent modification of the fourteenth article of the
                        United States treaty, it will be necessary first to represent the
                        circumstances and argument of your present despatch upon the subject to the
                        government at Washington. When I have received a reply I will communicate
                        further upon the matter.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Imperial Highness Prince <hi rend="smallcaps">Kung,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">E.</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Notice to the consuls in China.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-10-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 22, 1863.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The United States minister having been in
                        consultation with his Imperial Majesty’s ministers respecting the penalty to
                        be levied under the treaty of Tientsin for presenting false manifests of
                        cargo, it has been agreed between them that, pending a reference to
                        Washington, the fourteenth article of the said treaty shall be defined in
                        this respect and for this offence by the last sentence <pb facs="0357"
                            n="337" xml:id="pg_337"/> of article thirty-seven of the British treaty,
                        and the legal penalty on conviction shall be a fine of 500 taels.</p>
                    <p>I am directed to make known this modification of article fourteen of the
                        American treaty for your guidance and the information of American
                        citizens.</p>
                    <p>By order:</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>S. WELLS WILLIAMS.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>To —— ——, <hi rend="italic">United States Consul at ———, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
