<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Burlingame to  to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1864p3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-11-26T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212" lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-11-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-11-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="398" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d398">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 59.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 26, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your despatch No. 32, covering circular No. 39. I need not
                            inform you how great was my gratification at reading the circular. There
                            could not be a more lucid history of our victorious period. Our
                            diplomatic circle was charmed with it, and exulted with me in the hopes
                            it awakened. The glorious news of Gettysburg, Vicksburg, and Port Hudson
                            reached us by the way of Russia, and it would have given you pleasure to
                            have seen how warmly I was congratulated upon if by every member of the
                            other legations. The sympathy for us here is real, as you learned from
                            my despatch No. 56, in which I called your attention to the noble
                            conduct of Sir Frederick Bruce, the British minister, in relation to the
                            flotilla. I now send a letter of thanks as addressed by me to him, to
                            which I beg leave respectfully to call your attention.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Sir Frederick Bruce.</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of this United
                                            States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 7, 1863.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: When the Chinese government refused to
                                rectify the doings of Mr. Lay, and there was nothing left for
                                Captain Osborn but to dissolve the force of the flotilla, the
                                question was, how it could be done with safety. I feared that the
                                ships might fall into the hands of the confederates, who were
                                supposed to have agents in China; and then there was the common
                                apprehension from lawless men on the coast, in the interests of the
                                Taepings, as well as from pirates, and the desire of the Daimios in
                                Japan to procure steamers at any price. It was clear that the <pb facs="0370" n="350" xml:id="pg_350"/> Chinese could do nothing
                                of themselves with the steamers, and that unless something were done
                                they would certainly fall a prey to one of these several dangers. In
                                my solicitude on account of the rebels in my own country, I made an
                                earnest protest against the delivery of the ships to the Chinese.
                                You responded in that spirit of comity which has ever distinguished
                                our relations, that the ships should be taken back to England, and
                                that no effort on your part should be spared to prevent them from
                                taking a direction against the interests of my country.</p>
                    <p>Though subsequent events made it necessary for the ships to take the
                                direction indicated by the desire of the Chinese themselves, still I
                                should be wanting in appreciation of your conduct did I not mark it
                                with my most heartfelt thanks, and at as early a period as possible
                                bring it to the attention of my government.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Sir <hi rend="smallcaps">Frederick Bruce,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">British Minister.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
