<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-06-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="420" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d420">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 78.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-06-03"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 3, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to forward the papers
                            relating to the trial, conviction, and execution of John D. Buckley, at
                            Shanghai, April 1, 1864. He, like Williams, claimed to be a British
                            subject; but the claim was not allowed. A rigorous effort was made by
                            Mr. Eames, the counsel of the prisoner, to secure a reference to the
                            President; but I could not see my way clear to grant his request. Such
                            men as Williams, White and Buckley had so long escaped punishment that
                            they had come to believe that they could take life with impunity. The
                            United States authority was laughed at, and our flag made the cover for
                            all the villains in China. I felt that any relaxation of our purpose to
                            punish the guilty would only aggravate the evils of our situation. That
                            the lawless would find fresh inspiration in the uncertainty of
                            punishment. The result has shown the wisdom of the course taken. There
                            has been a regular exodus of foreigners from China since. I received
                            from Sir Frederick Bruce the following letter, which is in proof of what
                            I say:</p>
                        <p rend="right">“<hi rend="smallcaps">Peking,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 15, 1864.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">“My Dear Sir</hi>: Mr. Adkins, our vice-consul at
                            Chin-Kiang, in writing to me on the decrease of rowdyism on the Yangtse
                            river, states, ‘the steps taken by the United States consul general of
                            Shanghai will have the best effect. I do not hear of many acts of
                            violence now.’ You will be glad of this impartial testimony to the
                            soundness of his action in the cases of Williams and others.</p>
                        <p>“Yours, sincerely,</p>
                        <p rend="right">“FREDERICK W. A. BRUCE.”</p>
                        <p>The French admiral stated the same thing to me. Buckley was one of the
                            worst villains of his class, and would have been lynched, probably, had
                            he been taken on the evening of the murder of Captain McKennon. Please
                            find the papers marked A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, I, J.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c., &amp;c.,
                                &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">A.</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. G. F. Seward to Mr.
                                Buckley</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of the United
                                            States,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-01-18"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 18, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: You are aware that you are held in
                                custody for trial upon a charge of murder. My intention, not less
                                than my duty, is to allow you every facility to defend yourself. In
                                order that you may not delude yourself with any false hope of
                                frustrating the law by declaring yourself of different nationality
                                than American, I call your attention to your declaration to her
                                Britannic Majesty’s consul at Nagasaki; also to your letter to Mr.
                                Walsh. It will be well for you, therefore, to see your case
                                thoroughly defended; therein is your only hope.</p>
                            <p>You will be allowed to choose a lawyer yourself. This must be your
                                own expense, as no provision is made for legal services in
                                prosecution or defence by the United States government; I trust to
                                see counsel upon both sides, however. <pb facs="0421" n="401" xml:id="pg_401"/> You will be allowed three days to secure your
                                lawyer; after you have chosen, a selection will be made by me on the
                                part of the United States. You will then be furnished with a copy of
                                the commitment. Upon trial you will be allowed to challenge the
                                associates, and any reasonable objection made on your part will be
                                considered. The number of associates is four; three, with myself,
                                form a competent court to try you, and the judgment made [requires]
                                only the assent of the minister to make it final. Your trunk,
                                pistol, and $30 in money are in my hands; you will please hand over
                                the key of the former, and, after examination, it will be handed the
                                jailer for your convenience. The money you will probably leave in my
                                hands to remunerate, in part, your lawyer.</p>
                            <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>GEORGE F. SEWARD, <hi rend="italic">Consul
                                    General.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>J. D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Buckley,</hi> Esq.</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. G. F. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Buckley</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate General of the United
                                            States,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-01-25"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 25, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: One week has elapsed since I wrote,
                                stating that you would be allowed three days to secure a lawyer, and
                                that when your choice was made known to me I should furnish you with
                                a copy of your commitment. I am not yet in receipt of any
                                information regarding your choice of a lawyer, although a much
                                longer time has elapsed than I expected. I have now to inform you
                                that your trial will be docketed for Monday of next week. I enclose
                                a copy of your commitment.</p>
                            <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>GEORGE F. SEWARD, <hi rend="italic">Consul
                                    General.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">J. D. Buckley,</hi> Esq.</p>
                            </postscript>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Court of the United States,
                                                Consulate General,</hi>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-01-25"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 25,
                                        1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                                <p>John D. Buckley stands charged with having, on the evening of the
                                    22d day of May, 1863, wilfully and maliciously, and without
                                    provocation, caused the death of one Captain John McKennon,
                                    against the peace of the people of the United States.</p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Shanghai, China, ss:</hi></p>
                                <p>An inquisition taken for the people of the United States at the
                                    International hotel, in the port of Shanghai, China, on the 24th
                                    day of May, 1863, before me, George S. Porter, deputy consul of
                                    the United States, in and for said port, upon the body of
                                    Captain McKennon, then and there lying dead, upon the oaths of
                                    J. S. Brown, Captain J. S. Dolliver, Captain Abbot, Captain
                                    McKay, W. C. Clemens, and J. E. Wainwright, good and lawful men
                                    of said port, who, being duly sworn to inquire on the part of
                                    the people of the United States into all the circumstances
                                    attending the death of the said Captain John McKennon, and by
                                    whom the same was produced, in what manner, when and where the
                                    said McKennon came to his death, do say upon their oaths
                                    aforesaid, that one J. D. Buckley, of Shanghai, on the 22d day
                                    of May, 1863, at 7.30 o’clock in the evening of <pb facs="0422" n="402" xml:id="pg_402"/> that day, with force and arms,
                                    did, at Shanghai aforesaid, then and there feloniously and
                                    violently make an assault in and upon the body of Captain John
                                    McKennon, then present; and the said J. D. Buckley, then and
                                    there, with a pistol which he held in his right hand, did
                                    violently and feloniously inflict a mortal wound in the abdomen,
                                    about four inches above, to the right of the navel, the ball
                                    passing through his body and lodging on the right side of his
                                    spine, near the surface, of which mortal wound the said John
                                    McKennon died at the hour of 3.15 o’clock p. m. on the 22d day
                                    of May, 1863. And so the said jurors do say, that the said John
                                    D. Buckley did, then and there, feloniously, mortally wound and
                                    murder the said Captain John McKennon, against the peace of the
                                    people of this port.</p>
                                <p>In witness whereof, as well the said deputy consul as the jurors
                                    aforesaid have to this inquisition set their hands and seals, on
                                    the day of the date thereof aforesaid.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>GEORGE S. PORTER. <hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi></signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed>J. S. DOLLIVER. <hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi></signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed>J. H. BROWN. <hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi></signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed>W. C. CLEMENS. <hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi></signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed>J. McKAY. <hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi></signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed>C. L. ABBOTT. <hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi></signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed>JAMES E. WAINWRIGHT. <hi rend="smallcaps">[seal.]</hi></signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Court of the United States
                                            Consulate General,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-01-25"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 25, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>John D. Buckley stands committed for trial on the first day of
                                February next, for the crime of murder, as more particularly set
                                forth in the attached report of inquisition.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>GEORGE F. SEWARD, <hi rend="italic">Consul General, acting
                                        judicially.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Court of the United States
                                            Consulate General,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-02-01"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 1, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>In the case in which United States is plaintiff, John D. Buckley
                                defendent; charge murder; before George F. Seward, consul general,
                                acting judicially; eight associates called in.</p>
                            <p>W. Scott Fitz has heard of the case, and thinks he is biased against
                                the prisoner—told to stand aside. G. M. Boyd is also biased against
                                the prisoner, and stands aside. Mr. E. Hawkins is called, to whom
                                the prisoner objects without any questions—he stands aside. Mr. J.
                                M. Nixon thinks he can sit and give an impartial verdict—he is
                                accepted. Mr. T. W. Stillman is of the same opinion, and is
                                accepted. Mr. A. L. Freeman is also accepted. Mr. H. C. Endicott
                                knows nothing of the case, and is accepted without further
                                questions.</p>
                            <p>The court is composed of the following gentlemen: George F. Seward,
                                consul general United States of America; H. E. Endicott, A. L.
                                Freeman, T. W. Stillman, J. D. Nixon, associates; E. Lawrence,
                                attorney for the prosecution; T. B. Eames, attorney for the
                                defence.</p>
                            <p rend="right">JOHN L. SEWARD, <hi rend="italic">Clerk.</hi></p>
                            <pb facs="0423" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/>
                            <p>Objected to by prisoner:</p>
                            <p>Prisoner claims the right to be tried by a jury of (12) twelve men,
                                and objects to the court consisting of the consul general and four
                                associates, as unconstitutional in a case of felony.</p>
                            <p>Objection overruled.</p>
                            <p>The prisoner, upon being asked by the court whether he is guilty, or
                                not guilty, pleaded not guilty.</p>
                            <p>Charles J. Ashley, being duly sworn, says: I am a sailmaker by trade.
                                I remember the evening of the murder; cannot say as to date, whether
                                it was the 22d or 23d of May. I was stopping in the large house on
                                the French Bund known as General Wade house. I had my meals at the
                                International hotel. I arrived there on the evening of the murder. I
                                saw the prisoner; he was dining that evening at the International
                                hotel. The deceased, Captain McKennon, was also among them that
                                evening. They were sitting nearly opposite to each other. My
                                attention was called by hearing some loud talking and harsh
                                language—so much so, that I spoke to the proprietor of the house. I
                                heard some of the remarks, but do not remember what they were. The
                                subject was secession. The conversation commenced about that. The
                                parties were Captain Abbott and Captain McKennon. They were at first
                                talking about the trouble in the United States. They were not
                                excited. I could not hear all that was going on. The prisoner took
                                part at the end of the conversation. He sat on the opposite side
                                from me. During this high talk, the prisoner got up and left the
                                room. Dinner was not over then. The deceased went out some six or
                                ten minutes after. The prisoner said, as he went out, that he would
                                make the deceased answer for that, or words to that effect. I did
                                not hear deceased make any reply to that. When deceased went out he
                                said, in a quiet manner, that it was always his way to allow
                                everybody to have his own opinion. I left shortly after the deceased
                                left. I went into the hall. As I was going from the dining-room, I
                                saw two parties scuffling in the office—the prisoner and Captain
                                McKennon. They seemed to be fighting; were clenched together as they
                                came out. I was close enough to rub against them. I saw then the
                                prisoner with his left arm around McKennon’s neck. As they came to
                                me the prisoner was stooping. I saw him take a pistol from his
                                sleeve or his breast pocket, I cannot say which; the gleam of the
                                lamp was upon it, and I knew it was some weapon. The prisoner placed
                                it up against the deceased, and I heard the report; it was almost
                                against the deceased. The prisoner then stepped back and passed me,
                                and then turned round and faced the whole party with the revolver in
                                his hand. I saw it distinctly. I could not identify the pistol. I
                                was the next one to the prisoner. I said, “Buckley, don’t shoot
                                here.” He said, “I will, by God.” I heard the pistol click, but
                                cannot say whether it snapped on a bad cap or whether he was cocking
                                it. I ran back into the dining-room as quick as I could; some more
                                were then in there. We shortly after went out and assisted Captain
                                McKennon up stairs; I staid with him and helped to undress him. When
                                he was laid upon the bed I saw the wound; it appeared to be in the
                                pit of the stomach. I saw Dr. Walden feeling the back of the
                                deceased. I did not see the prisoner after that. I did not see the
                                deceased give the prisoner any provocation. I knew nothing of
                                Captain McKennon. I am quite sure that the prisoner is the man who
                                fired the pistol; I am positive of it. Knew nothing of the prisoner
                                before that, except that he was a boarder in the house.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross-examined by defendant’s attorney.</hi>—The
                                dispute was about secessionism; they were discussing that subject. I
                                am prepared to say, that the prisoner answered the captain—he was
                                talking about that. I can’t remember the words; he used harsh
                                language. Prisoner was addressing a person opposite. I cannot say
                                whether there was any conversation with Captain Abbott; <pb facs="0424" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/> do not recollect the
                                language used; do not remember Captain Abbott’s addressing the
                                prisoner about the San Francisco vigilance committee. The prisoner
                                was talking to Captain McKennon. I do not know what the prisoner
                                said. The dinner was not finished when the prisoner went out. The
                                deceased went out five to eight minutes after the prisoner; I went
                                out with several others, among whom were Dr. Walden and wife, Mr.
                                Lozey and wife. I saw the scuffle when I was going out of the
                                dining-room. I saw the parties coming out of the office door. The
                                prisoner had his left arm around Captain McKennon’s neck; they were
                                both in a leaning posture. The captain is a large man; not much
                                larger than the prisoner. I saw him distinctly after he was laid
                                upon the bed. I cannot say that he was much stronger than the
                                prisoner, but he was an older man. I am sure that the deceased did
                                not have the prisoner’s head under his arm. I could not tell what
                                the pistol was. I saw the gleam of light upon it; could not tell
                                whether it was a revolver or not. The prisoner was dressed in a long
                                dark coat. There were half a dozen people about there. I did not see
                                any blows struck; I am positive that I saw no blows; I was looking
                                right at them; they appeared to be scuffling out of the door. I
                                cannot tell what the Captain did; he might have been striking, but I
                                did not see it. No one was taking any part in it. Mr. Lozey, Dr.
                                Walden, Dominick Lynch, were present. Lynch was close to me; I saw
                                him in the dining-room afterwards. Do not remember any others at
                                present, except Captain Abbott, and Mr. Dow, owner of the bark Emily
                                Banning. No one was interfering when I was looking at them. The
                                struggle did not occupy a half minute after I saw the discharge of
                                the pistol. I was not acquainted with Captain McKennon. I heard of
                                the reward that was offered for the prisoner; I offered to subscribe
                                my share. I never paid, as they never came to me for anything. I
                                heard no one offer to lynch him; am not aware that any one carried a
                                rope in his pocket to hang him with; never heard that before; have
                                heard talk if he had been caught, it would have gone hard with him.
                                He would probably have been lynched. I have no opinion on that
                                subject. Did not notice the captain at the table. He did not appear
                                excited— he was cool; was not angry. Did not appear to have been
                                drinking. I will not say that the deceased had not been drinking at
                                the table; he sat at the same side that I did. Do not remember
                                seeing him rise from his seat; did not keep my eyes on him; was
                                eating my dinner. I did not get through before the others. Others
                                went out with me; do not know why. Captain McKennon came to the
                                hotel that night. Did not hear it stated that he was looking after
                                Dominick Lynch, or that he had a quarrel with him. There was
                                something snapped about the pistol after the shot was fired. I
                                distinctly heard a click. Could not see whether he took it from his
                                pocket or his sleeve. The prisoner was leaning over sidewise in the
                                scuffle. His coat was a long, dark-colored one. I did not aid the
                                United States marshal in searching for him. I gave information to
                                French police, and inquired several times about the prisoner. Did
                                not see any blood on the prisoner’s face; he was facing me a short
                                time. I wanted to get away from the pistol. His face might have been
                                hurt, but I did not see it. Do not know what bystanders said; there
                                was a great deal of confusion after the pistol was fired. I heard no
                                remarks like, “Give it to him, captain.” Was not acquainted with the
                                prisoner, no more than he was a boarder in the house. Do not
                                remember hearing Captain Abbott charge the prisoner with having been
                                sent away from California by the vigilance committee. Do not know
                                who spoke first about the vigilance committee. I heard nothing about
                                it; could not hear everything that was said. Prisoner said, when he
                                left the room, he would make him answer, or something like that. Am
                                not positive as to the words he used. I do not remember the prisoner
                                telling Captain Abbott that he lied; did not hear the deceased say,
                                “You are no gentleman.” I heard something that he would make the
                                deceased answer. I heard distinctly, also, something about a
                                gentleman, but I do not know who it came <pb facs="0425" n="405" xml:id="pg_405"/> from. I cannot give any idea of position of
                                the bystanders. Do not know whether there was any interfering.</p>
                            <p>W. C. Waldron, being duly sworn, says: I am a doctor by profession.
                                Was a boarder there in May, 1863, and dined there, as usual, on the
                                evening of the 22d of May. Captain McKennon and the prisoner also
                                dined there that evening. I was not sitting near the prisoner, but
                                at the other end of the table, on same side with prisoner. I heard
                                them talking, but could not understand any particular part of the
                                conversation, as I was too far off. There was considerable loud
                                talk. I saw Buckley leave the table. He said, as he was going out,
                                “I’ll see you after dinner.” Heard no reply to that. Doctor Kennief
                                and deceased then left the table. I saw the prisoner and deceased
                                were coming into the hall from the office. Captain McKennon had the
                                prisoner by the hair, and was using his fist. I then heard the
                                report of a pistol immediately after. Captain McKennon said he was
                                shot. Did not see the pistol. Took deceased up stairs from the
                                dining-room; attended him professionally. The wound was in left side
                                of the abdomen, and came out at the spine. Deceased said Buckley had
                                shot him. Was not with him when he died, but a few minutes before.
                                Do not know whether he made any statement before he died. Have seen
                                him frequently. He was a very good, clever man. Never heard any one
                                say anything against him. He was of a pleasant disposition, so far
                                as I can judge. Did not see the origin of the scuffle.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross-examined.</hi>—Could not hear what they said.
                                Do not remember seeing Captain McKennon rise from his chair. They
                                scuffled from the sitting-room or office into the hall. There were a
                                great many people in the hall—say from ten to twenty; could not tell
                                exactly. They seemed to be rushing out from the office. I did not
                                see any one taking part in the scuffle; was getting my family out of
                                the way of it. Did not see any wound on the prisoner’s face. Was
                                there only a few seconds. Went into the hall after the shot was
                                fired. Don’t remember when Mr. Ashley left the table. Know Mr. Lozy.
                                He was at the table, and came out with me. Position of the prisoner
                                was fronting the door. Captain McKennon was coming out first.
                                McKennon seemed to have Buckley by the hair. He was a powerful,
                                thick-set man; was an invited guest of Doctor Kennief. Do not know
                                of any others coming with him. Did not hear any conversation about
                                McKennon being in search of Dominick Lynch; did not know of their
                                having any quarrel. Have known Captain McKennon about a month— from
                                the time he arrived up to his death. Knew him by visiting his
                                vessel; had no particular acquaintance with him. Do not think he was
                                a quarrelsome man. Do not think I could find out his disposition in
                                a month. Was not aware there was any difficulty between Lynch and
                                McKennon about the affair. Was slightly acquainted with the
                                prisoner. Do not remember how he was dressed; think he had a long,
                                dark coat on. The light in the hall was not good; it came from the
                                dining-room. Can’t say whether there was a lamp in the hall. Had not
                                heard of the struggle until I opened the door; from what I saw,
                                thought it had been commenced in the office. I continued to board at
                                the house some time after the affair. Heard some talk about lynching
                                the prisoner if he was captured. I was one of the persons that were
                                looking after him. Heard persons say he would be lynched; heard
                                Dolliver say it. I think he would have been lynched at the time if
                                found. Am not aware that people went about with ropes prepared to
                                lynch him. When I saw the prisoner his head was down. Captain
                                McKennon had his hand on his head, and was putting it down. Heard
                                something about vigilance committee—not distinctly. Did hear
                                something about McKennon saying that he was no gentleman.</p>
                            <p>B. Kennief, being duly sworn, says: I am a dentist by profession.
                                Came to Shanghai the beginning of May, 1863, in the Emily Banning,
                                of San Francisco. Deceased was master of her. Remember the
                                evening—22d of May. Was a <pb facs="0426" n="406" xml:id="pg_406"/>
                                boarder in the house. The deceased was a guest of mine. On the
                                evening of the murder he sat on my left at the table. The prisoner
                                sat on the opposite side. I heard the conversation between Captain
                                Abbott and the deceased about the north and the south. The prisoner
                                took part in it. Cannot describe exactly what he said. Know he took
                                part in the conversation. Cannot say what took place exactly. The
                                parties were not excited, in my judgment. Buckley at the latter end
                                appeared to be excited, and went from the table first. Going out he
                                said, “When you come out I’ll see you,” or words to that effect,
                                addressed to Captain McKennon. Deceased, made no reply, that I
                                recollect, nor did he appear excited when Buckley left. Five or ten
                                minutes after the prisoner left, I went out, followed by the
                                captain. I went into the sitting-room. Deceased also came in there.
                                The prisoner was then there. I was conversing with Mr. Dow, the
                                owner of the Emily Banning, and Mr. Eckfeldt, a clerk of Russell
                                &amp; Co., who was a passenger in the Emily Banning. Immediately
                                after the captain came in there were some words took place between
                                the prisoner and the deceased. Then I saw the prisoner strike the
                                deceased over the head with a stick or cane. They got clinched, and
                                commenced fighting, and went on until they got into the hall. The
                                next I heard was the report of a pistol. I did not see the prisoner
                                fire it, but the universal cry was Buckley had shot the captain.
                                They then took the captain up to a room. I followed immediately, and
                                saw where he was shot. Saw no more of the prisoner after that. Am
                                quite sure I saw the prisoner strike the captain first. The captain
                                was a man of exemplary character; he was liked by his officers and
                                passengers; perfectly sober man, and, I think, would be incapable of
                                commencing a quarrel.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross-examined.</hi>—I am not a particular friend
                                of Captain McKennon. Was with him sixty-two or sixty-three days—the
                                passage over. Was one of the parties at the dinner-table. Do not
                                remember all the remarks made, or that deceased said prisoner was no
                                gentleman—don’t recollect. Cannot say whether I heard the prisoner
                                say anything before the vigilance committee subject was brought up.
                                The discussion was between the prisoner and Captain Abbott; the
                                origin about “secession.” Captain Abbott introduced the subject of
                                vigilance committee, to the best of my recollection. Captain
                                McKennon did drink occasionally; was my guest that evening. There
                                was wine on the table, but we were not drinking freely—a bottle of
                                claret between two of us. Do not know that any one came to the hotel
                                with deceased. I think prisoner went into the sitting-room after me.
                                The deceased went in there. Saw the prisoner when he went into the
                                sitting-room. First saw prisoner strike deceased on the head with a
                                cane; that was the first I saw, and am confident that was the first
                                of the quarrel. Did not see Dolliver there. Dow and Eckfeldt were
                                there. Did not see Captain Abbott there. Do not recollect Mr.
                                Parsells being there. The prisoner struck deceased with a cane. I
                                will swear that he struck him on the head or shoulders. The prisoner
                                was on the opposite side of the room from me; and hearing high words
                                passing between him and deceased, I looked and saw prisoner strike
                                the deceased in the way I have represented. Was not looking that way
                                before, as I know of. Can swear the deceased did not strike the
                                first blow. There was no striking on the part of the deceased. I was
                                looking in that direction when the captain came in, so there could
                                not be any striking. Did not follow them out of the room. Saw them
                                in contact with each other. After they got into the hall I saw no
                                more of it. Did not follow my guest out. Do not think he was in the
                                room more than a minute before the blow was struck. Do not know what
                                was said. I was about the middle of the room. The table was between
                                the prisoner and me. The deceased’s side was towards me. I do not
                                know exactly whether he had arrived at the table or not; it was not
                                exactly between the prisoner and me. The prisoner was sitting right
                                back of the <pb facs="0427" n="407" xml:id="pg_407"/> table. The
                                deceased was getting his hat from off it, and was facing Buckley.
                                Did not try to arrest the prisoner. Did not hear that they intended
                                to lynch him.</p>
                            <figure n="1" xml:id="figure1">
                                <graphic url="figure1"/>
                            </figure>
                            <p>Do not remember of hearing about lynching. I expressed no opinion
                                that I wished he was caught, and punished accordingly. I did not
                                offer any opinion whether he ought to be lynched or not. Do not
                                recollect the high words that passed. Do not know who fired the
                                pistol. The position of the parties the last time I saw them was
                                close together, tussling like. Do not know the deceased had the
                                prisoner by the hair. I saw no mark upon the deceased, except the
                                pistol shot. Did not see the prisoner’s face bleeding. Do not know
                                the weight of Captain McKennon; he was a small, strong man—stronger
                                than the prisoner, and heavier. Cannot remember who was present, or
                                if those present took part in the struggle or not. I know no one
                                interfered while they were scuffling in the office. I heard Captain
                                Dolliver say, “Let them be.” I was under the impression that the
                                prisoner was rather getting “jessie” than otherwise. There was a
                                number crowding in. Captain Dolliver’s language I cannot account
                                for; no one offered to interfere during the time they were in the
                                room. The prisoner had a long black coat on. I cannot tell how many
                                crowded around; might have been more than 5; don’t think more than
                                20 when they got into fisticuffs. I do not know how many men there
                                were in the hall. Dolliver was within a few feet of them when he
                                made the remark; am not sure he was close enough to take hold of one
                                of the parties. I did not crowd in with the rest; there were people
                                between the parties and myself. I can say it was impossible for
                                anything to occur I did not see; do not undertake to swear
                                positively that no person interfered. Do not know whether Captain
                                McKennon was in the habit of carrying a pistol.</p>
                            <p>T. W. Eckfeldt, being duly sworn, says: I was passenger in the Emily
                                Banning, from San Francisco; had abundant opportunity to judge of
                                the character of Captain McKennon; thought it good; never saw him
                                intoxicated; he was very much liked by his passengers and crew;
                                never saw him use violence towards any one; was at the hotel on the
                                evening of the 22d of May; went there to see Dr. Kennief, who was
                                also a passenger in the Emily Banning, and was boarding at the
                                International hotel at the time. It was dinner hour when I arrived;
                                I called at Dr. Kennief’s room; found he was not in. I sent my card
                                to him in the dining-room, and the proprietor showed me a seat in
                                the sitting-room. I remained there about fifteen minutes when a
                                stranger to me came in. He was talking, but what he said I do not
                                know. Cannot be positive as to the subject. Ten or twelve minutes
                                after the first person there were three or four gentlemen came in
                                the sitting-room from the room opposite, which I believe was the
                                dining-room. The next I heard was a scuffle between parties in the
                                room. As soon as I heard this I ran out of the room into the hall to
                                the door of the long hall of the hotel, some distance from the
                                office. A few moments after this I heard the report of a pistol;
                                stopped some five minutes after, and heard persons saying Captain
                                McKennon was shot; did not see the prisoner <pb facs="0428" n="408" xml:id="pg_408"/> after that. I saw the captain after he was put
                                to bed; he said to me, I am shot, but did not mention names.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross-examined.</hi>—Never saw Captain McKennon
                                excited; did not see him before he was shot—that is, did not know it
                                was he who was scuffling. I ran from the room as soon as I could;
                                there was one or two there when I first went in; before I left three
                                or four came in with the captain; afterwards three or four more came
                                in from the opposite room. I was sitting on a lounge when two or
                                three came in, and I then heard the commencement of the struggle;
                                was talking with Mr. Dow; no other person was talking with me. Dr.
                                Kennief had just come in from the dining-room, and said “Good
                                evening” to me, but nothing more; the room was full when I broke and
                                ran away; did not know any of them; have not seen any of them since
                                to know them; there were four or five mixed in the scuffle when I
                                saw it in the office; never thought Captain McKennon was
                                quick-tempered.</p>
                            <p>J. D. Riley, being sworn, says: I am foreman to Mr. Ashley. The
                                evening of May 22, 1863, I was stopping at the International hotel;
                                arrived that evening. The prisoner and Captain McKennon dined there
                                that evening. I sat near the door next to the prisoner—he on my
                                right and Captain Abbott on my left—and Captain McKennon sat right
                                opposite. The conversation commenced between Captains Abbott and
                                McKennon about the trouble at home in the States. After a while the
                                prisoner took part in it, when it turned upon a privateer schooner
                                that was fitted out in San Francisco, which was captured and taken
                                back. Captain Abbott was telling McKennon, when the prisoner joined
                                in and said the privateer was right, and he hoped she would succeed.
                                The prisoner left the table soon after—eight or ten minutes before
                                the rest. He made some remark to the captain about settling with him
                                when he came out. The captain replied, Very well; you are a
                                gentleman. I left the room about the same time as the deceased, and
                                went into the office a little behind him; he picked up his cap from
                                off the table; the prisoner rose and struck him two or three times
                                over the head; they then closed in, and had a fist-fight of it; as
                                they were going round the table it tilted and upset the lamp; the
                                globe fell to the floor, but I caught the lamp, and held it in my
                                hand; as they got to the door I put the lamp back on the table and
                                followed them out; just as I got to the door I heard the report of a
                                pistol; I saw the prisoner; the pistol was in his hand; he seemed to
                                be in the act of firing the second time; as he was backing down the
                                hall some one asked if the captain was shot; he walked towards the
                                door and Captain Dolliver took hold of him; he began to unbutton his
                                vest, and Captain Dolliver walked off with him; I did not go up
                                stairs.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross-examined.</hi>—I sat near the door; Ashley
                                sat near the other end of the table. There were about thirty-six
                                people at dinner, I should think. Table 25 or 30 feet long; might be
                                less; about 18 people on a side; might have been 20 or 30; do not
                                recollect the first words of the conversation; the first I heard the
                                prisoner say was, the people that sent the privateer out were right;
                                did not pay much attention, it did not interest me; I am rather
                                deaf; the prisoner seemed to be talking with Captain Abbott, who
                                asked him what made him say so? The captain did not arise in his
                                seat when he said prisoner was a gentleman. I understood that he
                                meant it; the latter part of the conversation was about the San
                                Francisco vigilance committee. The captain made no remark about a
                                gentleman before the prisoner left the table; prisoner was going out
                                when the remark was made. There were five or six persons in the
                                office when I went in. I went out of the door with the captain, but
                                he was in the office before me. I stopped to get my cap; was about
                                seven feet from Buckley; when he stood up he was close to the table.
                                I saw the scuffle until they got to the door. The lamp did not go
                                out; was occupied a short time putting it to rights; know Captains
                                Lynch, Dolliver, Abbott, and Purcells were there; do not remember
                                any one else; there were others—about six people in the office—don’t
                                    <pb facs="0429" n="409" xml:id="pg_409"/> think there were more;
                                have seen Dr. Kennief; don’t know whether he was there or not; did
                                not see Mr. Eckfeldt; will swear there were not twenty; there were
                                only two taking part in the scuffle. I beard some one say “Let them
                                go;” did not hear anything else said; did not see any one touch
                                either party; will swear no one interfered in the office; did not
                                see Dolliver interfere; was not ten feet off; was not trying to get
                                into the crowd. Dolliver is a medium-sized man; have seen Mr. Dow;
                                did not notice where he was; Dow and Dolliver were larger than me;
                                all were taller men than me; there was quite a crowd between the
                                prisoner and me; the prisoner was nearest to me; the crowd followed
                                them up; there were blows struck by both in the scuffle; Buckley had
                                his hands on the deceased; the captain appeared to be trying to get
                                off; did not see him have his hands on the prisoner, nor on his
                                head; he might have; did not see blood on the prisoner’s face. Saw
                                the prisoner strike the deceased about the neck and shoulders with a
                                light cane; he struck more than once. Saw Captain McKennon after he
                                was shot; did not see any marks on his face; the prisoner raised the
                                stick and did strike him; there were two lamps burning in the hall;
                                have been with Ashley as foreman ten months; have not frequently
                                discussed this case with him. Ashley did not tell me what he
                                testified the other day; did go into hall; was in the door when the
                                shot was fired; there were a number there, say fifteen or twenty;
                                cannot remember any others; do not know their names; the prisoner
                                had a long dark coat—black suit on; the light was only a little dim;
                                did not hear anything said in the hall; only Lynch said, “Let them
                                go.” Did not hear any one say “Give it to him, captain;” I have no
                                interest in this case for or against the prisoner.</p>
                            <p>G. S. Stephens, being duly sworn, says: I am a pilot; I was dining at
                                the International hotel May 22, 1863; was a boarder there, and sat
                                next to Captain McKennon the evening of the murder; Dr. Kennief sat
                                the other side of him; the prisoner sat nearly opposite. The
                                conversation began about a schooner which was fitted out in San
                                Francisco to go down and take the mail-steamer. It was carried on by
                                deceased and Captain Abbott. The prisoner did not join in at that
                                time. It then turned to the Alabama, Florida, and other confederate
                                privateers. Prisoner then joined in and said that “he wished there
                                were more vessels fitted out as privateers; that he was a southerner
                                and of southern principles, and thought their cause was right.” They
                                were not much excited at that time; then something was said about
                                “vigilance committee;” do not remember what; do not know why the
                                prisoner left the room; he left before the deceased, and said he
                                would see the deceased after dinner as he was going out of the door.
                                The deceased said “Very well, if you are a gentleman;” deceased left
                                in ten or twelve minutes. I did not leave until some time after.
                                After the pistol was fired, was sitting in the room; when I heard
                                the report, I saw the deceased coming in with other parties, and
                                heard him say be was shot. Did not see the prisoner afterwards.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross examined.</hi>—The prisoner sat nearly
                                opposite Captain Abbott; was on the same side as the prisoner; four
                                or five persons between them, as near as I can remember; I was not
                                acquainted with either party before; have not referred to the
                                conversation; have not talked it over. Dr. Kennief was at the table
                                next to deceased. He did not appear excited, and had very little to
                                say. I noticed the deceased, he was drinking wine; he did not appear
                                excited; did not rise in his chair at the time he said “You are a
                                gentleman.” It was not said in a sarcastic manner. Captain McKennon
                                was respectfully cool. I thought they were perfect friends. I cannot
                                say how long I boarded in the hotel—three weeks, I think. There were
                                about thirty boarders. Table was about fifty feet long; imagine he
                                was toward lower end, opposite the door; do not know whether they
                                could hear where Ashley sat; think they could hear considerable, if
                                they were listening. Conversation was genera. Captain McKennon
                                addressed Captain Abbott, and the prisoner spoke when the Alahama
                                and Florida were mentioned. <pb facs="0430" n="410" xml:id="pg_410"/> Am sure the prisoner took part in the conversation before the
                                vigilance committee was named; they first seemed to get excited when
                                the vigilance committee was brought up; the prisoner was talking
                                with deceased and Captain Abbott. Abbott first mentioned the
                                “vigilance committee;” do not remember the conversation on that
                                subject; do not know if he was provoked by some remark of the
                                deceased; do not remember that they appeared angry; did not see any
                                one excited, except the prisoner, when he left the table; I did not
                                take notice who else went out; know Ashley by name; cannot say
                                whether he went out before me or not; the majority had gone out:
                                only four or five remained. The report was just as I was getting up;
                                heard the prisoner say he was a southerner; do not know that he is;
                                did not search for the prisoner after the murder; nor did J. L. S.
                                subscribe to the reward, or pay anything towards it.</p>
                            <p>Hugh Kennedy, being duly sworn, says: I know C. J. Ashley; saw him
                                last Monday, the first day of this trial. I was standing outside
                                when be came out and spoke to a witness; he told him he must be
                                careful—be on his guard— “you must be very particular in what you
                                say.” He asked how the trial was going; he said all right. I did not
                                hear Ashley tell Kelly that the captain was struck first; he did not
                                tell witness which to say struck first.</p>
                            <p>James Scott, being duly sworn, says: I am steward of the Steamship
                                Navigation Company’s steamer Hu-Quang. The 22d of May, 1863, I was
                                steward of the International hotel, and I carved at a side table,
                                and overlooked the boys. My attention was called (I was in and out
                                of the kitchen and wine cellar) to a conversation. The deceased
                                dined with Dr. Kennief; I recognize the prisoner as having been
                                there; I heard them talking politics; they got rather wrathy about
                                vigilance committee in San Francisco. Mr. Dow was at the house; he
                                sent a chit in by me to say he wanted to see the captain after
                                dinner. I went into the office and saw Mr. Dow and another gentleman
                                there. Buckley was sitting near a round ring-po table with Captain
                                Lynch. I wanted to deliver the chit to the captain; he came in with
                                Dolliver, Abbott, and others. Buckley had a cane in his hand. I
                                spoke to the captain, saying there was a person waiting to see him.
                                Buckley then rose and struck the captain, saying, “If you are a man
                                resent that, or defend yourself;” and then a scuffle ensued. Did not
                                hear either make any other remark. They scuffled towards the door,
                                the deceased striking the prisoner. About three minutes elapsed in
                                scuffle to the passage-way, and then I saw a weapon in prisoner’s
                                hand; could not tell what it was; immediately after I heard the
                                report of a pistol. Ashley was on the opposite side; he said,
                                “Buckley, don’t shoot anybody here.” He had then fired, and had the
                                pistol in his hand, cocked, and replied, “By God, I will.” Backing
                                himself out of the passage, I saw no more of him. The captain was
                                carried up stairs and his wound examined. They had a hand-to-hand
                                fight I was within two or three feet of the prisoner when I saw the
                                glance of the pistol. I saw Purcells run. The deceased had no weapon
                                in his hand; saw him strike Buckley with his fists; did not see
                                Buckley return the blow, when they were scuffling, after he struck
                                with the cane. I had heard nothing of the deceased before he said
                                “By Cod, I am shot!”</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross-examined.</hi>—I keep the wine cards. Dinner
                                was nearly over; when I went out some had left the table; there were
                                persons there generally. I generally sold considerable wine; do not
                                remember how much Dr. Kennief ordered; he went in with deceased. I
                                remember snatches of conversation. The cane was a small ratan; the
                                prisoner struck deceased over the shoulders; it was intended as an
                                insult to the captain, and he had no chance to speak before Buckley
                                struck him. Buckley was standing up; Captain Lynch was sitting on a
                                chair. I did not get further than the middle of the room; there was
                                a sofa in the corner of the room. Buckley was at the table, about
                                eight feet from the door; he advanced towards the captain as he came
                                in, and made the assault. The people interfered to part them; saw no
                                one strike except the captain. I <pb facs="0431" n="411" xml:id="pg_411"/> know Dolliver; he was in the crowd and tried
                                to part them. The deceased had the best of the trouble. Abbott also
                                tried to part them. Do not remember the deceased having hold of the
                                prisoner’s hair. Lynch said, “Let them be.” I lived there a month
                                and a half after that. There were from fifty to sixty people there
                                to dinner; most of them had left the table and gone out. I heard of
                                people searching for Buckley; heard say if he was caught he would be
                                hung; do not think any lynching would have been done; did not
                                interfere. Could not say how many blows were struck. Was a witness
                                here before, on Lynch’s trial. The deceased had no chance; to my
                                mind, he could whip Buckley; did not see any blood on prisoner’s
                                face; saw deceased strike the prisoner a good many times, and he did
                                not strike back; am not sure that he did not address any remarks to
                                the prisoner. I never saw any one have a pistol there before. Do not
                                know who came with deceased to the hotel; when the dinner bell was
                                rung they all came in together. Abbott and Kennief lived in the same
                                house. Do not remember Dolliver speaking about Lynch; Dolliver was
                                very much annoyed, and took a prominent part; do not remember
                                hearing him say “Let them be;” Lynch said that; the other did not
                                wish to see anything of the kind going on; they tried to pull them
                                apart—tried to pull the captain away; cannot swear which they pulled
                                on; did not see prisoner after the struggle; did not see blood on
                                his face. There were good lights right over where the fight
                                occurred. They were all in the hall together. I have seen the
                                prisoner before; he boarded at the hotel a month and a half; he had
                                never been in a row before, and always conducted himself properly.
                                Never heard Dolliver say anything about the prisoner. The prisoner
                                kept company with Dominick Lynch. I have been in Shanghai about
                                eight months.</p>
                            <p>Case closed for the prosecution.</p>
                            <p>S. B. Quick, being duly sworn, says: I was in Shanghai in May last,
                                and remember the 22d instant. I know the prisoner; saw him between
                                eight and nine o’clock that evening; he had the appearance of having
                                been in a scuffle with some one; he was bruised and cut on the
                                cheek; it was not bleeding when I saw him. I asked if he had been
                                hurt; there were spots of blood upon his shirt-bosom. I knew of the
                                search that was made for him; I was living in a Chinese bazaar; they
                                searched there for him; Baron, the pilot, Clemens, Hathaway, and
                                Dolliver were the parties; they were around my house. I asked them
                                what they were there for. They replied, to find Buckley; that it
                                would not be well for him if they found him.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross-examined.</hi>—I made a statement on the 25th
                                of May before the consul. I met Barker that night. I remember
                                Langan; he was in my house; he came in; Barker saw me first; Buckley
                                was up at my house, and he wanted me to go up; I went up and saw
                                Buckley there; that was the occasion that I saw blood; he told me he
                                had been at the dinner table, and that a discussion arose, about
                                which I knew nothing, and Captain McKennon struck him; and he showed
                                me the marks and said there were two or three others struck at him.
                                That is all I remember of; he said that McKennon struck him.</p>
                            <p>Edward Dias, being duly sworn, says: I have not been acquainted with
                                the prisoner long; saw him the night of the murder; it was between
                                seven and eight o’clock p. m., on the 22d of May. He was disfigured
                                about the face; blood on it and sores. I fancied that he had been
                                struck by the blood.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Cross-examined.</hi>—His appearance was not as if
                                he had been in a severe row or fight. He did not speak to me. I saw
                                him on the “Bund;” did not speak. I saw him as he went by; I knew
                                him by sight; I remarked to a party in the house about it. I am in
                                her Majesty’s jail now for desertion.</p>
                            <p>William Richards, being duly sworn, says: I was in Shanghai in May
                                last. Knew the prisoner by sight; he came into Langan’s the night of
                                the affray. He was cut in the right eye, and had blood on his face
                                and shirt. Some parties came into Langan’s and tore up the floor
                                looking for Buckley; they asked for <pb facs="0432" n="412" xml:id="pg_412"/> all of the small-arms in the house; I told
                                them I had no small-arms, but would give them a bottle of brandy.
                                Did not know McKennon; did not speak to the prisoner that night; his
                                eye was cut, face scarred, and face bloody. I did not ask him
                                anything about it.</p>
                            <p>Case closed for the defence.</p>
                            <p>The court finds the prisoner guilty of murder, and assesses upon him
                                the punishment of death by hanging.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>GEORGE F. SEWARD, <hi rend="italic">Consul General, acting,
                                        judicially.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Assented to:</p>
                                <p rend="right">H. C. ENDICOTT.</p>
                                <p rend="right">A. L. FREEMAN.</p>
                                <p rend="right">T. W. STILLMAN.</p>
                                <p rend="right">J. M. NIXON.</p>
                            </postscript>
                            <postscript>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Court of the United States
                                                Consulate General,</hi>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-02-13"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 13,
                                        1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                                <p>I hereby certify that the foregoing is a true and faithful copy
                                    of the original documents on file in this office.</p>
                                <p>[<hi rend="smallcaps">l. s</hi>]</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>JOHN L. SEWARD, <hi rend="italic">Clerk of
                                        Court.</hi></signed></closer>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">B.</note>
                            <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">ss</hi>:</p>
                            <p>On the 1st of February, A. D. 1864, John Buckley was arraigned as
                                John D. Buckley at Shanghai aforesaid, before George F. Seward,
                                United States consul general, and four associates, without a jury,
                                on the following charge:</p>
                            <p>“John D. Buckley stands charged with having, on the evening of the
                                22d day of May, 1863, wilfully and maliciously, and without
                                provocation, caused the death of one Captain John McKennon, against
                                the peace of the people of the United States.” To which charge the
                                said Buckley, having first claimed a trial by jury, <hi rend="italic">pleaded not guilty;</hi> and he was, on the 4th
                                day of February aforesaid, by the court aforesaid, found guilty of
                                the crime of murder; all of which fully appears by the record.</p>
                            <p>And now the said John Buckley, by his attorney, J. B. Evans, prays
                                that said judgment be arrested as erroneous; and for error
                                assigns—</p>
                            <p>1st. That the said Buckley was not indicted or presented by a grand
                                jury, as required by Article V of the amendments of the Constitution
                                of the United States of America.</p>
                            <p>2d. That said Buckley was not tried by a jury, as required by Article
                                VI of the amendments aforesaid.</p>
                            <p>3d. That the charge does not support the judgment, inasmuch as it
                                contains—</p>
                            <p>1. No allegation that said Buckley is a citizen of the United
                                States.</p>
                            <p>2. No statement of the place where the offence charged was
                                committed.</p>
                            <p>3. No charge of malice prepense.</p>
                            <p>4. No statement of the manner of death.</p>
                            <p>5. No statement of the time of death.</p>
                            <p>6. No statement that said McKennon died of a wound inflicted by said
                                Buckley, or that said Buckley inflicted upon the body of said
                                McKennon a wound in its nature mortal.</p>
                            <p>4th. That the assessors or associates were permitted to separate and
                                go about their ordinary business for two days after the commencement
                                of the trial.</p>
                            <pb facs="0433" n="413" xml:id="pg_413"/>
                            <p>Finally. That the judgment is not supported by the evidence, there
                                being—</p>
                            <p>1. No sufficient evidence of malice prepense.</p>
                            <p>2. No evidence that said McKennon <hi rend="italic">died</hi> of a
                                wound inflicted by said Buckley, or that said Buckley inflicted upon
                                the body of said McKennon a wound necessarily mortal.</p>
                            <p>The precise nature and extent of the power conferred, or intended to
                                be conferred, by the acts of Congress giving to the consuls and
                                ministers in China judicial power, may be matter of doubt. As,
                                however, the decision of the consular court, in a capital case, must
                                be referred to the minister for his sanction, it would seem to
                                follow, as a natural consequence of the minister’s power to examine,
                                that he would have power to set aside a judgment manifestly
                                erroneous.</p>
                            <p>Where it is apparent on the face of the record that the consular
                                court has no power to convict, there would seem to be great hardship
                                in keeping the prisoner in confinement until the case can be
                                corrected by the President. Moreover, if the judgment was improperly
                                rendered, the prisoner has, in common justice, a right to have it
                                reversed, instead of being obliged to sue for pardon of an offence
                                never committed—or, what is in law the same thing, not proved; and
                                unless the power to reverse the decision of the consular court is
                                vested in the minister, it has no place under the acts referred to.
                                Should your excellency decline to reverse the decision of the
                                consular court, I pray that the execution may be stayed, and that
                                the case be submitted to the President.</p>
                            <p>1st and 2d. As to the first and several objections, it is submitted
                                that the case is too clear for argument. The amendments of the
                                Constitution, V and VI, expressly secure, in cases like the present,
                                the right to a trial by jury, and only on indictment or presentment
                                by a grand jury, and an act of Congress authorizing a trial in any
                                other manner is so far void.</p>
                            <p>The word “jury” has, by long usage, received a precise signification
                                at common law, and through the common law, as such, has no place in
                                the federal courts; yet it is always to be consulted for the
                                definition of words used in the Constitution or laws of the United
                                States; and when the word “jury” was used in the Constitution, a
                                common-law jury must have been intended.</p>
                            <p>But, admitting that a jury may consist of a less number than twelve,
                                the argument is the same; for the “associates” cannot, in any just
                                sense, be deemed jurors, as, except in capital cases, the consul
                                decides irrespective of the opinions of the associates.</p>
                            <p>The exterritoriality of the proceedings cannot affect the question.
                                Congress has no power not delegated to it by the Constitution; and
                                that territorial limits of the power cannot exceed those of the
                                instrument from which it is derived.</p>
                            <p>3. But, aside from the unconstitutionality of the court, the defects
                                in the proceedings are fatal to the judgment, for—</p>
                            <p>1. The charge contains no allegation of citizenship, and in the
                                absence of such allegation it does not appear that the court had
                                jurisdiction, the presumption being that all offences committed
                                without the limits of the United States are out of the jurisdiction
                                of the United States courts until the contrary is shown. Upon the
                                9th Geo. IV, c. 31, giving the courts of Great Britain jurisdiction
                                of offences committed by British subjects out of her Majesty’s
                                dominions, it has been held that the indictment must contain an
                                allegation of citizenship.</p>
                            <p>2. No statement of the <hi rend="italic">locus in quo.</hi> This
                                objection, like the last, goes to the jurisdiction, but it also
                                leaves the charge undefined, and it would be impossible to plead
                                this judgment effectually to another trial for the same offence.</p>
                            <p>3. Any indictment for murder becomes an indictment for manslaughter
                                upon erasing the words “malice prepense,” which is the very essence
                                of the crime of murder.</p>
                            <p>4. No statement of the manner of death. It does not appear from the
                                charge whether death was caused by prisoner’s stabbing or shooting.
                                An allegation of the manner has always been claimed indispensable in
                                indictment for murder, and its omission is fatal.</p>
                            <pb facs="0434" n="414" xml:id="pg_414"/>
                            <p>5. It is only by the dates of the proceedings that it appears that
                                the death occurred within a year and a day after the wound was
                                inflicted.</p>
                            <p>6. This objection goes to the whole body of the offence, and it is
                                submitted, that unless the whole system of criminal proceeding is to
                                be swept away, and the government is to be permitted to convict and
                                punish, as the testimony may seem to warrant, without any previous
                                charge, this indictment must be held to be unmistakably bad, and
                                judgment must be arrested on that account.</p>
                            <p>4. If my view of the character of the associates be sustained, and
                                they be held to be mere advisers of the consul, this objection
                                falls; but if they are considered as judges, it was an error to
                                allow them to mingle with the public for two days after the
                                commencement of the trial.</p>
                            <p>Finally. The judgment is not supported by the evidence. I shall not
                                urge the want of proof of deliberate malice, though it seems to me
                                utterly wanting. The possession of a pistol by an old Californian,
                                or even by a man who has been long in Shanghai, raises no
                                presumption that a crime is meditated. That the prisoner always, as
                                most Californians do, carried a pistol, is probably true; but on
                                account of the absence of the only person who was intimately
                                acquainted with his habits, his room-mate, it was impossible to
                                prove this fact. Moreover, the prisoner engaged counsel on Saturday
                                night, and the trial commenced on the following Monday, leaving an
                                interval of one day for preparation. But as to the killing, there
                                was absolutely no testimony, except that the prisoner discharged a
                                pistol, and that John McKennon was wounded.</p>
                            <p>There was not one word of testimony to show that death did result
                                from the shot, or that the wound inflicted by it was, in its nature,
                                mortal. The testimony would barely support a charge of aggravated
                                assault with a deadly weapon, and only by setting at defiance all
                                the established rules of criminal practice could it be made to
                                support a verdict of murder. All the precautions of the law have
                                not, in all cases, preserved the innocent from conviction; and it is
                                of vital importance to preserve intact all the safeguards of
                                personal security and civil liberty,</p>
                            <p>In conclusion, I pray that your excellency will carefully consider
                                the testimony in the case, even if the objections taken should be
                                overruled, and recommend the case of the prisoner to the
                                consideration of the President.</p>
                            <p>It will appear from the testimony, that at the time when the shot was
                                fired the prisoner was struggling at great disadvantage with a man
                                much more powerful than himself; that several persons, not one of
                                whom was a friend of the prisoner, were interfering in the quarrel,
                                though the nature of their interference does not appear, and was
                                probably unknown to the prisoner, and that the prisoner was entirely
                                without aid or hope of assistance. Can it be possible that, under
                                such circumstances, a homicide, even if one were committed, would
                                amount to murder? How many men would have hesitated to avail
                                themselves of any means in their power to release themselves from
                                such a situation? Where was the opportunity for deliberation?</p>
                            <p>I beg to suggest, moreover, that the prisoner’s health is failing,
                                and to urge the importance of deciding this question of the validity
                                of the judgment, without the delay necessarily incident to a
                                reference to the President, if possible. Confinement in his present
                                quarters through the summer would probably prove fatal to the
                                prisoner, and a reversal of the judgment would come too late.</p>
                            <p rend="right">J. B. EVANS, <hi rend="italic">Attorney for
                                    Prisoner.</hi></p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Note.</hi>—If the finding of the coroner’s jury
                                should be made part of the case, I beg to object to its being so
                                used, as it was not put in evidence at the trial and the prisoner
                                had no opportunity to present his objections to said inquest.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>J. B. EVANS.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency the Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Anson
                                        Burlingame,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">United States Resident Minister in
                                    China.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <pb facs="0435" n="415" xml:id="pg_415"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">C.</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. G. F. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Burlingame</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 17.]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-02-13"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 13, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit to you,
                                enclosed, the minutes of the consular court in the trial of John D.
                                Buckley, for the murder of John McKennon, together with the
                                objections taken by the prisoner’s counsel, and a memorandum of same
                                by myself.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>GEORGE F. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Anson Burlingame,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;., &amp;c., Peking.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">D.</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Memorandum concerning objections</persName>
                                to <persName type="to">decision in United States vs. John D.
                                    Buckley</persName></head>
                            <p>To the first and second objections no remarks are offered. If the act
                                of Congress is unconstitutional, the undersigned will be glad to
                                know it, as the idea of committing a judicial murder is abhorrent to
                                him.</p>
                            <p>To the third objection, generally and in detail, he would remark that
                                the commitment of the prisoner, of which the inquisition formed a
                                part, is sufficiently full upon the points made, excepting as to the
                                citizenship of the prisoner; this is dwelt upon in his original
                                letter to him. Moreover, the citizen does not even claim that he is
                                not a United States citizen.</p>
                            <p>To the fourth objection the undersigned finds no prohibition in the
                                act against such separation.</p>
                            <p>To the fifth, if the evidence does not prove malice aforethought, the
                                minister will be able to correct the opinion of the members of the
                                lower court as to an alleged want of evidence that McKennon <hi rend="italic">died,</hi> and from the effects of a wound
                                inflicted by Buckley; the undersigned believes that the evidence
                                offered will leave no room to doubt on this point. Moreover, the
                                prisoner does not claim that he did not so die.</p>
                            <p>The undersigned is aware that he is not rebutting technical arguments
                                in a technical way. He has no desire to do so, because he has never
                                understood that the government expects that his court will be
                                conducted with reference to the numerous formalities of courts at
                                home. He submits that in this instance there is no reason to think
                                that any injustice has happened to the prisoner from the manner of
                                procedure, and that, on the contrary, if he is allowed to avail
                                himself of the merely technical points raised, a great injustice
                                will be done to the inimitable laws of right.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>GEORGE F. SEWARD.</signed><lb/><dateline rendition="#left"><placeName>Shanghai</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-02-13">February 13,
                                1864</date>.</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">E.</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. George F. Seward</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-03-11"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 11, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: John D. Buckley having been tried and
                                convicted, according to law, of the crime of murder, by virtue of
                                the power in me vested, as envoy extraordinary and minister
                                plenipotentiary of the United States to China, and by act of <pb facs="0436" n="416" xml:id="pg_416"/> Congress approved June 22,
                                1860, I order that the said John D. Buckley shall, on the second
                                Friday after the receipt of this, be hanged by the neck until he is
                                dead.</p>
                            <p>This sentence shall be executed, under your direction as consul
                                general of the United States, at ten o’clock in the forenoon of the
                                above day, and this shall be your warrant for the same.</p>
                            <p>In testimony whereof, I have hereunto signed my name and caused the
                                seal of the United States to be affixed, at Peking, this 11th day of
                                March, 1864, and the 88th year of the independence of the United
                                    States.<seg type="margin">[<hi rend="smallcaps">l.
                                s</hi>]</seg></p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Attest:</p>
                                <p rend="right">S. WELLS WILLIAMS.</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">George F. Seward,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">United States Consul, Shanghai.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">F.</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. George F. Seward</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-03-11"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 11, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of your despatch (No. 17) informing me of the trial and
                                conviction of John D. Buckley for murder.</p>
                            <p>After a careful examination of the proceedings of the consular court,
                                and an attentive consideration of the objections made to the same by
                                the learned counsel for the prisoner, I am constrained to approve of
                                the conviction of the said John D. Buckley, and have accordingly
                                issued my warrant for his execution. You will be so kind as to
                                observe in this case the general instructions contained in my letter
                                directing the execution of David Williams.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">George F. Seward,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">Consul General, Shanghai.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">G.</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. George F. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Burlingame</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate
                                            General,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-04-01"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The execution of John D. Buckley
                                having taken place this day, pursuant to the warrant issued from
                                your office on the 11th ultimo, I have to report as follows:</p>
                            <p>The despatch and warrant were received on the morning of the 24th
                                ultimo. The same day the prisoner was brought before me and the
                                warrant read to him. He remarked at considerable length upon the
                                evidence adduced at the trial, declaring that certain witnesses had
                                sworn falsely. He said, also, that he was not an American citizen;
                                that he was born in Ireland; had lived some time in the United
                                States, but had never been naturalized; that he did not shoot
                                McKennon with a revolving pistol, as generally believed, but with a
                                Derringer; and that if he had had a revolver he would have used it
                                again.</p>
                            <pb facs="0437" n="417" xml:id="pg_417"/>
                            <p>On Saturday evening, the 26th ultimo, I received a. despatch from her
                                Majesty’s consul, Sir Harry Parker, K. C. B., a copy of which, and
                                my answer is enclosed. This morning, at about 9 a. m., the prisoner
                                was removed from her Majesty’s jail to the jail building of this
                                consulate. A force of twelve members of the municipal police acted
                                as a guard in making the transfer, while as many more were on duty
                                at the place of execution. The prisoner was placed in the lower room
                                of the jail until the hour of 10. Admission was allowed to a
                                relative of his, and to Pere de Jaques, one of the clergy of the
                                Roman Catholic community of this port.</p>
                            <p>The details of the execution are sufficiently set forth in the
                                accompanying certificate of the attending physician and of five of
                                the persons who witnessed it.</p>
                            <p>It is a matter of much regret to me that the remark made by the
                                deceased at the reading of the warrant for his execution, that he
                                would have used a revolver a second time if he had had one, was
                                reported in one of the local prints in a manner which, if correct,
                                would have evinced the utmost depravity on his part. I had fully
                                explained the manner in which the misreport had occurred to the
                                previously named relative of the deceased, and would have done so to
                                the public had I entertained any idea the same would be traced to
                                any source other than that from which it actually sprung, or if the
                                slightest intimation had been given that the prisoner felt himself
                                aggrieved.</p>
                            <p>I have only to say, in conclusion, that I trust no similar duty will
                                be imposed upon me again so long as I remain in this office. There
                                is no reason, excepting the absence of appropriate legislation, why
                                American citizens in China, charged with grave offences, should not
                                have the privilege of a trial by jury as elsewhere throughout the
                                world where the institution of civilization prevails. When such is
                                the case, I think it not right to deprive those thus charged from a
                                privilege so dear to all freemen, nor yet to impose upon a consular
                                officer the responsibilities so grave as they are now obliged to
                                assume.</p>
                            <p>The occasion also affords me an opportunity to speak of the
                                disabilities which we are under in carrying out the present system.
                                In this case, fearing to trust the rickety jail building of this
                                consulate, I caused the prisoner to be confined in her Majesty’s
                                jail. For the expense thus incurred, together with a gratuity which
                                I think it is right to hand the keeper, it is likely I shall have to
                                provide from my personal income. I <ref target="http://thought.it">thought it</ref> right, also, for many reasons, to engage the
                                services of a prosecuting attorney, the chief of which was, that it
                                would be unfair to forbid the prisoner, who had no means of access
                                to his witnesses, counsel for his defence, and still more unfair to
                                the government to allow counsel for the defence without providing
                                the same for the prosecution. Thus an expense of nearly $200 has
                                been incurred—an amount I would not speak of were there not so many
                                drains upon my limited means—no portion of which I may hope to
                                collect from the government. Similar expenses have been accrued in
                                other instances, and we are continually liable to them.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>GEORGE F. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Anson Burlingame,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Minister, Peking.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">H.</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Parker</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. George F. Seward</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 100.]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">British Consulate,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-03-26"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 26, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose, for your
                                perusal, a letter or statement which I have received this day from
                                Mr. Eames, the counsel for the prisoner, John D. Buckley, claiming
                                for him protection as a British Subject, although I learn the <pb facs="0438" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/> prisoner has already been
                                tried in your court as an American citizen, without any objection
                                being taken at the time of trial to the jurisdiction of your court,
                                and has been sentenced to undergo capital punishment for the offence
                                of which he was found guilty. I am by no means, therefore, prepared
                                to find that his claim to British protection can be sustained; but I
                                should be glad to receive any information on the subject which you
                                can kindly furnish me, and I would beg your attention to the closing
                                remarks of Mr. Eames’s letter, which allege that he was not charged
                                with being an American citizen at the time of his trial. May I
                                request you to return Mr. Eames’s letter and the two papers enclosed
                                when you have read them.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>HARRY S. PARKER, <hi rend="italic">Consul.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">George F. Seward,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">United States Consul General,
                                    Shanghai.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">I.</note>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. George F. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Parker</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 77.]</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate
                                            General,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Shanghai,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-03-26"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 26, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have had the honor to receive your
                                despatch of the 26th instant covering enclosures which, as
                                requested, are returned herewith.</p>
                            <p>The prisoner, Buckley, was not charged upon his trial with being an
                                American citizen, but he was charged as an American citizen. You
                                will note the wording of the indictment, which says, “against the
                                people of the United States.”</p>
                            <p>It was not thought necessary to inquire into the prisoner’s
                                nationality, for two reasons: because it has never been customary to
                                do so in similar cases, but to accept the prisoner’s own statement,
                                and because Buckley had definitely surrendered himself to me for
                                trial. I enclose a copy of a communication addressed by him to the
                                United States consul at Nagasaki, which is in point. I was informed
                                by the said official that Buckley, while in prison at that port,
                                claimed British protection, but that upon being visited by her
                                Majesty’s consul he said that he was not a British subject. Buckley
                                explains this by saying that he said he was not an Englishman, he
                                now declaring that he is of Irish parentage. Buckley’s counsel
                                objected to the proceedings upon the trial, after the same had been
                                concluded and the minutes had been prepared for transmission to his
                                excellency Mr. Burlingame, upon the ground that it had not been
                                proven that the prisoner was an American citizen. There was no claim
                                made to me at that time or before that he was a British subject, but
                                this was reserved until the decision of the minister had arrived.
                                The case thus stands, in fact, quite the same as that of D.
                                Williams, in which his excellency the British minister refused to
                                interfere.</p>
                            <p>I need not say that, under other circumstances, the idea of assuming
                                any power whatsoever over her Majesty’s subjects would be extremely
                                repugnant to me. The many difficulties arising from the mixture of
                                jurisdictions and the impossibility of receiving evidence as to the
                                proper nationality of individual criminals, are a sufficient excuse
                                for a manner of procedure which otherwise would be highly
                                objectionable.</p>
                            <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                            <p rend="right">GEORGE F. SEWARD.</p>
                            <p>Sir <hi rend="smallcaps">Harry Parker,</hi> K. C. B., <hi rend="italic">Her Majesty’s Consul, Shanghai.</hi></p>
                            <pb facs="0439" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/>
                            <p>The undersigned hereby certify that they were present at the
                                execution of John D. Buckley, convicted of the murder of John
                                McKennon, master of the hark Emily Banning, which took place as
                                follows: At the hour of 10 a. m., the 1st day of April, A. D. 1864,
                                the prisoner was brought from a low room of the jail buildings of
                                the United States consulate general at Shanghai, of a flight of
                                stairs to a verandah, and thence to the scaffold, which was
                                constructed in front of the same, and the floor upon the same level.
                                He was placed upon the drop, and asked by Mr. Lewis, the deputy
                                consul, whether he had anything to say. He remarked, in reply, that
                                he was innocent of the crime of murder, he having shot McKennon in
                                self-defence; that he was of Irish birth, and had never denied his
                                nationality, but he could forgive those who had perjured themselves
                                upon his trial, and those who had informed upon him, but that he
                                could not forgive Mr. Seward, who had caused the publication of
                                alleged remarks of his at the time when his sentence was read to
                                him, which was false. He then said that he had nothing more to say,
                                and after repeating a few words of prayer after the attending
                                clergyman, Pere de Jaques, forgiving his enemies and committing his
                                soul to God, the fatal noose and death-cap were adjusted, and, at a
                                signal, the support of the drop was instantaneously removed. He fell
                                nearly ten feet, and hardly made a struggle. Upon subsequent
                                examination it was shown that the vertebræ of the neck was
                                dislocated by the fall, and it is probable that he suffered no more
                                than a momentary pain.</p>
                            <p>The conduct of the deceased was remarkably firm and collected
                                throughout. No evidence of emotion or of faltering spirit could be
                                seen. His hands, which were pinioned behind, were tightly gripped,
                                and the almost purple hue they exhibited when the preparations were
                                complete evinced the point of tension to which his nerves were
                                strained. His remarks occupied a period of perhaps five minutes, the
                                substance of which is given above. At the end of a half hour— no
                                sign of life remaining—he was taken down and placed in a coffin
                                prepared by his friends.</p>
                            <p>The utmost care was taken by Mr. Deputy Consul Lewis and Mr. Howard,
                                the marshal, and no untoward circumstance occurred to render the sad
                                duty they were called to perform more difficult.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>J. J. HOWARD.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>JOHN P. BENNETT.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>S. C. FARNHAM.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>JAMES S. WHITMAN.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>DAVID S. CAUNELL.</signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">J.</note>
                            <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Shanghai,
                                        China,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-04-01"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 1, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>I hereby certify that I was present at the execution of “John
                                Buckley,” examined his body, and pronounced life extinct.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>W. G. HAY, <hi rend="italic">M. D</hi>.</signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>