<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-01-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-01-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="469" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d469">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Pruyn</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 10.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in
                                        Japan</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Kanagawa</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-01-22"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 22, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I regret to have to inform you that the
                            Japanese government has declined to pay the indemnities I have been
                            instructed to demand. I enclose, No. 1, a copy of translation of the
                            letter of the minister, which, you see, does not attempt to deny or even
                            explain the facts set forth in my letter, which, I think, fully
                            establish the liability of the Japanese government.</p>
                        <p>The chief object in the proposed transfer of the negotiations to
                            Washington is probably to gain time, as the embassy is first to visit
                            all the treaty powers in Europe. It may be hoped, likewise, that if it
                            finally yields to these claims, the Japanese government may secure the
                            coveted closing of this port.</p>
                        <p>I enclose, No. 2, a copy of my reply. I do not yet despair of an amicable
                                <pb facs="0496" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/> and satisfactory
                            settlement, though I am without a national vessel, and nothing has been
                            accomplished here as yet by any nation in the absence of force, or the
                            prospect of its immediate presence.</p>
                        <p>Additional proof of this will soon be given. Baron de Rehfus has been
                            here since the month of September, vainly urging the exchange of
                            ratifications of the Prussian treaty. He has now gone to Yedo, and has
                            landed a large guard of marines and sailors from the corvette Gazelle,
                            and announced his determination to remain in that city till the exchange
                            of ratifications shall have been effected, and I have no doubt he will
                            now succeed.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your obedient
                            servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>ROBERT H. PRUYN, <hi rend="italic">Minister Resident in
                                    Japan.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><persName type="from">The Gorogio</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Pruyn</persName></head>
                            <p>We received your letter No. 136, dated the 21st December, and
                                understood all that you stated therein. In the first place, in
                                regard to what has been said about the fire at Dzenfkujee, it has
                                been not only stated to your excellency on that occasion in writing,
                                but the circumstances have also been fully and clearly explained by
                                governors for foreign affairs, under our instructions; hence, you
                                must have understood them well; we therefore thought that you would
                                clearly explain this to your government, and would have received
                                instructions accordingly. Your communication surprised us
                                greatly.</p>
                            <p>The treaty of peace and amity having been concluded, good faith must
                                be mutually shown as a matter of course; but your suspicion that the
                                fire was caused by secret instigation of criminals would be an
                                extraordinary indignity for our government. If our government,
                                because the public feeling in our country is mostly unsettled,
                                desired, in the conciliation of that public feeling, to put an end
                                to the intercourse with foreign powers, there would be a different
                                action; if such were the case, the engagement entered into of peace
                                and amity would go for naught, and all the care we have hitherto
                                taken would have been in vain; wherefore, we are in great anxiety.
                                That, without taking this into consideration, you should have made
                                us the said communication, is very disagreeable to us.</p>
                            <p>If now we were to give the money for indemnity, according to your
                                demand, it would then be taken for granted that your suspicion was
                                correct and founded on reality. There could be no greater disgrace
                                for our government than to do this; it is, therefore, absolutely
                                impossible to comply with your demand, however much you might, urge
                                us. If, however, owing to the strict orders which you received from
                                your government, you should not be able to settle this on your own
                                responsibility, we will then, through our embassy about to be sent
                                to your country, fully confer with your government on the subject.
                                As regards the temple as the temporary residence of the minister at
                                Yedo, we have already given orders to the proper persons, wherefore
                                the building of it will be proceeded with.</p>
                            <p>And as regards the Yokohama matter, we instructed the governor of
                                Kanagawa to investigate the real circumstances thereof, wherefore we
                                will shortly give your excellency a definite answer when it is
                                entirely arranged; but on the occasion of the excitement among the
                                residents of Yokohama last summer, many mistakes among them,
                                originating in trifling causes, occurred, and unlawful acts were
                                probably not committed by the Japanese only, and the <pb facs="0497" n="477" xml:id="pg_477"/> forcible urging, by Japanese, of their
                                claim on your countryman, must have been caused by his improper
                                refusal of the same. In regard to the matter, however, we shall,
                                after full examination, address ourselves, in further reply, to your
                                excellency.</p>
                            <p>In conclusion, upon the matter of the resident of the Ogasawara Sima,
                                (Bonin islands,) we already had a correspondence, but the real
                                circumstances of the case have not yet become perfectly evident; we
                                propose, therefore, through the proper person, fully to confer with
                                your excellency on that subject.</p>
                            <p>We regret that we cannot comply with your demand as stated in the
                                said letter; but as we find ourselves compelled, for the reason
                                already given, to state the foregoing to your excellency, it is
                                desirable that you will not take it in evil part.</p>
                            <p>As your letter on the occasion of the destruction, by fire of the
                                castle was destroyed, and there have been many things to attend to,
                                we fear that the expiration of the time proposed has been caused
                                thereby, which we have to state, in preliminary reply, to your
                                letter.</p>
                            <p>With respect and esteem.</p>
                            <closer><dateline rendition="#left"><date calendar="gregorian japanese-nengō" when="1864-01-18">The
                                        10th day of the 12th month of the 3d year of Bunkiu, (18th
                                        January, 1864</date>.)</dateline>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>MIDSUMO IDSUMI-NO-KAMI.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>ITAKURA SUWO-NO-KAMI.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>INOWUYE KAWATSI-NO-KAMI.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>ARIMA TOTOMI-NO-KAMI.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert H. Pruyn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Minister Resident of the United States of
                                        America, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>