<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1864-02-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1864-02-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="476" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d476">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Pruyn</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 19.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in
                                        Japan</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Kanagawa</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-02-25"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 25, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose No. 1, a copy
                            of the agreement for the extension of the time of opening the new ports
                            and cities to trade and residence, which is of the same duration as that
                            granted by the other treaty powers.</p>
                        <p>On my arrival in Japan no action had been taken by the treaty powers in
                            reference to the application of the Japanese government for such
                            extension. Mr. Harris was unable to act when first authorized, because
                            some of his colleagues, in concert with whom he was empowered to grant
                            such extension, had recommended their respective governments to refuse
                            their assent. In the month of February, 1862, Sir Rutherford Alcock
                            addressed a letter to Mr. Harris, informing him that he was ready to
                            confer with him on the subject, but Mr. Harris replied that he was in
                            daily expectation of my arrival, and he wished to leave me to act free
                            from any embarrassment which might arise from his discussion of the
                            subject. Shortly after the Japanese left for Europe, and the subject was
                            again referred back to the home government by the ministers of the
                            several European powers.</p>
                        <p>On the occasion of my first interview with the Gorogio, the subject was
                            introduced, and Mr. Harris informed the ministers he had given me his
                            views, and the government would find me very friendly, and disposed to
                            do all that was proper.</p>
                        <p>From that time till December no application for such consent was made by
                            the Japanese government, nor was the subject referred to, though
                            meanwhile I had been empowered to act independently of my
                            colleagues.</p>
                        <pb facs="0503" n="483" xml:id="pg_483"/>
                        <p>Early in December I addressed a letter to the ministers, in which I
                            proposed certain modifications of the treaty, reducing duties and
                            establishing bonded warehouses. I also informed the ministers I had
                            received a letter from American merchants residing in Yokohama, asking
                            what arrangements had been made for the accommodation of foreigners at
                            Hiogo and Osacca, when those cities should be opened the ensuing month.
                            No reply was given or notice taken of either of those letters.</p>
                        <p>A few days before the 1st of January, 1863, I had an interview with
                            Sinano-no-kami, governor of foreign affairs, in which, after expressing
                            a wish that all unfinished business should be disposed of before New
                            Year’s day, I referred, among other subjects unacted on, to these
                            letters, and expressed my surprise that they had received no notice. He
                            at once replied: We do not intend to open the port of Hioga and city of
                            Osacca. I thanked him for the information, but said I was under the
                            impression that I had something to say on that subject. He said no, Mr.
                            Harris has given the consent of the United States.</p>
                        <p>I then said the Japanese government certainly labored under a mistake;
                            that Mr. Harris had informed me he had not given such consent, nor could
                            he have done so, as he was only authorized to act in conjunction with
                            his colleagues; that they had no such authority till February, 1862, and
                            when they were prepared to act Mr. Harris had declined a conference, as
                            he was daily expecting my arrival. The governor replied that Mr. Harris
                            had certainly given such assent, and that the government had his letter
                            to that effect.</p>
                        <p>I then produced the letter of the Japanese government asking Mr. Harris
                            to reduce to writing what he had said on the subject of an official
                            interview, and his indorsement that no answer was necessary. I also
                            produced the letter of the President and of the department in answer to
                            the letter of the Tycoon and the ministers, and read Mr. Harris’s letter
                            to Sir Rutherford Alcock, and I expressed my surprise that, while an
                            embassy had been despatched to Europe to ask for such extension, the
                            only minister in Yedo had never been addressed on so important a
                            subject.</p>
                        <p>The governor hastily left the legation, and returning the next day, said
                            the government had been laboring under a great mistake; that it had no
                            such letter as had been supposed; that it had been grossly negligent,
                            and must throw itself on my indulgence, and now ask me to give such
                            consent on behalf of the United States.</p>
                        <p>I replied I had not overlooked the subject nor underrated its importance,
                            and had supposed the Japanese government knew its own business best, and
                            when ready would propose such modification of the treaty. It had now
                            done so, and I was prepared to act, but I thought it could scarcely be
                            expected, that the United States would consent to a modification of the
                            treaty proposed that day, when not even the receipt of my letters
                            proposing other modifications had been acknowledged. This led to the
                            appointment of commissioners, the negotiations of which you have been
                            advised, and the framing a treaty for the reduction of duties, the
                            establishment of bonded warehouses, &amp;c. As originally agreed on, the
                            postponement of the opening of Hioga, Osacca, &amp;c., formed one of the
                            articles; but on my suggestion, as the reduction of duty was to be
                            permanent, and such postponement to be made only for five years, and as
                            the Japanese government might wish to publish the one and not the
                            others, such postponement was omitted from the treaty and embraced in a
                            distinct article.</p>
                        <p>When the convention was finally signed, I executed the agreement of which
                            I now enclose a copy, and the ministers for foreign affairs have
                            promised to appoint commissioners to visit me in June to agree on the
                            bonded warehouse system. I enclose, No. 2, translation of that
                            letter.</p>
                        <p>The above is a brief history of so much of the negotiations as has not
                            already been communicated; and will explain the delay in giving the
                            consent of the <pb facs="0504" n="484" xml:id="pg_484"/> United States
                            to the postponement asked for by the Japanese government, and which I
                            see by your letter to Mr. Pike, our minister at the Hague, you supposed
                            had been given.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your most obedient
                            servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>ROBERT H. PRUYN, <hi rend="italic">Minister Resident in
                                    Japan.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>No. 1.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in
                                            Japan</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Kanagawa</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-01-28"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 28, 1864.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>By virtue of the power vested in me by the President of the United
                                States of America, I, Robert H. Pruyn, minister resident of the
                                United States in Japan, do hereby consent that the time for the
                                opening of the cities and ports of Yedo, Osacca, Hioga, and Néeé
                                Gata shall be, and is hereby, extended for the period of five years,
                                dating from the 1st January, 1863.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>ROBERT H. PRUYN, <hi rend="italic">Minister Resident of the
                                        United States in Japan.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">No. 2.</seg></opener>
                            <head><persName type="from">The Gorogio</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Pruyn</persName></head>
                            <p>In regard to the establishment of bonded warehouses at each of the
                                opened ports, we fully understood, as stated in our reply recently
                                sent to your letter.</p>
                            <p>And before the 28th day of the 5th month of our next year (July 1,
                                1864) we shall appoint commissioners to negotiate and determine
                                about the regulations, and also to confer about the time when they
                                shall go into operation.</p>
                            <p>With respect and esteem.</p>
                            <closer><dateline rendition="#left"><date calendar="gregorian japanese-nengō" when="1864-02-02">The
                                        24th day of the 12th month of the 3d year of Bunkiu,
                                        (February 2, 1864</date>.)</dateline>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>MIDSUMO IDSUMI-NO-KAMI.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>ITAKURA SUWO-NO-KAMI.</signed>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>INOWUYE KAWATSI-NO-KAMI.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert H. Pruyn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Minister Resident of the United States of
                                        America, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>