<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom ( (Matthews) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d104</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">104</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-02-20T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-02-20T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec8HXmBQjKyPk0EY" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062603"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Housing</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-20T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-20T09:00:00-05:00" n="104"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d104">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/3609: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-02-20T15:00:00+01:00"
                            >February 20, 1943—3 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received February 21—1:30 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1309. Richard Law<note n="4" xml:id="d104fn4">British Parliamentary
                        Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.</note> asked me to call at the
                    Foreign Office yesterday afternoon. He discussed the question of what steps
                    might be taken looking toward some concerted action by the United Nations on
                    behalf of such Jews on the continent of Europe as are able to escape Hitler’s
                    policy of extermination. He said that while much to his regret he was not sure
                    that much practical help could be given these unfortunate people, public opinion
                    in Great Britain has been rising to such a degree that the British Government
                    can no longer remain dead to it. The temper of the House of Commons is such that
                    the Government will be unable to postpone beyond next week some reply to the
                    persistent demands to know what it is doing to help the Jews. With the foregoing
                    explanation and assuring me that he was aware of the many difficulties involved
                    in any attempt to improve the lot of the Jews, he handed me the following
                    memorandum: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The United States Embassy will be aware of the intense public interest
                            shown in the United Kingdom over refugees from German oppression and in
                            particular over the fate of the Jews. This has grown since the Allied
                            declaration of December 17<note n="5" xml:id="d104fn5">Department of
                                State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, December 19, 1942, p.
                                1009.</note> which revealed the extent of Germany’s policy of
                            extermination. Distinguished public men, for example the Archbishop of
                            Canterbury, members of Parliament of all parties and innumberable
                            responsible public bodies have made intensive representation to His
                            Majesty’s Government that every effort should be made to meet the
                            extermination policy by rescuing such Jews as are able to escape into
                            neutral countries, and facilitate the reception of more. His Majesty’s
                            Government and various colonial governments have already received very
                            large numbers of refugees, and war exigencies, pressure on food and
                            housing, now make further action on any substantial scale quite
                            impracticable, except in Palestine where independently His Majesty’s
                            Government have announced their arrangements for taking many thousands
                            of Jews from Southeastern Europe, provided the necessary transport can
                            be secured.</p>
                        <p>On the main problem, which is so much agitating the public conscience in
                            this country, His Majesty’s Government feel sure that the United States
                            Government will agree that it is one for common consideration, and
                            action where possible, on the part of all the governments who
                            participated in the Allied declaration of December 17th. Accordingly His
                            Majesty’s Government on January 12<note n="6" xml:id="d104fn6"
                                >Presumably the British <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of
                                January 20, <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi>
                            </note> addressed themselves, through His Majesty’s Ambassador in
                            Washington, to the United States Government to secure that Government’s
                            views and if <pb facs="0149" n="139" xml:id="pg_139"/> possible its
                            cooperation on the most pressing aspects of the problem. On receipt of a
                            definite answer from Washington it was suggested that an approach could
                            then be made to the other Allied Governments. Up to the present no
                            statement of the views of the United States Government has been received
                            which could form an agreed joint basis of approach to those Governments,
                            and His Majesty’s Government are under the necessity of answering public
                            representations vaguely and of avoiding, naturally, any reference to the
                            American share in finding a solution to the pressing general
                            problem.</p>
                        <p>His Majesty’s Government gratefully acknowledge the cooperation of the
                            United States authorities in Spain and North Africa over the local
                            refugee problems in those territories; this, although of undoubted
                            importance, does not meet the main problem, and His Majesty’s Government
                            are therefore anxious to enlist the help of the United States Embassy in
                            London in explaining to the appropriate authorities in Washington the
                            precise urgency and scope of the question as seen in London.</p>
                        <p>Responsible British opinion will no doubt accept the position that
                            measures of rescue and relief on any great scale are impracticable in
                            the present stage of the war. But there are three steps which, it
                            appears to His Majesty’s Government, might be taken without prejudice to
                            vital war needs, and would, in addition to what is already being done in
                            regard to Palestine and elsewhere, go far to meet the legitimate public
                            anxiety over this humanitarian issue. They are: (1) That the United
                            States Government should associate themselves with His Majesty’s
                            Government in convening in London a meeting of the Allied Governments to
                            examine the problem and its possible solutions. (2) That both
                            Governments should agree on a number of special visas for refugees, and
                            with this contribution invite similar assistance from countries with the
                            necessary territorial facilities. (3) That the United States Government
                            should associate themselves with His Majesty’s Government in promoting
                            an international guarantee to the various neutral governments now, with
                            increasing difficulty and apprehension, receiving refugees, that they
                            would not be left alone to carry this burden at the end of the war.</p>
                        <p>It appears to His Majesty’s Government that if these three steps could be
                            taken at an early date, this would be an effective reply to the
                            agitation aroused in the conscience of the civilized world; it would
                            also demonstrate the practical limitations to which the Allied
                            Governments with all their intense sympathy for the victims of Germany’s
                            policy, must at present be inexorably subjected.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I told him that I would be pleased to communicate the memorandum to my Government
                    and that he could rest assured that we fully shared the British Government’s
                    desire to do what little may be feasible to help the tragic lot of these poor
                    people insofar it is in our power to do so. I said that I did not know the
                    Department’s views as to the proper approach to this question and with regard to
                    point 2 of the Foreign Office memo it occurred to me that Congressional action
                    might be required and that this might present some difficulties.</p>
                <p>I asked specifically what the Foreign Office had in mind with regard to
                    assurances that neutral governments receiving Jewish refugees <pb facs="0150"
                        n="140" xml:id="pg_140"/> now “would not be left alone to carry this burden
                    at the end of the war”. He said it meant in part that we should exert our
                    influence to see that when the war is over the Jewish nationals of various
                    countries who have sought and been given a haven of refuge by various neutral
                    governments could be repatriated to their native lands. He said, for instance,
                        Sikorski<note n="7" xml:id="d104fn7">Gen. Wladyslaw Sikorski, Polish Prime
                        Minister and Commander in Chief.</note> has already declared that after the
                    war all Polish Jews would be welcomed back to Poland. He felt that similar
                    assurances might be obtained with regard to other areas.</p>
                <p>I recalled that some thought had once been given before the war to finding a home
                    for oppressed Jews in Madagascar, and asked whether this thought had recently
                    been pursued. Randall,<note n="8" xml:id="d104fn8">Alec Randall, Counsellor in
                        the British Foreign Office.</note> who was with Law, replied that the area
                    did not seem climatically well suited, that it was planned to send other refugee
                    groups there, if possible, and that transport presented outstanding
                    difficulties.</p>
                <p>I should appreciate receiving the Department’s early instructions as to the reply
                    I should make to the foregoing memo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Matthews</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
