<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Winant) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">152</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-05-26T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-05-26T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="rec83f6d11c10a4344" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="league-of-nations" subject="league-of-nations">League of Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-05-26T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-05-26T17:00:00-05:00" n="152"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">548.G1/142: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-05-27T00:00:00+02:00"
                            >May 27, 1943—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received May 27—10:25
                        p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3657. Mr. Eden asked me and Lord Winterton, Chairman of the Intergovernmental
                    Committee on Refugees, to meet him in his office this afternoon in order to go
                    over certain points which he thought our two Governments would like to consider
                    before the meeting of the Executive Committee. He said the invitations were
                    ready to go out to the other members of the Executive Committee, namely, the
                    Argentine, Brazilian and Netherlands Governments (it being agreed that France
                    should be omitted) as soon as the place and time of meeting had been determined.
                    He mentioned he hoped he would hear from us shortly about this on the basis of
                    his note transmitted in my 3415, May 17, 12 midnight.</p>
                <p>The points raised by Mr. Eden on which he would like the American Government’s
                    opinion with a view to completing our understanding before the Executive
                    Committee meets were the following: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Shall the Executive Committee, when it meets, invite to the plenary
                            meeting all the original members of the Intergovernmental Committee?
                            With the agreed upon omission of France, the British Government’s
                            opinion was in the affirmative, and Mr. Eden thought that the member
                            Governments would find the invitations acceptable, with the possible
                            exception of Switzerland. He believed in any case that should a
                            sufficient number of member Governments agree, the meeting of the
                            Plenary Committee could then be called.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>In order to eliminate the necessity of the Executive Committee first
                            calling together a full meeting of the Intergovernmental Committee with
                            its present membership we felt that the Executive Committee could
                            consult with the Governments as to the final membership of the Plenary
                            Committee to be called in Washington and as to the agenda to be
                            considered. If you approve of this procedure then the question of the
                            Governments to be asked should be agreed upon by the British and
                            ourselves before the Executive Committee meets. The British thought
                            certainly that Russia, Poland, Greece and Yugoslavia also should be
                            invited, and they sought our views with respect to Spain and
                            Portugal.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Where should the headquarters of the Intergovernmental Committee be
                            established? Mr. Eden reiterated the reasons outlined in my 3415, May
                            17, 12 midnight in favor of the choice of London as the place of meeting
                            of the Executive Committee, but suggested Washington as the place of
                            meeting of the Plenary Committee.</item>
                        <label>(4)</label>
                        <item>For which category of refugees should the full Intergovernmental
                            Committee be responsible? The British favored the Bermuda Conference
                            formula as set forth in chapter 5 of the conference report,<note n="56"
                                xml:id="d152fn56">Not found in Department files.</note>
                            <pb facs="0197" n="187" xml:id="pg_187"/> namely all refugees from
                            religious, racial and political oppression in Axis held
                            countries.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In the course of our conversation Lord Winterton raised the question of the
                    relationship between the Intergovernmental Committee and the League of Nations
                    refugee bodies. Since Sir Herbert Emerson is director of the former and is also
                    League of Nations High Commissioner for Refugees there is at present no problem,
                    but should it be decided later to have a younger man replace Sir Herbert the
                    relationship referred to above would need to be considered. Lord Winterton also
                    mentioned that should the headquarters of the Intergovernmental Committee be
                    established in Washington, as he personally hoped it might be, his parliamentary
                    duties in London might make it difficult for him to continue as chairman, and he
                    suggested that he be replaced by an American. Lord Winterton finally raised the
                    point of financing future refugee work. He referred to the funds hitherto
                    largely derived from private Jewish organizations and he suggested that in view
                    of the wider scope recommended by the Bermuda Conference, financing henceforth
                    be made a Government responsibility. No definite opinions were expressed
                    concerning these questions raised by Lord Winterton since we felt they were
                    matters which might more appropriately be taken up later when the Plenary
                    Committee meets in Washington.</p>
                <p>With respect to the numbered points set forth above I would be grateful if the
                    Department could give me its views for communication to Mr. Eden as soon as
                    possible, as he believes that a preliminary understanding with us would assist
                    the Executive Committee in drawing up its agenda and proceeding quickly with its
                    work.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Winant</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
