<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-03-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="240" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d240">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/3673</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 8175</seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-03-10">March 10,
                            1943</date>.<lb/>[Received March 15.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my despatch No.
                        8103 of March 8, 1943<note n="20" xml:id="d240fn20">Not printed.</note>
                        reporting on my conversations with the Foreign Minister<note n="21" xml:id="d240fn21">Ezequiel Padilla.</note> and the Undersecretary<note n="22" xml:id="d240fn22">Jaime Torres Bodet.</note> concerning the
                        admission of Polish refugees into Mexico from Iran via India and a West
                        Coast port of the United States.</p>
                    <p>This morning the Polish Minister, Dr. Wladyslaw Neuman, who has only recently
                        presented his credentials called and I outlined to him the rather
                        unfortunate situation which has developed here due principally to the lack
                        of an organization to receive the first batch of refugees. I told him of my
                        conversations at the Foreign Office and emphasized the preoccupation of the
                        Mexican Government as well as my Government that no arrangements have so far
                        been made for the selection of a site where these people may reside, much
                        less for their housing or provisioning. I told him that I was loath to
                        interfere <pb facs="0276" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/> in this matter but that
                        following my conversations in Washington and my knowledge of the situation
                        here, I felt I had an obligation since my Government has assumed some
                        measure of responsibility in agreeing to financing the maintenance of these
                        refugees. I said that I had reported to the Department fully on this matter
                        and had recommended that a committee be composed of a Mexican citizen, a
                        Polish citizen and an American citizen (possibly an officer of this Embassy)
                        to work out the details looking forward to the reception of the
                        refugees.</p>
                    <p>I found the Minister understanding and himself deploring the lack of
                        organization. He attributed this to the departure of his predecessor and his
                        recent arrival. I was somewhat relieved when he told me that it was his
                        understanding that the first group of refugees had not yet left Iran and
                        that therefore there was time to effect some sort of an organization and to
                        carry on the conversations which must be preliminary to any definitive
                        arrangements. He told me that immediately after presenting his letters of
                        credence he had while calling on the Minister of Gobernación<note n="23" xml:id="d240fn23">Miguel Alemán.</note> as a matter of courtesy
                        mentioned this matter to him. He found that Mr. Alemán had no knowledge
                        whatsoever of the expected arrival of these refugees but that after
                        consulting with his undersecretary, the Minister of Gobernación said that it
                        might be possible to place the refugees in either Guanajuato or Querétaro.
                        The Polish Minister said that Guanajuato might be the better of the two
                        places because Señor Ernesto Hidalgo, formerly chief clerk of the Foreign
                        Office, who conducted the negotiations preliminary to the signing of the
                        agreement between General Sikorsky, and the Mexican Government<note n="24" xml:id="d240fn24">Exchange of notes between Polish Prime Minister
                            Sikorski and Mexican Foreign Secretary Padilla regarding the admission
                            of Polish refugees to Mexico, December 30, 1942, transmitted to the
                            Department by the Ambassador in Mexico in his despatch No. 6270,
                            December 81, 1942 (840.48 Refugees/3508). For texts of the notes
                            exchanged, see <hi rend="italic">Memoria de la Secretaría de Relaciones
                                Exteriores</hi>, 1942–1943 (Mexico, D.F., 1943), pp. 457–460.</note>
                        concerning these refugees is now a candidate for Governor of that State. The
                        Polish Minister expressed himself as believing he would be the next
                        Governor.</p>
                    <p>The Minister explained that on leaving my office he was going directly to the
                        Ministry of Gobernación to speak with Mr. Alemán and that he would keep me
                        closely informed of the results of conversations he may have there as well
                        as with other officials of the Mexican Government.</p>
                    <p>I desire to emphasize that I will be very appreciative if the Department will
                        give me the benefit of its precise instructions as soon as possible.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">G. S. Messersmith</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>