<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-04T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-04T20:00:00-05:00" n="391" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d391">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.48 Refugees/4856b: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            American Representative to the French Committee of National Liberation
                            at Algiers</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi></persName>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-04T21:00:00-04:00">December 4,
                                1943—9 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>64. For Murphy and Gordon<note n="52" xml:id="d391fn52">Paul W. Gordon,
                            Office of Foreign Relief and Rehabilitation Operations; on staff of
                            Robert D. Murphy, Chief Civil Affairs Officer at Algiers.</note> from
                        Fryer and Latimer.<note n="53" xml:id="d391fn53">Presumably Murray Latimer,
                            Assistant Director, Liberated Areas Branch, Foreign Economic
                            Administration.</note> In view agreement for establishment refugee
                        center Morocco, cable us authority from AFHQ for transportation from U.S.
                        for one administrative <pb facs="0393" n="383" xml:id="pg_383"/> officer,
                        two nurses, one nutritionist, two stenographers, and one port and
                        transportation officer,—all for refugee center. This personnel will be sent
                        when we receive notice from you. Cable was recently sent British requesting
                        them to furnish initially one doctor, two nurses, one recreational organizer
                        and one person with experience in camp operations. Advise Hoehler when they
                        will be needed.</p>
                    <p>Beckelman<note n="54" xml:id="d391fn54">Moses William Beckelman,
                            representative of the Office of Foreign Relief and Rehabilitation
                            Operations.</note> is directed to communicate with Hayes regarding
                        advisability his going to Spain to canvass situation with refugees. In this
                        connection we feel it very desirable refugees should understand fully nature
                        and conditions of center and accept before they leave Spain.</p>
                    <p>Fryer indicates following steps in completing final arrangements for center: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Official designation of Camp Marshal Lyautey and its assignment by
                                Army for purposes refugee center.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Confirm arrangements previously made with Army for necessary
                                equipment and supplies and advise us accordingly.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Renew arrangements for temporary assignment of automotive and
                                truck transportation. Passenger cars from here for center have been
                                shipped and trucks already purchased and awaiting shipment.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed> [Fryer and Latimer.] <lb/>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>