<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summary of the Proceedings of the Fifth Session of the Tripartite Conference,
                    October 23, 1943, 4 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d587</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">587</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-10-23T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-10-23T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7MjCJlGL6L85Od" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Joint statement</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recmcLXlokIhw3k5j" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recoyEZyJxNLXsgki" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016002167"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Guerrilla</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-10-23T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-10-23T08:00:00-05:00" n="587"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d587">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Moscow/10–1843</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary of the Proceedings of the Fifth Session of the
                        Tripartite Conference, October 23, 1943, 4 p.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1943-10-23T16:00:00+03:00">October 23, 1943, 4 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> opened the session by designating Mr.
                    Vyshinski and Mr. Golonski, an official of the Soviet Foreign Office, as Soviet
                    representatives on the Drafting Committee. He then inquired whether there were
                    any proposals in regard to articles 1 and 2 of the Joint Agreement and stated
                    that in his understanding items 3 and 4 were to be referred to the Drafting
                    Committee, as item 2 had already been. The Secretary and Mr. Eden agreed that it
                    would be desirable to refer items 3 and 4 to the Drafting Committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> then suggested that we consider the Soviet
                    proposals in regard to Italy.<note n="55" xml:id="d587fn55">Conference Document
                        No. 13, <ref target="#pg_714">p. 714</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> replied that he thought it better to await
                    instructions from his Government and that in the meantime he had turned in to
                    the Conference a joint statement together with the United States Delegation of
                    Allied policies up to the present in Italy.<note n="56" xml:id="d587fn56"
                        >Conference Document No. 15, <ref target="#pg_715">p. 715</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that he likewise had transmitted
                    the Soviet proposals on Italy to his Government but that he could say that in
                    his opinion they were very much in line with the political philosophy of the
                    United States and other members of the United Nations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> then suggested that the second part of
                    item 4 dealing with the Balkans be discussed.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> then read a statement in regard to the
                    British attitude toward the resistance movement in Yugoslavia. He said that the
                    long-term desire of the British Government was to see Yugoslavia restored to her
                    former freedom and independence with the preservation of the three kingdoms of
                    Serbia, Croatia and Slovenia. He said that the British had been in touch with
                    both of the main resistant groups in Yugoslavia, Mikhailović<note n="57"
                        xml:id="d587fn57">Gen. Draža Mihailović, Leader of the Yugoslav Nationalist
                        guerrilla forces.</note> and the Partisans.<note n="58" xml:id="d587fn58"
                        >The Yugoslav Communist guerrilla forces, led by Marshal Tito (Josip Broz).
                        For related documents on this subject, see vol. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >ii</hi>, section under Yugoslavia entitled “Concern of the United States
                        regarding disunity among Yugoslav resistance forces.” See also Sir Llewellyn
                        Woodward, <hi rend="italic">British Foreign Policy in the Second World
                            War</hi> (London, Her Majesty’s Stationery Office, 1962), <ref
                            target="#pg_332">pp. 332</ref> ff.</note> When he had been in Cairo he
                    had discussed with King Peter<note n="59" xml:id="d587fn59">Peter II, King of
                        Yugoslavia.</note> and the Yugoslav Government the attitude toward
                    Mikhailović and had said that the British Government’s chief desire was to have
                    him actively engage in operations against the enemies Germany and Bulgaria. He
                    had outlined to the King two operations which the British would like to see
                    Mikhailović carry out, namely the destruction of the Bor copper mines and the
                    cutting of the strategic railroad between Belgrade and <pb facs="0628" n="618"
                        xml:id="pg_618"/> Nishi. King Peter had promised that if at this Conference
                    a common policy in regard to Yugoslavia could be agreed upon he would send
                    immediate orders to Mikhailović to carry out these operations for which it was
                    believed he had adequate forces. It was made quite plain to the King that if
                    these orders were not carried out the British Government would have to
                    reconsider its attitude toward Mikhailović and the question of sending him
                    further supplies. Mr. Eden added that the British were continuing to supply the
                    Partisans and it was hoped in the near future that more ample supplies could be
                    sent by the Adriatic. Mr. Eden then outlined his proposals which were simply
                    that efforts be made to unite the two factions in the common struggle against
                    Germany and to prevent in the future their fighting each other. He said that he
                    thought this would be possible since they were operating in different areas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that he had nothing to add to the
                    statements of Mr. Eden at this time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> said he likewise had little to add,
                    particularly as it was the first time that he had heard of the suggested two
                    operations and he would like to have more time to consider the question. He then
                    stated that he had understood that under item 4 there was to be a discussion of
                    the general situation in the Balkans since the specific question of resistance
                    movements in Yugoslavia was provided for in item 16.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> replied that he had given out this
                    information as he thought it would be of value to the Soviet Delegation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> said he would study the British statement
                    and it could be discussed when item 16 on the Agenda was reached.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> said that in regard to general policy the
                    British aim was to assist guerrilla bands in that area in their struggle against
                    the German occupying forces and whenever possible to prevent these bands from
                    fighting among themselves; that the British had had officers in touch with Greek
                    guerrilla bands who up until recently had been cooperating with each other, but
                    that very lately this agreement had broken down and he felt that efforts should
                    be made to patch it up. He said that the Italian attitude in the Balkan
                    countries had varied a great deal, that in some places such as the island of
                    Corfu the Italians had joined wholeheartedly with the Greeks in fighting the
                    Germans but this was not uniformly true in other parts. He went on to say that
                    Rumania had recently approached the British Government in regard to the
                    possibility of separate peace but he felt that that had better be considered
                    under the specific item of the Agenda dealing with such peace feelers. Mr. Eden
                    added that they had very little information with regard to Bulgaria and hoped to
                    obtain some from their Soviet colleagues. The only thing that <pb facs="0629"
                        n="619" xml:id="pg_619"/> they did know was that Bulgarian divisions had
                    relieved German forces in northern Greece and northern Serbia.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that in this connection he would
                    like General Deane to be permitted to make a statement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Deane</hi> said that the United States Chief of
                    Staff considered that there was great opportunity in the Balkans, particularly
                    during the winter months, to intensify sabotage and disruptive work in order to
                    undermine German military strength. He said that the Office of Strategic
                    Services had the equipment and trained personnel to carry on this work and was
                    prepared to penetrate the area by air or other means. He said that the American
                    Military authorities hoped that this would be agreeable to the Soviet Government
                    and he wished to assure them that the purpose of these operations was purely
                    military.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> inquired whether it would be possible to
                    get a clearer picture of the operations envisaged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Deane</hi> answered that it was somewhat difficult
                    since all such operations were of necessity opportunistic, but that the Office
                    of Strategic Services had done very valuable work in other countries.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that he would like to postpone
                    that question until another session since he would like to have more information
                    on that point.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> said that if it would be agreeable to Mr.
                    Molotov he would ask General Ismay to submit a paper on sabotage activities in
                    the Balkans.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>, then turning to the establishment of a
                    Politico-Military Commission in London and machinery for carrying out the
                    Italian terms of surrender, said he would like to propose that these two
                    questions be separated and to deal first with the Italian aspect.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> inquired how the economic phase was to
                    be brought into the work of these commissions.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that the economic question had not
                    yet been raised but he saw no reason for necessarily excluding such questions.
                    He emphasized, however, that the situation with regard to Italy was urgent since
                    the Soviet Government had no representative on the spot. He proposed therefore
                    that in accordance with Mr. Eden’s suggestion of October 17 and his remarks on
                    October 22<note n="60" xml:id="d587fn60">For latter, see summary of the fourth
                        session of the Conference, October 22, <ref target="#pg_604">p.
                        604</ref>.</note> the Advisory Council of High Commissioners in regard to
                    Italy be set up at once. He said that if we could agree on this basis the
                    question might be referred to the Drafting Committee.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> said that he fully shared the desire of Mr.
                    Molotov to see a Soviet representative in Italy as soon as possible and that he
                    had <pb facs="0630" n="620" xml:id="pg_620"/> already recommended that the
                    Advisory Council be set up at once without waiting for the end of the so-called
                    first period in Italy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> stated that he had received information
                    that his Government had already commenced action along those lines.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> stated that the name of the commission was
                    of course not of vital importance but that there might be some advantage in
                    having the commission with regard to Italy called the Politico-Military
                    Commission since that designation had already been widely used by the press, but
                    that the main thing was to expedite the setting up of a commission in Italy, and
                    he again proposed to submit it to the Drafting Committee. This was agreed to by
                    the Conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> then proposed an intermission, but before
                    doing so said he had the pleasure of announcing that the town of Melitopol had
                    been captured by the Soviet armies.</p>
                <postscript>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> proposed that the terms of reference
                        of both the Italian commission and the London commission should be agreed
                        upon here and he proposed to accept as a basis the British memorandum of
                        July 1, taking into account the observations which Mr. Eden had made at the
                        previous session. He added that if the Secretary considered the British
                        draft of July 1 acceptable it would be referred to the Drafting
                        Committee.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that this question could be
                        referred to the Committee and that from the results of their work we would
                        be able to make our recommendations and decisions.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> said that in his view the only difficulty
                        of using the memorandum of July 1 was that it dealt only with the question
                        of the terms of armistice for the ending of hostilities in Europe.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> replied that such was not his
                        impression and he had given very careful study to the contents of the
                        document.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> replied that the contents of the
                        memorandum of July 1 referred to conditions after the war whereas he had in
                        mind for the Politico-Military Commission in London consideration of current
                        questions such as the peace feelers from satellite states and other
                        political questions affecting Europe.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> answered that in our work we should
                        endeavor to improve and not worsen the memorandum of July 1, but that he
                        felt that if the powers of the Politico-Military Commission in London were
                        made too broad there would be no work left for the Foreign Ministers and
                        that personally he saw merit in the proposals advanced by the Secretary
                        yesterday that there be tripartite meetings utilizing existing diplomatic
                        machinery in the capitals of our three countries under the presidency of the
                        Foreign Minister of the capital selected <pb facs="0631" n="621"
                            xml:id="pg_621"/> and with the participation of the Ambassadors of the
                        other two countries. He went on to say that the London mission might well
                        start with the consideration of the preparation of armistice terms but that
                        perhaps some combination of the British and United States proposals could be
                        worked out on this. It was then agreed to turn over the question to the
                        Drafting Committee on the basis of the British memorandum of July 1.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> said that he had only just received
                        the United States proposals in regard to the treatment of Germany<note
                            n="61" xml:id="d587fn61">Conference Document No. 20, <ref
                                target="#pg_720">p. 720</ref>.</note> and wished to have time to
                        study it and prepare Russian translations and therefore wished to postpone
                        consideration of this question until a later session.</p>
                    <p>It was agreed that the Conference would discuss items 7 and 8 and possibly 10
                        and 12 at the next session, which was set for 3 p.m. on the following
                        day.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
