<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-10-23T14:05:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-10-23T14:05:00-05:00" n="588" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d588">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The British Prime Minister</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Churchill</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                            </hi><note n="62" type="source" xml:id="d588fn62">Copy of telegram
                                obtained from the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Hyde Park,
                                N.Y.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-10-23T20:05:00+01:00">23 October
                                    1943—8:05 p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>472. From Former Naval Person. My immediately preceding telegram.<note n="63" xml:id="d588fn63">In his telegram No. 471, October 23,
                                Churchill said: “I send you in my immediately following extracts
                                from a telegram I have sent to Eden who asked for guidance about the
                                Russian wish to bring Turkey and Sweden immediately into the war. I
                                wonder what you think on these subjects?” No record has been found
                                of a reply by Roosevelt.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Following are extracts from telegram I have sent to Eden. (Begins). Your
                            number 48.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Para 5: Turkey. If we force Turkey to enter the war she will
                                insist on air support, etc., which could not be provided without
                                detriment to main operations in Italy. If however Turkey enters on
                                her own initiative, perhaps moving through a phase of
                                non-belligerency, we should not have the same obligation and yet
                                great advantages might be reaped. Obviously timing is vital and
                                dependent upon what is the aggressive strength of the enemy in
                                Bulgaria and Thrace. The prize would be to get into the Black Sea
                                with supplies for Russia, warships and other forces. This is what I
                                call giving Russia the right hand. Such a movement by Turkey is not
                                impossible, especially if the Germans should begin to cut their
                                losses in the Balkans and withdraw towards the Danube and the
                                Sava.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Finland and Sweden. It would be a great advantage to bring Sweden
                                into the war. We do not think the Germans have the strength to
                                undertake a heavy invasion of Sweden. We should gain a new <pb facs="0632" n="622" xml:id="pg_622"/> country and small but good
                                army. Our gains in Norway would be far-reaching. Valuable facilities
                                would be afforded to Russian Air Forces. For ourselves, we can do
                                far better bombing of Germany from East Anglia where we are mounted
                                on a vast scale than from Sweden where everything would have to be
                                improvised and imported by air. Our range from England over Germany
                                is just as good as from Sweden. In fact with present British
                                facilities plus those we hope to acquire North of Rome there is no
                                part of Germany we cannot reach with great weight.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Personally I would like to see Turkey come in on her own and also
                                Sweden. I do not think either of them would be overrun, and every
                                new enemy helps Hitler’s ruin. I suggest however that the first step
                                is to find out what we and the Russians want and what will help both
                                of us most in both quarters, and then as a second step go into ways
                                and means immediately thereafter. Try this, and let me know.
                                (Ends)</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>