<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Summary of the Proceedings of the Twelfth Session of the Tripartite
                    Conference, October 30, 1943, 4 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d615</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">615</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-10-30T08:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-10-30T08:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec8b79a8b95ce4a65" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="atlantic-charter">Atlantic Charter</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-10-30T08:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-10-30T08:00:00-05:00" n="615"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d615">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Moscow/10–1843</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary of the Proceedings of the Twelfth Session of the
                        Tripartite Conference, October 30, 1943, 4 p.m.</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1943-10-30T16:00:00+03:00">October 30, 1943, 4 p.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <p>In opening the last formal session of the Conference, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                        Molotov</hi> said there remained the following questions for consideration:
                    (1) the report of the Drafting Committee on the Commissions to be set up; (2)
                    the question of the press communiqué; (3) the Protocol of the Conference to be
                    signed by the three Foreign Secretaries; (4) the time when the communiqué and
                    public declarations were to be released; and (5) the report of the Committee for
                    Iran.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> stated that he would like to say a few words
                    in regard to points 1 and 4 of the declaration regarding general European
                    responsibility as against spheres of separate responsibility.<note n="34c"
                        xml:id="d615fn34c">See Conference Document No. 31, <ref target="#pg_736">p.
                            736</ref>.</note> He said he thought that the principles expressed in
                    points 1 and 4 would be a valuable addition to the work of the Conference if
                    they could be published.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> said that he had understood that Mr. Eden
                    had withdrawn his proposal on this question, to which <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                        Eden</hi> replied that <pb facs="0690" n="680" xml:id="pg_680"/> he had in
                    fact withdrawn his suggestion to embody points 1 and 4 in the Four-Nation
                    Declaration merely to facilitate the final adoption of the latter document.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Litvinov</hi> then said that in his opinion the
                    principles set forth in points 1 and 4 of the British document in question were
                    already embodied in the Atlantic Charter, and since there was no evidence that
                    any of the three powers here was seeking special areas of responsibility or
                    influence he felt that to make a special declaration denying this would give
                    rise to the belief that there had been some such intention on the part of one of
                    the three countries here represented. He also inquired why it was confined only
                    to Europe.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> answered that he felt that there was greater
                    suspicion in that regard on the part of the small nations of Europe, but added
                    that he did not feel he could press the point if there was any objection.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that he was agreeably disposed
                    toward Mr. Eden’s suggestion but he wondered whether there was sufficient time
                    at this closing session of the Conference to consider the question. It was then
                    agreed by the Conference to postpone Mr. Eden’s suggestion until the next
                    conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Vyshinski</hi> on behalf of the Drafting Committee said
                    that there had been agreement on all the documents submitted to the Committee
                    with the exception of a few minor points in the draft concerning the Advisory
                    Council for Italy and in the draft of the document regarding peace feelers.<note
                        n="34d" xml:id="d615fn34d">See Conference Documents Nos. 11, 33, and 34,
                            <ref target="#pg_712">pp. 712</ref>, <ref target="#pg_737">737</ref>,
                        and <ref target="#pg_738">738</ref>, respectively.</note> In regard to the
                    Italian Advisory Council he said there was some difference as to the wording of
                    the last paragraph which dealt with the time of putting into effect the agreed
                    policy in regard to Italy, since the Soviet draft provided that the
                    Commander-in-Chief would only take action in this sphere on the basis of
                    instructions from the combined Chiefs of Staff after consultation between the
                    three Governments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> proposed an amendment to alter the last
                    sentence of the last paragraph to read after the words “Chiefs of Staff”: period
                    (punctuation), and the following additional sentence: “The three Governments
                    parties to this declaration will at the request of any one of them consult on
                    this matter.” Mr. Molotov and Mr. Eden accepted the Secretary’s amendment.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> then said that in the declaration regarding
                    common policy toward Italy,<note n="34e" xml:id="d615fn34e">See Conference
                        Documents Nos. 13 and 14, <ref target="#pg_714">pp. 714</ref> and <ref
                            target="#pg_715">715</ref>, respectively.</note> he would like to
                    eliminate from paragraphs 3 and 4 the words that would indicate that there had
                    been some failure on the part of the British and American Governments to uproot
                    Fascism. He said that to leave those words in would carry an implied censure of
                    Allied policy in Italy which he thought was undeserved.</p>
                <pb facs="0691" n="681" xml:id="pg_681"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> said he felt that the Soviet wording in
                    paragraphs 3 and 4 of the declaration on Italy merely reflected the actual facts
                    since he understood that there were some Fascist institutions such as sport
                    organizations still in existence. He agreed, however, in deference to Mr. Eden
                    and Mr. Hull to eliminate these references as requested.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> in regard to the declaration on German
                        atrocities<note n="34f" xml:id="d615fn34f">See Conference Document No. 40,
                            <ref target="#pg_741">p. 741</ref>.</note> then stated that it was not
                    clear in the Russian text whether the names of the three Heads of Government
                    were to appear.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that he understood that it was to
                    be issued under the name of President Roosevelt, Prime Minister Churchill and
                    Marshal Stalin; that it was their desire that it be merely made public by the
                    Conference.</p>
                <p>In reporting on the draft of the peace feelers agreement <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr.
                        Vyshinski</hi> said that there was some difference of opinion as to the
                    wording of the paragraph concerning the applicability of the principle of
                    unconditional surrender by satellite states to those of the three Powers with
                    which they were at war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that he felt there would be some
                    objection on the part of the United States Government to the present wording
                    since it was obvious that the United States could not recommend unconditional
                    surrender for countries with which it was not at war.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> pointed out in this connection that the
                    principle of unconditional surrender was set forth in the preamble to the
                    Four-Nation Declaration and that therefore there was no inconsistency in
                    including it in the proposed agreement on peace feelers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> replied that he felt the general spirit
                    of the Four-Nation Declaration took care of that but that he would be glad to
                    consider the inclusion in the peace feeler draft of the exact wording used in
                    the preamble to the Four-Nation Declaration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> then said that the Soviet Government
                    interpreted the statement about unconditional surrender under discussion as
                    meaning that the United States would morally support the Soviet Union and Great
                    Britain as against Finland, and that the Soviet Union would give moral support
                    to the United States and Great Britain as against Bulgaria.</p>
                <p>After some further discussion on this point <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi>
                    agreed to resubmit it to the Drafting Committee and if an acceptable wording
                    could not be found the whole paragraph might be dropped. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >The Secretary</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> agreed to this
                    proposal.</p>
                <p>Following the intermission it was decided to sign the Four-Nation Declaration as
                    soon as the Russian and English texts had been compared and that the Chinese
                    Ambassador would be brought into the <pb facs="0692" n="682" xml:id="pg_682"/>
                    Conference Room for this purpose. While waiting for the texts to be compared the
                    Conference discussed the question of the exact time of the release.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi>
                    said they would like to see the British and American correspondents in Moscow
                    given an opportunity to send their stories several hours in advance of the
                    official announcement in order to assure simultaneous publication in the three
                    capitals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> said he was afraid that if this were done
                    the Germans would pick up the stories which would go by radio and would announce
                    to the world some garbled version before the official release. It. was agreed
                    that the press representatives of the three delegations should meet and agree on
                    the time and method of release and the time of making available to the British
                    and American correspondents the documents to be published.</p>
                <p>At 6:30 p.m., October 30, 1943, the three Foreign Secretaries and the Chinese
                    Ambassador at Moscow<note n="35" xml:id="d615fn35">Foo Ping-sheung.</note>
                    signed the Four-Nation Declaration. Soviet newsreel cameramen took pictures of
                    the ceremony.</p>
                <p>After the signature the Conference turned to the question of the report of the
                    Committee on Iran.<note n="35a" xml:id="d615fn35a">Conference Document No. 30,
                            <ref target="#pg_736">p. 736</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> proposed that the Conference refer this
                    question for discussion in Moscow by Mr. Molotov and the British and American
                    Ambassadors on the basis of a resolution on Iran which he presented to the
                    Conference (copy attached).<note n="36" xml:id="d615fn36">Presumably enclosure 1
                        to Conference Document No. 27, <ref target="#pg_732">p. 732</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> said he was agreeable to Mr. Eden’s
                    suggestion to refer the question to diplomatic channels but he felt that Tehran
                    might be a more suitable place than Moscow.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that he also felt that Tehran might
                    be more suitable since all materials and data on the subject would be there and
                    the diplomatic representatives of the three countries might be more closely in
                    touch with the local situation. It was agreed that no publicity would be given
                    to the resolution on Iran and that further discussions would take place between
                    the diplomatic representatives of the three powers in Tehran.</p>
                <p>In closing the Conference of the three Foreign Secretaries in Moscow, <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mr. Molotov</hi> expressed warm appreciation of the
                    unfailing cooperation which he had received from the Secretary and Mr. Eden and
                    to which he in large measure attributed the success of the Conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Secretary</hi> said that he was sure he was expressing
                    Mr. Eden’s sentiments when he said that he had never seen a better example of
                    skill and cooperation than Mr. Molotov had displayed during the <pb facs="0693"
                        n="683" xml:id="pg_683"/> Conference. He said that he had attended many
                    international conferences but he had never encountered one where the spirit of
                    cooperation and genuine desire to produce fruitful work had been more manifest
                    than at this meeting. This he attributed for the most part to Mr. Molotov’s able
                    direction of the work. He also thanked Mr. Molotov for the unfailing hospitality
                    and the many kindnesses which he and members of the American Delegation had
                    received throughout from the Soviet authorities.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Eden</hi> warmly seconded the Secretary’s remarks and
                    proposed that at any future meetings of the three Foreign Secretaries Mr.
                    Molotov be selected as permanent Chairman.</p>
                <p>The Conference ended on this note.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
