<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-10-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="666" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d666">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Moscow/10–1943</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adrian Holman</persName> of
                                the British Delegation to Mr. <persName type="to">John D.
                                    Jernegan</persName> of the American Delegation</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-10-25">25 October,
                                1943</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">Conference Document No. 27</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Jernegan</hi>: I enclose two copies of each of
                            two draft Declarations with respect to Allied policy in Iran which the
                            British Delegation wish to submit as a basis of discussion by the
                            sub-Committee on Iran.</p>
                        <p>Copies have been sent also the Soviet Delegation.</p>
                        <p>Yours sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Adrian Holman</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Draft Declaration No. 1</hi>
                            </head>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Governments of the U.S.S.R., the U.S.A. and the United
                                    Kingdom having in mind the adherence of the Government of Iran
                                    to the cause of the United Nations rely with confidence upon the
                                    desire <pb facs="0743" n="733" xml:id="pg_733"/> of the
                                    Government and people of Iran to make their contribution along
                                    the most effective lines in furtherance of the struggle against
                                    the common enemy.</p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The Government of the U.S.S.R., the U.S.A., and the United
                                        Kingdom undertake for their part to do all within their
                                        power to safeguard the people of Iran from the privations
                                        and difficulties which the present war must bring to them in
                                        common with all other peoples engaged in the conflict. They
                                        further undertake to collaborate closely with each other and
                                        to cooperate with the Government of Iran on all issues as
                                        they arise with a view to the furtherance of the United
                                        Nations’ war effort. They also undertake to give full moral
                                        support in any way acceptable to the Government of Iran to
                                        the efforts of the various individuals, groups and agencies,
                                        whether Iranian or foreign, which are endeavouring to
                                        relieve the existing economic difficulties of the country
                                        and to improve security through the strengthening of Iranian
                                        Governmental authority.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The three Governments similarly undertake to effect as
                                        soon as possible after the cessation of hostilities the
                                        withdrawal or the reduction to a normal peace time
                                        establishment of such non-military Governmental
                                        organisations as are now operating in Iran in connection
                                        with the United Nations’ war effort.”</item>
                                </list>
                            </quote>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Draft Declaration No. 2</hi>
                            </head>
                            <p>Under Articles 1 and 5 of the Treaty of Alliance between the United
                                Kingdom and the Soviet Union and Iran of January 29th, 1942, the
                                Governments of the United Kingdom and the U.S.S.R. undertake to
                                respect the territorial integrity, sovereignty and political
                                independence of Iran and to withdraw their forces from Iranian
                                territory not later than six months after all hostilities between
                                the Allied Powers and Germany and her associates have been suspended
                                by the conclusion of an armistice or armistices or on the conclusion
                                of peace between them, whichever date is earlier.</p>
                            <p>The Governments of the United Kingdom and the U.S.S.R. now desire to
                                take this opportunity of declaring that the undertakings given to
                                the Government of Iran in the foregoing paragraph still continue to
                                constitute the basis of their policy towards Iran, which has in no
                                way changed since the conclusion of the Tripartite Treaty.
                                Furthermore the two Governments affirm their intention of reducing
                                in the meantime their military commitments in Iran as quickly as
                                their general military situation permits.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>