<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-02-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-02-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="775" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d775">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50/1590</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Discussion in the Office of the Assistant
                            Secretary of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Acheson</hi>), <hi rend="italic">February 17, 1943</hi>
                    </head>
                    <dateline>
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1943-02-17">February 17,
                            1943</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <p>The British Ambassador, the Soviet Ambassador and the Chinese Ambassador met
                        with Mr. Acheson to discuss further the points raised by their Governments
                        with reference to the draft plan for the establishment of the United Nations
                        Relief and Rehabilitation Administration. Mr. Noel Hall, British Minister,
                        Mr. Liu Chieh, Minister and Counselor of the Chinese Embassy, and Mr. Roy
                        Veatch of the Department of State also were present.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Acheson referred to the discussion of the same group, on January 11,
                        1943, at which time consideration was given to certain points with respect
                        to the proposed draft agreement which had been raised by the British, Soviet
                        and Chinese Governments. He mentioned the British Ambassador’s letter of
                        January 24, 1943 in further comment upon some of the points discussed on
                        January 11, and said that the Soviet Ambassador had now received further
                        instructions from his Government on those points. The Soviet Embassy’s
                        memorandum of February 16, 1943 was then read and Mr. Acheson also read the
                        substance of the Canadian Legation’s memorandum of February 9, 1943 setting
                        forth the attitude of the Canadian Government on some of the issues
                        involved.</p>
                    <p>At the suggestion of the British Ambassador, the points at issue in the draft
                        agreement were discussed seriatim. The following is a résumé of that
                        discussion:</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">1. The Soviet Government’s proposal that Article I should be
                        so amended as to require the consent of the government of the state
                        receiving relief as regards the forms these activities may take in that
                        state, and as to admit of ways by which the government of <pb facs="0880" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/> the country receiving relief may undertake the
                        whole responsibility for relief measures within its territory.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Litvinov called attention to his Government’s statement in the
                        memorandum of February 16, 1943 that it was not intended to extend this
                        formula to enemy countries, which is a question deserving special
                        consideration. He said that his Government was concerned regarding the
                        position of recognized governments which would be members of the proposed
                        Administration, with respect to the degree of control which they might
                        exercise over relief measures within their territories—his Government’s
                        concern extended beyond its own territories.</p>
                    <p>The discussion led to a clarification of the Soviet Government’s suggestion.
                        Ambassador Litvinov emphasized the use of the word “admit” in the second
                        part of the proposal, pointing out that it was not the intention to require
                        or make mandatory the granting of full responsibility for relief measures to
                        any government which might desire such responsibility. He explained that it
                        was the concern of his Government to keep open the possibility of such full
                        responsibility for relief measures. He recognized the necessity for
                        agreement between the government in question and the United Nations
                        Administration with respect to methods of administering relief in the
                        territory of that government, pointing out that the Administration itself
                        would have the power to decide whether any relief should be granted to that
                        area. He suggested that all member governments should clearly have the
                        right, under the agreement, to advance proposals with respect to the
                        administration of relief in their territories, including the possibility of
                        full responsibility for such administration, but he recognized that in
                        making such proposals a member government would be required to make its
                        case, that the Policy Committee would have to have some criteria for judging
                        the soundness of that case, and that the Director General would need to have
                        access to pertinent facts concerning the situation for submission to the
                        Policy Committee.</p>
                    <p>While recognizing that the second part of the Soviet Government’s proposal
                        was not so worded as to be mandatory, Mr. Acheson pointed out that the first
                        part of that proposal was mandatory, giving the government receiving relief
                        a veto on the forms which the relief activities might take in the territory
                        in question. In his opinion such an arrangement would in effect give each
                        government the power to insist upon undertaking the whole responsibility for
                        relief measures within its territory since it would be able to veto any
                        other arrangement as unsatisfactory to itself. He suggested, therefore, that
                        Article I might be so worded as to give the mandatory power to any member
                        government to say whether it would wish to receive relief and rehabilitation
                        assistance or not and beyond that to provide or “admit” ways <pb facs="0881" n="871" xml:id="pg_871"/> in which a member government in actual control
                        should be able to determine in agreement with the Administration the forms
                        and methods of administering relief within its territory.</p>
                    <p>Lord Halifax saw no objection to agreement to the suggestion made by the
                        Soviet Government since as a practical matter he felt that the
                        Administration would have adequate bargaining power in reaching an agreement
                        on such questions in as much as it would be in a position to withhold relief
                        assistance if it felt that the forms of distribution proposed by any
                        government would not be satisfactory. He went on to say, however, that
                        paragraph two of Article IV, or some other provision of the draft, should be
                        so worded as to require consultation and collaboration with the governments
                        of the affected areas. Some escape clause would be needed to cover
                        territories in which no recognized civilian government existed or cases in
                        which even recognized governments might not have effective control of the
                        territory.</p>
                    <p>The suggestion was made that the Policy Committee should have the power to
                        determine whether the government of a given territory, even though
                        recognized by the Allies, was in effective control of that territory.
                        Ambassador Wei and Mr. Liu expressed the opinion, however, that it might be
                        dangerous to place with the Policy Committee the power to decide whether a
                        given government was an “effective” government; in their opinion the
                        important question would be whether the government was recognized or
                        not.</p>
                    <p>Lord Halifax thought that there might be cases in which recognized
                        governments were not in a position to make decisions for the territory over
                        which they had nominal sovereignty, and Ambassador Litvinov agreed that in
                        cases where a recognized government was not in control of its territory, the
                        Policy Committee would have to determine the authority with which the
                        Administration should deal.</p>
                    <p>It was agreed that Mr. Acheson should draft such provisions as would give
                        effect to the Soviet Government’s suggestions on this point, as developed by
                        the discussion outlined above.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">2. The Soviet Government’s suggestion, as set forth in the
                        Soviet Embassy’s memorandum of February 16, 1943, that the control of the
                        Policy Committee over the Committee on Supplies should be made explicit in
                        the proposed new paragraph four of Article III.</p>
                    <p>It was agreed that the object of the Soviet Government’s suggestion would be
                        achieved through substituting the word “recommend” for the word “report” in
                        the third sentence of the draft of that paragraph. It was thought that this
                        change would clarify the relationship between the Committee on Supplies and
                        the Policy Committee and the Council, emphasizing the fact that the
                        Committee on Supplies could only propose or recommend policies, final
                        decision resting with the Policy Committee and the Council.</p>
                    <pb facs="0882" n="872" xml:id="pg_872"/>
                    <p>It was also agreed, in response to Ambassador Litvinov’s suggestion, that the
                        order of the wording of this sentence should be changed so that the
                        Committee on Supplies should recommend “to the Policy Committee and the
                        Council”.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">3. Suggestions of the British Government with respect to the
                        wording of the proposed new paragraph four of Article III, concerning the
                        Committee on Supplies.</p>
                    <p>Lord Halifax and Mr. Hall suggested that the third sentence of the proposed
                        paragraph should be so worded as to require the transmission of
                        recommendations of the Committee on Supplies through the Director General to
                        the Policy Committee and Council, and so as to eliminate the word
                        “procurement”. It was their feeling that the responsibility of the Director
                        General as the channel for communications by the Committees should be made
                        explicit and that the wording should preclude any possibility of an
                        assumption that the Committee on Supplies itself would have anything to do
                        with procurement.</p>
                    <p>There was general sympathy with the British observation on the first point
                        and it was agreed that this could be achieved best through a new paragraph
                        under Article IV specifying the Director General’s responsibility for
                        serving as a means of communication between committees and for maintaining
                        records and files of such communications and of all action taken by the
                        Council and its committees.</p>
                    <p>It was agreed that the second point raised by the British Government with
                        respect to this sentence could be met by rewording the sentence in question
                        substantially as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“It shall consider, formulate and recommend to the Policy Committee
                                and the Council policies designed to ensure the provision and
                                distribution of required materials and their continued flow from
                                available sources of supply to areas of need”.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">4. The British Government’s proposal that the membership of
                        the Policy Committee be expanded to seven so as to include Canada and one
                        European Ally.</p>
                    <p>Lord Halifax reported that his Government still felt strongly that this
                        modification should be made. He had been impressed with and had reported
                        Ambassador Litvinov’s reference to the possibility that a decision in this
                        case might set a pattern for international organization in other spheres.
                        His Government had replied that there was a distinction between political
                        and economic subjects and that in the field of relief and rehabilitation it
                        would be possible to provide for a Policy Committee of seven without
                        prejudicing later decisions in other fields.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Litvinov said that the instructions from his Government, as set
                        forth in the memorandum of February 16, contained the same insistence on a
                        Policy Committee of four as provided in the draft agreement.</p>
                    <pb facs="0883" n="873" xml:id="pg_873"/>
                    <p>Ambassador Wei said that he had been instructed to say that his Government
                        supported the arrangement in the draft agreement, for a Policy Committee of
                        four.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Acheson said that, although the United States Government recognized that
                        strong arguments could be made in favor of both positions, it considered it
                        best, in view of the difference of opinion, to continue with the plan for a
                        Policy Committee of four. He said that the importance of Canada to the
                        scheme was recognized, and that the desire of Canada to be a member of the
                        Policy Committee was given considerable weight, that the United States would
                        like to do everything possible to meet Canada’s position, but that it felt
                        that any extension of the membership of the Policy Committee would create
                        difficult new problems. He believed that there was some misapprehension on
                        the part of the Canadian Government with respect to the powers of the Policy
                        Committee; he hoped that the Canadians would understand that the Council
                        would have the fullest possible discussions of policy at its semi-annual
                        meetings, and that the Supplies and regional committees of the Council would
                        be in constant session to give full consideration to policy matters
                        affecting them.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Acheson said that his Government was not opposing a Policy Committee of
                        seven as a matter of principle, but that it was concerned over the necessity
                        of securing rapid progress in establishing the proposed United Nations
                        Administration. Three of the four Powers were now in agreement on a Policy
                        Committee of four and he hoped that it would be possible for all four to
                        move forward on that basis.</p>
                    <p>Lord Halifax was in full agreement on the urgency of moving forward. He
                        inquired whether the question of the membership of the Policy Committee
                        could be left for the general meeting of the United Nations or for the first
                        meeting of the Council to decide. This arrangement might avoid the
                        possibility of forcing through an agreement which would be jealously
                        regarded and only grudgingly accepted by many of the smaller nations.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Litvinov expressed the fear that the conference of the United
                        Nations and the Council would not only favor a Policy Committee of seven
                        rather than four but would be led to a considerable extension of the
                        number.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Acheson expressed his conviction that the four Powers must be in
                        agreement when the full United Nations meeting takes place if discord and
                        the possibility of permanent harm to the program are to be avoided. He said
                        that in his opinion the question of membership on the Policy Committee was
                        not so important as appeared at first glance because of the necessary
                        relationship of that Committee and its functions to other committees and
                        their functions. In his view there were three main functions to be
                        performed: (1) The provision of supplies, in which the Director General and
                        the Committee on <pb facs="0884" n="874" xml:id="pg_874"/> Supplies must
                        take the leading role; (2) determination of requirements, in which the
                        Director General and his deputies would work largely with the regional
                        committees; (3) coordination and adjustment of these two, which should be
                        secured largely through the Council and the Policy Committee. He believed
                        that the European Allies would have very little to do with the function of
                        supplying and in the coordination of the supply program with requirements;
                        and he pointed out that in any event they were represented on the Council
                        and had the right to sit with the Policy Committee when the problems of
                        their respective countries were considered.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Litvinov expressed the wish that Lord Halifax would place this
                        problem before his Government again pointing out the fact of agreement
                        between the Soviet, Chinese and United States Governments on a Policy
                        Committee of four.</p>
                    <p>Lord Halifax said that he was certain that his Government would not wish to
                        be the cause of delay in moving forward and that it would be willing to have
                        the draft agreement, as it now stands on this point, submitted to the other
                        United Nations, with the understanding that the British Government would not
                        consider itself committed to pressing for a Policy Committee of four members
                        if subsequent discussions should prove a majority of the United Nations to
                        be strongly of a contrary opinion. Lord Halifax and Ambassador Wei were
                        forced to withdraw at that point, but Lord Halifax said that Mr. Hall was
                        fully informed of the British Government’s position and was empowered to
                        continue the discussions in the place of the Ambassador.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Hall explained that the British Government had been convinced at the
                        beginning that a Policy Committee of four members would be the most workable
                        arrangement; his Government had been led to press for an enlargement of the
                        membership only because of its desire to get the scheme accepted by all of
                        the United Nations involved. In order to facilitate progress the British
                        Government is now willing to go ahead, however, with general discussion of
                        the draft as it now stands on this point. Nevertheless the British
                        Government expects widespread opposition to this arrangement and suggests,
                        therefore, that the four powers consult again shortly before the scheduled
                        conference so that they may, at that time, reconsider the matter in the
                        light of the responses of other governments received in the meantime.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Litvinov expressed the belief that there would be less
                        dissatisfaction on the part of the smaller nations with a Policy Committee
                        composed of the four great Powers than would be the case with a larger body;
                        he felt that the leadership of the four powers was already widely
                        accepted.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Hall said that the proposal to circulate the draft as it now stands for
                        comments would afford an opportunity to test that point; <pb facs="0885" n="875" xml:id="pg_875"/> the four Powers would then be in a position to
                        know the point of view of the smaller Powers.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Acheson said that he would expect some proposal to be made at the
                        conference, on the part of some of the smaller Powers, for a larger Policy
                        Committee. He felt that the support of the smaller Powers could be secured
                        for a committee of four, however, because of three safeguards: (1) The
                        establishment, as standing committees, of the Committee of Supplies and the
                        regional committees; (2) the provision suggested by the Soviet Government
                        that the form of activities of the Administration within the territory of a
                        member government in control thereof should be determined after consultation
                        with and consent of that government; and (3) the existence of the Council
                        with the provision for at least semi-annual meetings at which each member
                        government would have full opportunity to discuss all policy matters, and
                        its right to participate in the discussions of the Policy Committee when its
                        interests were concerned.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador Litvinov inquired what position the British Government would take
                        in the event that some controversy arises at the proposed general
                        conference, with respect to the membership of the Policy Committee—would the
                        British Government be neutral or would it expect to take a position for
                        either a committee of four or a committee of seven?</p>
                    <p>Mr. Hall reiterated the statement that the British Government at this time
                        could not commit itself to pressing for a committee of four and he expressed
                        the opinion that it might wish actually to vote for a committee of seven if,
                        at the conference, there was strong support of a reasonable proposal for
                        such an amendment of the draft.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Acheson said that his Government would have to consider very carefully
                        whether it could sponsor the proposal without the full support of the other
                        three Powers. Should the proposal be launched without full agreement, there
                        would be the risk that it might lead to disagreement and disunity and this
                        would be a grave risk to take during the war. Rather than run such a risk,
                        the United States Government might wish to explore other methods of
                        organizing the relief work.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Hall said that he would report Mr. Acheson’s concern on this point to
                        Lord Halifax, and expressed the opinion that the views of the governments
                        should be reconciled.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">5. The suggestion of the British Government that Deputy
                        Directors General be appointed for each region with responsibility for close
                        cooperation with regional committees.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Acheson referred to an informal note from the British Embassy<note n="25" xml:id="d775fn25">Note of February 2, not printed.</note> setting forth
                        the following proposal: <pb facs="0886" n="876" xml:id="pg_876"/>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“The Director General shall recommend to the Policy Committee a
                                Deputy Director General to be appointed for each regional area, and
                                the Deputy Director General shall, with the approval of the Director
                                General, make periodic reports to the committee of Council, for the
                                regional area concerned, as to the general programme of relief
                                operations in that area, consult the committee on all questions of
                                policy and principle that may arise, and give effect so far as
                                practicable to any recommendations made by the committee.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Mr. Acheson said that this suggestion had been given some study and that an
                        alternative draft had been prepared designed to secure the principal
                        objectives of the British suggestion by (1) amendment of paragraph four of
                        Article IV so as to provide for appointment by the Director General of a
                        Deputy Director General for each organized region, and (2) amendment of the
                        proposed new paragraph five of Article III so as to provide that periodic
                        reports by each Deputy Director General should be transmitted by the
                        Director General to the appropriate regional committee, and that policy
                        recommendations of the regional committees should be transmitted to and
                        acted upon by the Council and the Policy Committee and appropriate
                        instructions transmitted by the Director General to the appropriate Deputy
                        Director General.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Hall recognized that this proposed arrangement would require close
                        collaboration between the regional Deputy Directors General and the regional
                        committees. He saw a definite advantage, however, in the British proposal
                        that the Deputy Directors General for the regions should be appointed by the
                        Policy Committee on recommendation of the Director General—he explained that
                        the intention of the proposal certainly was not to take the appointive power
                        away from the Director General but merely to require the approval of the
                        Policy Committee for these important appointments.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">6. The possibility of re-naming the Policy Committee.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Veatch made the suggestion that the name of the Policy Committee might be
                        changed to the “Central Committee of the Council”. In his opinion this name
                        would be more truly descriptive of the position and functions allotted to
                        the Policy Committee, especially with the addition to the draft agreement of
                        specific provisions for two regional committees of the Council and a
                        Committee on Supplies of the Council. He called attention to the fact that
                        the function of determining policy was placed with the Council and with the
                        Policy Committee when the Council was not in session. He advanced the
                        suggestion particularly as a means of reassuring the Canadian Government
                        which, in its memorandum of February 8 [<hi rend="italic">9</hi>], indicated
                        particular concern over restriction of effective participation in the
                        formulation of policy to the four big Powers.</p>
                    <pb facs="0887" n="877" xml:id="pg_877"/>
                    <p>There was general agreement that such a change might have merit, but
                        Ambassador Litvinov urged that, in the interest of expediting action, the
                        present form of the draft should not be changed unless some definite
                        advantages were assured. He suggested, therefore, that this change should
                        not be made unless it had been ascertained in advance that such a change
                        would definitely aid in meeting the fears of the Canadians.</p>
                    <p>It was agreed that Mr. Acheson should prepare a redraft of the agreement
                        embodying the proposed changes on which general agreement had been reached,
                        and that this new draft should be circulated as promptly as possible as a
                        basis for further consideration at an early date.</p>
                    <p>It was agreed also that Mr. Acheson should furnish copies of the Soviet
                        Embassy’s memorandum of February 16 to Lord Halifax and Ambassador Wei.<note n="26" xml:id="d775fn26">Copies of the Soviet Embassy’s memorandum were
                            transmitted by the Secretary of State to the British and Chinese
                            Ambassadors on February 20.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>