<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-06-09T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-06-09T13:00:00-05:00" n="794" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d794">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">840.50/2034b: Circular telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                            Certain <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Representatives</gloss>
                        </hi><note n="55" xml:id="d794fn55">Sent to the chiefs of mission accredited
                            to the Governments comprising the United Nations (except China, the
                            United Kingdom, and the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics) and to the
                            Governments associated with them (except Liberia); also to the Consul
                            General at Algiers. Sent as telegram No. 55, June 9, 1 p.m., to the
                            Mission in Liberia. The Consulate at Asmara having been closed, it was
                            impossible to communicate with the Ethiopian Government; the documents
                            were therefore handed to the Ethiopian Vice Minister of Finance, who was
                            in the United States to attend the conference at Hot Springs, Va.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-06-09T14:00:00-04:00">June 9, 1943—2
                                p.m.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Reference Department’s circular telegram May 21, 9 p.m.<note n="56" xml:id="d794fn56">See bracketed note, <ref target="#pg_907">p.
                            907</ref>.</note> The following is the text of the note to be used in
                        presenting the draft agreement for a United Nations Relief and
                        Rehabilitation Administration and the explanatory memorandum to the
                        governments concerned:<note n="57" xml:id="d794fn57">Memorandum not printed.
                            By a circular telegram dated June 9, 4 p.m., the chiefs of mission were
                            instructed to make the presentation early Thursday, June 10. Separate
                            telegrams with similar instructions were sent as No. 56, June 9, 2 p.m.,
                            to the Mission in Liberia, and as No. 1095, June 9, 5 p.m., to the
                            Consul General at Algiers.</note>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Acting on the instructions of my Government, I have the honor to
                                transmit to you herewith for the consideration of your Government a
                                draft agreement for the establishment of a United Nations Relief and
                                Rehabilitation Administration, together with an explanatory
                                memorandum relating thereto.</p>
                            <p>I know that your Government has been giving attention to the problems
                                of relief and rehabilitation which will exist after the war and in
                                war-torn areas as they are liberated from the control of the enemy
                                even before the termination of hostilities. My Government will be
                                happy to collaborate with the Government of . . . . . . . in
                                developing plans for joint action by the United Nations and the
                                other Nations associated with them in this war in meeting these vast
                                and challenging problems.</p>
                            <p>In order to secure a basis for general discussion of the subject, my
                                Government has been engaged in informal discussions with the British
                                Government, the Soviet Government and the Chinese Government; the
                                enclosed draft meets with the approval of those Governments. This
                                draft is being brought to the attention of all of the United Nations
                                and of the Nations associated with them in this war. It is also
                                being placed before the appropriate French authorities.</p>
                            <p>The representative of your Government in Washington is being informed
                                regarding the substance of this note and he is being told that the
                                Secretary of State and the other officers of the Department of State
                                dealing with this subject will hold themselves in readiness to
                                discuss with him any questions or suggestions which your Government
                                may wish to present.</p>
                            <pb facs="0920" n="910" xml:id="pg_910"/>
                            <p>In order to forestall speculation as to the terms of the proposal,
                                arising out of the wide public interest in the matter in many
                                countries, the text of the draft agreement will be released to the
                                Press for publication after 9 o’clock p.m. Washington time on the
                                day on which it is being placed before the Governments; the
                                explanatory memorandum will be given to the Press for background
                                purposes at the same time. In making this release to the Press my
                                Government will make it clear that the draft agreement is tentative
                                and that no action will be proposed until all of the governments
                                concerned have had an opportunity for full consideration and
                                discussion of the proposal. The Government of . . . . . . . will
                                feel free, of course, to release the text or to discuss the actual
                                terms of the draft agreement with the Press at any time after the
                                time set for the release in Washington.</p>
                            <p>In view of the tremendous scope of the problems of relief and
                                rehabilitation which will face our Nations and of the possibility
                                that large-scale assistance will be required for civilians who may
                                be freed from Axis domination in the near future, action by the
                                United Nations and the Nations associated with them is of the utmost
                                importance. It is the hope of the Government of the United States,
                                therefore, that your Government will be in a position shortly to
                                join with the United States and the other Nations in definitive
                                action on this matter.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>