<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1911-11-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1911-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="286" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d286">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 611.627/458.</note>
                        <head>[Untitled]</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bureau
                                        of Trade Relations</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                        of State</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-11-04"><hi rend="italic">November 4,
                                1911</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Referring to my memorandum of November 3, wherein I sought to show the
                            amount of saving effected for the American buyers of potash through the
                            settlement recently made with the German Syndicate and the independent
                            German mines, I now desire to call attention to a statement made by Mr.
                            Robert S. Bradley in a letter just received from him.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Bradley had evidently noted the published statements as they appeared
                            in the Boston News Bureau and the Financial Bulletin of Philadelphia. He
                            takes exceptions to the conclusions drawn with respect to the actual
                            savings of the Americans through the terms of the recent settlement. He
                            cites the case of the American Agricultural Chemical Co., which he says
                            had paid out in penalty or supercontingent taxes $710,371 of the
                            $3,500,000 so paid by the entire American interests. The A. A. C.
                            company obtains a refund from the German Government to the amount of
                            $568,157. From this refund a payment must be made to the Aschersleben
                            (independent) mine for the cancellation of the A. A. C. company contract
                            with it, and this payment, together with the expenses incident to the
                            “fight” made by the A. A. C. company amounts in all to $340,000. Thus,
                            so far as the A. A. C. company is concerned, it has left $228,157 as the
                            net refund of the taxes. Having paid penalty taxes to the amount of
                            $710,371 and obtained a refund, net, of only $228,157, Mr. Bradley
                            reckons that the balance, being the sum of $482,214, represents the net
                            amount of money that his company has had to pay out in consequence of
                            the German potash law, and of course he is right in this calculation.
                            This sum, $482,214, equals $12.54 per ton on the potash received by the
                            A. A. C. company under its contract with the independent mine, which,
                            added to the original contract price of $20 per ton, makes the potash
                            for the period of one year subsequent to the passage of the law cost the
                            A. A. C. company, net, $32J4 per ton, muriate basis. From the published
                            statements above referred to and which apparently had been authorized by
                            parties familiar with the settlement, I had reached the conclusion that
                            $28.34 per ton represented the actual settlement price, muriate basis,
                            for <pb facs="0325" n="243" xml:id="pg_243"/> invoices since May 28,
                            1910. The Department has had no official statement and in preparing my
                            memorandum I have had to depend upon the published statements that have
                            appeared, presumably emanating from reliable sources. According to Mr.
                            Bradley’s figures these published statements have not been reliable.
                            Instead of the independent mines receiving their settlement money from
                            the supercontingent fund paid in by the Americans, 40 per cent of this
                            fund was first deducted for the uses of the German Government and the
                            German Syndicate, and out of the other 60 per cent refunded to the
                            Americans the latter have had to pay the independent mines their price
                            for the cancellation of the 1909 contracts.</p>
                        <p>The German Government or the German Syndicate seems to have worked along
                            Bismarck’s lines of “real politics” in putting through this settlement,
                            if they have retained as their share of the rake-off 40 per cent of the
                            $3,500,000 supercontingent tax paid in by the Americans. This 40 per
                            cent amounts to $1,400,000, while the Americans get back $2,100,000.
                            They are obliged to pay out again the greater part of this sum in order
                            to obtain release from the mines with whom they made the low-priced
                            contracts which the German potash law rendered untenable.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">M. H. Davis.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>