<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1911-01-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1911-01-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="315" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d315">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 711.428.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Minutes of conferences held at Washington the 13th
                                and 14th of January, 1911, as to the objections of the United States
                                to existing laws and fishery regulations of Canada as recorded in
                                Protocol XXX of the proceedings upon the North Atlantic Coast
                                Fisheries Arbitration.</hi></head>
                        <p>The undersigned, having considered the best means of dealing with the
                            objections above referred to, subject to the minute of previous
                            conferences signed January twelfth, have arrived at the following
                            conclusion:</p>
                        <p>Having regard to the present method of administering the Canadian laws
                            and fishery regulations and to certain amendments which Canada is
                            willing to make therein and to the present state of the fisheries and
                            conditions under which they are carried on and places of fishing, the
                            United States does not press at present any of the objections referred
                            to in Protocol XXX which relate to Canadian laws and fishery
                            regulations, it being understood that the right of the United States to
                            renew such objections is not thereby in any way prejudiced should
                            conditions change.</p>
                        <p>The amendments in regulations above referred to are:</p>
                        <p>Subsection one of section five of the Special Fishery Regulations,
                            Province of Quebec, approved on the twelfth day of September, one
                            thousand nine hundred and seven, is repealed and the following
                            substituted therefor: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>1. Fishing by means of cod trap nets without a license from the
                                    minister of marine and fisheries is prohibited in the waters of
                                    the Gulf of St. Lawrence, except at the distance of one thousand
                                    yards from shore or one thousand yards from any similar net set
                                    from the shore.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Subsection four of section five is repealed and the following substituted
                            therefor: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>4. If the leader of a cod trap-net extends from the shore, any
                                    fishery officer may determine in writing or orally the length of
                                    the leader that shall be used.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Subsection (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of section eight of the said
                            Special Fishery Regutions is hereby repealed and the following
                            substituted therefor: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>1. (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Fishing by means of herring
                                    trap-nets without a license from the minister of marine and
                                    fisheries is prohibited in the waters of the Gulf of St.
                                    Lawrence, except at the distance of one thousand yards from
                                    shore or one thousand yards from any similar net set from the
                                    shore.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Subsection (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) of section eight is hereby repealed
                            and the following substituted therefor: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) If the leader of a herring trap-net
                                    extends from the shore, any fishery officer may determine in
                                    writing or orally the length of the leader that shall be
                                    used.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>Subsection nine of section five (added): <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Upon any inhabitant of the United States fishing with trap-nets
                                    in Canadian waters in the exercise of his liberties under the
                                    treaty of 1818 applying for a berth site under the licensing
                                    provisions, such a license shall be issued in the usual course
                                    for any unoccupied berth site selected by the applicant upon
                                    payment of the regular fee in consideration of the exclusive use
                                    of such site, subject to the usual rules and regulations.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <pb facs="0355" n="273" xml:id="pg_273"/>
                        <p>Clause (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) of subsection one of section eight
                            (added): <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Upon any inhabitant of the United States fishing with trap-nets
                                    in Canadian waters in the exercise of his liberties under the
                                    treaty of 1818 applying for a berth site under the licensing
                                    provisions, such a license shall be issued in the usual course
                                    for any unoccupied berth site selected by the applicant upon
                                    payment of the regular fee in consideration of the exclusive use
                                    of such site, subject to the usual rules and regulations.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <closer><dateline rendition="#left"><date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-01-14">January 14, 1911</date>.</dateline></closer>
                        <closer><signed>
                                <list>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Philander C. Knox</hi>.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">James Bryce</hi>.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">L. P. Brodeur</hi>.</item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">A. B. Aylesworth</hi></item>
                                    <item><hi rend="smallcaps">Chandler P. Anderson</hi>.</item>
                                </list>
                            </signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>