<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1911-10-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1911-10-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="403" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 765.67/131a.</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">American Chargé d’Affaires
                                    at Rome</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-10-27"><hi rend="italic">October
                                        27, 1911</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose herewith fourteen copies of the
                            proclamation of neutrality in the present war between Italy and the
                            Ottoman Empire, issued by the President on the 24th instant.</p>
                        <pb facs="0391" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/>
                        <p>It is desired that you send one copy to each of the American consular
                            officers in Italy.</p>
                        <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Alvey A. Adee.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">By the President of the United States of
                                    America</hi>.</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">a proclamation</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Whereas a state of war unhappily exists between the Kingdom of Italy
                                on the one side and the Ottoman Empire on the other side; and</p>
                            <p>Whereas the United States are on terms of friendship and amity with
                                both the contending powers and with the people inhabiting their
                                several dominions; and</p>
                            <p>Whereas in the state of war thus unhappily existing the United
                                States, looking to both parties for the appropriate reciprocal
                                treatment toward the United States and toward all persons owing
                                allegiance to them, are resolved to maintain and enforce in
                                accordance with the rules and principles governing the rights and
                                duties of neutrals in international warfare a strict and impartial
                                neutrality between the aforesaid contending powers, as well as
                                between themselves and the subjects of each, whether resident within
                                the jurisdiction of the United States or elsewhere,</p>
                            <p>Now, therefore, I, William Howard Taft, President of the United
                                States, do, in order that strict and impartial neutrality may be
                                observed in the premises, enjoin all persons owing allegiance to the
                                United States, as well as all other persons within the jurisdiction
                                of the United States, to obey in letter and spirit the laws, rules,
                                and principles governing the conduct of neutrals in time of
                                international conflict as such laws, rules, and principles are
                                prescribed by the statutes of the United States, by the treaties and
                                international conventions which have been signed, ratified, and
                                proclaimed by the Government of the United States and by the
                                recognized customs of nations;</p>
                            <p>And I do hereby give notice and warning that all persons within the
                                jurisdiction of the United States who may misconduct themselves in
                                the premises will do so at their peril and will be subject to the
                                strict and impartial enforcement of the penalties imposed by the
                                laws, rules, and principles involved; and that all persons owing
                                allegiance to the United States and so misconducting themselves
                                outside the jurisdiction of the United States can in nowise obtain
                                any protection from the Government of the United States against the
                                appropriate legal consequences of their misconduct.</p>
                            <p>In witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand and caused the seal of
                                the United States to be affixed.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <seg type="margin">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>.]</seg> Done
                                    at the city of <placeName>Washington</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian us-republic" when="1911-10-24">this
                                        twenty-fourth day of October, in the year of our Lord one
                                        thousand nine hundred and eleven, and of the independence of
                                        the United States of America the one hundred and
                                        thirty-sixth</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wm. H. Taft.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>By the President:<lb/><hi rend="smallcaps">P. C.
                                        Knox</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretary of
                                    State.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>