<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Untitled]</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1911</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d640</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">640</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1911-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1911-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1911-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1911-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="640"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d640">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.00/1284.</note>
                <head>[Untitled]</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy of Mexico</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-04-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 9, 1911</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1219.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: The authorities of the State of Chihuahua
                    report to the Federal Government the constant passing of men and war material
                    from El Paso, Tex., to Guadalupe. The activities of the disturbers of the peace
                    have lately assumed such proportions that it is feared that Ciudad Juarez may be
                    attacked by the organization recently formed around that place.</p>
                <pb facs="0534" n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/>
                <p>The Government of Mexico, appreciating to its value the very efficacious
                    cooperation of the Government of the United States for the prevention of public
                    disturbances in our country by groups that would not organize except for the
                    means they expect to find in American territory, calls, through this embassy,
                    the attention of the Government of the United States to the necessity of
                    establishing a stricter vigilance at El Paso, because it knows that foremost of
                    the purposes of this Government is that to repress filibustering severely and to
                    prevent sympathizers and associates of the Mexican rebels from finding
                    facilities for their schemes against established order.</p>
                <p>Having thus complied with my instructions, I avail myself of this opportunity to
                    offer to your excellency the assurances of the most profound gratitude for the
                    benevolent attention you have always and are still giving to a matter which
                    bears upon physical and moral interests very worthy of the care both Governments
                    bestow upon them.</p>
                <p>I express, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Carlos Pereyra.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
