<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Mexican Chargé d’Affaires.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1911</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d660</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">660</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1911-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1911-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1911-04-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1911-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="660"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d660">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 812.00/1284.</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">Mexican Chargé d’Affaires</gloss>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-04-19">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 19, 1911</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your note of the 9th instant, in which you advise the Department that the
                    authorities of the State of Chihuahua report to the Federal Government of Mexico
                    the constant passing of men and war material from El Paso, Tex., to Guadalupe,
                    and that it is feared that Ciudad Juarez may be attacked by the organization
                    recently formed around that place.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to say in reply that copies of your note have been transmitted
                    to the Attorney General and to the Secretary of War for their information and
                    such action, if any, as they may find it necessary to take in order to secure
                    the proper observance of the neutrality laws of the United States.</p>
                <p>As indicated in your note, the Government of the United States has every
                    disposition to secure a rigid observance of the provisions of its laws. In this
                    connection, however, the Department feels that it should again take occasion to
                    invite the embassy’s attention to the Department’s notes of January 24 and 28
                    and February 11, 1911, and the aide memoire of March 24, in which it was pointed
                    out that mere commercial trading in arms and ammunition is forbidden neither by
                    the rules of international law nor by the so-called neutrality statutes of the
                    United States, as has been clearly set forth by the Federal courts in the case
                    of The United States <hi rend="italic">v</hi>. Murphy, to which the Mexican
                    embassy was good enough to direct the attention of this Government in its note
                    of January 24.</p>
                <p>I have also the honor again to suggest that the passing of men from the United
                    States into Mexico either singly or in unarmed and unorganized groups, unless
                    constituting an expedition or a part of an expedition fitted out from this
                    country can not be regarded as in violation either of the laws of neutrality or
                    of the provisions of the Federal statutes.</p>
                <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">P. C. Knox.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
