<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1911-03-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1911-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="841" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d841">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 711.1216M/256.</note>
                        <head>[Translation.]</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexican
                                        Embassy</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1911-03-06"><hi rend="italic">March 6,
                                1911</hi>.</date></dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 1056.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: Confirming my confidential note No.
                            989 of the 4th instant, I have the honor to add that the forces designed
                            to protect the works of the Colorado River and in general all interests
                            in the northern part of Lower California will arrive on the 10th at
                            Ensenada de Todos Santos, where they will join the forces of Col.
                            Vega.</p>
                        <p>To the end that these forces may arrive without a moment’s loss at the
                            place where the works on the Colorado River are being: constructed, <pb facs="0645" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/> the Government of Mexico would
                            be disposed to request from that of the United States the passage of
                            said forces over the railroad, which they would take in San Diego,
                            provided the entry of our soldiers upon the territory of this country
                            would not subject them to conditions incompatible with the purpose that
                            takes them to Lower California, which is that of attacking the
                            adventurers, a majority of whom are fugitives from American justice and
                            whose presence in Mexicali causes alarm to the Colorado company, since
                            if the granting of said favor should be subject to any such conditions
                            it would be preferable that the united troops of Col. Vega and of the
                            expedition that started from Manzanillo should proceed over Mexican
                            territory from Todos Santos to Mexicali.</p>
                        <p>I beg [etc.],</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">F. L. de la
                            Barra.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>