<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944Quebec</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">168</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="168" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d168">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The document referred to as the President’s Log is a booklet entitled “The
                    President’s Log for the 1944 Quebec Conference (<gloss target="#t_Octagon1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Octagon</hi>
                    </gloss>), September 9–21, 1944” (14 regularly numbered pages of text, seven
                    pages at the front bearing roman numerals, an unnumbered page designated
                    Appendix A containing the text of the Communiqué, and 20 unnumbered pages of
                    illustrations). This booklet, which was prepared by Lieutenant (jg) William M.
                    Rigdon and approved by Rear Admiral Wilson Brown, contains a table of contents
                    (not printed), a list of the President’s party,<note n="1" xml:id="d168fn1">Not
                        printed. A substantially similar list of the party is given (although not in
                        the same order) in William M. Rigdon, with James Derieux, <hi rend="italic"
                            >White House Sailor</hi> (Garden City: Doubleday and Company, 1962), pp.
                        280–281. That source includes three names which do not appear in the list of
                        the President’s party in the Log: Colonel Richard Park, Jr., Captain Boyce
                        Price, and Lieutenant Ogden S. Collins, Jr. The Log list, on the other hand,
                        includes seven names not mentioned on the pages cited in <hi rend="italic"
                            >White House Sailor:</hi> Henry Morgenthau, Jr., D. L. Moorman, Herbert
                        Harwood, Leo DeWaard, Merriman Smith, Douglas Cornell, and Robert G. Nixon.
                        Morgenthau was included in the Log list of the President’s party because he
                        accompanied Roosevelt from Washington to Hyde Park; for the message in which
                        Roosevelt later asked Morgenthau to come to Quebec, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_43">p. 43</ref>.</note> the President’s
                    itinerary (not printed), a foreword by Lieutenant George M. Elsey, the main body
                    of the Log, and the text of the Conference Communiqué.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d168fn2">See <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_477">p.
                            477</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
