<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Combined Chiefs of Staff Minutes</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944Quebec</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">173</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-09-12T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-09-12T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                    <term ref="recpstiA6BlyU6T5H" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006447"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Logistics</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-12T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-12T11:00:00-05:00" n="173"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_JCS1">J.C.S.</gloss> Files</note>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1944-09-12T12:00:00-04:00">September 12, 1944, noon</date>
                </dateline>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Combined Chiefs of Staff Minutes</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-chapter-heading" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1944-09-12">September 12, 1944</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Chairmanship of the Combined Chiefs of
                        Staff</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Leahy</hi> said that the United States Chiefs of
                    Staff would be glad if Sir Alan Brooke would take the Chair at the forthcoming
                    series of meetings.</p>
                <pb facs="0361" n="301" xml:id="pg_301"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan Brooke</hi> thanked Admiral Leahy for this
                    proposal which he would be glad to accept.</p>
                <p rend="center">2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Personnel Shipping</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan Brooke</hi> said that he felt that the problem of
                    the use of personnel shipping after the defeat of Germany should be examined
                    during the Conference. There would be heavy calls for personnel shipping both
                    for the transfer of U.S. troops other than occupational troops from Europe to
                    the United States or the Pacific, as well as for the reorientation of British
                    forces to the Far East. In addition the New Zealand and South African divisions
                    and certain Canadian forces now in Europe would have to be returned to their
                    homelands. He suggested that the experts should be instructed to examine this
                    problem to see how best it could be met.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Leahy</hi> said that he could see no objection to
                    this review but it would be impossible to reach any decisions during the
                    Conference.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Portal</hi>, in agreeing with Admiral Leahy,
                    said that he felt that the scope of the problem should be examined.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Somervell</hi> stated that he had only one shipping
                    expert at present at <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <gloss target="#t_Octagon1">Octagon</gloss>
                    </hi> but agreed with a proposal made by Sir Alan Brooke that he should discuss
                    this matter with Lord Leathers.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Combined Chiefs of Staff</hi>:—</p>
                <p>Invited General Somervell to confer with Lord Leathers on this matter.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d173fn2">For a report on this subject, see <gloss target="#t_CCS1"
                            >C.C.S.</gloss> 675/1, <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref
                            target="#pg_448">p. 448</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Agenda and Hour of Meeting</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At the suggestion of Admiral Leahy</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Combined Chiefs of Staff</hi>:— <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Agreed to meet daily from 1000 to 1300.<note n="3" xml:id="d173fn3"
                                >i.e., from 10 a.m. to 1 p.m.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Approved the program for the Conference as set out in <gloss
                                target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 654/6,<note n="4" xml:id="d173fn4">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_40">p.
                                40</ref>.</note> subject to the transfer of the items for Saturday,
                            16 September, to Tuesday, 12 September. (Approved program subsequently
                            circulated as <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 654/7.)<note n="5"
                                xml:id="d173fn5">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_41">p.
                                41</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">4. <hi rend="smallcaps">Situation Report From</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_SCAEF1">SCAEF</gloss>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">(<gloss target="#t_Scaf1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Scaf</hi>
                    </gloss> 78<note n="6" xml:id="d173fn6">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_234">p. 234</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan Brooke</hi> said that, while agreeing in general
                    with General Eisenhower’s appreciation (<gloss target="#t_Scaf1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Scaf</hi>
                    </gloss> 78), the British Chiefs of Staff felt that sufficient emphasis had not
                    been laid on two points: firstly, the <pb facs="0362" n="302" xml:id="pg_302"/>
                    importance of securing sea communications and the ports of Antwerp and
                    Rotterdam, and secondly, the importance of a strong attack being launched on the
                    northern flank. General Eisenhower in his telegram had spoken of three possible
                    routes of advance into Germany. In his (Sir Alan Brooke’s) view the most
                    important was the northern route of attack which should be strengthened as much
                    as possible, the remaining two routes being retained as alternatives. The most
                    energetic efforts should be made to secure and open the port of Antwerp as a
                    valuable base for future operations on the northern flank. In order to open the
                    sea approaches to Antwerp, it seemed desirable to stage an airborne operation to
                    capture the islands at the mouth of the Schelde.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> said that in view of the apparent
                    massing of German forces on the islands guarding the port of Antwerp, and the
                    lack of cover which existed on the ground, it appeared that a more profitable
                    operation would be the bombing of enemy positions rather than an airborne
                    operation.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan Brooke</hi> felt that bombing alone would not
                    achieve the required results and occupying forces would have to be
                    introduced.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan Brooke</hi> presented a draft reply to <gloss
                        target="#t_Scaf1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Scaf</hi>
                    </gloss> 78 approving General Eisenhower’s proposals and pointing out the
                    advantages of the northern line of approach into Germany as opposed to the
                    southern and the necessity for opening up the northwest ports, particularly
                    Antwerp and Rotterdam.</p>
                <p>After further discussion,</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Combined Chiefs of Staff</hi>:—</p>
                <p>Approved the dispatch to the Supreme Commander, Allied Expeditionary Force of the
                    draft telegram proposed by the British Chiefs of Staff. (Subsequently dispatched
                    as <gloss target="#t_Facs1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Facs</hi>
                    </gloss> 78<note n="7" xml:id="d173fn7">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_428">p.
                    428</ref>.</note>).</p>
                <p rend="center">5. <hi rend="smallcaps">Situation Report From the
                        Mediterranean</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">(<gloss target="#t_Medcos1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Medcos</hi>
                    </gloss> 181<note n="8" xml:id="d173fn8">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_224">p. 224</ref>.</note>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">and <gloss target="#t_Naf1">Naf</gloss>
                    </hi> 774<note n="9" xml:id="d173fn9">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_230">p. 230</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Leahy</hi> presented a statement of the views of
                    the United States Chiefs of Staff with reference to the future role of the Fifth
                    Army and of the Twelfth and Fifteenth Air Forces (<gloss target="#t_CCS1"
                        >C.C.S.</gloss> 677).<note n="10" xml:id="d173fn10">
                        <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_429">p. 429</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> said that a message<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d173fn11">Not printed.</note> had just been received from the U.S.
                    Military Attaché in Switzerland<note n="12" xml:id="d173fn12">Brigadier General
                        Barnwell R. Legge.</note> to the effect that a German withdrawal of forces
                    in northern Italy had already begun. If this was so, it would seem that, of the
                    two situations envisaged by General Wilson in Part II of <gloss target="#t_Naf1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Naf</hi>
                    </gloss> 774, situation “<hi rend="italic">a</hi>” would be ruled out unless the
                    Allied armies could drive ahead with great speed, and <pb facs="0363" n="303"
                        xml:id="pg_303"/> situation “<hi rend="italic">b</hi>” would exist, that is,
                    there would be no possibility of another major offensive till the spring.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan Brooke</hi> said that as he visualized it, if the
                    Allied armies could break through to the Plains the enemy forces remaining in
                    northwest Italy would be badly placed. A threat to Verona would cut off these
                    forces and might result in their retirement to the westward and later the
                    retirement of the German forces in northeast Italy back to the Alps. It was to
                    be hoped that a large number of these eastern forces could be broken up. The
                    attack by the Fifth Army was planned to take place on 13 September and a
                    successful advance north of Florence might well result in driving the enemy
                    forces back to the Po and Piave.</p>
                <p>The indications were that the enemy was attempting to withdraw forces from Greece
                    and Yugoslavia, though there was some doubt whether he could succeed in getting
                    them out through bad lines of communications threatened by the Bulgarians,
                    Marshal Tito’s army and the Greeks. The enemy might, however, get some forces
                    out and it appeared that he was likely to endeavor to hold a line running
                    through Yugoslavia. In such an event the enemy might be reduced to covering the
                    Ljubljana Gap and endeavoring to hold a line through Yugoslavia and Istria. In
                    these circumstances any withdrawal of forces from the Fifth Army would be most
                    regrettable.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> said that it was not the intention to
                    weaken the Fifth Army at the present time.</p>
                <p>Continuing, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan Brooke</hi> said that the forces to be
                    maintained in Italy might later be limited by logistics and terrain, Pie saw,
                    however, great advantages in a right swing at Trieste and an advance from there
                    to Vienna. However, if German resistance was strong, he did not visualize the
                    possibility of our forces getting through to Vienna during the winter. Even so,
                    the seizure of the Istrian Peninsula would be valuable as a base for the spring
                    campaign or as a base from which our forces could be introduced into Austria in
                    the event of Germany crumbling. It had not only a military value but also
                    political value in view of the Russian advances in the Balkans.</p>
                <p>In view of the possibility of amphibious thrusts on the Istrian Peninsula Sir
                    Alan Brooke asked the United States Chiefs of Staff their intention with regard
                    to the U.S. landing craft now operating in support of <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <gloss target="#t_Dragoon1">Dragoon</gloss>.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral King</hi> said that these craft were earmarked for
                    other operations but no orders had been issued for their withdrawal. He too had
                    in mind the possibility of amphibious operations in Istria. Naval forces on the
                    other hand were in course of withdrawal for rehabilitation.</p>
                <p>Unless a decision to mount an amphibious operation were taken soon the landing
                    craft would lie idle, though required for operations in other parts of the
                    world, for instance, against Rangoon.</p>
                <pb facs="0364" n="304" xml:id="pg_304"/>
                <p>In reply to a question by General Marshall, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan
                        Brooke</hi> said that General Wilson was planning now for an amphibious
                    operation and the picture should be much clearer in a short time, particularly
                    if the German forces withdrew from north Italy.</p>
                <p>There was general agreement that a decision with regard to the launching of an
                    amphibious operation should be made by 15 October.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> said that if operations in the Alps
                    were undertaken in winter there was available the <gloss
                        target="#t_PloughForce1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Plough</hi> Force</gloss> now in south France and the
                    necessary sleds are obtainable.</p>
                <p>Referring to the views of the United States Chiefs of Staff on the future role of
                    the Fifth Army, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Portal</hi> said that he felt
                    that primary emphasis should be laid on the securing of a victory in Italy. As
                    he saw it, the possible withdrawal of units of the Fifth Army to France would be
                    dependent on the successful outcome of the campaign in Italy.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Leahy</hi> asked if it was Sir Charles Portal’s
                    thought that these forces should be retained in Italy if General Eisenhower was
                    in need of them in France.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Portal</hi> pointed out that it was a question
                    of short-term as opposed to long-term advantages. The important point as he saw
                    it was to prevent the German troops getting away in north Italy if it could be
                    avoided.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Leahy</hi> said it was not the intention to
                    withdraw troops from the Fifth Army unless the German troops withdrew.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Portal</hi> said that he would point out that
                    the withdrawal of forces from an army had a greater effect on that army than the
                    actual number of formations withdrawn, since such withdrawals had a discouraging
                    effect on the morale of the command and of the army itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Leahy</hi> re-emphasized that the United States
                    proposal was contingent on the destruction or withdrawal of a large part of the
                    German Army.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> said that there was no intention in
                    the mind of the United States Chiefs of Staff to effect the withdrawal of forces
                    from Italy at the present time.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral King</hi> confirmed that an option on the U.S.
                    landing craft now in the Mediterranean could be retained provided a decision was
                    reached by 15 October.</p>
                <p>In reply to a question by Sir Alan Brooke, <hi rend="smallcaps">General
                        Marshall</hi> confirmed that while there was no intention of moving major
                    units of the Fifth Army at the present time, small individual units (i.e., the
                    Japanese battalion) might be withdrawn.</p>
                <p>After further discussion,</p>
                <pb facs="0365" n="305" xml:id="pg_305"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Combined Chiefs of Staff</hi>:— <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Agreed that no forces should be withdrawn from Italy until the outcome
                            of General Alexander’s present offensive is known.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Agreed that the desirability of withdrawing formations of the United
                            States Fifth Army should be reconsidered in the light of the results of
                            General Alexander’s present offensive and of a German withdrawal in
                            northern Italy and in the light of the views of General
                            Eisenhower.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                        <item>Agreed to inform General Wilson that if he wishes to retain for use in
                            the Istrian Peninsula the amphibious lift at present in the
                            Mediterranean, he should submit his plan therefor to the Combined Chiefs
                            of Staff as soon as possible, and not later than 15 October; and took
                            note that the British Chiefs of Staff would prepare a suitable message
                            for consideration.<note n="13" xml:id="d173fn13">See enclosure A to
                                    <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 667/1, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_430">p. 430</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">6. <hi rend="smallcaps">Combined Intelligence Report on the
                        Situation in Europe</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">(<gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 660/1<note n="14"
                        xml:id="d173fn14">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_237">p. 237</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Combined Chiefs of Staff</hi>:—</p>
                <p>Took note of the estimate contained in <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss>
                    660/1.</p>
                <p rend="center">7. <hi rend="smallcaps">Command of “<gloss target="#t_Dragoon1"
                            >Dragoon</gloss>” Forces</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">(<gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 674<note n="15"
                        xml:id="d173fn15">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_232">p.
                            232</ref>, fn. 1.</note>)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Admiral Leahy</hi> presented a draft telegram to General
                    Eisenhower approving his proposals in <gloss target="#t_Scaf1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Scaf</hi>
                    </gloss> 77 (<gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 674/1).<note n="16"
                        xml:id="d173fn16">For the text of telegram No. <gloss target="#t_Scaf1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Scaf</hi>
                        </gloss> 77, see <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_232">p.
                            232</ref>. For the text of <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 674/1,
                        see <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_428">p. 428</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Charles Portal</hi> drew attention to a telegram
                        (<gloss target="#t_FX1">FX</gloss> 28818)<note n="17" xml:id="d173fn17">Not
                        printed.</note> from General Wilson to General Devers, inquiring as to how
                    soon General Devers’ communications with General Eisenhower would be sufficient
                    to permit General Eisenhower to assume command.</p>
                <p>It was generally agreed that this matter must be left to the commanders concerned
                    and that General Eisenhower’s proposal to assume command of <gloss
                        target="#t_Dragoon1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dragoon</hi>
                    </gloss> forces on 15 September would have taken account of this factor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> said that while General Eisenhower
                    had been anxious that General Devers should set up his headquarters and be able
                    to take over the lines of communications, logistic problems and civil affairs,
                    he also wished General Patch to continue in charge of the present battle.
                    Undoubtedly additional U.S. troops would be transferred at a later date to
                    General Patch from the center group of armies and further American divisions
                    would join him through the port of <pb facs="0366" n="306" xml:id="pg_306"/>
                    Marseilles. At that time the 6th Army Group could be conveniently split, General
                    Patch assuming command of the United States forces and the French forces forming
                    an army of their own.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Alan Brooke</hi> said that there was one point he would
                    like to make. He hoped the setting up of a large headquarters by General Devers
                    would not unduly deplete General Clark’s staff organization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">General Marshall</hi> reassured Sir Alan Brooke on this
                    point. General Devers’ staff had been formed for some time in Corsica and
                    General Clark’s forces would not be affected.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Combined Chiefs of Staff</hi>:—</p>
                <p>Agreed to dispatch to General Eisenhower and General Wilson the message proposed
                    by the United States Chiefs of Staff in <gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss>.
                    674/1. (Subsequently dispatched as <gloss target="#t_Facs1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Facs</hi>
                    </gloss> 76 and <gloss target="#t_Fan1">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Fan</hi>
                    </gloss> 413, respectively.)</p>
                <p>At this point the Combined Chiefs of Staff recessed until 1430.<note n="18"
                        xml:id="d173fn18">i.e., 2:30 p.m. During the recess Leahy and Marshall
                        lunched with Brooke and Dill. See Alanbrooke, <ref target="#pg_204">p.
                            204</ref>. For the minutes of the second part of the <gloss
                            target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 172d Meeting, following the recess, see
                            <hi rend="italic">post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_307">p. 307</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
