<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="259" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d259">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_JCS1">J.C.S.</gloss>
                                Files</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Note by the Secretaries of the Combined Chiefs
                                    of Staff</hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 520/6</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Quebec</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-14">14 September 1944</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Control of Strategic Bomber Forces
                                    in Europe Following the Establishment of Allied Forces on the
                                    Continent</hi></p>
                            <table>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>References:</cell>
                                    <cell><gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> 172d Meeting, Item
                                            10<note n="1" xml:id="d259fn1">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_309">p.
                                            309</ref>.</note></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> 173d Meeting Item
                                            2<note n="2" xml:id="d259fn2">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_320">p.
                                            320</ref>.</note></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> 174th Meeting Item
                                            2<note n="3" xml:id="d259fn3">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_331">p.
                                            331</ref>.</note></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell><gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss> 680/2, Paragraph
                                            7<note n="4" xml:id="d259fn4"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_471">p. 471</ref>. This
                                            reference was probably changed or added later, as <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 680/2 postdated
                                                <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss>
                                        520/6.</note></cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                            <p>The Combined Chiefs of Staff in their 174th Meeting approved the
                                directive in <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 520/4<note n="5" xml:id="d259fn5"><hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> as amended
                                by <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 520/5,<note n="6" xml:id="d259fn6">“Control of Strategic Bomber Forces in Europe
                                    Following the Establishment of Allied Forces on the Continent”,
                                    September 14, 1944. In this memorandum the British Chiefs of
                                    Staff accepted the enclosure to <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 520/4 subject to the inclusion of two new
                                    subparagraphs on important industrial areas and attacks in
                                    support of the Russian armies. These two proposed amendments
                                    were acceptable to the United States Chiefs of Staff and the
                                    language proposed by the British Chiefs of Staff became
                                    subparagraphs 5 <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and 5 <hi rend="italic">e</hi> in the directive as approved and printed
                                    here.</note> and the directive as approved (Enclosure) was
                                dispatched to the Deputy Chief of the Air Staff, <gloss target="#t_RAF1">RAF</gloss>, and the Commanding General, United
                                States Strategic Air Forces in Europe, by the Chief of the Air
                                Staff, <gloss target="#t_RAF1">RAF</gloss>, and the Commanding
                                General, United States Army Air Forces, for action and furnished to
                                the Supreme Commander, Allied Expeditionary Force, and the Supreme
                                Allied Commander, Mediterranean, for information.</p>
                            <closer><signed> A. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">McFarland</hi>
                                    <lb/> A. T. <hi rend="smallcaps">Cornwall-Jones</hi>
                                </signed><lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Combined Secretariat</hi></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Enclosure</head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                        secret</hi></seg>
                                </opener>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Control of Strategic Bomber
                                        Forces in Europe</hi>—<hi rend="smallcaps">Directive</hi><note n="7" xml:id="d259fn7">The approved
                                        directive is substantively identical with the enclosure to
                                            <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 520/4 except for
                                            (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the inclusion of the two new
                                        subparagraphs mentioned in fn. 6, above, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the consequent relettering of
                                        subparagraphs 5 <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and 5 <hi rend="italic">d</hi> of the enclosure to <gloss target="#t_CCS1">C.C.S.</gloss> 520/4 to become
                                        subparagraphs 5 <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and 5 <hi rend="italic">f</hi> in the final directive.</note></p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Control of the Strategic Bomber Forces
                                    in Europe</p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The Combined Chiefs of Staff have decided that executive
                                        responsibility for the control of the strategic bomber
                                        forces in Europe <pb facs="0495" n="433" xml:id="pg_433"/>
                                        shall be vested in the Chief of the Air Staff, <gloss target="#t_RAF1">RAF</gloss> and the Commanding General,
                                        United States Army Air Forces, jointly.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The Deputy Chief of the Air Staff, <gloss target="#t_RAF1">RAF</gloss> and the Commanding General, United States
                                        Strategic Air Forces in Europe, are designated as
                                        representatives of the Chief of the Air Staff, <gloss target="#t_RAF1">RAF</gloss> and the Commanding General,
                                        United States Army Air Forces, respectively, for the purpose
                                        of providing control and local coordination through
                                        consultation.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The over-all mission of the strategic air forces is the
                                        progressive destruction and dislocation of the German
                                        military, industrial and economic systems and the direct
                                        support of land and naval forces.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Under this general mission you are to direct your attacks,
                                        subject to the exigencies of weather and tactical
                                        feasibility, against the systems of objectives and in the
                                        order of priority now established by the Supreme Commander,
                                        Allied Expeditionary Force. When you decide that changes in
                                        objectives or priorities are necessary, you will issue the
                                        necessary directives and inform the Chief of the Air Staff,
                                            <gloss target="#t_RAF1">RAF</gloss> and the Commanding
                                        General, United States Army Air Forces.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>Objectives other than those covered in paragraph 4 above
                                        will be attacked in accordance with the following: <list>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic">Counter air force action</hi>.
                                                As the result of air action against the production,
                                                maintenance and operation facilities of the German
                                                Air Forces (<gloss target="#t_GAF1">G.A.F.</gloss>),
                                                its fighting effectiveness has now been
                                                substantially reduced. At the same time our combined
                                                air strength has been vastly increased. In these
                                                circumstances we are no longer justified in
                                                regarding the <gloss target="#t_GAF1">G.A.F.</gloss>
                                                and its supporting industry as a primary objective
                                                for attack. Our major effort must now be focused
                                                directly upon the vital sources of Germany’s war
                                                economy. To this end policing attacks against the
                                                  <gloss target="#t_GAF1">G.A.F.</gloss> are to be
                                                adjusted so as to maintain tactical conditions which
                                                will permit of the maximum impact upon the primary
                                                objectives. No fixed priority is, therefore,
                                                assigned to policing attacks against the <gloss target="#t_GAF1">G.A.F.</gloss> The intensity of
                                                such attacks will be regulated by the tactical
                                                situation existing.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic">Direct support</hi>. The direct
                                                support of land and naval operations remains a
                                                continuing commitment upon your forces. Upon call
                                                from the supreme commanders concerned either for
                                                assistance in the battle or to take advantage of
                                                related opportunities, you will meet their
                                                requirements promptly.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic">Important industrial areas</hi>.
                                                When weather or tactical conditions are unsuitable
                                                for operations against specific primary objectives
                                                attacks should be delivered upon important
                                                industrial areas by both Bomber Command <gloss target="#t_RAF1">RAF</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USSTAF1">USSTAF</gloss> (using blind
                                                bombing technique as necessary).</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_SOE1">S.O.E.</gloss> operations</hi>. All <gloss target="#t_SOE1">SOE</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_OSS1">OSS</gloss> operations undertaken
                                                by units of <gloss target="#t_RAF1">RAF</gloss>
                                                Bomber Command and United States Strategic Air
                                                Forces in Europe will be in accordance with the
                                                requirements of the Supreme Allied Commanders, who
                                                will issue the requisite orders from time to time,
                                                under existing procedure. </item>
                                            <pb facs="0496" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic">Attacks in support of the
                                                  Russian armies</hi>. Attacks in support of
                                                operations by the Russian armies should be delivered
                                                as prescribed from time to time by the Combined
                                                Chiefs of Staff.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                                            <item><hi rend="italic">Fleeting targets</hi>. There may
                                                be certain other targets of great but fleeting
                                                importance for the attack of which all necessary
                                                plans and preparations should be made. Of these an
                                                example would be the important units of the German
                                                Fleet in harbor or at sea.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>You are responsible that the operations of the strategic
                                        air forces are coordinated with the operations of the
                                        tactical air forces in the theaters.</item>
                                </list>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>