<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-09-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-09-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="88" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d88">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 Control
                                (Germany)/9–644</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Assistant Secretary of War</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Deputy Director of the Office of European
                                    Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Matthews</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-09-06">September 6, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Doc</hi>: Here is a draft of our
                                post-surrender directive to Eisenhower.<note n="1" xml:id="d88fn1">For a draft directive to the three Allied commanders-in-chief
                                    relating to the post-surrender period in Germany, prepared by
                                    the Planning Committee of the United States Delegation to the
                                    European Advisory Commission and dated July 12, 1944, see <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_244"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>,
                                        pp. 244</ref>–<ref target="frus1944v01#pg_246">246</ref>. In
                                    the absence of action on a tripartite basis with respect to such
                                    a directive, the Representatives of the British Chiefs of Staff,
                                    in <gloss target="#t_CCS1">CCS</gloss>. 658, August 23, 1944
                                    (not printed), suggested the preparation of an American-British
                                    directive to Eisenhower on the military government of Germany
                                    after Germany’s surrender. This suggestion was referred to the
                                    Combined Civil Affairs Committee for study and the War
                                    Department prepared a draft of such a directive. The draft
                                    printed below is not known to have been referred to at the
                                    Second Quebec Conference, but it formed part of the background
                                    of the discussion of German problems within the Cabinet
                                    Committee on Germany and between the Committee and Roosevelt.
                                    Following the Quebec Conference an amended version of this draft
                                    (dated September 22, 1944) was submitted to the Joint Chiefs of
                                    Staff as enclosure C to <gloss target="#t_JCS1">J.C.S.</gloss>
                                    1067, September 24, 1944, and was forwarded to Winant on
                                    September 27. For the covering instruction to Winant and for the
                                    text of the draft of September 22, see <ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_142"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, The Conferences at Malta and Yalta,
                                        1945, pp. 142</ref>–<ref target="frus1945Malta#pg_154">154</ref>.</note> It is something which the Committee, I
                                believe, in view of what has gone before, should approve. It seems
                                to me that this is very much in line with your paper<note n="2" xml:id="d88fn2">“Suggested Recommendations on Treatment of
                                    Germany From the Cabinet Committee for the President”, September
                                    4, 1944, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_95">p.
                                        95</ref>.</note> which was discussed in the Secretary’s <pb facs="0165" n="109" xml:id="pg_109"/> office yesterday. We would
                                now be able to add, of course, a provision regarding regional
                                movements. The directive would provide that they should not be
                                discouraged. We are generally working on improving the language and
                                in some cases the order of the document, but in general this is the
                                idea. I think that if the Committee could approve it generally,
                                without going through it with a fine tooth comb, it would leave us
                                room in the [Combined] Civil Affairs Committee to work out the final
                                language and the clearance with the British.</p>
                            <p>Secretary Stimson was very much disturbed this morning at the line
                                that was taken throughout the discussion on the matter of economic
                                repression of Germany. He felt that the last paragraph of the paper,
                                I believe it was sub-paragraph (<hi rend="italic">h</hi>),<note n="3" xml:id="d88fn3">See <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_97">p. 97</ref>.</note> although objectionable
                                in some form, could be interpreted in a way which would meet his
                                views, but the tone of the discussion convinced him that its
                                interpretation by those present amounted to such severe destruction
                                of values in the case of properties and facilities and such severe
                                limitation on the economy of the individual, that he felt he could
                                not go along with the implications of this paragraph and has so
                                communicated to Mr. Hull.<note n="4" xml:id="d88fn4">See Stimson’s
                                    memorandum for Roosevelt, September 5, 1944, <hi rend="italic">ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_98">p. 98</ref>, which was
                                    submitted via Hull.</note></p>
                            <p>I was not present at the discussion, so I do not know what happened.
                                I don’t believe that the Secretary, from my long talk with him
                                yesterday, however, is at all at variance with your and my thinking
                                on the subject. I hope you will take a look at Mr. Stimson’s
                                comments.</p>
                            <p>I have one other comment which I did not ask him to include because
                                it was relatively minor. Somewhere in your paper there is a
                                statement to the effect that Party members should not be permitted
                                any political or civic activity. I think this must refer only to the
                                leaders, because Party members who were only such in order to keep
                                jobs will have to be permitted to carry on some civic activity, and
                                possibly political activity if by political activity you mean
                                employment in a government field. The provision as written would
                                preclude any Party member from voting, practising law, or taking any
                                part at all in any municipal or other governmental activity. I just
                                do not believe that this is practicable and some modification of
                                this language may be necessary in order to enable the military
                                government to function.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">John J
                                McCloy</hi></signed></closer>
                            <pb facs="0166" n="110" xml:id="pg_110"/>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]<note n="5" xml:id="d88fn5">Not filed with the ribbon copy of McCloy’s letter to
                                            Matthews, above; sup plied from Roosevelt Papers. McCloy
                                            also sent a copy of this draft to Hopkins on September
                                            6, 1944 (Hopkins Papers), and another copy is in the
                                            Morgenthau Diary, vol. 768 (see <hi rend="italic">Morgenthau Diary</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>), vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                                            509).</note></seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Draft of an Interim Directive to the Supreme
                                        Commander, Allied Expeditionary Force</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Eisenhower</hi>)<note n="6" xml:id="d88fn6"><p>At the same time that this draft directive was in
                                            preparation, a draft <hi rend="italic">Hand-hook of
                                                Military Government in Germany</hi>, prepared to
                                            provide guidance to military government officers on the
                                            objectives of military government, was under discussion
                                            in Washington. Morgenthau called Roosevelt’s attention
                                            to the <hi rend="italic">Handbook</hi> and in a
                                            memorandum for the President dated August 25, 1944,
                                            quoted extracts which he considered particularly
                                            objectionable. Using the Morgenthau memorandum as a
                                            basis, Roosevelt instructed Stimson on August 26 to
                                            withdraw the <hi rend="italic">Handbook</hi>.
                                            Roosevelt’s memorandum to Stimson stated: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                <p>“It is of the utmost importance that every person
                                                  in Germany should realize that this time Germany
                                                  is a defeated nation. I do not want them to starve
                                                  to death but, as an example, if they need food to
                                                  keep body and soul together beyond what they have,
                                                  they should be fed three times a day with soup
                                                  from Army soup kitchens. That will keep them
                                                  perfectly healthy and they will remember the
                                                  experience all their lives. The fact that they are
                                                  a defeated nation, collectively and individually,
                                                  must be so impressed upon them that they will
                                                  hesitate to start any new war.</p>
                                                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                                                <p>“There exists a school of thought both in London
                                                  and here which would, in effect, do for Germany
                                                  what this government did to its own citizens in
                                                  1933 when they were flat on their backs. I see no
                                                  reason for starting a <gloss target="#t_WPA1">WPA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_PWA1">PWA</gloss>,
                                                  or a <gloss target="#t_CCC1">CCC</gloss> for
                                                  Germany when we go in with our Army of
                                                  Occupation.</p>
                                                <p>“Too many people here and in England hold to the
                                                  view that the German people as a whole are not
                                                  responsible for what has taken place—that only a
                                                  few Nazi leaders are responsible. That
                                                  unfortunately is not based on fact. The German
                                                  people as a whole must have it driven home to them
                                                  that the whole nation has been engaged in a
                                                  lawless conspiracy against the decencies of modern
                                                  civilization.”</p>
                                            </quote></p>
                                        <p>For the text of Morgenthau’s memorandum to Roosevelt, see
                                                <hi rend="italic">Morgenthau Diary</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Germany</hi>), vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 440–442. For the full
                                            text of Roosevelt’s memorandum to Stimson, see <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 443–445; <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_544"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 544</ref>–<ref target="frus1944v01#pg_546">546</ref>.</p></note></head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top
                                        secret</hi></seg>
                                </opener>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Interim Directive to <gloss target="#t_SCAEF1">SCAEF</gloss> Regarding the Military
                                        Government of Germany in the Period Immediately Following
                                        the Cessation of Organized Resistance</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps">Post-Defeat</hi>)</p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>In the event that <gloss target="#t_RankinC1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rankin “C”</hi></gloss> conditions
                                        obtain in Germany or that the German forces are either
                                        defeated or surrender before you have received a directive
                                        containing policies agreed upon by the three governments of
                                        the U.S., U.K. and U.S.S.R., you will be guided by the
                                        following policies, principles and instructions.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Your primary objectives are of short term and military
                                        character rather than of a long view governmental policy
                                        type. Germany will not be occupied for the purpose of
                                        liberation but as a defeated enemy nation. The clear fact of
                                        German military defeat and the undesirability of the results
                                        of aggression must be appreciated by all levels of the
                                        German population. The German people must bear the
                                        inevitable <pb facs="0167" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/>
                                        consequences of their own acts. Your occupation and
                                        administration will be just but firm and distant. You will
                                        strongly discourage fraternization between Allied troops and
                                        the German officials and population.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>Military government will be established and will extend
                                        over all parts of Germany under your command. Your rights,
                                        powers and status in Germany are based upon the
                                        unconditional surrender or the complete defeat of
                                        Germany.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. By virtue of your position you
                                        are clothed with supreme legislative, executive and judicial
                                        authority and power in the areas occupied by forces under
                                        your command. This authority will be broadly construed and
                                        includes authority to take all measures deemed by you
                                        necessary, desirable or appropriate in relation to military
                                        exigencies and the objectives of a firm military
                                        government.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. You are authorized at your
                                        discretion to delegate the authority herein granted to you
                                        in whole or in part to members of your command and further
                                        to authorize them at their discretion to make appropriate
                                        subdelegations.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">c</hi>. You should take the necessary
                                        measures to enforce the terms of surrender and complete the
                                        disarmament of Germany.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">d</hi>. The military government shall be
                                        a military administration which, until you receive further
                                        advices, will show the characteristics of an Allied
                                        undertaking acting in the interests of the United
                                        Nations.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>The administrative policies shall be uniform throughout
                                        those parts of Germany occupied by forces under your command
                                        subject to any special requirements due to local
                                        circumstances.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>Representatives of civilian agencies of the U.S. or U.K.
                                        Governments or of <gloss target="#t_UNRRA1">UNRRA</gloss>
                                        shall not participate unless and until you consider such
                                        participation desirable when it will be subject, as to time
                                        and extent, to decision by the Combined Chiefs of Staff on
                                        your recommendation.</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>It is contemplated that a tripartite administration by the
                                        U.S., U.K. and U.S.S.R. covering the whole of Germany will
                                        be established. You have previously received advices in this
                                        connection.</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>You are authorized as <gloss target="#t_SCAEF1">SCAEF</gloss> to enter into arrangements with the
                                        U.S.S.R. military commanders as may be necessary for the
                                        occupation of Germany by the three powers.</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>Appendix “A”, Political Directive; Appendix “B”, Financial
                                        Directive; Appendix “C”, Economic Directive; and Appendix
                                        “D”, Relief Directive, are attached hereto. At Appendix “E”
                                        there is a chart<note n="7" xml:id="d88fn7">Not attached to
                                            the source text.</note> suggestive of the tripartite
                                        form which military government for Germany might take. At
                                        Appendix “F” there is attached the draft instrument of
                                        unconditional surrender for Germany.<note n="8" xml:id="d88fn8">Not attached to the source text.
                                            Concerning the drafting of the German surrender
                                            instrument, see <ref target="frus1944v01#pg_484"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 484</ref>
                                            ff.</note></item>
                                </list>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <pb facs="0168" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Appendix “A”</head>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Political Directive</hi></p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The following persons will be arrested and held, pending
                                        receipt by you of further instructions as to their
                                        disposition: <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Adolf Hitler, his chief Nazi associates, and Nazi
                                                officials down to and including the secretaries of
                                                local party units.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>All persons suspected of having committed war
                                                  crimes.<note n="9" xml:id="d88fn9">There is the
                                                  following notation, in an unidentified
                                                  handwriting, in the margin opposite this
                                                  paragraph: “How many thousand?”</note></item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The leading officials of all ministries and other
                                                high political officials of Germany and those
                                                persons who have held high position, either civil or
                                                military, in the administration of German occupied
                                                  countries.<note n="10" xml:id="d88fn10">There is
                                                  the following notation, in an unidentified
                                                  handwriting, in the margin opposite this
                                                  paragraph: “Are they to be put to work while in
                                                  custody?”</note></item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Prominent Nazis holding important and key
                                                positions in (1) National and <hi rend="italic">Gau</hi> civic and economic organizations, (2)
                                                corporations and other organizations in which the
                                                government has a major financial interest, (3)
                                                industry, (4) finance, (5) education, (6) the
                                                judiciary, (7) the press and other agencies
                                                disseminating news and propaganda.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>All judges, prosecutors and officials of the
                                                People’s Court.</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Any national of any of the United Nations who is
                                                believed to have committed offenses against his
                                                national law in support of the German war
                                                effort.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>You will issue a proclamation dissolving the Nazi party
                                        and its affiliates throughout Germany. You will take all
                                        practicable measures to uproot and discredit Nazi doctrines.
                                        No secret organizations or societies of any kind shall be
                                        permitted. Property, real and personal, of the Nazi party
                                        and its affiliates, wherever found, will be regarded as
                                        public property.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>You will make special efforts to preserve all records and
                                        plans of <list>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The German government</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>German military organizations</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>All organizations engaged in military
                                                research</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>The Nazi party and affiliated organizations</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Security, criminal and ordinary police</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Nazi economic organizations and industrial
                                                establishments</item>
                                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)</label>
                                            <item>Institutes and special bureaus established in
                                                Germany, devoting themselves to race, political, or
                                                similar research.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>You will take immediate steps to abrogate all laws,
                                        decrees, regulations or aspects thereof, which discriminate
                                        on the basis of race, color, creed, or political opinions.
                                        All persons who are detained or placed in custody by the
                                        Nazis on these grounds will be released, subject to
                                        requirements of security and interests of the individuals
                                        concerned.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0169" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>The criminal and civil courts of Germany will be closed.
                                        After the elimination of all Nazi elements, at such time and
                                        under such regulations, supervision and control as you may
                                        determine, you may permit the courts to resume functioning.
                                        All politically objectionable courts, e.g., People’s Courts,
                                        will be abolished. All security and political police,
                                        excluding criminal and order [<hi rend="italic">ordinary?</hi>] police, but including the <gloss target="#t_Gestapo1">Gestapo</gloss> and <hi rend="italic">Sicherheitsdienst der <gloss target="#t_SS1">S.S.</gloss></hi>, will be
                                        disbanded, arrested and their members disarmed and held for
                                        disposition. Criminal and ordinary police, and such others
                                        as it may be proper to retain, must be purged of Nazi or
                                        otherwise undesirable elements, who will also be arrested
                                        and held for disposition. It is imperative to arrest and
                                        hold all high police presidents and leaders.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>No person in Germany, other than United Nations nationals
                                        as authorized by you, shall be permitted to possess arms of
                                        any character except that such local police as you may
                                        utilize to maintain order may be armed with such law
                                        enforcement weapons as you may deem appropriate.</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>You will decide whether the objectives of military
                                        government are better served by the appointment of officers
                                        of the occupation forces or by the use of the services of
                                        Germans. It shall be made clear to all other government
                                        officials and employees that their continued employment is
                                        solely on the basis of cooperation, performance and behavior
                                        satisfactory to you. The replacement of any local government
                                        officials who may be removed will rest with you. In general,
                                        the entire Nazi leadership shall be removed from all posts
                                        of authority and no person who was a member of the German
                                        General Staff or Supreme Command or the Nazi hierarchy will
                                        occupy any important govern mental or civilian position.
                                        Under no circumstances shall active Nazis or ardent
                                        sympathizers be retained in office for the purpose of
                                        administrative convenience or expediency.</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>Subject to the provisions of paragraph 11 and to the
                                        extent that military interests are not prejudiced, freedom
                                        of speech and press, and of religious worship will be
                                        permitted. Consistent with military necessity, all religious
                                        institutions will be respected and all efforts will be made
                                        to preserve historical archives, classical monuments and
                                        fine arts.</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Diplomatic and consular
                                        officials of countries at war with any of the United Nations
                                        will be taken into protective custody and held for further
                                        disposition. Diplomatic and consular officials of neutrals
                                        will be dealt with in accordance with instructions to be
                                        issued by the Combined Chiefs of Staff.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. All German diplomats and
                                        consular officials and other agents will be recalled. If
                                        their recall cannot be effected or if their recall is not
                                        practicable by reasons of nationality, their authority as
                                        agents for <pb facs="0170" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> Germany
                                        will be terminated. All records and files of these agents
                                        and officers will be ordered returned to Germany or
                                        otherwise made available for appropriate inspection.</item>
                                    <label>10.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. All practical measures will be
                                        taken to insure the health and welfare of United Nations
                                        nationals and neutral internees, including provision of
                                        employment as practicable, and repatriation should be
                                        undertaken as rapidly as military conditions permit. It
                                        shall be within your discretion to determine whether such
                                        persons should or should not be allowed to disperse, pending
                                        the completion of plans for their employment or other
                                        disposition.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. Nationals of countries with
                                        which any of the United Nations are or have been at war
                                        (except Germany) will be identified and registered, and
                                        those whose freedom of movement would endanger the security
                                        of the armed forces or be otherwise undesirable will be
                                        interned or their activities curtailed as may be necessary
                                        under the circumstances.</item>
                                    <label>11.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Propagation of Nazi doctrines
                                        and Nazi propaganda in any form shall be prohibited. All
                                        schools and universities will be closed. Elementary schools
                                        only will be reopened as soon as possible after Nazi
                                        personnel has been eliminated and text books and curricula
                                        provided which are free of Nazi doctrines. Further guidance
                                        on German education and schools will be given to you in a
                                        separate directive.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. No political activities of any
                                        kind shall be countenanced unless authorized by you. Unless
                                        you deem otherwise, no political personalities or organized
                                        political groups shall have any part in determining the
                                        policies of the military administration. It is essential to
                                        avoid any commitments to or negotiations with any political
                                        elements.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">c</hi>. The publication of all
                                        newspapers, magazines, weeklies and other publications and
                                        the operation of all German radio stations throughout the
                                        area under your command will be suspended. Thereafter you
                                        will permit the dissemination of news or information subject
                                        to such censorship and control as you consider necessary in
                                        the interests of military security and intelligence and to
                                        carry out the principles laid down in this directive.</item>
                                    <label>12.</label>
                                    <item>No persons shall be permitted to leave or enter the area
                                        under your command without your authority.</item>
                                </list>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Appendix “B”</head>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Financial Directive</hi></p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>United States, British and other Allied forces will use
                                        Allied Military marks and Reichsmark currency or coins in
                                        their possession. Allied Military marks and Reichsmark
                                        currency and coin now in <pb facs="0171" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/> circulation in Germany will be legal
                                        tender without distinction and will be interchangeable at a
                                        rate of 1 Allied Military mark for 1 Reichsmark. Records
                                        will be kept of the amounts of the German marks used by the
                                        forces of each nation. <hi rend="italic">Reichskreditkassenscheine</hi> and other German
                                        Military currency will not be legal tender in
                                        Germany.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>In the event, however, that for any reason adequate
                                        supplies of Allied Military marks and/or Reichsmarks are not
                                        available, the United States forces will use yellow seal
                                        dollars and regular United States coins and the British
                                        forces will use British Military Authority notes and regular
                                        British coins. Records will be kept of the amounts of
                                        currencies used by the United States and British
                                        forces.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>If it is found necessary to use U.S. yellow seal dollars
                                        and <gloss target="#t_BMA1">BMA</gloss> notes, the following
                                        provisions will apply to such use: <list>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>The rate of exchange between the U.S. yellow seal
                                                dollar and the <gloss target="#t_BMA1">BMA</gloss>
                                                notes will be 4.035 dollars to one pound, and the
                                                two currencies will be interchangeable at that rate.
                                                The United States Treasury will make the necessary
                                                arrangements with the British Treasury.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>You will issue a proclamation, if necessary,
                                                requiring all persons to accept U.S. yellow seal
                                                dollars and <gloss target="#t_BMA1">BMA</gloss>
                                                notes at the decreed rates. Transactions at any
                                                other rates will be prohibited.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>The issuance of yellow seal dollars and <gloss target="#t_BMA1">BMA</gloss> notes will cease and
                                                Allied Military mark and/or Reichsmark currency will
                                                be used in their place as soon as available.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>U.S. yellow seal dollars and <gloss target="#t_BMA1">BMA</gloss> notes will be
                                                withdrawn from circulation as soon as such
                                                withdrawal can be satisfactorily
                                                accomplished.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>Records will be kept of the amounts of such
                                                currencies used by the United States, British and
                                                other Allied forces.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The rate of exchange to be used only for the purpose of
                                        paying personnel of the armed forces will be——<note n="11" xml:id="d88fn11">Blanks in this paragraph appear in the
                                            source text.</note> marks to the dollar and —— marks to
                                        the pound sterling. A general rate of exchange may be
                                        furnished to you later. Holders of mark currency or deposits
                                        will not be entitled to purchase foreign exchange without
                                        special permission. They will obtain dollars or pounds, or
                                        any other foreign currency or foreign exchange credits, only
                                        in accordance with exchange regulations issued by
                                        you.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>The Financial Division of the Civil Affairs Section for
                                        Germany will include in its functions the control of all
                                        funds to be used by the Allied Military forces within the
                                        area, except yellow seal dollars and <gloss target="#t_BMA1">BMA</gloss> notes which will be under the control of
                                        U.S. and British forces respectively. It will maintain all
                                        the accounts and records necessary to indicate the supply,
                                        control, and movement of these currencies including yellow
                                        seal dollars and <gloss target="#t_BMA1">BMA</gloss> notes,
                                        and other funds, as well as <pb facs="0172" n="116" xml:id="pg_116"/> financial data required for the
                                        determination of expenditures arising out of operations or
                                        activities involving participation of Allied Military
                                        forces. <list>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>Insofar as operations relate to the provision of
                                                currencies for the pay and other cash requirements
                                                of military components of the Allied forces, the
                                                Financial Division will supply Allied Military marks
                                                from currency on hand and will record the debit
                                                against the military force concerned at the rate of
                                                exchange prescribed in paragraph 4 above.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>Insofar as operations relate to the provision of
                                                currencies for civil administration, the Finance
                                                Division will supply Allied Military marks from
                                                currency on hand and will record the debit against
                                                the Allied Military Government.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>If found practicable and desirable, you will
                                                designate, under direct military control and
                                                supervision, the Reichsbank, or any branch thereof,
                                                or any other bank satisfactory to you, as agent for
                                                the Financial Division of the Civil Affairs Section.
                                                When satisfied that the Reichsbank, or any branch
                                                thereof, or other designated bank, is under adequate
                                                military control and supervision, you may use that
                                                bank for official business, and, if necessary, by
                                                making credits available, place such bank or banks
                                                in a position to finance other banks and branches
                                                thereof, for the conduct of their business as
                                                approved by the Allied Military authorities.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>The records of the Financial Division of the Civil
                                                Affairs Section established within the area will
                                                indicate in all cases in what currency receipts were
                                                obtained or disbursements made by the Financial
                                                Division.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>You will take the following steps and will put into effect
                                        only such further financial measures as you may deem to be
                                        necessary from a strictly military standpoint: <list>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>You will declare a general or limited moratorium
                                                if you deem such measure to be necessary. In
                                                particular, it may prove desirable to prevent
                                                foreclosures of mortgages and the exercise of
                                                similar remedies by creditors against individuals
                                                and small business enterprises.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>Banks should be placed under such control as
                                                deemed necessary by you in order that adequate
                                                facilities for military needs may be provided and to
                                                insure that instructions and regulations issued by
                                                military authorities will be fully complied with.
                                                Banks should be closed only long enough to introduce
                                                satisfactory control, to remove Nazi elements and
                                                other objectionable personnel, and to issue
                                                instructions for the determination of accounts to be
                                                blocked under paragraph <hi rend="italic">e</hi>
                                                below. As soon as practicable, banks should be
                                                required to file reports listing assets,
                                                liabilities, and all accounts in excess of 25,000
                                                marks.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>You will issue regulations prescribing the
                                                purposes for which credit may be extended and the
                                                terms and conditions governing the extension of
                                                credit. If banking facilities are not available you
                                                may establish such credits or make such loans as you
                                                deem necessary for essential economic activities.
                                                These will be restricted to mark credits and
                                                loans.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>You will close all stock exchanges and similar
                                                financial institutions for such period as you deem
                                                desirable.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>Pending determination of future disposition, all
                                                gold, foreign currencies, foreign securities,
                                                accounts in financial institutions, credits, <pb facs="0173" n="117" xml:id="pg_117"/> valuable
                                                papers and all similar assets held by or on behalf
                                                of the following, will be impounded or blocked and
                                                will be used or otherwise dealt with only as
                                                permitted under licenses or other instructions which
                                                you may issue: <list>
                                                  <label>(1)</label>
                                                  <item>German national, state, provincial, and
                                                  local governments, and agencies and
                                                  instrumentalities thereof.</item>
                                                  <label>(2)</label>
                                                  <item>Other enemy governments, the agencies and
                                                  instrumentalities thereof and their
                                                  nationals.</item>
                                                  <label>(3)</label>
                                                  <item>Owners and holders, including neutral and
                                                  United Nations Governments or national
                                                  authorities, absent from the areas of Germany
                                                  under your control.</item>
                                                  <label>(4)</label>
                                                  <item>Nazi party organizations, including the
                                                  party formations, affiliates, and supervised
                                                  associations, and the officials, leading members,
                                                  and supporters thereof.</item>
                                                  <label>(5)</label>
                                                  <item>Persons under detention or other types of
                                                  custody by Allied Military authorities and other
                                                  persons whose activities are hostile to the
                                                  interests of the military government.</item>
                                                </list></item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>No governmental or private bank or agency will be
                                                authorized to issue banknotes or currency except
                                                that, if found practicable and desirable, you may so
                                                authorize the Reichsbank and the Rentenbank when
                                                they are under adequate military control and
                                                supervision.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>You will issue immediately a proclamation
                                                prohibiting all transfers of or other dealings in
                                                securities, other than central government
                                                securities, for such period as you may deem
                                                desirable. You may, however, prohibit or limit
                                                dealings in central government securities, but only
                                                pending resumption of service on the public
                                                debt.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>All dealings in gold and foreign exchange and all foreign
                                        financial and foreign trade transactions of any kind,
                                        including all exports and imports of currency, will be
                                        prohibited except as permitted under such regulations as you
                                        may issue relative thereto. Except as you may otherwise
                                        authorize, local banks will be permitted to open and operate
                                        only mark accounts, but if yellow seal dollars and <gloss target="#t_BMA1">BMA</gloss> notes are legal tender,
                                        they may be accepted at the decreed general rate of exchange
                                        and will be turned in as directed by you in exchange for
                                        mark currency at the decreed general rate of
                                        exchange.</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>Non-yellow seal U.S. dollar notes and regular British
                                        pound notes will not be legal tender. No person, agency or
                                        bank engaged in the exchange of money will acquire or
                                        otherwise deal in those notes except as you may so
                                        authorize. U.S. Army and Navy Finance Officers and British
                                        Paymasters may, however, be authorized to accept non-yellow
                                        seal U.S. dollar notes and regular British pound notes from
                                        United States and British Military or authorized personnel
                                        for con version into Allied Military mark or Reichsmark
                                        currency at the de creed general rate of exchange, after
                                        satisfying themselves as to the source of the notes.</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>All bona fide government pensions, allowances, and social
                                        security payments will continue to be paid, but steps will
                                        be taken as soon as practicable for a study of pensioners’
                                        records with a view to nullifying <pb facs="0174" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/> all unnecessary and undesirable
                                        pensions and bonuses of Nazi inception.</item>
                                    <label>10.</label>
                                    <item>The railways, postal, telegraph and telephone service,
                                        radio and all government monopolies will be placed under
                                        your control and their revenues made available to the
                                        military government.</item>
                                    <label>11.</label>
                                    <item>You will, consistent with international custom and usage,
                                        maintain existing tax laws, except that discriminatory taxes
                                        introduced under the Nazi regime will be abolished. Prompt
                                        action should be taken to maintain the inflow of revenue at
                                        the highest possible level. You will resume service on the
                                        public debt as soon as military and financial conditions
                                        permit.</item>
                                </list>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Appendix “C”</head>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Economic Directive</hi></p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>You will assume control of existing German industrial,
                                        agricultural, utility, communication and transportation
                                        facilities, supplies and services, and of German domestic
                                        and foreign trade, for the purposes of <list>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>Assuring the immediate cessation of the
                                                production, acquisition or development of implements
                                                of war.</item>
                                            <label><hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                            <item>Assuring the production and maintenance of goods
                                                and services essential <list>
                                                  <label>(1)</label>
                                                  <item>to prevent or alleviate epidemic or serious
                                                  disease and serious civil unrest and disorder
                                                  which would endanger the occupying forces and the
                                                  accomplishment of the objectives of the
                                                  occupation.<note n="12" xml:id="d88fn12">There is
                                                  a marginal manuscript notation on the source text
                                                  that the following language is to be inserted in
                                                  this paragraph: “and the necessity for the pro
                                                  vision of civilian relief”.</note></item>
                                                  <label>(2)</label>
                                                  <item>to the prosecution of the war against Japan
                                                  (but only to the extent that specific directives
                                                  of higher authority call for such goods or
                                                  services) and</item>
                                                  <label>(3)</label>
                                                  <item>to the provision of relief and
                                                  rehabilitation supplies to the Allied nations and
                                                  to the performance by Germany of such further acts
                                                  of restitution as may be determined by the Allied
                                                  governments.<note n="13" xml:id="d88fn13">At this
                                                  point in the source text there is the following
                                                  addition, in an unidentified handwriting: “(4) to
                                                  contribute to the expenses of the
                                                  occupation”.</note></item>
                                                </list></item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>You may impose such other economic measures as you deem
                                        necessary to prevent serious civil unrest and disorder which
                                        would endanger the occupying forces and the accomplishment
                                        of the objectives of the occupation.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>A plan should be prepared by you<note n="14" xml:id="d88fn14">A handwritten notation on the source
                                            text substitutes “You should take measures” for the
                                            first seven words of this paragraph.</note> to prevent
                                        transfers of title of real and personal property intended to
                                        defeat, evade or avoid the <pb facs="0175" n="119" xml:id="pg_119"/> orders, proclamations or decrees of
                                        the military government or the decision[s] of the courts
                                        established by it.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>Substantial amounts of private property of various
                                        categories has [<hi rend="italic">have</hi>] been seized,
                                        looted or otherwise improperly acquired by various Nazi
                                            officials.<note n="15" xml:id="d88fn15">The last four
                                            words of this sentence have been changed by hand on the
                                            source text to read “the Nazi Govt, its officials and
                                            nationals”.</note> While it is contemplated that a
                                        suitable commission will ultimately deal with this problem,
                                        you should take such steps as may be practicable to collect
                                        any available information and to preserve<note n="16" xml:id="d88fn16">The source text has been changed at
                                            this point to read “to identify, preserve and
                                            control”.</note> any property of this kind found in the
                                        area under your control.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">a</hi>. All property in the German
                                        territory belonging to any country with which any of the
                                        United Nations are, or have been, at war may be controlled,
                                        subject to such use thereof as you may direct.</item>
                                    <label/>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">b</hi>. Your responsibility for the
                                        property of the United Nations, other than U.K. and U.S. and
                                        their nationals, in areas occupied by Allied forces shall be
                                        the same as for the property of U.K. and U.S. and their
                                        nationals, except where a distinction is expressly provided
                                        by treaty or agreement. Within such limits as are imposed by
                                        the military situation you should take all reasonable steps
                                        necessary to preserve and protect such property.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>You will permit the formation of democratic labor unions
                                        and other forms of free economic association, exercising
                                        safeguards necessary to eliminate Nazi labor institutions
                                        and to prevent or eradicate underground, secret, or
                                        subversive activities or organizations.</item>
                                </list>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <head>Appendix “D”</head>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Relief Directive</hi></p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>You will be responsible for the provision and distribution
                                        of sup plies for civilian relief, to the extent defined
                                        below, in all areas of Germany under your command. In
                                        connection with this responsibility, you will make maximum
                                        use of supplies, stockpiles and resources available within
                                        Germany in order to limit the extent to which imports, if
                                        any, will be required.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The scale of relief to be provided will in no event exceed
                                        the minimum quantity of food, fuel, medical, sanitary and
                                        agreed essential supplies necessary to maintain the health
                                        and working capacity of the civilian population, to preserve
                                        public order, to develop local resources in order to lighten
                                        the burden on the Allied armies, and to accomplish the
                                        objectives of the occupation.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0176" n="120" xml:id="pg_120"/>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>You will provide for importation of civilian supplies into
                                        Germany only to the extent that critical shortages of any
                                        essential items threaten clear and imminent interference
                                        with the policies set forth in paragraph 2 of this
                                        directive.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>You will undertake measures necessary for the control,
                                        prevention and treatment of epidemic and other diseases and
                                        the promulgation of such medical and sanitation measures,
                                        including emergency shelter, as will preserve the state of
                                        public health and protect the occupying forces.</item>
                                </list>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>