<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>310. Memorandum From the Director of Military Assistance of the Department of
                    Defense (Heinz) to the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Near Eastern
                    and South Asian Affairs () to the Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Near
                    Eastern and South Asian Affairs (Schwartz))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">310</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-04-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-04-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="310"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                <head>310. Memorandum From the Director of Military Assistance of the Department of
                    Defense (<persName type="from">Heinz</persName>) to the Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary of Defense for Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName
                        type="to">Schwartz</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d310fn1"
                        >Source: Washington National Records Center, RG 330, OASD/ISA Files: 72 A
                        1498, 091.3 Saudi Arabia, 29 April 1968. Confidential. Copies were sent to
                        Director for Operations Joseph J. Wolf in the Department of State’s Office
                        of Politico-Military Affairs and Deputy Director of Military Assistance
                            <persName>James D. Dunlap</persName> in <gloss target="#t_DOD1"
                            >DOD</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">I-5794/68</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-04-29">April 29, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> for Saudi Arabia</item>
                </list>
                <p>Over the past three years Congress has questioned with increasing intensity the
                    rationale for a grant program to Saudi Arabia. Basically the concern is not with
                    providing training or a training mission to Saudi Arabia, but why Saudi Arabia
                    should not pay the expenses when they are so rich in oil and can afford to spend
                    large amounts to purchase military equipment as well as to aid Jordan.</p>
                <p>Each year the grant program has become more difficult to defend. Insofar as
                    student training is concerned, we have used the argument of having more control
                    over the program and being able to select the students. This argument is getting
                    weak, particularly since Saudi Arabia does purchase large amounts of other
                    training.</p>
                <p>Insofar as support of the <gloss target="#t_USMTM1">USMTM</gloss> is concerned,
                    we have stated that Saudi Arabia does provide assistance-in-kind of about $1.4
                    million for the Mission. Congress wonders why they cannot pay it all, and I <pb
                        facs="0626" n="594" xml:id="pg_594"/> find it difficult to justify, in view
                    of Saudi Arabia’s increasing expenditures and cash assets. The <gloss
                        target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> costs of maintaining <gloss target="#t_USMTM1"
                        >USMTM</gloss> will be about $600 thousand in <gloss target="#t_FY1"
                        >FY</gloss> 69, and will probably decrease in the future as we reduce the
                    size of the training mission.</p>
                <p>As <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> is reduced, it will become more and more
                    difficult to justify <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> funds of $600-$800
                    thousand annually for Saudi Arabia. Therefore I propose that we undertake to
                    have Saudi Arabia pick up all of its student training on a sales basis, and to
                    provide either a cash payment or contributed currency in the amount of <gloss
                        target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> costs associated with the support.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador probably would resist such an effort on the basis that it would
                    disturb the current relationships we have with Saudi Arabia, and that it is hard
                    to explain why the U.S. can’t afford this amount. The trouble is that while the
                    U.S. can, <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> can’t. My opinion is that we will
                    have to bite this bullet sooner or later, and the sooner we get started the
                    better.</p>
                <p>Saudi Arabia has freely picked up the tab for training missions in connection
                    with sales contracts. We have a large Army Engineer group there in connection
                    with the vehicle sales program. There are other trainers there supporting the
                    Hawk program. In fact, each sales contract with Saudi Arabia carries with it
                    costs for training.</p>
                <p>If we start now we should be able, for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 70, to
                    arrange to have Saudi Arabia pick up all student training costs on a sales basis
                    and to provide contributed currency to offset <gloss target="#t_USMTM1"
                        >USMTM</gloss> costs. I note that Ethiopia provides contributed currency to
                    offset MAAG costs and I see no reason why Saudi Arabia cannot do the same. There
                    should be a way of approaching this diplomatically without rocking the boat.
                    Saudi Arabia has always contributed assistance-in-kind toward the Mission costs,
                    and a new arrangement would require only that they also provide contributed
                    currencies. We would then be in a position to justify <gloss target="#t_USMTM1"
                        >USMTM</gloss> before being forced to do something about it by Congressional
                    action.</p>
                <p>Request your reaction to this proposal.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Luther C. Heinz</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="2" xml:id="d310fn2">Printed from a copy that indicates Heinz signed
                            the original.</note>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Vice Admiral, USN</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
