<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-02-25T18:39:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-02-25T17:05:00-05:00" n="391" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d391">
                        <head>391. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d391fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1964-66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 YEMEN. Secret. Drafted by
                                Sterner on February 28 and approved in S on March 28. The time of
                                the meeting is taken from Rusk’s Appointment Book. (Johnson
                                Library)</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1966-02-25T17:05:00-05:00" to="1966-02-25T18:39:00-05:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">February 25, 1966, 5:05–6:39
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Yemen</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>His Excellency <persName corresp="#p_SAMAAS1">Anwar
                                    al-Sadat</persName>, President of the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> National Assembly</item>
                            <item>His Excellency Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KM2">Mostafa
                                    Kamel</persName>, Ambassador of the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss>
                            </item>
                            <item>His Excellency Ahmad Hassan al-Feqi, Under Secretary of the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> Foreign Ministry</item>
                            <item>The Secretary</item>
                            <item>NEA—<persName corresp="#p_HRA2">Raymond A. Hare</persName>,
                                Assistant Secretary</item>
                            <item>NE—<persName corresp="#p_SRMM1">Michael Sterner</persName>, Escort
                                Officer</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Secretary said that since seeing <persName corresp="#p_SAMAAS1">Sadat</persName> last, he had had a chance to talk to the Saudi
                            Defense Minister, Prince Sultan, and get his views on the Yemen
                            situation. After hearing both the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss>
                            and Saudi views, the Secretary felt there were no major obstacles to
                            settlement. He would like to encourage the thought that with a little
                            more work on the part of both of these great countries the gap between
                            them could be narrowed.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SAMAAS1">Sadat</persName> hoped the Secretary’s
                            optimism would prove to be well founded. Since the Jidda agreement, the
                                <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss>’s objective in Yemen was to
                            evacuate its troops from the country completely. Now, in view of King
                            Faisal’s ambiguous attitude, the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss>
                            might be forced to change this objective. Faisal kept saying he wanted a
                            settlement in Yemen, but his acts were beginning to point to another
                            conclusion, and it was the acts that counted, not the words.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary hoped the Saudi reply, which should have been received in
                            Cairo by then, would be constructive. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SAMAAS1">Sadat</persName> said this raised another question. Suppose the
                            latest Saudi response turned out to be more of the same—sugared words
                            but no constructive action underneath—what should the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> do?</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he had the impression from his recent conversations
                            with both sides that the gap was not so great as might seem. It did not
                            appear to be one which further discussion had no hope of bridging. The
                            Secretary said he would like to make two comments, both against the
                            background of our relations with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> The fewer things that were said about the other
                            side publicly with sharp <pb facs="0769" n="737" xml:id="pg_737"/> edges
                            on them the better. Secondly, he strongly urged that a decision not be
                            made too quickly that further discussion was pointless. For one thing,
                            the alternatives to discussion were not too pleasant. The Secretary felt
                            diplomacy had a duty to be persistent.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SAMAAS1">Sadat</persName> agreed with the last
                            statement. Before coming on this trip he had met with President
                                <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> on Yemen and they had
                            agreed the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> would give Saudi
                            Arabia another two months, from the date that they informed the U.S.G.,
                            before deciding on a “change of strategy” in Yemen.<note n="2" xml:id="d391fn2">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KM2">Kamel</persName> later told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HRA2">Hare</persName> that this statement was not
                                intended to be an ultimatum. He said the intention of the Speaker
                                was to say that the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss>G. had
                                decided to wait at least another two months before reviewing the
                                situation to see whether a change of strategy was required.
                                [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Secretary said the U.S. would continue its friendly interest in a
                            settlement but we didn’t feel we could play a role that could substitute
                            for direct contact between the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss>
                            and Saudi Arabia. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SAMAAS1">Sadat</persName>
                            said he knew this was U.S. policy, but he wished the U.S.G. would give
                            further consideration to playing a helpful role. The <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> saw the need to compromise but it
                            could not abandon the field empty handed. The Saudis seemed now to want
                            the complete extinction of the Yemeni Republic and the total
                            discrediting of the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> for having
                            supported it. This the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> would
                            never accept. Aside from the blood and treasure the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> had expended in Yemen, there was the
                            consideration that the Yemeni Republic had been recognized by the U.N.
                            and most of the nations in the world.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary emphasized that internationally the U.S. had a great
                            interest in seeing peace maintained between Saudi Arabia and the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">U.A.R.</gloss> We also wanted to see a government
                            in Yemen that was acceptable to the Yemenis themselves. The Secretary
                            promised the U.S. would continue to follow the situation and if there
                            were things the U.S. might do to help matters along, we would give them
                            consideration.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>