<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-07-07T07:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-07-07T07:30:00-05:00" n="403" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d403">
                        <head>403. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Saudi
                                Arabia</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d403fn1">Source:
                                National Archives and Records Administration, RG 59, Central Files
                                1964-66, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 YEMEN. Secret;
                                    <gloss target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>. Repeated to Beirut,
                                Cairo, Kuwait, London, and Taiz.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Jidda</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-07-07T12:30:00+00:00">July 7, 1966,
                                1230Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>67. Jidda 36 (<gloss target="#t_NOTAL1">Notal</gloss>).<note n="2" xml:id="d403fn2">Dated July 5. (Ibid.)</note> Kuwaiti Mediation
                            Effort.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>In my first talk with King July 6 since his and my return to Jidda
                                (Jidda 66),<note n="3" xml:id="d403fn3">Dated July 7. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7 SAUD)</note> I recalled our
                                conversation in car en route <persName>JFB</persName> airport June
                                30 when King told me had just received details latest <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> proposal as conveyed by Kuwaitis.
                                King’s initial reaction had been <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                proposal represented retrograde step over what Kuwaitis had earlier
                                led <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> to believe was <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s position (Jidda
                                    1272),<note n="4" xml:id="d403fn4">Dated June 13. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 YEMEN)</note> but King had
                                wished study matter further following his return to Saudi Arabia. I
                                asked King if he had any further thoughts on subject and about
                                status of Saudi reply. King answered <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> still studying latest <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> proposals. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pharaon</persName> currently drafting reply for his
                                consideration. Observed he personally had not had much opportunity
                                since his return to consider question further in view heavy
                                accumulated backlog of work.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I recalled Secretary’s observation to King that most important
                                aspect Yemen problem is to get <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                troops out (<gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 867).<note n="5" xml:id="d403fn5">Telegram 867 to Jidda, June 24,
                                    summarized the Secretary’s June 22 conversation with King
                                    Faisal. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 7
                                    SAUD)</note> In this <pb facs="0798" n="766" xml:id="pg_766"/>
                                context I stressed need keep dialogue going and expressed hope that
                                King not overlook any practical opportunity achieve this aim even
                                though some price might have to be paid for it. While caution
                                clearly needed in dealing with Nasser, I urged that King earnestly
                                consider further areas of “give” which would not jeopardize Saudi
                                security. Where King felt he could not agree to <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> proposals as advanced by Kuwaitis,
                                I further urged he offer constructive counter proposals. Seemed to
                                me that area of disagreement was being reduced, even though slowly
                                and painfully, and it important effort do so continue. In this
                                context it also important that ways be sought give <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> honorable way out.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>King listened carefully. Re last point, claimed he had been
                                seeking offer <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                                honorable way out of Yemen for last three years. Trouble is
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> cannot be trusted.
                                He recalled had agreed with Secretary’s view on importance getting
                                    <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> troops out. He also recalled
                                Secretary’s observation that perhaps problem could be tackled
                                piecemeal, first by setting up Yemeni interim govt on 50-50 basis
                                and carrying on from there. Latter would have been consistent with
                                earlier Kuwaiti proposal which Saudis believed Kuwaitis had first
                                cleared with <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. Latest <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> proposal, as conveyed by Kuwaitis,
                                drops equal representation in interim govt and deliberately seeks
                                weigh govt on republican side. King emphasized he not prepared give
                                    <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> diplomatic victory in Yemen
                                when its massive military interventions had failed to achieve
                                this.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>King then dwelt on <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> insistence
                                that he specifically agree to exclusion <persName corresp="#p_HSA1">Hamid ad-Din</persName>. Reiterated he had no interest in
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HSA1">Hamid ad-Din</persName> or anyone
                                else in Yemen, but claimed sole purpose <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> desire name <persName corresp="#p_HSA1">Hamid
                                    ad-Dins</persName> is to achieve by political means what <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> has failed achieve militarily. King
                                candidly admitted that <persName corresp="#p_HSA1">Hamid
                                    ad-Din</persName> family, with all its shortcomings, is
                                currently core of royalist cause. In King’s view, the moment he
                                specifically agrees to exclusion <persName corresp="#p_HSA1">Hamid
                                    ad-Din</persName>, royalist cause will disintegrate and
                                transform into tribal rabble. <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> knows this which is sole reason, King
                                insisted, that <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> is so
                                persistent about point. Moment King agrees to specific exclusion
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HSA1">Hamid ad-Din</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> will leak word of it.
                                Thereafter, he will jettison any guarantee he has given and keep in
                                Yemen whatever number <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> troops
                                remain there. This is constant <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> tactic. I argued any such effort by <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> to renege on solemn
                                guarantee would mobilize world public opinion against him. King
                                dismissed argument saying world public opinion, even if it could be
                                mounted which he doubted, had never deterred <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> from overt or covert
                                activities against other states.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>King continued his position remains that interim Yemeni Govt, if
                                constituted on mutually agreeable basis, should be authorized
                                exclude <pb facs="0799" n="767" xml:id="pg_767"/> any Yemenis whose
                                continued presence is believed to be harmful to stability, but that
                                he would not agree to specific exclusion <persName corresp="#p_HSA1">Hamid ad-Din</persName> except after last <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> soldier out. Thereafter Yemeni
                                people could decide in plebiscite or any other way type of govt they
                                want for future and persons they want in it. If such Yemeni Govt
                                wants financial help, <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss>, along
                                with other states, would be prepared consider such help.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>I said I appreciated King’s position, but cautioned against <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> appearing inflexible. If latest
                                proposals not fully agreeable, I again urged that constructive
                                counter proposals be offered. For example, would 2/5-3/5 ratio be so
                                bad if Yemeni third force were charged to republican side. In any
                                event, once <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> troops out, there
                                likely be considerable realignment of political forces in Yemen on
                                both sides with various what are now republican and royalist
                                elements crisscrossing to form new groupings. I understood
                                anti-Egyptianism rampant in Yemen which should offer some safeguard
                                against <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> influence. As for
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HSA1">Hamid ad-Din</persName>, could they
                                perhaps be kept out during period of interim govt before plebiscite
                                or perhaps they might be withdrawn after larger number <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> troops out than half but before all
                                are out. I stressed I was advancing purely personal thoughts solely
                                for illustrative purpose to identify possible further areas of
                                “give” which might be explored in order to achieve principle aim
                                getting <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> troops out. King, in his
                                wisdom, Dr <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pharaon</persName> and other
                                Saudi officials intimately acquainted with Yemeni situation could
                                doubtless devise other even better alternatives which would show
                                    <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> willingness compromise, yet
                                prove viable. Important thing was that <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> dialogue carry
                                on. King said <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> would do utmost,
                                but noted “after three years of futile talks, <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> has tired US on Yemen just as
                                    <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> efforts with North Vietnam
                                to find peaceful solution have tired you.” I seized on this to
                                remind King that, despite all frustrations of Vietnam, President has
                                made it clear <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> continues search
                                for peaceful solution and is doing so. I hoped King would do
                                likewise in Yemeni situation. King merely responded “I will continue
                                to do my best.”</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>I shall also seek opportunity discuss matter with Dr <persName corresp="#p_PR1">Pharaon</persName> next few days. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1924 July 6<note n="6" xml:id="d403fn6">Telegram 1924 to Jidda, July 6, endorsed the
                                    Ambassador’s intention to further explore with the King specific
                                    areas of give in the Saudi position, and instructed him to
                                    encourage Faisal not to overlook any practical possibilities for
                                    achieving withdrawal of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                    troops from Yemen. (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                                    27 YEMEN)</note> just received. I believe my remarks consistent
                                with it.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_EHF1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Eilts</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>