<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>421. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in the
                    United Arab Republic</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d421</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">421</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1967-01-28T18:44:00-05:00" notAfter="1967-01-28T18:44:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-01-28T18:44:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-01-28T18:44:00-05:00" n="421"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d421">
                <head>421. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Arab Republic</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d421fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, RG 59, Central Files 1967-69, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                            >POL</gloss> 27 SAUD-<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. Secret;
                        Immediate. Drafted by Bennsky, <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Moore</persName>,
                        and Korn; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_DRP1">Davies</persName>, in
                        substance by Director of the Office of UN Political Affairs Elizabeth Ann
                        Brown, Quinn, and Judd; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_KNB1"
                            >Katzenbach</persName>. Also sent to Jidda and repeated to London,
                        Amman, Beirut, Kuwait, Sanaa, Dhahran, Taiz, <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                            >USUN</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CINCSTRIKE1">CINCSTRIKE</gloss>, and
                            <gloss target="#t_CHUSMTM1">CHUSMTM</gloss> Dhahran.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1967-01-28T18:44:00-05:00">January 28, 1967, 6:44 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>127476. Ref: State’s 127384,<note n="2" xml:id="d421fn2">Telegram 127384 to
                        Cairo, January 28, informed the Embassy that the Under Secretary had called
                        in <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KM2"
                            >Kamel</persName> to express U.S. concern over the <gloss
                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> air attacks on Najran. (Ibid.)</note>
                    Jidda’s 2926<note n="3" xml:id="d421fn3">Dated January 28. (Ibid., E
                        11-3)</note> and 2930.<note n="4" xml:id="d421fn4">In telegram 2930 from
                        Jidda, January 28, <persName corresp="#p_EHF1">Eilts</persName> proposed
                        possible measures to signal U.S. concern at the Najran bombings while also
                        demonstrating U.S. support for Saudi Arabia’s integrity, such as a public
                        statement, a strong U.S. démarche to <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                            >Nasser</persName>, a symbolic military gesture, and an effort to get a
                        leading international personality, possibly through UN channels, to mediate.
                        (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 SAUD-<gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                            >UAR</gloss>)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Acting Secretary made following points to <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                            >UAR</gloss> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KM2">Kamel</persName> this
                        afternoon re <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> bombing of Najran. <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> has informed us Najran bombed
                                twice January 27 by <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> aircraft
                                with loss at least eight lives, others wounded and property <pb
                                    facs="0825" n="793" xml:id="pg_793"/> damaged. One of these
                                raids reportedly witnessed by foreign journalists. We also have
                                reports of third raid on January 28.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>We have no evidence <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> has taken
                                any actions which would have provoked such bombing raids. Our
                                indications are Faisal has been making determined and successful
                                efforts restrain Yemeni royalists from resuming hostilities in
                                Yemen.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Such raids can only serve to harden positions and make solution in
                                Yemen more difficult reach.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Acting Secretary expressed <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>
                                concern (1) over these raids in an area of world where we have
                                strong interests and (2) that such incidents be avoided in this
                                region where we desire see peace and stability maintained.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>When these raids are reported by our press they will cause public
                                reaction which, as Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KM2"
                                    >Kamel</persName> knows, will make more difficult our joint
                                efforts improve US-<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> relations and
                                reach agreement on various matters under discussion between
                                us.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KM2">Kamel</persName> responded at length making
                        following points: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>He did not have facts this matter from his government.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Questioned fact foreign correspondents would be in out of way
                                place such as Najran as raising doubts validity alleged bombing
                                raids.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Gave detailed coverage Yemen problem from beginning, as seen from
                                Egyptian viewpoint, concluding that Faisal out to humiliate and
                                defeat Egyptians there rather than seeking mutually acceptable
                                solution allowing their withdrawal. Made strong pitch <gloss
                                    target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> should get active in Yemen matter
                                via mediation or other means as he had been urging for some
                                months.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>Emphasized Najran was base for royalist infiltrators who were
                                killing Egyptian “boys” and Egyptians could not give up right
                                self-defense. If <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> bombed Najran
                                there must have been provocation.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>In response Acting Secretary stated we believe it true <gloss
                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> planes had bombed Najran. He wanted
                        emphasize strongly that this in no way helped situation of <gloss
                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> or made solution Yemen problem easier.
                        Faisal has been restraining resumption royalist activities including
                        infiltration according to our information. Suggested correspondents could
                        have been in Najran because of recent reports gas bombing by <gloss
                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> in North Yemen near Saudi border.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KM2">Kamel</persName> said he would do his best
                        express <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> concern to his government and
                        requested we restrain Saudi Arabia from provoking <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                            >UAR</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Without specifically mentioning current top-level <gloss target="#t_USG1"
                            >USG</gloss> consideration <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> food
                        request, presentations Acting Secretary (and Dep. <pb facs="0826" n="794"
                            xml:id="pg_794"/> Asst. Sec. <persName corresp="#p_DRP1"
                            >Davies</persName> afterwards) gave <persName corresp="#p_KM2"
                            >Kamel</persName> clear impression <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss>
                        concern over bombing raids could at the least slow up the
                        deliberations.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">For Cairo</hi>: You requested take up Najran bombing raids
                        with highest appropriate level <gloss target="#t_UARG1">UARG</gloss> drawing
                        on Acting Secretary’s presentation paras 1 and 3 above for substance
                            démarche<note n="5" xml:id="d421fn5">In telegram 4219 from Cairo,
                            January 29, <persName corresp="#p_BLD2">Battle</persName> reported that
                            he had expressed U.S. concern over the bombing to Foreign Office Under
                            Secretary el-Feki, following the Department’s guidance, and had pointed
                            out that there were newspaper reports from journalists who had witnessed
                            the bombing. He noted that el-Feki, who was unable to give him an
                            official response, made no real effort to deny the fact of the bombings.
                            (Ibid.)</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">For Jidda</hi>: In response Saudi query re proposed US
                        action (paragraph 2, Jidda telegram 2925)<note n="6" xml:id="d421fn6">Dated
                            January 28. (Ibid.)</note> request you speak to Saqqaf as follows: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Inform him of foregoing representation in Washington and of
                                planned follow up in Cairo.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Should make clear to him that we deeply concerned over <gloss
                                    target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> action and that we indicating this
                                concern in response press queries. (Unprovoked attack on Saudi
                                territory should place <gloss target="#t_SAG1">SAG</gloss> in
                                powerful position vis-a-vis world press and public opinion. Presence
                                foreign journalists in Najran strengthens Saudi case.)</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Request he convey to King our renewed assurances of concern for
                                Saudi integrity and indicate that various courses action in support
                                Saudi Arabia are under active study by <gloss target="#t_USG1"
                                    >USG</gloss>. We understand need for rapid action. At same time
                                believe it of major importance that we avoid any precipitate step
                                which could redound to ultimate disadvantage of both Saudi Arabia
                                and US. King should be assured problem receiving urgent attention at
                                highest levels <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> and that we
                                prepared consult continuously with <gloss target="#t_SAG1"
                                    >SAG</gloss> re most useful courses action.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. Believe decision on issuance public
                        statement should be deferred until receipt <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                            >UAR</gloss> reaction to our démarches. Concerning recommendation for
                        dispatch infantry unit on “training mission,” we need better assessment
                            <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> intentions and motives before making
                        decision. Our 1963-64 experience with Operation Hard Surface demonstrated
                        problems involved in sending token force. If faced with determined <gloss
                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> action, would probably be necessary either
                        withdraw or strengthen such symbolic force. (May be appropriate allow <gloss
                            target="#t_USMTM1">USMTM</gloss> advisers travel Najran but would prefer
                        delay decision at least until Army Attaché Col. Broady returns from
                        projected visit.) We studying possibilities of action within UN framework
                        (initiated either by Saudis or others) or of prompting third party mediation
                        as suggested by Jidda. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</item>
                    <pb facs="0827" n="795" xml:id="pg_795"/>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">For London</hi>: Have informed British Embassy in general
                        terms of representation to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KM2"
                            >Kamel</persName>. You may similarly keep Foreign Office
                        informed.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
