<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-02-21T10:28:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-02-21T10:28:00-05:00" n="177" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d177">
                        <head>177. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the Soviet Union</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d177fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, POL US–USSR. Secret; Priority. Drafted and initialed by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HMJA1">Hillenbrand</persName> on February
                                19; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TWR2">Tyler</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GJC2">Guthrie</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>; and approved and initialed
                                by <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>. Repeated to Bonn,
                                London, Paris, and Berlin.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-02-21T10:28:00-05:00">February 21, 1963, 10:28 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1771. Eyes only for Ambassadors and <persName corresp="#p_LEAJ1">Lightner</persName>. In light of Chancellor’s attitude reported
                            Bonn’s 2149 repeated Moscow 243<note n="1" xml:id="d177fn1">See <ref target="#d176fn2">footnote 2, Document 176.</ref></note> and
                            weighing <pb facs="0512" n="490" xml:id="pg_490"/> all factors, we have
                            concluded that, given our underlying assumption that responsible
                            governments must do all they can to keep open channels of diplomatic
                            communication on issues as potentially explosive as Berlin, there is no
                            sound alternative to resumption of talks, now that Soviets have taken
                            initiative.</p>
                        <p>During course of next meeting with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> at which you will presumably have at least one
                            other subject to cover (wide diameter pipe), you should inform him along
                            following lines: 1) US Government has carefully considered statement
                            which Soviet Foreign Minister made during your meeting with him on
                            January 26;<note n="2" xml:id="d177fn2">See <ref target="#d171">Document
                                    171</ref>.</note> 2) you have been instructed to advise him US
                            agrees to resumption bilateral exploratory talks on Berlin and Germany
                            to see whether basis for fruitful negotiations exists; 3) US will not
                            have mandate to speak for three occupying powers in Berlin; 4) we have
                            weighted considerations as to best location for talks and would prefer
                            that they be held in Washington. Since we assume from <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s statement of January 26 that
                            this would be acceptable, we anticipate that Soviet Government will wish
                            to instruct Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                            accordingly.</p>
                        <p>In view of foregoing, believe you will wish to avoid any further
                            discussion of Berlin during meeting with <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>. If, however, he insists on making substantive
                            comments, you are sufficiently aware of US position to make appropriate
                            responses within your discretion. While we have not come to final
                            conclusions as to precise tactics which we will follow here, primary
                            objective of any resumed talks must obviously be to ascertain whether
                            Soviet position has in any way softened on vital question of continuing
                            Western troop presence. If <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s remarks make this appropriate, you may wish to
                            comment along same lines as reported penultimate para of Moscow’s 1764
                            of January 18,<note n="3" xml:id="d177fn3"><ref target="#d170">Document
                                    170</ref>.</note> noting that, if Soviets have any concrete
                            suggestions to make, they should do so when talks are resumed in
                            Washington.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. While we have considered fully case
                            for resumption of talks in Moscow, on balance we have concluded that
                            arguments in favor of Washington, with which you are familiar, seem
                            prevailing at this point. We will, of course, keep you fully informed of
                            all developments, and do not exclude later use of Moscow should this
                            prove desirable.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RD3"><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>