<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-10-18T10:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-10-18T10:40:00-05:00" n="229" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d229">
                        <head>229. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Germany</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d229fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, POL 38–10. Confidential; Immediate; Limit Distribution.
                                Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_AJC1">Ausland</persName> on October
                                17; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_CLD1">Clay</persName>,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> (in draft), <persName corresp="#p_TWR2">Tyler</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KD4">Klein</persName>, the Department of Defense (<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss>), <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>,
                                and <gloss target="#t_GER1">GER</gloss>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_DRH2">Davis</persName>. Repeated to Paris, Berlin,
                                London, Moscow, U.S. Element Live Oak, <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">SHAPE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CINCEUR1">CINCEUR</gloss>,
                                    <gloss target="#t_USAREUR1">USAREUR</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_USAFE1">USAFE</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-10-18T11:40:00-04:00">October 18, 1963, 11:40 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1130. Paris also for <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss>. Ref: Berlin
                            504, Bonn 1378.<note n="1" xml:id="d229fn1">Dated October 16, telegram
                                504 from Berlin reported that at their meeting on that day, the
                                Berlin Commandants agreed that the only way to settle Autobahn
                                harassments was to make convoy procedures “cut and dried” and convey
                                them tothe Soviet Union at a high level. (Ibid.) Telegram 1378 from
                                Bonn, also dated October 16, summarized a meeting of the Bonn
                                Quadripartite Ambassadorial Group that day, which discussed a
                                British convoy that was being held up by the Soviet Union. The Group
                                agreed that convoy procedures should be harmonized and the Soviet
                                Union notified about the agreedprocedures. (Ibid.)</note> Subject:
                            Allied Autobahn Convoys.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Possibility exists we may be faced with Soviet challenge on
                                autobahn in effort to impose new convoy procedures, this despite <pb facs="0634" n="612" xml:id="pg_612"/>
                                <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>’s categorical
                                assurances to Secretary that Soviets were not trying to change
                                procedures or cause incidents. Therefore, planning should proceed on
                                this assumption.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Soviets have been trying for some time to alter established
                                procedures for Allied autobahn convoys, as they relate to advance
                                notification and dismounting. They have alsobeen trying to get US to
                                adopt British and French practice of lowering tailgates on request,
                                although US vehicles are so constructed as to make this
                                unnecessary.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Question of advance notification has had checkered career over the
                                years, with practices varying widely. In recent past, however,
                                Soviets have sought to demand that the checkpoint be informed in
                                advance of all convoys of more than five vehicles. Although
                                notaccepting this requirement, Allies have so composed their convoys
                                as to avoid issue.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>So far as we are aware, dismounting to be counted is relatively
                                new practice, introduced by US convoy commander for first time when
                                US augmentation battle group sent to Berlin in August, 1961. Soviets
                                apparently took liking to practice and it became standard part of
                                convoy ritual. Allied practices have varied from timeto time, and
                                Soviet desires have never been entirely clear.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>During 1962 Allied authorities in Bonn and Berlin unsuccessfully
                                attempted to reach agreement on standard procedures. This attempt
                                apparently failed because US and French were unwilling to adopt UK
                                procedures. These went too far to meet Soviet demands, which USand
                                French deemed unreasonable. British were unwilling to adopt US
                                procedures since to do so would require them in effectto engage in a
                                roll-back vis-à-vis the Soviets.Bonn Embassies recommended to
                                governments that they agree to disagree on procedures but to back
                                each other in case of trouble. UK Foreign Office approved this
                                recommendation and declined our (bilateral) proposal to consider
                                question in Ambassadorial Group.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Recent Soviet actions have focused attention again on procedural
                                differences. Three Commandants in Berlin have suggested common
                                procedures to Live Oak and recommended that Soviets not be informed
                                of differing Allied procedures until attempt made to agree on common
                                procedures (Berlin 504). Quadripartite Bonn Ambassadorial Group
                                (Bonn 1378) has recommended to governments and Washington
                                Ambassadorial Group that Soviets be informed ofAllied procedures in
                                such a way as to preclude negotiations on procedures. It has also
                                recommended that this should be done independently of harmonization
                                but that subsequent attempt be made to harmonize procedures in such
                                way as to avoid weakening our position.</item>
                            <pb facs="0635" n="613" xml:id="pg_613"/>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item><p>We propose now to take up following questions on urgent basis
                                    in Ambassadorial Group: <list>
                                        <label>a.</label>
                                        <item>Should Allied governments make another attempt to
                                            agree on harmonized procedures?</item>
                                        <label>b.</label>
                                        <item>Whether procedures are harmonized or not, should
                                            Allies inform Soviets of their procedures?</item>
                                        <label>c.</label>
                                        <item>If so, in what form and where?</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>In view opportunity presented by recent incidents, we believe we
                                    should make serious new effort harmonize procedures. We are
                                    mindful, however, that convoy procedures, even on three disputed
                                    questions, are complicated, and it may not be easy to work out
                                    agreed formulae. We are now awaiting General <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName>’s recommendations
                                    (Berlin 504).</p></item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Whether we can agree on procedures or not, we are also inclined
                                support recommendations of Commandants and Bonn Ambassadors that we
                                inform Soviets. (We have already given Soviets certain information
                                on dismount procedure in connection recent convoy incident.)</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>Our attitude toward locale for informing Soviets will depend on
                                whether Allies agree on procedures. If we do, we would favor
                                aide-memoire delivered in Moscow. If we do not, we would favor
                                capitals.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RD3"><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>