<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-11-04T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-11-04T17:00:00-05:00" n="235" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d235">
                        <head>235. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Germany</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d235fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, POL 38–10. Secret; Immediate. Received at 6:58 p.m. and
                                passed to the White House at 7:50 p.m. and to the Office of the
                                Secretary of Defense, the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>, and
                                the CIA at 8:03 p.m. Repeated to Berlin, Moscow, Paris, London,
                                    <gloss target="#t_USAREUR1">USAREUR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CINCEUR1">CINCEUR</gloss>, and U.S. Element Live
                                Oak.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Bonn</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-11-04T23:00:00+01:00">November
                                    4, 1963, 11 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1677. Paris also for <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss> and Burns;
                                <gloss target="#t_USAREUR1">USAREUR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CINCEUR1">CINCEUR</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>s. Autobahn convoy.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>If, despite approach to <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss> Charge
                                and setting of time limit,<note n="1" xml:id="d235fn1">Regarding the
                                    approach to the Soviet Charge, see <ref target="#d234">Document
                                        234</ref>. At 10 p.m. the U.S. Provost Marshal with the
                                    convoy had delivered a 2-hour time limit ultimatum for release
                                    of the convoy; at midnight, when the time limit ran out, the
                                    convoy attempted to move forward, but was blocked by Soviet
                                        <gloss target="#t_APC1">APC</gloss>s. (Telegram 621 from
                                    Berlin, November 5; Department of State, Central Files, POL
                                    38–10)</note><gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss>s continue block
                                passage of convoy, I believe we should follow two-pronged course
                                designed (a) to put maximum pressure on SovGovt from point of view
                                its relations with US and (b) to intensify confrontation on Autobahn
                                (withoutany threat of resort to arms) to point where <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss>s realize we not likely to back down
                                and <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss> posture of detente placed in
                                jeopardy.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>To do this I would suggest following: <list>
                                    <label>A.</label>
                                    <item>US Charge in Moscow should be instructed make urgent
                                        approach highestavailable level emphasizing serious impact
                                        Autobahn harassments could have on our efforts find areas of
                                        accommodation with USSR.</item>
                                    <label>B.</label>
                                    <item>As soon as possible thereafter non-dismount convoy, of
                                        approximately same makeup as US–2, should be dispatched from
                                        Berlin westward. If held up publicity, and pressure on
                                            <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss>s, certain to
                                        mount.</item>
                                    <label>C.</label>
                                    <item>Agreement of other governments should be sought to
                                        authorize Live Oak to order Free Style assembly.<note n="2" xml:id="d235fn2">At 7:30 p.m. Washington time, the Joint
                                            Chiefs of Staff, in a Flash message, ordered the
                                            assembly of a Free Style probe. (<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> 3399 to <gloss target="#t_CINCEUR1">CINCEUR</gloss>; Kennedy Library, National Security
                                            Files, Countries Series, Germany, Berlin, Autobahn
                                            Crisis)</note> Word of this will undoubtedly reach
                                        Moscow, particularly in light recent activation, and would
                                        make <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss>s realize they face
                                        more intensified tripartite action.</item>
                                    <label>D.</label>
                                    <item>British and French Govts should be requested make
                                        supporting demarches in Moscow, emphasizing <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss> interference with Berlin
                                        access is matter of most serious joint concern.</item>
                                    <label>E.</label>
                                    <item>If no progress made in 48 hours some form of tripartite
                                        convoy should be launched, clearly in non-dismount category.
                                        Some modification of Free Style might be used for
                                        thispurpose. Important point would <pb facs="0645" n="623" xml:id="pg_623"/> be to emphasize tripartite nature of
                                        exercise. If passageprevented, <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss>s will stand in defiance all three govts and
                                        should by then be under most serious pressure both in terms
                                        of worldwide publicity and prospects of imminent deflation
                                        of their peaceful coexistence posture.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>I believe approach along above lines would have good chance of
                                success without serious danger of exchange of fire. If it fails,
                                then we would be clearly in second phase of contingency plans with
                                invocation of further diplomatic pressures, non military
                                countermeasures, and preparatory military and precautionary
                                measures.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> should, of course, be kept
                                fully informed.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Foregoing has been discussed over KY–9 with <persName corresp="#p_PMGJH1">Gen Polk</persName> who concurs. Suggest
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">Lemnitzer</persName> may also wish
                                comment directly to Washington.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>If Department approves course of action suggested, it may wish to
                                alert Allies in Washington today,<note n="3" xml:id="d235fn3">The
                                    Department of State informed the Washington Ambassadorial Group
                                    along these lines at a meeting at 10 p.m. (Telegram 1353 to
                                    Bonn, November 4; Department of State Central Files, POL
                                    38–10)</note> or authorize us to do so here where we have time
                                    advantage.<note n="4" xml:id="d235fn4">At 3 a.m. on November 5,
                                    the Mission at Berlin transmitted its strong endorsement of this
                                    course of action. (Telegram 610 from Berlin; ibid.) 3
                                4</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_MGGC2"><hi rend="strong">McGhee</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>