<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-05-12T18:55:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-05-12T18:55:00-05:00" n="49" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d49">
                        <head>49. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Germany</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d49fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 762.00/5–1262. Secret. The source text indicates that the
                                telegram was drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>, but he told <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> in a telephone call at 3:48 p.m. that the
                                President had “worked hard on it in an effort to communicate sharply
                                with the old gentleman.” (Ibid., Rusk Files: Lot 72 D 192) It was
                                cleared by <persName corresp="#p_TWR2">Tyler</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HMJA1">Hillenbrand</persName> and
                                initialed by <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-05-12T19:55:00-04:00">May
                                    12, 1962, 7:55 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>3100. Eyes only Ambassador. Following which supplements <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL1">Deptel</gloss> 3071<note n="1" xml:id="d49fn1">Telegram 3071, May 9, transmitted the text of a broadcast by Daniel
                                Schorr that morning that stated that the Chancellor was torpedoing
                                the U.S.-Soviet talks and recited a list of German grievances. The
                                telegram stated that this and other similar statements out of Bonn
                                could only be damaging to the President’s relations with the
                                Chancellor. If the Chancellor had serious reservations about U.S.
                                policy, the President expected “to hear about them directly and not
                                through offensive remarks repeated by journalists.” (Ibid., Central
                                Files, 762.00/5–962)</note> is intended to provide broader framework
                            for your talk with Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK3">Adenauer</persName>. You may wish to begin by saying that we regret
                            situation which has developed and which has resulted in sensational
                            press treatment and speculation detrimental to our common interests.
                            Both sides need to take stock, to correct misconceptions and to plan
                            course for future which will avoid repetition of events of past few
                            weeks. It is in this spirit that US Government has instructed you to
                            make observations which follow.</p>
                        <p>On Berlin question, we are sending you in separate telegram chronologies
                            relating to consultation on “Principles Paper” and International Access
                            Authority paper.<note n="2" xml:id="d49fn2">Telegram 3095 to Bonn, May
                                12. (Ibid., 762.0221/5–1262)</note> You may wish to draw on these as
                            appropriate to illustrate that process of substantive consultation with
                            Germans has been both continuing and full. In this connection, you may
                            also draw as pertinent on various messages repeated to Bonn reporting on
                            Secretary’s discussions with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Point on consultation leads logically to Chancellor’s alleged feeling, as
                            indicated to General <persName corresp="#p_CLD1">Clay</persName> in
                            Berlin, that he was badly treated because he had not received reply to
                            his letter of April 14, 1962, to President.<note n="3" xml:id="d49fn3"><ref target="#d37">Document 37</ref>.</note> You may wish to
                            note that, upon his return here, General <persName corresp="#p_CLD1">Clay</persName> had mentioned the Chancellor’s feeling in this
                            matter. You might point out that, on April 15, 1962, Secretary of State
                            discussed telephonically Chancellor’s letter with President, who was in
                            Virginia over Sunday. You were thereafter directed immediately by
                            telephone to communicate to <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> that, while Secretary would go ahead with his
                            scheduled meeting with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                            on April 16, he would not put forward any further <pb facs="0165" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/> paper at this meeting. You might add that
                            while you were unable to reach <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> you did reach Dr. <persName corresp="#p_CK1">Carstens</persName> on evening April 15, who said he would inform
                            both Chancellor and Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> same evening. In view of this prompt response
                            to Chancellor’s letter which dealt with no other subject, a formal reply
                            was not considered necessary as it was assumed governments would be in
                            touch with each other in continuous consultation on substance of Western
                            position. At almost same time, unfortunate leaks occurred of which we
                            are all too sadly aware and distracted attention from normal
                            consultative process.</p>
                        <p>You should note that we had impression Athens meeting between Foreign
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_SG3">Schroeder</persName> and Secretary
                            of State as well as between four Western Foreign Ministers<note n="4" xml:id="d49fn4">See <ref target="#d45">Document 45</ref> and <ref target="#d45fn5">footnote 5</ref> thereto.</note> had gone off
                            in good fashion, had cleared up remaining misconceptions and had
                            resulted in large measure of agreement. Consultations in Athens between
                            senior officials of two countries carried forward work on substantive
                            paper, and we are now awaiting through regular diplomatic channels final
                            German response to points worked out at Athens ad referendum. We were,
                            therefore, naturally surprised by press reports and speculations
                            following upon Chancellor’s two press conferences in Berlin which tended
                            to create impression of major differences between us.</p>
                        <p>At this point line of argument set forth in <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL1">Deptel</gloss> 3071 should be presented, but last two sentences of
                            Schorr broadcast should be omitted.</p>
                        <p>You should supplement <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL1">Deptel</gloss> 3071 by
                            emphasizing that continuing reports from Bonn in recent days have
                            carried similar material. You should state as your own view this can
                            only be increasingly irritating to the President and may raise in his
                            mind a question whether German and American understanding is clear as he
                            thought it was in his most satisfactory meeting with the Chancellor last
                            November. You should state that it is this stream of reports of private
                            comments, rather than any particular disagreement over a minor
                            negotiating tactic, that is bound to give the President concern.</p>
                        <p>You should point out as your own observation that Chancellor probably has
                            no idea how many accounts of this kind have been reported by
                            newspapermen, broadcasters, and weekly journalists in recent weeks. If
                            Chancellor should attempt a denial, you should indicate that there are
                            so many of these sources that the President cannot be expected to
                            believe that their accounts are invented. Finally, you should indicate
                            as your own idea that a President who has plenty of important and
                            pressing political problems on all fronts can hardly be expected to look
                            with good humor on hints that these things were all done better by <pb facs="0166" n="144" xml:id="pg_144"/>
                            <persName>John Foster Dulles</persName>. It is a principle of this
                            Administration that President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> and not <persName>John Foster Dulles</persName>
                            is now in charge of foreign policy.</p>
                        <p>You should then expand on the President’s basic views as you understand
                            them. Beginning after Vienna last June he committed his country to a
                            major military response to <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName>’s challenge. 160,000 reserves were called to
                            service; the budget was unbalanced by an additional three and one-half
                            billion dollar defense appropriation, and the United States took the
                            lead in determined preparations to meet all contingencies arising from
                            the Berlin crisis. The response of the US to this crisis far exceeded
                            that of any other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> nation, both
                            absolutely and relatively. And as the crisis deepened each moment of
                            real test found the US at the center of responsibility. Every test of
                            will in Berlin has been a test fundamentally for the US, and you may
                            wish to note that each of these tests has been passed, so that in spite
                            of the Wall the self-confidence of Berlin has been essentially restored,
                            as the Chancellor will have seen last week. <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. Our information is that the Berliners are much less
                            troubled with the particular provisions of the International Access
                            Authority than some of those in Bonn. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>The President thus does not understand public or private doubts about the
                            determination of the US and he understands still less any inclination
                            for Germans to say that General <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De
                                Gaulle</persName> is the only hope; General <persName corresp="#p_DGC1">De Gaulle</persName> has talked very energetically
                            but has thus far done very little; there are still only 2 French
                            divisions in West Germany. It is American determination and not French
                            rhetoric that is holding the line against Soviet pressure. Moreover, we
                            not only carry the main burden in Berlin but the overwhelming
                            responsibility also for the critical areas of Southeast Asia which are
                            under Communist pressure. Statesmen like the Chancellor, whose principal
                            concern is with the resistance of Communism, should be the first to
                            understand that covert criticism of the US is destructive.</p>
                        <p>Nor does the President understand how there can be an objection at this
                            late date to the diplomatic explorations on Berlin which have been going
                            on. At every stage these have been the subject of intense and careful
                            consultation, and if the Chancellor has been surprised at any point it
                            can only be because he did not fully inform himself of the work of his
                            own government. Thus the President was indeed startled by the
                            Chancellor’s letter of April 14th with its sudden and unexplained
                            request that negotiations be discontinued. What the President did, as
                            the Chancellor knows, was to continue the discussions without putting
                            into them anything that had not long been agreed between our two
                            countries. The US remains determined to continue this close
                            consultation, but the President is glad that the Federal Government now
                            definitely supports further negotiation.</p>
                        <pb facs="0167" n="145" xml:id="pg_145"/>
                        <p>The President, in short, is determined to keep on with the double policy
                            of strong military defense and a constant search for an honorable
                            settlement if possible. He fully understands and has repeatedly stated
                            himself that negotiations may not succeed. But he believes the effort
                            must be made.</p>
                        <p>If appropriate opportunity occurs you should also make it clear to the
                            Chancellor that we would be greatly troubled if there were any serious
                            change in his government’s long-stated desire to have Great Britain join
                            the Common Market. Arguments on this point are being sent forward
                                separately,<note n="5" xml:id="d49fn5">Not found.</note> and the
                            President thinks you may wish to press them with the Foreign Secretary
                            and other Bonn officials rather than directly with the Chancellor. But
                            there should be no doubt in anyone’s mind that if Bonn should join Paris
                            in making entry into the Common Market unreasonably difficult, the main
                            responsibility for results will fall on Germany and not on France, with
                            grave consequences to Bonn’s position in the Western alliance.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RD3"><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>