<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The United States Political Adviser for Germany
                        (
                        Murphy
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d213</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">213</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-05-31T14:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-05-31T14:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-05-31T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-05-31T14:00:00-05:00" n="213" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d213">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">864.412/5–3146: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi>
                        (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-05-31T21:00:00+02:00">May 31, 1946—9 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received June 1—10:10 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1392. Refourdes 2113, February 27, 1946 and note from American Mission to the
                    Vatican dated April 30, 1946,<note n="8" xml:id="d213fn8">In a note of December
                        22, 1945, to the Assistant to the Personal Representative of President
                        Truman to Pope Pius XII, the Vatican Secretariat of State, on behalf of the
                        Catholic people of Hungary, requested that the Hungarian crown might either
                        be returned to Church authorities in Budapest or entrusted to the Vatican
                        for safe keeping. Copies of the note were subsequently sent to the
                        Department as well as to Murphy in Berlin on January 22, 1946.
                        (864.404/1–2246) Despatch 2113, February 27, 1946, from Berlin, transmitted
                        a note which Murphy had sent to the President’s Personal Representative to
                        Pope Pius XII stating that restitution to Hungary was not being made, but
                        that the Vatican might be invited to present any available information
                        regarding the history of the ownership of the crown and its presence in
                        Germany (864.412/2–2746). The Vatican Secretariat of State presented such
                        information in a <hi rend="italic">note verbale</hi> of April 25, a copy of
                        which was transmitted to Murphy on April 30, 1946 (846.404/4–3046).</note>
                    concerning the request of the Holy See on behalf of the Catholic people of
                    Hungary for restitution to the Church of the Crown of St. Stephen.</p>
                <pb facs="0315" n="301" xml:id="pg_301"/>
                <p>Investigation indicates that Crown in question was not removed from Hungary by
                    force but was turned over to the American Army for safekeeping by Hungarian
                    authorities. Consequently it does not fall into the category of objects
                    restitutable as defined by quadripartite agreement. Hence its unilateral
                    disposition by US authorities would in no way violate quadripartite restitution
                    agreement. After consultation with <gloss target="#t_RDRDivisionOMGUS1">R.D. and
                        R Division OMGUS</gloss> it is suggested that matter be handled in one of
                    three ways: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Consign it to the Holy See for safekeeping until such time as it can
                            be safely returned to Hungary. <hi rend="italic">Note verbale</hi> from
                            the Vatican April 25 states that Cardinal Mindszenty, Primate of
                            Hungary, recommends this action.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>Remove Crown to the US for trusteeship and safekeeping. In view of
                            purported great political and religious influence and significance of
                            Crown with Hungarian people, physical location in US may prove
                            advantageous for future bargaining or return at propitious time. Removal
                            to US might be made with agreement or knowledge of Hungarian Primate but
                            does entail possibility of public repercussions similar to those
                            resulting from shipment of German paintings to US.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Keep Crown in military collecting point in Germany until it can be
                            safely returned to Hungarian Church.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Department’s advice desired.<note n="9" xml:id="d213fn9">Telegram 812, August 14,
                        1946, to Budapest, repeated to Berlin and Rome, stated that the Department
                        viewed unfavorably alternatives 2 and 3 posed by American authorities in
                        Germany. It was the Department’s view that final disposition of the Crown
                        and other insignia should be in accordance with the wishes of the Hungarian
                        Government, and Schoenfeld was asked to ascertain the current views of the
                        Hungarian Government in the matter. (864.412/5–3146)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sent to Department as 1392, repeated to Rome as 31.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
