<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-12-14T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-12-14T04:00:00-05:00" n="369" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860C.00/12–1446: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Poland</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Lane</hi></persName>)<note n="76" xml:id="d369fn76">Ambassador Lane bad returned to Warsaw from
                                Washington on December 12.</note>
                            <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret   <gloss target="#t_Niact1">niact</gloss></hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Warsaw</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-12-14T10:00:00+01:00">December 14, 1946—10
                                    a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 10:47 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1930. I impressed on Mikolajczyk evening December 13 with great
                            earnestness our considered opinion that it would be most unwise for him
                            to make an appeal to Yalta Powers re steps taken against Polish Peasant
                            Party including arrests which Mikolajczyk estimated to be at least
                            10,000. (He estimated total of persons now under arrest for political
                            reasons to be at least 150,000. He said that after elections Bentinck
                            and I would be completely isolated and any Poles having dealings with us
                            would be arrested.) I argued that appeal to foreign govts would
                            undoubtedly be exploited by Polish Govt as treasonable net and would
                            result in elimination of Polish Peasant Party from the elections. Such
                            action would result in virtual boycott of elections by <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss> and possibly might bring about civil
                            war. This would in our opinion be greatest calamity which could befall
                            Poland and Polish people and might entail Soviet occupation for purpose
                            of “restoring order”. I continued that it is most important for
                            democratic political parties including <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss> to bear in mind public opinion in US which would
                            probably be from long range viewpoint greatest restraining force to
                            foreign domination of Poland. If Mikolajczyk should make such an appeal
                            to foreign govt over the head of his own Govt he would run risk of
                            incurring popular disfavor in US. If on other hand his party should
                            enter elections even though they should not be free his position could
                            not be effectively assailed.</p>
                        <p>Mikolajczyk replied that Executive Committee of <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss> had already taken decision to acquaint Yalta Powers
                            with facts of existing situation. He had succeeded in rejecting former
                            proposal of committee to appeal to three powers to supervise elections
                            but he could not resist consensus of party as evidenced by many
                            petitions signed by thousands that Yalta Powers should be informed (he
                            showed me one of such petitions). Mikolajczyk said communication to
                            three powers would not be an appeal but merely transmitting facts. He
                            said from practical viewpoint whether note to Yalta Powers is sent or
                            not effect will <pb facs="0551" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/> be the same:
                                <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss> candidates will not be permitted
                            to appear on lists in many districts and not at all in western provinces
                            and as soon as” elections are held Mikolajczyk will be tried for
                            treason. Mikolajczyk said that he has this information from many
                            reliable quarters. Furthermore he prophesied that civil war will take
                            place in April or May due to following three reasons: (1) fraudulent
                            elections; (2) economic crisis because of necessity of peasants being
                            forced to contribute 17 billion zloty prior to January 15 (4 billions
                            for internal loan 8 billions for land [?] 2 billions for agrarian reform
                            and 3 billions for seeds and horses) and (3) dissolution of Polish
                            Peasant Party.</p>
                        <p>I emphasized that proposed action of <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss>
                            would embarrass US Govt that I might be forced to reject his
                            communication and that in any case I felt sure I would not acknowledge
                            it. I said that our attitude should not be construed as hostility
                            towards Polish Peasant Party but that we did not wish to be accused of
                            dealing with only one political party which would result not only in
                            attacks on US but also on <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Mikolajczyk countered by saying that Yalta decision provides that British
                            and US Ambassadors should be kept informed of internal conditions here
                            and that <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss> therefore had right to
                            communicate with us. I said that in my interpretation Yalta decision
                            merely provided that British and US Ambassadors should keep respective
                            govts informed that this did not provide for govts to communicate
                            formally and directly with various parties. Mikolajczyk said that
                            communication would be made to three Embassies here and would not be
                            made public. He cited fact that to date his communication to Soviet Govt
                                (<gloss target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 1560 October 8) had not
                            been made public. He said furthermore that he did not expect us to
                            acknowledge his communication but he trusted we would not reject it as
                            this would be terrific blow to <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss>
                            hopes.</p>
                        <p>I requested him to inform Executive Committee re our conversation and
                            impress upon it our view. He said he would do so but he made it clear
                            that die had already been cast and that he could no longer resist
                            pressure from committee and from party as a whole especially because of
                            his having rejected committee’s proposal to request supervision of
                            elections by Yalta Powers.</p>
                        <p>Mikolajczyk did not attempt to conceal his concern re very critical
                            situation and probability of civil war shortly after elections are held
                            which he admitted could not be won by <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss> despite peasant majority in country. He was nervous and
                            at times spoke in low whisper apparently fearing he was being overheard
                            altho conversation was held in his private apartment.</p>
                        <p>I made point as discussed with <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>
                            officials that perhaps Communist <pb facs="0552" n="538" xml:id="pg_538"/> minority knowing strength of <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss>
                            might decide to allow free election be held and thus open way for
                            continuance of party. I emphasized that US could not take active
                            intervention in Poland and that any thought of such action should be at
                            once dispelled. Mikolajczyk replied that strength of <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss> was known to all and that after
                            elimination of <gloss target="#t_PSL1">PSL</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_PPS1">PPS</gloss> would be liquidated as indicated by
                            recent arrests of members of Polish Socialist Party. He said he realized
                            that result of election would not result in us initiating hostilities
                            but that note to Yalta Powers was “last hope”.</p>
                        <p>Conversation ended with Mikolajczyk promising to acquaint Executive
                            Committee with my views. I apprehend however that communication will be
                            sent to US and to British and Soviet Embassies. I recommend that I be
                            instructed not to reply to communication but that I accept it as a
                            matter of information for our Govt as one of the Yalta Powers. British
                            Ambassador concurs in my recommendation.</p>
                        <p>Please instruct by telegraph urgently.<note n="77" xml:id="d369fn77">Telegram 1190, December 16, to Warsaw, approved the recommendations
                                set forth by Ambassador Lane (860C.00/12–1446).</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Lane</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>