<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-02-12T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-02-12T13:00:00-05:00" n="390" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d390">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">871.00/2–846: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Representative in Rumania</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Berry</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-02-12T13:00:00-05:00">February 12, 1946—1
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>98. <gloss target="#t_urtel1">Urtel</gloss> 159, Feb. 8. I do not feel
                            that any purpose will be served by requesting further specific
                            confirmation from Groza of the guarantees he has already given in
                            writing and orally as set forth in note sent to him on Feb. 5. As
                            Tatarescu’s reply does not take issue with the statement contained in
                            that note of our understanding of those guarantees, it seems to me that
                            his reply may be regarded as a satisfactory formal acknowledgment of
                            those undertakings. I believe we will be more likely to obtain the
                            practical execution of those guarantees by maintaining vigilance and
                            protesting any violations as they occur than by engaging in further
                            correspondence in an effort merely to achieve more specific affirmation
                            of assurances already definitely given.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly please acknowledge receipt of Tatarescu’s communication along
                            the following lines: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“My Government has been pleased to receive the communication of
                                    Feb. 7, 1946 from the Minister for Foreign Affairs which my
                                    Gov’t. considers happily confirms the U.S. Gov’t.’s
                                    understanding of the assurances received from the Rumanian
                                    Government in execution of the decisions taken at Moscow. In the
                                    circumstances the U.S. Government is prepared to entertain a
                                    request for its agreement to the appointment of a Rumanian Envoy
                                    Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the United
                                        States.”<note n="44" xml:id="d390fn44">The note quoted here
                                        was delivered by Mr. Berry on February 14, and the text was
                                        released to the press by the Department on February 15; see
                                        Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                                        February 28, 1946, p. 298.</note></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>We are informing the Brit. Embassy in the foregoing sense.<note n="45" xml:id="d390fn45">Telegram 1701, February 11, from London, reported
                                that the Rumanian reply to the British note on recognition had been
                                a simple acknowledgment and did not contain any further guarantees.
                                The Foreign Office felt that it would be useless to press for any
                                additional guarantees from the Rumanian Government.
                                (871.01/2–1146)</note></p>
                        <p>Sent to Bucharest, repeated to London, Moscow, and Sofia.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>