<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chief of the United States Representation on the Allied
                        Control Commission for Rumania (
                        Schuyler
                    ) to the War Department</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d449</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">449</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-11-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-11-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-11-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="449" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d449">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">871.00/11–946: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chief of the United States Representation on the Allied
                        Control Commission for Rumania</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schuyler</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">War Department</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bucharest</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-11-16">16 November
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>R–102. Mister Berry last evening transmitted to me instructions just received
                    from the State <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> in its message number 723
                    dated 14 Nov. The <gloss target="#t_ACC1">ACC</gloss> action contemplated by
                    these instructions appears to be based upon incomplete knowledge of the actual
                    British position in the matter. I have discussed the problem with the British
                    political and military representatives in Rumania who have shown me all
                    pertinent communications and have particularly emphasized to me the following
                    considerations: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>HMG never contemplated taking up directly in <gloss target="#t_ACC1">ACC</gloss> Rumania the question of assuming free elections but
                            rather proposed a joint approach to the Moscow Govt urging that that
                            government issue appropriate instructions to the <gloss target="#t_ACC1">ACC</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>HMG now considers it is now too late for even that approach and
                            prefers to let the matter rest entirely on the basis of its
                            communication to the Rumanian Govt, including its final note which is to
                            be delivered at noon today and with which I am familiar.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>HMG considers it highly undesirable approach the matter at this time
                            in the <gloss target="#t_ACC1">ACC</gloss>, anticipating merely a rebuff
                            from the Russians which they fear might draw attention from the
                            importance of their last note to the Rumanian Govt.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>HMG considers it also undesirable to base any protest of the Russians
                            on a polite note from the opposition parties. HMG considers it
                            preferable to discuss the entire matter of political fraud in Rumania on
                            a high level after the elections have been completed, at a time when the
                            general question of the conduct of the electoral <pb facs="0667" n="653" xml:id="pg_653"/> campaign can be brought up, on the basis of
                            factual observation by British representatives in Rumania.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Mister Berry and I both interpret the instructions in State <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> message number 723 to require my action in
                    the <gloss target="#t_ACC1">ACC</gloss> only if and when my British colleague is
                    prepared to take parallel action. Since his instructions do not permit him to
                    take the initiative or to parallel or support me, I am not approaching Susaikov
                    on this question unless I receive further definite instructions to this effect.
                    In this connection both Berry and I believe it is now too late to warrant an
                    attempt to provoke <gloss target="#t_ACC1">ACC</gloss> action; even assuming
                    Russian willingness to discuss the question in the <gloss target="#t_ACC1">ACC</gloss> (which I consider most unlikely), that we could not reasonably
                    expect at this late date the <gloss target="#t_ACC1">ACC</gloss> to issue
                    instructions to the Rumanian Government which would require that Government to
                    alter its electoral procedures through entire nation on 19 Nov, only 2 days
                    away.</p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Schuyler</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
