<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-12-03T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-12-03T13:00:00-05:00" n="457" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d457">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">871.00/12–346: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Representative in Rumania</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Berry</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bucharest</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-12-03T20:00:00+02:00">December 3, 1946—8
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received December 4—1:10 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1124. From first hubbub of election aftermath facts have emerged. Govt
                            was severely disillusioned by paucity of support received from what it
                            had considered to be most trusted elements, while being rudely shocked
                            by strength of political outcry against regime. Opposition, on other
                            hand, was very surprised and gratified by surge of country’s support in
                            face of every conceivable Govt-inspired pressure. Strong national
                            feeling demonstrated by elections may eliminate future Constituent
                            Assembly election, with constitutional changes now likely to be work of
                            existing Parliament.</p>
                        <p>Private sources, basing estimates on reliable information, assert Govt
                            received only eight percent of votes cast, aside from Hungarian Popular
                            Union which will work with Govt and which received about 9 percent of
                            vote total. It should not be forgotten immense support <pb facs="0683" n="669" xml:id="pg_669"/> for political opposition, National
                            Peasants alone receiving estimated 70 percent of total vote cast, was
                            compiled despite elimination 30 to 50 percent of electorate through
                            non-inclusion in electoral lists and withholding of voting cards.
                            Balance was somewhat redressed by multiple votes of ostensibly staunch
                            Govt contingents who in secrecy of voting booths [voted?] for Maniu.
                            Most striking instance reported was that of Bucharest <hi rend="italic">gendarmerie</hi> whose 3,000 personnel voted at headquarters after
                            political harangue by comanding general. Actual polling results showed
                            not single vote for DPB,<note n="71" xml:id="d457fn71">The Bloc of
                                Democratic Parties, composed of parties supporting the current
                                Rumanian Government, had been organized in May 1946.</note> so
                            commanding general and staff officers were obliged to rectify in light
                            fashion this evidence of their unanimous defection.</p>
                        <p>So stunned were Rumanian Communists by true poll figures reaching
                            Bucharest that they felt it inconceivable disaster could be concealed.
                            Comintern group of Ana Pauker, Laszlo Luca and Bodnaras heartened their
                            Rumanian comrades and asked for and received instructions from Moscow to
                            falsify results at all costs on basis of predetermined policy. Although
                            press reports have been published concerning popular vote by districts,
                            no authoritative count has even yet been published in <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette</hi>. Communist circles in viewing state of public
                            mind consider unless substantial new factors arise to change picture, it
                            will be needlessly difficult to hold subsequent election for Constituent
                            Assembly to revise constitution as originally envisaged in Communist
                            time schedule. Present Chamber of Deputies is expected later to shoulder
                            that function.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Berry</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>