<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Secretary of State, at London</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d568</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">568</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1946-01-22T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-01-22T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-01-22T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-01-22T17:00:00-05:00" n="568"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d568">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.24/1–1946: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>, at London</hi>
                    <note n="88" xml:id="d568fn88">Repeated to Moscow as No. 120.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-01-22T17:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 22, 1946—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>686. For the Secretary from Acheson. <gloss target="#t_reurtel1">Reurtel</gloss>
                    677, January 19.<note n="89" xml:id="d568fn89">Not printed; but see footnote,
                        82, <ref target="#pg_819">p. 819</ref>.</note> I repeat Harriman’s reply re
                    sale of surplus to U.S.S.R.</p>
                <pb facs="0836" n="822" xml:id="pg_822"/>
                <p>[Here follows text of telegram 184, January 19, 4 p.m., from Moscow, <ref
                        target="#pg_820">page 820</ref>.]</p>
                <p>I agree, of course, with Harriman’s general analysis with respect to economic
                    arrangements with the U.S.S.R. I question whether surplus property disposal is
                    an apt case. I recall your conversation with Messrs. Clayton,<note n="90"
                        xml:id="d568fn90">William L. Clayton, Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Economic Affairs.</note> McCabe<note n="91" xml:id="d568fn91">Thomas B.
                        McCabe, Special Assistant to the Secretary of State and Foreign Liquidation
                        Commissioner.</note> and myself after signing the British arrangement in
                    which you indicated the most important thing was to get rid of surplus as
                    quickly as possible and get it off our hands, also your desire not to raise at
                    this time the question of a loan through <gloss target="#t_Eximbank1"
                        >Eximbank</gloss> to the Soviets. In view of the extremely difficult nature
                    of the problem of surplus disposal throughout the world and of the pressure by
                    the Army to be relieved of the necessity of guarding and otherwise taking care
                    of U. S. property abroad so that the troops may come home, foreign governments,
                    including the Soviets, know that we are at a tactical disadvantage in the sale
                    of surplus which increases with the passage of time. Therefore I believe that
                    surplus property is the poorest type of economic arrangement with the Soviets to
                    which to attempt to tie satisfaction of any or all of our own desiderata. They
                    would, I think, want to tie in a loan to such broad negotiations.</p>
                <p>I did not have any specific problems in mind and my reference in <gloss
                        target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 520, January 17, to other questions was
                    merely to give you an opportunity to instruct us. Perhaps you would wish to
                    consult Bohlen.<note n="92" xml:id="d568fn92">Charles E. Bohlen, Assistant to
                        the Secretary of State.</note> As I see it the question is whether or not we
                    wish to sell to the Soviets who apparently want to buy.</p>
                <p>Please indicate to me and Harriman whether you agree with the views above so that
                    McCabe can take appropriate action.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
