<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Ambassador of the Soviet Union (
                        Novikov
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d586</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">586</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-06-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="586" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d586">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.51/5–1746</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador of the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Novikov</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-06-13">June 13,
                            1946</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: Reference is made to your note of May 17,
                    1946. The Government of the United States has noted that the Government of the
                    Union of Soviet Socialist Republics is now prepared to extend the scope of the
                    negotiations so as to include a preliminary exchange of opinions on the
                    questions specified under (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)
                    and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) of this Government’s note of April 18, 1946. At
                    the same time the Government of the United States must reaffirm the view,
                    expressed in its note of February 21, 1946, that the settlement of all the
                    questions enumerated in that note is necessary to provide a sound basis for the
                    mutually beneficial development of economic and financial relations between the
                    United States and the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. Accordingly, while
                    the Government of the United States welcomes the willingness of the Government
                    of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics to widen the scope of the
                    negotiations, it is unable to agree to a merely preliminary exchange of opinions
                    on some of the questions to be included in the negotiations.</p>
                <p>Taking account of the views of the Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist
                    Republics as set forth in your note of May 17, 1946, the Government of the
                    United States makes the following proposals with regard to the procedure to be
                    followed in arriving at a comprehensive settlement of these questions.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <item>Negotiations on the following questions to begin at an early date,
                        preferably July 10, 1946: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The request of the Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist
                                Republics for a credit of one billion dollars.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Preliminary discussions of a comprehensive treaty of friendship,
                                commerce, and navigation between the United States and the Union of
                                Soviet Socialist Republics and agreement to enter into negotiations
                                in the near future for the conclusion of such a treaty.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Methods for giving effect to the terms of Article VII of the
                                Soviet Master Lend-Lease Agreement of June 11, 1942, such as are
                                suggested in this Government’s “Proposals for Expansion of World
                                Trade and Employment”, which were transmitted to the Government of
                                the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics on December 21, 1945.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>General settlement of lend-lease obligations in accordance with
                                the provisions of the Soviet Master Lend-Lease Agreement, concluded
                                on June 11, 1942, between the Governments of the United States and
                                the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, on the basis of an
                                inventory of lend-lease supplies in the possession <pb facs="0859" n="845" xml:id="pg_845"/> of the Union of Soviet Socialist
                                Republics or subject to its control at the end of hostilities, as
                                indicated in the note on this subject addressed by this Government
                                to the Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics on
                                February 18, 1946.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Claims of American nationals against the Government of the Union
                                of Soviet Socialist Republics including claims arising from actions
                                of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in occupied and liberated
                                areas.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Determination of concerted policies to be followed by the United
                                States and the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics together with the
                                United Kingdom, under the terms of the agreement reached at the
                                Crimea Conference, in assisting the peoples liberated from the
                                domination of Nazi Germany and the peoples of the former Axis
                                satellite states of Europe to solve by democratic means their
                                pressing economic problems.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Arrangements to assure adequate protection of the interests of
                                inventors and of writers and other holders of copyrights.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">h</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Discussions of other economic questions, pertinent to the scope of
                                negotiations as herein proposed, the settlement of which questions
                                in the opinion of either Government would be conducive to the
                                attainment of the aims of these negotiations.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <item>Negotiations on civil aviation matters of mutual interest to the two
                        countries to begin two weeks after the commencement of the negotiations
                        referred to in item (1) above.</item>
                    <label>(3)</label>
                    <item>Negotiations on the following question to be held at a time to be fixed in
                        the course of negotiations referred to in item (1) above: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Arrangements to guarantee that navigation on rivers of international
                                concern should be free and open on terms of entire equality to
                                nationals, vessels of commerce, and goods of all members of the
                                United Nations.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label>(4)</label>
                    <item>It is further proposed that the negotiations herein referred to be held in
                        Washington.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Government of the United States wishes to reiterate its view that neither the
                    present correspondence, nor such negotiations in Washington as may result from
                    this correspondence, nor the outcome of these negotiations should in any way
                    preclude or postpone the separate discussion and settlement of the matters
                    enumerated in this note. In particular, nothing in the present note should be so
                    interpreted as to preclude or postpone negotiation and settlement of these
                    matters at the forthcoming Conference of Foreign Ministers.</p>
                <p>The Government of the United States begs to call the attention of the Government
                    of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics to the last paragraph of this
                    Government’s note of April 18, 1946, referring to the adherence of the
                    Government of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics to the International
                    Monetary Fund and the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development. The
                    Government of the United States wishes to reaffirm the view expressed therein
                    that successful <pb facs="0860" n="846" xml:id="pg_846"/> conclusion of the
                    proposed financial and economic discussions will be facilitated by cooperation
                    of the two Governments in these two of the principal United Nations
                    organizations designed to further international economic progress.</p>
                <p>The Government of the United States would appreciate an early reply to the
                    present note.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James F. Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
