<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        Ambassador in Yugoslavia (
                        Patterson
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1946v06</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d656</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">656</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1946-08-25T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1946-08-25T07:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-08-25T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-08-25T07:00:00-05:00" n="656" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d656">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.2360H/8–2546: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Yugoslavia</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Patterson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-08-25T13:00:00+01:00">August 25, 1946—1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>45. For Ambassador Patterson from the Secretary. In accordance with the
                    instructions of your Govt you delivered a written note to the Yugoslav Govt
                    regarding the shooting down of American planes without warning by Yugoslav
                        aviators.<note n="35" xml:id="d656fn35">For text of note, see telegram 856,
                        August 30, from Belgrade, <ref target="#pg_933">p. 933</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Your account of your conversation with Marshal Tito and the reports of newspaper
                    correspondents of the statements made to them by Marshal Tito would indicate
                    that the Yugoslav Govt expressed its regrets regarding the loss of American
                    lives and had issued instructions that would insure that such incidents would
                    not recur.<note n="36" xml:id="d656fn36">Ambassador Patterson’s report of his
                        conversation with Marshal Tito was contained in telegram of August 22, 9
                        p.m., from Bled, printed in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, September 1, 1946, p. 418.</note>
                </p>
                <p>You should immediately make clear to Marshal Tito that it is necessary that the
                    assurances given by him to you and newspaper correspondents in this regard would
                    be communicated to the US Govt in writing in order to enable the American Govt
                    to determine its future course and to avoid any misunderstanding as to the
                    course which may be expected from the Yugoslav Govt in the event that American
                    planes, despite precautions taken, should be forced by weather conditions over
                    Yugoslav territory. In view of the fact that the American note to the Yugoslav
                    Govt was in writing, it is impossible not to attach significance to the omission
                    from any written reply received from the Yugoslav Govt of any reference to the
                    regrets expressed to you by the Yugoslav Govt regarding the loss of American
                    lives or to the orders you were advised were given by the Yugoslav Govt that no
                    foreign planes are to be shot at, that planes forced off course by weather
                    trouble, loss of direction or mechanical difficulties in reasonable numbers are
                    not to be molested, and that means for signalling distress by such planes be
                    worked out. It is the hope of the American Govt that this omission will be
                    promptly rectified. <pb facs="0944" n="930" xml:id="pg_930"/> If Ambassador is
                    away this approach should be made by Chargé.<note n="37" xml:id="d656fn37">In
                        telegram 98, August 27, from Belgrade, the Chargé (Shantz) reported that
                        after many fruitless efforts he had delivered the message orally to Acting
                        Foreign Minister Velebit. Mr. Velebit had promised to inform Marshal Tito,
                        who was traveling in various areas of Yugoslavia, as soon as possible.
                        (811.2360H/9–746)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Sent Belgrade as 45; repeated to <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> as
                    4229.</p>
                <closer>[<signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>]</closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
