<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1946-10-05T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1946-10-05T13:00:00-05:00" n="684" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d684">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20200(D)/10–546: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Yugoslavia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Patterson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">us urgent</hi></seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Belgrade</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1946-10-05T19:00:00+01:00">October 5, 1946—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 9:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1025. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 657, October 2. When I
                            handed Tito Department’s note on USIS today he would not reply before
                            studying it but added reason for closing was not circulation Pridonoff
                            articles only but “whole work of USIS” which was anti-Yugoslav
                            Government and anti-Yugoslav people as well as against Yugoslav laws. If
                            his Government were to allow it to reopen, they would request guarantees
                            from US Embassy. US reading room, Tito said, had been subject constant
                            complaints. It was not closed for any other reason, as proved by
                            continuing operation of British, French and other reading rooms.</p>
                        <p>Marshal expressed regrets that small or big incidents between Embassy and
                            Yugoslav authorities always got enormous publicity in US press in form
                            of anti-Yugoslav campaign. He thought it more important to prevent
                            incidents than to publicize them. He added that American papers usually
                            do not give real reasons for incidents, giving American side only.</p>
                        <p>I said our press would publish anything he cared to write and added that
                            what he said of our press was much more true of his own, as example I
                            pointed out our press published Yugoslav notes on plane crashes whereas
                            Yugoslav press published <hi rend="italic">none</hi> of ours. Tito said
                            “We have different methods of acting and working. After all, it is not
                            possible to hide subject of American notes from the people. Everyone can
                            listen to the radio.” Velebit said US notes were “not interesting
                            enough” and Yugoslavs needed the space for more interesting items such
                            as reconstruction. Tito promised early written reply USIS note.</p>
                        <p>During rest of conversation we <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Protested Wedge sentence as excessive.<note n="94" xml:id="d684fn94">Regarding the sentencing of Embassy guard
                                        Wedge, see footnote 21, <ref target="#pg_922">p.
                                        922</ref>.</note></item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Reported imprisonment one of our Yugoslav employees,
                                    requesting information.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Requested return of $8,000 belonging to Embassy staff
                                    confiscated by Yugoslav police in black market raids last spring
                                    and Marshal agreed to return it.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Mentioned US commercial air service saying sorry to see
                                    Belgrade cut off routes of main airlines. Marshal replied he
                                    would study question and hoped have something for us on it
                                    soon.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Mentioned Tito’s charges against our staff, requesting further
                                    details, and briefly discussed Burnup case.<note n="95" xml:id="d684fn95">Robert Burnup, an American road
                                        construction engineer working for <gloss target="#t_UNRRA1">UNRRA</gloss> in Yugoslavia was arrested by the
                                        Yugoslav authorities at the end of September 1946 for
                                        alleged espionage activities.</note> Velebit said Burnup’s
                                        <pb facs="0980" n="966" xml:id="pg_966"/> case would
                                    probably be settled favorably soon. <gloss target="#t_UNRRA1">UNRRA</gloss> saw him this morning.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Finally, Velebit said he couldn’t understand why America did
                                    not return Yugoslav Danube barges.<note n="96" xml:id="d684fn96">Telegram 1024, October 5, from Belgrade, read in part as
                                        follows: “Aside from Trieste problem our failure to return
                                        Yugoslav barges has probably been the sharpest thorn in our
                                        Yugoslav relations for more than year. We have more than
                                        once acknowledged Yugoslav rights to the barges but
                                        continued to keep them. This has been subject of some bitter
                                        press comment in recent months.”
                                    (860H.85/10–546)</note></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Sent Department 1025, repeated Paris for <gloss target="#t_Secdel1">Secdel</gloss> 128 and Moscow as 50.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Patterson</hi></signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>[On October 11, 1946, Acting Secretary of State Acheson made a public
                                statement regarding the trial and conviction of Aloysius Stepinac,
                                Archbishop of Zagreb, for alleged war crimes. For text, see
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, October 20,
                                1946, page 725.]</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>