<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 114.Mr. Hoffman to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1876</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1876-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1876-04-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recLrhH3r9BIhQsGe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Extradition</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1876-04-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1876-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="124"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                <head>No. 114.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hoffman</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1876-04-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 13, 1876</date>. (Received April
                        25.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 62.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose to you a copy of a
                    note which I received this morning from Lord Derby.</p>
                <p>His lordship refers to a telegram from New York which appeared in the Daily News
                    of the 29th ultimo, and which he has ascertained from Her Majesty’s legation at
                    Washington to be substantially true, to the effect that the United States
                    district court for the southern district of New York had decided that the forger
                    Lawrence can be tried for other crimes than those mentioned in the warrant, and
                    inquires whether the district court at New York has the power to carry out this
                    decision.</p>
                <p>In case that it has such power, Lord Derby thinks that it would be nugatory to
                    enter into such an arrangement as he proposed in his note of the 8th ultimo, and
                    sees no solution of the present difficulty except through an act of
                    Congress.</p>
                <pb facs="0276" n="220" xml:id="pg_220"/>
                <p>Lord Derby further requests me to express to you the hope of Her Majesty’s
                    government that the negotiation of a new treaty of extradition, which may be
                    beneficial to the interests of both nations, may be renewed as soon as possible,
                    and in conclusion calls my attention to the twelfth section of the act of 1870,
                    to the effect that a fugitive cannot be detained in custody beyond two months
                    from the date of his committal, unless the Secretary of State can show
                    sufficient cause for further detention, and adds that therefore, however much
                    Her Majesty’s government may regret not being able to comply with the wishes of
                    the Government of the United States, they will be unable to detain him in
                    custody beyond that specified time.</p>
                <p>The two months expire on the 2d proximo.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WICKHAM HOFFMAN.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 62.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Lord <persName type="from">Derby</persName> to Colonel
                                <persName type="to">Hoffman</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1876-04-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 11, 1876</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to previous correspondence
                        respecting the extradition of Ezra D. Winslow, and especially to the letter
                        I had the honor of addressing to you on the 8th ultimo, in which I stated to
                        you, for the information of the United States Government, that Her Majesty’s
                        government would not feel themselves justified in authorizing the surrender
                        of that prisoner until they should have received the assurance of your
                        Government that he should not, until he has been restored or had an
                        opportunity of returning to Her Majesty’s dominions, be detained or tried in
                        the United States for any offense committed prior to his surrender, other
                        than the extradition crimes proved by the facts on which the surrender would
                        be grounded, I have now the honor to call your attention to the inclosed
                        copy of a telegram which appeared in the Daily News, of the 29th ultimo, and
                        which I have ascertained from Her Majesty’s legation at Washington to be
                        substantially correct; and to request that you will be good enough to
                        ascertain from your Government, for the information of Her Majesty’s
                        government, whether the district court at New York has the power to carry
                        out the decision it is reported to have arrived at, viz, that the forger
                        Lawrence, who was surrendered to the United States Government under the 10th
                        article of the treaty of 1842, can be tried for other offenses besides those
                        mentioned in the warrant.</p>
                    <p>In this country the attorney-general would enter a <hi rend="italic">nolle
                            prosequi</hi>, and so put a stop to further proceedings in any
                        prosecution; but Her Majesty’s government are not aware whether the
                        Attorney-General of the United States has similar powers. The reported
                        language of the district court leads them to think that he has not.</p>
                    <p>If so, it would, in the opinion of Her Majesty’s government, be nugatory to
                        enter into an arrangement such as I had the honor of proposing in my letter
                        to you of the 8th of March, above alluded to; and Her Majesty’s government
                        see no solution of the present difficulty but the passing of an act of
                        Congress which, while recognizing the acknowledged principle of
                        international law, that a fugitive can only be tried for the crime or crimes
                        for which he was surrendered, will enable the Government of the United
                        States to guarantee that the condition, which Her Majesty’s government are
                        compelled to require under section 3, subsection 2, of the act of 1870, will
                        be complied with.</p>
                    <p>With regard to future difficulties which may possibly arise on the general
                        subject of extradition, Her Majesty’s government can see but one
                        satisfactory solution, namely, the conclusion of a more comprehensive treaty
                        between the two countries, and one more suited to the requirements of the
                        day than the existing arrangement.</p>
                    <p>I have, therefore, to request that you will express to your Government the
                        hope of Her Majesty’s government that the negotiation of a treaty which will
                        be so beneficial to the interests of the two nations may be renewed as soon
                        as possible.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, I have the honor to remind you that, under the provisions of
                        the twelfth section of the extradition act of 1870, a fugitive cannot be
                        detained in custody longer than two months from the date of his committal,
                        unless the Secretary of State can show sufficient cause for further
                        detention; and that, therefore, however much they may regret being unable to
                        comply with the wishes of your Government respecting the surrender of
                        Winslow, they will be unable to detain him in custody beyond that specified
                        time.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>DERBY.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0277" n="221" xml:id="pg_221"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in inclosure in No. 62.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1876-04-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">Tuesday</hi>, 28<hi rend="italic">th</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">[Daily News, March 29.]</p>
                    <p>The United States district court of New York has decided that the forger
                        Lawrence, who was brought from England under the extradition treaty, can be
                        tried for other offenses besides those mentioned in the warrant. The court
                        cannot regard the order of the President to the contrary, or take notice of
                        any agreement between the English and American governments to that
                        effect.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
