<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 183.Mr. Bingham to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1876</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="193"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                <head>No. 183.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bingham</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokei, Japan</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-12-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 4, 1875</date>. (Received January
                        5,1876.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 303.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 29th ultimo, I was present by invitation
                    at the inauguration by Her Majesty, the Empress of Japan, of a normal school for
                    the education of Japanese girls. The edifice for this school is a large and
                    elegant structure recently erected in this city.</p>
                <p>On the occasion referred to Her Majesty, the Empress, attended by His Excellency
                    Mr. Sanjo, prime minister of the empire, His Excellency Mr. Okubo, minister of
                    the interior, also by officers of the imperial household, and in the presence of
                    many persons, including about eighty pupils of the school, read an address in
                    the Japanese language, a translation of which, as published in the Japan Daily
                    Herald of the 1st instant, I have the honor to inclose.</p>
                <p>I also inclose the congratulatory addresses of the superintendent of the school,
                    Mr. Nakamura Massanawo, and of Mr. Tanaka, vice minister of education, as
                    published in the Japan Weekly Mail of the 4th instant.</p>
                <p>The establishment of this institution, at the instance and largely by patronage,
                    as I am advised, of Her Majesty, may be considered an event of great
                    significance in the East, and, if maintained, will doubtless contribute most
                    effectively to the moral and intellectual elevation of the women of this
                    empire.</p>
                <p>By this beneficent action Her Majesty has acquired an additional title to the
                    respect of mankind and the gratitude of her people.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JNO. A. BINGHAM.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Extract from the Japan Daily Herald.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Address of Her Majesty the Empress at the opening of the
                            Tokei normal school</hi>.</head>
                    <p>My joy was very great last year on learning the decision for the
                        establishment of an institution of this nature. To-day the wish that I have
                        so often expressed has been, realized. The building is finished, and the
                        opening has taken place. I venture to hope that this great event will be the
                        epoch of a new source of happiness for the entire empire.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
