<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 249.Mr. Adee to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1876</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d259</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">259</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1876-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1876-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1876-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1876-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="259"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d259">
                <head>No. 249.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adee</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1876-10-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 1, 1876</date>. (Received October
                        17.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 313.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: * * * The Cuban loan was awarded yesterday, with
                    much solemnity, to Messrs. Lopez, Calvo, Vinent, and Cabezas, the signers of the
                    previously-reported provisional contract of August 5. Some two hundred persons
                    witnessed the proceedings.</p>
                <p>Only two bids were put in, viz, that above mentioned and that of the Marques de
                    Campo.</p>
                <p>Mr. Llaseras, by letter from Paris, withdraw his bid, by reason of inability to
                    make the required deposit of three-quarters of a million of dollars.</p>
                <p>The scheme of the Marques de Campo offered $15,000,000 for ten years at 10 per
                    cent., to be advanced to the government in four installments at intervals of two
                    months each, on the guarantee of the Cuban customs: one million to be advanced
                    forthwith on account and credit opened for another million if needed; the loan
                    to be repaid within ten years by <pb facs="0517" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/>
                    retaining from the customs receipts a sum sufficient to pay principal and
                    interest due in monthly parts; guarantee of the Cortes required before December
                    31, or else the contract to be rescinded with indemnification.</p>
                <p>The Bank of Havana put in a protest against any pledge of the customs of Cuba in
                    prejudice of its own claims secured by the same guarantee. This protest was not
                    admitted.</p>
                <p>After public discussion of the plans presented, Mr. Calvo raised his offer for an
                    immediate advance, without interest, to $1,500,000, half to be paid in
                    Havana.</p>
                <p>The ministers were then left alone to deliberate, which they did till 8 o’clock,
                    when public announcement was made that they had unanimously decided in favor of
                    Mr. Calvo’s offer, which was accordingly formally accepted.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. AUGUSTUS ADEE.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
