<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1876-09-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1876-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="321" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d321">
                        <head>No. 312.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Maynard</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1876-09-13"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 13,
                                    1876</date>. (Received October 12.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 94.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that on
                            Thursday last, the 7th instant, occurred the grand inaugural ceremony of
                            girding the new Sultan with the imperial sword. The act of investiture
                            appears to have been a simple affair, performed by a high religious
                            official from Koniah, (the ancient Iconium,) hereditary to this
                            function, in presence of but few, and they of the faithful, to the
                            exclusion of all non-Mussulmans, and within the little mosque of Eyoub
                            on the Golden Horn, just beyond the old walls of Stamboul. From this
                            point the Sultan, now emperor <hi rend="italic">de</hi>
                            <pb facs="0641" n="585" xml:id="pg_585"/>
                            <hi rend="italic">jure</hi> as well as <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>,
                            rode in the procession, entering the city by the Adrianople gate, the
                            same, according to tradition, entered originally by his conquering
                            ancestor, and following his course quite through the city to the
                            seraglio. The way on both sides was lined by a countless multitude: men,
                            women, and children, of all ages and conditions. Handsome accommodations
                            were provided by the ministry of foreign affairs for the Diplomatic
                            Corps. * * *</p>
                        <p>The inaugural <hi rend="italic">hatt</hi> was read with the usual
                            solemnities at the Sublime Porte on the 10th, Sunday last. An official
                            translation appeared in the papers last evening, of which a copy is
                            inclosed.</p>
                        <p>It will be observed that the former ministry is retained, indicating that
                            for the present, at least, public affairs will keep in the accustomed
                            channel.</p>
                        <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>HORACE MAYNARD.</signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="smallcaps">The Imperial “Hatt.”</hi></head>
                            <p rend="center">[From the Daily Levant Herald of September 12,
                                1876.]</p>
                            <p>The following is the text of the inaugural address of the new
                                Sultan’s reign, read at the Porte on Sunday last, of which we gave
                                the chief points in our impression of yesterday:</p>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Illustrious Vizier, Mehemet Rushdi
                                Pasha</hi>: My beloved brother Sultan Murad V having, by the will of
                                Providence, had sovereign power and the khalifate withdrawn from
                                him, I have ascended the throne of my ancestors in conformity with
                                the prescriptions of Ottoman law.</p>
                            <p>Considering your known experience, integrity, and zeal, and your long
                                acquaintance with state affairs, I confirm you in the post of grand
                                vizier and president of the council of ministers, and I maintain all
                                the members of the cabinet and the other state functionaries in
                                their respective posts. In placing my full and entire confidence in
                                God, I firmly hope that all the ministers and public functionaries
                                of the empire will aid and co-operate with me in carrying my
                                intentions into execution. Those intentions have exclusively in view
                                the consolidation and glory of my empire and the complete enjoyment,
                                by all my subjects, without distinction, of freedom, of the benefits
                                which result from public tranquillity and the good and even-handed
                                administration of justice.</p>
                            <p>All the world knows that the present situation of the Ottoman Empire
                                is critical. The multifarious causes which have brought about this
                                sad state of things all spring chiefly from one source, namely, the
                                insufficient and inequitable execution of the laws, based upon the
                                prescriptions of the sheri, (the public and sacred law,) as also the
                                fluctuating diversity and want of uniformity in the administration
                                of the affairs of the country. Irregularities and illegalities have
                                crept into the administration for some years past. Mistrust has
                                taken possession of the public mind on the subject of our finances,
                                and the failure of our credit has been the consequence. The working
                                of the tribunals has been defective, and they have not succeeded in
                                insuring the rights of the public. Our industry, commerce,
                                agriculture, and all the elements which contribute to the prosperity
                                of a people have lacked development, although our country, as all
                                the world admits and recognizes, is well placed for the enjoyment of
                                these advantages. All that has been attempted hitherto for the
                                prosperity of the nation and for individual liberty, for the
                                tranquillity and well-being of all our subjects, natives and
                                foreigners, without exception; all the endeavors hitherto made to
                                accomplish these ends have not been crowned with success; and this
                                has chiefly arisen from frequent changes in the administration and
                                the failure to follow out steadily a uniform system. This general
                                regrettable result, in fine, is traceable to the fact that the laws
                                and regulations of the country have not been adhered to in letter or
                                in spirit in a stable and persistent manner.</p>
                            <p>The great object to be aimed at is, therefore, to adopt measures for
                                placing the laws and regulations of the country upon bases which
                                shall inspire confidence in their execution. For this purpose it is
                                indipensable to proceed to the establishment of a general council,
                                or national assembly, (the original Turkish expression is <hi rend="italic">medjiliss oumoumi</hi>,) whose acts will inspire
                                every confidence in the nation, and will be in harmony with the
                                customs, aptitudes, and capabilities of the populations of the
                                empire. The mission and duty of this council will be to guarantee,
                                without exception, the faithful execution of <pb facs="0642" n="586" xml:id="pg_586"/> the existing laws or of those which shall be
                                promulgated in conformity with the provisions of the <hi rend="italic">sheri</hi>, in connection with the real and
                                legitimate wants of the country and its inhabitants, as also to
                                control the equilibrium of the revenue and expenditures of the
                                empire.</p>
                            <p>The council of ministers is called upon to devote itself to a
                                thorough consideration of this important question, and to submit to
                                me the result of its deliberations.</p>
                            <p>Another impediment to the good execution of the laws and regulations
                                has arisen out of the facility with which public functions are often
                                confided to incompetent hands, and from the fact of public servants
                                and employés being subject to frequent changes, unjustified on
                                legitimate grounds, which entails very serious inconvenience upon
                                the state and the transaction of public affairs. Henceforward every
                                public function and employment will constitute a special career. To
                                employ in the service of the state capable and competent persons;
                                not to allow of any dismissal or transfer without valid cause; to
                                establish ministerial responsibility, as well as the graduated
                                responsibility of all public functionaries of every rank, each in
                                what concerns his own duties: this is the invariable rule which it
                                is advisable to adopt.</p>
                            <p>The material and moral progress which all the world is at one in
                                acknowledging in European nations has been accomplished, thanks to
                                the diffusion of public instruction, science, and the fine arts. Now
                                as my subjects of all classes have, I am happy to declare, by their
                                intelligence and natural capacity, special aptitudes for progress,
                                and as the propagation of education constitutes in my eyes a
                                pressing and vital question, you will consider without delay the
                                best means of insuring this important result, by raising the
                                aggregate amount allotted to public instruction in the budget in a
                                sufficient proportion and as far as possible.</p>
                            <p>Moreover, immediate reform must be effected in the
                                provinces—administrative, financial, and judicial reform—in order to
                                create throughout the provinces a really normal state of things, and
                                one in conformity with the bases adopted for the central
                                organization.</p>
                            <p>To the disturbances which broke out last year in the Herzegovina and
                                Bosnia, at the instigation of evil-intentioned people, the rebellion
                                of Servia has been since superadded. Considering that the blood
                                spilt on one side and the other is that of sons of a common country,
                                I am profoundly afflicted at the continuation of this state of
                                things. It behooves you, therefore, to take the most effectual
                                measures for putting an end to so deplorable a situation.</p>
                            <p>I confirm all the treaties concluded with friendly powers. While
                                maintaining their faithful execution, you will endeavor to draw
                                still closer the amicable relations which we entertain with these
                                powers.</p>
                            <p>Such are, in substance, my wishes, such my intentions! May the
                                Almighty deign to crown our efforts with success!</p>
                            <closer><dateline rendition="#left">Given on Sunday, <date calendar="iranian-persian" when="1876-09-10">the 23d day of
                                        the month of Shaban, 1293, (September 10,
                                    1876</date>.)</dateline></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>