<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-03-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-03-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="102" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d102">
                        <head>102. Paper Prepared by <persName corresp="#p_BEA1">Elizabeth Ann
                                Brown</persName> of the Office of United Nations Political and
                            Security Affairs<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d102fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss> Files: Lot
                                59 D 237, Membership. Confidential. An addressee is not indicated on
                                the source text which, however, contains the handwritten notation:
                                “DHP—11:00 a.m. Mtg 3/9/55.” <persName corresp="#p_PDH1">David H.
                                    Popper</persName> was Director of the Office of United Nations
                                Political and Security Affairs.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-03-08">March 8,
                                    1955</date>.</hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">SURVEY OF MEMBERSHIP PROBLEM, 1955</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The applications of 19 states remain pending before the United
                                Nations. Fourteen of the 19 have been supported for admission by the
                                United States and a majority of the United Nations members, but
                                their applications have been blocked by the Soviet veto in the
                                Security Council. These 14 states are Austria, Cambodia, Ceylon,
                                Finland, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Jordan, Libya, Laos, Nepal,
                                Portugal, Republic of Korea, and Viet-Nam. In addition, there are
                                five Soviet sponsored candidates (Albania, Bulgaria, Hungary, “the
                                Mongolian People’s Republic”, Rumania), none of whom have received
                                the required majority in the Assembly or Security Council. Finally,
                                the North Korean and Viet-Minh regimes submitted applications, which
                                were never officially acknowledged by any Security Council action,
                                but which are nevertheless sometimes listed by Secretariat and other
                                sources as applicants for <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                                membership.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In the 9th Session of the General Assembly a resolution was
                                adopted according to which all the pending applications were sent
                                back to the Security Council “for further consideration and positive
                                recommendations”. The Security Council was also requested to
                                consider the possibility of invoking the provisions of Article 28(2)
                                of the Charter which provides for periodic meetings of the Council.
                                Furthermore, the Good Offices Committee consisting of
                                representatives of Egypt, the Netherlands, and Peru, which was
                                established by the 8th session, was continued; and both this
                                Committee and the Security Council were requested to report to the
                                10th Assembly. This means that at some time shortly, probably this
                                summer, the Security Council will have to consider the membership
                                question. Unless there has been some basic change in the position of
                                the respective members, however, it may be that Council
                                consideration can be limited to confirming the fact that positions
                                have not changed, making it unnecessary to vote on the pending
                                applications once again.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>In initiating negotiations for a peace treaty with the USSR, Japan
                                has indicated its intention to try to get from the USSR a commitment
                                to support its admission into the United Nations as a <pb facs="0291" n="265" xml:id="pg_265"/> part of the overall
                                negotiations. So far the USSR has never included Japan in its
                                “package”. Last year Japanese sources were inclined to believe that
                                Japan had no chance for admission unless a solution of the Chinese
                                representation issue was reached simultaneously. In the current
                                negotiations, however, there have been no indications whether Japan
                                would seek an outright unqualified commitment from the USSR or would
                                be willing to accept a “deal” of some sort that would tie Japan’s
                                admission to the admission of certain other outstanding candidates.
                                It seems likely that Japan will insist upon an unqualified
                                commitment, if it seriously desires admission into the United
                                Nations. Whether the USSR would make such a commitment depends upon
                                the importance it now attaches to regularizing its relations with
                                Japan in the context of the present Far Eastern situation and on its
                                position generally regarding membership. It is possible, however,
                                that Japan might simply accept inclusion in the Soviet “package”, if
                                it can obtain other substantial concessions in return, in which case
                                there would be increasing pressure upon the United States to relax
                                its position on a “package” arrangement.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The issue of Chinese representation has an important bearing on
                                the membership question. It is possible that the USSR will not
                                modify its present position on membership until this issue has been
                                resolved in some way. Furthermore, any relaxation of the present
                                position of the United States with respect to the Soviet sponsored
                                candidates could have undesirable repercussions so far as the
                                Chinese representation question is concerned. Accordingly, it may be
                                that this issue precludes any progress toward a solution of the
                                membership impasse, with the possible exception of an agreement to
                                admit several of the “non-committed” states, which in itself seems
                                unlikely.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>There are certain other prospects for action on membership: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>Last year the Secretary General suggested the possibility
                                        of reaching agreement on several states not clearly aligned
                                        with either East or West. Corridor rumors in New York
                                        mentioned such states as Austria, Finland, Libya, and Jordan
                                        in this connection. No actual proposals along this line were
                                        considered, however, apparently because informal soundings
                                        in the Soviet Delegation disclosed that the USSR would not
                                        go along on such a limited arrangement. It might
                                        nevertheless be worthwhile to try this tack again if we feel
                                        we could afford to add three or four such states at the
                                        expense of strong supporters of the West, who have equal if
                                        not better claims to prompt admission. If it were decided to
                                        proceed along these lines, the matter could be informally
                                        discussed with one or more members of the Good Offices
                                        Committee with a view to its developing some such
                                        recommendation.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>The possibility of an overall agreement to admit all
                                        outstanding candidates should be reviewed just prior to
                                        Security Council consideration of the membership question.
                                        It is assumed, <pb facs="0292" n="266" xml:id="pg_266"/>
                                        however, that in the absence of a basic change in the
                                        current international situation it would not be possible to
                                        agree to admission of all nineteen candidates.</item>
                                    <label>(c)</label>
                                    <item>The position which the United States takes on the
                                        membership question this year should be considered in
                                        relation to the proposals we may develop in connection with
                                        Charter review. If we intend to seek amendment of Article 4
                                        of the Charter, it might be possible to move toward a
                                        settlement which would not take place until sometime in 1956
                                        as a consequence of Charter review. At the least we could
                                        work toward a recommendation by the 10th Assembly that
                                        Members review their position on membership in light of the
                                        forthcoming Charter Review Conference.</item>
                                    <label>(d)</label>
                                    <item>As suggested by the United States in 1954, arrangements
                                        could be devised for non-member participation in the General
                                        Assembly, pending the time that agreement can be reached on
                                        admission of qualified outstanding applicants. There is
                                        attached a separate paper on this subject,<note n="2" xml:id="d102fn2">Not printed.</note> suggesting its
                                        study during the current year by the Interim
                                        Committee.</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>