<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-08-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="118" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                        <head>118. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                            International Organization Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_WDW1" type="from">Wainhouse</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary
                                of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d118fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 310.2/8–2455. Secret. Drafted by
                                Bond. Initialed by <persName corresp="#p_WDW1">Wainhouse</persName>.
                                Cleared by <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>, NEA, and <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>. The Bureau of Far Eastern Affairs
                                wrote a dissenting memorandum; see<ref target="#d119">
                                    <hi rend="italic">infra</hi></ref>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-08-24">August 24,
                                        1955</date>.</hi></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>U.S. Position on Admission of New Members to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss></item>
                        </list>
                        <p>At a meeting in your office on August 9, 1955 representatives of this
                            Bureau (including Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName>) and
                            of certain other interested areas of the Department discussed with you
                            the possibility of resolving the current membership deadlock, having in
                            mind the anticipated early review of outstanding applications by the
                            Security Council and the scheduled discussion of that subject at the
                            Tenth General Assembly.</p>
                        <pb facs="0320" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/>
                        <p>It was pointed out at that meeting, as well as in <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>’s memorandum of August 5, 1955 (<gloss target="#t_TAB1">Tab</gloss> A),<note n="2" xml:id="d118fn2">Printed as <ref target="#d115">Document 115</ref>.</note> that there had been
                            certain indications of a prospective relaxation of the Soviet position
                            on membership, with particular reference to the Bandung group and
                            possibly Austria (which the Soviets appear to want to link with the
                            other “peace treaty” states). It was mentioned also that such a change
                            in the Soviet attitude, should it in fact materialize, would be likely
                            to give new impetus to a tendency which was already discernible to shift
                            the onus for the membership deadlock from the USSR to the U.S.</p>
                        <p>In the present climate of relaxing tensions there can be little doubt
                            that expectations of a break in this deadlock are high, and that any
                            Member which allows itself to be placed in the position of appearing to
                            block an overall solution will incur the ill will of a large majority of
                            the other member nations, as well as of any qualified applicants which
                            may continue to be excluded. We have particularly in mind the situation
                            which would arise should the USSR press for the admission of all
                            outstanding applicants with the exception of the divided states of Korea
                            and Viet-Nam. Under our present position, we would have to oppose the
                            admission of the satellites, thus blocking a comprehensive package deal.
                            We would then have to be prepared to deal with Soviet acquiescence in
                            the admission of at least the Bandung group, and possibly also Austria.
                            Since presumably we could not oppose any of these, their admission would
                            be assured. The reaction of the remaining qualified applicants, and
                            particularly of Italy, would certainly be strong and vociferous. The
                            onus for Italy’s failure to gain admission would in the present
                            atmosphere attach not to the USSR, but to the U.S., a circumstance which
                            would tend to encourage a resurgence of Italian neutralist sentiment.
                            Moreover, the admission of the Bandung group alone would strengthen the
                            anti-colonial and neutralist forces in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and probably impel the UK, France, and other European
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Members to press for the admission
                            of Italy and Portugal even at the cost of admitting the European
                            satellites.</p>
                        <p>As indicative of the current thinking of other member nations on this
                            question, Canada, supported by Australia, has already expressed interest
                            in a package arrangement which would admit all of the outstanding
                            applicants (including the Mongolian Peoples Republic and the European
                            satellites) with the exception of Korea and Viet-Nam.</p>
                        <p>In considering the feasibility of our supporting a package arrangement on
                            membership, and in particular of our agreeing to the admission of some
                            or all of the European satellites, you raised the <pb facs="0321" n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/> question of possible adverse effects on
                            anti-Communist elements within the satellites, and requested that
                            inquiries on this subject be made of our diplomatic representatives (in
                            the cases of Hungary and Rumania) and through other channels (in the
                            cases of Albania and Bulgaria). Replies received from our Legations in
                            Budapest and Bucharest are attached (<gloss target="#t_TAB1">Tab</gloss>
                                B).<note n="3" xml:id="d118fn3">Not found with the source text, but
                                presumably reference is to telegrams 73 from Budapest, August 17,
                                and 37 from Bucharest, August 15. (Department of State, Central
                                Files, 310.2/8–1755 and /8–1555)</note> While the results of other
                            agency inquiries concerning Albania and Bulgaria have not yet been
                            received, the principal points made by our two Legations are the
                            following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The failure of the U.S. to block the admission of the
                                    satellite applicants would, at least temporarily, have a
                                    negative and demoralizing effect on the anti-Communist
                                    populations of those countries.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>This effect might be at least partly mitigated if the U.S.
                                    were to accompany its renunciation of the use of the veto on
                                    satellite admissions by a statement making clear our continued
                                    strong disapproval of the satellite regimes and our serious
                                    reservations as to their qualifications for <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership; this would be
                                    particularly true if the admission of the satellite applicants
                                    were to be offset by the admission of a substantially greater
                                    number of non-Communist applicants.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Should the U.S. decide on a course of action which would lead
                                    to the admission of the European satellites, the fullest
                                    possible advantage should be taken of the bargaining value of
                                    that decision in seeking concessions from the satellite regimes
                                    concerned.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Pursuant to your desire to include Spain in any membership arrangement to
                            which we might agree, a telegram was despatched to Embassy Madrid on
                            August 20 (<gloss target="#t_TAB1">Tab</gloss> C)<note n="4" xml:id="d118fn4">Not found with the source text, but presumably a
                                reference to telegram 163 of August 20, that stated the United
                                States anticipated detailed and serious consideration of the entire
                                membership question by both the Security Council and General
                                Assembly in coming months. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                310.2/8–2055)</note> designed to stimulate an early application by
                            Spain.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendations</hi></p>
                        <p>It is recommended that you approve a course of action by this Government
                            along the following lines: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>As a first step the U.S. should discuss with the UK, and
                                    subsequently with the French, Canadians, and possibly certain of
                                    the other Commonwealth countries, the feasibility of reaching
                                    general agreement on an understanding to admit (a) all of the
                                    qualified applicants with the possible exception of the divided
                                    states of Korea and Viet-Nam (i.e., Austria, Italy, Finland,
                                    Portugal, Ireland, Japan, Ceylon, Cambodia, Laos, Nepal, Jordan
                                    and Libya), (b) Spain (provided it submits its application in
                                    time), and (c) the four European <pb facs="0322" n="296" xml:id="pg_296"/> satellite applicants (Albania, Bulgaria,
                                    Hungary and Rumania). Such consultations might logically be
                                    followed at a later date by discussion with Chairman <persName corresp="#p_BVA1">Belaunde</persName> (Peru) of the
                                    Committee of Good Offices with a view to enlisting his support
                                    on behalf of such an arrangement.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The U.S. should seek an agreement to postpone Security Council
                                    review of pending membership applications until after the
                                    convening of the General Assembly. The U.S. position on
                                    membership might then be set forth in your general debate speech
                                    (see suggested text attached as <gloss target="#t_TAB1">Tab</gloss> D)<note n="5" xml:id="d118fn5">Not
                                        found.</note> in which the following points would be
                                    emphasized: <list>
                                        <label>(a)</label>
                                        <item>The continued exclusion of a significant number of
                                            qualified nations confronts the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> with an intolerable situation which, if
                                            allowed to persist, can result only in a progressive
                                            deterioration in the prestige and effectiveness of the
                                            organization.</item>
                                        <label>(b)</label>
                                        <item>The fourteen nations already found by a majority of
                                            the Security Council and the General Assembly to be
                                            qualified for membership have been prevented from
                                            gaining admission solely by the Soviet abuse of the
                                            veto.</item>
                                        <label>(c)</label>
                                        <item>(If Spain has applied) It is the view of the U.S. that
                                            Spain, a new applicant, is also fully qualified for
                                            membership and we shall strongly support its
                                            admission.</item>
                                        <label>(d)</label>
                                        <item>It is the hope of the U.S. that the USSR, as its
                                            contribution toward a solution to this urgent and
                                            compelling problem, will forego further use of the veto
                                            to block the admission of these qualified
                                            applicants.</item>
                                        <label>(e)</label>
                                        <item>For its part the U.S., consistent with its view that
                                            the veto should not be used to block the will of the
                                            majority on the issue of membership, will not use its
                                            vote to prevent the admission of any state which
                                            receives seven or more votes in the Security Council.
                                            Specifically, the U.S., while still of the opinion that
                                            the regimes presently in control of Albania, Bulgaria,
                                            Hungary and Rumania have by their own conduct cast the
                                            gravest doubt on their readiness to abide by the
                                            principles of the Charter and their willingness to
                                            undertake the obligations of membership, will no longer
                                            oppose the admission of those four states if it is the
                                            will of the majority that they should be admitted to
                                            membership, although we shall continue to hold them
                                            accountable for past agreements.</item>
                                        <label>(f)</label>
                                        <item>The U.S. will continue to oppose the admission of the
                                            so-called Mongolian Peoples Republic, which in our
                                            opinion cannot present a valid claim for membership
                                            since it does not possess the commonly recognized
                                            attributes of statehood.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The U.S. should then request an urgent meeting of the Security
                                    Council to consider the question of membership; at that meeting
                                    it should state its position along the same lines as the
                                    foregoing.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Rather than seeking a prior agreement with the USSR, which
                                    would be regarded as acceptance of a “package deal”, we should
                                    see <pb facs="0323" n="297" xml:id="pg_297"/> to it that the
                                    USSR Delegation is apprised of our intentions just prior to your
                                    speech, and undertake any necessary consultations with that
                                    Delegation as soon as possible thereafter.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>In the meantime the Department should explore ways and means
                                    of taking advantage of a decision on our part not to block the
                                    admission of the Soviet satellites as a bargaining weapon in
                                    obtaining desired concessions from those regimes, pursuant to
                                    recommendations set forth in the two telegrams attached as
                                        <gloss target="#t_TAB1">Tab</gloss> B.</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>