<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>212. Telegram From the Embassy in the Republic of China to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d212</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">212</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-12-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-12-10T00:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recxRLdoJs9wm7rck" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002408"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Press coverage</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-12-10T00:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-12-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="212"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d212">
                <head>212. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Republic of
                        China</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d212fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 310.2/12–1055. Secret. A handwritten notation on the source text
                        reads: “Eyes Only.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Taipei</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1955-12-10T13:00:00+08:00">December 10, 1955—1 p.m.</date>
                        </hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>541. Department’s 349.<note n="2" xml:id="d212fn2">
                        <ref target="#d209">Document 209</ref>.</note> Suggestion that visit Far
                    Eastern subcommittee offered “unique channel influence Chiang’s decision
                    membership issue” underestimates intensity sub-committee’s feelings and intimate
                    individual and collective knowledge this and related issues. I feel certain they
                    would say their position resulted from their own convictions regardless any
                    guidance they received or might have been given in Taipei. I said “I was in
                    position add very little to what they already knew” because they were as fully
                    informed as I with <pb facs="0469" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/> their extensive
                    background and worldwide press coverage of almost every detail in present
                    case.</p>
                <p>Sub-committee arrived Taiwan, after some 8 weeks travel, shocked, alarmed at
                    expansion of Communist influence and power in various areas and correspondingly
                    sensitive to any evidence of what might appear to them as new Communist
                    successes. Department will have noted that sub-committee’s message made no
                    reference to Outer Mongolia but reflected grave concern with larger issues
                    implicit in package deal. Presumably they felt that <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> membership for this or that country was comparatively secondary
                    consideration. If so, it is scarcely surprising that President Chiang takes
                    similar view re both new applicants and <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>’s
                    own membership.</p>
                <p>Of course I discussed with them messages from President and Secretary, which
                    already widely known through press and <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>
                    coverage including latter’s November 29 release. I stressed US anxiety obtain
                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>’s agreement refrain from using veto. I
                    told Zablocki and Judd directly that Washington would be most grateful if they
                    could change Chiang’s mind. Response clearly presaged sub-committee’s message
                    subsequently transmitted in Embassy telegram 528.<note n="3" xml:id="d212fn3">
                        <ref target="#d205">Document 205</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I did not feel free show Embassy’s file this subject to subcommittee and saw no
                    purpose doing so. If Department still dissatisfied after reading above I suggest
                    complete file of exchanges on this matter between Washington and Taipei from
                    November 13 to date be made available to sub-committee upon arrival Washington.
                    If this done, however, I believe much fuller explanation be available of
                    apparent change in US position than that given in Department’s 305.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d212fn4">
                        <ref target="#d177">Document 177</ref>.</note> I should appreciate learning
                    results of such steps, with Department’s comments.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RKL1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rankin</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
