<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-02-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="22" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d22">
                        <head>22. Draft Report Prepared by <persName corresp="#p_BLP1">Lincoln
                                Bloomfield</persName>, Special Assistant to the Assistant Secretary
                            of State for International Organization Affairs<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d22fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: Lot 60 D 113, Studies US Policy re <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. Confidential. The source text is
                                undated, but was subsequently identified as having been drafted on
                                February 9; see <ref target="#d24fn2">footnote 2, Document 24</ref>.
                                Sent to Niles Bond, Director of the Office of United Nations
                                Political and Security Affairs; <persName corresp="#p_FJE1">John E.
                                    Fobes</persName>, Director of the Office of International
                                Administration; D. Vernon McKay, Acting Deputy Director of the
                                Office of Dependent Area Affairs; James F. Green, Deputy Director of
                                the Office of International Economic and Social Affairs; and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHG1">Harold G. Kissick</persName>,
                                Director of the Office of International Conferences, all of the
                                Bureau of International Organization Affairs. In a covering note,
                                dated February 15, <persName corresp="#p_BLP1">Bloomfield</persName>
                                wrote: “The attached report, which is slightly revised from the
                                earlier draft, has been reproduced in anticipation of a meeting
                                which Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_PCH1">Phillips</persName> plan to call to
                                discuss its contents and its implications for future action. You
                                will be notified of the time of the meeting. No distribution of the
                                report is being made outside this Bureau for the present.” No record
                                of the proposed meeting hereunder reference has been found. An
                                earlier draft of this report, dated January 31, 1956, and sent by
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BLP1">Bloomfield</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_WFO1">Wilcox</persName> is in Department of State,
                                    <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss> Files: Lot 60 D 113, Studies
                                US Policy re <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-02-09">February 9,
                                        1956</date>.</hi></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Report on “Evaluation of Role of US in 10th General
                                Assembly”</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Problem</hi></p>
                        <p>To analyze objectively the effect which the 10th Session has had on the
                            international position of the United States, particularly upon the
                            factors of prestige and general reputation in the American role of world
                            leadership, both in and out of the United Nations. To draw appropriate
                            conclusions from the analysis and, where feasible, to suggest possible
                            courses of action for the immediate future.</p>
                        <pb facs="0066" n="40" xml:id="pg_40"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Note on Method</hi></p>
                        <p>This analysis involved initially a study of all pertinent documents such
                            as agenda, telegrams between the delegation and Department, resolutions,
                            voting records, written reports where available, press clippings and
                            public opinion analyses for the entire period, and such foreign public
                            and press reactions as have been reported. Interviews were held with the
                            seven committee executive officers, the four geographic liaison
                            officers, press officers, delegation advisers, correspondents, and
                            selected desk officers in the Department.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi></p>
                        <p>This study grows out of a sense of official concern at the recent
                            widespread criticism of the American position and performance at the
                            10th Assembly. It aims at objective self-scrutiny with a view to
                            possible corrective action. At the same time, such an evaluation must be
                            made in proper perspective. For example, caution must be applied to
                            sweeping claims that in the United Nations the United States either wins
                            monumental diplomatic victories or suffers irreparable diplomatic
                            defeats. It is necessary to discriminate between gains or losses which
                            have significant public and foreign impact, as against local episodes in
                            the Assembly setting that may seem equally important to those who lived
                            through them, but have little lasting or widespread effect. Another
                            order of distinction is between difficulties that grow out of the
                            substance of American foreign policies, i.e., strategic, and those
                            caused by the way we execute such policies, i.e., tactical. A final
                            prefatory caution is against viewing all such problems as suddenly acute
                            or suddenly remediable. Often they have persisted over a period of
                            years. Sometimes they grow out of larger conflicts of interest that will
                            produce tensions at other levels so long as the larger conflicts
                            persist. And in some cases they reflect the American constitutional
                            system, or partisan domestic policies, or the <pb facs="0067" n="41" xml:id="pg_41"/> free range of public and press criticism in this
                            country—that is to say, the “disabilities” under which diplomacy must
                            labor in a free democratic society.</p>
                        <p>Sometimes public criticisms tend to cancel each other out or reflect
                            primarily the political bias of the source. On the Chinese
                            Representation issue, for example, the US position is portrayed by some
                            as a victory (e.g. <hi rend="italic">Watertown Times</hi>), and by
                            others as increasingly costly to US prestige (<hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian</persName> Science
                                Monitor</hi>). Hostility toward the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> often colors estimates of US performance (although it
                            may be the other way around in this case, since Gallup polls in the same
                            period reported <hi rend="italic">80%</hi> support of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, compared with only <hi rend="italic">59%</hi> a year ago and 55% in 1954).</p>
                        <p>The effort below is to sort out the various problems for US diplomacy
                            that arose in the 10th Assembly, with these caveats in mind.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">1. General evaluation:</hi></p>
                        <p>The aftermath of the 10th Assembly has produced an unusual degree of <hi rend="italic">generalized criticism</hi> of American performance in
                            the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, coupled with concern about the
                            future effect of current trends on this nation’s role in the
                            organization. Two major external factors significantly affected that
                            role at the 10th Assembly: (a) the increased cohesiveness of the
                            Arab-Asian neutralist, anti-colonial coalition as a result of the
                            Bandung Conference, including noticeable trends away from the US
                            position by such peripheral states as Liberia, along with growing
                            defection of stragglers from the Latin American bloc; and (b) the
                            “softer” attitude of the Soviet Union, at least for a part of the
                            Assembly session. Undoubtedly both the Bandung and “Summit” meetings
                            influenced the situation in New York (although both factors can equally
                            be seen as projections of earlier trends and possibilities, rather than
                            brand-new forces). At the same time, they have not been used by friendly
                            critics to excuse defects in the American position, but rather as
                            reasons why American diplomatic failures can less and less be tolerated.
                            This point of view is often linked to the theme that the 10th General
                            Assembly was simply a landmark along a path of general deterioration in
                            the US position in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>A consensus of the generalized criticism encountered both internally and
                            in the public prints would read somewhat as follows: the United States
                            lost ground at the last Assembly, largely through its own doing. It
                            displayed unusually weak and wavering leadership, particularly on
                            important issues, and often abdicated the leading role to the UK, India
                            or the Soviet Union. It misdirected its energies by <pb facs="0068" n="42" xml:id="pg_42"/> expending unbalanced efforts on relatively
                            unimportant points, often succeeding only in irritating its friends. It
                            tended to take rigid stands and seemed to lack adequate flexibility for
                            the necessary diplomatic give-and-take. It beat tactical retreats after
                            such retreats had lost their political value. It does not know how to
                            give in or lose gracefully. It failed to consult or collaborate
                            adequately with its Allies (or, conversely, overwhelmed them with
                            multiple and overly-insistent approaches). It abused its predominant
                            position among, e.g., Latin American states, our usually staunch
                            supporters in that area and in Europe felt keenly the inconsistency and
                            confusion surrounding certain American positions and our failure to give
                            a decisive lead. We firmed up our policies much too late. Our liaison
                            was ineffective and took place at too low levels. Asian representatives
                            still detect a real or imagined sense of American racial superiority. US
                            public relations and propaganda tended to be gauche and
                            counter-productive. Increased numbers of American abstentions suggest to
                            some that bilateral relationships alone give shape to US interests. On
                            the whole, US policy in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> was
                            characterized as generally negative and aimed almost exclusively at
                            warding off policies and programs we do not support.</p>
                        <p>On the other hand, some internal views depict the US as having done “not
                            badly” in the face of positions that were unpopular, and having employed
                            skillful tactics on some items where there was a lack of fixed
                            policy.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Generalized public and press criticism</hi> pursued
                            variations of some of the same themes, often tinged with partisan
                            attitudes; the US is characteristically “defensive” in its “wavering,
                            quibbling, half-hearted support of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>…<note n="2" xml:id="d22fn2">All ellipses are in the
                                source text.</note> ever fearful of doing anything that might look
                            to some nervous right-winger on Capitol Hill as a concession to Moscow”
                                (<hi rend="italic">Cincinnati Enquirer</hi>). The US “mechanical
                            majority” has come to an end with the “stunning defeats” we suffered and
                            our “failure of leadership” (<hi rend="italic">New Republic</hi>). The
                            US is widely thought to have the power to control the outcome in the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, but does not (<hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian</persName> Science
                                Monitor</hi>). We blundered because the “men at the top” did not
                            stop to think about what they were doing (W. Lippmann).<note n="3" xml:id="d22fn3"><persName>Walter Lippmann</persName>, nationally
                                syndicated political columnist.</note> “The role of absentee is out
                            of character for the US. On every major issue … the US should take a
                            stand. To straddle is to invite contempt” (<hi rend="italic">New York
                                World-Telegram</hi>). Small nations are showing a new spirit of
                            independence vis-à-vis the US (Philadelphia <hi rend="italic">Inquirer</hi>). American diplomacy was “clumsy …. We shall be
                            missing a bet if we do not view the experience of this fall as a cue to
                            re-examine our tactics for winning friends and influencing <pb facs="0069" n="43" xml:id="pg_43"/> people” (<hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>). The US “has not played a wholly creditable
                            role” in condoning “ward politics” (<hi rend="italic">Lynchburg
                                News</hi>).</p>
                        <p>Abroad, both the <hi rend="italic">London Times</hi> and the Indian press
                            agreed that the US has lost control of the small powers, and that its
                            influence in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> is on the wane.</p>
                        <p>The prevailing opinion was summed up in the <hi rend="italic">Chicago
                                Daily News:</hi> “US prestige took a beating”. Our only victory was
                            in keeping the Chinese Communists out. “US stubborness” is to be
                            condemned. We damaged ourselves on the whole range of
                            issues—colonialism, atomic energy, disarmament, and membership. An echo
                            of this estimate is summed up this way in the <hi rend="italic">Manchester Guardian:</hi> “The most important changes, which this
                            Assembly has reflected rather than caused, are a weakening in the
                            guiding force of the United States and the rise of India as a unique
                            arbitrator”. For instance, the Latin American states “no longer leap in
                            on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>’s cues”. Or,
                            according to Tom Hamilton in <hi rend="italic">The New York Times:</hi>
                            US failures at the 10th Assembly merely reflected the declining American
                            position due to the growth of neutralism (for which we are responsible),
                            the widespread suspicions our policy toward Chinese representation
                            arouses as to our “reliability” and “good judgment”, and the resentment
                            of anti-colonial powers at our alleged colonial attitudes.</p>
                        <p>Only a small <hi rend="italic">minority praised the U.S. role: e.g.: the
                                “matchless</hi> team” of <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName>-<persName corresp="#p_NA1">Nutting</persName> held
                            the initiative successfully (NY <hi rend="italic">Journal
                            American</hi>).</p>
                        <p>Internal estimates of regional reactions tend to go to the fundamental
                            conflicts of world political interests. Generally speaking, the Near
                            Eastern States had no new or special fault to find with the US voting
                            record, but the entire relationship remains colored by the Arab
                            conviction that the US is still pro-Zionist, and the belief, sharpened
                            at Bandung, that the US is more pro-colonial than ever.</p>
                        <p>Far Eastern states reportedly have doubts as to the basic course the US
                            is following and the way we meet problems of interest to them at the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. The 10th Assembly, particularly
                            the membership “deal”, reportedly raised some disturbing questions about
                            the consistency of American anti-communism. On the credit side, to some
                            Far Eastern states, a policy of abstention is apparently a good one for
                            the US to follow, as in the Irian dispute.</p>
                        <p>Latin Americans feel we are taking them too much for granted, either
                            neglecting them or insensitively trying to command their support. The
                            addition of new members is seen as foreboding a further weakening of
                            Latin solidarity with the US, particularly on economic issues.</p>
                        <p>European states were reported as sensing that US relations with them are
                            closer in the NATO setting than in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. They felt we “overdid it” on most issues, and are
                            increasingly impatient with the <pb facs="0070" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/>
                            test of Chinese representation the US applies to every issue, whatever
                            its merits. Needless to say, they are increasingly concerned with the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>’s anti-colonial bias.</p>
                        <p>It will be noted that these criticisms summarized on the last few pages
                            are usually directed, not toward the substance of American policies, but
                            far more often toward the tactics of formulating and executing those
                            policies. There was, to be sure, considerable private and public comment
                            on substantive policies. But in the main, the correctives that have been
                            suggested bear either on improved tactics (in the broadest sense), or on
                            broad national postures, such as the overall American attitude toward
                            East-West political warfare in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>,
                            toward the colonial revolution, and toward the way in which we try to
                            mediate between international and domestic political demands.</p>
                        <p>These general critiques, while helpful in confirming the existence of
                            overall trends and public moods, need to be evaluated in the light of
                            the concrete issues at the 10th Assembly. Before doing this, however, a
                            glance at the voting record is instructive.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">2. Voting Record</hi></p>
                        <p>The voting record at the 10th Assembly does not have impressive
                            significance as a real measure of parliamentary power, since there were
                            a number of unanimous or top-heavy votes on critical items (e.g.,
                            Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy, Radiation Effects, <gloss target="#t_SUNFED1">SUNFED</gloss>, etc.) which do not reflect the
                            sizeable differences that actually existed on these subjects. For
                            example, the vote of 56 to 7 on disarmament can be seen variously as a
                            propaganda victory for the US or a “vote against sin”, but in neither
                            event does it reflect the private feelings of 56 other governments
                            regarding the US position on disarmament. The votes on admission of new
                            members took place after the “deal” was arranged and do not show the
                            conflict that previously existed (although the 50 or 51 votes received
                            by the four satellites did not indicate much moral support for the
                            continuing US distaste that was simultaneously being registered).</p>
                        <p>On East-West issues, the vote to postpone consideration of Communist
                            Chinese representation passed 42–12–6 compared to 43–11–6 in 1954, and
                            44–11–2 in 1953, suggesting a slight slippage. The motion to delete the
                            “decision in principle” to hold a Charter Review Conference failed
                            14–35–9; this may be compared to the vote of 15-28-9 in 1953 to delete
                            mention of Article 109. The difference is insignificant, but the
                            resolution as a whole passed 43–6–9, compared to 54–5–0 in 1953.</p>
                        <p>The US was on the losing side or on the fence on a number of important
                            colonial or related issues. The inscription of the Algerian item was the
                            most significant, representing as it did the overturning <pb facs="0071" n="45" xml:id="pg_45"/> of a General Committee recommendation, and
                            an indication of the numerical majority the anti-colonial coalition can
                            muster against strenuous opposition: 27–28–5. On Apartheid, with the US
                            abstaining, the vote was 41–6–8. In 1954 it was 41–10–10, and in 1953
                            38–11–11. Renewed declarations in favor of trusteeship for Southwest
                            Africa carried 43–2–9 with the US abstaining, an increase of 3 in favor
                            and a loss of one among those opposed compared with 1954 (40–3–11). A
                            sharp example of anti-colonial parliamentary strength was the vote of 34
                            in favor of transmitting the Rev. Scott’s<note n="4" xml:id="d22fn4">The
                                Reverend Michael Scott was Director of the Africa Bureau in London
                                and frequently testified before various U.N. committees on South
                                West African tribal matters.</note> statements to the Committee on
                            Southwest Africa, with 6 opposed and 14 (US) abstaining. Forty-five
                            voted in favor of examining the progress achieved by Non-Self-Governing
                            Territories, with the US and 11 other western states abstaining. And the
                            assertion of General Assembly competence to decide when administering
                            authorities could cease to transmit information passed 33 to 16 (US)–12,
                            little change from the vote of 33–12–5 in 1954. A sharper instance of
                            the fall-off of pro-colonial strength was the vote to approve cessation
                            of reporting on Surinam, which passed 21 (US)–10–33, compared with the
                            vote on Greenland in 1954 (45–1–11).</p>
                        <p>The American-inspired resolution curtailing further the powers of the
                            Administrative Tribunal<note n="5" xml:id="d22fn5">Reference is
                                presumably to Resolution 957 (X), “Procedure for Review of United
                                Nations Administrative Tribunal Judgements … ,” adopted at the 541st
                                plenary meeting of the General Assembly on November 8, 1955. For
                                text, see United Nations General Assembly Official Records, Tenth
                                Session, Supplement No. 19 (A–3116), <hi rend="italic">Resolutions
                                    adopted by the General Assembly during its Tenth Session from 20
                                    September to 20 December, 1955</hi>, pp. 30–31.</note> passed
                            33–17–9. (The 1954 resolution,<note n="6" xml:id="d22fn6">For
                                documentation on U.S. interest in the U.N. Administrative Tribunal
                                in 1954, see <ref target="frus1952-54v03#pg_312"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1952–1954, vol. III, pp. 312</ref>
                                ff.</note> which was not entirely comparable, received 52 favorable
                            votes.)</p>
                        <p>The 16 additional members are bound to have an important impact at the
                            next session in terms of colonial issues (probably 10 “anti” out of the
                            16) and on cold war issues (possibly 12 anti-West or neutral out of the
                            16). But it is difficult to single out the 10th Assembly as signalling a
                            sharp change in the voting pattern in terms of US interests. It can be
                            said that the trends toward neutralism in the East-West conflict, toward
                            greater accretions of anti-colonial strength, and toward anodyne
                            resolutions on important issues that can pass unanimously, continue to
                            follow a consistent pattern.</p>
                        <pb facs="0072" n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">3. Critique According to Specific Issues</hi></p>
                        <p>United States policies and/or tactics with respect to several issues at
                            the 10th Assembly have evoked widespread criticism, both internal and
                            external.</p>
                        <p>It might be pointed out that according to official American expectations
                            prior to the Assembly, the United States would win victories in the
                            sense of gaining maximum credit for taking the initiative on two items:
                            Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy, and Information Regarding the Effects of
                            Radiation (see <hi rend="italic">Current Foreign Relations</hi>,
                            September 21, 1955<note n="7" xml:id="d22fn7"><hi rend="italic">Current
                                    Foreign Relations</hi> was a weekly classified publication
                                circulated by the Executive Secretariat of the Department of State
                                to bureaus, offices, and posts abroad for policy guidance and
                                information.</note>). Our expectations as the rest of the agenda
                            were apparently modest, anticipating that we would either steer a middle
                            course, block undesirable results, or appear to be impartial. At the
                            same time, however, such responsible papers as <hi rend="italic">The New
                                York Times</hi> had forecast that the 10th Assembly would be “the
                            most momentous in the history of the organization”. The <hi rend="italic">Boston Post</hi> said the session would “make or
                            break” the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, and the same idea was
                            given currency by the <hi rend="italic">Newark News</hi>,<hi rend="italic">Washington Post</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Portland
                                Oregonian</hi>. Such apocalyptic views of continuing diplomatic
                            operations rarely produce mature public understanding of the
                            process.</p>
                        <p>a) <hi rend="italic">Membership</hi>. The great bulk of public and press
                            criticism was focussed on the membership issue, and the “package deal”
                            that ultimately seated 16 new members.</p>
                        <p>In general, the American press supported the package deal itself as
                            “realistic” and a major step toward universality: “A good horse trade”,
                            as the <hi rend="italic">Washington Star</hi> said. But this country’s
                            role harvested sharp criticism on almost every side. As to policy, a few
                            critics saw us as pusillanimously abandoning principle in another
                            “Munich” (32 of 37 letters received by Department, Scripps Howard
                            papers, Constantine <persName corresp="#p_BEA1">Brown</persName>, <hi rend="italic">New Bedford Standard-Times, St. <persName corresp="#p_GL1">Louis</persName> Globe-Democrat</hi>,
                                <persName>William</persName> Meany), while others condemned our
                            fastidiousness over Outer Mongolia as “stiff-necked” (e.g. <hi rend="italic">Providence Journal</hi>).</p>
                        <p>But the vast majority of public criticism had to do with US tactics—the
                            way we handled ourselves and our interests in the bargaining process.
                            The general feeling was that this country “has been out-maneuvered,
                            out-played, and left in a most unhappy position of being neither
                            practical nor principled” (<hi rend="italic">New York Herald
                                Tribune</hi>). We were seen as having tried futilely to play it both
                            ways (<hi rend="italic">Washington News</hi>), blundering into a Soviet
                            trap because of our “cowardice”, (<hi rend="italic">Washington
                            Post</hi>), aimlessly zigging and zagging (<hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian</persName> Science Monitor</hi>),
                            overreacting to right-wing domestic pressures and overlooking the rule
                            that you can’t beat somebody with nobody (T. <pb facs="0073" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/> Hamilton, <hi rend="italic">NY Times</hi>), and
                            falling into the trap we ourselves had dug (W. Lippmann).</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Indianapolis Star</hi> wrote “Whoever (was calling
                            the US signals) ought to be benched”. (See also <hi rend="italic">Long
                                Island Newsday, Commonweal, Nation</hi>.)</p>
                        <p>The US representative’s press conference statement that Outer Mongolia
                            could not “make the grade” was viewed as a tactical error, undermining
                            the impression US policy was attempting to convey (Arab Parsons, <hi rend="italic">NY Herald Tribune</hi>).</p>
                        <p>A detailed post-mortem in the <hi rend="italic">Reporter</hi> by William
                                Frye<note n="8" xml:id="d22fn8">Reference is to the <hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian</persName>
                                    Science Monitor</hi>.</note> of the <hi rend="italic">Monitor</hi> says the membership issue, while “not a colossal
                            American diplomatic snafu”, showed “inept American leadership”, and
                            failure to settle on either principle or practical politics lost us
                            considerable prestige and credit.</p>
                        <p>Such disparate voices as the <hi rend="italic">New York Post</hi>, George
                                Sokolsky,<note n="9" xml:id="d22fn9">Syndicated national
                                columnist.</note> and the <hi rend="italic">Los Angeles Times</hi>
                            agreed that Russia was the <persName corresp="#p_BVA1">victor</persName>, holding the ace of Japan, and the US, with only the
                            deuce of Outer Mongolia, the loser, Russia taking full credit for the
                            seating of the other sixteen. (See also <hi rend="italic">Boston Herald,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian</persName> Century,
                                Hartford Courant, Norfolk <persName corresp="#p_HV1">Virginia</persName> Pilot</hi>, et al.) The Indian press
                            gleefully echoed this judgment. Only the Hearst press felt the US had
                            won a victory.</p>
                        <p>US Delegation officers generally agree that the US abdicated its
                            leadership on the membership issue by failing to have a timely policy
                            that was clear-cut and consistent, appearing to be paralyzed when
                            flexible action was called for, and underlining what appeared to other
                            nations to be our “righteous hypocrisy” by urging them to dirty their
                            hands to achieve the end we came to share, while trying to keep our own
                            skirts immaculate.</p>
                        <p>According to <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, some Far Eastern states
                            are concerned at our acquiescence on the four satellites and, by
                            implication, on the dropping of Japan. (Japan is reported as now in
                            doubt as to US ability to achieve Japanese goals, and as contemplating
                            postponement of a new bid until it is “independent of all blocs”.) Near
                            Eastern spokesmen feel no one appreciated the “subtlety” of the US
                            position, seeing only that we were abstaining on the package proposal
                            while the Russians voted in favor, and won the kudos.</p>
                        <p>On balance, it is hard to recall as disturbed a reaction from so many
                            quarters to the techniques and skill of American diplomacy on a single
                            issue in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. It is not uncommon for a
                            policy stand to be widely criticized. But the target here was not
                            primarily policy, but strategy and tactics. Americans apparently hate to
                            see their diplomats flounder in a test of skill.</p>
                        <pb facs="0074" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/>
                        <p>b) <hi rend="italic">Security Council Elections</hi>. Running a close
                            second to the membership issue in terms of the volume and intensity of
                            criticism, was the protracted fight over the Security Council seat
                            involving Poland, the Philippines and Yugoslavia.</p>
                        <p>Public approval of the US stand as sound in principle, and helpful in
                            showing that we do not dominate our allies, was expressed by <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, Joseph C. Harsh in the <hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian</persName>
                                Science Monitor</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Lynchburg News,
                                Worcester Telegram and Spokane Spokesman</hi>.</p>
                        <p>But a considerably larger number were critical, usually on the grounds
                            that a great nation was making itself look small by making a mountain
                            out of a molehill, “getting in so deep we can’t get out”, “bulldozing
                            our allies”, and reaping ill-will out of all proportion to the real size
                            of the issue; “Why crack the whip over our wavering allies, when the
                            issue doesn’t really matter?” (<hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian</persName> Century</hi>). Also <hi rend="italic">Boston Herald, Kansas City Star, Nation, Providence
                                Journal, Washington Post, Kansas City Times, Milwaukee Journal,
                                Philadelphia Bulletin</hi> and many others.</p>
                        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Des Moines Register</hi> charged that the US
                            precipitated the deadlock by repudiating the “Gentlemen’s Agreement”. To
                            Barry Brown (<hi rend="italic">Providence Journal</hi>) the failure of
                            the US to agree to compromise on Yugoslavia when Poland was dropped
                            signified “an automatic reflex—an expression of a desire to beat the
                            Russians just for the sake of beating them … a dead end into which
                            American policy instinctively runs”. The <hi rend="italic">St. <persName corresp="#p_GL1">Louis</persName> Post Dispatch</hi> wrote that
                            the US Delegation “has been frittering away its prestige”.</p>
                        <p>Only Senator Jenner<note n="10" xml:id="d22fn10">William Jenner,
                                (R.–Ind.).</note> was heard to criticize the US for “letting down”
                            the Philippines.</p>
                        <p>The consensus within the Department was that this was an instance of a
                            policy getting out of hand in that the original commitment did not
                            envisage the US making a do-or-die stand, without the support of its
                            major allies, in opposition, not to a Soviet satellite state, but a
                            friendly power, i.e., Yugoslavia. Apart from the unplanned
                            over-engagement of US prestige, additional criticism arises from the
                            refusal of the US to go along with the majority on the “Eastern European
                            seat”. The UK apparently took a certain relish in proving to us how
                            difficult it is to secure a ⅔ vote without their support. It is felt
                            that we should save our ammunition for important substantive items, and
                            learn to lose gracefully in such procedural issues as elections. The one
                            regional estimate on the credit side represents the Far Eastern states
                            as in complete support of the US stand on the Philippines; <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> feels the detachment of Indonesia from
                            India in the voting on this item was of real importance.</p>
                        <pb facs="0075" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/>
                        <p>c) <hi rend="italic">Disarmament</hi>. With this and succeeding issues,
                            the quantity of domestic press comment falls off drastically. Although
                            the resolution<note n="11" xml:id="d22fn11">Reference is presumably to
                                Resolution 914 (X), “Regulation, Limitation, and Balanced Reduction
                                of all Armed Forces and all Armaments … ,” adopted at the 559th
                                plenary meeting of the General Assembly on December 16, 1955. For
                                text, see United Nations General Assembly Official Records, Tenth
                                Session, Supplement No. 19 (A–3116), <hi rend="italic">Resolutions
                                    adopted by the General Assembly during its Tenth Session from 20
                                    September to 20 December, 1955</hi>, pp. 5–6.</note> that passed
                            was officially represented as a victory for the US, the press did not
                            generally share this view. According to the <hi rend="italic">Special PS
                                Report on Disarmament</hi>,<note n="12" xml:id="d22fn12">Presumably
                                a report prepared by the Political Studies Division of the Bureau of
                                Public Affairs.</note> while the majority of the press was favorable
                            to the President’s “open skies” proposal, a majority of the general
                            public is opposed to it. (43% of those polled felt its acceptance would
                            make a surprise attack on the US more likely, while only 13% thought it
                            would make it less likely.)</p>
                        <p>Delegation officers felt that while US policy was “uncertain” at the 10th
                            Assembly this fact was successfully concealed. Such critics of the US
                            proposal as the Indians and Scandinavians suppressed their private
                            criticisms of what they called the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            “non-disarmament” plan, and in this case a weak position turned out
                            satisfactorily, with credit given the US delegation for skillful
                            handling.</p>
                        <p>d) <hi rend="italic">Cyprus</hi>. Because of its special nature, this
                            issue is isolated from other inscription problems (Algeria and Western
                            New Guinea) and from colonial issues.</p>
                        <p>Press comment was divided. <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>
                            applauded the US vote against inscription. The <hi rend="italic">Portland Oregonian</hi>, on the other hand, wrote: “The role of the
                            US in the ugly Cyprus question does not arouse our pride. This country
                            has again placed military expediency and old ties with Britain above
                            ethical and legal requirements of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            Charter”.</p>
                        <p>Delegation officers feel the US was forthright and emerged relatively
                            unscathed.</p>
                        <p>Needless to say, Greece was unhappy with our stand. The Netherlands was
                            unable to understand why we could not have taken the same position on
                            the inscription of Western New Guinea. No real criticism has been
                            encountered on US tactics.</p>
                        <p>e) <hi rend="italic">Algeria</hi>. Most newspapers (according to <hi rend="italic">PS Studies #113</hi><note n="12" target="d22fn12">Presumably a report prepared by the Political Studies Division of
                                the Bureau of Public Affairs.</note>) felt the final vote to
                            inscribe was a violation of the Charter. On the other hand, the <hi rend="italic">Des Moines Register</hi> saw US policy as “weak and
                            wobbly … when it should have been clear and fearless”. (This sort of
                            comment is fairly typical of the domestic press on colonial issues where
                            the US appears to it to be “trimming” rather than taking a doctrinaire
                            anti-colonial stand.)</p>
                        <pb facs="0076" n="50" xml:id="pg_50"/>
                        <p>According to some internal estimates, the US did not lose ground with the
                            anti-colonial powers by supporting France, although the French were
                            resentful that our support was not more vigorous. But other officers
                            felt we suffered by contributing to the portrayal of the US as a
                            pro-colonial power. The vote on inscription was also seen as
                            demonstrating the growing authority of small powers in the changing
                            power-patterns of the Assembly. “Most” other delegations reportedly
                            disagreed with our legal stand on the question of competence, and
                            believed that our decision was ad hominem and inconsistent with the
                            stand we have taken on, e.g., South-African items. The sharpest
                            criticism of this nature comes from <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>
                            sources, where our abstention on Irian, which was “understood”, could
                            not be reconciled with our negative vote on Algeria.</p>
                        <p>f) <hi rend="italic">Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy</hi>. On this and the
                            next two items the opinion has been voiced that the US dissipated the
                            initial strength of its positions by a rigid initial insistence on
                            restrictive and unpopular features such as limiting the participants,
                            requiring us ultimately to swallow changes which were of real prestige
                            significance to other countries, and for which we got no credit and
                            considerable blame.</p>
                        <p>Again, estimates vary. It was agreed, in retrospect, that we were
                            unrealistic in thinking we could control the formation of the agency,
                            with hand-picked membership. Not only the Indians and Soviets, but also
                            the Scandinavians, Mexicans, Dutch, New Zealanders, Israelis, etc. were
                            unwilling to accept the Statute on a take-it-or-leave-it basis, or the
                            provision that only recipients of materials would be subject to
                            inspection. The final result was that the US had to accept (a) four
                            additional sponsoring powers (Brazil, Czechoslovakia, India and the
                            USSR), (b) provision for the Secretary General to study the agency’s
                            relationship to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, and (c)
                            invitations to all governments to a conference to consider the final
                            text.</p>
                        <p>Some officers felt we were adequately flexible in making timely
                            concessions. According to others, we were overly rigid, grudgingly
                            giving way under pressure from our friends, and as a result, forfeiting
                            the credit and goodwill we deserved for an important lead.</p>
                        <p>g) <hi rend="italic">Effects of Radiation</hi>. This item, also billed in
                            advance as a primary US initiative, was believed by some of those
                            involved to have lost its punch because of US insistence on restricting
                            the membership of the committee. Although our position was defensible on
                            its merits, in retrospect we were seen as honestly mistaken in our
                            concern over the qualifications of participants, since four more were
                            added in a process of “log-rolling” in which the US again had to appear
                            to be blocking a role for others which they felt important to their
                            prestige. While we were able to defeat a Syrian-Indonesian amendment to
                            ban nuclear tests and a Russian amendment to <pb facs="0077" n="51" xml:id="pg_51"/> include the Chinese Communists, the Latin
                            Americans, for instance, were particularly indignant at the narrowness
                            of the participation we had proposed.</p>
                        <p>h) <hi rend="italic">Charter Review</hi>. This was the third instance of
                            the US having to give way under pressure for enlarged participation of a
                            committee, based on prestige considerations in the minds of friendly
                            states. However, despite the lukewarm attitude of the Assembly as a
                            whole to the US interest in a Review Conference, it was believed that by
                            minimizing the US tactical role and eventually accommodating US policy
                            to the prevailing atmosphere, we came out “not badly”.</p>
                        <p>i) <hi rend="italic">Economic Development</hi>. Ninety percent of the
                            Committee II discussion centered on the question of economic development
                            of underdeveloped countries. According to <hi rend="italic">Current
                                Economic Developments</hi> (Dec. 20<note n="13" xml:id="d22fn13"><hi rend="italic">Current Economic Developments</hi> was a
                                classified internal publication of the Department of State.
                                Published semimonthly between 1945 and 1974, it was circulated to
                                various Bureaus and offices as a policy and information guide.
                                (Washington National Records Center, <hi rend="italic">Current
                                    Economic Developments:</hi> FRC 72 A 6248) This collection of
                                reports was released in <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations, Current
                                    Economic Developments, 1945–1954</hi>, microfiche
                                publication.</note>) the Soviet bloc “continued to exhibit apparent
                            reasonableness in their analysis of international economic problems and
                            at the same time strongly emphasized their concern for the problems of
                            the under-developed countries, particularly their efforts at
                            industralization”.</p>
                        <p>The US, while well-equipped on Technical Assistance and actively
                            supporting the International Finance Corporation, had planned to
                            continue its opposition to <gloss target="#t_SUNFED1">SUNFED</gloss>
                            “pending savings from disarmament”, and there has been some internal
                            criticism of the way the US handled this item. It was felt that we were
                            constantly on the defensive, largely because of our “weak”,
                            “vacillating” or “fuzzy” position. In <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> the US had abstained on setting up an Ad Hoc
                            Committee to study the question, a proposal which is considered by
                            delegation officers to have been innocuous. But the Assembly delegation
                            was given the same position to take, because of Treasury opposition. The
                            delegation was thus felt to be “forced” to make its own decision to
                            support the Ad Hoc Committee. US indecision was apparently obvious to
                            others, and of course the internal effect of having the delegation
                            override its instructions is harmful. There is agreement that the
                            Department should have taken a firmer stand with Treasury at the time
                            the instructions were drafted. As it was, this is considered another
                            instance of US half-heartedness and foot-dragging on a highly popular
                            item.</p>
                        <p>j) <hi rend="italic">Racial Issues</hi>. As with several other items, the
                            UK played a far more active role on <hi rend="italic">Apartheid</hi>
                            than the US. The same was true with <pb facs="0078" n="52" xml:id="pg_52"/> respect to Indians in South Africa, although the US
                            reportedly reaped some credit for voting in favor of the Indian
                                resolution.<note n="14" xml:id="d22fn14">Reference is to Resolution
                                No. 917 (X), “Question of Race Conflict in South Africa Resulting
                                from the Policies of <hi rend="italic">Apartheid</hi> … ,” adopted
                                at the 551st plenary meeting of the General Assembly on December 6,
                                1955. For text, see United Nations General Assembly Official
                                Records, Tenth Session, Supplement No. 19 (A–3116), <hi rend="italic">Resolutions adopted by the General Assembly during
                                    its Tenth Session from 20 September to 20 December, 1955</hi>,
                                pp. 5–6.</note></p>
                        <p>k) <hi rend="italic">Korea</hi>. Delegation staff estimates no losses and
                            no gains. We had intended to minimize debate as unhelpful at this time,
                            and apparently invited the skepticism of e.g., India by standing pat on
                            anodyne reaffirmations of principle. (It is difficult to see what else
                            we could have done.)</p>
                        <p>l) <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss>
                                Elections</hi>. According to delegation officers, the US policy of
                            holding back until the last minute before making a commitment to a
                            candidate irritated both the potential candidates, and the US’ final
                            choice. We vacillated between Indonesia and Afghanistan and also between
                            Brazil and Costa Rica, even though Brazil was much the better candidate,
                            and even after we knew that a majority of the Latin American nations
                            favored her candidacy.</p>
                        <p>m) <hi rend="italic">Self-Determination</hi>. The US delegation was able
                            to bring a number of the have-not nations to agree to an amendment to
                            paragraph 3 of Article I of the draft covenant that might have satisfied
                            US overseas business interests. However, the US neither introduced nor
                            voted for it, and even though it embodied changes we had sought, it was
                            adopted over US opposition 33–12–13. In this case, as in other cases
                            where the US eventually votes against humanitarian measures on such
                            subjects as slavery, forced labor, etc., because they are in convention
                            or treaty form, some officers feel important foreign policy
                            considerations are being sacrificed to domestic policy at a net loss to
                            the national interest. (But the Legal Adviser’s Office, for example,
                            considers that our opposition to the self-determination draft language
                            was based on dissatisfaction with the text, and uncertainty whether it
                            would indeed be satisfactory to the business community.)</p>
                        <p>n) <hi rend="italic">Administrative Tribunal</hi>. The debate to amend
                            the Statute to provide for judicial review was conducted on a rational
                            level and the ammunition used on both sides was largely restricted to
                            legal arguments. The US position was reasonable and based on precedent,
                            but there was stiff resistance on all sides largely because of the
                            remaining emotional undercurrents created by the past history of this
                            issue. Majority support was, however, mustered for the US position as a
                            result of strong US political pressure behind the scenes, and the active
                            support and lobbying of the UK. While the results seemed to leave no
                            hard feelings, there was a general feeling among delegation <pb facs="0079" n="53" xml:id="pg_53"/> advisers that success on this
                            item sapped the support for US positions on other administrative issues,
                            such as the level of the budget.</p>
                        <p>o) <hi rend="italic">Other Administrative Items</hi>. While the US
                            position on numerous other items in the Fifth Committee, notably on
                            salary and budget increases, did not command majority support, this
                            appeared to be due less to sharp governmental differences than to the
                            increasingly strong position of the Secretary-General with the majority
                            and his willingness to put it to a test regardless of whether his
                            proposals had the support of the larger contributors, notably the UK and
                            the US. The United States did not appear to enjoy the previous
                            privileged position of a confidant of the <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> and his staff on important issues. While the old
                            relationship did not eliminate public disagreement it did minimize
                            unnecessary public divergencies and friction. While some initiative on
                            US part to re-establish more effective relations can help, one of the
                            basic problems is that, while the Secretary-General appears to want to
                            keep administrative matters under close review and supervision, he is
                            not himself accessible enough to the Fifth Committee because of other
                            demands on his time, and the officers who represent him in Fifth
                            Committee matters often cannot speak authoritatively for him and do not
                            seem to have much latitude for independent action.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">4. “Internal” Problems</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Among both departmental and public critics of the US performance at the
                            10th Assembly, there was agreement that our participation was
                            handicapped by one or more administrative shortcomings that do not bear
                            on the substance of our policies or on our diplomatic tactics.</p>
                        <p>a) <hi rend="italic">Timing of US preparations</hi>. A perennial
                            difficulty that underlay much criticism of the US role in the 10th
                            Assembly was the repeated lateness in determining our positions and
                            communicating them to friendly governments in good time. Many
                            difficulties in liaison, such as the multiplicity of US approaches to
                            foreign capitals, waste of diplomatic effort and ammunition, and
                            irritation of other delegations and governments, would be obviated or
                            lessened if the US could come up with timely positions and consult with
                            other nations at the time they are formulating instructions to their own
                            delegations. Unfortunately (though often understandably) it is
                            frequently on the most sensitive issues that the US appears unable to
                            make up its mind in sufficient time to accumulate needful international
                            understanding and support. (The Department apparently realized in
                            advance that restricting the composition of the peaceful uses
                            negotiating group, for instance, would not succeed in New York, and
                            would thus have to be changed on the ground, always a painful
                            process.)</p>
                        <pb facs="0080" n="54" xml:id="pg_54"/>
                        <p>This general problem of timing is too well known to require further
                            elaboration.</p>
                        <p>b) <hi rend="italic">Multiplicity of Diplomatic Representations</hi>.
                            Several regional sources complained of unnecessary multiplication of
                            approaches to other nations. In several cases we made representations to
                            delegations in New York, embassies in Washington, and to the foreign
                            offices as well, resulting in over-use of pressure, causing resentment
                            and loss of good-will, and implying lack of trust of the particular
                            General Assembly delegation, the foreign embassy in Washington, or the
                            US Embassy in the country concerned.</p>
                        <p>Both <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss> felt we had squandered diplomatic efforts in repeated
                            approaches to other nations for support on <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> questions that were of relatively minor importance. This
                            tended to inflate the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> problems out of
                            proportion and used up our limited stock of ammunition, at times on
                            questions where nothing could have been accomplished regardless of the
                            pressure we brought to bear. Sometimes this tactic forced friendly
                            delegations to stiffen their positions on matters on which they had not
                            felt strongly at first.</p>
                        <p>c) <hi rend="italic">Liaison</hi>. There was, as has often been the case
                            before, some dissatisfaction with the arrangements within the US
                            delegation on communicating with other delegations. The regional
                            advisers felt it was a mistake to assign liaison officers on the basis
                            of subject rather than area. On the other hand, staffs of some
                            committees who claim they rarely see the liaison officers, were pleased
                            to have the use of one.</p>
                        <p>Some officers in this Bureau deplore <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>’s
                            inability to select the liaison officers and “having to take whoever is
                            free”. And at least one of the senior regional advisers has complained
                            that he was used, in effect, as an “errand boy”, thus losing the
                            confidence of senior members of his “client” delegations who were quick
                            to note his lack of participation at high levels in the US
                            Delegation.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Findings</hi></p>
                        <p>1. Of 11 basic substantive issues at the 10th Assembly, in 9 cases the
                            substance of US <hi rend="italic">policy</hi> did not command wide
                            approbation: (a) Membership, i.e., previous US opposition to “package”
                            deal, and continuing US opposition to Outer Mongolia; (b) Security
                            Council elections, i.e., US rejection of the so-called Gentlemen’s
                            Agreement; (c) Disarmament, i.e., the feeling on the part of some
                            members that our inspection proposal, while good, is insufficiently
                            pointed to disarmament; (d) Algeria, and colonial issues generally,
                            where we are usually damned by both sides; (e) Charter Review; (f)<gloss target="#t_SUNFED1">SUNFED</gloss>; (g) Self-Determination and US
                            abstention from treaty-drafting involving human rights; (h) the
                            Administrative Tribunal; and (i) the perennial <pb facs="0081" n="55" xml:id="pg_55"/> issue of Chinese representation, where our
                            supporters increasingly chafe under the US position and deplore the
                            overriding importance we attach to it.</p>
                        <p>But in 5 of the 9 cases in which US policy itself was criticized, the
                            most intense criticism was actually directed toward the <hi rend="italic">tactics</hi> this Government employed in executing its
                            policy: Membership, Security Council elections, <gloss target="#t_SUNFED1">SUNFED</gloss>, Self-Determination and
                            Algeria.</p>
                        <p>In the other four cases where US policy was something less than
                            universally popular, adequate tactics seem to have done much to preserve
                            our standing: Disarmament, Charter Review, Administrative Tribunal and
                            Chinese Representation.</p>
                        <p>Conversely, while US policy on two other issues—Peaceful Uses and the
                            Effects of Radiation—were generally applauded, US tactics appear to have
                            caused loss of credit and prestige.</p>
                        <p>The ideal is of course sound policy and effective tactics. If policies
                            are unpopular or difficult to put across, sovereign importance attaches
                            to tactics.</p>
                        <p>From the record of the 10th Assembly one might conclude that efficient,
                            consistent and mature tactics can offset the disadvantages inherent in
                            an unpopular policy. But one can also conclude that no tactical
                            approach, however skillful, can compensate for policies which are
                            unattractive to a significant number of other governments. Probably the
                            truth lies somewhere between the two.</p>
                        <p>2. There are two underlying causes of US “unpopularity” in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> at the present time which do not grow out
                            of specific American policies, attitudes or tactics: <list>
                                <label>a)</label>
                                <item>A primary psychological factor that is always present is
                                    resentment at the power, wealth and predominant position of this
                                    nation. It affects the attitudes of enemies, neutrals and allies
                                    alike. This is an inescapable consequence of the world power
                                    situation. It is a “built in” characteristic of such
                                    relationships, and little can be done about it other than on the
                                    surface. The sooner we accept this fact of life, the less
                                    handicapped we will be by a sense of chronic uneasiness and
                                    guilt that we are not smaller, or that we are not
                                    “loved”.</item>
                                <label>b)</label>
                                <item>Another persistent cause of difficulty for the US in the
                                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> stems from the demands of
                                    the cold war, i.e., the necessity for the US to maintain a firm
                                    position vis-à-vis the force of world communism. So long as that
                                    force threatens our values and, at times, our existence, we will
                                    not be able to minimize it to the extent desired by those who
                                    would prefer we not assume a posture of vigorous resistance.
                                    Under these circumstances we cannot have the unqualified support
                                    of neutralist nations. We can, however, decide whether certain
                                    emphases <hi rend="italic">in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> setting</hi> on the cold war are fruitful
                                    for US interests, or whether they are counter-productive. Our
                                    purposes are <pb facs="0082" n="56" xml:id="pg_56"/> not well
                                    served by choices based on other than a rational evaluation of
                                    the net loss or gain to the national interest of such
                                    tactics.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>3. Other causes of US “unpopularity” <hi rend="italic">do</hi> relate to
                            specific American policies which do not command wide and ungrudging
                            support in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>: <list>
                                <label>a)</label>
                                <item>is the complex of <hi rend="italic">cold war policies</hi>
                                    referred to above.</item>
                                <label>b)</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Colonial policy</hi>. The US could probably
                                    pick up large-scale support in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, and ease its troubled national conscience in
                                    the bargain, if it adopted a doctrinaire anti-colonial position
                                    across the board. To do so would, of course, be to abdicate the
                                    bulk of our other responsibilities and commitments, not to
                                    mention our judgment. Thus, we will doubtless have to continue
                                    to maneuver precariously and thanklessly between two conflicting
                                    forces in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. It might be
                                    that we could find a way to reconcile our verbal policies, which
                                    tend to alienate the colonial powers, with our action policies,
                                    which tend to alienate the anti-colonial powers. But there is
                                    not much real latitude for American policy here under present
                                    conditions, and it would be wise to realize that we are not
                                    going to win any popularity contests on the colonial issue
                                    within the framework of our present overall policy
                                    structure.</item>
                                <label>c)</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Economic development</hi>. Unless the US is
                                    prepared to commit significantly larger sums of money than at
                                    present, the underdeveloped countries will probably remain
                                    generally dissatisfied with our performance. Even within the
                                    limits imposed by an election year, it would be desirable to
                                    explore new avenues for US leadership in this field, with
                                    particular reference to the joint statement of December 9, 1955,
                                    by the members of the US Assembly Delegation. It must be
                                    remembered, however, that even if we raise the ante appreciably,
                                    it will not necessarily buy us the affection and respect of the
                                    recipients or their support in the cold war. It might increase
                                    their stability and viability, and we should perhaps be content
                                    with that important objective when and if we can raise our bid.
                                    In this connection it is well to keep in mind that a significant
                                    increase in the French standard of living over the past few
                                    years seems to have made no real dent in the Communist vote. The
                                    uncomplicated notion of “belly communism” may contain a fallacy,
                                    and the US should devote more thought to the ideological and
                                    prestige issues of passionate concern to the under-developed
                                    countries which may be equally important in fixing their
                                    political orientation.</item>
                                <label>d)</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Self-Determination, Human Rights, etc</hi>.
                                    This area involves a whole set of symbols which in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> tend to evoke emotional responses
                                    from the non-Western world. It is quite true that the West gave
                                    those symbols whatever meaning they possess today, and that the
                                    Communists repudiate the real values that underlie them.
                                    Nevertheless the argument in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> is not always a rational one. There, <pb facs="0083" n="57" xml:id="pg_57"/> these symbols are
                                    imbedded in the concrete human rights issues on which countries
                                    stand up to be counted: Self-determination, Apartheid, Human
                                    Rights Covenant, etc. So long as the US appears to oppose such
                                    symbolic affirmations, however good our reasons, we are not
                                    going to look good either to doctrinaire libertarians, or to the
                                    non-Western countries to whom they are of such acute
                                    concern.</item>
                                <label>d)</label>
                                <item>[<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Chinese
                                        Representation</hi>. It has become quite clear that in
                                    demanding support on this generally unpopular issue, we are
                                    draining the reserves of goodwill and solidarity which we would
                                    like to have available to us on other matters. The US cannot
                                    tamper with its present policy on this subject, but we should
                                    recognize clearly its underlying effect as a chronic irritant
                                    and factor for divisiveness.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>4. Thus, there is a hard core of US policies which encounter strong
                            opposition in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> on political,
                            strategic, economic and ideological grounds. If the policies designed to
                            advance our grand strategy are based on sound principles, or at least on
                            realistic balancing of domestic and international political imperatives,
                            there is obviously little room for change in them, and certainly they
                            should not be changed for the sake of popularity alone. At the same
                            time, it must be understood that, barring such substantial change, it is
                            fruitless to search for miracles, or rabbits that can be pulled out of a
                            hat to offset the basic impact of these policies on other nations.</p>
                        <p>It may be, however, that in the realm of tactics and the handling of
                            procedural issues, there is more room for maneuver in the American
                            position.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">5. Procedural</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>a)</label>
                            <item><p><hi rend="italic">Elections</hi>. At least twice in recent
                                    years (1951, 1955) we have become involved in extraordinary
                                    difficulties in Assembly sessions because of our unwillingness
                                    to countenance the election of an Eastern European state to a
                                    non-permanent Security Council seat. The validity of the US
                                    position rested on principle—the manifest inability of a Soviet
                                    satellite to satisfy the requirements of Article 23, Paragraph
                                    1; and on expediency—the desire to keep a second Soviet vote off
                                    the Council. These arguments were weakened by the fact of
                                    Security Council impotence, the inconsistency with election of
                                    Soviet satellites to other posts, and above all by the
                                    understanding of many other states that this particular seat was
                                    to go to an Eastern European state. Unfortunately, in both cases
                                    the fight turned out to be with our closest allies rather than
                                    primarily with our enemies.</p>
                                <p>The fact that the US has now tacitly approved the election of
                                    four more satellites to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>,
                                    in combination with the above considerations, suggests that our
                                    interests might be best served in the future if a new agreement
                                    is reached with respect to the election <pb facs="0084" n="58" xml:id="pg_58"/> of non-permanent seats, possibly in
                                    connection with a move to expand the Security Council’s
                                    membership, so that in the future we can be guided on this
                                    prestige-laden procedural issue by the legitimate wishes of each
                                    recognized grouping, rather than pressing for an independent
                                    candidate against the opinion of the majority.</p>
                                <p>(Any future decision to vote in favor of a Soviet bloc candidate
                                    for the Security Council will have to be taken in conjunction
                                    with present US policy not to vote for Soviet candidates for any
                                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> post whatever, a policy
                                    that strikes some observers as “toughness” at a minor level of
                                    diplomatic courtesy which is not necessarily matched at the
                                    level of major policies.)</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>b)</label>
                            <item><p><hi rend="italic">Inscription</hi>. Questions of inscription
                                    usually represent policy rather than procedural decisions, but
                                    if they are considered at least partly procedural it might help
                                    to clarify our problem. Inscription on the agenda usually
                                    relates to the question of domestic jurisdiction, most commonly
                                    in the colonial field. Neither the US nor, for that matter, the
                                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> as a whole has ever
                                    decided on legal grounds whether the threshold of Article 2(7)
                                    is crossed at the point of inscription, debate, or
                                    recommendation. The US has modified its earlier insistence on
                                    the freedom of the Assembly to discuss, by voting against
                                    inscription of such issues as Algeria and Cyprus. It is right
                                    and proper that political rather than legal considerations
                                    should guide us in making what are essentially political
                                    decisions of this nature. However, Asian countries, for example,
                                    saw our vote against inscribing the Algerian item as
                                    contradicting the neutrality we proclaimed when we abstained on
                                    inscribing the Irian item. On the other hand, our vote against
                                    inscribing the Cyprus item was generally understood, except by
                                    Greece, as based on genuine concern for the pacification of the
                                    problem.</p>
                                <p>An announced policy of favoring or at least not opposing
                                    inscription of any item that is at least arguably of an
                                    international nature, and then dealing with it on the merits,
                                    might have the advantage of restoring consistency to the moral
                                    position first enunciated by Senator <persName corresp="#p_VAH1">Vandenberg</persName>, and might undercut the special
                                    pressures that are always applied to us on close questions of
                                    jurisdiction. This would also enable us to maintain our
                                    pragmatic position, which avoids rigid and restrictive
                                    interpretation of Article 2(7), but retains flexibility to
                                    decide on Assembly action in each case on its merits.</p>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">6. Tactics</hi></p>
                        <p>This comes in two parts: <list>
                                <label>a)</label>
                                <item><p>The presence of the cold war in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> runs directly athwart another powerful set
                                        of currents which involve the neutralist movement, the
                                        economic and human rights drives, and the motif of
                                        anti-colonialism which seems to be the dominant trend in the
                                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> today.</p>
                                    <pb facs="0085" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/>
                                    <p>In this context, a growing majority of countries entertain a
                                        set of expectations about the US which would probably
                                        require us, as suggested earlier, to dispense with the cold
                                        war, satisfy economic and social demands to a far greater
                                        extent, and support the anti-colonial coalition on colonial
                                        issues. Our inability to do these things automatically
                                        detracts from our leadership position in the present
                                        parliamentary setting of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. But it is still possible to win support for
                                        issues of importance to us, as we have demonstrated in the
                                        past, by the use of tactics which imply that we view our
                                        relations with other countries as co-equal, respectful,
                                        conciliatory, and friendly, yet vigorous enough, when
                                        appropriate, to give the necessary lead.</p>
                                    <p>So far as the cold war is concerned, while the bulk of the
                                        membership wishes us to subdue our anti-communism, we have
                                        compelling national reasons for emphasizing it on
                                        appropriate occasions. When we do so purposefully it is
                                        because it serves our larger interests, only remembering
                                        that the price we pay is to annoy a significant number of
                                        other governments. But when we do so unnecessarily or
                                        gratuitously it apparently seems petty and childish to our
                                        friends, and exacerbates relations with the neutrals. We
                                        cannot have it both ways, at least not in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</p>
                                </item>
                                <label>b)</label>
                                <item>In the realm of detailed tactics there may be significant room
                                    for improvement. Numerous criticisms have been noted regarding
                                    the failure of the US: to prepare its positions on important
                                    issues in time to undertake advance negotiations with friendly
                                    governments with either adequacy or timeliness, to conform our
                                    public statements to the immediate ends we are pursuing, to
                                    conduct liaison with other delegations in ways which are
                                    productive rather than counterproductive, to improve our press
                                    relations, to prepare the delegation on each item in sufficient
                                    time, to limit and aim our diplomatic representations with
                                    accuracy rather than using the shotgun method involving three
                                    centers of negotiation, to distinguish between matters of little
                                    and major importance to us and of little and major importance to
                                    other governments, to execute our policies on the ground with
                                    skill, consistency, and self-confidence, and to learn to give
                                    up, give in, or lose on relatively unimportant matters, with any
                                    degree of grace. At least some of these seem to be within the
                                    range of rational and purposeful control by the Department, and
                                    might well be intensively re-examined in order to improve our
                                    posture before the next General Assembly.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Summary of Conclusion</hi></p>
                        <p>Barring basic changes in major contemporary US policies in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, this country is going to be the target
                            of a certain amount of <pb facs="0086" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/>
                            resentment and dissatisfaction. If the strategy reflected in those
                            policies is sound, it would be wise for us to forget about winning
                            popularity contests (which is a questionable desire for a great power
                            anyway) and concentrate a great deal harder on procedural and tactical
                            improvements. If it is important to our vital interests to appear tough
                            and unyielding in pursuing our ends, the only sensible course is to stop
                            worrying about the affection of others, and concentrate on maintaining
                            our prestige in the sense of reputation for power, as the British did
                            when the Royal Navy rather than the US Strategic Air Command kept the
                            peace.</p>
                        <p>If this is unacceptable, as it undoubtedly is in the light of our
                            national temperament, then we must either give way on some of the basic
                            “core” issues, or extract every ounce of profit we can from the field of
                            tactics. As suggested, there seem to be many opportunities available for
                            offsetting tactics in the areas of elections, diplomatic consultations,
                            press relations, attentiveness to the wishes of others, magnanimity,
                            hospitality, and all the other lubricants and amenities of diplomatic
                            (and human) relationships.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Recommendations</hi></p>
                        <p>It is beyond the scope of this paper to recommend remedial action in
                            detail, but it is suggested that early attention be given to the
                            following possibilities: <list>
                                <label>a)</label>
                                <item>We should take the initiative without delay to sponsor an
                                    agenda item for the next Assembly session to expand the
                                    membership of the Security Council and <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> in order to account for
                                    the increased membership. We should not allow this bid, which
                                    aims importantly at Asia, to go by default to the USSR. We are
                                    aware of the difficult political problems involved, but the
                                    inevitability of this action suggests that the US plan now to
                                    get full credit for taking the initiative.</item>
                                <label>b)</label>
                                <item>Perhaps as part of the expanded Council membership, we should
                                    support a clear understanding of geographic allocation on the
                                    non-permanent Security Council seats, putting a stop to the
                                    perennial squabble over the Eastern European seat. This might be
                                    done informally, or possibly through a declaration or
                                    resolution. Our policy should then be to accept the candidate of
                                    each bloc for the appropriate seat, as a general rule.</item>
                                <label>c)</label>
                                <item>We should consider whether a larger allocation of the current
                                    and projected US economic aid appropriation could not be
                                    channeled to multi-lateral programs (on the assumption that,
                                    particularly in an election year, a significant increase in the
                                    appropriation is unrealistic). We might meanwhile be
                                    blueprinting new economic programs that the US could at some
                                    other time advance in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, as
                                    well as <pb facs="0087" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/> new approaches
                                    in the social and human rights fields which would represent
                                    American values and concepts most meaningfully to those
                                    countries which misread our purposes.</item>
                                <label>d)</label>
                                <item>We should re-examine the consistency of our position regarding
                                    Article 2(7) and perhaps undertake consultations looking to a
                                    more satisfactory consensus, before the 11th Session.</item>
                                <label>e)</label>
                                <item>We should revive earlier programs for intensive advance
                                    diplomatic consultations, and utilize all existing
                                    intra-departmental and intra-governmental machinery to ensure
                                    that US policies are determined sufficiently in advance so that
                                    they can be executed intelligently and with profit to this
                                    country.</item>
                                <label>f)</label>
                                <item>We should take steps to improve drastically the state of press
                                    relations in New York, possibly by assigning the Department’s
                                    top press officer to the next General Assembly
                                    delegation.</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>