<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-12-14T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-12-14T23:00:00-05:00" n="221" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d221">
                        <head>221. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Japan</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d221fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 310.2/12–1555. Confidential; Niact.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Tokyo</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-12-15T13:00:00+09:00">December 15, 1955—1
                                        p.m.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1361. Re <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1255.<note n="2" xml:id="d221fn2">Not printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                                310.2/12–1455)</note> In accordance with instructions I called on
                            Shigemitsu at 12:15 pm at House of Councillors. He expressed
                            appreciation of United States efforts to obtain Japan’s admission to
                            United Nations and said he had no objection to press release concerning
                            my call. Verbatim text of statement released to press 1:00 pm Tokyo time
                            in my immediate following unclassified telegram.<note n="3" xml:id="d221fn3">Not printed.</note></p>
                        <p>Shigemitsu said he and government had been subjected all morning in House
                            of Councillors to vigorous attack as result of Soviet Union veto. He and
                            Prime Minister are being held responsible and Shigemitsu said there was
                            real danger that he might not be able to remain in office. Government is
                            being attacked for too much dependence on United States and for
                            stubbornness in negotiations with Soviet Union which, according to
                            Socialist opposition, is cause of Russia’s veto. He said Government
                            would remain firm in its position and it realizes that Soviet action had
                            been taken for deliberate purpose of causing trouble between friends and
                            putting pressure on Japan to speed up negotiations. I have never seen
                            Shigemitsu look as worried as he did this noon and I believe there is
                                <pb facs="0480" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/> real substance in his
                            fears that he may be forced to assume responsibility and have to leave
                            government.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AJM1"><hi rend="strong">Allison</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>