<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>3. Telegram From the Mission at the United Nations to the to the Department
                    of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">3</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-06-02T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-06-02T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-06-02T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-06-02T19:00:00-05:00" n="3"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d3">
                <head>3. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission at the United Nations</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d3fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 310.1/6–255. Confidential; Priority.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1955-06-02T19:00:00-05:00">June 2, 1955—7 p.m.</date>
                        </hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>850. Re Charter review. <persName corresp="#p_DSPJ1">Dixon</persName> (UK) called
                    on me today to discuss, among other things, Foreign Office’s instructions
                    concerning Charter review. These instructions have gone out to all UK posts in
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> member countries.</p>
                <p>The UK is opposed to taking any definite decision at the 10th <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> concerning the convening of a Charter review
                    conference. They hope that the outcome of the discussions at the next session
                    will show the Charter to be sufficiently flexible as is. They would probably
                    accept a decision only to the effect that the 11th <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                        >GA</gloss> should decide the question of whether to convene the
                    conference.</p>
                <p>UK Delegation pointed out, without in any way committing themselves or even
                    advocating it, that, if there are any parts of the Charter on which there is
                    hope of adopting amendments, the procedures in Article 108 of the Charter<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d3fn2">Article 108 of the U.N. Charter reads: “Amendments to
                        the present Charter shall come into force for all Members of the United
                        Nations when they have been adopted by a vote of two thirds of the members
                        of the General Assembly and ratified in accordance with their respective
                        constitutional processes by two thirds of the Members of the United Nations,
                        including all the permanent members of the Security Council.”</note> could
                    be used. Their interpretation of this article is that the <gloss target="#t_GA1"
                        >GA</gloss>, in regular session, could put forward an amendment to the
                    Charter by a ⅔ vote. This would, of course, have to be followed by normal
                    ratification processes. They believe such a procedure is better suited for
                    achieving specific objectives, such as change in procedure for admission of new
                    members or for increasing the size of the Security Council. They regard it as
                    definitely undesirable to open up the whole Charter for discussion at this time
                    and presumably in the foreseeable future.</p>
                <p>The UK missions in all of the member countries are also instructed to try to
                    discourage representatives from raising the question of Charter review in their
                    speeches at San Francisco. They have some doubts about the success of this
                    operation but they intend to make a good try at it.</p>
                <p>As I told <persName corresp="#p_DSPJ1">Dixon</persName>, it is obvious that we
                    are quite far apart on this question. On thinking over the UK idea, it seems to
                    me they miss the whole point of our position which is that it is possible on
                    certain issues to build up so much pressure in world opinion that the Soviets
                    are less likely to veto a particular amendment. Under the UK suggestion for
                    Article 108 procedure, to which they do not commit <pb facs="0030" n="4"
                        xml:id="pg_4"/> themselves, you could not achieve such a build up of
                    pressure. The Article 108 procedure would, in fact, prevent the maximum use of
                    public opinion forces. It would leave the Soviet attitude to be determined
                    solely on the basis of the more regular forces at play during an assembly
                    session.</p>
                <p>I intend at next opportunity to ask British point blank whether they would stand
                    with us on revision of membership requirements under Article 108 procedure as
                    they suggested. When they reject this proposal in addition to turning us down on
                    Charter review, they should be feeling at least slightly penitent and they may
                    just be willing to go along on non-member participation.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d3fn3">Telegram 721 to New York, June 6, reads as follows: “Your
                        850. Similar representations made Department by British Embassy Friday.
                        Embassy officer told no change US position favoring decision hold
                        conference. Memorandum conversation being pouched. Mission will shortly
                        receive request initiate conversations this matter other friendly <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> delegations in order to effect an exchange of
                        views. Response UK representations should await assessment situation basis
                        outcome these conversations and similar talks to be undertaken our Missions
                        abroad.” (Department of State, Central Files, 310.1/6–255)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Lodge</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
