<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-11-25T19:34:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-11-25T19:34:00-05:00" n="353" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d353">
                    <head>353. Circular Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of
                            State</gloss> to <gloss type="to">Certain Diplomatic
                            Missions</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d353fn1">Source:
                            Department of State, Central Files, 701.022/11–2557. Official Use Only;
                            Priority. Drafted and initialed for the Secretary by H. Alberta
                            Colclaser, Assistant Chief of the Aviation Division, Office of Transport
                            and Communications, Bureau of Economic Affairs. Sent to 21
                        posts.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-11-25T19:34:00-05:00">November 25, 1957—7:34
                                    p.m.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                    <p>475. President Council International Civil Aviation Organization
                            (Binaghi<note n="2" xml:id="d353fn2"><persName>Walter
                            Binaghi</persName>, Argentina.</note>) letter October 22 to US
                        representative Council (<persName>David</persName><note n="3" xml:id="d353fn3">Presumably Paul T. David, American economist. The
                            letter is not printed.</note>) inquired whether in view development
                        satellite capable traversing outer space states consider time ripe for
                        international action re question of sovereignty outer space; if so whether
                        they consider <pb facs="0796" n="770" xml:id="pg_770"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> or some other existing organization or
                        special conference should handle problem; if <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> how it should be undertaken. A copy of Binaghi letter and
                        US reply pouched with DS–4.<note n="4" xml:id="d353fn4">Not further
                            identified.</note></p>
                    <p><persName>David</persName> directed reply that considerably more experience
                        and technical development needed prior action on problem. To evolve at this
                        time theories re international principles applicable outer space or rules
                        and regulations this matter might create undesirable and unnecessary
                        obstacles and could do little further this work. Reply also noted that
                        predominance interests other than civil aviation makes it appear unlikely US
                        Government would desire make <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss>
                        responsible consideration this problem.</p>
                    <p>Embassies requested promptly discuss this problem appropriate officials
                        government addressee posts pointing out inability predict this early date
                        what may be desirable methods dealing this problem. Unknown whether similar
                        letters sent other Council representatives. However in view importance this
                        matter every appropriate effort should be made to obtain concurrence US view
                        expressed above and instruction by governments to Council representatives in
                        accord with it. November 18 Council session Japan, Belgium and Mexico
                        requested <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> study outer space at early
                        date. Long-range <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> work program lists
                        outer space study as project “which may possibly be undertaken in 1959”. We
                        believe Council should shelve any such projects, and hope other members will
                        join with us in opposing <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> study space
                        problems when question comes up again in Council.</p>
                    <p>Report soonest views governments approached and reaction US view. Since
                        Council increasingly pushing toward study approach governments soonest.</p>
                    <p>Background includes anxiety <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> Secretariat
                        assume action responsibility this field and note in report Legal Commission
                        Tenth Assembly <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> approved by Assembly
                        that when work re law outer space timely <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> appropriate forum. Nevertheless view <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> responsibilities international civil
                        aviation and nature development outer space activities US Government wishes
                        avoid action this organization. Canadian representative likewise received
                        letter from Council President and replied to effect matter should first be
                        examined by United Nations and that even preliminary explorations <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> states would be of no avail until more
                        important aspects covered by <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. However
                        reply continued by suggesting report and analysis <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> Observer at <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> be
                        circulated asking states comments. Further stated that problems did fall
                        within <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> functions and that there might
                        be some benefit from having matter on future <pb facs="0797" n="771" xml:id="pg_771"/> general work program Legal Committee. We hope Canada
                        and any others holding latter views can be persuaded to revise them.<note n="5" xml:id="d353fn5">In circular telegram 495, December 2, the
                            Department informed 20 diplomatic missions that “Letters comparable
                            Binaghi letter Oct. 22 to <persName>David</persName> received by
                            representatives US, UK, Canada and France only. Nov. 25 <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> President circulated memo all Council
                            representatives raising question whether now appropriate initiate
                            studies outer space and suggesting informal Council discussion this
                            matter Fri. Dec. 6.<gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>. hopes
                            instructions Council representatives received by that date.” (Department
                            of State, Central Files, 701.022/12–257) No formal action was taken by
                            the <gloss target="#t_ICAO1">ICAO</gloss> on this issue during the
                            remainder of 1957. For additional information, see <hi rend="italic">Yearbook of the United Nations</hi>, 1957 (New York, United Nations
                            Office of Public Information, 1958), pp. 471-476.</note></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DAW1"><hi rend="strong">Dulles</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>