<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Hale to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1868p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d138</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">138</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1868-02-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1868-02-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1868-02-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1868-02-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="138"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d138">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Hale</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 115.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Agency and Consulate-General of the United States
                                of America,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Alexandria, Egypt,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-02-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 29, 1868.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your instruction No. 49, under date of January 13, relating to the proposed
                    changes in <pb facs="0209" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> judicial arrangements here,
                    which were the subject of my dispatch No. 111. Your instruction has received my
                    careful attention. It is the purpose of the present dispatch to give you
                    information of the progress of the negotiations relating to the subject.</p>
                <p>I have prepared translations, hereto annexed; first, (marked A,) of the original
                    proposition of Nubar Pacha, and secondly, (marked B,) of his remarks in
                    explanation and qualification of the original proposition, these papers having
                    been communicated to me by order of his Highness the Viceroy, just before your
                    instruction was received. An extract (marked C) of a pamphlet written in support
                    of the proposed changes by a lawyer in the employ of the Egyptian government, is
                    also appended. These papers serve to show what it is that has been proposed, and
                    how the proposition was supported by those appointed to defend it.</p>
                <p>As you have observed by Lord Stanley’s communication, certainly an able and
                    statesmanlike paper, the proposition was, on the whole, rather favorably
                    received by the British government. By the government of France, the proposition
                    was referred to a commission consisting of French statesmen, including Mr.
                    Outrey, the French agent and consul-general for Egypt, then and still remaining
                    in Paris. Nubar Pacha, also in Paris, was invited to attend their deliberations
                    in behalf of the Egyptian government. The commission made a report to the French
                    minister of foreign affairs, which is regarded as unfavorable to the scheme.</p>
                <p>The governments of Prussia, Italy, and Russia so far accepted the scheme as to
                    express their willingness to appoint representatives to consider it at a
                    conference which, it was supposed, would be held in Egypt, and it was understood
                    that Austria would accord a like measure of assistance.</p>
                <p>To these governments, or most of them, as explained in my No. 111, the scheme has
                    been communicated by agents in Europe.</p>
                <p>His Highness the Viceroy, in informing me in January that he had directed the
                    papers already mentioned to be communicated to me, expressed the hope that the
                    United States would be represented in such a conference should it be held. At a
                    later date, as I understand, the same invitation was extended to my colleagues
                    here, or at any rate to some of them, representing governments to whom the plan
                    had not already been communicated. But no other steps have been taken, so far as
                    I can learn, for convening the conference, nor has any time been appointed for
                    assembling it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Rangabé has told you of the dislike with which the scheme was received by the
                    Greek community here, and it is proper that I should state that the same feeling
                    of dislike was general among Europeans. The English newspapers were invited by
                    correspondents resident in Egypt to oppose the plan, and to criticise what was
                    supposed to be Lord Stanley’s support of it; but this feeling of opposition,
                    although almost universal, would no doubt be considerably mitigated if the
                    scheme were better understood.</p>
                <p>It is not now proposed to persevere in the proposition for any change in the
                    hearing of criminal cases. As regards civil cases, it is certainly true that
                    there have been complaints, not wholly without reason, of the existing state of
                    things, some of the inconveniences of which are indicated in the papers annexed.
                    Now, while an Englishman may very well view with distrust the justice of any
                    other tribunal than that of his own consulate, it is well to remember that it is
                    only in cases in which he is defendant of which his own consulate can take
                    jurisdiction. For cases in which he may be plaintiff, having a claim against a
                    native, or the subject <pb facs="0210" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> of some other
                    power, as matters stand he can have no better justice than may be meted out by
                    tribunals which have no special claim to his confidence.</p>
                <p>The problem to be considered by a merchant of any nation, therefore, is this:
                    supposing a good and efficient tribunal could be set up, in which all cases
                    might be brought without regard to the nationality of the parties, would it not
                    on the whole be a convenience? Every merchant would gain the right to bring his
                    claims against others before such a court simply at the expense of being himself
                    subject to its jurisdiction. The fact that the English court here, for instance,
                    is rigorously just, is a circumstance inuring less to the benefit of Englishmen
                    than of subjects of other nations, so far as cases of mixed nationality are
                    concerned. As regards cases between parties both of whom are subjects of the
                    same power, no change in the existing arrangements is now proposed.</p>
                <p>But I must not conceal from you that the difficulty most reasonably apprehended
                    is not so much want of justice in the decisions of any new tribunal as want of
                    confidence in a just and impartial execution of its decisions, and the
                    “guarantees” proposed in the accompanying papers go but little way to abate an
                    apprehension of this sort. The existing “tribunal of commerce,” for hearing
                    cases of Franks against natives, is composed of a native president, with two
                    native assessors and two Frank assessors; the latter serve in turn by months,
                    from a list chosen by the “notables” of the several Frank communities, the list
                    of “notables” serving as electors being prepared by the several consul-generals.
                    The operation of the tribunal is at best unsatisfactory, but a great and
                    substantial grievance is found in the fact than even when the tribunal may have
                    given judgment in favor of the plaintiff, there is no sure means for obtaining
                    execution of the judgments against the native defendants; the case, if at all
                    difficult or important, generally becomes a question to be urged by the
                    consul-general against the Egyptian government, the decision of the tribunal
                    adding but little substantial strength to the case.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, I doubt whether the large European communities would willingly
                    accept at present a measure which should arm any tribunal of the Egyptian
                    government, however composed, with power to touch the persons or property of
                    Europeans otherwise than through their respective consulates.</p>
                <p>The difficulty of the position would appear, therefore, to be insoluble, unless
                    it is met in some such manner as the following, which I beg to submit for your
                    judgment, as the basis of counsel which we might offer to the Egyptian
                    government, should you deem it convenient: Let the Egyptian government, should
                    it wish to do so, proceed at once, without further consultation with other
                    governments, to create a tribunal of five judges, of whom two or three should be
                    able and learned Frank gentlemen of unspotted integrity, assured of permanent
                    salaries for at least a certain term of years. Let this tribunal have certain
                    jurisdiction only of cases brought by Franks against the government or against
                    native subjects. Let the Egyptian government request the consulates to give the
                    same assistance to this tribunal, in requiring the attendance of witnesses and
                    other incidental proceedings, as is now accorded in comity by one consulate to
                    another. Let this tribunal hear and determine cases of the kind that has been
                    described, and whenever its decisions may be in favor of the plaintiff, let them
                    be promptly and fully carried into execution by the Egyptian government. If this
                    is fairly done, the tribunal would at once become among Franks the most popular
                    institution in Egypt. Then let it be a part of the plan that the same tribunal
                    might also hear cases in which subjects of different nationalities were parties,
                        <pb facs="0211" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/> whenever both parties agreed in
                    advance to accept its jurisdiction; and let the Egyptian government request the
                    Christian powers to instruct their consuls to give prompt and full execution to
                    the decisions of the tribunal against any of their respective subjects resident
                    in Egypt, in such cases—that is, only cases in which the parties had accepted
                    the jurisdiction before the case was heard.</p>
                <p>I entertain a very confident opinion that if such a tribunal proved itself to be
                    really honest and impartial—a genuine seat of justice—it would be eagerly
                    accepted by suitors of different nationalities in a very great number of cases,
                    in preference to the complicated jurisdiction of the consulates; nor would any
                    very long time be required for it to earn a good reputation were such reputation
                    deserved. In process of time it might, perhaps, be made the necessary resort of
                    suitors in mixed cases; but it would appear to me unwise for the Egyptian
                    government to insist upon this beforehand.</p>
                <p>For obvious reasons, the Egyptian government might except from the jurisdiction
                    of the tribunal cases against the government arising from transactions anterior
                    in date to the time of its institution, and might make other proper limitations,
                    such as those which restrict the jurisdiction of the United States Court of
                    Claims. Perhaps, even in the beginning, the jurisdiction might be confined to
                    cases against native subjects, excluding at first cases against the Egyptian
                    government; but this would be far less satisfactory.</p>
                <p>Not to protract this dispatch to too great a length, some points of detail which
                    would require attention are not touched upon. As regards the question of a code,
                    this need make little trouble; it would be open to the suitors of all nations
                    coming before the tribunal to plead the laws and usages of their own countries
                    as affecting the case in hand, and the court would allow so much weight to these
                    as seemed just in each case. In process of time the series of decisions made by
                    the tribunal would of themselves make a sort of code, or, at all events, furnish
                    a basis for one, better than any attempt to evolve such a work as a
                    preliminary.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very, respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES HALE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>A.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Note to his Highness the Viceroy of Egypt, on the proposed
                            changes in the judicial relations between foreigners and natives.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The jurisdiction which governs the Europeans in Egypt and determines their
                        relations with the government and with the inhabitants of the country, has
                        no longer for basis the “capitulation.” Of these capitulations there exists
                        now only the name; they have been replaced by a legislation of custom which
                        is arbitrary, the result of the character of each chief of agency,
                        (principal consular officers,) a legislation based upon precedents more or
                        less bad, which the force of circumstances presumes on one side, and the
                        desire to give facilities for the establishment of foreigners in the country
                        on the other, have introduced into Egypt, and which, in point of fact,
                        leaves the government without strength and the population without regular
                        justice in their relations with Europeans. This state of things profits
                        nobody—as little the general interests of foreign powers as the honest
                        population of the country, whether native or alien; it is employed to the
                        injury of the country, the injury of the government, and to the advantage
                        only of those who make it their business to turn it to their selfish
                        account.</p>
                    <p>The need of a reform is keenly felt; the European colony increasing, the
                        foreign <pb facs="0212" n="152" xml:id="pg_152"/> agencies (consulates)
                        themselves understand the necessity of this; they even claim it. The
                        government and the consulates agree as to the principle of this necessity.
                        Their disagreement begins when the means of putting the principle into
                        practice is reached. It is not wished to have any hold of the capitulations.
                        The abuses which have been introduced are brought forward as if they were
                        laws or principles incapable of aboliion. In one word, the end, which is
                        justice, is demanded; but as the means are refused, it results from this
                        that Egypt presents to view a state where the native, whether plaintiff or
                        defendant, unable to find justice, is in fact plundered, and is even happy
                        if he gives up no more than his house to his tenant.</p>
                    <p>The government finds itself assailed by claims which the consuls themselves
                        often cannot refrain from characterizing as scandalous. The population puts
                        itself on its guard against the European. Is the government obliged, while
                        it sees the progress of this same European, in the fear of being
                        compromised, to hold it at a distance? Examples are not wanting; it would be
                        tedious to enumerate them. It is enough to know that the government, in the
                        space of four years, has paid 72,000,000 of indemnities. [This is understood
                        to mean 72,000,000 francs, about $14,400,000, and probably includes the
                        indemnity of the Suez Canal Company under the award of the Emperor
                        Napoleon.] But it must be added that, paid under consular pressure, directly
                        or indirectly exereised, these indemnities are characterized and represented
                        by those very persons who have exercised the pressure as acts of generosity,
                        without example, on the part of his Highness. If only this were the end of
                        the evil! But the government, which perceives that progress can only come to
                        it from Europe; which aspires to the introduction of this civilizing
                        element, and which wishes to confide to it the great works on which are
                        based agriculture and commerce; which wishes to attract capital, in giving
                        it a remunerative employment—the government is reduced to impotence, and
                        finds itself obliged to abandon the country to itself. Of all the works
                        intrusted to Europeans, the dry dock at Suez alone is finished; all the
                        others are either unfinished or not even begun, and, such as they are, have
                        given and give ground for indemnities.</p>
                    <p>The manner in which justice is exercised tends to demoralize the country. All
                        the efforts of his Highness are broken against the invasion of their
                        demoralization. The Arab, forced to see Europe in the light of the European
                        who takes selfish advantage of him, opposes himself to the progress of the
                        west, and accuses the Viceroy and his government of weakness or mistake.</p>
                    <p>For more than forty years the Europeans have enjoyed the right of holding
                        real estate in Egypt; he possesses estates said to be under the jurisdiction
                        and legislation of the country. The consuls, in theory, agree with regard to
                        this principle; but in practice, under the pretext of the capitulations
                        which shield, they say, the European, the European owner of houses, or
                        exercising a trade, pays no taxes; and if owner of a farm, he pays no
                        titles; the consul then intervenes, and the consul’s intervention ends
                        almost always in a non-payment.</p>
                    <p>This state of things, contrary to the spirit, contrary even to the letter of
                        the capitulations, not only prevents the country from developing its
                        resources, from furnishing to the industry and wealth of Europe all which it
                        is fitted to give them, but puts an obstacle in the way of its organization,
                        and ruins it morally as well as materially.</p>
                    <p>Your Highness has thought that the only remedy to bring to this state of
                        things is the organization of a good system of justice, presenting to Europe
                        all the guarantees which she has the right to ask.</p>
                    <p>Your Highness has thought that the foreign element ought to enter into the
                        organization of our tribunals; in fact, this element, not numerous at Cairo,
                        equals at Alexandria the native element; a number of Europeans are
                        established in the provinces; all are merchants or workmen; their relations
                        with the population are consequently of every day, of every hour, so to
                        speak. This element ought then to be regarded in the organization of our
                        tribunals, and even in principle; guarantees which are superfluous ought to
                        be given, so as to inspire it with confidence among men and with the
                        government.</p>
                    <p>The principle is the complete separation of justice from the administration.
                        Justice ought to emanate from the government, not to depend upon the
                        government; it ought no more to depend upon the government than upon the
                        consulates. To be able to attain the object which your Highness proposes,
                        the foreign powers should be persuaded of this fact: “justice emanates from,
                        does not depend upon, the government.” The way to inspire this conviction is
                        to have a body of magistracy. In fact, to make a good magistrate, the
                        natural equity inherent in an honest native is not enough; knowledge of the
                        law is indispensable; a study, a complete education. Our magistrates now in
                        service have a perfect acquaintance with the civil and religious law which
                        was enough when they had only to administer equal justice to a population
                        homogeneous in its customs and its wants. But now necessities require new
                        laws, and the Europeans, in establishing themselves in the country, have
                        brought with them new usages, new relations. A mixed system has begun to
                        introduce itself in our laws and in our codes. New men accordingly are
                        required to apply this new system. It is required that Egypt should do for
                        the administration of justice what Egypt has already done so effectively for
                        her army, her railways, her engineers of roads and bridges, her services of
                        health and <pb facs="0213" n="153" xml:id="pg_153"/> hygiene. The competent
                        element, the foreign element, has been introduced, and this element has
                        served to mold the native element. That winch has been done in the material
                        order must be done in the moral order—that is, in the organization of
                        justice. The necessity of this mixed system has made itself so keenly felt
                        that since many years the embassies have demanded its introduction at
                        Constantinople. Constantinople has established a mixed tribunal of commerce,
                        where all the commercial processes between natives and Europeans, whether
                        plaintiff or defendants, are alike judged.</p>
                    <p>It is proposed to extend this system and to apply it to civil and criminal
                        cases. The tribunal of commerce sitting at Alexandria and Cairo is not,
                        properly speaking, a tribunal; it differs from that of Constantinople. It is
                        rather a jury; but for commercial questions the basis of the institution,
                        such as it is, is good, and deserves to be retained; it is only requisite to
                        improve it. This jury or tribunal, instituted originally to take cognizance
                        of commercial lawsuits arising between foreigners and natives, whether
                        plaintiffs or defendants, is in point of fact abandoned. The consuls claim
                        cognizance of cases in which persons of their nationality appear as
                        defendants, and the tribunal often finds itself refused by them, even when
                        the defendant is a native. They justify themselves in this by their want of
                        confidence in the members composing the tribunal. I do not care to discuss
                        the accusation against this tribunal, which I do not believe well founded.
                        The phrase which your Highness has pronounced is enough for my purpose: “Let
                        us give guarantees even that are superfluous.”</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to propose to your Highness the preservation of the two
                        mixed tribunals of commerce established at Cairo and Alexandria; but instead
                        of three members chosen by the consuls from the merchants of the European
                        colony, and three native members, called by the government to sit in turn, I
                        would propose to your Highness to compose them of four members only, two of
                        whom the consuls would choose from the merchants presenting the best
                        guarantees and the best known, and two others whom the government would
                        choose from the natives whose relations are most intimate with the
                        Europeans. The same as is now done, these members would sit in turn. I would
                        propose to your Highness to give the presidency to an Egyptian, but to
                        concede the vice-presidency to a magistrate selected in Europe; and to have
                        a “guarantee on the subject of his character,” it would do well to address
                        the ministry of justice, [that is of the county from which he is selected.]
                        This magistrate would be permanent.</p>
                    <p>Above these tribunals it would be necessary to have a tribunal of appeal,
                        sitting at Alexandria. This would be composed of three Egyptian members,
                        whom your Highness might select from our young men who have studied law in
                        Europe, and three other members, competent magistrates, whom your Highness
                        would summon from Europe, addressing for their choice their governments.</p>
                    <p>This tribunal would perform its functions under the presidency of an
                        Egyptian. Together with the two tribunals of commerce, there would be two
                        tribunals for civil cases. They might be composed of two competent members,
                        engaged abroad, and two Egyptian members, always under the presidency of an
                        Egyptian subject.</p>
                    <p>The tribunal of appeal sitting at Alexandria would have also among its powers
                        the revision of judgments given by the civil tribunals.</p>
                    <p>As to disputes arising from questions of land and real estate, the Europeans
                        have always been subject to our tribunals. These tribunals work well; the
                        members who compose them understand the business from the bottom; the
                        foreign element would not be more competent in the matter. I propose to your
                        Highness to leave them as they are.</p>
                    <p>The question of the immovability of the magistrates has attracted the
                        attention of your Highness. Your Highness, after mature consideration, has
                        thought, and with reason, that absolute immovability might present great
                        inconvenience for a state of things that is new; that an engagement of five
                        years for the magistrates is enough, and will give to parties in suit every
                        guarantee, and will also allow time both for your government and for foreign
                        powers to judge of the merit of the new institution.</p>
                    <p>As to criminal questions, they are not so simple as the civil and commercial.
                        Nevertheless, they can be resolved, if reference is had both to the spirit
                        and the letter of the capitulations, and especially to the state of things
                        under Mehemet-Ali.</p>
                    <p>In fact, how were affairs carried on in the time of the great Viceroy? When a
                        crime or offense was committed by a foreigner, the governor of the citadel
                        took jurisdiction of it, made the examination, rendered the judgment, and
                        sent the judgment and the delinquent to his consul for the execution of the
                        sentence. As the number of Europeans was at that time very limited, and
                        crimes and offenses rare, the care of the consuls over persons of their
                        nationality was easier and more effectual. I do not remember any case of
                        impunity presenting itself, or indeed if there were some discreditable
                        tolerance, that any gave rise to claims or produced serious inconveniences.
                        Such affairs passed off, so to speak, <hi rend="italic">en famille,</hi> it
                        being everybody’s interest to maintain good order, and every one having both
                        the will and the power to do so.</p>
                    <p>I must, however, call the attention of your Highness to the fact that this
                        matter of proceeding is not quite in conformity to the capitulation, which
                        by no means removes foreigners from the jurisdiction of the country, and
                        limit themselves to granting them, <pb facs="0214" n="154" xml:id="pg_154"/>
                        in criminal cases, the privilege of being tried, assisted by their dragomen
                        or interpreters, by the supreme tribunal; the penalty always to be
                        enforced.</p>
                    <p>Since Mehemet-Ali, as the number of Europeans increases, and consequently the
                        number of offenses in proportion, the government, in view of the
                        non-application by the consuls of the sentences which it decreed, hoped to
                        gain its object, the enforcement of penalties, by including in the
                        examination and in the judgment either the consul or the interpreter. But
                        this mode of proceeding, which at the beginning produced satisfactory
                        results, things still going on, as I have said, <hi rend="italic">en
                            famille,</hi> in its turn degenerated. About 1848, the consuls, under
                        the pressure of persons of their nationality, having become arbiters in the
                        place of the law, found themselves powerless, made of their weakness a
                        principle, and were led, little by little, by pressure of circumstances, to
                        assume making examinations for themselves outside the government, or at any
                        rate to connect with themselves a functionary of the native police, under
                        pretext that as the penalty must be applied and executed in their own
                        country, the examination had no value except as it was conformable to their
                        own laws. Such is actually the state of things, not only in regard to
                        crimes, but for misdemeanors and simple infractions of law. Thus justice is
                        completely given over, not to institutions, but to the arbitration of
                        individuals. The position of the government is no longer tolerable, when we
                        consider that its police is powerless to repress the most trivial
                        infractions, unable even to cause the execution of highway regulations, or
                        those referring to stations for public carriages; for if one consul is
                        inclined to recall to order on the demand of the police some coachman who
                        refuses to take his place, another treats the affair with indifference,
                        sometimes for the reason alone that his colleague takes the other side.</p>
                    <p>Thus, Highness, the object now pursued by your government is not the
                        destruction of the capitulations, but, on the contrary, to restore to them
                        both letter and spirit, by demanding of the governments the abandonment of
                        abuses and of personal arbitration. That, in fact, is the spirit of the
                        capitulations; the protection of foreigners, but not impunity for them; that
                        is their letter; the judgment of foreigners by the tribunals of the country,
                        with the guarantee of the supreme tribunal, and the assistance of their
                        dragomen.</p>
                    <p>The same objection is made to your Highness regarding the civil tribunals,
                        and objection founded on the absence of laws and of magistrates who present
                        sufficient guarantees. But your Highness, in your desire to regulate your
                        relations with the powers, laying aside what you might demand as a natural
                        right, and resulting from the capitulations themselves—the right, not to be
                        prescribed, of all governments to apply the police and security laws to all
                        who live within your jurisdiction, (territory,) has been willing to apply to
                        the criminal code the idea which you had conceived for the civil, that is,
                        to institute mixed correctional tribunals.</p>
                    <p>The capitulations protect inviolably the domicil and the person of
                        foreigners. There is no thought of disturbing this principle; your Highness,
                        in fact, wishes to strengthen it; to surround Europeans accused of crime
                        with more guarantees than are granted by the capitulations; instead of a
                        dragoman, who is but a silent witness, your Highness grants them judges
                        chosen in Europe, and a jury half of Europeans and half native.</p>
                    <p>If more guarantees are required, your Highness will give them. Your object is
                        the protection of honest citizens, more and more endangered by the impunity
                        enjoyed by the guilty.</p>
                    <p>The case of less serious infractions, such as the French law calls <hi
                            rend="italic">délits</hi> or <hi rend="italic">contraventions,</hi> will
                        be submitted to the same mixed tribunals. In all cases appeal will be made
                        to the superior tribunal established at Alexandria; this power of appeal
                        presents all the guarantees desired. All penalties should be applied in
                        Egypt, except in the case of imprisonment, which should be enforced in the
                        respective consulates if this should be exacted by the consul. With the
                        organization of the tribunals there would be occasion to give attention to
                        the legislation which they should follow and apply. The commercial
                        legislation now followed in Egypt is that of Constantinople, accepted by the
                        foreign powers, “The French Code of Commerce.” For civil affairs your
                        Highness has the intention to summon a commission of foreign jurisconsults,
                        who, assembled with our lawyers, would reconcile the provisions of the Code
                        Napoleon with those of our own legislation. This reconciliation is already
                        half made; the work would neither be long nor difficult. This commission
                        would also be charged to put our penal laws in harmony with those of the
                        French penal code.</p>
                    <p>To sum up, that which your Highness asks, whether as regards civil or
                        criminal affairs, is the return to the capitulations, and not only a return
                        pure and simple, but on the contrary a return which would allow to
                        foreigners guarantees far superior to those which the capitulations give
                        them. In fact, according to the capitulations, it is a native tribunal which
                        gives judgment in presence of the dragoman, a mere witness without voice in
                        the deliberations; according to the reform proposed, your Highness, instead
                        of this mute witness, gives to foreigners the guarantee of a tribunal in the
                        composition of which enters a European element, and a code revised in
                        conformity with European penal and civil laws.</p>
                    <p>The organization proposed by your Highness, calculated upon the judicial
                        organization of Algeria, offers, it seems to me, all the desirable
                        guarantees.</p>
                    <pb facs="0215" n="155" xml:id="pg_155"/>
                    <p>It would appear impossible to your Highness that the foreign powers should
                        refuse to admit them. Hitherto, on the contrary, the foreign powers have
                        availed themselves of every opportunity to come to the support of the
                        material and moral development in Egypt. To-day, placed in presence of the
                        real state of the country in refusing the establishment of the most precious
                        guarantees, they would put themselves in the position of denying not only
                        the progress, but even the very existence, of Egypt.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>NUBAR.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>B.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Some explanations of the guarantees which will be
                            presented by the judicial organization proposed for Egypt.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The majority in the tribunals which the government proposes to organize will
                        rest with the European magistrates. These magistrates will be appointed by
                        the Egyptian government, and chosen by it among the magistrates in Europe.
                        The government will surround itself for this choice with all possible
                        precautions. The making choice from magistrates already in office is itself
                        a guarantee, because the French government, for example, is always free to
                        accord or refuse its permission to the magistrates who would have been
                        chosen. Irremovability will be granted to the magistrates either in the
                        beginning or after a certain time, three or four years for instance. Add to
                        these guarantees, already so effective in themselves, the publicity of
                        proceedings, the complete liberty of defense, the institution of the court
                        of appeal, and the Egyptian tribunals will present the same guarantees as
                        the tribunals in Europe. But if there is added also the right, which would
                        be granted to the party in suit, or to his consul, to refuse one of the
                        judges of the tribunal, without giving reasons for his refusal, there is a
                        guarantee which I will call substantial. Moreover, when the difference of
                        position is considered, the advantage on the side of Egypt is obvious, for
                        in France or England a magistrate has only to encounter the public opinion
                        of a homogeneous public, while in Egypt two camps are watching him, the
                        Moslem and the Christian, and in this latter sixteen different nationalities
                        restless and eager. Under these conditions, it is difficult, if not
                        impossible, that a magistrate should be false to the law and give judgment
                        against his conscienee. The clerks and officers of the court would be chosen
                        in Europe from the persons who have exercised or still exercise the
                        functions of ministerial officers.</p>
                    <p>Civil cases between natives will be submitted to these tribunals, (questions
                        of state, as marriage, divorce, &amp;c., between natives will necessarily
                        remain for resort to the existing tribunals, but the tribunals may be
                        attached to the general organization in such manner as not to make a
                        separate body.) Civil questions between natives and foreigners, whether
                        plaintiffs or defendants, will be submitted to these tribunals. Commercial
                        questions between natives, or between natives and foreigners, will be
                        submitted to these tribunals, which, in these cases, will summon as
                        assessors merchants selected from the well-known Europeans and Arabs of the
                        country.</p>
                    <p>The inconveniences which arise from fifteen or sixteen foreign jurisdictions
                        for the persons of the nationality at the different consulates in the
                        questions of litigation which arise every day among them are always
                        increasing; it would be desirable, therefore, in their own interest, that
                        the processes between Europeans of different nationalities should be
                        submitted to these tribunals, or at least that this should be permitted with
                        the consent of both parties. But the power of these tribunals will not cover
                        lawsuits between Europeans of the same nationality. The tribunal will have
                        power over all questions which concern the administration of the domains of
                        the Viceroy (present and past) and of the princes. It will take cognizance
                        of all the demands made by the government against private persons, natives
                        or Europeans, and of all such as may be brought against the government by
                        such private persons for the execution of a contract. Nevertheless, it is
                        understood that the tribunal cannot ordain any measure which may be of the
                        nature to prevent or suspend the execution of an act of administration; it
                        will take cognizance simply of claims for indemnity brought against the
                        government on account of acts of administration alleged to be contrary to an
                        engagement or concession previously granted. Mere violations of police
                        regulations might be judged by the civil tribunal, or better by a European
                        magistrate delegated by the tribunal and sitting at the police office.
                        Punishment in correctional matters will be pronounced by the tribunal
                        composed of two European magistrates and one native, and if thought
                        necessary, upon the verdict of a jury. Punishment in criminal matters will
                        be pronounced by a court composed of three magistrates, of which three will
                        be Europeans and one native, on the verdict of a jury. The composition of
                        the jury lists, the number of jurors, their manner of voting, whether by
                        majority or unanimity, are among the questions which should be settled by
                        the commission of jurisconsulst which <pb facs="0216" n="156"
                            xml:id="pg_156"/> will come to Egypt to determine the proceedure and
                        adopt the European law to the wants of the country.</p>
                    <p>This same commission might determine the conditions under which the officers
                        of police will have the right to make an arrest, or to enter houses; it will
                        fix the terms within which preliminary investigations should be concluded;
                        but it is important that it should be understood after this that these
                        conditions, once fulfilled, the action of the police cannot be interfered
                        with by the consuls, for the Viceroy having the responsibility of
                        maintaining order in Egypt, it is necessary to establish as a principle that
                        he ought to have the means to fulfill this responsibility. The police must
                        possess, as regards foreigners, the same powers as regards natives; and in
                        order that thieves and assassins may no longer be seen after having fired a
                        pistol, or being taken breaking open a safe, walking about at Alexandria,
                        thanks to the intervention of the consuls, the police must have the right to
                        put in execution the regulations of the highway, and other police
                        regulations, without having recourse to the consulates.</p>
                    <p>The establishment of the tribunals is only half of the organization; nothing
                        will be accomplished if judgments are obtained which are not put in
                        execution.</p>
                    <p>If the tribunals present the desired guarantees, and if accordingly they are
                        accepted, there will be no objection, I think, that, as in France, the
                        officers of these tribunals should be charged with the execution of the
                        sentence, with power to require the officers of police if necessary.</p>
                    <p>This mode of proceeding is all the more necessary now the consuls have for a
                        principle (not at all admitted by the government) to make the government
                        responsible for the execution of sentences given against natives. The
                        representative of the tribunal proceeding to the execution of its judgment,
                        with the assistance of the public force in case of need, this pretended
                        solidarity will disappear, and with it many really petty questions which are
                        raised to the rank of diplomatic questions. It is very evident that if, for
                        example, the government should refuse the aid of the public force for the
                        execution of a judgment, the diplomatic intervention of the consuls would
                        immediately have a reason for existing.</p>
                    <p>Thus, neither the government nor the consulates will be able to interfere
                        with the execution of the sentence, either to prevent or suspend it.</p>
                    <p>If the consulates were charged with the execution, if they had even only the
                        power to interfere, the firmness of some might take example from the
                        weakness or want of power of others, and we should fall back with
                        arbitrariness and the present confusion. If, in order to execute a sentence,
                        it is necessary for the officer to enter a private house, it cannot be said
                        that the domicile is violated by the government. It is not the government
                        who forces itself in, it is the law, represented by the officer of the
                        tribunal, and the law penetrates everywhere.</p>
                    <p>Besides questions of organization for civil, commercial, and criminal
                        justice, there is room for regulating different points which are connected
                        with simple administration, for instance, in relation to highways or to
                        taxes. Thus, a European who wants to build in Alexandria, does it without
                        the preliminary authorization of the council on highways or that of
                        fortifications; whenever he finds against him the regulations of these
                        councils, no native workman can labor for him under these conditions, to be
                        sure, but he engages European workmen; his building is raised and finished
                        under the eyes of the authorities, who appeal in vain to his consulate,
                        which answers not at all, or after the building is completed.</p>
                    <p>The capitulations have never pretended to remove from the action of
                        government any European who puts himself in opposition to the local laws. In
                        the present state of disorder, it is necessary in such cases that the
                        government should bring an action against the opposing party before the
                        consul; and the consul, on this very account, interprets and comments upon
                        the regulations made by the government, and has, consequently, power to
                        approve or annul them.</p>
                    <p>The capitulations, and even French jurisprudence, if I am not mistaken, do
                        not authorize the holding of real estate by Europeans in Egypt. This is a
                        great misfortune for Egypt; therefore not only is it tolerated in Egypt, but
                        even recognized and established for more than forty years. Europeans buy,
                        sell, inherit property, like the natives, in their own names, inscribed upon
                        the registers of the Melkiemés.</p>
                    <p>It is just that European proprietors should be submitted to the same expenses
                        as the native, and that the laws in this case, laws well known, fixed, and
                        determined, should be applied as to the native. This is a principle admitted
                        and recognized; no consulate really denies it. But in application this
                        principle is becoming impossible. A European possesses a farm; he does not
                        pay his taxes; can the government proceed with him as with a native, that
                        is, deprive him of a part of his land, which, sold at public auction, would
                        restore to the exchequer the amount due to it? Government cannot do this; it
                        must address itself to a consul, who may or may not give an answer, and who
                        finally, whether he insists upon payment or not, becomes the arbiter and
                        judge of the laws of the government. An examination may be made, if desired,
                        whether anything can be modified in the present regulations so as to protect
                        the rights and interests of all; but it is necessary to leave to the
                        Egyptian authority, alone and without the intervention <pb facs="0217"
                            n="157" xml:id="pg_157"/> of the consulates, administrative action and
                        jurisdiction in such matters, and the government must not abandon this
                        principle.</p>
                    <p>This action and jurisdiction are a public right, and the capitulations never
                        were intended to take them from Egypt.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>NUBAR.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>C.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Extract from a pamphlet by P. Maunoury.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>What shall be said of certain consulates where it is impossible to get
                        justice? The least bad are those which, in the interest of persons of their
                        nationality, hold back the decision and even the execution of their
                        judgments until the foreign plaintiffs are worn out.</p>
                    <p>Thus, upon many complaints laid before the tribunal of Persia, not one
                        judgment has been passed.</p>
                    <p>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Note.</hi>—Were the capitulations intended for
                        unchristianized Asiatics?]</p>
                    <p>The consulate of France was obliged, in the affair of Marquet &amp; Co. <hi
                            rend="italic">vs.</hi> Hauna Giamati, to interfere with the Spanish
                        consulate to compel them to protest a bill of exchange for non-payment.</p>
                    <p>There is a consulate general of Brazil, although not a single Brazilian is
                        established in Egypt. The consul general, an Italian, in order to create for
                        himself a nation, had to put all the members of his family under the
                        protection of his flag. His nephew, Abd-allah-el-Adin, attached to the
                        consulate, became bankrupt. The difficulties thus caused were judged, in
                        spite of the creditors, by the uncle of the bankrupt, all demands being
                        refused.</p>
                    <p>The denials of justice on the part of the consul general of Greece have been
                        so violent, that one day, in full hearing of the French tribunal, at the
                        trial of an affair begun by a Greek against a Frenchman, Mr. Fricon, French
                        consul, president of the tribunal, summoned before him the plaintiff, and
                        said to him word for word as follows: “Your affair is erased from the
                        docket. Go and tell your consul that as soon as he begins to render justice
                        to the French, I will render it to persons of his nationality.”</p>
                    <p>It is useless to say that the local tribunals leave as much to be desired as
                        does consular justice.</p>
                    <p>About a year since the European judges of the mixed tribunal at Cairo sent in
                        their resignation <hi rend="italic">en masse,</hi> on account of the
                        partialities which they had witnessed.</p>
                    <p>Something quite curious has presented itself in connection with these mixed
                        tribunals. They were instituted as tribunals of commerce.</p>
                    <p>Now, as none of their members clearly understood the distinction between
                        civil and commercial affairs, for several years they passed judgment
                        indiscriminately on all questions arising between Europeans and natives.</p>
                    <p>At the beginning of 1867 they bethought themselves to decide that they were
                        incompetent in civil matters—a wise decision. But now comes a difficulty.
                        Possibly a local civil tribunal may exist; but we can affirm that there is
                        not a single person who might be the subject of its jurisdiction, nor even a
                        European lawyer, who, after careful research, knows where this tribunal
                        holds its sittings.</p>
                    <p>So that, for the last ten months, no civil complaint can be brought by a
                        European against a local subject.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
