<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Plumb to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1868p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d320</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">320</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1868-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1868-08-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1868-08-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1868-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="320"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d320">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Plumb</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 178.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">City of Mexico</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-08-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 21, 1868.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Under the instructions contained in your dispatch
                    No. 65, of the 29th of May last, received by duplicate on the 13th instant,
                    relating to the death of Mr. John Braniff, a citizen of the United States, from
                    wounds inflicted by a band of robbers while at work upon the Puebla branch of
                    the Mexico and Vera Cruz railway, in April last, I addressed a note to the
                    department of foreign affairs of this government, on the 14th instant, of which
                    I beg to transmit a copy herewith. I have to-day received a reply, under date of
                    the 18th instant, from Mr. Azpiroz, in charge of the department, of which I beg
                    also to transmit a copy and translation herewith.</p>
                <p>In this reply it is stated that as there are not in the department of <pb
                        facs="0629" n="569" xml:id="pg_569"/> foreign affairs antecedents relative
                    to whether the apprehension of the murderers of Mr. Braniff has been effected,
                    the necessary information has been asked from the governors of the States of
                    Puebla and Tlax-cala, and that when it arrives the government will direct what
                    injustice may be required.</p>
                <p>Mr. Azpiroz takes exception to the observation contained in my note, that cases
                    such as that treated of are unfortunately common in Mexico, and that their
                    frequency is no doubt owing to the comparative impunity of the offenders.</p>
                <p>I have not thought it necessary to make any reply to his remarks under this head,
                    unless I should receive your instructions to that effect.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be. very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>E. L. PLUMB.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Plumb</persName> to <persName type="to">Señor
                            Azpiroz</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Mexico</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-08-14">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 14, 1868.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In a dispatch under date of the 29th of May
                        last, but which only reached me yesterday, I am advised that the Department
                        of State at Washington has been informed by Mr. Black, the vice-consul of
                        the United States in this city, of the death of Mr. John Braniff, a citizen
                        of the United States, from wounds inflicted by a band of robbers at a bridge
                        on the Puebla branch of the Mexico and Vera Cruz railway, in April last.</p>
                    <p>The Secretary of State adds, that although such events may and do happen in
                        every country, they are unfortunately common in Mexico, and their frequency
                        is no doubt owing to the comparative impunity of the offenders.</p>
                    <p>I am instructed to bring this case to the attention of the Mexican
                        government, and to express the expectation of the government of the United
                        States that the government of Mexico will exert all its authority to bring
                        the murderers of Mr. Braniff to justice. I have the honor to be, very
                        respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>E. L. PLUMB.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Manuel Azpiroz</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chief
                                Cleric in charge of the Department of Foreign Affairs of the Mexican
                                Republic.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Señor Azpiroz</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Plumb</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Relations</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Mexico</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-08-18">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 18, 1868.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I received yesterday your note of the 14th of
                        the present month, in which you have been pleased to communicate to me that
                        you have instructions from your government to submit to the consideration of
                        the Mexican government the case of the assassination committed by certain
                        robbers upon the person of the citizen of the United States, Mr. John
                        Braniff, at Santa Cruz, between Apizaco and Puebla, in the month of April
                        last; and to state that the government of the United States expects that of
                        Mexico will use all its authority to have the assassins delivered up to
                        justice.</p>
                    <p>As there are not in this department antecedents relative to whether the
                        apprehension of the murderers of Mr. Braniff has been effected, the
                        necessary information was yesterday asked from the governors of Puebla and
                        Tlaxcala, and when it arrives the government will direct what in justice may
                        be required.</p>
                    <p>To this I should limit myself, if in your said note there was not found the
                        idea that to the impunity which, up to a certain point, criminals have in
                        Mexico, it is due, without doubt, that cases such as that treated of are
                        more frequent in this than in other countries.</p>
                    <p>If with impartiality the circumstances of Mexico are considered—due to the
                        war which for a long time has overthrown public order in this country, and
                        to other causes well known to all, but beyond the volition and against the
                        interests of the people and of the government of Mexico—neither the
                        government nor the people of Mexico can be <pb facs="0630" n="570"
                            xml:id="pg_570"/> blamed because robberies and assassinations are
                        committed here; nor, in comparing these crimes with those that are found to
                        be committed in established countries in identical circumstances with those
                        of Mexico, can the statement be ventured that they are here more
                        frequent.</p>
                    <p>Notorious are the efforts that the government has made and is making to
                        completely re-establish security for the lives, the rights, and the property
                        of all the inhabitants of the republic. These efforts have so far had the
                        best possible results.</p>
                    <p>The malefactors apprehended are submitted to the tribunals, or exemplarily
                        punished in the act of being caught <hi rend="italic">en flagrante</hi>, in
                        conformity with the laws of the country.</p>
                    <p>The constant and efficacious persecution of evil doers, and their treatment
                        according to the laws, is very far from signifying impunity.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>MANUEL AZPIROZ, <hi rend="italic">Chief Clerk.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward Lee Plumb</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chargé
                                d’Affaires of the United States of America in Mexico.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
