<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1868-09-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1868-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="326" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d326">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Plumb</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 184.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">City of Mexico</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-09-10"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 10, 1868.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The efforts of this government to put an
                            end to the insurrections that have occurred in various parts of the
                            republic since the outbreak in Yucatan in December last, appear to have
                            been signally successful.</p>
                        <p>Near the close of last month the forces under General Alatorre effected
                            the complete suppression of the rebellion in the sierra of the State of
                            Puebla, with which General Negrete and the remnant of his followers had
                            united.</p>
                        <p>A short time before, the forces under the orders of General Escobedo put
                            an end to the revolt in the sierra of the State of Queretaro.</p>
                        <p>Aureliano Rivera, who pronounced in the sierra of Ajusco, in this State,
                            has not been heard of since the first few weeks of his movement when
                            forces were sent against him, and appears to have altogether
                            disappeared.</p>
                        <p>Recent risings in the State of Vera Gruz have also quickly been
                            suppressed.</p>
                        <p>The differences in the State of Guerrero appear finally to have been
                            adjusted, and a general election has now been called in that State.</p>
                        <p>The insurrection in the State of Sinaloa, under Martinez, was quickly put
                            down by the federal forces under General Corona; and thus, so tar, in
                            every instance success has attended the arms and the measures of the
                            government, until it may now be stated that at no period since the
                            accession of President Juarez to the chief magistracy, in February,
                            1858, has the whole country been under such entire acquiescence in the
                            rule of the constitutional government, and the measures of reform put in
                            practice by the constitutional party, as it is to-day.</p>
                        <p>The military forces and the civil employés of the federal government are
                            now regularly and promptly paid.</p>
                        <p>This may be one of the important causes of the improved state of affairs;
                            but I think it must also be acknowledged that the people generally
                            throughout the republic are showing a greater unwillingness to look
                            quietly upon, or to permit a resort to unauthorized armed movements as a
                            means of redress for local or federal grievances, and are more <pb facs="0638" n="578" xml:id="pg_578"/> clearly seeing that there are
                            sufficient and surer remedies by peaceful means through the press, the
                            tribune, and the ballot.</p>
                        <p>It is too early yet safely to assert that the round of pronunciamientos
                            may not again be recommenced, or that legislative differences may not
                            occur to mar the present favorable prospects; but it must be admitted
                            that there are hopeful signs that a greater degree of tranquillity will
                            be maintained hereafter.</p>
                        <p>The condition of general insecurity for life and property throughout the
                            country continues to be most undesirable, but the government manifests a
                            determination to now turn its attention to that necessity, as its most
                            important work.</p>
                        <p>President Juarez has expressed to me his personal assurances under this
                            head, and unquestionably feels the most earnest desire to accomplish
                            what is so vitally demanded in this regard.</p>
                        <p>His confidence in the future of his country appears not only to be
                            unabated but strengthened; and he sees perhaps more clearly than many
                            how important an element time is in the difficult task of giving to
                            Mexico, under all the disadvantages the past has left as its legacy, a
                            durable peace, order, and progress.</p>
                        <p>There appears to be also on the part of the government, and of their
                            public men generally, an increasing appreciation of the necessity of
                            giving an impulse to the material interests of the country.</p>
                        <p>Should the coming session of their congress meet the public expectation
                            and the promises of its leading members, and the government use the
                            initiative it can in this regard, a great improvement in the state of
                            affairs here cannot but take place.</p>
                        <p>In this point of view the proximate session is looked upon as of critical
                            importance. Employment, to keep the people from the necessity of crime
                            and revolt, is a vital requirement of their present situation.</p>
                        <p>A useful document, which is at the same time an encouraging sign, has
                            recently appeared in the shape of a manifesto from General Gonzalez
                            Ortega, issued shortly after his recent unconditional release from
                            confinement.</p>
                        <p>In this paper he relinquishes any claim he may have been supposed to have
                            to the executive office or to the presidency of the supreme court, and
                            admits the necessity as well as propriety of accepting the existing
                            order.</p>
                        <p>His constitutional term as Vice-President expired on the 31st of May
                            last, and that office is now filled by Mr. Lerdo de Tejada, but the
                            manifesto of General Ortega is useful as showing the convictions and
                            expressing the advice of one who was the only claimant of the position
                            President Juarez occupies.</p>
                        <p>I beg to inclose a translation of this document herewith.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>E. L. PLUMB.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#center">[From the Diario Oficial, city of
                                        <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-09-01">September 1,
                                    1868</date>.—Translation.]</dateline></opener>
                            <head>Manifesto of General Gonzalez Ortega.</head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">The citizen Jesus Gonzalez Ortega to
                                    the Mexican nation.</hi></p>
                            <p>Useless it appears to me to make here a statement of the occurrences
                                that, relative to my person with the character of President of one
                                of the supreme powers of the Mexican <pb facs="0639" n="579" xml:id="pg_579"/> federation, have taken place before and after
                                the decrees of the 8th of November were issued, and before and
                                during the time of my imprisonment, because the circumstances of all
                                these events appear in official documents and papers that have been
                                published.</p>
                            <p>It remains to me, therefore, only to say a few words to my
                                fellow-citizens as the sincere voice of my heart and of my head, as
                                the intimate expression of my conscience, as the result of the
                                liberty in which I now find myself, and after profound meditations
                                in view of accomplished events, and in the presence of
                                imprescindable measures which are exacted by the interests of the
                                country and the peace of the republic.</p>
                            <p>On the 1st of the present month there was transcribed to me the
                                communication of the general government, dated the 18th of July
                                last, in which it was ordered that I should be placed at liberty, to
                                the end that I might reside at the place that I might myself
                                select.</p>
                            <p>As in the said note the supposed offenses were insisted upon, of
                                flight and abandonment perpetrated by the general and by the
                                president of the supreme court of justice, I had to return the note,
                                asking only in a verbal manner, if, notwithstanding that step that
                                the honor of the nation obliged me to take, I could make use of the
                                liberty that was offered to me, to which I believed myself entitled,
                                as, without motive whatever, I had been deprived of it; and an
                                affirmative answer having been returned to me, I have removed to the
                                capital of the State of Coahuila. I had thought of proceeding, in
                                order to issue this manifesto, to some other capital of the more
                                central States of the republic, but accidental causes have prevented
                                me from realizing my purpose.</p>
                            <p>Placed at liberty, possessed already of my rights, and consequently
                                of the faculty to emit my thoughts and to speak to the nation in
                                compliance with the duty imposed upon me, the first that I have done
                                has been to direct a retrospective view in order to examine the past
                                with relation to the present, and another view to the actual
                                situation in order to examine in the present the events to which the
                                same past now has given an authority.</p>
                            <p>The order of things actually established is an accomplished event
                                which rests in the most grave and vast interests. The legislatures,
                                the tribunals of justice, and the governments of all the States of
                                the republic being installed, the councils of all the municipalities
                                of the same States being elected; the congress of the Union having
                                been in session; the supreme court of justice of the republic
                                exercising its functions, no voice has been raised protesting in the
                                name of the people against the violation of law, against the decrees
                                of the 8th of November, against the imprisonment of the president of
                                the supreme court of justice, and if there have been some isolated
                                voices with reference to this latter event, and they have been heard
                                in congress, they have become silent soon after without result
                                whatever.</p>
                            <p>Nearly all of the eminent men of the liberal party are forming or
                                have formed part of the actual administration. The legislatures of
                                some of the States have graved medals, have emitted votes of thanks
                                and issued titles of well-deserving in favor of the author of the
                                decrees of the 8th of November, and all without distinction have
                                called legitimate government, constitutional government, that of
                                which the head is the author of those same decrees; titles which
                                have also been given in the press and the tribune by many of the
                                democratic notabilities.</p>
                            <p>The author of the said decrees being accused by me before the
                                national representation, the latter has not been willing to occupy
                                itself with this affair and has seen with indifference, the same as
                                all the authorities of the nation, the imprisonment of the president
                                of the supreme court of justice, and by mandate of the law,
                                President ad interim of the republic.</p>
                            <p>The men who, with myself, have raised the voice to defend the
                                immunities of the law, some early, some later, and some at the last
                                hour, have disappeared to form a part of the actual administration,
                                or to recognize it tacitly or expressly.</p>
                            <p>No one do I accuse before the present or before history. I state
                                facts, whose causes, perhaps grave and patriotic, I am still
                                ignorant of, and I state them because those same facts not only
                                authorize it, but reclaim in the name of the country the course that
                                I am going to adopt.</p>
                            <p>I have remained, therefore, alone, absolutely alone, and without
                                other support than that which a tranquil conscience affords when, in
                                its judgment, a painful and difficult duty has been fulfilled.</p>
                            <p>To that same conscience I have addressed these inquiries, not once
                                but many times. In the midst of this general abandonment common to
                                all men and to all peoples, in view of so many interests created by
                                a power tolerated by the people, under constitutional and democratic
                                forms or appearances, and which interests cannot be destroyed except
                                among rivers of blood, in the presence of grave diplomatic
                                complications between Mexico and powerful nations, is it desirable,
                                is it just, is it patriotic to put forward my individuality, by the
                                official character which I have, as a constant menace to the public
                                peace and tranquillity?</p>
                            <p>Is it desirable, is it just, is it patriotic to retain titles in the
                                name of the people when that same people have not desired to save
                                them nor even to recognize them, notwithstanding <pb facs="0640" n="580" xml:id="pg_580"/> there are established, legally or
                                illegally, all the democratic organs by means of which they could
                                have caused their rights to have been enforced, or at least their
                                voice to have been heard?</p>
                            <p>Is it just, is it patriotic, is it desirable to retain titles which
                                the law has given, when the violation of the law is an event
                                consummated or tolerated by the nation itself, and when their
                                retention, under the present circumstances, might bring civil war,
                                the only means that the representation of the people has left to
                                save them, a war which would put an end, perhaps, to the Mexican
                                nationality?</p>
                            <p>The voice of the passions silenced, conscience has answered these
                                inquiries in the negative.</p>
                            <p>All of them involve a political problem; and of the present, whose
                                prompt solution the epoch exacts, the interests of the republic
                                reclaim, and to which I am led by my political position, parsed
                                events, and the affection without limits that I have for my country.
                                One of two extremes I have to touch in order to give this
                                solution—to launch with the law in my hand, into civil war. or to
                                abdicate in a patriotic and sincere manner the titles with which the
                                nation has invested me.</p>
                            <p>Between these two extremes I have not vacillated for a moment in
                                accepting the latter, and much more when this acceptation is imposed
                                upon me by the reasons before stated, and is not indirectly exacted
                                from me in the darkness of a prison.</p>
                            <p>I separate myself, therefore, from the constitutional titles and
                                powers with which I have been invested by the vote of the people and
                                the precepts of the law; whether as constitutional president of the
                                supreme court of justice, or as President ad interim of the
                                republic, I renounce them, and I return them complete and without
                                spot to that same people, when so it is required by the force of
                                past and present events and the peace of the nation.</p>
                            <p>In returning to the obscurity of private life, accompanied by the
                                calmness and tranquillity of my conscience after a prolonged and
                                stormy struggle, I have no embarrassment in order to remove all
                                pretext for civil war, in recognizing, as I recognize, with my
                                character of simple citizen, the authorities and functionaries
                                actually established, to the end that under the shadow of the
                                existing order, the patriotism of good Mexicans can secure the
                                peace, the liberty, the progress, and the well-being of our
                                exhausted republic.</p>
                            <p>No unpatriotic caprice, no ignoble and unfounded ambition, has led me
                                to defend, with the force of truth and of reason and not with the
                                force of arms, the isolated cause on the side of which I have been
                                found until to-day.</p>
                            <p>I have defended with loyalty what, by my oath, I was required to do.
                                The fulfillment of my obligations I have believed absolutely
                                necessary to the national honor. Besides, I have always felt in the
                                depths of my conscience that I have defended the best of causes, I
                                abdicate it when the entire nation so exacts by means of a multitude
                                of events which it has sanctioned. In abdicating it I have adopted
                                the measure which is most in harmony with the public interests.</p>
                            <p>Upright, patriotic, and disinterested have been my intentions;
                                upright, patriotic, and disinterested they are to-day. May the God
                                of the universe, who knows my sincerity, grant that they shall
                                contribute to the happiness of the dear land that has given me
                                birth.</p>
                            <p>I should blush before myself if any ignoble passion should remain in
                                my heart; if in it there should be given place to any low and base
                                resentment against men and against events, and still more should I
                                be ashamed when I know that the torrent of the latter almost always
                                bears the former forward by unexpected, unknown, and even
                                involuntary ways.</p>
                            <p>Mexicans, I swear to you before God, in addressing to you the
                                fullness of my last official word, no sacrifice will I omit, not
                                even that of going to seek an asylum and a tomb in a foreign land,
                                if this shall be necessary, in order that there shall be realized
                                the prayers that I make to-day for the peace of Mexico; no sacrifice
                                is there that I will shun, if from this sacrifice shall result to my
                                country honor and prestige at home, honor and prestige befores the
                                enlightened peoples of the world, honor and prestige in the present,
                                and honor and prestige before history.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Saltillo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-08-19"><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 19,
                                        1868</date>.</dateline>
                                <lb/>
                                <signed>JESUS GONZALEZ ORTEGA.</signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>