<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Sullivan to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1868p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d648</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">648</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1868-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1868-03-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1868-03-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1868-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="648"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d648">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Sullivan</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 59.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Bogota,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-03-22">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 22, 1868.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>On the 20th of January last, in conformity with your instructions <pb facs="1118"
                        n="1058" xml:id="pg_1058"/> of September 23, No. 14; October 30, No. 25;
                    December 3, No. 28; I addressed a supplemental note, of which Inclosure A is a
                    copy, to the Colombian government, demanding indemnities in behalf of the
                    families of the American citizens murdered, as well as on behalf of the
                    survivors of the outrage at Carthagena on the 1st of September last.</p>
                <p>Secretary Martin had given me to understand, from time to time, that this demand
                    would be settled without any difficulty; * * * but as the present administration
                    was about to go out of office, and finding no communication from you on the
                    subject, it addressed me a note, of which Inclosure B is a translation. * * * As
                    I have resolved to defer my reply to said communication until after the new
                    administration shall have been inaugurated, on the 1st of April instant, I
                    thought I ought to inform you of the progress of this perplexing case up to the
                    present time.</p>
                <p>Unless changed by the action of President Johnson, * * I shall in my said reply
                    hold the Colombian government responsible for said indemnities, believing that
                    this is the desire of our government. * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>PETER J. SULLIVAN.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">A.</note>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Sullivan</persName> to <persName type="to">Señor
                            Martin</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Bogota,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-01-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 20, 1868.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In obedience to instructions from my
                        government, and as supplemental to my note which on the 5th of October last
                        I did myself the honor to address to your excellency on the subject of the
                        murder of George A. Borchart and J. W. Murdaugh, and of the murderous attack
                        upon T. L. Dornin and Lieutenant Smith by a mob of Colombians at Carthagena
                        on the 1st of September last, I now further demand of the Colombian
                        government indemnities in money for the relatives of the persons so
                        murdered, as well as on behalf of the survivors of said outrage.</p>
                    <p>Colombia owes it to herself and to the high position which she occupies among
                        the family of republics to convince her oldest sister and best friend, the
                        United States of America, that justice and fair play shall ever be the
                        unselfish object of the younger toward the children of the older
                        republic.</p>
                    <p>I request that your excellency will inform me without delay of the action of
                        your government on this demand.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your excellency’s obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>PETER J. SULLIVAN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency Señor Doctor <hi rend="smallcaps">Carlos Martin,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Interior and of Foreign Relations, U.
                                S. Colombia.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">B.</note>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Señor Carlos Martin</persName> to <persName type="to"
                            >General Sullivan</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Office of the Interior and Foreign
                                    Relations,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Bogota,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-03-24">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 24, 1868.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>I have had the honor to receive the note of 20th January last, in which your
                        excellency, in addition to that of the 5th of October last, which referred
                        to offenses committed in Cartagena on 1st of September, 1867, upon the
                        persons of Messrs. G. A. Borchart, J. W. Murdaugh, J. L. Dornin, and J.
                        Smith, demands of the Colombian government indemnities in favor of the
                        families of the two former, who died in consequence of the said offenses,
                        and of the persons of the two latter.</p>
                    <pb facs="1119" n="1059" xml:id="pg_1059"/>
                    <p>The government has entertained a feeling of regret upon being informed of the
                        contents of the said additional note, because it cannot perceive upon what
                        basis the demand made therein can be supported. On the contrary, it finds
                        clear and precise rules in the law of nations, corroborated by the
                        stipulations of the treaty at present in force between this republic and the
                        United States of America, consonant with the internal laws of Colombia, and
                        which demonstrate that the occasion for the government to concede the
                        indemnification which your excellency solicits has not arrived.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency is aware that the Colombian government, as soon as it was
                        informed of the crimes committed on the 1st of September, condemned them in
                        the most solemn manner, and gave orders to the attorney general of the
                        nation to carry into effect, by means of the respective agents of the public
                        ministry, the investigation of the facts, with a view to inflict upon the
                        parties responsible for the said crimes the punishment which the law
                        decrees.</p>
                    <p>Your excellency lost no time, in the note which you were pleased to address
                        to this office on the 11th of October above mentioned, to express your
                        satisfaction with the conduct observed by the Colombian government
                        respecting this affair, considering it a “fresh proof of the friendly spirit
                        of the republic of the United States of Colombia toward the government and
                        people of the United States of America,” and your excellency will have seen
                        published in the Diario Oficial, No. 1,055, the note which, in consequence
                        of the said requisition, the attorney general of the nation transmitted to
                        the attorney general of the sovereign State of Bolivar, under date 14th
                        October last.</p>
                    <p>Neither the recommendation of the federal executive power, nor that of the
                        attorney general of the nation, was, however, necessary. On the very night
                        of the 1st of September the competent authorities of Carthagena proceeded to
                        draw up the procès verbal of the occurrence, visiting the places in which
                        the crimes were committed, and receiving the declaration of such persons as
                        were supposed to have been present.</p>
                    <p>Subsequently nothing has been omitted, with a view to obtain as complete a
                        procès verbal as possible. The North American consul in Carthagena, who had
                        handed your excellency a report of the said events, as being perfectly
                        acquainted with them, was requested to point out the individuals who might
                        be able to give information upon the subject. In this capital the testimony
                        of Señor Juan Manuel Grau was received and added to that of such other
                        individuals as the public papers have pointed out as having been present at
                        the events of the 1st of September. Finally, Messrs. Miguel Cespe-des,
                        Teodoro Yates Marquez, Vicente Barrios, and Nicholas Franco were arrested,
                        as your excellency was informed from this office, as appearing to be
                        responsible for the said crimes, and they still remain in prison at the date
                        of the last advices received by the executive power.</p>
                    <p>As far as regards the design of this note, the narration of the few preceding
                        facts, already known for the most part to your excellency, and taken from
                        authentic documents, is sufficient, together with a statement of the
                        principles of the law of nations, as regards the matter.</p>
                    <p>Vattel, treating of the responsibility which may accrue to a nation from the
                        actions of the members who form it, after establishing the principle that
                        whoever maltreats a citizen indirectly offends the state whose duty it is to
                        protect him, and that if a sovereign, who has the power to restrain his
                        subjects within the bounds of justice and peace, permits them to offend a
                        foreign nation or citizen, he aggravates the said nation as much as if he
                        himself had offended it, expresses himself in the following terms:</p>
                    <p>“Neverthless, as it is not possible for the best organized state, or the most
                        vigilant and absolute sovereign, to regulate at his pleasure all the actions
                        of his subjects, and maintain them always in the strictest obedience, it
                        would be unjust to impute to the nation or to the sovereign all the faults
                        of the citizen, consequently it cannot generally be said that an offense has
                        been received from the nation because it may have been received from one of
                        its members.</p>
                    <p>“But if the nation, or its chief, approves or ratifies the action of the
                        citizen, he makes it his own affair, and the offended party must then look
                        upon the nation as the real author of the offense, of which, perhaps, the
                        citizen has been but the instrument.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>“And since the latter, the sovereign of the individual who has committed the
                        offense, ought not to permit his subjects to molest or injure those of
                        another, and still less audaciously to offend foreign powers, he must oblige
                        the culpable party to make reparation for the injury or the insult, if it be
                        possible, or to punish him in an exemplary manner, or finally, according to
                        the case and circumstances, deliver him up to the offended state, in order
                        that the latter may do justice.</p>
                    <p>“The sovereign who refuses to oblige his subject to repair the injury caused,
                        or to punish the culpable party, or finally to deliver him up, makes
                        himself, in some respects, an accomplice in the injury, and responsible for
                        the same.”</p>
                    <p>Mr. Bello, in his treatise on international law, while stating the rights and
                        duties of foreigners, established a doctrine similar to that of Vattel.</p>
                    <p>The before-mentioned author declares “that the foreigner, as soon as he
                        enters the territory of another nation, contracts the obligation of
                        submitting to the laws and <pb facs="1120" n="1060" xml:id="pg_1060"/> local
                        jurisdiction, and the state offers him the protection of the public
                        authority deposited in the tribunals; so that if the latter should unjustly
                        refuse to hear his complaint, or should do him a manifest injustice, the
                        foreigner may then interpose the authority of his own sovereign, having
                        recourse to the minister of the nation near the government in whose
                        territory he resides, or in order to be heard in judgment or to be
                        indemnified for the injuries he may have received. He adds that the acts of
                        jurisdiction of a nation over the foreigners residing therein, if they are
                        in conformity with its own laws, must be respected by other nations, in
                        virtue of the obligations which every person contracts on entering the
                        territory of a foreign state to submit himself to its laws, and consequently
                        to the regulations which it has established for the administration of
                        justice, and finally from the obligation which the state contracts of
                        observing the said laws as regards the foreigner, he infers that if the
                        state approves, instigates, or tolerates the acts of injustice and violence
                        of its subjects against foreigners, it makes them in reality its own, and
                        makes itself responsible for them as regards other nations.”</p>
                    <p>It is apparent, therefore, that the cases in which a government is
                        responsible for the acts of its subjects executed against foreigners are
                        limited to those in which the said government approves, instigates, or
                        tolerates the said acts, refusing to punish the culprits, or that the latter
                        make good the injuries they have caused. The American legation has not made,
                        nor could it in justice make, against the Colombian government the
                        accusation of having approved, instigated, or tolerated the crimes of the
                        1st of September.</p>
                    <p>The contrary has been recognized by your excellency, and is proved by the
                        facts related at the commencement of the present note, as well as by the
                        trial in progress in Carthagena in consequence of the said crimes.</p>
                    <p>The injured individuals will possess the right to be indemnified for the
                        damages received by the persons who caused them, establishing their claim
                        before the authorities of Colombia, and in accordance with the laws of the
                        republic to which they submit themselves, when they entered the territory of
                        the union.</p>
                    <p>Equally clear with the statements of the law of nations above cited are, as
                        regards the present case, those of the treaty rights between Colombia and
                        the United States of America.</p>
                    <p>The treaty in force between the two countries states in the 13th article that
                        the two contracting parties undertake reciprocally to dispense their special
                        protection to the persons and properties of the citizens of each one in the
                        territories, subject to the jurisdiction of the other; but in the same
                        article the manner is determined in which the said protection is to be
                        afforded them, “leaving open and free to them the tribunals of justice, in
                        the same terms as are used and accustomed by the natives or citizens of the
                        country.”</p>
                    <p>Besides, the laws of Colombia do not confer either upon foreigners or
                        citizens the right to claim of the Union indemnification for injuries caused
                        by crimes such as those committed on the 1st of September.</p>
                    <p>The said right is conferred upon the injured parties against the culprits,
                        and consequently it is from the latter that the imdemnification which your
                        excellency claims from the government must be exacted. Besides, the amount
                        of the said indemnifications must be taken into consideration, as a matter
                        of proof and judicial settlement.</p>
                    <p>The conclusion, therefore, of the trial which is at present being conducted
                        in Carthagena, will be the means which may lead to the satisfaction of the
                        claims to which I have referred.</p>
                    <p>The time has not yet arrived, in the absence of official data, for the
                        solution of this question.</p>
                    <p>The result of the trial, at present in progress in Carthagena, will afford
                        the clear and precise data required for the examination of the question
                        respecting the responsibility for the lamentable assassinations to which the
                        undersigned had referred. If, in accordance with the results of the judicial
                        investigations actually in progress, the principles of the law of nations,
                        and the stipulations of the treaty in force between Colombia and the United
                        States of America, the Colombian government should appear to have incurred
                        any responsibility, the republic will not refuse to satisfy the same.</p>
                    <p>The executive power will reiterate the orders communicated to Carthagena for
                        the acceleration of the course of the judicial process before alluded
                        to.</p>
                    <p>With sentiments of high and distinguished consideration, I have the honor to
                        subscribe myself the honorable General Sullivan’s very attentive
                        servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CARLOS MARTIN.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
