<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1868-05-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1868-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="66" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Hay</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 23.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Vienna,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1868-05-27"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 27, 1868.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The official Gazette of yesterday
                            contained the text of the laws in regard to schools and civil marriage,
                            commonly called the confessional laws. On the 24th of October last I
                            announced to you the passage of the first of these measures through the
                            lower house of the Reichsrath. On the night of the 21st of March the
                            city of Vienna was illuminated, the ministers serenaded, and the
                            national hymn sung by a vast concourse of people around the statue of
                            Joseph II, in honor of a favorable vote in the same matter in the House
                            of Lords. But it was only on Monday last that these measures received
                            the imperial sanction and became laws of the empire. By a singular and
                            touching coincidence, the promulgation of these laws took place on the
                            same day with the funeral of Dr. Mühlfeld, who was their principal
                            framer and most strenuous advocate in the House of Representatives. He
                            died on Sunday, unconscious that his great work was at last
                            completed.</p>
                        <p>No intelligent persons, whom I have seen, have at any time seriously
                            doubted that the Emperor would sanction these measures. Since he has
                            entered upon the new constitutional path which he is now treading, he
                            has acted with the utmost propriety and good faith, in submitting his
                            personal sentiments and desires to the regularly expressed wish of the
                            people of the empire. But the very long delay in the matter; the
                            mysterious silence of Count Crivelli in Rome, from his arrival there
                            until his sudden death; the presence at Pesth-Ofen of members of the
                            imperial family of notorious reactionary sympathies; and the ceaseless
                            activity of the higher clergy in Austria, all combined to excite a vague
                            feeling of distrust among the people, which is now finally relieved.
                            There is, however, no enthusiastic demonstration over the result. The
                            effervescence ended in March, when the Herrenhaus voted.</p>
                        <p>Baron Heysenbug started yesterday for Rome, to resume the negotiations
                            with the Pope, which were broken off by the death of Count Crivelli. It
                            is not thought that the Papal government will push matters to an open
                            breach with this court. They will more probably prefer to accept the
                            inevitable state of things—saving all their rights or claims by a strong
                            protest, and trusting by their still great influence, in every class
                            from palace to hovel, to prevent the recent legislation from inflicting
                            any practical damage upon the ecclesiastical power.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, with great respect, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>JOHN HAY.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>