<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-06-22T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-06-22T15:00:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A4/1148: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Acting Chairman of the American Delegation
                                        (<persName corresp="#p_GHS1" type="from">Gibson</persName>)
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-06-22T21:00:00+01:00">June
                                        22, 1932—9 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received June 22—8:20 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>268. Following is text of my remarks at the General Commission today:
                                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>I am desired by the President of the United States to
                                        communicate to the Conference the text of a statement which
                                        he is giving out at this moment. It is his hope that the
                                        public statement of such a program will fire the imagination
                                        of the world and lead all nations to consider deeply and
                                        state openly how much they can contribute to a great general
                                        program (here was inserted text of President’s
                                        statement).</p>
                                    <p>The significance of the President’s statement will be
                                        apparent to all. It is clear, self-contained and
                                        comprehensive. I am well aware that every one here will wish
                                        to study it in detail. There are, however, certain
                                        clarifications and explanations which I can make at once in
                                        order to clear up one or two points.</p>
                                    <p>With reference to cruiser strength it is proposed that the 25
                                        percent reduction of the total tonnage of the United States
                                        and Great Britain should be calculated on the present total
                                        London Treaty tonnage of Great Britain, namely: 339,000
                                        tons. Furthermore, the total tonnage allowed under that
                                        treaty for 8-inch gun cruisers shall be limited to 150,000
                                        tons each for the United States and Great Britain and the
                                        proportionate 90,000 tonnage for Japan.</p>
                                    <p>I also feel that there should be a clarification on the
                                        subject of submarines. In order to make the acceptance of
                                        such a sweeping reduction possible, the President’s
                                        communication must be examined on the basis that no nation
                                        whether or not a party to existing naval treaties shall
                                        retain a tonnage in submarines greater than 35,000 tons or
                                        more than 40 submarine units of which no single vessel shall
                                        exceed 1200 tons.</p>
                                    <p>In view of the reductions suggested for the five leading
                                        naval powers under the President’s plans it seems evident
                                        that the other powers should here agree to corresponding
                                        sacrifices through the reduction or limitation of their
                                        naval armaments.</p>
                                    <p>I have not labored here all these months with my colleagues
                                        present today without becoming convinced of their
                                        earnestness of purpose and their desire to see the greatest
                                        possible accomplishment in disarmament. Therefore, I am sure
                                        that the principle of maximum accomplishment to which each
                                        nation makes substantial contributions, as my country is
                                        doing by the provisions of the text which I have just read,
                                        will appeal to them.</p>
                                    <p>In our most powerful arm, the Navy, we are prepared as a part
                                        of this program to scrap over 300,000 tons of existing ships
                                        and to forego the right to build over 50,000 tons. In land
                                        material our proposal would affect over a thousand heavy
                                        mobile guns and approximately 900 tanks, and in aviation
                                        about 300 bombardment airplanes.</p>
                                    <pb facs="0341" n="221" xml:id="pg_221"/>
                                    <p>The American delegation is at your disposal for further
                                        explanations and clarification as they may become necessary,
                                        and these points will no doubt be forthcoming as the
                                        conversations in which we are now engaged progress. These
                                        very real sacrifices of strength which the United States is
                                        willing to make in a predominant arm as part of a world
                                        scheme cannot fail, I am convinced, to find equally generous
                                        response.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GHS1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gibson</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>