<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to the Chairman of the American Delegation
                    (Gibson)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-07-02T20:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-07-02T20:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-07-02T20:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-07-02T20:00:00-05:00" n="176"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A4/1238: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        the Chairman of the American Delegation (<persName corresp="#p_GHS1"
                            type="to">Gibson</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-07-02T21:00:00-04:00"
                            >July 2, 1932—9 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>168. Your 295 July 2, 10 a.m. and 296 July 2, 11 a.m. Our 166 July 2, 1 p.m.
                    which was drafted and despatched before the receipt of your two telegrams under
                    reference, shows that the Department views the problem in essentially the same
                    terms as the Delegation. If you can obtain in advance British and French support
                    for your resolution (we can, I suppose, assume Italian and German approval), you
                    will have gone a long way toward avoiding the dangers to which we called your
                    attention this morning. The resolution submitted in your 296 is well-conceived
                    and in general accords with our views, but before making use of it in even a
                    preliminary way, we must ask you to make two important modifications.</p>
                <p>Section II, point B should be abbreviated so as merely to read “The abolition of
                    all bombardment aviation.” The references to the limitation of maximum unladen
                    weight and to numbers of airplanes should be omitted.</p>
                <p>It has been found impossible thus far to reach a meeting of minds with the War
                    and Navy Departments on these points, concerning which you also asked for
                    instructions in your 297 July 2, 12 noon.<note n="23" xml:id="d176fn23">Not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>As to the maximum limit of unladen weight of airplanes: <list>
                        <label>(A)</label>
                        <item>the Navy Department cannot recommend a limitation of size. If,
                            however, (1) aerial bombing can be definitely prohibited and (2) if
                            proper provision can be made for an adequate supply for naval purposes
                            of planes of a large size, a general limitation in size might prove
                            acceptable to the Navy Department. Such general limitation <pb
                                facs="0380" n="260" xml:id="pg_260"/> should be fixed at not lower
                            than 6,000 pounds unladen weight. For transport and flying boat types,
                            Navy Department opposes a limit of less than 20,000 pounds, the weight
                            which it considers necessary for a flying boat capable of making aerial
                            passages to the island possessions of the United States.</item>
                        <label>(B)</label>
                        <item>The War Department remains firmly opposed to fixing maximum limit of
                            unladen weights for airplanes which it feels should receive no
                            consideration as a compromise for universal abolition of bombardment
                            aviation. It holds that rapid technical development unquestionably would
                            negative in a short period any attempt to limit the offensive character
                            of aircraft and that the needs of the several nations as to the
                            characteristics even of peculiarly defensive aircraft, vary so widely
                            that the fixing of unladen weight limits could only result in grossly
                            unequal effects.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>As to the numerical restriction of aircraft: <list>
                        <label>(A)</label>
                        <item>The Navy Department advocates the basis of limitation as the “full
                            needs of naval armament agreed upon by treaty, including the essential
                            auxiliary services under naval administration.” In no case, should the
                            naval aircraft strength allotted to the United States be less than that
                            allotted to the British Empire and in a ratio to that of Japan
                            equivalent to the Washington ratio of 5 to 3. Navy Department continues
                            “Under the present treaty navy allowed the United States, there are
                            needed a total of 1847 airplanes under 6,000 pounds and 218 over 6,000
                            pounds. Abolition of bombing would not affect these totals as the
                            bombers removed would be replaced by planes of other types. Reduction of
                            the treaty navy would cause a proportionate reduction of the planes
                            carried on board vessels under 6,000 pounds but would not affect the
                            number required of heavier types. It is evident that the 250 planes of
                            the transport and flying boat types suggested in the Delegation’s
                            despatch are barely adequate to cover naval needs, irrespective of the
                            needs of the Army for these types.”</item>
                        <label>(B)</label>
                        <item>The War Department feels that no decision on this point should be made
                            until the question of the abolishing of bombardment aviation has been
                            disposed of.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The differences of viewpoint quoted above graphically illustrate the difficulties
                    that you will undoubtedly run into if you try to include in your resolution
                    anything but the broadest generalities. This is the type of problem that can be
                    handled far more effectively in a small committee.</p>
                <p>Section II, point F. We fear it will be necessary to omit this reference to
                    limitation of expenditures, which was not included in the President’s proposal,
                    and which goes far beyond anything we have agreed to or authorised. In view of
                    your numerous recommendations we have given special and sympathetic
                    consideration to this question but still believe that an acceptance of the
                    principle would be impossible.</p>
                <pb facs="0381" n="261" xml:id="pg_261"/>
                <p>Before finally agreeing to an extension of the armaments truce it would be
                    necessary for us to know and approve the period of extension.</p>
                <p>We appreciate that the fate of the Conference will probably depend in large
                    measure on the events of the next 2 or 3 days, and look forward to your handling
                    of a most difficult situation with complete confidence.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Castle</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
