<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Chairman of the American Delegation (Gibson) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d189</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">189</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-07-07T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-07-07T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recA365XAlFrgaB1r" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft Convention</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="air-safety"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Civil aviation</term>
                    <term ref="recuNUGXUJaLrhxGj" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85010862"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Bacteriological</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recOnXrY2VMpZg7fA" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="biological-warfare" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85010862" lcsh-match="exact">Bacteriological</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-07-07T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-07-07T18:00:00-05:00" n="189"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d189">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A4/1269: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting Chairman of the American Delegation (<persName
                            corresp="#p_GHS1" type="from">Gibson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                            >Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-07-08T00:00:00+01:00"
                            >July 8, 1932—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received July 8—11:37
                        p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>315. Following is text of projected resolution as drafted by <persName
                        corresp="#p_SSJ1">Simon</persName> last night, July 7: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="center">“I</p>
                        <p>The Conference for the Reduction and Limitation of Armaments.</p>
                        <p>Being firm in its determination to achieve a substantial measure of
                            disarmament, which should be sought along the lines of article <pb
                                facs="0405" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/> No. 8 of the Covenant of the
                            League of Nations expected to make and which would be the natural
                            consequence of the undertaking given by the states of the world in
                            signing the Briand-Kellogg Pact;</p>
                        <p>Welcoming heartily the initiative taken by the President of the United
                            States in formulating concrete proposals;</p>
                        <p>Bearing in mind also the Draft Convention of the Preparatory Committee,
                            the statements made to the Conference by a number of delegations and the
                            reports and resolutions of the various commissions of the
                            Conference;</p>
                        <p>Declares that it accepts forthwith and unanimously the underlying
                            principles of President <persName corresp="#p_HH1">Hoover</persName>’s
                            declaration: <list>
                                <item>First, That the present Conference should decide on a
                                    substantial reduction of armaments;</item>
                                <item>Second, That this reduction should apply to all three
                                    arms—land, sea and air;</item>
                                <item>Third, That a primary objective should be the weakening of
                                    methods of attack so as to strengthen defense.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">II</p>
                        <p>The Conference notes that a sufficient measure of agreement has been
                            reached upon a number of important points to enable it to record already
                            at this stage a considerable advance toward the goal which it is seeking
                            to reach. It is now able to declare that, without prejudice to more far
                            reaching proposals that have been made or may be put forward by
                            different delegations, there is agreement on the following
                            propositions:</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Air Armaments</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>1. The chapter of the disarmament convention dealing with air armaments
                            shall contain provisions to secure the civil population against air
                            attack.</p>
                        <p>2. With this object in view the high contracting parties should accept
                            and observe provisions defining strictly the area, if any, within which
                            bombardment from the air may be practiced in the event of hostilities
                            between them.</p>
                        <p>3. It should further go as far as possible towards the elimination of
                            types of aircraft specially suited for bombardment by providing for the
                            limitation to (blank) tons of the unladen weight of any individual
                            airplane, capable of use in war, in commission and in immediate reserve
                            in the land, sea and air armed forces of each of the high contracting
                            parties. A limited number of exceptions may have to be made to meet
                            special circumstances.</p>
                        <p>4. In addition the maximum number and total tonnage of airplanes, capable
                            of use in war, in commission and in immediate reserve in the land, sea
                            and air armed forces of each of the high contracting parties shall be
                            limited.</p>
                        <p>5. Airplanes above the specified weight, devoted to civil aviation,
                            should be subject to a special international regime.</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Land Armaments</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>6. In order to reduce the offensive character of all land forces as
                            distinguished from their defensive character the chapter of the
                            disarmament <pb facs="0406" n="286" xml:id="pg_286"/> convention dealing
                            with land armaments shall contain a provision prohibiting the possession
                            by any high contracting party of any tank exceeding (blank) tons in
                            weight. Any tank exceeding this limit of weight shall be destroyed
                            within (blank) months of the coming into force of the convention.</p>
                        <p>7. The number and calibre of heavy land artillery shall be limited.</p>
                        <p>8. The chapter of the disarmament convention dealing with chemical,
                            bacteriological and incendiary weapons shall contain the provisions
                            recommended by the special committee on such weapons as summarized in
                            the annex to this resolution (the annex seems unnecessary to cable).</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Supervision</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>9. The disarmament convention shall provide for the establishment of a
                            permanent disarmament commission with the constitution, rights and
                            duties generally as outlined in part 6 of the draft disarmament
                            convention submitted by the Preparatory Commission for the Disarmament
                            Conference.</p>
                        <p>10. It is for consideration whether and under what conditions the
                            Permanent Disarmament Commission shall be given rights of local
                            investigations of complaints.</p>
                        <p rend="center">III</p>
                        <p>11. The Conference decides to invite the Bureau to meet during the
                            adjournment of the Conference, with a view to making agreed
                            recommendations for giving detailed effect to points 1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 7
                            and 10 above in so far as these have not been settled by the present
                            declaration.</p>
                        <p>The Bureau shall endeavor to find a rule or standard whereby the numbers
                            and total tonnage of airplanes referred to in point 4 can be
                            determined.</p>
                        <p>In each case where an agreed recommendation is secured, the Bureau shall
                            draft—with the assistance if need be of a special drafting
                            committee—articles giving effect to the recommendation, for insertion in
                            the convention.</p>
                        <p>Certain other points raised in President <persName corresp="#p_HH1"
                                >Hoover</persName>’s declaration, in the draft disarmament
                            convention and by various delegations in the course of the present
                            session call for further detailed examination before concrete
                            propositions can be furnished.</p>
                        <p>The Conference requests the Bureau to examine, with the assistance of
                            such other delegations as it may decide to be necessary, the proposal
                            made by President <persName corresp="#p_HH1">Hoover</persName> and other
                            proposals with regard effectives and to consider the various proposals
                            that have been made for the limitation of the caliber of mobile land
                            guns.</p>
                        <p>In any case this committee shall furnish a report on the results of its
                            deliberations, with the text of any articles that may have been drafted
                            in time for circulation to the delegations to the Conference one month
                            before the opening of the next session.</p>
                        <p>The Subcommittee of the National Defense Expenditure Commission shall
                            continue and complete its work as soon as possible in order that the
                            Conference on its resumption may be in a position to decide whether a
                            system of budgetary limitation or publicity can be accepted.</p>
                        <pb facs="0407" n="287" xml:id="pg_287"/>
                        <p>As regards the proposals made by President <persName corresp="#p_HH1"
                                >Hoover</persName> and other proposals concerning naval armament the
                            Conference invites the powers parties to the naval treaties of
                            Washington and London to confer together and to report to the
                            Conference, if possible, before the resumption of its work the
                            conditions which they have been able to reach. It is recognized that the
                            limitations and reductions to be accepted by the naval powers other than
                            the powers parties to the above treaties will be dependent on the nature
                            of these conclusions.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GHS1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Gibson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
