<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-06-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-06-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="430" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d430">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51W89 Hungary/84</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Hungarian Minister (<persName corresp="#p_SCL1" type="to">Széchényi</persName>)</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-06-03">June 3,
                                    1932</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to your
                                note No. 243/Res, dated May 17, 1932, in which, upon instructions
                                from the Royal Hungarian Foreign Office, you stated that while the
                                Royal Hungarian Government had decided to sign the postponement
                                agreement regarding payments during the fiscal year 1932, it
                                expected that should the Government of the United States at any time
                                grant to another debtor nation more favorable terms for the
                                repayment of the amount postponed under the so-called moratorium,
                                the same terms and benefits will be extended to the Royal Hungarian
                                Government also.</p>
                            <p>I have brought your note under reference to the attention of the
                                Secretary of the Treasury, who is authorized by the Joint Resolution
                                of Congress, approved December 23, 1931, to make, with the approval
                                of the President, debt postponement agreements on the terms and
                                conditions set forth in that Resolution. The Secretary of the
                                Treasury has replied in the following terms: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The Joint Resolution of Congress approved December 23, 1931,
                                        authorizes agreements to be concluded with our foreign
                                        debtors for the payment over a period of ten years beginning
                                        July 1, 1933, of the amounts postponed during the fiscal
                                        year 1932, with interest at the rate of four per centum per
                                        annum, in ten equal annuities. <pb facs="0749" n="629" xml:id="pg_629"/> This is the authority under which the
                                        Treasury Department is proceeding and there can be no
                                        deviation from the terms of the Joint Resolution.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>For the Secretary of State <lb/>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BHH1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harvey H. Bundy</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>