<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-07-12T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-07-12T10:00:00-05:00" n="480" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d480">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00R296A1/227: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Basel (<persName corresp="#p_CHM1" type="from">Cochran</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Basel</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-07-12T16:00:00+01:00">July 12,
                                    1932—4 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received July 12—1:52 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>For <persName corresp="#p_CWR1">Castle</persName>. The following is the
                            text of the Gentlemen’s Agreement of July 8:<note n="25" xml:id="d480fn25">In the official British White Paper, this document
                                is dated July 2 (Great Britain, Cmd. 4129, Misc. No. 8 (1932): <hi rend="italic">Further Documents relating to the Settlement
                                    reached at the Lausanne Conference</hi>, p. 3).</note>
                            <pb facs="0808" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The Lausanne agreement<note n="26" xml:id="d480fn26">Great
                                        Britain, Cmd. 4126, Misc. No. 7 (1932): <hi rend="italic">Final Act of the Lausanne Conference, Lausanne, July 9,
                                            1932.</hi>
                                    </note> will not come into final effect until after ratification
                                    as provided for in the agreement. So far as the creditor
                                    governments, on whose behalf this <hi rend="italic">procès-verbale</hi> is initialed,<note n="27" xml:id="d480fn27">Initialed by <persName corresp="#p_RJ1">Jules Renkin</persName> on behalf of Belgium; <persName corresp="#p_HE1">Edouard Herriot</persName> on behalf of
                                        France; <persName corresp="#p_CAN1">Neville
                                            Chamberlain</persName> on behalf of Great Britain; and
                                            <persName corresp="#p_MA1">Antonio Mosconi</persName> on
                                        behalf of Italy.</note> are concerned, ratification will not
                                    be effected until a satisfactory settlement has been reached
                                    between them and their own creditors. It will be open to them to
                                    explain the position to their respective parliaments, but no
                                    specific reference to it will appear in the text of the
                                    agreement with Germany. Subsequently if a satisfactory
                                    settlement about their own debts is reached the aforesaid
                                    creditor governments will ratify and the agreement with Germany
                                    will come into full effect. But if no such settlement can be
                                    obtained, the agreement with Germany will not be ratified; a new
                                    situation will have arisen and the governments interested will
                                    have to consult together as to what should be done. In that
                                    event, the legal position, as between all the governments, would
                                    revert to that which existed before the <persName corresp="#p_HH1">Hoover</persName> Moratorium.</p>
                                <p>The German Government will be notified of this arrangement.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CHM1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Cochran</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>