<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the British Ambassador (Lindsay)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d532</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">532</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-12-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recbfb6dc62c599a48" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recRIwGRq2ONxRdH9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022007585"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigrant</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-12-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-12-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="532"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d532">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.51W89 Great Britain/356</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        British Ambassador (<persName corresp="#p_LSRC1" type="to"
                            >Lindsay</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-12-07">December 7,
                            1932</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: My Government has considered with the
                    greatest care the note of December 1, 1932, from the British Government in which
                    it has set forth at length the reasons which it advances for a reconsideration
                    of the whole question of intergovernmental war debts, and for the postponement
                    of the payment due by the British Government to the Government of the United
                    States on December 15th, next.</p>
                <p>Whatever part debt payments may have played in the economic history of the
                    post-war years, it is clear that in the present conditions of world-wide
                    depression, accompanied by a sweeping fall of prices, their weight has greatly
                    increased, and that they have a very definite relationship to the problem of
                    recovery, in which both the British and the American people have so vital an
                    interest.</p>
                <p>The President of the United States is prepared, through whatever agency may seem
                    appropriate, in cooperation with the British Government, to survey the entire
                    situation and to consider what means may be taken to bring about the restoration
                    of stable currencies and exchange, the revival of trade, and the recovery of
                    prices.</p>
                <p>I welcome the suggestion contained in the note of your Government of a close
                    examination between the United States and Great Britain of the whole subject in
                    preparation for the International Economic Conference, for I believe that there
                    are important avenues of mutual advantage which should be thoroughly explored.
                    Such an examination does not imply cancellation. In such an examination there
                    would necessarily be consideration of other forms of tangible compensation
                    available for the expansion of markets for products of American agriculture and
                    labor. And you will understand that the <pb facs="0892" n="772" xml:id="pg_772"
                    /> problem of foreign debts has in the American mind very definite relationship
                    with the problem of disarmament and the continued burden which competitive
                    armament imposes upon the entire world.</p>
                <p>In order that you may understand more fully the attitude of the American people,
                    I feel that I should refer briefly to certain implications in your note as to
                    which the facts are viewed by our people differently from the understanding set
                    forth by you.</p>
                <p>Your note seems to carry the thought that the loans made by the United States
                    Government represent in their entirety expenditures on destruction; that the
                    payments heretofore made to the United States have been largely responsible for
                    the existing world depression and the concentration of a large amount of gold in
                    the United States; and that complete cancellation of war debts, as indicated in
                    the Balfour Note, is essential to world recovery. We cannot agree with these
                    conclusions.</p>
                <p>Many of the loans made before the armistice and substantially all the loans made
                    after the armistice were not for destruction. Of the amount expended in the
                    United States by our debtors after we entered the war, both before and after the
                    armistice, most of which was borrowed from the United States Government on war
                    and relief loans, less than a third was spent for munitions and remounts. Very
                    large amounts were spent for food, tobacco, etc., for cotton and exchange, for
                    relief and surplus supplies sold on credit, for repayments of commercial loans,
                    and for interest. Much of the food, tobacco, cotton, relief and other supplies
                    sold on credit were resold by the governments for use of their own civilian
                    population. In certain cases these supplies were actually resold and the funds
                    turned into the treasury of the debtor governments. The amounts used to purchase
                    exchange were in reality loans by the United States to the allied countries
                    which were no doubt expended by them in part at least in countries other than
                    the United States; they served to maintain the value of allied currencies. Some
                    of the loans made after the armistice were vital to the recovery, and indeed, to
                    the very existence of the borrowing nations.</p>
                <p>It does not seem accurate, therefore, to treat all of what are termed in the
                    United States “War Debts” as representing sums devoted in their entirety to
                    expenditures on destruction and totally unproductive in so far as the borrowing
                    governments are concerned.</p>
                <p>The United States Government in reaching the settlements with its debtors has
                    combined loans made during the war period and loans made after the armistice,
                    including commercial credits, funding all in the debt agreements. It is our
                    understanding that a different practice has prevailed in Europe. The figures
                    cited in the note of <pb facs="0893" n="773" xml:id="pg_773"/> the British
                    Government covering advances made by the United States of America and advances
                    made by the United Kingdom, as well as receipts to date on these advances, are
                    not therefore strictly comparable.</p>
                <p>The note of the British Government also seems to us to overemphasize the
                    influence which war debt payments may have had in the past on world economy.
                    With various observations and figures presented by the British Government in
                    that regard the American Government is not in accord, but it does not desire to
                    enter into detailed discussion in the face of the larger immediate issues. In
                    general it is our view that the causes of this depression lie in much more
                    potent forces than these debt transactions. We notice that similar conclusions
                    have been indicated in the careful study published by the League of Nations
                    entitled, “The Course and Phases of the World Economic Depression.”<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d532fn4">[Bertil Gotthard Ohlin,] <hi rend="italic">The Course and
                            Phases of the World Economic Depression: Report presented to the
                            Assembly of the League of Nations</hi> (Geneva, Secretariat of the
                        League of Nations, 1931).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Furthermore, in its inferences as to the difficulties of payment, the British
                    Government treats merely some of the items of the balance of payments, leaving
                    out of account service items. It may be pointed out that the expenditures of
                    American tourists in foreign lands during the period 1924 to 1930 have totalled
                    approximately $3,900,000,000, and that during that period immigrant remittances
                    have aggregated net $1,495,000,000. This is in comparison to the total receipts
                    of $1,673,000,000 on account of debt settlements during the same period. Again
                    in measuring the transfer question, account must be taken not only of trade
                    directly with the United States but of the whole area of international dealings.
                    In the total of receipts and outgo arising from the international transactions
                    of both our debtors and ourselves, debt payments have been a relatively minor
                    item.</p>
                <p>The argument that the payment of these debts to the United States has drained the
                    gold reserves of other countries to the United States, does not seem to us borne
                    out by actual experience. The gold holdings of the United States at the time
                    these payments upon debts began were about $4,028,000,000, and they stand now at
                    about $4,338,000,000. It is true that our gold supply has at times exceeded this
                    sum but this extra gold was demonstrably temporary deposits by other nations not
                    related to debt payments. The main fault in the distribution of gold supplies
                    seems to us to have occurred as between the different countries of Europe as the
                    gold supplies of Europe increased from about $3,018,000,000, on January 1st,
                    1924, to about <pb facs="0894" n="774" xml:id="pg_774"/> $6,963,000,000 at
                    present; the distribution of which as between the countries of Europe cannot be
                    attributed to forces originating in the United States.</p>
                <p>I feel I must also call attention to the misunderstanding which might arise from
                    the following statement in your note: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The initiative in devising settlement of reparations was taken by the
                            creditor governments of Germany, at Lausanne with the cognizance and
                            approval of the United States Government.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The facts in this connection were more accurately set out in a statement issued
                    by the British Treasury on July 14th last: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Misunderstanding has arisen regarding Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CAN1"
                                >Chamberlain</persName>’s reference in his speech to the House of
                            Commons on Monday, referring to conversations with representatives of
                            the United States. He did not suggest, and of course had no intention of
                            suggesting that representatives of the United States had approved,
                            either tacitly or explicitly, what was done at Lausanne. The proceedings
                            there were throughout on the basis that the course was to seek European
                            solution of reparations without involving the United States in the
                                discussion.”<note n="5" xml:id="d532fn5">Statement telegraphed to
                                the Department by the Ambassador in Great Britain in his telegram
                                No. 225, July 14, 5 p.m., <ref target="#pg_690">p. 690</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>In 1923 when the British Government sent a mission to settle the debt of Great
                    Britain to the United States, the United States Treasury held demand obligations
                    of Great Britain calling for interest at the rate of 5 per cent. As a result of
                    the negotiations these obligations were refunded on an interest basis of 3⅜ths
                    per cent, which was a lower rate of interest than the credit of either country
                    at that time commanded. The policy adopted by the United States in its
                    settlement was stated by the Debt Funding Commission: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“The Commission in its settlement with Great Britain, made on June 19,
                            1923, and in subsequent negotiations or settlements has adhered to the
                            principle that the adjustments made with each government must be
                            measured by the ability of the particular government to put aside and
                            transfer to the United States the payments called for under the funding
                            agreement. Nor does the principle of capacity to pay require the foreign
                            debtor to pay to the full limit of its present or future capacity. It
                            must be permitted to preserve and improve its economic position, to
                            bring its budget into balance, and to place its finances and currency on
                            a sound basis, and to maintain, and if possible, to improve the standard
                            of living of its citizens. No settlement which is oppressive and retards
                            the recovery and development of the foreign debtor is to the best
                            interests of the United States or of Europe.”<note n="6"
                                xml:id="d532fn6">See <hi rend="italic">Combined Annual Reports of
                                    the World War Foreign Debt Commission, 1922–1926</hi>, pp.
                                37–38.</note>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The representatives of no country have set their hands to any agreement which
                    they believed at the time did not fulfill this policy.</p>
                <pb facs="0895" n="775" xml:id="pg_775"/>
                <p>While it seems desirable to state these facts from the standpoint of historical
                    accuracy and as necessary to explain the point of view of the American people
                    towards these obligations, the real question raised by the British note is how
                    can the problems which arise from the existence of these obligations best be
                    dealt with under the conditions in the world today.</p>
                <p>As to the payment due on December 15th, I appreciate the cogency of the
                    difficulties which you present as to the transfer of these monies in the present
                    state of foreign exchanges. In an endeavor to meet this situation, it already
                    has been suggested to you that the President might be willing to recommend to
                    the Congress the acceptance of deposits in sterling in England, to be guaranteed
                    as to dollar value and transferred at such time as would not interfere with the
                    stability of exchange. This I understand your Government has declined in the
                    belief that the existence of a large sum of sterling awaiting transfer would
                    affect the exchange markets almost as seriously as the actual purchase of
                    exchange. Accordingly further informal suggestions have been made to your
                    government of methods of minimizing these difficulties which it has not been
                    able to find acceptable.</p>
                <p>Recognizing these difficulties of effecting transfer I am confident that the
                    Congress will be willing to consider any reasonable suggestion made by your
                    government which will facilitate payment of the sum due on December 15th.</p>
                <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHL1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry L. Stimson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
