<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-04-20T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-04-20T08:00:00-05:00" n="60" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d60">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">500.A15A4 General Committee/32:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Acting Chairman of the American Delegation
                                        (<persName corresp="#p_GHS1" type="from">Gibson</persName>)
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-04-20T14:00:00+01:00">April
                                        20, 1932—2 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received April 20—10:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>131. This morning when the American proposal No. 7 was reached on the
                                agenda we decided to pass it over for the present as the Secretary
                                is having certain conversations with the French and these will be
                                followed by others with various delegations in order to give
                                possible chance of a favorable reception to the idea.</p>
                            <p>Therefore I spoke to the following effect. I stated that when in my
                                opening speech I had made the proposal with regard to the
                                computation of armed forces on the basis of those necessary for
                                police purposes and those for defense I had hoped that the
                                Conference would have arrived at a point where further analysis of
                                this subject <pb facs="0216" n="96" xml:id="pg_96"/> would be
                                useful. In view, however, of the fact that the studies by our
                                delegation had not been completed and as there had been no time as
                                yet for discussion with other delegations it would appear wiser to
                                postpone this discussion. I further expressed the view that as this
                                type of analysis of armed forces was germane to any discussions of
                                the problem of effectives I hoped that the Conference would be glad
                                to hear our views. These would be presented when they have been
                                perfected by consideration of the special circumstances and
                                obligations which affected many of the states represented with
                                regard to the relation which their respective armed forces bore one
                                to another. I concluded by saying that in yielding the place
                                occupied by our proposal on the agenda I felt I was acting in a
                                spirit compounded of desire to make every suggestion helpful at the
                                time of its introduction and to be sure that it would be worked out
                                on the broadest possible basis.</p>
                            <p>The Commission accepted my proposal unanimously.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GHS1">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gibson</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>