<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul at Geneva (Gilbert) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1932v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d633</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">633</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1932-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1932-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPzhKrgmOsdzocC" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recEW0owgbzhRSO8d" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Secretary-General</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-10-31T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-10-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="633"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d633">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">511.4a6/712</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva (<persName corresp="#p_VSRG1" type="from"
                            >Gilbert</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 396 Political</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-10-31">October 31,
                            1932</date>.<lb/>[Received November 9.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Department’s
                    telegram No. 161 dated October 13, 7 p.m. and to the Consulate’s reply thereto,
                    No. 301, October 15, 11 a.m.,<note n="4" xml:id="d633fn4">Neither
                        printed.</note> with particular reference to paragraph “2” of the telegram
                    last cited, and to state that due to <persName corresp="#p_DSE1">Sir Eric
                        Drummond</persName>’s recent absence from Geneva I was unable until today to
                    take up this matter with him.</p>
                <p>In pursuance of the Department’s directions I have now, however, informally made
                    known to the Secretary-General the position of the American Government as
                    follows: (1) That the American Government desires very much that the Convention
                    for the Limitation of Manufacture and Regulating the Distribution of Narcotic
                    Drugs be made operative in 1933 and that it is thus hoped that the League will
                    use every effort to bring about the Convention’s early implementation; (2) That
                    in case financial considerations enter into the question of the League’s action
                    in the premises, the American Government as a party to the Convention will be
                    prepared to defray its proportionate share of the expenses incident to
                    implementing and administering the Convention.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DSE1">Sir Eric</persName> declared that he was fully
                    acquainted with the action taken by the Supervisory Commission of the League
                    respecting the non-inclusion in the League budget of expenses connected with the
                    Limitation Convention and the statement which was made in the Commission in
                    explanation of this action. This matter was discussed in this Consulate’s
                    telegrams No. 256, September 21, 6 p.m., No. 286, October 6, 10 p.m., and 295,
                    October 11, 9 a.m. [<hi rend="italic">p.m.</hi>],<note n="5" xml:id="d633fn5"
                        >None printed.</note> to which reference is hereby made. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DSE1">Sir Eric</persName> then stated that it was he who had
                    inspired the position taken in the Supervisory Commission, inasmuch as he
                    thought that there had been too much indifference on the part of the powers
                    respecting their ratification of the Convention in question, and that a
                    statement in the Commission indicating the Secretariat’s knowledge of this
                    attitude would bring the matter into the open and would serve a useful purpose.
                    He expressed himself as gratified by the discussions which this had evoked and
                    he said that he felt that the subsequent expression of an intention to ratify
                    the Convention on the part of a number of governments was a direct result of the
                    incidents described.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Prentiss B. Gilbert</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
