<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1932-04-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1932-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="641" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d641">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">580.7A3/662</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the British Ambassador (<persName corresp="#p_LSRC1" type="to">Lindsay</persName>)</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1932-04-29">April 29,
                            1932</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to refer to your note
                        No. 455 of December 31, 1931, regarding the Revised Collision Regulations,
                        Annex II of the Convention for Promoting Safety of Life at Sea, and
                        enclosing a copy of a memorandum containing certain suggested amendments to
                        the Revised Text of the regulations.</p>
                    <p>With reference to the suggested amendments the views of this Government are
                        as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Article 2</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The United States Government has conducted a number of tests with
                                regard to the location on submarines of the two steaming lights
                                required by Article 2 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>). While it has not been
                                found practicable to comply with the requirements of Article 2 (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) as to the vertical height of the forward
                                of these two lights, it has been found practicable to install a
                                forward range light on all submarines of the United States Navy, now
                                in active service, and it is the opinion of the Navy Department that
                                the fitting of such forward range lights is especially desirable for
                                the safe navigation of vessels of this type.</p>
                            <p>In the case of some of the cruisers, it has not been possible to
                                install the after range light so as to prevent its being obscured
                                for a small angle on each bow by the structure of the foremast. In
                                no type of naval vessel, however, has it been found impracticable to
                                fit the two steaming lights in question.</p>
                            <p>This Government is of the opinion that it is in the interests of safe
                                navigation that the two steaming lights required by Article 2 (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) should be fitted on naval vessels as well
                                as on merchant vessels and that every effort should be made to meet
                                the provisions of this article “as closely as circumstances will
                                permit.”</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Article 10</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The proposal of the Netherland Government is satisfactory and
                                thoroughly desirable. In our Navy we are providing a standby stern
                                light on the conning tower fairwater (“turret”) which is used in the
                                event of failure at sea of the low stern light, which is placed “at
                                the stern”.</p>
                            <pb facs="1030" n="910" xml:id="pg_910"/>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Article 9 (b) and (c)</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The change proposed by the Japanese Government is acceptable.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Article 15</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The change in this article proposed by the Belgian Government is
                                acceptable.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">Article 11</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The change in this article proposed by the Netherlands Government is
                                satisfactory. There are some advantages in not having the anchor
                                light too high since the areas in which the vessel may be anchored
                                are frequented by small craft. It is, however, preferable that the
                                lights should be visible around the horizon than that they should be
                                especially conspicuous to small boats.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CWR1">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">W. R. Castle, Jr.</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>