<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-11-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-11-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="100" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d100">
                    <head>No. 404.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-11-30"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 30, 1874</date>.
                            (Received December 19.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 213.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 24th instant I received a telegram from
                        Mr. J. Ulrich, consul at Monterey, advising me of the arrival at that place
                        of Mr. H. M. Atkinson, the commissioner appointed by the Department of the
                        Interior to secure the removal of the Kickapoo Indians still remaining in
                        Mexico to their reservations, and asking me to procure the appointment of
                        commissioners on the part of the Mexican government, and to request the
                        co-operation of the governor of the State of Coahuila.</p>
                    <p>Although I was not advised of the coming of Mr. Atkinson, and had no
                        instructions on the subject, I on the next day called upon Mr. Lafragua,
                        minister of foreign affairs, and asked the co operation of his government in
                        accomplishing the object of Mr. Atkinson’s mission, leaving with him a note,
                        of which I inclose a copy.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lafragua stated that the present mission of Mr. Atkinson had not
                        heretofore been brought to his attention, but he promised that the subject
                        should be laid before the President immediately.</p>
                    <p>This morning, in a call which I made at the foreign office, I was informed by
                        the chief clerk, in the absence of Mr. Lafragua, that the same instructions
                        would be telegraphed to-day to the governor of Coahuila as <pb facs="0189" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/> those under which he acted last year; that
                        Señor Montero, who formerly acted as Mexican commissioner, would leave this
                        city within a few days with full instructions upon the subject, and would
                        probably be again appointed by the governor of Coahuila; and that the war
                        department had given instructions to the military commandant on the Rio
                        Grande frontier. A copy of instructions of the war department was
                        subsequently sent me in a note from Mr. Lafragua, which I inclose, and from
                        which it will be seen that action is limited to such of the Kickapoos as
                        have not entered the State of Durango and are still on the frontier.</p>
                    <p>I am not advised whether this limitation will materially interfere with the
                        object of Mr. Atkinson’s mission.</p>
                    <p>I have advised the consul at Monterey by telegraph and mail of the action of
                        the Mexican government.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 213.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to My.
                                    <persName type="to">Lafragua</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-11-25"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 25,
                                    1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to inform your excellency that I
                            have received a telegram from the consul of the United States at
                            Monterey, in the State of Nuevo Leon, stating that Mr. H. M. Atkinson,
                            the commissioner appointed by my Government for the purpose of securing,
                            if possible, the return of the remaining portion of the Kickapoo
                            Indians, still in Mexico, to their reservation in the United States, has
                            arrived at Monterey, and that he desires the co-operation of the
                            national and State authorities of Mexico to facilitate the object of his
                            mission.</p>
                        <p>In view of the past cordial co-operation of the authorities of this
                            republic in this business, I venture to request that your excellency’s
                            government will send such instructions as it may deem proper to the
                            governor of the State of Coahuila, and take such other measures as it
                            may think necessary to promote the success of Mr. Atkinson’s
                            mission.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to renew to your excellency the assurances of my
                            distinguished consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">J. M. Lafragua</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Minister of Foreign Affairs.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                                213.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Lafragua</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-11-30"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 30,
                                    1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the satisfaction of replying to the
                            note of your excellency of the 25th of this month, in which you are
                            pleased to state that there has arrived at Monterey Mr. Atkinson,
                            commissioner of the Government of the United States, to effect the
                            removal to their reservations in that country of the rest of the
                            Kickapoo Indians still in Mexico, and asking the co-operation of the
                            Mexican government, to the end that the said gentleman may be aided in
                            the accomplishment of his mission. I inclose to you a copy of the order
                            of the department of war, which I have just received, in which it
                            appears that instructions have been given to General Fuero, military
                            commandant of the line of the Bravo, that he place no obstacles in the
                            way of the return of the Indians.</p>
                        <p>I reiterate to your excellency the assurances of my distinguished
                            consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed>J. M. LAFRAGUA.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">John W. Foster</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary
                                    of the United States of America.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0190" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in 2 in No.
                                213.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Mejia</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Lafragua</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of War and Marine</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-11-26"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 26,
                                    1874</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">To the Citizen Minister of Foreign
                                Affairs, present:</hi></p>
                        <p>In reply to your communication, dated the 25th of the present month, in
                            which you transcribe to me the communication of the minister of the
                            United States, stating that a commissioner from his Government has
                            arrived at Monterey, for the purpose of effecting, if possible, the
                            return to their reservation in the United States of the rest of the
                            Kickapoo Indians who are still in Mexico, and that he desires the
                            co-operation of the national and State authorities in promoting the
                            success of his mission, I have to state to you that citizen General
                            Fuero has already been advised that, if it is the will of the Kickapoos
                            who may not have entered the State of Durango, as he was previously
                            informed, and are upon the frontier, to return to their reservations in
                            the United States, he place not obstacle or difficulty in the way of
                            their doing so.</p>
                        <p>Independence and liberty.</p>
                        <closer><signed>MEJIA.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>