<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 417.Mr. Foster to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">118</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-02-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107724"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Protestants</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-02-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-02-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="118"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                <head>No. 417.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-15">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 15, 1875</date>. (Received March
                        1.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 243.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose herewith a copy of a communication
                    dated on the 3d instant, from Mr. Sutter, consul at Acapulco, with its
                    accompaniments, giving an account of events subsequent to the assault to which
                    my Nos. 237 and 241 relate, and of the state of public sentiment in that
                    community. Your attention is directed to the recommendation of the consul, that
                    a United States naval vessel be temporarily stationed at that port. In view of
                    the facts developed in the interview which I had with the Mexican minister on
                    the 11th instant, to which reference is hereinafter made, I respectfully suggest
                    that the presence of an American man-of-war would have a salutary influence upon
                    the community and encourage the local authorities to greater firmness and
                    activity in punishing the assassins. I also inclose a copy of my reply to the
                    communication of the consul, dated February 12.</p>
                <p>On the 11th instant I called upon Mr. Lafragua, minister of foreign affairs, and
                    read to him a translation in Spanish of the greater part of <pb facs="0215"
                        n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/> Mr. Sutter’s communication, as well as a
                    translation of your dispatch, No. 178, of the 14th of January last, in relation
                    to the assassination at Ahualulco, of which latter I left with him a copy.</p>
                <p>After the reading was concluded, Mr. Lafragua said to me that the character of
                    the people in the State of Guerrero made it very difficult for the government to
                    deal properly with the affair at Acapulco; that it was very different from other
                    parts of the republic, such, for instance, as Guanajuato or Puebla, where the
                    laws and authority of the government were respected; but that in the south of
                    Mexico the people were ignorant and fanatical; that the statements of the consul
                    just read, which were confirmatory of the information received by the executive,
                    showed the embarrassment of the authorities; neither the governor nor judges
                    having sufficient power to inflict the full measure of punishment demanded; and
                    that it would require a whole division of the federal army to do it. Mr.
                    Lafragua asked me not to forget the present politico-religious condition of the
                    country, the long struggle which the liberal party had carried on for years
                    against the political power of the Catholic Churchy and that the government was
                    now contending against three hundred years of prejudice and intolerance. He
                    acknowledged the justice of my demand for the punishment of the criminals and
                    for the protection of the lives and property of Americans in Acapulco, and said
                    that the government was doing all it could to secure these ends, and hoped to
                    fully vindicate the law and secure full religious toleration.</p>
                <p>In reference to the judicial proceedings growing out of the Ahualulco affair, the
                    cases were before the federal supreme court on appeal, and not under the control
                    of the executive department of the government; that he (Mr. Lafragua) had three
                    times asked for an early decision, and that he would again address the court
                    upon the subject.</p>
                <p>I answered the minister that I was far from forgetting the peculiar political
                    situation of the country; that I had no disposition to embarrass this government
                    by any factious or unnecessary demands, but was anxious to do all I properly
                    could to strengthen it in its efforts to establish and maintain a liberal
                    republican government, and that in this course I was satisfied I was
                    representing the wishes of my Government; but that these religious massacres, in
                    which American citizens were being murdered, could not be passed over in
                    silence; that I was thoroughly convinced that it was an imperative necessity of
                    the present liberal administration of Mexico, for its own safety and permanence,
                    to repress and punish these outbreaks with a prompt and vigorous use of power 5
                    and that the lives and property of American citizens and companies at Acapulco,
                    according to the report of the consul, confirmed by those of the local
                    authorities, were exposed to the fury of a fanatical community, and it was for
                    his government to decide whether Mexico or the United States would protect
                    them.</p>
                <p>I am just in receipt of a communication from the consul at Acapulco, a copy of
                    which I inclose, from which it will be seen that, up to the 7th instant, the
                    only culprits discovered by the judicial authorities were the two wounded
                    assailants left in possession of the officials, who have since died. Twelve days
                    have elapsed without any arrests, and it appears that the consul’s prediction,
                    that no one would ever be convicted and punished, is in a fair way to be
                    realized.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0216" n="870" xml:id="pg_870"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 243.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Sutter</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate, Acapulco</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 3, 1875</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 27.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt
                        of your communication of January 27th ultimo. I presume that Mr. Skilton has
                        communicated to you the contents of my letters to him of January 27 and 1st
                        instant, Nos. 3, 4, 5.</p>
                    <p>Rev. M. N. Hutchinson left Acapulco on the evening of the 1st instant, per
                        steamer “Montana” for San Francisco, in good health. His servant and his
                        horse I have still here.</p>
                    <p>When I received your communication yesterday I had already paid my respects
                        to the governor, General Alverez. This morning I addressed to him a
                        communication, of which please find inclosed copy, (inclosure 1,) and
                        delivered the same to him personally, before his departure for Coyuga. He
                        requested me to assure you that he would do all in his power to bring the
                        guilty parties to light, and would take measures to prevent a repetition of
                        the massacre, and that in a few days he would return to Acapulco. He
                        expressed already yesterday a hope to be able to discover the instigator
                        (meaning probably the Catholic priest) of the crime, saying that the people,
                        without any instigation, never would have committed so atrocious a murder.
                        At the same time the governor had a fair opportunity yesterday afternoon to
                        judge of the excitement existing among the population. A demonstration was
                        made publicly by a band of, say, eighty women and about the same number of
                        men, who, having assembled at and marched from the church-door, went to
                        accost him while he was taking a walk with some friends, and asked him not
                        to deprive them of the priest, and to banish or exterminate all the
                        Protestants.</p>
                    <p>The governor spoke to the people, who then quietly disbanded: but, in my
                        opinion, this demonstration means as much as the rough words the foreman of
                        the Matricula of the port, on the night of the massacre, addressed to the
                        district judge, Mr. Bonilla; that is, that they would rise armed to attack
                        the federal troops should he dare touch the priest.</p>
                    <p>The State militia is not to be relied on; the parish priest has, in fact,
                        more power than the governor, who would render himself very unpopular should
                        he actively interfere.</p>
                    <p>These opinions of course cannot be expressed here with safety. The district
                        judge, whom I visited to-day and handed the communication already mentioned,
                        partakes of and concurs in them, however; but candidly confesses that he can
                        do absolutely nothing if the supreme government does not station here a
                        battalion of federal troops, for which he says he has asked already. Nothing
                        to inculpate any person has been elucidated, and I fear ever will be
                        discovered.</p>
                    <p>Threats against the Freemasons have also been uttered already; still it would
                        be impossible to prove it.</p>
                    <p>A United States vessel of war should remain stationed here for some time. In
                        case of a rising, the office of the Pacific Mail Steamship Company, where
                        everybody knows there is a good supply of money, and the bazar, the
                        mercantile establishment of Mr. A. Dempwolff, who, among his stock of about
                        $40,000, has rifles, guns, pistols, knives, powder, lead, &amp;c., would be
                        attacked very quick, together with the United States consulate, and the
                        large German importing house of Oetling, Gericke &amp; Co., and our lives
                        just then might be in danger.</p>
                    <p>As far as the legal technicalities of the case are concerned, it appears that
                        Mr. Procopio Diaz, the chief of the Protestants hero, probably for the
                        reason of his being the secretary of the prefect of the district, carelessly
                        neglected to give to the prefect due notice in writing of the establishment
                        of the Protestant place of worship. All what Mr. Hutchinson says on the
                        subject I have communicated to the district judge, and in all the
                        proceedings so far, the place of the massacre has been called “el templo
                        protestante,” whereby virtually the right to the name is acknowledged, and
                        the existence of the congregation granted.</p>
                    <p>In closures numbers 2 and 3 are the letters of Mr. Hutchinson on the
                        subject.</p>
                    <p>It is now frequently said, in extenuation of the massacre, that the
                        Protestants have often insulted the Catholics and the priest personally. I
                        doubt it, and as far as Mr. Hutchinson is concerned, I deny it <hi
                            rend="italic">in toto.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The antecedents of the priest are well known. He always has been, and is now,
                        one of the most fanatical, pure-blooded Indian priests, who already in 1859
                        was found at the head of a revolution in Costa Chica, and when taken
                        prisoner by General Don Juan Alvarez, sent to the fort of Acapulco, and
                        sentenced to be shot. At the intercession of the people, however, General
                        Alvarez pardoned him with the condition that he must leave the country. I
                        was then in the office of the Pacific Mail Steamship Company, and procured
                        him a free cabin-passage to San Francisco, whence he returned during the
                        empire. You will perceive that I know Mr. Justo Pastor Nava well.</p>
                    <pb facs="0217" n="871" xml:id="pg_871"/>
                    <p>Another incident which shows the situation of Acapulco is this: last Sunday
                        two of the aggressors wounded were given up by the surgeons, and expressed a
                        desire to receive the sacraments of the Catholic Church, which naturally was
                        granted to them, but the authorities feared that, should the priest be seen
                        entering the prison, people might believe he had been arrested and might
                        rise at once against the garrison, consequently, as a measure of prevention,
                        the wounded men had to be carried to the church, and after the ceremony back
                        to the prison again. One has since died, the other one is still lingering;
                        he says he was merely a spectator, looking on.</p>
                    <p>Should anything important take place I shall not fail to advice you of it,
                        either by telegraph or by mail, as the case may require it, and remain,</p>
                    <p>Your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN A. SUTTER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jr.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in 1 in No. 243.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Sutter</persName> to <gloss
                                type="to">Governor Alvarez and the district judge</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-03">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">February</hi> 3</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In obedience to instructions received
                        yesterday from Hon. John W. Foster, envoy extraordinary and minister
                        plenipotentiary of the United States of America in Mexico, I have the honor
                        to request you, in his name, to promptly take the necessary measures within
                        your power to procure the speedy punishment, according to the law, of the
                        instigators and perpetrators of the atrocious massacre of Protestants, which
                        took place on the evening of Tuesday, January 26th ultimo, whilst they were
                        peaceably assembled in their chapel for the purpose of religious
                        worship.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN A. SUTTER,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">J. W. Foster</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of
                                the United States of America, Mexico.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in 1 in No. 243.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hutchinson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Suite</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">On Board the Ida Lilly</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-01-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 30, 1875</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Friend Sutter</hi>: I am surprised to hear that Don
                        Procopio Diaz did not give the proper notice respecting the place of
                        worship. He came with Don Catarino Franco to speak of it, and it was
                        understood that they should go at once and give the required notice, both
                        that we were holding services in the house of Don Procopio, for the time
                        being, and that San José had been taken for the same purpose, &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>I was told that this notice had been given. I am sure the authorities took
                        notice of this to the extent of putting another lamp at the upper corner of
                        the church. I was therewith the chief of police in person to indicate what
                        seemed to us the proper place to locate it. It was one of the first things I
                        called attention to when I came, and, from what I saw and learned, concluded
                        that the proper parties had given the necessary notice to the proper
                        authorities. I was also told that there would be nine soldiers in readiness,
                        &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>The spirit of the law was practically complied with, I am confident. I am
                        very sorry it was not to the very letter. * * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>Yours, most cordially,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>M. N. HUTCHINSON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in 1 in No. 243.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hutchinson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Sutter</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">On Board the “Ida Lilly,”</hi>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Off Acapulco</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 1, 1875</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Friend Sutter</hi>: * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>I am very sorry about the notice not being sufficiently formal. My relation
                        to the church being a general one, it seemed more proper for those who had
                        been in charge of <pb facs="0218" n="872" xml:id="pg_872"/> the congregation
                        for a year to give the notice in their name; hut I said, “If more is needed,
                        rind out exactly what, and we will give it.” It certainly is the duty of the
                        officer to whom this should be reported to indicate the legal form of the
                        notice. It is a strong point, it seems to me, that the authorities did
                        actually take notice of Don Procopio’s notice. I was in his house when the
                        authorities (I speak of the authorities in general, not knowing each one in
                        particular) sent to know where we thought another lamp would afford the most
                        protection. We went, according to appointment, at 4 o’clock p.m. the same
                        day, to consult, and the lamp was placed at the upper corner of the church,
                        so as to give light behind and in front of the church. The chief of police
                        was there in person. This was, it seems to me, a virtual acknowledgment of
                        notice, and I did not think there was any question. If more details,
                        &amp;c., were required to fill up his report to be forwarded to the
                        government, these could have been given at any time. I am not sure that all
                        such details as a full report would call for are absolutely necessary before
                        protection can be claimed under the law. I believe the case would stand the
                        test of law for the purposes of protection. Of course it is to be regretted
                        that there is any question about it. A contract may not be drawn in exact
                        legal form, but if, with a knowledge of this, work is done or payments made,
                        the contract takes a binding form, and so it seems to me in this case. The
                        authorities took notice of pur opening a new place of worship by placing
                        another lamp for special protection.</p>
                    <p>Yours, very truly,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>M. N. HUTCHINSON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 243.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Sutter</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 12, 1875</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I thank you for your full and interesting
                        report of the assault upon the Protestant church at Acapulco, No. 27, of
                        February 3, with a statement of the subsequent events. I will transmit a
                        copy of it to the Department of State for its information and action. I have
                        called the attention of the government here to the condition of affairs as
                        represented by you, and I am assured that the federal government is doing
                        and will do all within its power to punish the criminals and preserve the
                        peace.</p>
                    <p>Permit me to call your attention to a point which does not sufficiently
                        appear in your letter to the governor. You will notice that in my letter I
                        referred only to the murder of Americans, and not to Protestants in general.
                        While we desire to see full enjoyment of religious worship for all, we can
                        only officially interfere in behalf of American citizens.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Skilton has not yet returned.</p>
                    <p>Very truly,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John A. Sutter</hi>, Esq.,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Consul, Acapulco.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No. 243.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Sutter</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Acapulco</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 7</hi>, 1875</date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 28.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Confirming to you my communication (No. 27)
                        of the 3d instant, I have the honor to report to-day that on the afternoon
                        of the 3d, just as General Alvarez was ready to leave, a second
                        demonstration, similar to the one of the day before, was made; otherwise the
                        town is quiet, although in case of need I fear the State militia now here
                        could not be relied on, and although menaces against the lives of the
                        wounded Protestants, who are being taken care of together in the house of
                        Mr. Procopio Diaz and guarded every night by some twenty resolute and
                        well-armed brethren, (Mr. Hutchinson’s servant among them,) are repeatedly
                        and openly uttered. The wounded men, I am happy to say, are all out of
                        danger.</p>
                    <p>Yesterday afternoon I called upon the district judge to inquire if anything
                        relative to the massacre had been elicited. He replied that everything
                        remained <hi rend="italic">in statu quo</hi>, <pb facs="0219" n="873"
                            xml:id="pg_873"/> the only culprits discovered so far being, singularly
                        enough, the two aggressors who lost their lives in the affray, the second
                        one having died on last Sunday, the 31st, from a pistol-shot received during
                        the affray of the 26th.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">JOHN A. SUTTEE, Jr.</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">John W. Foster</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of
                                the United States of America, Mexico.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
