<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 422.Mr. Foster to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">123</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-03-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-03-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-03-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-03-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="123"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d123">
                <head>No. 422.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Foster</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation o the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Mexico</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-03-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 23, 1875</date>. (Received July
                        22.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 265.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your dispatches numbered 190, 192, and 197, relating to the assault upon the
                    Protestant church at Acapulco and the murder of the American citizen, Henry
                    Morris. I shall endeavor to conform my action to the views expressed
                    therein.</p>
                <p>You will allow me respectfully to suggest that, referring to your dispatch No.
                    192, while Morris did not come to his death “by an act of a person in
                    authority,” his murder might have been prevented had not the authorities omitted
                    the precautions necessary to protect the church against the assault, which I am
                    informed was premeditated and had been repeatedly threatened. I have every
                    reason to believe that no judicial punishment will ever follow this murder, and
                    if the government is not pecuniarily responsible, it is probable the crime will
                    remain entirely unavenged.</p>
                <p>The consul at Acapulco informs me that nothing has been done toward the arrest or
                    punishment of the criminals since my last dispatch on the subject.</p>
                <p>I called upon Mr. Lafragua today, to inquire if the government had any further
                    information upon the subject, and learned from him that it had not. In answer to
                    my inquiry, he also stated that no federal troops had been sent to Acapulco, and
                    no further measures had been taken by the government. Our conversation was quite
                    lengthy, and on my part as decided as I felt justified in making it, but it
                    developed no facts of importance beyond those stated in my previous dispatches.
                    Mr. Lafragua stated to me that the reason why no troops had been sent to
                    Acapulco was because they could not, in the present grave condition of the
                    country, be spared from this city and the central portion of the republic. He
                    again reiterated the determination of the government to do all that was possible
                    to secure the punishment of the murderers of Morris.</p>
                <p>I did not in the conversation hesitate to express my disappointment at and
                    disapproval of the inaction and apparent indifference o the governor of Guerrero
                    and the local authorities of Acapulco, and my well-grounded fear that no
                    adequate punishment would be inflicted upon the criminals.</p>
                <p>The consul at Acapulco has informed me of the arrival at Acapulco of the United
                    States steamer Saranac.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JOHN W. FOSTER.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
