<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 428.Mr. Fish
                            to Mr. Foster.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-04-13T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558" lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-04-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="129" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                <head>No. 428.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Foster</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department
                                    of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-04-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 13,
                            1875</date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 213.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I transmit a copy of a letter of the 7th
                        instant and its inclosure addressed to this Department by the Secretary of
                        War upon the subject <pb facs="0244" n="898" xml:id="pg_898"/> of
                        depredations in Texas by Indians from Mexico. The facts stated in the
                        communication tend to confirm the impressions of the Department which have
                        already been conveyed to you as to the impolicy on the part of the Mexican
                        government to keep within their territory Indians properly belonging to the
                        United States.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HAMILTON FISH.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 213.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Belknap</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">War
                                        Department</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington
                                    City</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-04-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 7, 1875</date>.
                                (Received April 9.)</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit, for your
                            information, copy of report of the commanding officer of Fort Duncan,
                            Texas, of depredations supposed to have been committed by Mexican
                            Indians, including the report of a scout, made by Lieutenant Markley
                            Twenty-fourth Infantry, and map of the country traveled over.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. W. BELKNAP.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure 1 in No. 213.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Lieut. Col. <persName type="from">Shafter</persName>
                                to <gloss type="to">Assistant Adjutant-General</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Headquarters Fort Duncan, Texas</hi>
                            </placeName>,<lb/>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 22, 1875</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I very respectfully report, for the
                            information of the brigadier-general commanding the department, that a
                            party of Indians, live to seven in number, have been recently raiding
                            within a few miles of this post.</p>
                    <p>On the 14th instant, they attacked a couple of herders near the stone
                            ranch between this post and Fort Clark, capturing several horses. On the
                            16th inst., near the Pendencia road, and about fifteen miles east of
                            here, they attacked a Mr Vivien, citizen, wounding him in the hand;
                            after following him some distance, he succeeded in frightening them away
                            by shouting for help. About a mile from where the Indians left Vivien,
                            they came across a Mexican with an ox-cart, and attacked him. Finding
                            that he was unarmed, they went up to the cart, pulled him out, and made
                            him take off his clothes, kneel down, and then shot him through the body
                            with an arrow. It is reported by Mexicans that on the 18th, near the
                            mouth of the San Pedro, about fifty miles below this post, just as the
                            Indians were about to cross into Mexico, they were attacked by two
                            Mexicans their horses taken from them, and one little boy they had
                            captured from a ranch near by retaken. In the fight, one of the
                            Mexicans, a resident of Presidio Rio Grande, was killed. The Mexican who
                            was shot through the body with an arrow is now in post-hospital. He
                            states that the Indians spoke Mexican fluently, and that he knows them
                            to be Mexican Indians. From his description and that given by Mr.
                            Vivien, and the appearance of the arrows, those best able to judge of
                            such matters pronounce them to be Lipans or Mescaleros. The Mexican
                            troops recently on this frontier have all been withdrawn to Monclora. I
                            have not, therefore, reported the raid to the authorities on the other
                            side. It is reported that a large camp of Lipans and Mescaleros is now
                            some distance above Ramolino, and it is well known that Mexicans from
                            the other side are constantly trading with them.</p>
                    <p>The first alcalde of Piedras Negras recently came from their camp with a
                            number of horses which he had gotten from them. Lieutenant Markley,
                            Twenty-fourth Infantry, with two Seminoles, were sent out in pursuit of
                            the Indians, but too late to accomplish anything. His report accompanies
                            this letter.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. R. SHAFTER,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Lieut. Col.
                                    Twenty-fourth Infantry, Commanding.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0245" n="899" xml:id="pg_899"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure 2 in No. 213.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant <persName type="from">Markley</persName>
                                to the <gloss type="to">Post-Adjutant</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Fort
                                        Duncan, Texas</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-02-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 22,
                                    1875</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Post-Adjutant</hi>:</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to make the following
                            report of a scout: On the forenoon of Thursday, February 18, 1875, I was
                            ordered by the lieutenant-colonel commanding to take my detachment of
                            Seminole negro scouts and five days’ rations, and proceed to the
                            Pendencia, where Indians had appeared, and then use my judgment. I
                            arrived with ten men at Ferry’s ranch, on the Pendencia, that night
                            about 11 o’clock, and next morning consulted with Mr. Ferry, an
                            intelligent man, as to what was best to be done. The result was that I
                            thought they were Mexicans, or Mexicans and Indians, from the
                            neighboring districts of Mexico; so I determined to follow the trail,
                            though sixty hours old, so as to be able to report upon it. The Indians
                            had on Thursday evening, 16th, attacked a Mexican, driving a cart, on
                            the road that I came, about fifteen miles back. I returned to that spot,
                            took up the trail of seven horses leading about south. Owing to the soft
                            ground and the frequent scattering of the Indians I was two days getting
                            to the Rio Grande, about forty-five miles, near Pegauche. From the
                            articles dropped by them I then believed them to be Indians, not
                            Mexicans, and four men from the ranch at that place, known to my men,
                            informed me that they had a fight with these same Indians, drove them
                            off, and they had gone down the river about thirty-five miles to
                            Refugio, when they had a fight with the people there, killing one
                            Mexican, and then had gone off eastward into Texas. The next morning the
                            trail would be four days old. My judgment was that I might as well
                            return to the post, which I did on Sunday, February 21, (thirty
                            miles.)</p>
                    <p>The Indians abandoned and dropped on their trail a pony and new Mexican
                            saddle-tree, (brought in by me,) and pieces of United States blue kersey
                            clothing, new stockings, and new boots, with legs cut off, and a filthy
                            shirt, sewed with sinews, (mentioned as possible clues to their
                            recognition.)</p>
                    <p>I inclose a map of the country traveled over by me.</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>A. C. MARKLEY,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">First Lieutenant
                                    Twenty-fourth Infantry</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Commanding
                                    Detachment Seminole Negro Scouts.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
