<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 336.Mr. Bassett to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-10-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-10-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="32"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                <head>No. 336.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bassett</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Port au Prince</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-10-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 12, 1875</date>. (Received October
                        29.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 397.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have read with especial interest and attention
                    the Department’s dispatch numbered 236, of the 26th of August last, together
                    with its four inclosures covering correspondence between the Department and Mr.
                    Preston, the Haytian minister at Washington, and I have to thank you very
                    sincerely for the virtual acceptance which that dispatch gives of the views
                    advanced in my Nos. 383 and 389.</p>
                <p>There are, however, one or two points in the said dispatch and inclosures which
                    may, with your permission, befit a word of observation from me. And first of
                    all, it may be due to myself to say that I really had no partiality for Boisrond
                    Canal, and that no motive of personal <pb facs="0078" n="732" xml:id="pg_732"/>
                    preference or friendship for him in any way whatever, as far as I can judge,
                    influenced my action in his case. This fact is in substance stated in that
                    portion of my No. 364, of the 8th of May last, in which is detailed the entrance
                    of Boisrond Canal and two of his followers into my house on the morning of the
                    3d of that month. It is due to General Canal to remark, however, that I now feel
                    justified in all that is said of him in my Nos. 364 and 365, of the 8th and 19th
                    of May, 1875. And in the next place, I may remark, what I suppose is now not
                    unknown to you, that that person was not tried or sentenced previously to his
                    seeking asylum under our flag.</p>
                <p>I must not fail to express my grateful appreciation of the strong and efficient
                    views conveyed to Mr. Preston in Mr. Cadwalader’s note of August 6, 1875, to
                    that gentleman. The annoyances and dangers to which I and my family were
                    subjected by the soldiers stationed under government orders all around my
                    premises here were most outrageous, nay, almost inconceivable. (See my No. 384,
                    of July 22, 1875, and its inclosure H.) But it is a source of very great
                    satisfaction to us, and, if it be not unbecoming in me to say so, highly
                    creditable to our Government that, as early as the 6th of August last, the
                    Department squarely informed the Haytian minister at Washington that it was then
                    expected that those annoyances should at once be discontinued; that if this
                    “expectation should be disappointed, it will (would) be regarded as an
                    unfriendly proceeding on the part of the Haytian government,” and that in
                    consequence of the demonstrations adverted to (the surrounding of my premises by
                    soldiers) the Secretary of the Navy would be requested to order a United States
                    man-of-war to Port au Prince. Indeed I hardly know how adequately to express my
                    gratification at this strong but, under the circumstances, exceedingly befitting
                    position. This is, in my opinion, full of justice and full of credit to our
                    flag. I do not wish to be understood as alluding to any other course that might
                    or might not have been adopted, when I say that I think this ground taken in Mr.
                    Cadwalader’s note will do much to uphold and maintain the prestige and dignity
                    of our flag on these seas and before the world.</p>
                <p>I shall avail myself of an early opportunity to revert to statements advanced in
                    the correspondence covered by Department’s No. 236<note n="*" xml:id="d32fn1">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante.</hi>
                    </note> relative to the right of asylum.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>EBENEZER D. BASSETT.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
