<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-05-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-05-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="338" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d338">
                        <head>No. 630.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Goodenow</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-05-07"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 7, 1875</date>.
                                (Received June 1.)</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 4.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Herewith T have the honor to transmit a
                            copy of a communication addressed to Mr. Boker by the American
                            missionaries and teachers in Robert College, residing here, just before
                            his departure from Constantinople. Mr. Boker expressed his
                            acknowledgments to the deputation who presented the communication in
                            suitable terms.</p>
                        <p>As an evidence of the very high esteem in which Mr. Boker was held by his
                            colleagues, as well as by the public in Constantinople, I may mention
                            the fact that the English, French, Russian, and Austrian ambassadors and
                            the Persian minister took leave of him on board the steamer.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>J. H. GOODENOW.</signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 4.]</seg></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American
                                        missionaries</gloss> to Mr. <persName type="to">Boker</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Constantinople</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-05-01"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 1, 1875</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Sir</hi>: As American citizens residing in
                                Turkey, we desire to express to you our appreciation of the uniform
                                courtesy and kindness which have marked all your intercourse with us
                                during the period in which you have so ably represented our
                                Government at the Sublime Porte.</p>
                            <p>We are sensible, to some degree at least, of the embarrassments of
                                your position, and the difficulties which you have had to encounter
                                in the performance of your duty in defending the rights of American
                                citizens residing within the bounds of the Ottoman Empire. You have
                                frequently had to meet with vexatious delays, postponements, and
                                prevarications, complicated, also, in some cases by restrictive
                                instructions from home; and we feel that we are doing but simple
                                justice to acknowledge our indebtedness for efforts which, even when
                                not successful, were earnest and well directed, and which, in so
                                many instances, have gained the results that were sought. The honor
                                of the American name and the dignity of the American legation have
                                hot suffered at your hands.</p>
                            <p>Permit us to assure you that in leaving this post for one of higher
                                diplomatic rank, you bear with you our sincere congratulations,
                                together with our best wishes for your personal welfare and your
                                official success.</p>
                            <p>We remain, your sincere friends and well-wishers,</p>
                            <closer><signed>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>ALBERT A. LONG.</item>
                                        <item>GEO. W. WOOD.</item>
                                        <item>EDWIN E. BLISS.</item>
                                        <item>SANFORD RICHARDSON.</item>
                                        <item>T. R. GREENE.</item>
                                        <item>HENRY O. DWIGHT.</item>
                                        <item>LEWIS R. WEBER.</item>
                                        <item>GEORGE WASHBURN.</item>
                                        <item>EDWIN A. GROSVENOR.</item>
                                        <item>GEO. T. HERRICK.</item>
                                        <item>EDWIN M. BLISS.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Geo. H. Boker</hi>.</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>