<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 340.Mr. Fish to Mr. Preston.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d36</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">36</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-06-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-06-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-06-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-06-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="36"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d36">
                <head>No. 340.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Fish</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Preston</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-06-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 29, 1875</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The undersigned, Secretary of State of the United States, has the honor to
                    acknowledge the receipt of the note of the 25th instant addressed to this
                    Department by Mr. Preston, the minister plenipotentiary of Hayti. It refers to a
                    recent conversation between him and the uni dersigned upon the subject of
                    certain Haytians to whom Mr. Bassett, the United States minister at Port au
                    Prince, had granted an asylum in his legation. As a result of that conference an
                    instruction was at once addressed by this Department to Mr. Bassett, on grounds
                    which were orally indicated by the undersigned to Mr. Preston. Too short a time,
                    however, has since elapsed for Mr. Bassett to have carried those instructions
                    into effect and to have reported to this Department upon the subject.</p>
                <p>The undersigned acknowledges that it is desirable that the question, which has
                    been raised by the course of Mr. Bassett, should be promptly and satisfactorily
                    settled.</p>
                <p>The undersigned is, however, not a little surprised at that part of Mr. Preston’s
                    note in which he represents that the undersigned had <pb facs="0085" n="739"
                        xml:id="pg_739"/> given him assurances that no United States men-of-war
                    would be ordered into Haytian waters. The undersigned is sure that he neither
                    made any such promise nor used words which could fairly be construed as a pledge
                    of the kind. Pursuant to general orders, naval vessels of the United States
                    sometimes touch at ports where the lives and property of citizens may be
                    supposed to be in peril. If any have recently visited the harbors of Hayti, the
                    undersigned is not aware that they have been specially ordered thither.</p>
                <p>This Department will furnish Mr. Bassett with a copy of Mr. Preston’s note, some
                    of the statements in which require explanations which have not yet been
                    received.</p>
                <p>The undersigned avails himself, &amp;c.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HAMILTON FISH.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
