<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 675.Mr. Russell to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d383</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">383</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="383"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d383">
                <head>No. 675.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Russell</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Caracas</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-03-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 6, 1875</date>. (Received March
                        22.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 53.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that the British
                    minister, Mr. Middleton, has requested me to join him and one or more of his
                    colleagues in remonstrating against the Venezuelan law which requires masters of
                    foreign vessels to deposit their papers in the custom-house while in the ports
                    of Venezuela.</p>
                <p>I declined, for the following reasons: 1. I have no right to comply with his
                    request without instructions to do so. 2. The question is one of internal and
                    municipal law, to be settled by each country for itself. 3. No practical
                    inconvenience has arisen from the law, and no complaint has ever been made to me
                    by any United States citizen of its working.</p>
                <p>Courtesy to my colleagues, however, seems to require me to state the facts, and
                    to ask whether the Department desires to give me instructions. The law requires
                    that the vessel’s “roll or register be deposited in the custom-house. (Codiyo de
                    Hacienda, 2d ed., ch. 2, art. 41, clause 6, p. 38.) Our law requires the
                    register to be deposited with the United States consul. (Act of February 28,
                    1803, sect. 2, vol. 2, page 651, United States Statutes.) The United States law
                    now corresponds with that of most maritime nations. The United States law, act
                    of March 3, 1817, vol. 3, p, 362, provides for the deposit of foreign vessels’
                    papers with foreign consuls in the United States, except when the foreign nation
                    does not give the same privilege.</p>
                <p>In former times United States consuls have asked instructions on this subject,
                    and captains have feared that they might incur a penalty by failing to comply
                    with the United States law. Of course such fears were groundless j up to this
                    time no practical trouble has ever arisen <pb facs="0712" n="1366"
                        xml:id="pg_1366"/> under this law, nor is any likely to arise, for there are
                    other means to enforce the obligations of ship-masters besides the consuls power
                    to withhold papers.</p>
                <p>Awaiting instructions, I am, &amp;c.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>THOMAS EUSSELL.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
