<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 345.Mr. Preston to Mr. Cadwalaler.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d41</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">41</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1875-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1875-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccPNaD9EAQIn4zj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="asylum"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2012001331"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Asylum</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="reckOJp7RF2apAIO3" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85004558"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Amnesty</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1875-08-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1875-08-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="41"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d41">
                <head>No. 345.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Preston</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Cadwalaler</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Hayti</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1875-08-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 26, 1875</date>. (Received August
                        26.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The undersigned, envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary of the Republic
                    of Hayti to the Government of the United States, has <pb facs="0089" n="743"
                        xml:id="pg_743"/> the honor to acknowledge the reception of the note of the
                    17th of August, 1875, which the Honorable, Mr. Cadwalajder, Secretary of State
                        <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>, addressed to him.</p>
                <p>In the note of the 14th, to which the Honorable Mr. Cadwalader answered on the
                    17th, the undersigned had said that the opinion of the United States Government
                    relative to the pretended right of asylum was in perfect accord with that of the
                    government of Hayti.</p>
                <p>It seems that these words, <hi rend="italic">the pretended right of asylum</hi>,
                    have been given, in the English translation of bis note, quite a different
                    meaning from that which the undersigned had given them. In fact, the Honorable
                    Mr. Cadwalader is too thoroughly acquainted with the opinion expressed by the
                    most distinguished authors who have written on the law of nations relative to
                    this practice, to be astonished at the undersigned adding a qualificative to the
                    words “right of asylum.” When all the authors who have given utterance to
                    opinions on this question declare that this usage is contrary to the law of
                    nations, and when Phillimore, among others, calls it a monstrous and useless
                    abuse, (see Phillimore, vol. 2, par. 204,) the undersigned thought himself
                    entitled to speak of a pretended right. The undersigned does not think he ought
                    to urge the observations which the Honorable Mr. Cadwalader has made relative to
                    the attitude which the Government of the United States might take in the future
                    concerning the question of the right of asylum. The undersigned, in fact, thinks
                    he understands the liberal and benevolent intentions of the Department of State,
                    and knows how to estimate the political considerations which have dictated the
                    caution which the note betrays. The undersigned now comes to the proposition
                    which the Honorable Mr. Cadwalader made to him, and which had already been
                    submitted by Mr. Bassett to the Haytian government; which was, that Boisrond
                    Canal and other refugees would be handed over to the Haytian government,
                    provided “that it would pledge itself not to punish the refugees in case, after
                    trial, they might be condemned, but that of its own accord it would allow them
                    to leave the country, and, to that end, would give them passports.” “This
                    condition,” added Mr. Cadwalader, “does not indicate the necessity of exercising
                    the bright of mercy, of which Mr. Preston speaks in his note.” The undersigned
                    regrets not being able to accept in the name of his government this proposition,
                    which has already been rejected in Hayti. He does not think he can even
                    recommend it to his government; in fact, it seems tfyat up to this point there
                    has arisen a confusion of ideas concerning this subject, which it is necessary
                    to dissipate. Anterior to the <hi rend="italic">entree</hi> of Boisrond Canal
                    and others at Mr. Bassett’s, a resolution of the President, rendered conformably
                    to the constitution and laws of Hayti, had put Boisrond Canal and others beyond
                    the pale of the law. Here is the text of that document: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Whereas the General Boisrond Canal has answered the legal requisition
                            which has been made on him by the government, by recourse to arms, and
                            in prolonging his criminal resistance he puts himself beyond the pale of
                            the law;</p>
                        <p>Resolution. <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.—General Boisrond Canal
                            and all of his followers are put outside the pale of the law.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.—The execution of the present
                            resolution will depend on the diligence of the secretary of state for
                            general police and the secretary of war.</p>
                        <p>Executed at the National Palace of Port au Prince, the 2d May, 1875.</p>
                        <p>(Signed)</p>
                        <p rend="right">DOMINGUE.</p>
                        <p>By the President:</p>
                        <p>The secretary of states president of the council.</p>
                        <p rend="right">S. RAMEAU.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The undersigned will call attention to the fact that this decree, rendered the
                    2d, was published the same day in Hayti, and that it was not <pb facs="0090"
                        n="744" xml:id="pg_744"/> until the morning of the 3d that Boisrond Canal
                    and others entered armed into the official residence of Mr. Bassett. Besides,
                    the undersigned will call attention to the fact that he is unable to comprehend
                    how the Honorable Mr. Cadwalader explains that it is possible for the President
                    to put individuals at liberty, or to put them in a position to leave the Haytian
                    territory without exercising his pardoning power; in fact, there is in the
                    constitution of Hayti but one article which can even allow the President to act
                    in a circumstance similar to this which occupies us, namely, that which gives
                    him the right to pardon. That article is thus expressed: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The President of Hayti has the right to pardon and that of commuting
                            punishment; the exercise of this right will be regulated by a law. He
                            can also exercise the privilege of granting amnesty only for political
                            delinquencies. (Constitution of Havti of 1874, article 125.)</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The undersigned now passes to another class of ideas, the importance of which he
                    hopes will impress the honorable Secretary of State <hi rend="italic">ad
                        interim</hi>. The undersigned will commence by bringing to his notice the
                    text of a decree of May 1st, executed by the President of Hayti: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Michel Domingue, President of Hayti, considering that the maintenance of
                            the internal peace of the state is one of the most important obligations
                            prescribed by the constitution; considering that this peace, already
                            guaranteed by the wisdom and moderation of the government, is seriously
                            menaced, and that it is of vital importance to take the most pacific
                            measures for preventing, anv bloodshed; whereas the government is
                            convinced of the culpability of some individuals, who are further
                            denounced either as authors of, or accomplices in, the conspiracy which
                            has broken out;</p>
                        <p>By the advice of the council of secretaries of state, considering article
                            124 of the constitution, decrees as follows: <list>
                                <item>Article I. Are banished from the territory of the republic,
                                    the citizens * * *. 4. Nathan Modé. * * * 11. Jean
                                    Alerte.</item>
                                <item>Article II. The secretaries of state for general police and
                                    foreign relations are charged with the execution of the present
                                    decree.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Done at the National Palace of Port au Prince, 1st May, 1875, the
                            seventy-second year of the independence.</p>
                        <p rend="right">DOMINGUE.</p>
                        <p>By the President:</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of State, Vice-President of the
                                Council</hi>,<lb/>S. RAMEAU.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of State for General, Police,
                                &amp;c.</hi>,<lb/>C. HEURTELON.</p>
                        <p rend="right">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of State for Foreign Relations,
                                &amp;c.</hi>,<lb/>EXCELLENT.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The undersigned will call attention to the fact that among the individuals to
                    whom this decree of banishment applies, several were refugees in the different
                    legations, and that <hi rend="italic">Nathan Modé and Jean Alerte</hi>, whose
                    names happen to reappear above, had found an asylum in the official residence of
                    Mr. Bassett. It was from that residence that they were taken to the beach and
                    embarked, and the decree with respect to them <hi rend="italic">was executed by
                        agents of the Haytian authority with the consent and cooperation of Mr.
                        Bassett</hi>. In thus lending his aid to the government of the country to
                    which he is accredited, Mr. Bassett simply conformed to the conduct of his
                    colleagues of the diplomatic corps. In presence of these facts, the undersigned
                    confesses that it is difficult for him to comprehend how the same Mr. Bassett is
                    since pleased to affirm in his official correspondence with the government of
                    Hayti, that he had never, nor would ever render up an individual who had taken
                    refuge or who would take refuge under the protection of his fla. The undersigned
                    thinks he sees in these precedents a solution of the pending difficulty; if the
                    Government of the United States would give instructions to Mr. Bassett that
                    Boisrond Canal and others should be handed over to the competent Haytian
                    authorities, thegovernment of Hayti would pledge itself to commute <pb
                        facs="0091" n="745" xml:id="pg_745"/> the resolution of 2d May last, which
                    puts Boisrond Canal and others outside the pale of the law, to a decree of
                    simple banishment these individuals would be immediately embarked. Such is the
                    proposition which the undersigned thinks he ought to suggest to the honorable
                    Secretary of State <hi rend="italic">ad interim;</hi> and in case he might think
                    it a possible solution of the pending question, the undersigned would recommend
                    it without delay to his government. The undersigned hopes also that, until he
                    would be able to receive, either by mail or telegraph, the definite answer of
                    his government, things would remain in actual <hi rend="italic">statu quo</hi>.
                    The undersigned flatters himself that the honorable Secretary of State <hi
                        rend="italic">ad interim</hi> will see in these propositions a new proof of
                    the friendly spirit and conciliatory intentions which inspire the undersigned
                    with regard to the great Government to which he has the honor of being
                    accredited.</p>
                <p>The undersigned takes advantage of this occasion to renew, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>STEPHEN PRESTON.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
