<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 354.Mr. Marsh to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1875v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">50</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1874-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1874-10-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="protection-of-americans-abroad" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="protection-of-americans-abroad">American citizens abroad</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Women</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028935"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Offenses</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1874-10-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1874-10-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="50"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d50">
                <head>No. 354.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Marsh</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1874-10-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 12, 1874</date>. (Received Nov.
                        4.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 522.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to the personal instructions to the
                    diplomatic agents of the United States, under date of the 15th of August, 1874,
                    section 48, I beg leave to submit some observations respecting the laws of Italy
                    on the subject of the marriage of foreigners in that country, and respecting the
                    practice of citizens of the United States marrying in Italy since the passage of
                    the act of Congress of June 22, 1860, the 31st section of which makes certain
                    provisions in regard to the marriage of American citizens abroad.</p>
                <p>The requirements of the Italian Codice Civile, in regard to marriages between
                    Italian citizens, can seldom be complied with by citizens of the United States,
                    or other foreigners in Italy, and I remember no instance in which any attempt
                    has been made to conform to them by foreigners, except where one of the parties
                    was an Italian citizen.</p>
                <p>In order not to burden this long dispatch with unnecessary manuscript matter, I
                    simply refer to the Codice Civile, which is, no doubt, in the library of the
                    State Department, title V, chap. I, section second, ¶ 55, 57, 60, 62, 63, 64,
                    65; chap. II, ¶ 70, 74, 79, 80, 81; chap. III, entire; chap. V. ¶ 102, 103.</p>
                <p>Paragraphs 102 and 103 are, I believe, the only provisions of the Italian code
                    which relate especially to the marriage of foreigners in Italy, except that by ¶
                    9, of title I, it is declared that “a foreign woman marrying an Italian citizen,
                    acquires citizenship and retains it even as a widow.”</p>
                <p>It will be observed that ¶ 102 refers merely to the capacity of the parties to
                    contract matrimony, and not to the mode of celebration; and that ¶ 103 evidently
                    contemplates the performance of marriage before the civil authorities of Italy,
                    in conformity with the general provisions of the code; but it is proper to
                    observe here, that, though I have never taken the formal opinion of counsel on
                    the subject, in writing, I have been more than once assured by eminent Italian
                    lawyers that any marriage between foreigners in Italy, which would be valid by
                    the laws of their own country, would be recognized as such by the tribunals of
                    Italy.</p>
                <p>I think it proper to draw the attention of the Department to the provision in ¶
                    103 respecting the “declaration of the competent authority” in regard to the
                    absence of impediments to the marriage. What would be regarded as “the competent
                    authority” does not appear from the code. I was once called upon to make such a
                    declaration, in a case where I happened to have personal knowledge of the
                    history of the party. I gave the declaration, but at the same time I informed
                    the party and the civil officer who asked it that I could not vouch for the
                    authority of the legation to issue such a certificate as an official act. It has
                        <pb facs="0102" n="756" xml:id="pg_756"/> very lately, for the first time,
                    come to my knowledge that consuls of the United States in Italy, if not
                    elsewhere, sometimes give, under their official seals, certificates of this sort
                    which are accepted by the civil authorities as a sufficient compliance with the
                    provision in question.</p>
                <p>When the parties to marriages in Italy are both citizens of the United States—a
                    ease of by no means frequent occurrence—they are generally married by some
                    American clergyman who happens to be officiating in a church or congregation in
                    Italy. The consul is requested to attend the ceremony, and his presence in his
                    official capacity, duly certified by him, has been supposed to be a sufficient
                    legal sanction to the marriage. I do not know that it is a point of any
                    importance, but it may not be amiss to say that, so far as I know, no American
                    church or congregation in Italy, except that of the Rev. Mr. Nevin, at Rome, has
                    any corporate or other legally recognizable existence, according to the laws of
                    this country.</p>
                <p>Marriages of American citizens with foreigners in Italy are almost uniformly
                    between American women and Italians, and sometimes French and German men, and I
                    remember but two cases of marriage between male citizens of the United States
                    and foreign women in Italy during my residence in this kingdom.</p>
                <p>In the case of marriages of mixed nationality, I have always been careful to warn
                    the parties, when I have had opportunity to do so, that possibly a marriage
                    which would be recognized as legal by the courts of one country, in cases
                    affecting the rights and liabilities of the party citizen of that country, would
                    not be deemed valid by the tribunals of the other country; and I have never
                    failed to add that I could venture no opinion on questions of this sort, and to
                    advise the parties to take legal counsel on the subject. I have also thought it
                    my duty to inform American women, about to contract marriage with Italian
                    citizens, that, by Italian law, the act of marriage deprives such women of their
                    American nationality, and invests them with that of the husband, and hence Ithat
                    they should inform themselves how far their rights of inheriting, holding, and
                    conveying or transmitting real estate in the United, States might be affected by
                    their marriage abroad.</p>
                <p>With regard to marriages between citizens of the United States in foreign
                    countries, I have always supposed the statute of June 22, 1860, to be an
                    enabling act, and that its purpose was to invest the consul “before” whom such a
                    marriage is celebrated with higher functions than those of a witness as a mere
                    certifying officer. I have construed the statute as designed to facilitate
                    marriages between American citizens abroad, by clothing an officer of the United
                    States with power, if not technically to solemnize them by pronouncing a form of
                    espousal, still to give them a valid sanction by his official presence; and the
                    law seems to me nugatory on any other supposition. So far as the proof of the
                    fact of marriage is concerned, the testimony of any other witness would be as
                    good as that of the consul, and I do not know any principle upon which Congress
                    can be supposed to have intended to give special value to the certificate of a
                    consul to a purely private and unofficial act of third persous, in which, as
                    seems to be supposed by the instructions, he figures in no other character than
                    that ot a simple spectator. In the case of marriages before magistrates or
                    clergymen, authorized by law to perform the ceremony, at least in the United
                    States, the certificate is issued, not by a bystander, official or private, but
                    by the functionary whom the law empowers to give a legally binding sanction to
                    the act. The certificate prescribed by the consular regulations (p. 324, Form
                    No. 80) seems to assume that the consul is a witness and nothing more, for it
                        <pb facs="0103" n="757" xml:id="pg_757"/> requires him to certify, not an
                    act in which he participates, but the celebration by some other person, whom he
                    abjudicates to be “authorized by the laws of to perform such ceremony.” Whether
                    the blank is to be filled with the name of the country where the marriage is
                    solemnized, or with that of the American State of which the parties are
                    citizens, does not in the least appear. And though the consul is treated as
                    having no functions with regard to the marriage itself, he is empowered to
                    pronounce, afterward, a legal decision oh the question, what lay or
                    ecclesiastical officer is authorized by foreign or by State law [as the case may
                    be] to celebrate marriage in a foreign country. Now, on these points the statute
                    is absolutely silent. It says nothing whatever in regard to the form of
                    solemnization, or to the character of the functionary by whom it is to be
                    performed, nor does it require or authorize the consular officer to certify
                    anything beyond the simple fact of the marriage; still less does it empower him
                    to adjudicate on what may be, and in fact, according to some opinions, at this
                    moment is, in Italy, a difficult question of law.</p>
                <p>In Section XLVIII of the new instructions, the Department expresses doubts
                    whether marriage can be legally celebrated at all between citizens of the United
                    States in a foreign country, unless it be solemnized in conformity with the laws
                    of such country. It does not appear whether the Departmentquestions the power of
                    auy government to legislate respecting marriage between its citizens within a
                    foreign territorial jurisdiction; whether it questions the power of the Federal
                    Government, as a government of limited attributions, to legislate on the subject
                    of marriage at all, except as respects the citizens of the District of Columbia;
                    or whether, as a matter of legal construction of the statute, it questions the
                    intention of Congress to provide a mode of celebrating marriages between
                    American citizens abroad.</p>
                <p>With regard to the first point, it may be observed that such doubts are not
                    entertained by the governments of Europe. The British statute (George IV, chap.
                    91) declares marriages between British subjects solemnized abroad by clergymen
                    of the Church of England to be valid; the statute 12 and 13, Victoria, chap. 68,
                    provides that British consuls in foreign countries may “solemnize or allow to be
                    solemnized” such marriages at their consulates; and I am informed that in 1853
                    Lord Clarendon decided that marriages between British subjects, under those
                    acts, could be celebrated, in foreign countries, nowhere but at British
                    consulates, and that the actual presence of the consul was necessary to the
                    validity of the marriage. Marriages between British subjects, however, continue
                    to be solemnized occasionally at the legations, under the principal of
                    exterritoriality. The British statutes prescribe no observance of any of the
                    requirements of the local law of the place of marriage, and in fact such
                    observance would be impossible when the ceremony is solemnized either at the
                    legation or at a consulate. The number of British citizens domiciled in this
                    country is vastly greater than of American, and marriages bet ween them are
                    frequent. In practice, they content themselves with complying with the
                    provisions of their own statute, and observe no formality whatever ordained by
                    the laws of Italy.</p>
                <p>France and Germany have analogous laws, and though I am unable to quote them
                    specifically, I am informed that they require no conformity to any provision of
                    the Italian code in case of the marriage of their citizens in Italy.</p>
                <p>As to the jurisdiction of Congress over the subject, it would be a singular
                    anomaly if the Federal Government, the only government in the Union legally
                    recognized by foreign states and officially known to them, <pb facs="0104"
                        n="758" xml:id="pg_758"/> cannot provide a mode of legalizing all contracts
                    between its citizens while temporarily without the limits of its territorial
                    jurisdiction. Nor does this appear to be the view generally entertained by the
                    Federal Government in regard to its own powers. Not to speak of the authority
                    conferred on consuls in this respect by Congress, § XLIII of the personal
                    instructions of August 15, 1874, empowers secretaries of legation to administer
                    oaths, take depositions, and to perform any notarial act which a notary public
                    is authorized by law to do or to perform, and such acts he is required to attest
                    under the special seal of his secretaryship. No act of Congress is referred to
                    in this paragraph, and if any exists on this subject it has escaped me; but, in
                    either ease, it is not easy to see how the Government of the United States can
                    by law or departmental regulation authorize secretaries of legation or consuls
                    to perform in foreign countries acts necessary to give legal force to contracts
                    as solemn and as weighty in the eye of the law as the celebration of a marriage,
                    unless, it has the power to make regulations on the latter subject also. The
                    performance of notarial acts is a duty everywhere discharged by local officers,
                    but the power of the United States to confer upon its diplomatic and consular
                    officers notarial authority, in respect to acts of American citizens in foreign
                    countries, does not appear to be doubted. Unless, then, marriage is a contract
                    more completely <hi rend="italic">sui generis</hi> than it is now considered to
                    be in countries where English jurisprudence is the basis of legislation, I am
                    unable to perceive why the Federal Government has not as large powers respecting
                    it as respecting any other contracts between its citizens abroad not relating to
                    real estate.</p>
                <p>It appears to me that there is room for serious doubt whether the laws of the
                    several States of the Union have any legal force in relation to the marriage of
                    their citizens when out of the jurisdiction of those States, and, consequently,
                    whether Congress is not the only body which can legislate on the subject. I do
                    not forget that acknowledgments of deeds of lands in the States, executed
                    abroad, taken and certified by consuls, are generally considered as owing their
                    validity not to the position of the consul as a Federal officer, but to the laws
                    of the State, which authorize him to receive and certify such acknowledgments.
                    But in this case the land, the subject-matter, remains always within the
                    territorial jurisdiction of the State, while in the case of a marriage or other
                    personal contract entered into in a foreign country, by persons not at the time
                    amenable to the laws of the State or within reach of process from its tribunals,
                    it is not clear that the laws of the State have any greater applicability than
                    to offenses committed by such persons on foreign soil.</p>
                <p>Whatever doubts may be entertained as to the power of Congress to legislate on
                    this subject at all, except in regard to citizens of the District of Columbia, I
                    cannot find in the language of the statute of June 22, 1860, any room for
                    question as to the intention of the national legislature. The construction which
                    I find myself obliged to give to the law is, that it regards the form and
                    minister of the ceremonial part of the celebration as altogether indifferent, as
                    mere matters of taste and feeling with the parties, and makes the legal and
                    effectual solemnization to consist exclusively in the mutual assent of the
                    parties, solemnly pronounced by them in the presence of the consul in his
                    official capacity, as a special functionary <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi>,
                    precisely as in the case of a marriage before a justice of the peace or other
                    civil magistrate in many of the United States. The consul appears to me to be
                    acting in this case as a notary acts in receivig and certifying an
                    acknowledgment of a deed of law; while the construction given to the statute by
                    form No. 80, treats him as merely a witness to the act, though attesting it by a
                    separate instrument <pb facs="0105" n="759" xml:id="pg_759"/> instead of
                    subscribing the contract in that capacity. If it were the purpose of Congress to
                    make valid a marriage which, perhaps, without its provisions would not be so, I
                    do not know what stronger language it could have used than that actually
                    employed in the statute in question; and, unless it is interpreted as conferring
                    upon the consul the same authority as that which British legislation in the like
                    case and in like terms confers on British consuls, and which the laws of the
                    several American States confer on magistrates and clergymen, I do not perceive
                    that it serves any purpose whatever. For if the presence of the consul does not
                    give validity to the act of the parties in taking each other as man and wife,
                        <hi rend="italic">per verba de presenti</hi>, without the recitation of a
                    matrimonial formula, not alluded to in the statute by a clergyman or magistrate,
                    then his presence has no legal effect at all, inasmuch as it can hardly be
                    contended that a consular opinion on the legal powers of a foreign magistrate,
                    certified in pursuance of a simple administrative regulation of a Department,
                    but neither required nor authorized by the statute, can make legal an act which
                    would be void without such certificate, or that the judgment of a consul would
                    be any evidence at all incase of a doubt as to the authority of the officiating
                    magistrate.</p>
                <p>At the same time the consideration of possible questions of conflicting
                    jurisdiction has led me to advise the parties, in the few cases of marriage
                    beween American citizens in Italy, where I have been consulted, to conform as
                    far as possible to the laws of the State to which they belong, but always to
                    secure the presence of a consular officer at the ceremony.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, I beg pardon for the freedom with which I have discussed this
                    important question. I have gone into it at length, not with the purpose of
                    asking a reconsideration of any of the questions which my official superiors
                    have decided, or even a reply to the arguments which have had weight with
                    myself, but simply as an explanation of the grounds on which I have thought that
                    a marriage in Italy between citizens of the United States, competent to contract
                    matrimony, celebrated by any ceremony whatever, or without any ceremony, but the
                    formally expressed assent of the parties before or in the presence of a consular
                    officer of the United States, is “valid to all intents and purposes.”</p>
                <p>At all events, I shall hereafter strictly conform to the instructions whenever I
                    have occasion to give any advice on the subject.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>GEORGE P. MARSH.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
