<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>161. Transcript of Telephone Conversation Between the Chairman of the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff (Moorer) and the Deputy Secretary of Defense () and the Deputy
                    Secretary of Defense (Clements))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d161</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">161</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-10-12T09:55:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-10-12T09:55:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-10-12T09:55:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-10-12T09:55:00-05:00" n="161"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d161">
                <head>161. Transcript of Telephone Conversation Between the Chairman of the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff (<persName corresp="#p_MT_1">Moorer</persName>) and the Deputy
                    Secretary of Defense (<persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clements</persName>)<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d161fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 218, Records of Admiral <persName
                            corresp="#p_MT_1">Thomas Moorer</persName>, Diary, October 1973. Secret.
                        The original is an entry in <persName corresp="#p_MT_1">Moorer</persName>’s
                        Diary.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-10-12T10:55:00-04:00">October 12, 1973, 10:55 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Omitted here is material unrelated to the Middle East.]</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—I talked to <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Ken
                        Rush</persName> a few minutes ago (are you by yourself)?</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—Yes.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—I also told <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Ken
                        Rush</persName> that I thought that it was wrong for us not to have a <gloss
                        target="#t_WSAG_1">WSAG</gloss> Meeting.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—I do, too, because I just can’t find out
                    anything.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—That’s right and I am in the same position
                    and God dammit, Tom, I don’t like this a bit with Jim and he’s not running the
                        <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and you have certain responsibilities
                    and they are clearly established and in several different directives. And, I
                    also feel that I have certain responsibilities that come right from the
                    President himself and, at the time I took this appointment, God dammit, Tom, I
                    want to know what is going on. And, not only do I want to know what is going on
                    I also feel I have the right of expression, as I know you do and if I make these
                    expressions and they don’t like my ideas that’s fine—but dammit, Tom, I want to
                    express them and that’s the basis on which I came up here!</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—I agree with you. We haven’t had a <gloss
                        target="#t_WSAG_1">WSAG</gloss> Meeting since . . .</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—Monday.<note n="2" xml:id="d161fn2">October
                        8. See <ref target="#d129">Documents 129</ref> and <ref target="#d131"
                            >131</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—And I can’t get, you know, any decision
                    and then yet when something happens they call over here raising hell because
                    they didn’t like it. Yet we never get a chance to talk about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—I told <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Ken
                        Rush</persName> that I wanted to know how he felt about this before I
                    started anything moving or made any inquiries as I have here. And you know,
                    yesterday I called Brent and got them to schedule a <gloss target="#t_WSAG_1"
                        >WSAG</gloss> meeting and the God damned thing got cancelled and I’m going
                    to call Brent again and tell him that what I’d like to do, Tom, is to tell Brent
                    that you and I want a <gloss target="#t_WSAG_1">WSAG</gloss> Meeting today—is
                    that a fair statement?</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—Sure.</p>
                <pb facs="0484" n="449" xml:id="pg_449"/>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—Because I am absolutely going to tell him
                    that it has to happen and that you and I also feel the same way; but, if you
                    don’t, that’s all right too, but I’m going to do it.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—I think it’s crucial to have a <gloss
                        target="#t_WSAG_1">WSAG</gloss> meeting; that way we we can bring everything
                    up-to-date and take a new point of departure here.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—I think that’s absolutely right. We’re
                    entering a critical period here this weekend and, in the next three days, could
                    really be the turning point of what we do and how we do it and in what the
                    Israelis are going to do and I’d like to have a <gloss target="#t_WSAG_1"
                        >WSAG</gloss> so that everybody could express their feelings as to where
                    this thing sits and to know what we are doing.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—I couldn’t agree with you more. I am in
                    the dark.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—One last word, then I am through, I don’t
                    like (and I told Ken and he agrees) I am going to come back in a moment to this,
                    but I don’t like the idea of Jim and <gloss target="#t_HAK_1">HAK</gloss>
                    informally meeting whether it be in the Men’s Room, or the White House, or on a
                    Street Corner and those two people are informally making decisions which affect
                    anything as important as what we are involved in here and that is not right and
                    I don’t like it a damn bit and I’m sure you don’t either.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—No, because we are going to have to
                    testify on this some day and it wouldn’t be good if we had to tell them “like it
                    is.”</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—That’s right and Ken came back and said, “I
                    couldn’t agree with you more. I don’t want <gloss target="#t_HAK_1">HAK</gloss>,
                    on these kind of issues, I don’t want <gloss target="#t_HAK_1">HAK</gloss>
                    speaking for me.” And, I know that and in the same sense that you feel
                    responsible to what you are doing and the charter you have and that you have a
                    responsibility to the President and you don’t want Jim speaking for you. He may
                    be in complete accord with what you agree to but, on the other hand, it may not
                    be true and you don’t know what he is saying and, under these circumstances, we
                    do need to have a meeting. His final point being that, for the protection of the
                    President himself we need to have a meeting. That the President needs to have
                    this documented that there was a meeting and, generally we agreed to do this and
                    this and that. But, on the other hand, if it is not generally agreed, he needs
                    to know about that, too.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—Absolutely and I couldn’t agree with you
                    more.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—I wanted you to know what I am going to
                    do.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—Right. And, sure as hell, what they’ll do
                    is when the thing comes down to a “crunch” that they’ll want us to bail them out
                    by saying, “Yes, we supported that and it was a wonderful thing to do.” When, in
                    fact, we didn’t know a thing about it.</p>
                <pb facs="0485" n="450" xml:id="pg_450"/>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—Exactly right, Tom, and you and I (for one)
                    am overly sensitive to this after having gone through the Menu Exercise<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d161fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWP_1">Clements</persName> is referring to Operation
                        Menu, the secret bombing of North Vietnamese and Viet Cong bases within
                        Cambodia, which was authorized by President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1"
                            >Nixon</persName> in February 1969.</note> and Freedom Deal
                        Exercise.<note n="4" xml:id="d161fn4">In response to reports in late 1971
                        that the North Vietnamese were planning an invasion of the South, President
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> authorized in the spring
                        of 1972 “Operation Freedom Deal,” which called for the renewal of air
                        strikes throughout North Vietnam above the 20th parallel for the first time
                        since 1968.</note> If anything points out that we needed to inform those
                    involved and formalize some of these things, that’s just the kind of deal that
                    shows it.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—Absolutely, I couldn’t agree with you
                    more.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—Ken agrees with everything and he said I’m
                    absolutely right, etc., but then he finally ended up by saying, “Of course, you
                    know what my position is. I can’t say these things to <gloss target="#t_HAK_1"
                        >HAK</gloss>.” Shoot, you know that anyway.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—All right, sure I have been trying and
                    hoping that they’d have one every day now.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—That’s fine, Tom. I’m going to call Brent
                    and tell him again that is the way I feel about it and that we should have a
                        <gloss target="#t_WSAG_1">WSAG</gloss> Meeting this afternoon and, if I have
                    to—in the final analysis—I am going to tell him something else and that is if we
                    don’t have a <gloss target="#t_WSAG_1">WSAG</gloss> that I’m going over to talk
                    to <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Al Haig</persName> and tell him what I think
                    about this in not having a <gloss target="#t_WSAG_1">WSAG</gloss> Meeting and
                    that it is important for the President himself this is absolutely a
                    requirement—we must do this and get it on the record as to where we stand. Tom,
                    how do you feel about that?</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—Good.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—Do you agree with this?</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—I sure do.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—That position is well-taken?</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—I think it’s reasonable, I think logical,
                    and the way to do business.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—That’s fine. I’ll let you know what
                    happens. I am going to come down in a few minutes and see what the board looks
                    like.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_CJCS_1">CJCS</gloss>—Have Janey give me a call and I’ll join
                    you.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_DSD_1">DSD</gloss>—That’ll be fine, thank you, bye.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d161fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MT_1">Moorer</persName> wrote the following note at
                        the end of the transcript: “The events of the last weeks indicate that in a
                        crisis situation the <gloss target="#t_SecState_1">SecState</gloss> finds it
                        almost impossible to also act as Director of the National Security Staff and
                        preside at <gloss target="#t_WSAG_1">WSAG</gloss> meetings.”</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
