<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-02-22T15:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-02-22T15:30:00-05:00" n="23" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d23">
                    <head>23. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d23fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 135, Country Files, Middle
                            East, <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_DS_1">Dinitz</persName> Sensitive Memcons, 1973. Top
                            Secret; Sensitive; Exclusively Eyes Only. The meeting took place in the
                            Military Aide’s office at the White House. Brackets are in the
                            original.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1973-02-22T15:30:00-05:00">February 22, 1973, 3:30–4
                                p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName></item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName></item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_RPW_1">Peter Rodman</persName></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName> talked to me this morning and
                        yesterday. I said to him as to you about the Libyan business . . .<note n="2" xml:id="d23fn2">See <ref target="#d22fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                22</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Basically, it’s a bore
                        to me, unless you have something for me that is not previously known. It is
                        the sort of problem that will go away in a few days.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: I said that to
                            <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName>. I said, “This meeting with
                        Ismail and President is something new. Let’s at our own level distinguish
                        between the basic issues and incidents like this.”</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: What did <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName> want?</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Something on the
                        airplane incident.</p>
                    <p>My people did not follow my advice. They are holding lots of press
                        conferences, with the pilots and so forth, to defend themselves.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s a mistake. It
                        keeps the issue alive.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: I said they were
                        fools. I said to them, the more detail you give the more it becomes clear
                        that more and more people were involved, for a longer time, at a higher
                        level. The basic issue then is a higher-level decision to open fire on a
                        civilian airliner.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Right, why did they do
                        it?</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: They are fools. I
                        told them to pipe down.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: What worries me is if
                        the Arabs learn that at every crisis <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName> goes into his usual pattern, there will be more
                        crises.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: I said to <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName>, let’s talk about the two visits. He
                        said the two visits will be under the shadow of the incident. I said, yes,
                        publicly, but it should not be so on a government-to-government level.
                        Secondly, I asked him what do you have on Ismail? <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName> said there was a report on Ismail’s
                        talks in London<note n="3" xml:id="d23fn3">In telegram 2084 from London,
                            February 22, the Embassy reported that in February 20 discussions with
                            British Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DA_2">Douglas-Home</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> had taken a “very hard line” against an interim
                            agreement or direct negotiations with Israel under U.S. auspices. He
                            seemed uninterested in significant negotiations until the U.S.
                            Government attitude had been brought around from being a 100 percent
                            pro-Israel stance to being disengaged. Ismail said that as long as the
                            United States remained identified with Israel, Egyptian interests would
                            clash with U.S. interests. (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 666, Country Files, Middle
                            East, <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>-Egyptian relations,
                            1973)</note> but he had not read it. I <pb facs="0096" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/> said, come on, Joe. I told him I was suspicious about
                        Ismail’s pressing to come prior to the Prime Minister’s visit.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s not fair to
                        me.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: I asked <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName>, how did <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> manage to insert his own visit before Golda? He said
                        they would like to prevent the President from committing himself to Golda to
                        give us planes.</p>
                    <p>I said to <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName>: what he’ll bring with
                        him in terms of political ideas I don’t know. Will he agree to an interim
                        settlement? Will he agree to an interim if it is linked to an overall
                        settlement? I said I thought he would try to link beginning negotiations
                        with U.S. military assistance to Israel. This is the only reason he would
                        have to insert his visit before Golda. <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName> said “I cannot say you are wrong, I think they
                        will.”</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s a pack of lies.
                        We are right back where we were before. In London <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> was so intransigent that even the
                        British thought there was no hope for any progress.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: He said the same
                        things to <persName corresp="#p_GJN_1">Greene</persName>, too.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That does not exclude
                        that he will give me something. But in London he refused to agree to any
                        direct talks with Israel, he refused any discussion of the interim
                        settlement—only a total settlement. Like in this Yugoslav paper,<note n="4" xml:id="d23fn4">Not identified.</note> it all had to be linked. Even the
                        British felt there was no hope at all for any negotiation.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName> refused to give us any information at
                        all about <persName corresp="#p_GJN_1">Greene</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>—because of the kind of a position
                        that <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> took.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s right.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: I have never heard
                        any Egyptian talk in such a brutal uncompromising way as he talked to
                            <persName corresp="#p_GJN_1">Greene</persName> before he went to
                        Moscow.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: But since he is now
                        dealing on two tracks, it makes sense to keep tough with State and to make
                        any concessions—if there are going to be any concessions—to me. He was
                        totally intransigent with the British. He was even tougher than with the
                        Yugoslav. I can assure you that our report from the British is that he was
                        totally intransigent, and Home concluded that there was no hope whatever,
                        and that there was nothing they could support in the way of any
                        negotiation.</p>
                    <pb facs="0097" n="62" xml:id="pg_62"/>
                    <p>The British know from the <persName corresp="#p_HE_1">Heath</persName> visit
                        that I am seeing <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> alone.<note n="5" xml:id="d23fn5"><persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> met
                            with British Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_HE_1">Edward
                                Heath</persName> February 2, 10:35 a.m.–12:15 p.m. and 4:08
                            p.m.–6:05 p.m. (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, White House Central Files,
                            President’s Daily Diary)</note> So I yesterday asked <persName corresp="#p_CL_1">Cromer</persName> for a special report.</p>
                    <p>I am seeing <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> Sunday and
                            Monday<note n="6" xml:id="d23fn6">February 25 and 26.</note> in a suburb
                        of New York. I will present nothing. I will present no proposal of any kind.
                        My line will be—and this will quickly find out what his line is—that I have
                        absolutely no contribution to make if they continue the pattern that has
                        been going on. I will suggest that if there is nothing new they can continue
                        to talk to State and in the United Nations.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: I think he will
                        stick to the same line.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: What is the line? Let
                        me show you the message he sent to me. [Tab A, Statement made by <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> to Trone in Cairo on February
                            13]<note n="7" xml:id="d23fn7">See <ref target="#d19">Document
                            19</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: That says nothing.
                        That says nothing.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That’s all I know
                        about the subject.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Practically nothing,
                        because it stresses the Egyptian leadership role. This means he has to meet
                        Egyptian national needs as well as the overall Arab world requirements. This
                        is a tough beginning. I am more involved than you are in studying these Arab
                        formulations.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I know. I will tell
                        him that right away.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: The most
                        uncompromising formula was the one <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName> gave to <persName corresp="#p_JG_1">Jarring</persName>
                        in February 1970 [<hi rend="italic">1971</hi>].<note n="8" xml:id="d23fn8">See <ref target="#d10fn3">footnote 3, Document 10</ref>.</note> It
                        cleverly distinguished between an agreement between Israel and Egypt, the
                        essence of which is total withdrawal, but without committing Egypt on the
                        issues that are really necessary for peace. Their basic strategy is to
                        distinguish between the two phases of the struggle—<persName corresp="#p_NGA_1">Nasser</persName> called it land and people.
                        Eliminating the consequences of aggression is one part of it. This is the
                        difference between Syria and Egypt. For Syria the struggle is one protracted
                        war, and there is no distinction between Golan and the rest.</p>
                    <p>And he says it here.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: You mean the three
                        kinds of countries, the confrontation states and the other kinds of
                        states?</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: That’s the way they
                        would like to mobilize their Arab friends.</p>
                    <pb facs="0098" n="63" xml:id="pg_63"/>
                    <p>You see how they lie to the Jordanians.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: And to the Yugoslavs,
                        too. They lied to the Yugoslavs. I have reviewed the record of our contacts.
                        They started it in April, not we.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: I explained that to
                        the Prime Minister.</p>
                    <p>What I meant was, they state their intentions here [<persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_MGI_1">Miskovic</persName> memcon, Tab B].<note n="9" xml:id="d23fn9">Not
                            attached and not found.</note> Their objectives are to weaken the link
                        between the U.S. and Israel. They say there is no possibility of having
                        peace unless after the solution of the armed struggle. After the Israelis
                        withdraw from the territories, then there will be a peace conference. You
                        see these terms “Israeli entity” and “Palestinian entity.” This is very
                        clever use of the concepts you use in Vietnam. It’s what you are accustomed
                        to.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I am accustomed to
                        negotiations on the basis of reality.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Basically they have
                        found a new formula which you used in your press conference; namely, the
                        separation of military and political issues. The military issues will be the
                        territories, and the political issue will be the settlement between Israel
                        and the Palestinians.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: That works in your
                        favor.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: If the people who
                        are going to discuss this with <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>
                        are clever.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: They are not
                        clever.</p>
                    <p>You have a massive problem, in that there is great desire here to achieve
                        another spectacular success.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: I do not know why
                        the Prime Minister allowed the raid into Lebanon.<note n="10" xml:id="d23fn10">On February 21, Israeli troops entered Lebanon to raid
                            what the Israeli Government said were two Arab guerrilla bases.</note>
                        When I was Chief of Staff, whenever we were trying to achieve something from
                        the United States in the political arena, I piped everything down.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: What do you think is
                        the reason for these moves?</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Frankly I think the
                        only motive is <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Dayan</persName>’s desire to
                        prevent a successful visit by the Prime Minister. Because his chances are
                        better if she retires before the election. It is a political year.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: My strategy with
                            <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> will be to say next to
                        nothing, or to speak at such a level of generality that it doesn’t mean
                        anything. <persName corresp="#p_CE_1">Chou En-lai</persName> was asked at a
                        press conference about me and he <pb facs="0099" n="64" xml:id="pg_64"/>
                        said the only man who can talk a half hour to the press without saying
                        anything is <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry Kissinger</persName>. I
                        mentioned this to Chou. He said, no not a half hour, an hour and a half.</p>
                    <p>I will start this way: “I want a serious talk with you, I don’t know
                        anything, I have not dealt with the Middle East lately. I’ve been
                        preoccupied with Vietnam as you know. I have not had a chance to prepare
                        myself adequately. If you think I am a miracle worker, remember that every
                        negotiation I have been involved in took years to complete. The Vietnam
                        negotiations took four years. The <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>
                        negotiations took three years. So there cannot be a quick solution.
                        Secondly, I promise nothing that I cannot deliver, therefore I can promise
                        nothing. Thirdly, from a viewpoint of an outsider, I see no hope whatever in
                        the normal methods—the United Nations, Resolution 242. If you think there is
                        hope in these methods, pursue them through the State Department. If you have
                        something new, I will listen to it.”</p>
                    <p>I will make no proposals to them, no promises. I may make philosophical
                        statements, such as that any settlement in the Middle East will inevitably
                        leave both sides equally unhappy, and that running back and forth trying to
                        trick two sides into an agreement by some procedure only leads to disaster.
                        [Laughter] But as to concrete solutions, I will have nothing to present to
                        them.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: So you will stress
                        these themes: that you are a newcomer, that you are not prepared and that
                        you are not a miracle worker.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Right. First of all, I
                        do not have a plan. I will never propose a plan that I have not discussed
                        with you and have your approval on—since any solution has to have your
                        approval anyway.</p>
                    <p>Take my negotiations with <persName corresp="#p_LDT_1">Le Duc Tho</persName>.
                        First, I controlled all our assets. Here, my position is not as strong as it
                        was when dealing with Vietnam. Secondly, in any time frame, my strategy is
                        totally different from the <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName>
                        strategy. My strategy is to give them just enough to keep them talking but
                        never to give them much until they make a massive move. With <persName corresp="#p_LDT_1">Le Duc Tho</persName> three years were spent in
                        abstract discussion. This summer we discussed possible approaches to a
                        political settlement which I knew were unacceptable—until they dropped the
                        whole idea of a political settlement.</p>
                    <p>Nothing will come out of this meeting unless they come in with a new
                        proposal. And if they do that, I will tell them I will study it. My guess
                        from these papers is that they will not have a new proposal.</p>
                    <p>After this I will leave it that we will stay in touch and see if we should
                        have another meeting.</p>
                    <pb facs="0100" n="65" xml:id="pg_65"/>
                    <p>Contrary to <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName>, I believe I should sell my
                        involvement only in return for something from them. At this meeting I have
                        to let them feel we are taking them seriously; otherwise there would not be
                        enough to fill two hours, let alone two days.</p>
                    <p>I do not know what’s going to happen. I will be seeing you Wednesday<note n="11" xml:id="d23fn11">February 28. They met on February 27; see <ref target="#d31">Document 31</ref>.</note> morning.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Can I see you before
                        then?</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Sure. Maybe Tuesday or
                        Monday afternoon.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Because I would like
                        to get something from you before Wednesday morning, so the Prime Minister
                        and I can consider it.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: I will do it no later
                        than Tuesday. Where will you be, in New York?</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Here in
                        Washington.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: If I get back Monday
                        afternoon, I will talk to you Monday afternoon. If I get back Monday night,
                        I will see you Tuesday.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: She will want to
                        discuss with you after thinking over the meaning of what happened with
                        Ismail.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: On Vietnam, I knew
                        what I wanted. Here I would not know how to speed up the process even if I
                        wanted to. I do not want to speed it up, so you need not worry about
                        something coming out of this meeting.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: There will also be
                        meetings with <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_REL_1">Richardson</persName>. With <persName corresp="#p_REL_1">Richardson</persName> there are three items:
                        self-sufficiency in production, the Phantoms, and reciprocity.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: What is
                        reciprocity?</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Waiving the Buy
                        American Act.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: What do you want to
                        take up with the President?</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: The political issue,
                        and planes and numbers, to get a commitment after 1973 of on-going supplies
                        of planes to Israel. Let us stick to the present policies, maintenance of
                        the balance, until and unless there is a change in the policy of the other
                        side.</p>
                    <p>I hope the production question will get a positive response from <persName corresp="#p_REL_1">Richardson</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: Let me know.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: On production I will
                        let <persName corresp="#p_REL_1">Richardson</persName> be the good guy. For
                        the President, then there would remain only discussion of the political
                        issue and the question of the principle of maintaining the balance.</p>
                    <pb facs="0101" n="66" xml:id="pg_66"/>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: My advice is do not
                        give him a lecture that nothing can be done. Mention the interim settlement,
                        mention the principles you gave to me last January, those five
                        principles.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Yes.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Rush</persName> wanted to cut our credit. It is
                        so stupid. What Israel gets from the United States Government is $300
                        million in credits in the Military Sales Act, out of the total of $400
                        million. We are a cover for the U.S. Government; because of us they get
                        these credits from Congress. It effectively releases $150 million for the
                        United States Government for credits for other countries, mainly Southeast
                        Asia. I tell <persName corresp="#p_RK_1">Rush</persName>, do you want us to
                        tell the Congress the deal we worked out?</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: At the meeting there
                        will be <persName corresp="#p_DS_1">Dinitz</persName>, you and the Prime
                        Minister?</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: Yes.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: On our side it will be
                        me and <persName corresp="#p_RPW_1">Rodman</persName>. One other thing. In
                        China for the first time there was a discussion on the Middle East. Their
                        only interest is keeping the Russians out of the Middle East and their whole
                        strategy is for that. They said they are not meddling. I said, “Yes, but we
                        have one difference, you are against the existence of Israel.” He said, “No,
                        we just raise the moral issue of the Palestinians.” After a long discussion,
                        Chou said that if Israel goes to the 1967 borders, they are prepared to
                        recognize it. “We are against imperialism, not against Israel. In any case,
                        we will do nothing to disturb the situation.”<note n="12" xml:id="d23fn12">See <ref target="frus1969-76v18#d13"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume XVIII, China, 1973–1976,
                                Document 13</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName>: That’s very
                        interesting.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>: It’s a beginning.</p>
                    <p>[From 4:15 to 4:30 Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and
                        the Ambassador conferred privately.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>