<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>26. Memorandum for the President’s Files by the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (Scowcroft))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-02-23T11:22:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-02-23T11:22:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        presence</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recMNSn3ulaoClE2c" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003007715"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Hostages</term>
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recfABRQvTqVuIjoA" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="rec3vXdKC3r5GaUzW" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85119735"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Self-determination</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-02-23T11:22:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-02-23T11:22:00-05:00" n="26"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                <head>26. Memorandum for the President’s Files by the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_1"
                        >Scowcroft</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d26fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 131,
                        Country Files, Middle East, Egypt/Ismail, Vol. III, Feb. 23–26, 1973. Top
                        Secret; Sensitive. The meeting was held in the Oval Office. Brackets are in
                        the original. There is a Presidential tape recording of this meeting ibid.,
                        White House Tapes, Oval Office, Conversation No. 862–10.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-02-23T11:22:00-05:00">February 23, 1973, 11:22 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>The President’s Meeting with <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Hafiz
                            Ismail</persName>, President <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1"
                            >Sadat</persName>’s Adviser for National Security Affairs</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The President</item>
                    <item>Hafiz Ismail, National Security Affairs Adviser to President <persName
                            corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName> of Egypt</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GMH_1">Muhammad Hafiz Ghanim</persName>, Political
                        Advisor to President <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>B/<gloss target="#t_Gen_1">Gen.</gloss>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Brent Scowcroft</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>[<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName> joined toward
                        end of meeting]</item>
                </list>
                <p>The meeting began at 11:22 a.m. During the photo opportunity, the President told
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> that he had visited Egypt
                    three times and had great affection for the Egyptian people. He pointed out that
                    instant peace was only a dream and that permanent peace cannot be assured. What
                    we hope to have as a goal is some movement off the present dead center. We do
                    not know what can come of our discussions but it is important for us to have
                    frank talks and exchange honest opinions. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1"
                        >Ismail</persName> then handed the President a letter from President
                        <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName> [attached]<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d26fn2">Not attached, but printed as <ref target="#d21">Document
                            21</ref>. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> described
                        the message in his memoirs as “the polite phrasing” that “contained a threat
                        backing up a request for an overall settlement,” and noted that <persName
                            corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName> warned that “the situation in our
                        region has deteriorated almost to the point of explosion.” (<hi
                            rend="italic">Years of Upheaval</hi>, p. 213)</note> and said that he
                    brings <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName>’s greetings and the high
                    appreciation of the Government of Egypt and expressed his own honor to be
                    received in the White House. At this point [11:27 a.m.], the press departed.</p>
                <p>The President began the discussion by expressing a personal regret that in his
                    first four years in office, he did not make progress toward normalization of
                    relations with Egypt. He said that he was very fond of the Egyptian people and
                    that the present status was a loss for both sides. Nevertheless, the President
                    understood why it had not been possible to move toward more normal relations and
                    he expressed his understanding of the Egyptian Government’s position and
                    requirements in this regard.</p>
                <pb facs="0108" n="73" xml:id="pg_73"/>
                <p>He then said he wanted Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> to know
                    that we approach these talks with no illusions whatever, and that we do not know
                    what, if anything, can come of our discussions. He said he had made the same
                    comment to King <persName corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName> during his recent
                    visit and would say the same thing to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MG_1"
                        >Meir</persName>. The important thing was to see where we stand to explore
                    the possibilities that there might be some movement which could take place. The
                    President announced as his goal that Egypt and the United States be friends.
                    With this goal in mind, he thought it important to be very candid and to talk
                    frankly with each other.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> responded that his Government
                    appreciated the opportunity for the visit very much and felt that it could be
                    the starting point for a new relationship between the United States and Egypt
                    and, as well, a start on the way to peace in the Middle East. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> said he considered that Egypt’s
                    relationships with the great powers should be balanced and that Egypt wanted
                    good relations with both the Soviet Union and the United States. Egypt sought
                    U.S. friendship and the removal of all barriers to that friendship. He
                    emphasized that Egypt makes its decisions in Cairo and that it was not a
                    satellite of any country and intended to remain that way—and on good terms with
                    all. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> felt that the President’s
                    meeting in Moscow and Egypt’s termination of the Soviet military presence in
                    Egypt provided a basis for Egypt to normalize relations with the U.S. He felt
                    that Egypt was now in a correct position for steps to be taken by the U.S. He
                    observed that for 15 years Egypt and the U.S. had not seen eye to eye. The
                    President interjected that he felt that the decision on the Aswan Dam had been a
                    mistake.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> said that Egypt was proud of
                    its role in the Arab world, that Egypt promoted independence of the Arab States
                    and supported the welfare of the Arab people. This position of leadership had
                    been forced on Egypt as a result of its population size, geographic position,
                    and its ancient culture and tradition. The President interrupted to say that he
                    understood this point very well and that on his first trip to the Middle East in
                    1955, what had impressed him in all the countries that he visited was that most
                    of the teachers were Egyptian. The cultural impact of Egypt throughout the
                    region was profound, and the President wanted Ismail to know that he knew that
                    and respected it. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> responded
                    that Egypt had tens of thousands of teachers, farmers and other professionals
                    and technicians all over the Middle East making a contribution. He felt that the
                    U.S. should encourage such activities because a strong and vigorous Middle East
                    could be a strong, positive partner in the world and not a burden.</p>
                <p>The President said he wanted to speak very candidly and to point out that
                        <persName corresp="#p_NGA_1">Nasser</persName>, who was a strong and good
                    man, was so strong that Egypt’s neighbors feared him and the possibility that he
                    might be ex<pb facs="0109" n="74" xml:id="pg_74"/>porting revolution. The
                    President said he had the feeling that that was no longer the case and that
                    Egypt was not thought of in that way. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GI_1"
                        >Ghanem</persName> agreed with the President, pointing out that Saudi Arabia
                    used to fear that Egypt was exporting revolution but that they now welcomed
                    Egyptian teachers to their land.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> next moved to a discussion of
                    peace in the Middle East. He pointed out that if Egypt were strong, the Middle
                    East was strong, and that if Egypt were weak, the Middle East was weak. Egypt
                    wants peace. It has had now a decade of almost constant military activity, but
                    Egypt cannot accept peace at the expense of its sovereignty, territory, or
                    pride. Egypt will not be humiliated and the Egyptian leadership would take no
                    action for which its children would blame it in the future. Peace, said Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>, must be as just as it is
                    stable. Otherwise, it simply sows the seeds of another war. He said he noted
                    with care the recent U.S. position; the President had declared a decade of
                    peace. The President had brought peace to Vietnam and now was giving priority to
                    the Middle East at the beginning of his second four years. The U.S. is an
                    extremely important factor in the world and no peace in the Middle East is
                    possible without U.S. participation. Time, said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1"
                        >Ismail</persName>, is not on the side of peace, and he pointed out that
                    just two days ago, 110 people (hostages) were shot down in cold blood. He
                    compared this with the Egyptian diplomat in Bangkok who had rescued Israeli
                    hostages at considerable risk.</p>
                <p>The President said that Mr. Ismail had undoubtedly seen his statement on the
                    recent tragedy and observed that no statement was adequate at such a time.<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d26fn3">See <ref target="#d22fn2">footnote 2, Document
                            22</ref>.</note> He said he was very impressed that, despite this
                    tragedy, Mr. Ismail had kept on with his trip. The President felt that showed
                    real statesmanship. Mr. Ismail responded that before starting his recent
                    journeys, the Egyptian leadership had felt that they were in a dangerous stage
                    of confrontation with Israel. There were certain parties not in favor of peace
                    and they would attempt to dynamite any efforts. Egypt was therefore prepared for
                    provocative acts and prepared to continue its efforts.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> next stated that 30 months of
                    ceasefire was no reason for congratulations. The ceasefire was becoming a burden
                    and a strain, and that it was necessary either to break it or to establish
                    peace. He said that Egypt had not been at fault in obstructing peace, and that
                    Egypt had accepted and itself proposed peace initiatives. Israel, he felt, did
                    not want peace because it has not achieved its goals. It wishes to wait another
                    10 years until further immigration and its own efforts enable it to establish
                    its position in the occupied areas. What helps Israel to persist in this po<pb
                        facs="0110" n="75" xml:id="pg_75"/>sition—the President interrupted and said
                    he knew what the rest of the statement was going to be, that it was the support
                    that the U.S. gives to Israel. He urged Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1"
                        >Ismail</persName> to be frank and to openly state that he felt that U.S.
                    support was what made Israel intransigent. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1"
                        >Ismail</persName> responded that Egypt did not understand the U.S. policy
                    of balance of force. This policy permitted Israel to hold on to Egyptian land,
                    and Egypt thought it was not a fair policy. At one time, the Soviet Union was in
                    Egypt, but the Soviet Union has now left and Egypt saw no further genuine motive
                    for its support of Israel. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>
                    said he was not suggesting that the U.S. could stop that support tomorrow, but
                    it was time for the U.S. to begin a shift toward Egypt in the Middle East and to
                    readjust accordingly its relationship with Israel. Otherwise, said Mr. Ismail,
                    how can we move toward our goals?</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> said that Egypt saw a
                    settlement in the Middle East in light of the origins of the conflict. If a
                    settlement was seen in terms solely of the Suez issue, or a small agreement on
                    one or another detailed aspect, there would be no solution. The origin of the
                    conflict is in the Balfour Declaration<note n="4" xml:id="d26fn4">In November
                        1917, the British Government announced in a letter signed by Foreign
                        Secretary Arthur James Balfour that it favored “the establishment in
                        Palestine of a National Home for the Jewish people” and that it would use
                        “its best endeavours to facilitate the achievement of this
                        objective.”</note> and the emergence of two communities in Palestine—the
                    Jewish and the Palestinian communities. This is the core problem which must be
                    solved. Egypt is not a part of this core problem and complete disengagement
                    between Egypt and its neighbors would offer a means to a solution. Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> said he was aware that Israel was not
                    offered by the Arabs a homeland in Palestine but that was not a reality. He felt
                    that Israel’s wave of expansion must be stopped or it would continue to go on
                    and on. If it were possible to disengage parties to the international conflict
                    the Palestinian core problem would be solved on the basis of self-determination
                    between the Jews and Palestinians. Once this fundamental problem is solved it
                    would be possible to recognize new relationships in the area. If Israel would
                    agree to withdraw to its borders, Egypt could agree to safeguards and guarantees
                    and then it would be possible to work out the details of moving toward the
                    resolution of the core issue. If we attempt to reach a settlement by
                    step-to-step actions, said Ismail, we will bog down. We must have a final goal
                    clearly in mind and move firmly and rapidly toward it.</p>
                <p>According to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>, security was much
                    more of a need on the Arab side because of the Zionist objectives of expansion
                    at the expense of the Arabs. As long as Israel has these objectives, there is a
                    serious threat and the Arabs were on the defensive. In illustration of this,
                    Ismail pointed out that within 10 years, his people would all be liquidated in
                        <pb facs="0111" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/> the Gaza area. When Israel would be
                    willing to recognize itself simply as a Middle East country, the Arabs would
                    recognize it as such. But so long as it continued to bring in immigrants and
                    money and to fight for expansion, there was no possibility of any solution. He
                    pointed out that Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MG_1">Meir</persName> had
                    challenged President <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName> to say that
                    he would sign an agreement. She promised that if he would do so, she would put
                    her cards on the table. He did so and there is no response from Mrs. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MG_1">Meir</persName>. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1"
                        >Ismail</persName> pointed out the development of long-range missiles and
                    atomic weapon research going on in Israel. He asked rhetorically if Egypt could
                    rest in peace when a sick member of the Middle East club across the river was
                    doing such things. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> felt that
                    the Arabs had offered all the security measures they could, but that the
                    Israelis have offered none.</p>
                <p>The Israelis tell us to sit down with them and negotiate an agreement, said
                    Ismail. Our response, he said, is that Israel must sit down with the
                    Palestinians and the refugees and resolve that issue. With Egypt, there is
                    nothing to negotiate about with our land occupied. Egypt will negotiate, but not
                    at the expense of its land. He pointed out that if Egypt could get an
                    international commitment to a date of Israeli withdrawal, Egypt would negotiate.
                    Otherwise, however, the talking would be still going on in 1983, with Israel
                    still holding Arab land.</p>
                <p>The time has come, said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>, when
                    the United States and Egypt should start improved relations. Egypt is not
                    hostile to the United States, and he hopes that the U.S. is not hostile to
                    Egypt. He repeated that, because of their actions with respect to the Soviet
                    Union, they are now in a position to be receptive toward movement by the U.S. in
                    the direction of Egypt. It is time, said Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1"
                        >Ismail</persName>, for the U.S. to move toward an even-handed policy in the
                    Middle East—to define objectives, and to tell Israel it is in the interest of
                    all to get along. Ismail said he had no illusions about the prospects but he
                    hoped that his visit would be the point of departure for some new movement.</p>
                <p>At this point, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> entered the
                    discussions. The President noted that the Egyptian position was very firm, and
                    so was that of the Israelis, and that the situation was analogous of the
                    irresistible force meeting the immovable object. He said that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>’s trip had aroused much interest and
                    that the press will tend to believe that this diplomatic activity would bring an
                    early solution. Both sides, said the President, know that is not so. The
                    President said that the U.S. goal is to work for a solution, not to
                    procrastinate, and not to be content to let the situation continue for five to
                    10 years, although it was possible that it could continue that long. The
                    President expressed his concern about the present situation, noting that Egypt
                    and Israel were far apart and the situation was very explosive.</p>
                <pb facs="0112" n="77" xml:id="pg_77"/>
                <p>The President then said he wanted to speak on very sensitive matters and that
                    notes should not be taken. He said he thought discussions with Egypt should move
                    on two tracks—a public track with the State Department,<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d26fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> also met with <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RK_1"
                            >Rush</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName>, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName> on February 23. See
                            <ref target="#d27fn3">footnote 3, Document 27</ref>.</note> and a
                    private track with Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>. If the
                    private track was to produce any benefits, it would be absolutely essential to
                    keep it private. In responding to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1"
                        >Ismail</persName>’s previous statements, the President pointed out that
                    Israel sees a security threat from radical elements in the Arab world and that
                    this threat was, to Israel, a very serious one. As the President sees it, the
                    big issue is between Egyptian sovereignty and Israeli security. The two sides,
                    he felt, were very far apart and their positions were very hard. The President
                    did not think that it was possible to solve the entire Middle East problem all
                    at once and perhaps not at all. He expressed his understanding of Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName>’s point about interim solutions turning
                    into final solutions. The President gave his word that his goal was a permanent
                    settlement, but he reiterated that he did not think it was possible, in view of
                    the gulf between the parties, to reach such a settlement all at once. It may,
                    therefore, be necessary to consider interim steps along the way. He said that
                    perhaps the Egyptians would reject such an approach, but he urged Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> to discuss it with Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> and he stressed that we were
                    committed to a long-range solution to the problem. No possibility should be
                    overlooked in our search for a way to move toward our goal. The President said
                    he hoped that this would be only the first, and not the last, meeting. This
                    should be the beginning of a dialogue, and if nothing concrete emerged, he hoped
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> would not report back to
                        <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName> that the effort had failed.
                    Once again, the President pointed out the sensitivity of the private channel
                    negotiations—they must be kept quiet and private if they were to succeed.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> observed that he and Mr.
                    Ismail would explore all possibilities during their meetings on Sunday and
                        Monday.<note n="6" xml:id="d26fn6">February 25 and 26.</note> Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_IH_1">Ismail</persName> responded that he had received Dr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s note about a possible
                    second meeting in March, and he understood that the exchange must continue for
                    some time.</p>
                <p>The President said he had asked his daughter, Tricia, where she would prefer to
                    go if she could go back to one of the countries she had visited. Her response
                    was that she would like to return to Egypt, and the President said that he would
                    like to visit Egypt during his present term of office. It was, of course,
                    premature to talk of it now, but his statement was an earnest of his good will
                    to improve Egypt-American relations. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_IH_1"
                        >Ismail</persName> observed that with respect to those relations, every <pb
                        facs="0113" n="78" xml:id="pg_78"/> phase exhausts itself and that
                    diplomatic relations will come when the situation is ripe. Egypt would look
                    forward to a visit by the President because that would signify that the Middle
                    East problem was solved. The President responded that such problems are never
                    really solved but that it would mean that the situation was under satisfactory
                    control.</p>
                <p>The meeting concluded at 12:29 p.m.<note n="7" xml:id="d26fn7">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> recalled: “As was his
                        custom, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> expressed himself face
                        to face with Ismail much more elliptically than in his marginal comments to
                        me.” He added: “<persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>, always
                        uncomfortable with detailed negotiation, used my scheduled secret talks with
                        Ismail as a device to avoid a clear-cut reply. Indeed, he pushed a program
                        somewhat at variance from his marginal note to me. To my astonishment, he
                        seemed to favor an interim Suez Canal settlement after all.” (<hi
                            rend="italic">Years of Upheaval</hi>, p. 213)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
