<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>331. Telegram From Secretary of State Kissinger to the President’s Deputy
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs ( to the President’s Deputy Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (Scowcroft))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d331</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">331</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-11-09T03:50:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-11-09T03:50:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recfglDm81FXoMhAJ" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007327"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Ceasefire</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2007010556"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Helicopter</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-11-09T03:50:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-11-09T03:50:00-05:00" n="331"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d331">
                <head>331. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> to the President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d331fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 41, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> Trip Files, <gloss target="#t_HAK_1">HAK</gloss>
                        Trip—Mideast, Islamabad, Peking, Tokyo, Seoul, HAKTO 1–60, Nov. 5–16, 1973.
                        Secret; Sensitive; Immediate.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">En route, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-11-09T08:50:00+00:00">November 9, 1973,
                        0850Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_Hakto_1">Hakto</gloss> 28. Please deliver following report to
                    the President:</p>
                <p>I had an extremely cordial and relaxed two and a half hour meeting with King
                        <persName corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName> in Amman today.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d331fn2">November 8. A memorandum of conversation is ibid., <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Records of <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                            >Henry Kissinger</persName>, 1973–1977, Box 2, NODIS Action Memos
                        1973–1976.</note> He sends you his warmest regards which I reciprocated on
                    your behalf.</p>
                <p>The King explained in some detail the difficult choice he faced in the recent war
                    and spoke with some satisfaction of the way he had avoided the twin dangers of
                    full involvement, on the one hand, and isolation through total
                    non-participation, on the other. He reflected a basic confidence in his position
                    and in the correctness of his policies. At the same time he reiterated many of
                    his old underlying concerns: apprehension about the Soviet position in Iraq,
                    worry that other Arabs will make separate settlements with Israel which leave
                    him out, and suspicion that some Arab leaders may be working for a separate
                    Palestinian state at his expense. He said <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1"
                        >Sadat</persName> had told him the U.S. and Soviets favored this—an idea of
                    which I immediately disabused him.</p>
                <p>The King introduced an interesting new concept with regard to the Palestinian
                    question; instead of an immediate return of the West Bank <pb facs="0955"
                        n="920" xml:id="pg_920"/> to Jordan following Israeli withdrawal, an
                    international presence would be introduced in Gaza and the West Bank. A
                    plebisicite would then be held offering the Palestinians there the choice
                    between independence, federation with Jordan in a United Arab Kingdom, or
                    reintegration into the Hashemite Kingdom. I told him that we had always
                    envisaged the Palestinians remaining a part of Jordan but said that his concept
                    was an interesting one which could be kept in mind as the negotiations
                    proceed.</p>
                <p>I briefed the King fully regarding the proposal I negotiated with <persName
                        corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName> on the ceasefire and prisoner of war
                        question<note n="3" xml:id="d331fn3">See <ref target="#d324">Document
                            324</ref>.</note> (Israeli acceptance had not yet been received at the
                    time I left Amman). I also gave him in some detail our ideas for getting a peace
                    conference started under U.S.–Soviet auspices in early December. I assured him
                    that we were not being taken in by the Soviets and had no secret understandings
                    with them. Rather, we felt that the joint auspices idea offers the least
                    difficult and most manageable approach among the available alternatives.</p>
                <p>In response to my point that the Arabs could not expect help from us in bringing
                    about a settlement while we were subjected to pressure on the oil issue, the
                    King said he fully agreed with me and had said so to other Arab leaders.</p>
                <p>Towards the end of our meeting, the King brought up his need for additional
                    military assistance. I was frank about the Congressional limitations on our
                    ability to be helpful but assured him we would do our best. I was able to convey
                    to him our decision on rapid resupply of his tank losses in the war, which was
                    helpful, but it is clear that he has in mind a more ambitious program and more
                    sophisticated equipment than we have provided Jordan so far. This will be
                    discussed with his military people next month, and I said I would tell the
                    Defense Department to be sympathetic.</p>
                <p>After the meeting the King hosted a small informal [gathering?] laced with humor,
                    anecdotes and further examples of our common strategic approach to the Middle
                    East. I reassured him once again that we would always check with him if and when
                    we talked to the Palestinians. I noted that Jerusalem would probably prove to be
                    the most difficult issue, the Israelis showing no sign of give. The Jordanians
                    underlined again the importance of this question; we both agreed that the city
                    could ideally serve as a bridge between Israelis and Arabs. The King stated that
                    he had good relations with such common friends as Iran and Turkey who share our
                    overall approach to the region.</p>
                <p>Once again it was clear from this visit that the King highly values his
                    relationship with you. He wants to cooperate closely with us to re<pb
                        facs="0956" n="921" xml:id="pg_921"/>inforce our common interests in the
                    area and wants to be sure his policies and actions meet with your approval. I
                    assured him they did.</p>
                <p>The King capped our extremely warm reception by flying me to the airport in his
                    helicopter, and providing us with a fighter escort.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
