<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-11-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-11-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="350" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d350">
                    <head>350. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d350fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 129, Country Files, Middle
                            East, Middle East—1971–72–73–74. Secret; Nodis. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_KDA_1">Korn</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1973-11-21">November 21, 1973</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Meeting Between the Secretary and Syrian <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Permanent Representative <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Haytham Kaylani</persName>, Syrian
                            Permanent Representative to the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss></item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_BD_1">Diya’allah al-Bettal</persName>, Director,
                                <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Department, Syrian Ministry of
                            Foreign Affairs</item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, Secretary
                            of State</item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Joseph J. Sisco</persName>, Assistant
                            Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss></item>
                        <item><persName corresp="#p_KDA_1">David A. Korn</persName>, Country
                            Director, <gloss target="#t_NEA_1">NEA</gloss>/ARN</item>
                        <item>Camille Nowfel, Interpreter</item>
                        <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>I am grateful to you for taking the time to come down here to exchange ideas.
                        I have had an opportunity to talk to leaders of many Arab countries but have
                        not had the pleasure of having discussions with Syrians, other than your
                        Vice Foreign Minister whom I saw a few weeks ago.<note n="2" xml:id="d350fn2">See <ref target="#d310">Document 310</ref>.</note> So I
                        want to tell you what our general thinking is as to how discussions might
                        proceed and first to make clear the general proposi<pb facs="0998" n="963" xml:id="pg_963"/>tion that we are fully prepared to have an exchange of
                        views with Syria as well as with other Arab countries. The only reason we
                        did not propose a visit to Damascus during my last trip was that we thought
                        it might cause embarrassment for you. I want to tell you that I am
                        tentatively thinking now of visiting some Arab capitals again in December. I
                        will be in Europe from about December 9 to 11 and thought I might be in the
                        Middle East from about December 13 to 16. I would be pleased to come to
                        Damascus if your President were able to receive me and so wished.</p>
                    <p>All of your friends have given us advice on how to deal with the Syrians. The
                        only ones who have not advised us on this subject are the Syrians
                        themselves. One of your friends has said that the Syrians are impossible on
                        the first meeting but better during the second. Maybe we had better start
                        with the second. I couldn’t testify to the truth of that, however, because
                        your Vice Foreign Minister was very reasonable, but he did not tell me
                        anything.</p>
                    <p>I assume you have been informed by your Egyptian friends regarding our
                        conversations. Our thinking—and the Egyptians’—was that we should begin a
                        peace conference about the middle of December. We said December 8 or 9, but
                        now it appears that December 18 would be actually the most convenient. In
                        the first phase, the conference would include Syria, Jordan, Israel, Egypt,
                        the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> and maybe the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Secretary
                        General. We also recognize that there are others like the Palestinians and
                        the Lebanese who would have an interest but in the first phase it would
                        concentrate on military issues and there would be no need for Lebanon and
                        the Palestinians to participate at the beginning.</p>
                    <p>We think <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>–Soviet auspices would be the best
                        because if other permanent members attend it is possible the Israelis might
                        not attend. In addition, this procedure would give balance between the two
                        points of view. Also, management of the conference would become impossible
                        if too many are involved.</p>
                    <p>Those are our general views. Did I leave anything out?</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName></p>
                    <p>Did you mention the site?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>Geneva.</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName></p>
                    <p>And the level of participation?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>In the first two days it would be at the Foreign Minister level. After that
                        we would appoint someone of Ambassadorial rank as Permanent
                        Representative.</p>
                    <pb facs="0999" n="964" xml:id="pg_964"/>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>I would like to thank you for your kind and generous reception. Thank you for
                        your kind initiative which makes an exchange of views at the level of the
                        Secretary of State. I shall convey to my government your desire to visit
                        Damascus and to meet with President <persName corresp="#p_AH_1">Asad</persName>.</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>My security people forbid it, I might evoke too much popular feeling.
                        Seriously, I would be delighted to do it.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>You have had no previous dealings with Syria?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>No.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>Your knowledge may be based on what you have been told or read.</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>I have never been in an Arab country before my last trip, and I have the
                        warmest feelings from that experience. By the way, your friends in the Arab
                        world spoke of you with great affection.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>I believe you will bring back the very best remembrances from any visit you
                        might have with Syrian leaders. With your permission I would like to ask a
                        number of questions about what you said regarding the peace conference. You
                        said that in the first phase of the conference military questions will be
                        taken up. What is meant?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>What I have in mind, subject to the views of all the other participants, is
                        the disengagement of military forces from contact and the beginning of the
                        withdrawal process.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>Do I understand this implies taking up the question of Israeli withdrawal
                        from the occupied territories to the lines of June 4, 1967?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>I think we would take up the first stage of that process.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>As far as the participation of the Palestinians in the conference is
                        concerned—I ask inasmuch as you play the key role in organizing it—how can
                        the Palestinians be excluded?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>Since they have no direct military role, they need not take part in the first
                        stage. That does not imply a permanent intention to exclude them.</p>
                    <pb facs="1000" n="965" xml:id="pg_965"/>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>You did mention a number of countries you would like to have take part. Are
                        you in favor of having the permanent members of the Security Council
                        participate?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>Only the Soviet Union and the United States. Otherwise I think the permanent
                        members would have as much contention among themselves as between the Arabs
                        and Israel. If you have all the permanent members you have a guarantee for a
                        stalemate and then the solution will have to take place outside the
                        conference.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>Also I understand that the participation of any state other than the ones you
                        mention is undesirable.</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>What I am telling you is what we have agreed with the Egyptians. This
                        reflects also the views of President <persName corresp="#p_SAA_1">Sadat</persName>. Of course they must speak for themselves but this is
                        my impression. As you know I said publicly today in my press conference that
                        the United States is determined to play a major role and you know as well as
                        I do that the U.S. is the only country that can produce a settlement.<note n="3" xml:id="d350fn3"><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>’s November 21 news conference was devoted almost
                            entirely to the Middle East. Excerpts were printed in <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, November 22, 1973.</note> We will not do
                        it under pressure. We will do it because we think it is necessary for the
                        well being of the Middle East and of the world.</p>
                    <p>A lot of countries that are volunteering advice are in no position to be
                        helpful.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>One last question. It may be rather redundant but I hope you will accept it
                        with your characteristic generosity.</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sisco</persName> doesn’t agree
                        (laughter).</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>Can you assure us that the Palestinians will participate in the conference
                        after the first stage?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>I think some solution will be found to that problem. But this is one of the
                        subjects we should discuss, concerning the appropriate level and how it
                        would be done. It is not a question that we are in principle opposed to, but
                        it is a delicate issue.</p>
                    <pb facs="1001" n="966" xml:id="pg_966"/>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>Do you have any idea how long such a conference will last?</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>That is a good question. If it opens on December 18—I think your government
                        will find in its dealings with us that I am candid—I don’t think there will
                        be any real progress until after the Israeli elections of December 31. The
                        first phase could take place quite quickly; after that we will have to look
                        at things. The big problem is to get momentum going. After all, Israel has
                        never withdrawn from anything.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KH_1">Kaylani</persName></p>
                    <p>Sir, I want to thank you for your revealing answers. You have been very
                        generous. If there is anything else you have to add I would be glad to
                        listen. Otherwise, I would like to tell you that I leave this discussion
                        with an excellent and a very warm impression.</p>
                    <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName></p>
                    <p>You can communicate to your government that we will make a serious effort.
                        All the governments involved need to face up to the problem and to give it a
                            try.<note n="4" xml:id="d350fn4"><persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> also met with <persName corresp="#p_EA_1">Eban</persName> on November 21 to discuss plans for a peace
                            conference. According to a memorandum of conversation prepared by
                                <persName corresp="#p_SHH_2">Stackhouse</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> stated that while he
                            believed the conference would open on either December 17 or 18, he had
                            informed the Egyptians that no progress could be made until after the
                            Israeli elections on December 31. “Even if I had not said this,”
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_EA_1">Eban</persName>, “it is not reasonable to expect
                            progress immediately in an international conference on such a
                            long-standing problem . . . We have made clear to the Arabs that we want
                            them to lift the oil embargo before the peace conference, otherwise we
                            could not be helpful.” <persName corresp="#p_EA_1">Eban</persName>
                            replied that although Israel would participate in a multilateral
                            conference, “We want as much bilateralism as possible in the peace
                            conference. We want to discuss particular problems with those countries
                            directly involved. For example, we want to discuss freedom of navigation
                            in the [Suez] Canal with Egypt, not with Syria.” (National Archives,
                                <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_POL_1">POL</gloss> 7 ISR)</note></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>