<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-11-23T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-11-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="354" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                    <head>354. Backchannel Message From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> to the Ambassador to Jordan
                            (<persName corresp="#p_BLD_1">Brown</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d354fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 137, Country Files, Middle
                            East, Jordan/Rifai, January 3, 1973. Secret; Sensitive; Eyes Only. A
                            note on the message indicates that it was received in the White House
                            Situation Room at 1:40 p.m. on November 23.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-11-23">November 23,
                            1973</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p>Please make an appointment with the King as soon as possible and convey to
                        him the following points:</p>
                    <p>—We recently received a request from the Palestine Liberation Organization to
                        meet with them to hear their views.</p>
                    <p>—In response to this request and through the intermediary of King <persName corresp="#p_HII_1">Hassan II</persName>, we sent an intelligence officer
                        to Rabat to meet with a representative of the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>.<note n="2" xml:id="d354fn2">See <ref target="#d318">Document 318</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>—Our representative was under explicit instructions simply to listen to the
                        presentation of the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> representative and
                        convey the message to us. No proposals of any kind were put forward by the
                        U.S. side.</p>
                    <p>—Our representative did make clear, however, that there were certain
                        fundamental considerations on which U.S. policy toward a Middle East
                        settlement would rest:</p>
                    <p>—We would not consider any settlement which might threaten any vital
                        interests of Jordan.</p>
                    <p>—The special and longstanding bonds of friendship between the United States
                        and Jordan would guide U.S. attitudes toward settlement of the Palestinian
                        problem.</p>
                    <p>—We would not countenance any proposal which envisioned the destruction of
                        Israel.</p>
                    <p>—While nothing of substance was set forth by the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> representative, our impression is that the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss> is probing to ascertain the U.S. attitude
                        toward the Palestinian issue in the peace negotiations.</p>
                    <p>—Assure the King that we will arrive at a position on the Palestinian
                        question only after the closest consultation with him and strictly within
                        the frame-work of our discussions.</p>
                    <p>—The U.S. intends to work closely with Jordan on all aspects of the peace
                        negotiations which lie ahead.</p>
                    <p>—Please thank the King once again on my behalf for the generous hospitality
                        and friendship shown me during my recent visit to Amman.</p>
                    <p>Warm regards.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>