<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>77. Memorandum From Harold H. Saunders of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-07-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-07-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <head>77. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1">Harold H. Saunders</persName>
                    of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d77fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 618, Country Files, Middle
                        East, Jordan, IX, January–October 1973. Secret. Sent for action. All
                        brackets are in the original.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-07-03">July 3, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Aid for Jordan</item>
                </list>
                <p>Your message of June 2 to King <persName corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName>
                    informing him that we could not advance funds before July 1 led to two sharp
                    replies, one from Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zayd
                        Rifai</persName> and one from the King [See Tab A].<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d77fn2">Attached, but not printed. See <ref target="#d68">Document
                            68</ref>.</note> Basically, however, Jordan was in a position to get
                    through June until our July help could be provided.</p>
                <p>Related to the broader issue of aid for Jordan, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> has sent a memorandum [under memo at
                    Tab B]<note n="3" xml:id="d77fn3">Attached, but not printed.</note> to the
                    President recommending that he send a message to King <persName
                        corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName> advising him of the limits of our
                    economic support in the hope of encouraging greater budget discipline in
                    Jordan.</p>
                <p>This memo deals with (1) your replies to Prime Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_RZ_1">Rifai</persName> and to King <persName corresp="#p_HT_2"
                        >Hussein</persName> and (2) whether the President should become involved at
                    this point as Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>
                    recommends.</p>
                <pb facs="0268" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Reply to <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zayd
                        Rifai</persName>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Rifai</persName>, with his manner of
                    overdramatizing, found your message a surprise and shock. He admitted, however,
                    that Jordan could get through the month of June by engaging in a bit of domestic
                    borrowing. His more urgent—but unfounded—concern was that the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> had reneged on commitments made to King
                        <persName corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName> last February.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d77fn4">See <ref target="#d30">Document 30</ref>.</note> He claimed
                    that the $45 million in Supporting Assistance that we plan to provide between
                    July and November is $20 million less than promised, but this is not true.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> aid offer remains exactly as you described
                    it to <persName corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName> in February. All your
                    recent message did was to say that the next payment would come in July rather
                    than June. As you recall, we agreed to give Jordan $55 million in <gloss
                        target="#t_CY_1">CY</gloss> 1973, which includes a $10 million payment made
                    in the first half of <gloss target="#t_CY_1">CY</gloss> 1973. Thus the $45
                    million we promised between July and November is the remainder of that $55
                    million commitment. In addition, you told <persName corresp="#p_HT_2"
                        >Hussein</persName> that we would hold $10 million in reserve on a
                    contingency basis, pending the results of Jordan’s efforts to get support from
                    Saudi Arabia and Kuwait.<note n="5" xml:id="d77fn5">See <ref target="#d39"
                            >Documents 39</ref> and <ref target="#d44">44</ref>.</note> This $10
                    million could either be provided in December 1973 or early in 1974. In either
                    case it would be applied to the 1973 budget deficit. If we provide it in 1973,
                    however, Jordan will receive only $10 million more in the first half of 1974,
                    and Congress seems unlikely to agree to a supplemental appropriation. Thus, we
                    would prefer, if possible, to hold this $10 million until early 1974. There is
                    an element of choice here, however, and if you feel the time has come to release
                    the extra $10 million for payment in December 1973, you could so notify
                        <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Rifai</persName>. State would also have to be
                    told. The main reason for not doing so now is that it is still in our interest
                    and Jordan’s to maximize aid from Saudi Arabia and Kuwait. Also, the tone of
                    these particular messages is unusually shrill, and as a matter of principle it
                    would seem better not to change our position in response—especially when he has
                    misrepresented our commitments.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi> I propose that you send a brief,
                    straight-forward reply to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1"
                        >Rifai</persName>, as follows:</p>
                <p>“Dear Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Rifai</persName>,</p>
                <p>“I would like to reassure you that the commitment made to King <persName
                        corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName> concerning the amount of aid for Jordan
                    has not changed. Unfortunately, we were not able to advance funds before July 1
                    as we had hoped to do, but the total figure for Jordan in 1973 will not be
                    affected. The July installment is now being prepared. Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_BLD_1">Brown</persName> can <pb facs="0269" n="234"
                        xml:id="pg_234"/> clear up any misunderstandings that may remain on
                    accounting procedures. As you know, our funds for aid are always subject to
                    Congressional approval, but we continue to have the firm intention to maintain
                    our program in Jordan.</p>
                <p>“It is encouraging to hear of your efforts to bring Jordan’s budget deficits
                    under control. Even those friends like ourselves who are helping Jordan
                    significantly have been deeply concerned over Jordan’s increasing dependence on
                    outside assistance and its consequent vulnerability. It is gratifying to see
                    underway an effort to reverse that trend.</p>
                <p>“Warm regards, <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>.”</p>
                <p>Approve [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>]<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d77fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> initialed his
                        approval.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Revise to include extra $10 million in December 1973</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Reply to King <persName corresp="#p_HT_2"
                        >Hussein</persName>’s Message</p>
                <p>King <persName corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName> repeats his earlier expressed
                    concern about the deterioration of the Middle East situation.<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d77fn7">See <ref target="#d61">Document 61</ref>.</note> Military
                    conflict, he says, is imminent. Turning to financial problems, the King
                    categorically says that Jordan cannot find more financial aid in the Arab world
                    unless it agrees to turn over its armed forces to an Egyptian commander by
                    joining the Unified Arab Command. He feels left out when he sees large
                    quantities of military equipment going to countries on all sides of him, while
                    his requests encounter “delays.” He paints a sorry picture of Jordan’s military
                    forces. In conclusion, he states that the “string is stretched almost to the
                    breaking point.” Although he does not say so in this message, he remains
                    interested in knowing what diplomatic progress there has been on a peace
                    settlement and what <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> strategy is.</p>
                <p>This message came at a time when <persName corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName>
                    felt under pressure from Egypt and Syria to commit Jordan to military action
                    against Israel if hostilities resumed. He also had just appointed <persName
                        corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zayd Rifai</persName> Prime Minister, in part to try to
                    get a firmer grip on Jordan’s financial problems. It coincided with reports
                    about our military sales to Saudi Arabia and Kuwait—both nations from which
                    Jordan would like more financial help.</p>
                <p>As you know, we have pushed the limits of our own present aid resources, and we
                    have had a military team in Jordan to plan the next round of arms shipments. The
                    Jordanians naturally find it difficult to understand why Jordan gets much less
                    aid than Israel. On the other hand, the Jordanians have been guilty of
                    considerable fiscal irresponsi<pb facs="0270" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/>bility.
                    Our posture can be one of continuing support without wanting to see Jordan
                    become any more heavily dependent on outside aid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi> That you send the following reply to King
                        <persName corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName>:</p>
                <p>“Your Majesty:</p>
                <p>“I have very much appreciated having Your Majesty’s assessments of Jordan’s
                    situation. I hope that the pressures for Jordan’s association with any
                    resumption of military action have somewhat lessened. As you know, the United
                    States has no interest in seeing Jordan place its troops under a foreign
                    commander. The military team that recently visited Jordan is now preparing its
                    recommendations for further <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> military supply
                    shipments to Jordan, and we look forward to discussing our views with your
                    officers as soon as the report is ready.</p>
                <p>“The pace of diplomacy on a peace settlement has been slower than I thought it
                    might be when we talked in February, and it seems likely to be at least a little
                    while longer before we shall know what kind of negotiating process may be
                    possible between Egypt and Israel. I recognize that it is of primary concern to
                    Your Majesty to know in what context Jordan will be working. The main issue at
                    this point seems to be whether Egypt is prepared to make a decision to engage in
                    a negotiation. I shall inform you when there seems to be something of interest
                    to report.</p>
                <p>“I have written separately to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1"
                        >Rifai</persName> on the question of aid. In short, our overall position for
                    calendar year 1973 remains exactly as I described it to Your Majesty in
                    February, and the July disbursement is now being prepared. As Your Majesty
                    knows, we have made a significant contribution and will continue to do so this
                    year. We have two concerns: first, that Jordan have what it needs within the
                    limits of its friends’ ability to help; second, that the trend of Jordan’s
                    increasing dependence on outside aid gradually be reversed. In this latter
                    connection, it is encouraging to know that the Prime Minister is working
                    vigorously to tighten the grip on mounting government budget deficits. Knowing
                    our own problem of appropriations, I would not want Jordan to be dependent on
                    sharply increasing external assistance.</p>
                <p>“We continue to have Jordan’s interests very much at heart.</p>
                <p>“Warm regards. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName>.”</p>
                <p>Approve [<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>]<note n="8"
                        xml:id="d77fn8">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> indicated his approval
                        with a checkmark.</note>
                </p>
                <p>As revised</p>
                <pb facs="0271" n="236" xml:id="pg_236"/>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>’
                    Recommendation of Presidential Letter</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName> points out in his
                    memorandum to the President [under the memo at Tab B] that Jordan’s spending is
                    accelerating rapidly and that budget discipline appears to have broken down.
                    This is true, although since the Secretary’s memo was written the King has
                    appointed <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zayd Rifai</persName> Prime Minister with
                    instructions to get a grip on the budget deficits. [Action on this memo was held
                    by agreement with State until our own <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1974
                    Supporting Assistance picture clarified.]</p>
                <p>Some of the spending is for marginal items and projects. Given the trend of
                    rising Jordanian demands and declining <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> aid
                    levels, we are headed for problems. Our choices, as outlined by Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP_1">Rogers</persName>, are to do nothing now in the
                    hope that Jordan’s Arab neighbors will provide more help; to seek more funds
                    from Congress; or to advise the Jordanians that there are limits on <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> aid. The Secretary recommends the last course
                    and provides a draft message from the President to King <persName
                        corresp="#p_HT_2">Hussein</persName>.</p>
                <p>If you judge that a message from the President is appropriate at this time, a
                    memo from you to the President is attached. However, I would suggest that such a
                    message <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be sent at this time. I have included the
                    point in your two messages because it is a serious concern. It just seems to me
                    that the context is not right now for this kind of admonition. If the President
                    were writing a more general letter, this subject could be included, but it seems
                    a bit abrupt to send a letter on this subject alone.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi> That you <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
                    forward the memorandum at Tab B to the President and that, instead, State be
                    informed as follows: The President does not wish to send such a message by
                    itself at this time but would be prepared to reconsider if the approach could be
                    made in a broader context.</p>
                <p>Approve<note n="9" xml:id="d77fn9">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> initialed his
                        approval.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Send memo at Tab B to President</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
