<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-04-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-04-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="12" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d12">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/1652</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Minister in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Long</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-04-13"><hi rend="italic">April 13,
                                        1920</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 58</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to acknowledge the receipt of
                                your despatch No. 68, of April 5, 1920, with enclosure,<note n="19" xml:id="d12fn19">Neither printed.</note> in which you state that
                                the President of the Liberal Party, General Guerra, stated that it
                                was the desire of the Liberal Party to have the United States
                                Government supervise the coming elections in Cuba and asserted that
                                if this Government did not supervise the elections, the Liberal
                                Party would remain away from the polls.</p>
                            <p>In this connection I have to inform you that recent events have not
                                changed the Department’s position as to intervention, as it is still
                                relying upon the assurances given by President Menocal that fair
                                elections would be held in Cuba, as expressed in President Menocal’s
                                note to the American Minister, the Honorable William E. Gonzales,
                                dated Havana, November 3, 1919, a copy of which was transmitted to
                                the Department with despatch No. 1103 of November 7, last.<note n="20" xml:id="d12fn20"><ref target="frus1919v02#pg_79"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 79</ref>.</note></p>
                            <p>With regard to the Liberal Party’s refraining from taking part in the
                                elections, the Department’s policy as outlined in Department’s
                                telegram of March 31, noon, has not changed. Basing your action upon
                                the policy as outlined in that telegram, you may, when in your
                                judgment the time seems appropriate, orally inform members of any
                                political party expressing an intention of withdrawing from the
                                elections, of the attitude of the Department.</p>
                            <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                            <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Alvey A. Adee</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>