<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in France ( (Harrison) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d288</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">288</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-08-10T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-08-10T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-08-10T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-08-10T06:00:00-05:00" n="288"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d288">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">763.72119/10287: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harrison</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-08-10T12:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 10, 1920—noon</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received 7:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1521. B–194 for Davis.<note n="43" xml:id="d288fn43">Norman H. Davis, Under
                        Secretary of State, June 15, 1920.</note>
                </p>
                <p>[Reparation] Commission conclusions to date on collection costs of armies of
                    occupation excepting unimportant details as follows:<note n="44"
                        xml:id="d288fn44">See also Boyden’s cable of Aug. 2, paragraph 7, and
                        Department’s reply of Sept. 1, paragraphs 2 and 3, <ref target="#pg_415">pp.
                            415</ref> and <ref target="#pg_428">428</ref>, respectively.</note>
                    <pb facs="0422" n="332" xml:id="pg_332"/>
                    <list>
                        <label>1st.</label>
                        <item>Commission will transmit to Germany, claims presented by Governments
                            without any attempt to audit reserving right ask for subsequent
                            justification if any question raised by Germany.</item>
                        <label>2d.</label>
                        <item>Recommend[s] to Governments bills be prepared on capitation basis
                            classified for officers, men, horses, etc. Total cost then obtained by
                            multiplying capitation rate by actual number of effectives. Governments
                            requested to signify whether or not they have adopted this
                            system.</item>
                        <label>3d.</label>
                        <item>Bills to be accompanied by Government certificate to effect that claim
                            covers only expenses specified article 249 (United States certificate to
                            refer to agreement of June 28th, 1919,<note n="43" xml:id="d288fn46">For
                                text of agreement, see <hi rend="italic">Treaties</hi> (S. Doc. 348,
                                67th Cong., 4th sess.) vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p.
                                3524.</note> instead of article 249).</item>
                        <label>4th.</label>
                        <item>Accounts to be presented to Commission in national currencies and
                            transformed into gold marks at average rate of exchange of quarter
                            concerned prior to presentation to Germany. Paper marks to be converted
                            into gold marks at current official rate of exchange in use by armies of
                            occupation at date of transfer.</item>
                        <label>5th.</label>
                        <item>Present system whereby military authorities requisition paper marks
                            from Reichsbank approved.</item>
                        <label>6th.</label>
                        <item>Method of liquidating cost of armies reserved until Commission has
                            arrived at decision as to what deliveries, if any, can be credited
                            against twenty milliards.</item>
                        <label>7th.</label>
                        <item>Question technical opinion Legal Service that reimbursement by Germany
                            of billeting costs paid by armies in cash must be credited Germany under
                            article 235 although payments made by Germany to her nationals for
                            property requisitioned for billeting purposes need not be credited.
                            Former system used by United States troops. Latter system used by all
                            other armies. Therefore Commission requested me ascertain whether or not
                            in future American Army could arrange adopt same practice as other
                            armies.</item>
                        <label>8th.</label>
                        <item>Agreement of Governments of June 16th, 1919, that annual cost of
                            armies of occupation under certain conditions should not exceed
                            240,000,000 gold marks called to attention Commission by Finance Service
                            with the suggestion that delegates ascertain whether or not Governments
                            propose do this. In this connection see article 13, Spa inter-Allied
                            [percentage] agreement, my B–181.<note n="44" xml:id="d288fn47">Telegram
                                not printed; agreement referred to is printed on <ref
                                    target="#pg_406">p. 406</ref>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Have sent all papers to General Allen with comments asking for his
                            views. Our claims and accounts already correspond substantially with
                            Commission’s suggestions so these created no difficulty. Question of
                            transforming claims into gold marks raises question whether not
                            desirable avoid exchange risks by presenting bills in <pb facs="0423"
                                n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/> national currencies and so [obtaining?]
                            from Germany exact amount dollars, pounds, francs or lire actually
                            expended by each Government. This involves assumption exchange risk by
                            Germany which she could avoid by making her payments approximately
                            contemporaneous with expenditures, adjusting slight differences when
                            accurate figures determined. Protests [<hi rend="italic"
                            >Provisions</hi>] of article 249 requiring in part payment in gold marks
                            may raise difficulty in some technical minds but I cannot believe this
                            is a really practical difficulty. I thought Commission would take up
                            their request for change in American billeting system but thought it
                            involved practical difficulty possibly also question of policy. Expect
                            Allen to object to this change but wish to know whether War Department
                            objects if Allen sees no objection. Agreement to reduce costs to
                            24,000,000 [<hi rend="italic">240,000,000</hi>] gold marks not yet
                            effective because conditions not fulfilled so not likely to be practical
                            importance now.</item>
                        <label>10th.</label>
                        <item>You will see as I have previously reported, Commission apparently
                            proceeding collect United States Army costs with others and on exactly
                            same basis but cannot help feeling that sooner or later Commission will
                            run into technical difficulties in this connection because Commission
                            must act under the treaty and we have not ratified the treaty. They
                            would probably refer any such difficulty if it arises in their minds to
                            Powers but in my mind this possibility emphasizes necessity for taking
                            up question of army costs with Powers and arranging all details as I
                            previously suggested.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <list>
                            <item>Boyden<note n="45" xml:id="d288fn45">Roland W. Boyden, American
                                    unofficial representative on the Reparation Commission.</note>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Harrison</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
