<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-05-12T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-05-12T06:00:00-05:00" n="333" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d333">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00 R 29/211: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Wallace</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-05-12T12:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">May 12,
                                            1920—noon</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received May 13—1:12
                                    a.m.]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>1138. B–82 for Davis.</p>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>2d.</label>
                                <item>World opinion is evidently gradually forcing France consider
                                    more seriously immediate determination specific sum or more <pb facs="0477" n="387" xml:id="pg_387"/> likely minimum,
                                    eventually increasing from time to time according to increase in
                                    Germany’s ability, to be determined by Reparation Commission or
                                    other tribunal on basis some statistical standard agreed upon by
                                    Powers or determined by Commission or tribunal.</item>
                                <label>3d.</label>
                                <item>Present legal position of Reparation Commission clear. Seems
                                    to be accepted by our legal service and entire Commission that
                                    while we have certain powers with respect to postponement of
                                    payment, also certain power of determining when bonds shall be
                                    issued, we have maintained [<hi rend="italic">have no?</hi>]
                                    power to negotiate with Germany for payment of any fixed sum
                                    smaller than total reparation bill determined according to prima
                                    facie evidence as stated in treaty. Also settled that four
                                    months period allowed Germany to make offer of fixed sum either
                                    for whole or any specific part of reparations has expired
                                    because four months period dated from signature and not from
                                    coming into force of treaty. Baruch’s recent statement seems
                                    based on theory that Reparation Commission had full power which
                                    is fundamentally wrong. Legally matter is for Governments, not
                                    for Commission.</item>
                                <label>4th.</label>
                                <item>All members of Commission except France thoroughly convinced
                                    necessity of recognizing practical conditions and desirous
                                    having Commission at least formally recommend to Powers
                                    immediate definite determination Germany’s liability using all
                                    possible influence of Commission to secure this result. Matter
                                    not yet formally discussed in Commission. Poincaré’s attitude in
                                    article <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi> also
                                    article in <hi rend="italic">Matin</hi>, shows distinct hostile
                                    tendencies. We have been endeavoring arrange informal conference
                                    with him for interchange of views. Have had difficulty and delay
                                    even in arranging this informal conference which we regard as
                                    important preliminary to proposed discussions at Spa. We think
                                    delay probably due to fact Millerand and Poincaré not wholly in
                                    agreement and Poincaré probably trying to arrange understanding
                                    with Millerand before discussions with us. Poincaré in brief
                                    discussions relies mainly on technical legal situation inclining
                                    to view that our powers depend on treaty and not our business to
                                    close [<hi rend="italic">change?</hi>] treaty or even to suggest
                                    changes, also emphasizes France’s difficulties, saying France
                                    has no objection to determination of fixed sum if large enough
                                    to pay reparations but obvious purpose of all present
                                    discussions is not so much definiteness of indemnity as
                                    reduction in amount of indemnity, that reduction will not meet
                                    France’s needs and that even if Millerand should be convinced
                                    that reduction ought to be made very doubtful if he can get
                                    support of Chamber for necessary vote modifying treaty.</item>
                                <label>5th.</label>
                                <item>I have no hesitation in assuming your policy favors both
                                    definiteness and reduction of amount to some figure within the
                                    limits of economic possibility which is most strong personal
                                    view. In <pb facs="0478" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/> foregoing
                                    statement this policy shall of course emphasize that fundamental
                                    reason is no[t] charity towards Germany but belief it represents
                                    economic wisdom for the world and fully as important in interest
                                    of France as in interest of any other country.</item>
                                <label>6th.</label>
                                <item>Even if present endeavor to secure determination of definite
                                    figure for German indemnity [and] reduction in amount does not
                                    succeed and Reparation Commission still remains under obligation
                                    to determine full amount of Germany’s bill, some arrangement
                                    ought to be worked out sooner or later for determining amount of
                                    this bill in a wholesale way without going through all infinite
                                    details and complexities of accounting. If Governments call for
                                    any of their percentages in reparations then Commission ought to
                                    be able to arrange somewhat arbitrarily with Germany agreement
                                    on amount of total bill, the purpose being to reach definite
                                    idea of figure which would be reached by detailed accounting
                                    without bother expense and delay of such accounting. Mistake of
                                    a few milliards will be of slight importance compared with
                                    advantages to all parties but even this arrangement might be
                                    regarded as technically contrary to the treaty and so require
                                    assent of Governments.</item>
                                <label>7th.</label>
                                <item>Any determination of amount Germany is to pay and particularly
                                    any reduction in amount of her present returns of liability
                                    involves question how far United States is to share in
                                    reparation payments. My understanding is policy of
                                    administration not to share in reparation payments except so far
                                    as we retain ships and apply property in the hands of Alien
                                    Property Custodian, also reimbursement expenses Army of
                                    Occupation. This policy cannot be final without ratification by
                                    Senate perhaps by Congress. Anything possible to bring about
                                    final decision should be done. Whatever our decision we are of
                                    course to be charged with whatever dyes and pharmaceutical
                                    supplies we receive [garbled group]. In connection with
                                    discussion of our policy and application of policy when
                                    determined, also in connection with discussion various
                                    reparations [proposals] as they arise here from time to time, we
                                    shall need as accurate and complete information as possible
                                    about United States damages prepared on the same lines as damage
                                    claims of other Governments I transmitted. Think we are likely
                                    to need this even if we never ratify the treaty, therefore
                                    suggest your consideration arrangement for competent intensive
                                    study of problem. Possibly this already arranged but I seem to
                                    have nothing later than Lansing letter to you dated December 3,
                                        1919.<note n="68" xml:id="d333fn68">Not printed.</note> This
                                    seems very good but probably needs to be corrected in the light
                                    of further information and preparation should be made for
                                    supporting claims by evidence in case necessity arises.</item>
                                <pb facs="0479" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/>
                                <label>8th.</label>
                                <item>Every cent spent on Army of Occupation reduces amount
                                    available for reparation. Know nothing about subject but am
                                    wondering whether anything can be done by us or other
                                    Governments towards cutting off this expense. Substitution of
                                    French troops for our own troops would reduce expense somewhat.
                                    Ought any action to be taken on this subject? Boyden.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>