<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Wallace) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d354</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">354</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-08-27T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-08-27T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-08-27T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-08-27T06:00:00-05:00" n="354"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00 R 29/334: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wallace</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-08-27T12:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 27, 1920—noon</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received 8:35 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1616. B–220 for Davis.</p>
                <p>Inter-Allied Spa percentage agreement discussion was fixed for this morning.
                    Before meeting I communicated informally to delegates protest which I proposed
                    to place on record. In view of this proposed protest delegates decided postpone
                    discussion in order communicate protest to their Governments. Postponed probably
                    one week. Please advise any suggestions. Following copy of proposed protest:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“In connection with the inter-Allied agreement signed at Spa (annex 345)
                            which has been presented to the Reparation Commission, the United States
                            Unofficial Delegate desires to place on record a formal reserve with
                            respect to the rights of the United States, <hi rend="italic">id
                                est</hi>, which, either in case of ratification or non-ratification
                            of the treaties or any portion of them, may be affected thereby. Subject
                            to the foregoing reserve he states further that certain indications of
                            the agreement constrain him to decline to assent thereto and even to
                            protest against its acceptance by the Commission.</p>
                        <p>In explanation of the foregoing and without attempting to make a complete
                            statement of objections he expresses opinion that: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The agreement is in direct conflict with the provisions of the
                                    treaty with Germany. In view of the emphasis, which both at the
                                    beginning and since the end of the war, has been placed on
                                    Germany’s failure to respect her treaty obligations, any
                                    tendency in this same direction shown by Germany’s critics needs
                                    no comment.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The influence which such an agreement inevitably exercises
                                    upon the personal opinion of the members of the Commission is in
                                    itself objectionable. If to that influence is added the pressure
                                    of direct instructions to the delegates, the status of the
                                    Commission under the treaty is threatened. It is no longer a
                                    judicial body, it has become a mere registering machine
                                    controlled by governments in their own interests.</item>
                                <pb facs="0512" n="422" xml:id="pg_422"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Specifically, the provisions with respect to ex-enemy ships
                                    prescribe an arbitrary method of valuation which has no relation
                                    to established principles, either of law or equity, which
                                    conflict[s] with the treaty provisions and which is unfair to
                                    the ex-enemy powers.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The provisions of articles 6, 7 and 8 denying to Germany
                                    credit for certain property and for the use of certain ships are
                                    attempts to deprive the Commission [of] jurisdiction in matters
                                    of which the treaty makes the Commission the sole judge. The
                                    provisions of articles 7 and 8 are in direct conflict with
                                    opinions rendered by our legal service.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>The specific objections to which I have called attention would no longer
                            exist if the assent of ex-enemy countries interested were obtained or if
                            arrangements were made with ex-enemy countries interested such that
                            future indemnity payments would have no relation to the deliveries in
                            question or if the provisions of the inter-Allied agreement were treated
                            as arrangements for inter-Allied accounting and not as changes in the
                            treaty provisions. I express the hope that some one of these solutions
                            may be adopted.</p>
                        <p>To avoid misunderstanding the undersigned will add that there can be no
                            objection in principle to treaty changes which in the light of
                            experience commend themselves to all parties concerned. He is strongly
                            of opinion that experience has shown that important changes are
                            desirable particularly from the point of view of those powers most
                            interested in realizing substantial indemnity from Germany.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <list>
                            <item>Boyden</item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace</hi>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
