<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-09-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-09-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="369" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">462.00 R 29/337</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Geddes</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-09-13"><hi rend="italic">September 13,
                                        1920</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: In accordance with
                                the promise which I gave you yesterday, I send you, herewith, a
                                short memorandum <pb facs="0526" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/>
                                summarizing the position which has arisen with regard to the
                                proposed conference at Geneva on September 24th.</p>
                            <p>Believe me [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. C. Geddes</hi></signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British
                                            Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                            State</gloss></hi></head>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi></p>
                                <p>The proposal that a Conference should be held at Geneva on
                                    September 24th with a view more particularly to arriving at a
                                    settlement of the question of the financial advances to be made
                                    to Germany by the Allies under the terms of the Spa Gold [<hi rend="italic">Coal?</hi>] Agreement, was made by His
                                    Majesty’s Government in accordance with the decision of the Spa
                                    Conference to refer the Reparation question to a Special
                                    Commission at Geneva which should consist of “two delegates from
                                    each Delegation”.</p>
                                <p>While this proposal has been accepted by the Italian, Belgian and
                                    German Governments, the French Government, although prepared to
                                    be represented at this Conference on the same footing as His
                                    Majesty’s Government, have declined to accept the proposed date
                                    on the ground that it is the same as that chosen for the
                                    Financial Conference at Brussels, which many of their delegates
                                    for Geneva would be obliged to attend.</p>
                                <p>In reply to representations, the French Government have amplified
                                    the grounds for their refusal as follows: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>Not only have they found it necessary, on technical
                                            grounds to select the same delegates for the Brussels
                                            and Geneva Conferences but, having regard to the nature
                                            of the agenda for both Conferences and the necessity for
                                            avoiding the slightest difference of policy or
                                            interpretation between the French Representatives, they
                                            consider it out of the question for the French
                                            Government to be represented otherwise than by the same
                                            delegates at the two meetings.</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>They regard it as improbable that, in the present
                                            disposition of the German Government and in view of
                                            their evident desire to seek all possible opportunities
                                            of evading the obligations imposed by the Treaty of
                                            Versailles, any favourable result could be expected from
                                            discussion with their delegates at Geneva.</item>
                                        <label>(3)</label>
                                        <item>They allege that the proposed Conference at Geneva is
                                            not regarded favourably by the United States Government
                                            or by the Belgian Government. They claim that the United
                                            States delegate on the Reparation Commission has already
                                            lodged a formal protest against the Allied Agreement
                                            arrived at at Spa on the ground that it is incompatible
                                            with the Versailles Treaty, while the Belgian Government
                                            are said to wish to act through the Reparation
                                            Commission <pb facs="0527" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/> at
                                            Paris directly without the convocation of a Special
                                            Conference at a place so distant as Geneva. In addition
                                            to the above reasons the French Government deprecate the
                                            suggestion that any further action is necessary with
                                            regard to gold advances to Germany or that any
                                            undertaking on the subject has been given by the
                                            Reparation Commission to the German Government. Under
                                            existing arrangements the Germans receive advances in
                                            exchange for gold [<hi rend="italic">coal?</hi>] and
                                            deposit bills in return, leaving the Reparation
                                            Commission only the details of execution to
                                            arrange.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>His Majesty’s Government desire to point out that the policy
                                    which the French are now proposing appears to run entirely
                                    contrary to that which the Allies have attempted to carry out
                                    since the date of the San Remo Conference, the essential point
                                    in which has been that German cooperation in the execution of
                                    the Treaty should be obtained so far as possible through direct
                                    communication between the German Government and the Allies. With
                                    this policy His Majesty’s Government had always believed the
                                    United States Government to be in sympathy and they accordingly
                                    ask that some enquiry be made as to the reasons for the action
                                    of the American delegates on the Reparation Commission.</p>
                                <closer><dateline rendition="#left">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-09-13"><hi rend="italic">September 13, 1920</hi></date>.</dateline></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>