<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commission to Negotiate Peace to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d379</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">379</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-08-09T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-08-09T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-08-09T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-08-09T19:00:00-05:00" n="379"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d379">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.626/22: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                        to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-08-10T01:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 10, 1919</hi>—[<hi rend="italic">1
                            a.m.</hi>]</date>
                        <lb/>[Received August 10—10:32 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3601. At informal meeting[s] between British, French, Italian and Belgian dye
                    experts and German dye experts which have been proceeding at Versailles, very
                    acute differences developed between the different delegations. The British have
                    been represented by delegates chosen from dye manufacturers who are anxious to
                    reduce to a minimum the utilization of German dyes evidently in the hope of
                    keeping them off the market until Great Britain will be able to export. On the
                    other hand the delegates of France, Italy and Belgium are representatives of
                    textile industries who are exceedingly anxious to receive at once large
                    quantities of dyestuffs for the reestablishment of their industries and who are
                    under very great political pressure <pb facs="0536" n="446" xml:id="pg_446"/> to
                    accomplish this. The Germans appeared anxious to put into effect at once the
                    provisions of annex VI of the reparation clauses so as to know as soon as
                    possible precisely where they stand and what dyestuffs will be left to dispose
                    of after the exercise of the option given the Reparation Commission. The French,
                    Italians, and Belgians in agreement with the Germans accordingly proposed that
                    the German inventory of stock should be given and accepted as of August 15 and
                    the option exercised within 15 or 30 days thereafter. The British on the other
                    hand refused to accept this procedure.</p>
                <p>A meeting was held yesterday of the British, French, Italian, and Belgian experts
                    at which Dulles<note n="88" xml:id="d379fn88">John Foster Dulles, financial
                        adviser, American Commission to Negotiate Peace.</note> presided in an
                    effort to reconcile the conflicting views. Dulles stated that it would be
                    impossible for the United States to agree to an anticipation of the treaty
                    clauses. At the same time steps should be taken to ensure the French, Belgians,
                    and Italians facilities to purchase German dyestuffs pending the coming in force
                    of the treaty. It appears that the British through the Rhineland Commission and
                    the Army of Occupation have succeeded in practically impounding all German
                    dyestuffs on the theory that they could not be disposed of pending the coming in
                    force of the treaty and the exercise of the option referred to in annex VI,
                    reparation clauses.</p>
                <p>It was eventually agreed to accept the view that no effort would be made to
                    anticipate the time limits established by the treaty unless the United States
                    agreed to this procedure. The American delegate undertook to cable for
                    instructions in the matter. It was on the other hand agreed that German dye
                    requisites [<hi rend="italic">stocks</hi>] in occupied area should be made
                    available for French, Italian and Belgian purchasers and that France should
                    purchase 350 tons[, Italy 350 tons and Belgium 150 tons]. It was understood that
                    these [purchases] would be for domestic use only and not for [re-]export. It was
                    also agreed to recommend to the temporary Reparation Commission that it take
                    steps to bring about the immediate formation of a committee of experts to
                    consider the operation of annex VI.</p>
                <p>The foregoing recommendations were presented to the Committee on the Organization
                    of the Reparation Commission at its meeting held August 9 and were approved.</p>
                <p>The Mission is not advised as to what the policy of the United States will be
                    with regard to dyestuffs but whatever its policy is, [it is] believed that we
                    will be at a disadvantage unless an American dyestuffs expert is present in
                    meeting[s] of the experts of other committees which are taking place. Polk.</p>
                <closer>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Mission</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
