<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Wallace) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d424</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">424</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-01-05T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-01-05T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-01-05T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-01-05T18:00:00-05:00" n="424"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d424">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.85/983: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wallace</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-01-05T23:00:00+00:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 5, 1920—11 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[Received January 6—2:14 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>40. From Rathbone for Davis.<note n="24" xml:id="d424fn24">Norman H. Davis,
                        Assistant Secretary, U. S. Treasury, from Nov. 1919 to June 1920; assumed
                        duties as Under Secretary of State, June 15, 1920.</note> R–195.</p>
                <p>Department’s 9478, December 31st, 1919.<note n="25" xml:id="d424fn25">Not
                        printed.</note> Embassy’s 21 January 3rd, 1920, R–191.<note n="25"
                        xml:id="d424fn26">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0599" n="509" xml:id="pg_509"/>
                <list>
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <item>Embassy’s 21, January 3, 1920, my R–191, gives our views on questions of
                        importance raised.</item>
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <item>Following from minutes O[rganization] C[ommittee,] R[eparation]
                        C[ommission] meeting 2d October, delegates from the United States, England,
                        France, Italy, Belgium present, Loucheur presiding: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“Brazilian ships. Chairman recalled that on several occasions this
                                question had been raised before the Committee. In its meeting of
                                25th September 1919, it had charged Major Monfries to telegraph
                                again to A[llied] M[aritime] T[ransport] E[xecutive] on this matter.
                                In respect for decisions of the Commission, French Government had
                                refrained from entering into negotiations with Brazil for purchase
                                of these ships, but it stated that it considered it as formally
                                understood that no other Allied or Associated Power should enter
                                into or should authorize its subjects to enter into negotiations
                                before decision was received. Committee declared itself in
                                agreement.”</p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label>(3)</label>
                    <item>Under Wilson–Lloyd George Agreement it seems plain that irrespective of
                        amount of claims against Germany by country (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                        availing of that agreement and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) receiving
                        thereunder more tonnage than under the ton for ton theory, the reasonable
                        value of such excess must be paid into common reparation fund
                        notwithstanding the President’s reservation in signing agreement. If
                        Congress should refuse to make disposal of funds as contemplated, should
                        doubt whether Britain would then be bound by agreement. On other hand French
                        in accepting this agreement, so far as United States is concerned, did so
                        subject to power of Congress to make disposal of funds under resolution
                        approved May 12th, 1917. It is my view that Wilson–Lloyd George Agreement
                        applied to all ships whether or not legal tender [<hi rend="italic"
                            >title</hi>] has passed to Government capturing, seizing or detaining
                        same.</item>
                    <label>(4)</label>
                    <item>Annex III applies to German merchant ships, that is, ships the title to
                        which was in Germany at date of treaty. If a country not accepting
                        Wilson–Lloyd George Agreement has made [<hi rend="italic">taken</hi>] title
                        to ships before date of treaty in my opinion there is great force to
                        contention that such ships do not pass under treaty and proceeds of sale so
                        far as property of German nationals must be then dealt with in accordance
                        with article 297 of treaty. This opinion is granted [<hi rend="italic"
                            >given</hi>] without examination of international law bearing on
                        question. …</item>
                    <label>(5)</label>
                    <item>You will recall (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) that at meeting of second
                        subcommittee on reparations March 31 Hipwood, British expert, said it was
                        intention of draughtsman of annex III, paragraph 3, “to exclude from
                        delivery to be demanded only boats captured and definitely condemned by
                        prize courts”. The amendments were rejected that <pb facs="0600" n="510"
                            xml:id="pg_510"/> Robinson<note n="25" xml:id="d424fn27">Henry N.
                            Robinson, technical adviser, American Commission to Negotiate
                            Peace.</note> proposed on behalf of United States involving recognition
                        of [<hi rend="italic">by?</hi>] Central Powers, of validity of seizure
                        during war of merchant shipping and relinquishment of titles thereto, the
                        Government holding such ships to be charged with reasonable value thereof;
                            (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) that at meeting of Council of Four April 28
                        “it was agreed to inform Brazilians and Portuguese that it was not feasible
                        to meet their claim in regard to shipping and that they would share in
                        common pool.”</item>
                    <label>(6)</label>
                    <item>Would appreciate earliest possible information as to what position it is
                        determined United States will take, without this information it will be
                        difficult to discuss questions which will arise in connection with German
                        ships seized by Brazil. Rathbone.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wallace</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
