<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Cuba ( (Long))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">44</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-11-17T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-11-17T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107730"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protests</term>
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-11-17T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-11-17T11:00:00-05:00" n="44"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d44">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/1876: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Long</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-11-17T11:00:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 17, 1920—11 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>239. Your November 11, 5 p.m.</p>
                <p>The Department considers it highly important that the leaders of the Liberal
                    party be fully advised of the policy of this Government as regards interference
                    with the control by the properly constituted authorities in Cuba of the
                    electoral machinery. It appears to be the desire of the Liberal party to present
                    now to the Department reports of alleged frauds and outrages committed during
                    the electoral period in the hope of inducing this Government to investigate
                    immediately the manner in which the elections have been held and to review the
                    conduct of the Central Electoral Board, basing their request on the ground that
                    the statement of your Legation issued on August 30,<note n="54" xml:id="d44fn54">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_19">p. 19</ref>.</note>
                    promises such action. It is apparent that such an interpretation of the
                    statement issued at that time is entirely unfounded, since this Government
                    declared that while it would use all available means to observe the conduct of
                    the electoral procedure and the spirit in which the electoral law was enforced,
                    it stated most emphatically that the responsibility for the conduct of a fair
                    election rested with the Government and people of Cuba.</p>
                <p>A review of the present situation makes it apparent that no decision can as yet
                    be reached regarding the outcome of the elections, since the official returns
                    are not yet completed and there is no assurance as to which party has been
                    victorious; and since neither party has as yet been able to avail itself of the
                    recourses provided in the election law to bring its protests and complaints
                    before the properly constituted authorities for review and decision, any effort
                    at this time on the part of this Government to hear the complaints of the
                    Liberal party, or of the Conservative party, would remove from the judiciary of
                    Cuba the responsibility which legally and by right rests upon them to hear and
                    decide such complaints. Any action taken by this Government at this time would
                    constitute effectively an uncalled for and <pb facs="0131" n="41" xml:id="pg_41"
                    /> unwarranted intervention in the internal affairs of Cuba and could not but be
                    regarded as a hurtful precedent which would tend to render more difficult in the
                    future the determination by the Cuban people themselves of the problems which
                    confront them in the development of a democratic and independent government. For
                    these reasons, the Department is not at present willing to receive the protests
                    of the Liberal Commission, nor is it willing to enter into any conversations at
                    this time with the members of this Commission regarding the elections. The
                    Department has availed itself of the excellent opportunities afforded to observe
                    closely the manner in which the elections were conducted and the way in which
                    the Central Electoral Board has functioned and will be able, therefore, to reach
                    its own conclusions from an unbiased standpoint.</p>
                <p>You should take occasion to communicate the above verbally to the leaders of the
                    Liberal party and to impress upon them that the attitude so defined has been
                    reached by the Department after careful consideration and that its attitude has
                    changed in no way since the issuance by the Legation of the statement of August
                    30. You should likewise informally continue to use your best endeavors to
                    prevent the departure for Washington of any commission of Liberals or any other
                    attempt which may be made to transfer the center of Cuban political activity
                    from Cuba to Washington, and explain that all resources provided for under
                    electoral law should be exhausted before any appeal could properly be presented
                    here.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Colby</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
