<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Commission to Negotiate Peace to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d474</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">474</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-11-13T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-11-13T19:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="rec63886aa66e88522" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="reparation">Reparation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-11-13T19:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-11-13T19:00:00-05:00" n="474"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d474">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.85/933: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Commission to Negotiate Peace</gloss>
                        to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-11-14T00:00:00+00:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">November 14, 1919—midnight</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received November 15—11:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>5200. There was a long and very unsatisfactory discussion of the tanker question
                    this morning. I proposed that in view of the fact that the action of September
                        27th<note n="63" xml:id="d474fn63">See telegram no. 4409, Sept. 28, 1919,
                            <ref target="#pg_547">p. 547</ref>.</note> was taken without a full
                    knowledge of all the facts the action should be rescinded and the 9 ships should
                    be held in Hamburg pending negotiations between the French, British and myself.
                    This was vigorously opposed by Bérenger representing the French and by the
                    British. I pointed out that <pb facs="0658" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/> the ships
                    had been exempted from allocation in March and spoke of the understanding
                    Hoover, Davis and Dulles had had with the various representatives and urged for
                    political reasons that the action be rescinded. I pointed out that there was
                    considerable agitation [<hi rend="italic">irritation</hi>] in the United States
                    now growing out of the fact that it was believed these ships were really the
                    property of a United States company; that the allocation to the French had been
                    made as the result of an agreement between the British and French whereby the
                    French were to receive tank ships and the British passenger ships and that the
                    French had organized a company to operate the ships. Bérenger in his reply read
                    the various resolutions that had been passed; said he had no recollection of any
                    such agreement as we claim and then referred at length to the [seizure of the]
                        <hi rend="italic">Imperator</hi> group of ships by the Shipping Board and
                    the refusal in spite of the decision of the Reparation Committee to deliver the
                    ships. He spoke of the great shortage of oil in Europe; dwelt on the fact that
                    the Standard Oil Company had attempted to divest itself of title by sale;
                    pointed out that all these questions were questions that required the most
                    thorough investigation and said that he could not see why we should object to
                    the operation by Allies of these ships in the meantime, first primarily for
                    benefit of Germany and [then] for Europe pending a decision.</p>
                <p>I pointed out that the question of ownership was not one I was discussing at the
                    moment but at the same time my attempt to keep the Standard Oil Company out of
                    the discussion was futile as the whole fight seems to settle around that point.
                    The British objected to my statement that there had been a secret agreement with
                    the French covering the allocation of passenger ships and tank steamers. They
                    said they had an understanding with the French that they would waive their claim
                    to any share in temporary allocation of the tank steamers in view of the great
                    need of France, The British representatives dwelt on the fact that Germany had
                    been directed to deliver the ships; that the delivery had been prevented by the
                    agents of the Standard Oil Company in Germany; that this really amounted to a
                    defiance of the Supreme Council by a private corporation; that it would make an
                    extremely bad impression on Germany and on the world if it appeared that the
                    decisions of the Supreme Council were subject to modification at the election of
                    a private individual; that it would show to Germany a division among the Allies
                    and therefore they said they could not consent to the [revocation] of the order.
                    This view was shared by the French and by the Italians. Their proposal is that
                    the 14 tank steamers should be delivered immediately at the Firth of Forth; that
                    the 9 Standard Oil Company ships should be held there pending a decision as to
                    their temporary allocation <pb facs="0659" n="569" xml:id="pg_569"/> and if that
                    could not be determined then they should be held until the question of title
                    should be finally settled, the other 5 ships if seaworthy to be temporarily
                    allocated to Allies. The French however laid great stress on the fact that this
                    arrangement was conditional upon the immediate delivery of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Imperator</hi> ships in accordance with the decision previously reached.
                    They also laid great stress on the fact that we were objecting to a temporary
                    allocation on the ground that it might prejudice the final disposition of [the]
                    ships but at the same time we were setting an extremely bad example by
                    jeopardizing [<hi rend="italic">keeping</hi>] by force without any authority
                    whatever the <hi rend="italic">Imperator</hi> class.</p>
                <p>I told the Supreme Council that it would be necessary to refer the matter to my
                    Government to see if this arrangement would be satisfactory but I indicated in
                    order to protect myself that it was an open question as to whether it would be
                    satisfactory or not.</p>
                <p>During the course of the debate Sir Eyre Crowe stated that he had been instructed
                    by his Government on three occasions to bring before the Supreme Council the
                    question of the detention of the <hi rend="italic">Imperator</hi> and request
                    that the Council direct the Shipping Board to deliver the ships immediately. He
                    said there was great feeling on the subject in Great Britain and his Government
                    was pressing us for action. He and Clemenceau agreed however that the
                    consideration of the demand on the Shipping Board in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Imperator</hi> case should not be taken up today. Both the French and
                    British dwelt on the fact that the decision of this case would have serious
                    political and popular effect in their countries.</p>
                <p>In order to sum up the point on which I wish instructions please let me know
                    whether it would be satisfactory to have the 9 tank steamers claimed by the
                    Standard Oil Company delivered in the Firth of Forth and there held pending an
                    arrangement for their temporary allocation or until the question of the title
                    can be finally disposed of. It is an [<hi rend="italic">our</hi>] impression
                    that if we release the <hi rend="italic">Imperator</hi> and other ships our task
                    will be much easier and some think that we surely would be able to secure the
                    [operation] of these ships by the Americans. Polk.</p>
                <closer>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">American Mission</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
