<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Consul General at London ( (Skinner) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d538</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">538</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-07-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-07-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-07-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="538"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d538">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">300.115/20763</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Consul General at London</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Skinner</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-07-23">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 23, 1920</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received August 6.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 9946</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my telegram of July
                    22 [<hi rend="italic">23</hi>], 1920,<note n="49" xml:id="d538fn49">Not
                        printed.</note> reporting a very important decision of the Prize Court
                    relating chiefly to American goods held under the Order in Council of <pb
                        facs="0732" n="642" xml:id="pg_642"/> March 11, 1915, and to transmit
                    herewith prints of the judgment in question, as reported in the press.</p>
                <p>The Department will note that goods are to be released, or deposits made in the
                    course of the war in exchange for the goods are to be released, subject to the
                    payment of expenses properly incurred and cost of insurance.</p>
                <p>The Procurator General is now empowered to grant release in particular cases
                    where the title of the claimant is established to his reasonable
                    satisfaction.</p>
                <p>I am prepared, therefore, to receive instructions from the Department, or
                    applications from particular claimants in respect of their goods. Naturally, the
                    cases already before me will be re-examined and dealt with in the light of the
                    new situation.</p>
                <p>A full transcript of the proceedings of the Prize Court leading up to the
                    decision, will be forwarded as soon as prints can be obtained and put in
                    order.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert P. Skinner</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Press Report of the Judgment, July 22, 1920, of the Prize
                            Court in the Cases of the “United States” and Other Vessels</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Judgment was delivered in these test actions, which were brought before the
                        Court under a recent order of the President to decide how goods (or their
                        proceeds) which were seized under the Reprisals Orders in Council and were
                        ordered to be detained until the conclusion of peace, on the ground that
                        they were goods of enemy origin and/or enemy property, should be disposed
                        of.</p>
                    <p>The Crown did not oppose the release of the goods if the Court were satisfied
                        that they now belonged to neutrals, and it invited the Court to lay down
                        principles on which subsequent cases should be dealt with.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Raeburn, K.C., Mr. L. F. C. Darby, and Mr. Wilfrid Price appeared for the
                        American claimants; the Attorney-General (Sir Gordon Hewart, K.C.), the
                        Solicitor-General (Sir Ernest Pollock, K.C.), and Mr. James Wyllie for the
                        Procurator-General.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Judgment</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">President</hi>, in his judgment, said that whether
                        the matter was considered generally under the Order in Council, or in the
                        light of the practice of the Court in prize, the terms on which it was just
                        that these goods should be released were, in his view, terms of payment by
                        the claimants of the expenses properly and necessarily incurred by the
                        Marshal in the handling of their parcels. As to insurance, <pb facs="0733"
                            n="643" xml:id="pg_643"/> in ordinary circumstances captured goods in
                        the custody of the Marshal under a claim of condemnation did not bear the
                        expenses of insurance, where they had not been incurred by order of the
                        Court or at the request of the claimants. That practice resulted from the
                        relative positions of the captor and the claimant with regard to the
                        property in the goods, and from the obligations properly belonging to the
                        Marshal. Goods held by the Marshal for an owner, who by his own act, had
                        subjected his property to detention seemed to him, however, to be subject to
                        other considerations. No captor had an interest in them. The Marshal was
                        charged with their safekeeping for the sole purpose of eventual restitution.
                        He had incurred expenses of insurance on a system recognized in the
                        Registry, with the result that from time to time various claimants had
                        received policy moneys for goods which, without negligence, had been
                        destroyed and on which they would otherwise have suffered a total loss.
                        Insurance was a wise and almost indispensable precaution in these cases. In
                        his opinion it was just that the cost of the insurance should be borne by
                        the owners of the goods, and he directed that they should be so borne.</p>
                    <p>Outside the main question of expenses, he had been asked by the Crown for
                        some expression of opinion about the conditions under which detained goods
                        should ordinarily be released, and in particular about proofs of ownership
                        to be required and the precautions which were proper to avoid claims by
                        persons who were not now on the scene. He did not think it necessary to say
                        more than that the Procurator-General was under no obligation to consent on
                        his own responsibility to the release of goods where the title of the
                        claimant was not established to his reasonable satisfaction.</p>
                    <p>The order proper to be made in each of the cases before the Court was an
                        order for restitution to the several claimants on payment in each case of
                        the expenses properly incurred, including costs of insurance, the amount of
                        such expenses in case of dispute to be determined in the Registry.</p>
                    <p>Solicitors:—Messrs. Thos. Cooper and Co. for the claimants; the Treasury
                        Solicitor for the Procurator-General.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
