<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-08-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-08-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="579" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d579">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.73/246</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Acting Secretary of the Navy</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Coontz</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-08-09"><hi rend="italic">August 9,
                                        1920</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: There is transmitted herewith a copy
                                of a dispatch from Bear Admiral E. A. Anderson,<note n="96" xml:id="d579fn96">Not printed.</note> supervising the naval
                                operations in connection with the prevention of the laying of a
                                submarine telegraph cable off Miami and Key West, and the reply of
                                the Department<note n="97" xml:id="d579fn97">Not found in Department
                                    files.</note> indicating a suspension of action until the
                                matters in question could be referred to the Department of State.
                                Admiral Anderson has already been informed that no license or permit
                                exists for the running of new telephone or telegraph cables between
                                Key West and Cuba.</p>
                            <p>It would appear that the Master of the <hi rend="italic">Colonia</hi>
                                has definitely decided to comply with the wishes of the British
                                Ambassador, and although that vessel will be kept under observation
                                so long as she remains in the vicinity of Miami or Key West, her
                                movements will not be otherwise interfered with. The question at
                                issue which has not been met by any decision so far is the further
                                disposition of the Tug <hi rend="italic">Robert Clowry</hi>, which
                                is carrying the shore end of the submarine cable proposed to be run
                                between Miami and Barbados. If the tug is permitted to proceed to
                                Key West and place the cable it now has on board, in the company
                                tank at Key West, there develops a situation in which the Western
                                Union Company has at its immediate disposal a length of cable which
                                can be quickly run from a point on the Florida coast out to sea and
                                beyond the three mile limit. The Western Union Company has shown a
                                disposition to evade the law and there arises a question as to
                                whether the presence of this cable at Key West will not give the
                                company a signal advantage in case an evasion of the law is
                                persisted in.</p>
                            <p>As matters now stand, the <hi rend="italic">Robert Clowry</hi> will
                                be held off Miami upon her arrival. A decision as to further
                                disposition of this tug is requested of the Department of State.</p>
                            <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">R. E. Coontz</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>