<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-07-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="678" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d678">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">838.51/937</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Haitian Chargé</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Blanchet</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg></opener>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-07-30"><hi rend="italic">July 30,
                                        1920</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: In connection with
                                and as a consequence of the grave incidents which I have just had
                                the honor to bring to the notice of the Department of State, my
                                Government directs me to make known to Your Excellency that the
                                profound sense of its responsibilities toward the Haitien nation and
                                its earnest desire to maintain and strengthen the good understanding
                                and spirit of cooperation that are so necessary between itself and
                                the representatives of the Government of the United States to insure
                                a normal and useful execution of the Treaty of September 16, 1915,
                                and a faithful observance of the Haitien Constitution, make it its
                                plain duty urgently to ask Your Excellency kindly to institute an
                                investigation of the facts brought to your notice.</p>
                            <p>My Government is convinced that a serious investigation immediately
                                set on foot by special agents appointed for that purpose by Your
                                Excellency, will not fail to bring out the fact, not only that the
                                demands of the representatives of the Government of the United
                                States in Haiti are severe and unwarranted, but also exclude every
                                possible aid, and hamper the national Government.</p>
                            <p>My Government is also convinced that Your Excellency will not fail to
                                appreciate how timely and urgent such investigation will be. It has,
                                therefore, instructed me to express a firm hope that Your Excellency
                                in the interest of the Government of the United States as well as
                                the correctly understood interest of the Republic of Haiti, would
                                see fit to order that measure of great justice.</p>
                            <p>I beg [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. Blanchet</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>