<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-06-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="71" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">637.116/98</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Williamson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-06-28"><hi rend="italic">June 28,
                                        1920</hi></date>.<lb/>[Received July 7.]</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 232</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In compliance with the Department’s
                                telegraphic instruction No. 97, dated June 26, 2 p.m., concerning
                                the serious rice situation in Cuba, I have the honor to report that
                                today I took up the matter fully with Doctor Montoro, Secretary to
                                the President. He stated that he was aware of the situation and of
                                the fact that in many cases Cuban importers, on account of the
                                grievous loss occasioned to them by the sudden fall in the market
                                for that commodity, were trying to evade their obligations on one
                                technicality or another. He said that the importers had come to the
                                Government several times with requests to aid them in their
                                predicament. First they had asked that the Government fix an
                                arbitrary price arrived at purely on the consideration of the figure
                                at which their contracts had been made, a procedure which, of
                                course, the President could not countenance. <pb facs="0161" n="71" xml:id="pg_71"/> They then asked that the ex-German vessels be
                                used to distribute the rice so that the price could better be
                                maintained. This also was refused.</p>
                            <p>Doctor Montoro assured me that he would “keep his eye on the courts”
                                in order that justice might be sure of enforcement.</p>
                            <p>Inquiry has elicited the statement that Cuba has sufficient rice to
                                meet her demands for a period variously estimated at from one to
                                three years. The loss to the importers in the price, not to speak of
                                the loss occasioned by weevils and the dampness which the long
                                storage will render inevitable, leads me to respectfully suggest
                                that in fairness to Cuban merchants, who in many cases it is alleged
                                have taken the rice on the advice of American exporters who
                                represented the purchases as a good investment, as well as in
                                protection of exporters in the United States, all rice shipments be
                                at once cancelled, and the grain either kept at home or diverted
                                elsewhere.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Harold L.
                                Williamson</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>