<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-11-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-11-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="728" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d728">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">438.00/104</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The French Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Jusserand</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation<note n="72" xml:id="d728fn72">File translation
                                revised.</note>]</seg></opener>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-11-13"><hi rend="italic">November 13,
                                        1919</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: In the course of a
                                conversation with the American Financial Adviser in Haiti, the
                                Chargé d’Affaires of the Republic at Port au Prince gathered the
                                impression that the Federal Government intended to set up a special
                                commission to which all claims against the Haitian Government would
                                be referred.</p>
                            <p>My Government wishes me, in this connection, to remind Your
                                Excellency, for all pertinent purposes, that so far as the French
                                claims are concerned, the question is no longer an open one, and
                                that a protocol of arbitration was signed on September 10, 1913,
                                between the Government of the Republic and the Haitian Republic, a
                                protocol which remains to be executed.</p>
                            <p>If however the Federal Government should deem it necessary to
                                constitute a new commission, my Government would not in any way <pb facs="0918" n="828" xml:id="pg_828"/> interpose obstructions,
                                but it ought to be well understood in that event that the said
                                commission shall not have cognizance of the French claims already
                                determined or arbitrated, except for the purpose of insuring their
                                settlement, and that on the other hand its jurisdiction would extend
                                to all other claims, including those which are too recent to have
                                been entered in the schedule drawn up in 1913, as also the claims of
                                Syrians, which might be presented by the Legation of France.</p>
                            <p>With regard to the composition of the commission, my Government is of
                                opinion that, besides a French representative, there should be
                                included therein a representative of a disinterested third power
                                who, by siding with the one or the other of the parties, would carry
                                the decision under every desirable safeguard. Again, my Government
                                could see no objection, should such an arrangement promote an
                                understanding, to the Haitian Government being represented on that
                                commission by an American or even to the Financial Adviser being
                                made a member.</p>
                            <p>I should be very thankful to Your Excellency if you would kindly let
                                me know whether, as my Government hopes, you will favorably
                                entertain the foregoing suggestions.</p>
                            <p>Be pleased [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Jusserand</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>