<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Cuba ( (Long) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1920v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">77</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1920-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1920-09-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1920-09-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1920-09-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="77"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d77">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">637.116/142</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Long</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1920-09-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 9, 1920</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[Received September 14.]</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 393</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>Sir:</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>As reported in previous despatches of the Legation, the President categorically
                    promised to put into effect the decree which was agreed upon on August 17th.
                    General Agramonte was not in favor of this, and threatened to resign if it were
                    effected. The President, nevertheless, stated his determination to publish the
                    decree as agreed upon even if it should result in General Agramonte’s
                    resignation.</p>
                <p>Doctor Montoro wished to save General Agramonte, and proposed that the matter
                    should be settled by means of an inter-departmental order which would not be
                    published in the official gazette, and in a quieter way would bring about the
                    same result as the decree, but would spare General Agramonte from any
                    implication of having received a bribe offered to him as reported in the
                    Legation’s despatch No. 362 of August 27th.<note n="81" xml:id="d77fn81">Not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>The order was published yesterday and was not in the form of an
                    inter-departmental order to spare General Agramonte’s feelings as originally
                    stated, but as a proclamation, and the sense of it has been very materially
                    changed. A copy of it taken from <hi rend="italic">El Mundo</hi> of the 8th
                    instant, and the English translation of it published in the Havana <hi
                        rend="italic">Post</hi> of the same date, are enclosed herewith.</p>
                <p>It will be noticed that the wording of this proclamation differs considerably
                    from the original text transmitted to the Department in the Legation’s despatch
                    No. 312 of August 3rd.<note n="81" xml:id="d77fn82">Not printed.</note> Articles
                    2, 3, 5 and 6, are materially different as they throw the entire burden of
                    clearing the docks on the American Rice Exporters.</p>
                <p>The American rice exporters cannot assume the responsibility of clearing this
                    rice off the docks, as they would thereby admit the validity of the Cuban
                    consignees refused [<hi rend="italic">refusal</hi>] to accept it. And by Article
                    6, if the rice is not removed from the docks within the time specified, the
                    decree will be cancelled.</p>
                <p>In view of these divergencies there would appear to be no alternative except to
                    insist with the President that he publish the original decree, even though it
                    might cause the resignation of General Agramonte. <pb facs="0166" n="76"
                        xml:id="pg_76"/> The present substitute appears to have been drawn up by the
                    Secretary of the Treasury, Doctor Cancio, with a view to render nugatory the
                    original decree the stipulations of which are circumvented.</p>
                <p>The first article also stipulates that the decree will be in effect only until
                    January 1st. This is not sufficient time to induce the Cuban consignees to
                    accept the merchandise sent to them, and they have thus far shown no more
                    readiness to meet their obligations than they showed three months ago. Doctor
                    Montoro stated on September 4th, that the time limit of the decree could not be
                    made longer because the authorization under which it is issued is based on
                    certain war powers given to the President, and that these expire six months
                    after the exchange of ratifications of the Peace Treaty. He explained that this
                    time limit did not extend beyond January 1st.</p>
                <p>Mr. White pointed out to him that the exchange of ratifications was effected with
                    Germany on March 8th, and, therefore, if it were based only on that the time
                    would expire in four days; but that the President had informed him that he was
                    calculating from the exchange of ratifications of the Austrian treaty, and that
                    although this treaty has been signed and ratified by Cuba and the copies sent to
                    Paris, the exchange of ratifications, nevertheless, has not yet taken place, and
                    that there is still a six months period in which the decree can run. Doctor
                    Montoro then promised to change this date when the order should be issued. When
                    the proclamation was issued the old date was left in. Doctor Montoro then stated
                    that this was done on account of the adverse comments which would be made by the
                    sugar interests, as rice is the staple article of food of the laborers and the
                        <hi rend="italic">zafra</hi> is about to begin.</p>
                <p>Doctor Montoro promised that the decree would be prolonged for the requisite
                    time. Mr. White pointed out to him that it would be much better to have it done
                    once for all rather than to make two decrees of it. Mr. White added that the
                    proclamation was very unsatisfactory and the Legation would be obliged to
                    protest against it as soon as the full report on it should be received from the
                    attorney of the American rice exporters.</p>
                <p>This matter will be taken up with the President, and a demand be made that some
                    practical solution be given immediately.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Boaz W. Long</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Executive Decree of September 6, 1920, Regulating
                            Importations of Rice</hi>
                        <note n="83" xml:id="d77fn83">Published in the Habana <hi rend="italic"
                                >Post</hi>, Sept. 8, 1920.</note>
                    </head>
                    <p>Whereas, the Secretary of State has informed this presidency of his desire
                        that a formula be found that would quickly and satisfactorily <pb
                            facs="0167" n="77" xml:id="pg_77"/> bring a settlement of the conflict
                        over the rice imported into Cuba, by virtue of sales made by American
                        exporters to local merchants and others throughout the territory of the
                        island, and on which conflict the government of the United States has
                        already acted through its diplomatic representation in this island: and,</p>
                    <p>Whereas, the Cuban minister to Washington, in a cable dated August 24,
                        confirmed by letter of August 26, which cable and letter were turned over to
                        the Department of Agriculture, Commerce and Labor, informed the Department
                        of State that he had expressly been called by the State Department of the
                        United States of America to discuss the rice question, and had been informed
                        of the desire of that Government to see a quick and satisfactory settlement
                        reached between the merchants interested: and that measures be adopted by
                        the Cuban Government that would settle the controversy, which could by no
                        means be neglected; and further urged that a prompt answer be given, as said
                        Government thought it necessary to insist that measures should be taken to
                        secure the desired settlement agreed upon, or that another be suggested that
                        would protect the interests of the American exporters involved in the
                        affair; and,</p>
                    <p>Whereas, the cable of August 24 from the Cuban minister at Washington stated
                        that the American Department of State had informed him in the interview that
                        it did not want to impose an unreasonable price on the Cuban consumer, but
                        that owing to the special circumstances of the case, a settlement of the
                        affair was urged, and that measures be taken by the Cuban government to that
                        effect; and,</p>
                    <p>Whereas, in a document approved by Dr. Lavedan, consulting attorney for the
                        American rice interests, it stated that there is a rice stock at different
                        ports of the island, and especially Havana, that far exceeds the current
                        needs of the population, and that could not be consumed in any less than
                        eight months, the stock being over one million bags, and one of the causes
                        of the harbor and waterfront congestion;</p>
                    <p>Therefore, it is advisable to state that the Cuban government has had no part
                        in bringing about the situation, which is owing to the fact that unsettled
                        market conditions caused by the European war, and the appearance of the
                        first peace crops brought about an excess of speculation between local
                        importers and exporters at different markets that has created such conflicts
                        as that of rice in other branches of the trade; and,</p>
                    <p>Whereas, the economical objections pointed out against this resolution by the
                        Secretary of Agriculture, Commerce and Labor do not meet the circumstances
                        of the unsettled market conditions that we are still suffering from on
                        account of the European war:</p>
                    <pb facs="0168" n="78" xml:id="pg_78"/>
                    <p>Therefore, by virtue of the above considerations, it is incumbent on the
                        President of the Republic to act in order to bring a settlement of the
                        controversy; and, acting under the authority granted me by Article 2 of the
                        Subsistence Law,</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">I resolve</hi>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <item>First: That from this day our Consuls and Consular Agents will not
                            vise documents in connection with rice shipments to Cuba unless so
                            authorized by cable from the Cuban government, until January 1,
                            1921.</item>
                        <item>Second: Record of rice consignments imported into Cuba to date will be
                            kept at the Department of Agriculture, Commerce and Labor, so as to
                            avoid profiteering in a food article extensively consumed in Cuba, and
                            that all such rice consignments at present in stock at docks and bonded
                            warehouses of Havana, and ports throughout the island, shall be removed
                            by importers without any delay, once all due custom obligations have
                            been complied with.</item>
                        <item>Third: That at said warehouses and others that may be bonded under the
                            responsibility of customs collectors, there shall always be sufficient
                            space to receive and store from 150,000 to 200,000 bags of rice upon
                            presentation of the importation license until the date mentioned above,
                            January 1, 1921.</item>
                        <item>Fourth: That import licenses will be issued by the Department of
                            Agriculture, Commerce and Labor on the report of the corresponding
                            Collector of Customs that there is sufficient bonded warehouse space to
                            store the amount of rice in question, either public or retained by the
                            importer.</item>
                        <item>Fifth: In the case of failure to remove rice consignments within the
                            30 days specified from the docks or bonded warehouses, storage charges
                            for the following ten days will be double, with an additional charge of
                            25 per cent for every following week of seven days of such delay.</item>
                        <item>Sixth: Failure to remove rice consignments from docks and warehouses
                            within the time specified will lead to cancellation of the measures of
                            restriction upon importation.</item>
                        <item>Seventh: Licenses will be reported to the Secretaries of State and
                            Finance.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The Secretary of State will forward a copy of this resolution to Consuls and
                        Consular Agents, and the Secretary of Finance will see that the measure is
                        observed at Customs Departments.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Signed in the <placeName type="venue"
                                >Presidential Palace</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1920-09-06">this 6th day of September of
                            1920</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. G. Menocal</hi>
                        </signed>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">President</hi>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Sanchez Agramonte</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of Agriculture, Commerce and Labor</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
