<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-04-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-04-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="188" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d188">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Proclamation No. April 19, 1918, Extending Regulations
                                Prescribing Conduct toward Alien Enemies to Include Women</hi>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1918-04-19">April 19, 1918</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">By the President of the United States of
                                America</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">A PROCLAMATION</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, by Act of Congress, approved the
                            sixteenth day of April, one thousand nine hundred and eighteen, entitled
                            “An Act to amend section four thousand and sixty-seven of the Revised
                            Statutes by extending its scope to include women”, the said section four
                            thousand and sixty-seven of the Revised Statutes is amended to read as
                            follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Whenever there is a declared war between the United States and
                                    any foreign nation or government, or any invasion or predatory
                                    incursion is perpetrated, attempted, or threatened against the
                                    territory of the United States by any foreign nation or
                                    government, and the President makes public proclamation of the
                                    event, all natives, citizens, denizens, or subjects of the
                                    hostile nation or government, being of the age of fourteen years
                                    and upwards, who shall be within the United States, and not
                                    actually naturalized, shall be liable to be apprehended,
                                    restrained, secured, and removed, as alien enemies. The
                                    President is authorized, in any such event, by his proclamation
                                    thereof, or other public act, to direct the conduct to be
                                    observed, on the part of the United States, toward the aliens
                                    who become so liable; the manner and degree of the restraint to
                                    which they shall be subject, and in what cases, and upon what
                                    security their residence shall be permitted, and to provide for
                                    the removal of those who, not being permitted to reside within
                                    the United States, refuse or neglect to depart therefrom; and to
                                    establish any other regulations which are found necessary in the
                                    premises and for the public safety;</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, by sections four thousand and
                            sixty-eight, four thousand and sixty-nine, and four thousand and
                            seventy, of the Revised Statutes, further provision is made relative to
                            alien enemies;</p>
                        <pb facs="0277" n="193" xml:id="pg_193"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">And whereas</hi> a state of war has heretofore been
                            declared and proclaimed to exist between the United States and the
                            Imperial German Government and between the United States and the
                            Imperial and Royal Austro-Hungarian Government;</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Now, therefore, I, <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Woodrow Wilson</persName></hi>, President of the United States
                            of America, acting under and by virtue of the authority vested in me by
                            the Constitution of the United States and the said sections of the
                            Revised Statutes, do hereby further proclaim and direct that-the conduct
                            to be observed on the part of the United States towards all natives,
                            citizens, denizens, or subjects of Germany or Austria-Hungary of the age
                            of fourteen years and upwards, who shall be within the United States and
                            not actually naturalized, shall be as follows:</p>
                        <p>All such natives, citizens, denizens or subjects of Germany or
                            Austria-Hungary are enjoined to preserve the peace towards the United
                            States and to refrain from crime against the public safety, and from
                            violating the laws of the United States and of the States and
                            Territories thereof, and to refrain from actual hostility or giving
                            information, aid or comfort to the enemies of the United States, and to
                            comply strictly with the regulations which are hereby or which have been
                            or may be from time to time promulgated by the President; and so long as
                            they shall conduct themselves in accordance with law, they shall be
                            undisturbed in the peaceful pursuit of their lives and occupations and
                            be accorded the consideration due to all peaceful and law-abiding
                            persons, except so far as restrictions may be necessary for their own
                            protection and for the safety of the United States; and towards such of
                            said persons as conduct themselves in accordance with law, all citizens
                            of the United States are enjoined to preserve the peace and to treat
                            them with all such friendliness as may be compatible with loyalty and
                            allegiance to the United States.</p>
                        <p>And all of such natives, citizens, denizens or subjects of Germany or
                            Austria-Hungary who fail to conduct themselves as so enjoined, in
                            addition to all other penalties prescribed by law, shall be liable to
                            restraint, or to give security, or to remove and depart from the United
                            States in the manner prescribed by sections four thousand and sixty-nine
                            and four thousand and seventy of the Revised Statutes, and as prescribed
                            in the regulations duly promulgated by the President;</p>
                        <p>And pursuant to the authority vested in me, I hereby declare and
                            proclaim, as necessary in the premises and for the public safety, that
                            Regulations 1 to 12 inclusive in the Proclamation issued by me under
                            date of April 6th, 1917,<note n="1" xml:id="d188fn3">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_165">p.
                                165</ref>.</note> and Regulations 13 to 20 inclusive in <pb facs="0278" n="194" xml:id="pg_194"/> the Proclamation issued by me
                            under date of November 16th, 1917<note n="1" xml:id="d188fn4">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_180">p.
                                180</ref>.</note> shall be and they hereby are extended to and
                            declared applicable to all natives, citizens, denizens or subjects of
                            Germany, being females of the age of fourteen years and upwards, who
                            shall be within the United States and not actually naturalized;
                            provided, that this extension of Regulation 4 of the Proclamation issued
                            by me under date of April 6th, 1917 shall not become effective until
                            such time as may be fixed and declared by the Attorney General of the
                            United States.</p>
                        <p>And pursuant to the authority vested in me, I hereby declare and
                            proclaim, as necessary in the premises and for the public safety, that
                            Regulations 1 to 3 inclusive in the Proclamation issued by me under date
                            of December 11th, 1917<note n="2" xml:id="d188fn5">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_185">p.
                                185</ref>.</note> shall be and they are hereby extended to and
                            declared applicable to all natives, citizens, denizens or subjects of
                            Austria-Hungary, being females of the age of fourteen years and upwards,
                            who shall be within the United States and not actually naturalized.</p>
                        <p>This proclamation and the Regulations herein contained shall extend and
                            apply to all land and water, continental or insular, in any way within
                            the jurisdiction of the United States.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">In witness whereof</hi>, I have hereunto set my
                            hand and caused the seal of the United States to be affixed.</p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="margin">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>]</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Done</hi> in the District of Columbia, this
                            nineteenth day of April, in the year of our Lord one thousand nine
                            hundred and eighteen, and of the independence of the United States the
                            one hundred and forty-second.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WW1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Woodrow Wilson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>By the President: <lb/>
                                <persName corresp="#p_PFL1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank L. Polk</hi>
                                </persName>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary of State.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>