<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-06-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="320" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d320">
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Proclamation No. 1464, June 28, 1918, Taking over for
                                the United States Title to and Possession of Property on the Hudson
                                River Owned by the North German Lloyd Dock Co. and the
                                Hamburg-American Line Terminal and Navigation Co.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1918-06-28">June 28, 1918</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">By the President of the United States of
                                America</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">A PROCLAMATION</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi> the Act of Congress making
                            appropriations to supply urgent deficiencies in appropriations for the
                            fiscal year ending June 30, 1918, and prior fiscal years, on account of
                            war expenses and for other purposes, approved March 28, 1918 (Public—No.
                            109—65th Congress), contains the following provisions: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“The President is authorized to acquire the title to the docks,
                                    piers, warehouses, wharves, and terminal equipment and
                                    facilities on the Hudson River now owned by the North German
                                    Lloyd Dock <pb facs="0387" n="303" xml:id="pg_303"/> Company and
                                    the Hamburg-American Line Terminal and Navigation Company, two
                                    corporations of the State of New Jersey, if he shall deem it
                                    necessary for the national security and defense; <hi rend="italic">Provided</hi>, That if such property can not
                                    be procured by purchase, then the President is authorized and
                                    empowered to take over for the United States the immediate
                                    possession and title thereof. If any such property shall be
                                    taken over as aforesaid, the United States shall make just
                                    compensation therefor to be determined by the President. Upon
                                    the taking over of said property by the President, as aforesaid,
                                    the title to all such property so taken over shall immediately
                                    vest in the United States: <hi rend="italic">Provided
                                        further</hi>, That section three hundred and fifty-five of
                                    the Revised Statutes of the United States shall not apply to any
                                    expenditures herein or hereafter authorized in connection with
                                    the property acquired.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Now, therefore, I, <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Woodrow Wilson</persName></hi>, President of the United States
                            of America, pursuant to the authority vested in me by the said Act of
                            Congress approved March 28, 1918, do hereby determine and declare that
                            the acquisition of title to the foregoing docks, piers, warehouses,
                            wharves, and terminal equipment and facilities, is necessary for the
                            National security and defense, and I do hereby take over for the United
                            States of America the immediate possession and title thereof, including
                            all leaseholds, easements, rights of way, riparian rights and other
                            rights, estates and interests therein or appurtenant thereto.</p>
                        <p>Just compensation for the property hereby taken over will be hereafter
                            determined and paid.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">In witness whereof</hi>, I have hereunto set my
                            hand and caused the seal of the United States to be affixed.</p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="margin">[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal</hi>]</seg>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Done</hi> in the District of Columbia this
                            twenty-eighth day of June, one thousand nine hundred and eighteen, and
                            of the Independence of the United States, one hundred and forty-two.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WW1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Woodrow Wilson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>By the President: <lb/>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LR1">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                                </persName>
                                <lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>