<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-10-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="334" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d334">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72114/4036</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Swiss Chargé</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_OF1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Oederlin</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <p>The Secretary of State presents his compliments to the Chargé d’Affaires
                                <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> of Switzerland, in charge of
                            German interests in the United States, and has the honor to acknowledge
                            the receipt of his memorandum of August 21, 1918 (IX–Fort
                                Oglethorpe),<note n="1" xml:id="d334fn1">Not printed.</note>
                            inquiring on behalf of the committee of internees at the War Prison
                            Barracks, Fort Oglethorpe, Ga., whether the exemption of $500 which is
                            granted the internees by the Alien Property Custodian, would be
                            increased when their present available funds are exhausted.</p>
                        <p>In reply the Secretary of State informs the Chargé d’Affaires that it is
                            impossible for the Alien Property Custodian to increase the amount of
                            exemption for the reason that the Trading with the Enemy Act does not
                            permit any such arrangement. After the property of the enemy has been
                            delivered to the Alien Property Custodian, its distribution can, under
                            the provisions of the act, only be effected by an act of Congress after
                            the war, except that persons not enemies claiming an interest therein or
                            having a claim against the same, may pursue the remedy provided by
                            section 9 of the Trading with the Enemy Act, and with the assent of the
                            enemy person the President may order that the whole or part of such
                            property may be paid over to such claimant. This power the President has
                            delegated to the Department of Justice.</p>
                        <p>Whether a claim against such a fund presented on behalf of the dependent
                            family of an interned enemy would be held to come within the provisions
                            referred to above and would be entertained by the Department of Justice,
                            can be determined only when a specific claim is presented to be passed
                            upon.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-10-09"><hi rend="italic">October 9, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>