<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Switzerland ( (Stovall) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Supp02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-08-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-08-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="72"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72114A/74</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Switzerland</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_SPA1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Stovall</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-08-03">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 3, 1918</hi>
                        </date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received August 4, 9.34
                        p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4187. Department’s 1728, April 5. Pay of officer prisoners of war. I have
                    received following reply from German Government through Spanish Embassy: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The German Government agrees to the proposals of the Government of the
                            United States of America relative to the pay of officers who have fallen
                            into captivity on either side. The pay to be as follows: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>350 marks or $83.35 monthly— <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>First lieutenants, lieutenants and feldwebelleutnants
                                            of the German Army; first lieutenants, lieutenants,
                                            halboberleutnants and halbleutnants of the German
                                            Navy.</item>
                                        <pb facs="0128" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>First and second lieutenants of the American Army and
                                            the lieutenants (junior grade) of the American
                                            Navy.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>400 marks or $95.25 monthly— <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Captains, rittmeister and higher grades of officers of
                                            the German Army; kapitänleutnants and captains, also the
                                            higher grades of officers of the German Navy and the
                                            marine troops.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Captains and higher grades of officers of the American
                                            Army; the officers of the American Navy with the rank of
                                            lieutenant (senior grade) and higher, as well as
                                            officers of the American Marine Corps of corresponding
                                            rank.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>As regards the other grades referred to by the American Government as
                            class three, for which the German Government had proposed two-thirds of
                            the lower rate of pay for officers, while the American Government wishes
                            to pay these grades on an equal footing with lieutenants, a definite
                            decision is reserved which will shortly be made public. It is proposed
                            that these grades be given in the meantime two-thirds of the pay of the
                            lower grade and that the regular pay of officers be put in force
                            immediately independent of this question.</p>
                        <p>These rates of pay apply to all officer prisoners of war, regardless of
                            whether they are active officers, officers of the reserve grade,
                            officers of disposition or retired, or whether they are retired officers
                            of disposition, and it applies to the same class of officers who are
                            interned as civilian prisoners and whose rank is certified by the
                            government of the home state.</p>
                        <p>The German Government agrees that the pay to the amount now agreed upon
                            shall be paid for the time already passed in imprisonment in so far as
                            the payment has not taken place at all during this time or not to the
                            amount of the rates now agreed upon. In paying these sums, however, such
                            sums are to be subtracted which were paid temporarily by the protecting
                            power to the officers in place of the pay they had not received, as well
                            as the surplus amounts which were paid by the American Government to
                            German officers beyond the rates now fixed. The German Government
                            undertakes that these excess payments will be refunded after the
                            conclusion of peace.</p>
                        <p>These payments now agreed upon will be ordered as soon as telegraphic
                            information has arrived from the American Government that the
                            regulations in question in the sense of the foregoing remarks have been
                            made for the German officers in America.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SPA1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Stovall</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
