<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-06-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-06-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="833" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d833">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 811.2222/13528e</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                            President <persName corresp="#p_WW1" type="to">Wilson</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-06-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 4, 1918</hi></date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The President</hi>: On March 20, you requested the
                        Senate to return to you for reconsideration the two conventions between the
                        United States and Great Britain signed on the 19th day of February, 1918, in
                        respect to military service of British subjects in the United States and
                        citizens of the United States in Great Britain and Canada, which conventions
                        had been transmitted by you to the Senate on February 20, to receive the
                        advice and consent of the Senate to their ratification. On March 21, the
                        Senate returned to you these conventions, and since that date negotiations
                        with the British Government have been pressed with a view to making certain
                        changes in their phraseology. These negotiations having been concluded, the
                        undersigned, the Secretary of State, has the honor to resubmit to you the
                        amended conventions<note n="1" xml:id="d833fn1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_708">pp. 708</ref>, <ref target="#pg_714">714</ref>.</note> with a view to their transmission
                        to the Senate, unless you perceive objection thereto, for the advice and
                        consent of that body to their ratification. I also enclose an exchange of
                            notes<note n="2" xml:id="d833fn2">
                            <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_712">p. 712</ref>.</note>
                        relative to article 1 of the convention relating to citizens of the United
                        States in Great Britain, which notes are self-explanatory.</p>
                    <p>In the renewed negotiations it was sought to modify the earlier conventions,
                        if possible, by having inserted the American age limits for compulsory
                        military service in the United States; by making the conventions
                        inapplicable to subjects of Great Britain who were not liable to compulsory
                        military service at home; by amending or omitting the article in respect to
                        the determination of questions of “dual nationality,” and by modifying the
                        clause providing for the termination of the convention. In all these points
                        the negotiations have proceeded satisfactorily, except as to the first, in
                        respect to which it has again been necessary to make an exchange of notes
                        setting forth the reasons for the omission in the British convention of the
                        age limits within which American citizens in Great Britain would be subject
                        to compulsory military service. The conventions have also been modified in
                        order to make them applicable to subjects of Great Britain in the United
                        States from parts of the British Dominions which have adopted or may
                        hereafter adopt compulsory military service, and also to citizens of the
                        United States in Great Britain or Canada within the age limits which might
                        hereafter be adopted for compulsory military service in the United
                        States.</p>
                    <pb facs="0785" n="701" xml:id="pg_701"/>
                    <p>A few minor verbal changes which it is not necessary to mention specifically
                        have also been made in the interest of precision and clearness of
                        expression.</p>
                    <p>Respectfully submitted.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_LR1">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert Lansing</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>