<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-07-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="865" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d865">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 811.2226/180</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The French Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_JJJ1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Jusserand</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-07-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 3, 1918</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received July 8</hi>]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>: By a note dated the 7th of
                        last month, Your Excellency was pleased to inform me that the President of
                        the <pb facs="0831" n="747" xml:id="pg_747"/> United States as Commander in
                        Chief of the armed forces of the United States had authorized you to propose
                        to me a settlement, by exchange of notes, of the question of delivering the
                        deserters and absentees belonging to the American or French military forces
                        operating in France. Your Excellency communicated at the same time to me the
                        wording of the contemplated arrangement of which I reproduce the French text
                        herein below.</p>
                    <p>[Here follows French version of English text quoted in the preceding
                        document.]</p>
                    <p>Duly authorized thereto by my Government, I have the honor to inform Your
                        Excellency that those terms are accepted by it and that, conformably to the
                        suggestion made by the Federal Government the provisions therein contained
                        are from this moment put into force and effect.</p>
                    <p>In taking this action, I am directed to point out to the Federal Government
                        that, as Your Excellency will understand, it is only by reason of the
                        military interest involved in the question, that the Government of the
                        Republic accepts American military policing in the zone of the interior.</p>
                    <p>Be pleased to accept [etc.]</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_JJJ1">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Jusserand</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>