<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Switzerland ( (Wilson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Supp02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d94</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">94</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1917-12-11T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1917-12-11T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-12-11T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-12-11T11:00:00-05:00" n="94"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d94">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 763.72114/3099</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Switzerland</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_WHR1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-12-11T17:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 11, 1917, 5 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received December 13, 7.25 a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2213. My 1510, August 24, regard proposed conference with Germany on prisoner
                    matters. Two such conferences now being held Berne. First, between British and
                    Turks, takes place one room, four British delegates, of whom two Foreign Office,
                    two military, five Turks, sitting under presidency of Swiss military surgeon,
                    Colonel <persName>Hauser</persName>, also representative Swiss Red Cross
                    present. Delegates address chair, not each other. Subjects treated are: (1)
                    general treatment prisoners; (2) release of invalids; (3) exchange of civilians.
                    Progress slow as important questions referred to both Governments. Second,
                    between French and Germans, also held under chairmanship of Colonel
                        <persName>Hauser</persName> but delegates do not meet personally though
                    occupying adjacent offices in same building. Swiss chairman serves as medium.
                    Method appears cumbrous and <pb facs="0150" n="66" xml:id="pg_66"/> wasteful of
                    time but considered advisable by French Government. Two French delegates, both
                    Foreign Office specialists in prisoner matters, including Panafieu, ex-minister;
                    three German, of whom two military, one Foreign Office. This conference so far
                    has only considered questions of exchange and release but expects to take up
                    general treatment and other topics later. Both conferences likely to last some
                    weeks. Recommend serious consideration of similar scheme to reach agreement for
                    our prisoners. Berne or Geneva probably best place for meeting and believed
                    Swiss officials from previous experience especially suited to act as
                    intermediaries. Am advised that Spanish Embassy, Berlin, has created new special
                    department for American prisoners in charge of Minister Delgado, who expresses
                    anxiety to comply with our wishes in every respect and has already suggested
                    that all American prisoners be housed in separate camp.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_WHR1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
