<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1964-10-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1964-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="47" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d47">
                        <head>47. Report Prepared in the Department of State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d47fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1964–66, POL 17–6 <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Secret; No Foreign <gloss target="#t_Dissem1">Dissem</gloss>. No drafting information
                                appears on the memorandum but it is attached to a letter of
                                transmittal from the Director of the Bureau of Intelligence and
                                Research, <persName>George C. Denney, Jr.</persName>, to the
                                Director of Security of the Central Intelligence Agency, Howard
                                Osborn. None of the 28 attached annexes is printed.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1964-10-02">October 2, 1964</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">ESTIMATE OF DAMAGE TO U.S. FOREIGN POLICY INTERESTS</p>
                        <p rend="center">(From Net of Listening Devices in U.S. Embassy Moscow)</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The results of our review of the political effects of the bugging of our
                            Moscow Embassy are paradoxical. On the one hand, in the judgment of the
                            National Security Agency and the Central Intelligence Agency, the
                            Soviets achieved a major intelligence breakthrough, i.e., for a period
                            of years they had the capability to read most, if not all, of our
                            telegraphic messages between Washington and Moscow and between
                            Washington and posts in Eastern Europe. On the other hand an extensive
                            review of major crises and negotiations over the past twelve years does
                            not provide evidence that the Soviets made use of knowledge thus gained
                            to the detriment of our interests.</p>
                        <p>An explanation for this paradox may be that the Soviets valued the source
                            far more than the use of any particular piece of information they got
                            from it. In order to keep us from discovering their intelligence coup
                            the Soviets appear to have sacrificed many of the specific gains they
                            might have made, and eschewed actions that might have given them away.
                            We have not found instances where a specific Soviet action can be
                            clearly attributed to a particular American message they may have
                            intercepted, and we believe it likely that Moscow avoided taking such
                            actions out of fear that they might compromise their operation. But the
                            fact that damage to American political interests was not so direct and
                            gross as to be readily demonstrable does not mean that there was none.
                            In considering the possible impact which information derived from
                            bugging had upon Soviet policymakers’ thinking, we find large unknown
                            areas. In some instances Soviet awareness of American firmness may have
                            redounded to our advantage. On balance, however, we must conclude that
                            Soviet leaders gained considerable advantage in their dealings with us,
                            and, over time, they may have felt free to pursue more assertive
                            policies because they had a clearer idea of what our reaction might
                            be.</p>
                        <pb facs="0140" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Extensive Compromise</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_NSA1">NSA</gloss> assessment, the assessments by
                            State Department security experts and information which <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> acquired from a defector make it
                            virtually certain that extensive quantities of classified information
                            were compromised as a result of the Soviet microphone operation. [<hi rend="italic">8½ lines of source text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>The classified material compromised included Top Secret, Secret and
                            Confidential information. According to the definition of these
                            classifications contained in the Department’s security regulations
                            pursuant to law, the classifying officer is obliged to assign these
                            classifications when in his judgment the unauthorized disclosure of the
                            information could, with regard to U.S. foreign policy and defense
                            interests, be “prejudicial” (Confidential), result in “serious damage”
                            (Secret) or cause “exceptionally grave damage” (Top Secret). Thus, if a
                            message was correctly classified in these categories, its revelation to
                            the Soviet Union by definition could cause damage to the United States
                            although the Soviets were inhibited from exercising to the full their
                            potential to damage our interests. Some messages during this period
                            1952–62 were no doubt overclassified, but even if considerable allowance
                            is made for the bad habits of many officers in this respect, small
                            comfort can be derived.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Direct, Visible Damage</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The damage review described above, which was based upon the worst-case
                            assumption that everything had been compromised, found little evidence
                            of political damage. Indeed, some of the officers working on the
                            political assessment found it difficult to believe that an extensive
                            compromise had in fact occurred. No instance could be found in which
                            Moscow was shown to have made a specific decision detrimental to U.S.
                            interest on the basis of information derived from reading particular
                            messages.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Limits on Soviet Use of Information</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Soviets probably regarded their microphone installation as a major
                            intelligence asset. Certainly if the circumstances had been reversed the
                            United States Government would have thought so. Such a Soviet judgment
                            would have led to a policy of self-denial of use of the information
                            derived. Soviet intelligence officers may well have hoped that this
                            source of information might give them advance warning in the event that
                            the United States ever decided to attack the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, and they would have been reluctant to jeopardize the
                            source. In fact the very thing the Department’s reviewers looked for-a
                            Soviet action directly attributable to an intercepted message-would be
                            the very thing which a Soviet intelligence officer would have resisted
                            hardest-the use of information in a manner which might make us suspect
                            the source.</p>
                        <pb facs="0141" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/>
                        <p>The one instance in which a Departmental reviewer concluded that an
                            intercepted American message probably altered the course of negotiation
                            involved possible initiation of hostilities. The review of the Korean
                            armistice negotiations suggested that Soviet interception of a May 23,
                            1953 cable from the Department to Moscow revealing our contingency plans
                            to resume hostilities if our forthcoming proposal was not accepted may
                            have been the determining factor in prompting Moscow to accept a
                            settlement.</p>
                        <p>We know that Soviet intelligence regarded information derived from our
                            telegrams as especially sensitive, and we suspect that many of the
                            lower-ranking officials who conducted negotiations on such issues as the
                            hot line or the consular convention were never privy to the operation.
                            When <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> told Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> that he read his
                            message opposing sale of a large diameter pipe to the Soviet Union
                            (though <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName> did not
                            describe the message accurately), he was doubtless guilty of a serious
                            breach of security.</p>
                        <p>In addition to their reluctance to jeopardize their source of potentially
                            invaluable information, the Soviets were probably also concerned-though
                            to a much lesser extent-over possible embarrassment in being caught.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Operational vs. Background Information</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Both our review of the messages themselves and inferences about Soviet
                            handling of the information support the conclusion that Moscow derived
                            very little, if any, operational information upon which they based
                            specific actions.</p>
                        <p>They always had the hope that by preserving the source, they might one
                            day derive extremely useful operational information, namely, advance
                            warning of an American attack, and that very hope would have made them
                            very reluctant to sacrifice their source in exploiting it for lesser
                            purposes.</p>
                        <p>But apart from operational information, the Soviets did over the years
                            acquire a good deal of background information. No single piece of this
                            information would necessarily have altered particular decisions, but
                            this kind of information would have given the Soviets some valuable
                            knowledge of United States policymaking processes, some psychological
                            advantages and may over the longer run have strengthened Moscow’s
                            capability for confronting the United States.</p>
                        <p>If the Soviets read our notes before they were delivered, they may have
                            had a few extra hours to consider their responses which doubtless made
                            their own decision-making easier, though that may well have been to our
                            advantage at times. In reading our reporting messages, the Soviets would
                            have learned no little about how our foreign service operates, about the
                            personalities of various American officers and about <pb facs="0142" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> the kinds of démarches or talking points
                            which did or did not impress us. Even though they refrained from taking
                            any direct action on the basis of information in our messages the
                            Soviets would have derived either confirmation or disproof of their
                            estimates about our foreign policy based upon other sources of
                            information.</p>
                        <p>In the aggregate, background information was probably useful to the top
                            Soviet leadership. For example, in the period after the Sputnik and the
                            firing of the first Soviet <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss> our
                            estimates of Soviet strategic missiles were inaccurate. The Soviets
                            would not have learned the details of our estimates from their
                            microphone operations, but they probably would have had confirmation of
                            their impression based upon other sources that United States policy was
                            being made on the basis of estimates of the military balance which erred
                            in their favor. Also of general background utility would have been the
                            knowledge required of differences among the United States and its
                            Allies.</p>
                        <p>In attempting to assess the impact which background information may have
                            had on Soviet policy, we are faced with imponderables. We have no way of
                            proving how much of a role background information derived from bugging
                            played in the totality of information used by the Soviet decision
                            makers. We suspect that in general Moscow derived a clearer impression
                            of the limits of American tolerance for possible mischief. In many
                            instances it was doubtless to our advantage that the Soviet leadership
                            realized the dangers and stopped short of precipitating potentially
                            grave situations. At the same time, a better estimate of the limits of
                            safety may have tempted the Soviets to play a bit closer to the limits
                            than they might otherwise have done.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>