<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The American Representative on the Advisory Council for Italy ( (Murphy)) to
                    the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1005</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1005</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-04-10T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-04-10T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="rec4kNZ3bN6ephN7u" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027420"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Coalition government</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-10T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-10T03:00:00-05:00" n="1005"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1005">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">865.01/2316: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The American Representative on the Advisory Council for
                        Italy</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="23" xml:id="d1005fn23">Mr. Murphy was succeeded as American
                        Representative on the Advisory Council for Italy by Alexander C. Kirk, who
                        was appointed on March 31 but did not arrive at his post until April
                        29.</note>
                    <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Salerno</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-10T10:00:00+02:00"
                            >April 10, 1944—10 a.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 9 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>During course of a long conversation with Count Carlo Sforza on April 7 he said
                    that he could not describe with sufficient urgency the necessity of immediate
                    action by Great Britain and the United States to avoid all of Italy falling
                    under complete domination of Soviet Union. He said that extraordinary progress
                    had been made in Italy by Communist Party particularly since arrival of
                    Togliatti (Ercoli) whom he described as the brains and leader of the
                    organization stating that Tedeschi is a gangster type lacking in education and
                    playing a minor role. Sforza said that the problem may seem to the United States
                    in its security one of minor significance. He sees in it, however, the first
                    step in what he calls the process of the “Diplomatic Sovietization of Europe”.
                    Same process in his opinion will be applied to the Balkans, France, and Spain. A
                    different procedure will be applied to Germany where more direct and destructive
                    methods will be used. In his opinion the Comintern remains the active force it
                    has been in the past and the public statements regarding its dissolution are
                    pure hypocrisy. Sforza became bitter in his denunciation of Prime Minister
                    Churchill whose obtuseness he blames for failure to comprehend true nature of
                    problem. He realizes he said that Churchill is opposed to Communistic
                    encroachment in Central and Eastern Europe but he maintains that Churchill fails
                    to grasp necessity of pursuing a different line of action than he has adopted.
                    He asserts that Churchill’s blind and stubborn adherence to the notion of
                    supporting <pb facs="1103" n="1091" xml:id="pg_1091"/> present King and a weak
                    Badoglio government has given the Communists an ideal and fertile field for
                    their development. Ercoli, he said, has been conducting negotiations with
                    Badoglio which in Sforza’s opinion will place the eventual power squarely in
                    hands of Italian Communist Party. The latter, he states, is growing by leaps and
                    bounds and daily before the central office of the Communist Party is a long line
                    of applicants, former [<hi rend="italic">applicants for</hi>] membership in the
                    party including every type of citizens: businessmen, professional men and
                    artisans. Since Ercoli’s arrival the known funds of the party have increased to
                    25,000,000 lire.</p>
                <p>Sforza stated that he has had several conversations with Togliatti and Tedeschi.
                    The former suggested that in the new government the Communists want to see
                    Sforza included since he is an old tried anti-Fascist but they made the
                    suggestion that they would like to have the portfolio of Foreign Affairs and
                    hoped that Sforza would not insist on that particular portfolio.</p>
                <p>Sforza pleaded that both Britain and the United States take a more realistic view
                    immediately and intervene for purpose of bringing pressure upon King to retire
                    now and agree to appointment of Humbert as Lieutenant General of the Eealm. He
                    states, however, [<hi rend="italic">moreover?</hi>], that he has had exchanges
                    with Humbert and is convinced that Humbert is willing to work with him in the
                    formation of a strong liberal coalition government.</p>
                <p>Sforza urged again that we give prompt consideration to question whether it is in
                    Anglo-American interest to permit Soviet Union to lay cornerstone of its plan to
                    construct a diplomatic hegemony of Europe.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Murphy</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
