<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Department of State to the British Embassy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d110</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">110</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-10-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-10-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="110"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d110">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.796/8–3144</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                            <gloss type="to">British Embassy</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The British proposal for an understanding between the United States and British
                    Governments relating to the acquisition of air transport rights on a
                    non-exclusive basis, received in the Department of State on August 31, 1944, is
                    acceptable subject to certain proposed amendments.</p>
                <p>With reference to paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the Government of the
                    United States feels that it could not enter into a commitment to prevent United
                    States air transport undertakings from concluding any agreements with foreign
                    governments. However, it is fully disposed to adopt all practical means to
                    prevent United States air transport companies from concluding operating
                    agreements with foreign governments which would preclude such governments from
                    granting rights to the United Kingdom.</p>
                <p>As to paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) it is thought that the definition of
                    an air transport undertaking should include not only a company already engaged
                    in air transport, but one which may be seeking to engage in such transport.</p>
                <p>With regard to paragraph 2(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) it is the view of the United
                    States Government that there should be a more definite provision for possible
                    termination of the understanding, and it is thought that the understanding
                    should remain in force until the Government of the United States and the British
                    Government become bound by a future international agreement relating to the
                    operation of international air transport services, or until the understanding is
                    terminated on reasonable notice given by either Government to the other
                    Government.</p>
                <p>In line with the foregoing suggestions there is attached a draft of a suggested
                    form of exchange of notes for giving effect to the proposed understanding.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-10-02">October 2,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0177" n="165" xml:id="pg_165"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 1]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Proposed Note From the <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">British Ambassador</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Excellency</hi>: I have the honor to refer to
                        negotiations which have taken place between the Government of the United
                        States of America and His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom for the
                        reaching of a reciprocal agreement concerning the acquisition of air
                        transport operating rights on a non-exclusive basis.</p>
                    <p>It is understood that it has been agreed in the course of these negotiations,
                        now concluded, that so far as concerns the obligations to be assumed by the
                        Government of the United States of America this agreement shall be as
                        follows:</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article 1</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The Government of the United States of America undertakes that, except
                            after consultation with His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom,
                            it will not conclude any agreement with the government of any foreign
                            country which would preclude the government of that country from
                            granting flying rights to, in, and over its territory, to United Kingdom
                            air transport undertakings.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>The Government of the United States of America undertakes that it will
                            also by all practical means prevent United States air transport
                            undertakings from concluding any such agreement with the government of
                            any foreign country, except after consultation between the Government of
                            the United States of America and the Government of the United
                            Kingdom.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">Article 2</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>For the purposes of this understanding the expression “United States air
                            transport undertaking” means any company engaged wholly or partly in air
                            transport, or seeking to engage in such transport, which is incorporated
                            in the United States of America or in any territory or possession within
                            its jurisdiction.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p rend="center">Article 3</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The present understanding will remain in force until the Government of
                            the United States of America and His Majesty’s Government in the United
                            Kingdom become bound by a future international agreement relating to the
                            operation of international air transport services, or until the present
                            understanding is terminated on sixty days’ notice given by either
                            Government to the other Government.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>I shall be glad to have you inform me whether it is understood by His
                        Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom that the terms of the reciprocal
                        agreement so far as they constitute the obligations to be assumed by the
                        Government of the United States of America are as above set forth. If so, it
                        is suggested that your reply setting forth the corresponding obligations to
                        be assumed by His Majesty’s Government constitute the reciprocal agreement
                        to become effective <pb facs="0178" n="166" xml:id="pg_166"/> on the date of
                        your reply. If His Majesty’s Government concurs in this suggestion the
                        Government of the United States of America will regard the reciprocal
                        agreement as becoming effective on that date.</p>
                    <p>Accept [etc.]</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure 2]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Proposed Note From the <gloss type="from">British
                                Ambassador</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt
                        of your note of . . . . . . . in regard to the reaching of a reciprocal
                        agreement between His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom and the
                        Government of the United States of America, concerning the acquisition of
                        air transport operating rights on a non-exclusive basis.</p>
                    <p>In your note of . . . . . . . you have set forth your understanding of the
                        obligations to be assumed by the Government of the United States of America
                        in the carrying out of the terms of the reciprocal agreement which has been
                        the subject of negotiations between the two Governments, now concluded.</p>
                    <p>I am instructed by my Government to state that the corresponding obligations
                        to be assumed by His Majesty’s Government under the reciprocal agreement are
                        as set forth below:</p>
                    <p rend="center">Article 1</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom undertake that, except
                            after consultation with the Government of the United States of America,
                            they will not conclude any agreement with the government of any foreign
                            country which would preclude the government of that country from
                            granting flying rights to, in, and over its territory, to United States
                            air transport undertakings.</item>
                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom undertake that they
                            will also by all practical means prevent United Kingdom air transport
                            undertakings from concluding any such agreement with the government of
                            any foreign country except after consultation between the Government of
                            the United Kingdom and the Government of the United States of
                            America.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">Article 2</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>For the purposes of this understanding, the expression “United Kingdom
                            air transport undertaking” means any company engaged wholly or partly in
                            air transport, or seeking to engage in such transport, which is
                            incorporated in the United Kingdom or in any British colony, overseas
                            territory, protectorate, protected state or mandated territory in
                            respect of which the mandate is exercised by the Government of the
                            United Kingdom.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p rend="center">Article 3</p>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The present understanding will remain in force until His Majesty’s
                            Government in the United Kingdom and the Government of the <pb
                                facs="0179" n="167" xml:id="pg_167"/> United States of America
                            become bound by a future international agreement relating to the
                            operation of international air transport services, or until the present
                            understanding is terminated on sixty days’ notice given by either
                            Government to the other Government.</p>
                    </quote>
                    <p>I am further instructed to inform you that my Government concur in your
                        suggestion that the reciprocal agreement become effective on the date of
                        this reply, and will accordingly regard it as becoming effective on this
                        date.</p>
                    <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>[Subsequent correspondence on this subject dealt specifically with
                            individual Near Eastern countries. See section entitled “Representations
                            to the United Kingdom and Iran regarding American post-war civil air
                            rights in Iran, especially at Abadan Island,” <ref
                                target="frus1944v05#pg_486">volume V, pages 486</ref> ff.; also,
                            section entitled “Representations to Egypt and the United Kingdom
                            regarding American post-war civil air rights in Egypt,” <ref
                                target="frus1944v05#pg_56">
                                <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pages 56</ref> ff.]</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
