<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Harriman) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1155</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1155</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-01-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-01-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receKRNx87Ug7K5bW" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="prisoners-of-war" subject="prisoners-of-war" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971" lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-01-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-01-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="1155"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1155">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00116 European War 1939/1280: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-01-26">January 26,
                            1944</date>.<lb/>[Received January 27—8:37 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>260. <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Izvestiya</hi> for
                    January 26 devote over two and one-half pages to publication of the report of
                    the Special Commission for the Investigation of the Shooting of the Polish
                    Captured Officers in the Katyn Forest.<note n="57" xml:id="d1155fn57">
                        <p>The Moscow press on January 17, 1944, announced the formation of this
                            Special Commission by decision of the Extraordinary State Commission for
                            the Establishment and Investigation of the Crimes Committed by the
                            German Fascist Invaders and Their Accomplices, which had itself been
                            created by an ukaz of November 4,1942. See <ref
                                target="frus1942v03#pg_473">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi
                                    rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 473</ref>.</p>
                        <p>On September 18, 1951, a “Select Committee to Conduct an Investigation of
                            the Facts, Evidence and Circumstances of the Katyn Forest Massacre” was
                            unanimously authorized under House Resolution 390, 82d Congress, 1st
                            session. Extensive hearings were held by the Committee between October
                            11, 1951, and November 14, 1952. The testimonies received, together with
                            voluminous accompanying documents, were published under the full title
                            of <hi rend="italic">Hearings before the Select Committee to Conduct an
                                Investigation of the Facts, Evidence and Circumstances of the Katyn
                                Forest Massacre</hi> (Washington, Government Printing Office, 1952,
                            7 parts, 2362 pages). The text of the report of January 24, 1944, by the
                            Soviet Special Commission is printed in pt. 3, pp. 228–247 (Russian text
                            reproduced, pp. 248–309).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Both papers publish front page editorials on this subject. Editorials declare
                    that investigation establishes the truth regarding the German killing of the
                    Polish officers.</p>
                <p>They state that Polish prisoners who had been working in a Soviet camp fell into
                    the hands of the Germans during the Red Army retreat. The Germans, carrying out
                    their policy of physical annihilation of the Poles, in the autumn of ’41 shot
                    the Polish prisoners who had been in the captured camp. The Germans, in order to
                    conceal their crime and also to achieve their foul political aims, resorted to a
                    monstrous provocation.</p>
                <p>In the spring of ‘43 they published a communiqué attributing the Katyn crime to
                    Soviet organs, dating the murders back to the spring of 1940. The editorials
                    state that the Germans resorted to this trick early in ’43 when their military
                    fortunes were on the wane, and that they sought to incite Russians and Poles
                    against one another. This attempt was a failure. The Soviet Information Bureau
                    exposed the Hitlerite slander. Freedom-loving peoples looked with disdain on the
                    Hitlerite slander against the heroic Soviet people.</p>
                <p>However the emigrant Polish Government took an active part in the anti-Soviet
                    campaign regarding the “Murders in Katyn”. The <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi>
                    editorial states that as a result of the participation of the Polish Government
                    in the anti-Soviet campaign, diplomatic relations <pb facs="1251" n="1239"
                        xml:id="pg_1239"/> between the Soviet Government and the Polish Government
                    were broken off.</p>
                <p>Now, as a result of materials in the possession of the Special Commission,
                    including testimony of over a hundred witnesses and medical and other data, the
                    base sequence of German Fascist provocations, murders and falsifications which
                    constitute the “Katyn” affair has been revealed. The evidence establishes,
                    according to the editorials, that the Poles were killed in the fall of ‘41,
                    having been in the camp up to September’41.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> editorial cites the data in the communiqué of
                    the commission to the effect that a German military organization concealed under
                    the designation of “Staff of the 537th Construction Battalion” and headed by
                    Overlieutenant Arnes, Overlieutenant Rechst and Lieutenant Hott, carried out the
                    mass shootings.<note n="58" xml:id="d1155fn58">This organization was actually
                        the Army Group Signal Regiment No. 537, of which Lt. Col. Friedrich Ahrens
                        was the commanding officer only from early November 1941 until August 1943.
                        First Lieutenant Rekst was regimental adjutant, and Second Lieutenant Hodt
                        was with this regiment.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Germans by threats and tortures and bribery found false witnesses from whom
                    they obtained lying testimony about the “Katyn affair”. Moreover they brought to
                    the Katyn Forest corpses of prisoners shot in other places, utilizing Russian
                    prisoners, who after completing the work were also shot.</p>
                <p>The concluding paragraph of the <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> editorial
                    compare[s] the Katyn crime with the crimes investigated in Krasnodar and
                        Kharkov,<note n="59" xml:id="d1155fn59">For reports concerning the trial and
                        sentencing of German war criminals and their Russian accomplices in
                        Krasnodar and Kharkov, see <ref target="frus1943v03#pg_845">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 845</ref> ff.</note> and declare[s]
                    that the Katyn murders were executed by direct order from Berlin “in
                    effectuating the policy of physical destruction of the Slavic peoples”. These
                    base crimes will arouse the wrath and indignation of the Soviet and Polish
                    peoples and of all progressive humanity. None of the crimes committed by the
                    Hitlerite bandits will be forgotten and none will remain unavenged. The Red
                    Army’s blows and the unshakable will of all the freedom-loving peoples to
                    achieve final victory and the complete crushing of Hitlerite Germany in the
                    shortest period attest to this.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Izvestiya</hi> editorial, besides making similar statements
                    regarding vengeance against the Nazi criminals, contains a paragraph denouncing
                    the Polish Government. It declares that in the light of the facts the shameful
                    role of the Polish Government stands out more clearly. The Polish Government by
                    participating in the anti-Soviet campaign aided the hangmen of the Polish
                    people. It struck a blow at the Soviet Union whose people are exerting all their
                    efforts to defeat <pb facs="1252" n="1240" xml:id="pg_1240"/> the common enemy
                    of the Russian and Polish peoples and the peoples of all the freedom-loving
                    democratic countries.</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Acting in unison with Hitler, the most evil foe of the Polish people, the
                        Polish Government did enormous harm to the cause of Poland.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>The newspapers containing the full text of the Special Commission’s communiqué
                    are being sent to the Department through the usual channels.<note n="60"
                        xml:id="d1155fn60">Not printed, but see footnote 57, <ref target="#pg_1238"
                            >p. 1238</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
