<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Prime Minister ( (Churchill) ) to President Roosevelt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1166</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recDV1FNGQhoilizZ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90000897"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reconstitution</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-02-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-02-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="1166"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1166">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The British Prime Minister</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Churchill</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to"
                            >Roosevelt</persName>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="86" type="source" xml:id="d1166fn86">Copy of telegram obtained from the
                        Franklin D. Roosevelt Library. Hyde Park. N.Y.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-02-20">20 February,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>585. My immediately preceding telegram.<note n="87" xml:id="d1166fn87">In
                        telegram 584, February 20, 1944, the Prime Minister said that this telegram
                        to Stalin had been “textually agreed with the Poles” and he called the
                        attention of the President to the fact that it achieved, without actually
                        saying so, the essentials of “the settlement outlined at Teheran”. The Prime
                        Minister then added: “Anything you can do to commend its acceptance to the
                        Soviet Government will be of great assistance.”</note> Following is text of
                    telegram which I have sent to Marshal Stalin.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Foreign Secretary and I have had numerous long discussions with the
                        Polish Prime Minister and Foreign Minister. I shall not attempt to repeat
                        all the arguments which were used but only to give what I conceive to be the
                        position of the Polish Government in the upshot.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The Polish Government are ready to declare that the Riga Line no longer
                        corresponds to realities and with our participation to discuss with the
                        Soviet Government as part of the general settlement a new frontier between
                        Poland and the Soviet Union together with the future frontiers of Poland in
                        the north and west. Since however the compensations which Poland is to
                        receive in the north and west cannot be stated publicly or precisely at
                        present time the Polish Government clearly cannot make an immediate public
                        declaration of their willingness <pb facs="1272" n="1260" xml:id="pg_1260"/>
                        to cede territory as indicated above because the publication of such an
                        arrangement would have an entirely onesided appearance with the consequence
                        that they would immediately be repudiated not only by a large part of their
                        people abroad but by the underground movement in Poland with which they are
                        in constant contact. It is evident therefore that the Polish-Soviet
                        territorial settlement which must be an integral part of the general
                        territorial settlement of Europe could only formally be agreed and ratified
                        when the victorious Powers are gathered round the table at the time of an
                        armistice or peace.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>For the above reasons the Polish Government until it has returned to
                        Polish Territory and been allowed to consult the Polish People can obviously
                        not formally abdicate its rights in any part of Poland as hitherto
                        constituted but the vigorous prosecution of the war against Germany in
                        collaboration with the Soviet Armies would be greatly assisted if the
                        Russian Government will facilitate the return of the Polish Government to
                        the territory of liberated Poland at the earliest possible moment: and in
                        consultation with their British and American Allies as the Russian Armies
                        advance arrange from time to time with the Polish Government for the
                        establishment of the Civil Administration of the Polish Government in given
                        districts. This procedure would be in general accordance with those to be
                        followed in the case of other countries as they are liberated. The Polish
                        Government are naturally very anxious that the districts to be placed under
                        Polish Civil Administration should include such places as Vilna and Lwow,
                        where there are large concentrations of Poles, and that the territories to
                        the east of the demarkation line should be administered by the Soviet
                        Military Authorities with the assistance of representatives of the United
                        Nations. They point out that thus they would be in the best position to
                        enlist all such able bodied Poles in the war effort. I have informed them
                        and they clearly understand that you will not assent to leaving Vilna and
                        Lwow under Polish administration. I wish on the other hand to be able to
                        assure them that the area to be placed under Polish Civil Administration
                        will include at least all Poland west of the Curzon Line.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>At the frontier negotiations contemplated in paragraph 2 above, the Polish
                        Government, taking into consideration the mixed character of the population
                        of eastern Poland, would favour a frontier drawn with a view to assuring the
                        highest degree of homogeneity on both sides while reducing as much as
                        possible the extent and hardships of an exchange of populations. I have no
                        doubt myself, especially in view of the immediate practical arrangements
                        contemplated by the Polish Government as set out in paragraph 3 above, that
                        these negotiation[s] will inevitably lead to the conclusion you desire in
                        regard to the future Polish-Soviet frontier, but it seems to me unnecessary
                        and undesirable publicly to emphasize this at this stage.</item>
                    <pb facs="1273" n="1261" xml:id="pg_1261"/>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>As regards the war with Germany which they wish to prosecute with the
                        utmost vigour, the Polish Government realise that it is imperative to have a
                        working agreement with the Soviet Government in view of the advance of the
                        liberating Russian Armies onto Polish soil from which these armies are
                        driving the German invader. They assure me emphatically that they have at no
                        time given instructions to the Underground Movement to attack “Partisans”.
                        On the contrary, after consultation with the leaders of their Underground
                        Movement and with their accord they have issued orders to all Poles now in
                        arms or about to revolt against the Hitlerite tyranny as follows:—When the
                        Russian Army enters any particular district in Poland the Underground
                        Movement is to disclose its identity and meet the requirements of the Soviet
                        Commanders, even in the absence of a resumption of Polish-Soviet relations.
                        The local Polish Military Commander, accompanied by the local civilian
                        Underground Authority, will meet and declare to the Commander of the
                        incoming Soviet Troops that, following the instructions of the Polish
                        Government, to which they remain faithful, they are ready to coordinate
                        their actions with him in the fight against the common foe. These orders
                        which are already in operation seem to me, as I am sure they will to you, of
                        the highest significance and importance.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>For the first time on February 6th I told the Polish Government that the
                        Soviet Government wished to have the frontier in east Prussia drawn to
                        include, on the Russian side, Konigsberg. The information came as a shock to
                        the Polish Government who see in such a decision a substantial reduction in
                        the size and in economic importance of the German territory to be
                        incorporated in Poland by war [<hi rend="italic">way?</hi>] of compensation.
                        But I stated that in the opinion of His Majesty’s Government this was a
                        rightful claim on the part of Russia. Regarding as I do this war against
                        German aggression as all one and as a 30 years’ war from 1914 onwards I
                        reminded Monsieur Micolajczyk of the fact that the soil of this part of east
                        Prussia was dyed with Russian blood expended freely in the common cause.
                        Here the Russian Armies advancing in August 1914 and winning the battle of
                            Gumbinnen<note n="88" xml:id="d1166fn88">A significant Russian victory
                            over the Germans, August 19–20, 1914.</note> and other actions had, with
                        their forward thrusts and with much injury to their mobilization, forced the
                        Germans to recall two Army Corps from the advance on Paris, which withdrawal
                        was an essential part in the victory of the Marne.<note n="89"
                            xml:id="d1166fn89">During the period between September 5 and 12, 1914,
                            the German advance into France was here thrust back.</note> The disaster
                        at Tannenberg<note n="90" xml:id="d1166fn90">The complete defeat of a
                            Russian army occurred here between August 26 and 30, 1914.</note> did
                        not in any way undo this great result. Therefore it seemed to me that the
                        Russians had an historic and well founded claim to this German
                        territory.</item>
                    <pb facs="1274" n="1262" xml:id="pg_1262"/>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>As regards the composition of the Polish Government, the Polish Government
                        cannot admit any right of a foreign intervention. They can however assure
                        the Russian Government that by the time they have entered into diplomatic
                        relations with the Soviet Government, they will include among themselves
                        none but persons fully determined to cooperate with the Soviet Union. I am
                        of opinion that it is much better that such changes should come about
                        naturally and as a result of further Polish consideration of their interests
                        as a whole. It might well be, in my opinion, that the moment for a
                        resumption of these relations in a formal manner would await the
                        reconstitution of a Polish Government at the time of the liberation of
                        Warsaw, when it would arise naturally from the circumstances attending that
                        glorious event.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>It would be in accordance with assurances I have received from you that,
                        in an agreement covering the points made above, the Soviet Government should
                        join with His Majesty’s Government in undertaking vis-à-vis each other and
                        Poland first to recognize and respect the sovereign independence and
                        territorial integrity of the reconstituted Poland and the right of each to
                        conduct its domestic affairs without interference: secondly, to do their
                        best to secure in due course the incorporation in Poland of the free city of
                        Danzig, Oppeln, Silesia, East Prussia, west and south of a line running from
                        Konigsberg and of as much territory up to the Oder as the Polish Government
                        see fit to accept: thirdly, to effect the removal from Poland, including the
                        German territories to be incorporated in Poland of the German population:
                        and fourthly, to negotiate the procedure for an exchange of population
                        between Poland [and] the Soviet Union, and for the return to their mother
                        country of nationals of the powers in question. All the above undertakings
                        to each Kingdom should, in my view, be drawn up in such a form that they
                        could be embodied in a single instrument or exchange of letters.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>I informed the Polish Ministers that should the settlement which has now
                        been outlined in the various telegrams that have passed between us become a
                        fact and be observed in the spirit by all parties to it, His Majesty’s
                        Government would support that settlement at the conference after the defeat
                        of Hitler, and also, that we would guarantee that settlement in after years
                        to the best of our ability.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
