<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum for the Under Secretary of State ( (Stettinius))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-03-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-15T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="1172"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1172">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 Stettinius Mission/3–1944</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum for the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Stettinius</hi>)<note n="3" xml:id="d1172fn3">Prepared in the
                        Division of Eastern European Affairs in connection with the departure for
                        London of Under Secretary of State Stettinius for discussions with members
                        of the British Government, held April 7–29, 1944.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-15">March 15,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The United States Government continues to recognize the Polish Government as the
                    legal Government of Poland and no efforts have been made to bring any pressure
                    on this Government to change its composition because of pressure from any
                    foreign government since such action would be interference in the internal
                    affairs of a friendly government. Prior to the termination of hostilities when
                    the Polish people will be in a position freely to express their will, there
                    would appear to be no reason for the United States Government to recognize any
                    other government which may be set up as representative of the Polish people.</p>
                <p>The United States Government has offered its good offices to the Polish and
                    Soviet Governments for the purpose of reestablishing diplomatic relations
                    between them, and this offer is still open to acceptance by both parties.</p>
                <p>In regard to the territorial question it is the basic position of the United
                    States Government that general discussions of the many European frontier
                    questions during the period of hostilities against the Axis would run the risk
                    of creating confusion and diverting concentration on the over-all objective of
                    defeating Germany. It is felt, therefore, that a settlement of these problems
                    should by their very nature be postponed until the termination of hostilities.
                    If, however, the Polish Government should deem it advisable to attempt reaching
                    a solution of the territorial dispute with the Soviet Government, the United
                    States Government has indicated that it would, in principle, <pb facs="1280"
                        n="1268" xml:id="pg_1268"/> be prepared to assist through the offer of its
                    good offices to facilitate direct discussions between the Polish and Soviet
                    Governments. In any event it has been made clear to the Polish Government that
                    the United States Government cannot give guarantees for any solution which may
                    be reached.</p>
                <p>It would be difficult for the United States Government to give its official
                    approval to any territorial settlement which might be reached between the
                    British and Soviet Governments without the participation of the Polish
                    Government regarding the frontier between Poland and the Soviet Union. Moreover,
                    if the British Government should desire that the United States Government bring
                    pressure on the Polish Government to change its composition to conform to the
                    wishes of the Soviet Union, it is not felt that the United States Government
                    could acquiesce in this matter since, as indicated above, any such arrangement
                    would undoubtedly be considered to be interference in the internal affairs of a
                    foreign state on behalf of a third power.</p>
                <p>On the positive side, pending a final solution of these problems after
                    hostilities, the United States Government should continue to use its influence
                    wherever possible to bring about a resumption of relations between the Polish
                    Government-in-exile and the Soviet Government in order to heal this breach in
                    United Nations unity and bring the full weight of all allied nations to bear
                    against our common enemy.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
