<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Winant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-04-05T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-04-05T23:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-05T23:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-05T23:00:00-05:00" n="1244"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1244">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">760C.61/2253: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-06T00:00:00-04:00"
                            >April 6, 1944—midnight</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2715. The Polish Embassy just presented a note to the Department<note n="58"
                        xml:id="d1244fn58">Note of March 31, 1944, delivered by the Polish
                        Ambassador, Jan Ciechanowski, on April 1; not printed.</note> (indicating
                    that a similar note has been presented to the British Government) giving
                    detailed reports which the Polish Government states have been received from
                    Poland indicating that when units of the Polish Government’s Underground Army
                    disclosed itself to the advancing Red Army the Soviet authorities arrested the
                    Polish soldiers and executed their officers. The note refers to the previous
                    request (note of March 6)<note n="59" xml:id="d1244fn59">Not printed, but see
                        memorandum of March 16 by the Assistant Chief of the Division of Eastern
                        European Affairs, <ref target="#pg_1357">p. 1357</ref>.</note> received from
                    the Polish Government asking that the British and American Governments use their
                    influence with the Soviet Government to prevent possible Soviet repressions and
                    afford protection to members of the Polish Underground who disclose themselves
                    to the Red Army authorities.</p>
                <p>In view of this second request and the allegations made therein and in view of
                    the fact that cooperation between the Polish Underground and the Red Army would
                    have a direct and beneficial effect upon the prosecution of the war, please
                    ascertain whether the British Government, on the basis of this second request by
                    the Poles expects to reconsider <pb facs="1372" n="1360" xml:id="pg_1360"/> its
                    position as outlined in your 2432, March 25<note n="60" xml:id="d1244fn60">Not
                        printed; this telegram reported that the British Foreign Office considered
                        that relations between the Polish Underground and the Red Army formed only
                        one aspect of the whole Polish-Soviet problem, and that it was therefore not
                        advisable to take it up alone for discussion. The British Government was not
                        considering an answer to the Polish request (760C.61/2253).</note> and
                    whether it considers it advisable and desirable to make a parallel
                    British-American approach to the Soviet Government on this question.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
