<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="139" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">800.24/1667</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The British Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Halifax</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Stettinius</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-08">March 8,
                                    1944</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Ed</hi>: I am now in a position to give
                                an answer to the questions regarding Reciprocal Aid from Australia
                                and India<note n="55" xml:id="d139fn55">For correspondence on this
                                    subject relative to India, see <ref target="frus1943v04#pg_246">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 246</ref> ff., and <ref target="frus1943v04#pg_283">pp. 283</ref> ff.</note> raised
                                in the discussions that were held in the State Department on
                                February 15th.<note n="56" xml:id="d139fn56">These discussions
                                    involved British and U.S. representatives and concerned
                                    lend-lease and reverse lend-lease problems relating to British
                                    Commonwealth countries; memorandum of conversation not
                                    printed.</note> After your conversation with Opie on February
                                    29th,<note n="57" xml:id="d139fn57">No record of this
                                    conversation with Redvers Opie, Counselor of the British
                                    Embassy, has been found in Department files.</note> I think you
                                are probably aware of the general answer my Government were
                                proposing to give.</p>
                            <p>The position taken by my Government regarding these questions is as
                                follows:—</p>
                            <p>After the fullest consideration, the United Kingdom Government regret
                                that they find themselves unable to agree to the suggestions made to
                                them that they should purchase certain raw materials in Australia,
                                and turn them over to the United States Government as Reciprocal
                                Aid.</p>
                            <p>The United Kingdom Government’s position in this matter was made
                                clear at the meeting on September 16th<note n="58" xml:id="d139fn58">For a record of this meeting, see memorandum by Mr. Theodore C.
                                    Achilles, September 16, 1943, <ref target="frus1943v03#pg_84">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1943, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 84</ref>.</note> at which
                                Sir David Waley,<note n="59" xml:id="d139fn59">United Kingdom
                                    Treasury Representative, British Supply Council,
                                    Washington.</note> Mr. Opie and Mr. R. L. Hall<note n="60" xml:id="d139fn60">Robert Lowe Hall, Member of the British Raw
                                    Materials Mission, Washington.</note> met Mr. Acheson, Mr.
                                    White,<note n="61" xml:id="d139fn61">Harry Dexter White,
                                    Assistant to the Secretary of the Treasury.</note> Mr. Achilles
                                and Mr. Knollenberg.<note n="62" xml:id="d139fn62">Bernhard
                                    Knollenberg, Senior Deputy Lend-Lease Administrator.</note> The
                                matter was then discussed in terms of financial considerations, and
                                it was suggested <pb facs="0220" n="208" xml:id="pg_208"/> that the
                                United Kingdom Government might be prepared to consider giving
                                financial assistance to the Dominions or India, insofar as the bar
                                to those countries giving supplies on reciprocal aid was financial
                                in character. As I understand it, at no time in the discussions that
                                have taken place did the United Kingdom Government give any more
                                general undertaking to make supplies available where such supplies
                                were required by the United States Government, but fell outside the
                                limits within which the producing countries were prepared to provide
                                reciprocal aid themselves. Thus, apart from using their good offices
                                in bringing about an agreement between the Dominion and Indian
                                Governments on the one hand, and the United States Government on the
                                other, the United Kingdom Government was prepared to consider
                                further assistance only insofar as the major obstacle was at any
                                time financial in character.</p>
                            <p>If, then, the effect of the Australian Government’s supplying raw
                                materials under Reciprocal Aid would have been to deplete unduly the
                                sterling balances of the Commonwealth, the United Kingdom Government
                                would, in accordance with the above understanding, have readily
                                agreed to safeguard the Commonwealth Government in this respect, and
                                from the outset the United Kingdom Government gave the Commonwealth
                                Government the fullest assurances on this point. In fact, however,
                                the sterling liabilities of the United Kingdom to Australia are
                                rising, and military developments render it probable that they will
                                increase still further. The United Kingdom Government do not
                                consider that it is justifiable to ask them to contribute Australian
                                raw materials as Reciprocal Aid from the United Kingdom, for the
                                United Kingdom could only obtain such Australian raw materials by
                                incurring indebtedness to Australia. In any case, the United States
                                Government will no doubt take into account the fact that the volume
                                of Reciprocal Aid provided in Australia to United States forces is
                                on a very considerable scale having regard to the limits of the
                                economic resources available to Australia.</p>
                            <p>As regards India, while the United Kingdom Government will be glad to
                                use its good offices in so far as this may be practicable, it does
                                not feel able to provide raw materials on Reciprocal Aid to
                                supplement such raw materials as the Government of India may itself
                                feel able to provide. The reasons which apply in this case of
                                Australia apply even more strongly in the case of India, whose
                                holdings of sterling are increasing even more rapidly.</p>
                            <p>His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom accordingly trust that
                                when the United States Government realise that His Majesty’s
                                Government could not comply with its request without adding <pb facs="0221" n="209" xml:id="pg_209"/> to the problem of their
                                external liabilities, the United States Government will agree not to
                                press them further in the matter.<note n="63" xml:id="d139fn63">In a
                                    letter of May 13, 1944, from the Assistant Secretary of State
                                    (Acheson) to the Deputy Foreign Economic Administrator (Currie),
                                    which transmitted a copy of this letter from Lord Halifax, Mr.
                                    Acheson made the following statement: “It is the view of the
                                    Department that no further action on this matter is called for
                                    at this time.” (800.24/1667)</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>Yours ever,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Halifax</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>