<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-12-28T18:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-12-28T18:00:00-05:00" n="216" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">868.00/12–2944: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Alexander C.
                                        Kirk</persName>, Political Adviser, Allied Force
                                    Headquarters, to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Caserta</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-29T00:00:00+01:00">December 29, 1944—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received December
                                    30—2:25 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1968. We are reliably informed that Lieutenant Colonel Palmer was
                                instructed recently that British would regard despatch of Albanian
                                    <pb facs="0306" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/> forces to Greece as a
                                hostile duty and that it would remove any chance of recognition by
                                H.M. Government. To OSS Hoxha has categorically denied that his
                                troops are in Chameria or across the southern border in any place
                                and said he would not get mixed up in Greek business. December 26
                                issue of <hi rend="italic">Bashmimi</hi> FNC newspaper made a front
                                page denial of BBC reports of such movements signed by Major General
                                    Shehu.<note n="64" xml:id="d216fn64">Maj. Gen. Mehmet Shehu,
                                    Chief of Staff of the Albanian National Liberation Army.</note>
                                Hoxha did not react too badly over plans for a British military
                                mission which calls for a brigadier, Colonel Palmer as second and
                                political head, an additional political adviser, an economist, a
                                financial adviser, two intelligence officers and three roving
                                liaison officers. Foreign Office approval is still pending. Hoxha is
                                still stalling on OSS mission apparently awaiting a reply to his
                                request to send military and financial representatives to
                                Washington. OSS Bari is recommending that the mission in any case
                                proceed January 5.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>