<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-05-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="257" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d257">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EW (39)/2645½</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Embassy of the Soviet
                                        Union</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                        State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="75" xml:id="d257fn75">The Department reported receipt
                                    of this <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> in telegram 1403,
                                    June 2, midnight, to Moscow and summarized the document in
                                    telegrams 1481–1482, June 12, 89 p.m. (740.00119 E.W.
                                    1939/2664a, 2653, 2671a).</note>
                            </head>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>To the American Ambassador in Moscow in April were transmitted copies
                                of notes of the Soviet Government, handed to Mr. Stamenov, Bulgarian
                                Minister at Moscow, on April 17<note n="76" xml:id="d257fn76">See
                                    telegram 1468, April 27, 7 p.m., from Moscow, <ref target="#pg_323">p. 323</ref>.</note> and of the reply note
                                of the Bulgarian Government, transmitted by Mr. Stamenov to Mr. V.
                                Molotov, People’s Commissar for Foreign Affairs, on April 24.<note n="76" xml:id="d257fn78">See telegram 1468, April 27, 7 p.m.,
                                    from Moscow, <ref target="#pg_323">p. 323</ref>.</note> In reply
                                to the above-mentioned note of the Bulgarian Government, on April 26
                                Mr. Molotov handed to Mr. Stamenov a note,<note n="77" xml:id="d257fn77">See telegram 1727, May 15, 2 p.m., from
                                    Moscow, <ref target="#pg_327">p. 327</ref>.</note> in which
                                there was pointed out, that in spite of the statement of the Soviet
                                Government to the effect that it has in its possession authentic
                                facts regarding Germany’s use of Bulgarian ports and aerodromes in
                                the war against the Soviet Union, and that the Bulgarian Government
                                in its reply note of April 24 has restrained itself to bare denials
                                of these facts. There was pointed out further, that the proposal of
                                the Bulgarian Government to submit it, for the purpose of checking,
                                more detailed information, was not acceptable to the Soviet
                                Government, since onesided checking of facts by the Bulgarian
                                authorities cannot be regarded trustworthy by the Soviet Government.
                                In this note, the Soviet Government pointed out the fact, that the
                                Soviet Consulate at Varna was closed in fall of 1942 on request of
                                the Bulgarian <pb facs="0343" n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/> authorities
                                while the Consulates of countries, friendly to Germany continue to
                                exist at Varna and other ports.</p>
                            <p>The Soviet Government has also pointed out the fact that for more
                                than two years the Bulgarian authorities have denied the Soviet
                                representatives at Sofia entrance to Black Sea and Danube ports. It
                                was stated further, that, if the Bulgarian Government is striving to
                                ascertain the facts and check them, this should be done not only by
                                the representatives of the Bulgarian Government but by the
                                representatives of the Soviet Government as well. In view of this,
                                as it was said in the note, the Soviet Government deems it necessary
                                to reestablish the Soviet Consulate at Varna, and also to set up
                                Soviet Consulates at Burgas and Ruscuk on the Danube, and that the
                                presence in these cities of Soviet Consulates could make it possible
                                for the Soviet representatives together with the representatives of
                                Bulgaria to carry out the necessary checking of facts on the spot
                                and carry out such checking in the future if there will be a
                                necessity for it.</p>
                            <p>In reply to the above-mentioned note of the Soviet Government of
                                April 26, Mr. Stamenov handed to Mr. Molotov a note on May 6, in
                                which the Bulgarian Government made an attempt to justify the
                                closing down of the Soviet Consulate at Varna by the interruption of
                                economic relations between the U.S.S.R. and Bulgaria referring to
                                the “juridical nature of trade consulates” and put the question of
                                setting up Soviet consulates in Burgas and Ruscuk in subordination
                                to the resumption of Bulgaro-Soviet economic relations. The
                                Bulgarian Government promised to consider in the most favorable
                                manner the wishes of the Soviet Government regarding the
                                establishment of Soviet Consulates at Varna, Burgas and Ruscuk after
                                the resumption of economic relations between the U.S.S.R. and
                                Bulgaria. It was pointed out in the note that Bulgaria desired to
                                maintain “correct, loyal and friendly relations with the Soviet
                                Union.”</p>
                            <p>In reply to the above-mentioned note the Chargé d’Affaires of the
                                U.S.S.R. in Sofia on May 9 handed a note to D. Bashiloff.</p>
                            <p>It was said in the note that the Soviet Government did not interrupt
                                trade relations with Bulgaria and that the economic ties with the
                                latter had been interrupted due to the military operations on the
                                Black Sea, and that the reference of the Bulgarian Government to the
                                juridical nature of trade consulates was groundless, since trade
                                consulates as such do not exist and Consulates do not deal with
                                commercial matters. It was confirmed that the wish of the Soviet
                                Government in regard to setting up Soviet Consulates at Varna,
                                Ruscuk and Burgas was based on the necessity to make it possible for
                                the Soviet representatives to check together with the Bulgarian
                                representatives the facts relating to the utilization of Bulgarian
                                ports and aerodromes by the Germans in military operations against
                                the U.S.S.R.</p>
                            <pb facs="0344" n="332" xml:id="pg_332"/>
                            <p>The Soviet Government pointed out that the statement of the Bulgarian
                                Government about its readiness to consider the proposal of the
                                Soviet Government concerning the setting up Soviet Consulates at
                                Varna, Burgas and Ruscuk not before the economic relations between
                                Bulgaria and the Soviet Union are resumed, as a refusal to meet the
                                wishes of the Soviet Government, and as the intention of the
                                Bulgarian Government to render aid to Germany in the future as well
                                by letting her utilize Bulgarian aerodromes and ports against the
                                Soviet Union. It was pointed out further that the Soviet Government
                                insists on the meeting its wishes to reestablish the Consulate at
                                Varna and setting up Consulates at Burgas and Ruscuk.</p>
                            <p>On May 15 Mr. Bashiloff handed a reply of the Bulgarian Government to
                                the above-mentioned note, to the Chargé d’Affaires of the U.S.S.R.
                                in Sofia.</p>
                            <p>In this note the Bulgarian Government stated that it noted with
                                satisfaction that the Soviet Government admits that it has not
                                interrupted trade relations with Bulgaria and that the economic
                                relations with whom were interrupted because of military operations
                                on the Black Sea. The Bulgarian Government stated that it considered
                                it possible to develop economic relations with the Soviet Union
                                through Turkey and asked the Soviet Government to consider again the
                                arguments expressed in the note of the Bulgarian Government of May
                                6. The Bulgarian Government stressed again that it desired to
                                maintain friendly relations between Bulgaria and the U.S.S.R.</p>
                            <p>In reply to the above note of the Bulgarian Government, the Chargé
                                d’Affaires of the U.S.S.R. handed on May 17 to Mr. Bashiloff, a
                                reply note of the Soviet Government, in which the Soviet Government
                                drew the attention of the Bulgarian Government to the
                                incompatibility of facts of converting ports Varna and Burgas into
                                German bases, utilized by Germany against the U.S.S.R., with normal
                                relations between the U.S.S.R. and Bulgaria. The Soviet Government
                                proposed to the Bulgarian Government to stop immediately the
                                utilization of Bulgarian territory and Bulgarian ports by Fascist
                                Germany against the Soviet Union.</p>
                            <p>It was pointed out in the note that in view of wholesale denials of
                                these facts by the Bulgarian Government, the Soviet Government
                                expressed a wish to reestablish the closed[,] on request of the
                                Bulgarian Government, Soviet Consulate at Varna and set up Soviet
                                Consulates at Burgas and Ruscuk with the purpose of making it
                                possible for the representatives of the U.S.S.R. and Bulgaria to
                                check the facts on the spot and carry out such checking in the
                                future, in case of such a necessity and that the Bulgarian
                                Government has restrained itself from a direct reply to this wish of
                                the Soviet Government and has subordinated the question of setting
                                up Soviet Consulates to the resumption of trade relations between
                                Bulgaria and the <pb facs="0345" n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/> U.S.S.R.,
                                although there is no connection between the resumption of trade
                                relations with the establishment of Soviet Consulates in Bulgaria.
                                In view of this, the Soviet Government pointed out that the
                                suggestion of the Bulgarian Government did not have any practical
                                meaning due to military actions on the Black Sea and that the Soviet
                                Government’s statement regarding placing at the disposal of
                                Hitlerite Germany Bulgarian ports and aerodromes cannot be denied
                                and that the Bulgarian Government is seeking out pretexts to evade
                                from a direct reply to the proposals of the Soviet Government
                                regarding setting up Soviet Consulates in Bulgaria, and that, in
                                view of the aforesaid, the Soviet Government insists that the
                                Bulgarian Government meet the proposal of the Soviet Government
                                regarding the reestablishment of the Soviet Consulate in Varna and
                                setting up Soviet Consulates in Burgas and Ruscuk without further
                                delay. The Soviet Government has warned the Government of Bulgaria
                                that without meeting the wishes of the Soviet Government, the latter
                                will consider it impossible to maintain relations with Bulgaria as a
                                country which gives assistance and intends to give it in the future
                                to Hitlerite Germany in its war against the Soviet Union.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-05-27">May
                                        27, 1944</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>