<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Harriman) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d384</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">384</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-10-12T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-10-12T11:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recrhwaFiM6colpg2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-10-12T11:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-10-12T11:00:00-05:00" n="384"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d384">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 E.W./10–1244: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-10-12T19:00:00+03:00"
                            >October 12, 1944—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 11:10 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>3911. A meeting was held this afternoon at the Foreign Office attended by
                    Vyshinski, Gusev, Clark Kerr and myself at which armistice terms for Bulgaria
                    were discussed. The purpose of the meeting was to take advantage of the presence
                    in Moscow of Mr. Eden and other Foreign Office officials to reach agreement as
                    far as possible between the British and Russians here on these terms with the
                    understanding that the results of the discussions would be wired to their
                    respective representatives on the EAC and that final agreement between the three
                    countries would be arrived at there. I made it plain that I had no instructions
                    to discuss these terms here and that I could therefore participate only as an
                    observer.</p>
                <p>The Russians submitted a revised draft of their proposals which was used as the
                    basis for discussion. This draft together with the details of the discussions
                    will be wired to London by the British Embassy here as soon as one or two
                    questions have been cleared with Eden and the British have agreed to request
                    Strang to make all this material available to Winant. I have therefore not
                    undertaken to report it myself. The Department may wish however to know at once
                    the outcome of the discussions with respect to the article pertaining to the
                    Control Commission. The final wording of this article to which both Russians and
                    British agreed provides that an Allied Control Commission shall be established
                    in Bulgaria for the whole period of the armistice under the chairmanship of the
                    Soviet representative with the participation of representatives of the United
                    States and United Kingdom. It is further stipulated that the Commission is to
                    regulate and supervise the execution of the terms under the general direction of
                    the Soviet command. This final wording is the reflection of discussions
                    yesterday between Eden and Molotov and I understand from <pb facs="0462" n="450"
                        xml:id="pg_450"/> Eden that in practice it will be so interpreted as long as
                    hostilities with Germany continue [and that] the Control Commission will
                    function more or less as in Rumania but that after that time each of the three
                    countries will have an equal voice in its affairs.</p>
                <p>The British wish to add to this article an additional phrase binding the
                    Bulgarians to carry out any and all instructions of the Control Commission. The
                    Russians oppose the inclusion of such a phrase. No agreement has been reached on
                    this point which together with other unsettled points will presumably have to be
                    thrashed out.</p>
                <p>Repeated to London and Caserta for Kirk.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
