<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-27T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-27T09:00:00-05:00" n="470" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d470">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">859.01/141: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Sweden</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Stockholm</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-27T15:00:00+01:00">March
                                        27, 1944—3 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received March 27—2:31 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1031. There seems no doubt that great majority of Danish people will
                                be pleased and heartened by joint British-American declaration along
                                lines indicated Department’s 486, March 23, 5 p.m. This is a subject
                                often mentioned by visiting Danes and Legation has heard practically
                                no adverse comment. Formula outlined telegram under reference not
                                only presumably meets various practical objections from American
                                viewpoint, such as avoiding question of recognizing any particular
                                Danish group abroad, but also appears hardly likely to offend even
                                the most timid members anti-Nazi national front in Denmark, such as
                                certain non-activist Social Democrats who perhaps fear that such a
                                declaration might compromise their future Nordic independence.</p>
                            <p>King Christian’s probable reaction (mentioned Department’s 457,
                                January 18, 10 p.m., to London<note n="13" xml:id="d470fn13">Not
                                    printed.</note>) has occasionally come up in discussions with
                                visiting Danes, and though their views have differed, consensus of
                                opinion seemed to be that King would be definitely pleased, though
                                if asked in advance might answer that this was rather question for
                                political parties to express judgment on. Suggested secret Allied
                                message to King appears wise step in this connection.</p>
                            <p>Regarding maintenance Danish Legation Berlin (mentioned London’s 589,
                                January 21, 7 p.m. to Department<note n="13" xml:id="d470fn12">Not
                                    printed.</note>) following may be observed. Germans obviously
                                wish this to continue as part their propaganda regarding present
                                Danish administrative regime (compare page 2 to memorandum enclosed
                                despatch 2574, December 11<note n="14" xml:id="d470fn14">Despatch
                                    not printed.</note>) and would therefore regard its closing as
                                Danish provocation, even though Legation seems to be performing no
                                actual functions. Some observers fear Germans might reply by closing
                                down foreign legations still functioning Copenhagen including the
                                Swedish which latter would be a great blow to the Danes.</p>
                            <pb facs="0543" n="531" xml:id="pg_531"/>
                            <p>Finally, it is suggested that in order to achieve maximum effect
                                proposed declaration should emphasize idea “Allies in all but name”
                                and reasons why Danish people are so regarded, only incidentally
                                referring to anniversary of April 9th. For on this day Danish
                                thoughts will be so dominated by memories German occupation 4 years
                                ago and what has since been experienced that otherwise declaration’s
                                significance might be lost on many Danes particularly in view of
                                false rumors<note n="15" xml:id="d470fn15">Rumors were based on a
                                    press report to the effect that Denmark had been “recognized” by
                                    the United Nations.</note> circulated some weeks ago (compare
                                airgram A–97 January 26, 3:30 p.m.<note n="16" xml:id="d470fn16">Airgram not printed.</note>).</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>