<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-05-25T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-05-25T07:00:00-05:00" n="484" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d484">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">859.01/171: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bucknell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-05-25T14:00:00+02:00">May
                                        25, 1944—2 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received May 25—12:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>4202. Reference Department’s 4100, May 23, midnight. Warner of the
                                Foreign Office told us this morning that an urgent telegram had been
                                sent last night to the British Embassy in Moscow instructing it to
                                approach the Soviets again along the lines outlined in our 4179, May
                                24, 7 p.m. The Foreign Office’s telegram was repeated to the British
                                Embassy in Washington and Moscow was instructed to hold up any
                                action for 24 hours while the State Department was being consulted.
                                The British Embassy in Washington was instructed to cable Moscow
                                direct, should the State Department interpose any objection to the
                                British proposals, repeating the message to London. Warner is
                                sending off a second urgent telegram to the British Embassy in
                                Washington (for transmission to the Department) giving more in
                                detail his reasons for believing that the declaration should be made
                                and that the Soviets should be urged to participate.</p>
                            <p>Warner said that while he understood the Department’s reluctance to
                                issue the declaration now as given in Department’s 4100, May 23, he
                                nevertheless felt that there was good reason for going ahead and
                                that in fact the leakage made it more desirable to do so rather than
                                otherwise. Up to 11 o’clock this morning there had been no press
                                inquiries at the Foreign Office based on the CBS broadcast. The
                                Foreign Office is, therefore, hopeful that no undue publicity will
                                be given it.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bucknell</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>