<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="528" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d528">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">760D.61/1708</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chief of the Division of
                                    Northern European Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Cumming</hi>)<note n="5" xml:id="d528fn5">Addressed to the
                                    Director of the Office of European Affairs (Dunn) and to the
                                    Secretary of State.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-05">April 5,
                                    1944</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The British Embassy has made available to us the following
                                information regarding the Soviet-Finnish negotiations: <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>The Swedish Government considers that the Soviet terms
                                        regarding treatment of German troops and the indemnity to be
                                        paid by Finland to be impossible of fulfillment and
                                        therefore the Swedish Government cannot recommend Finnish
                                        acceptance of the Soviet offer.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>The British Government has expressed to the Soviet
                                        Government the view that it would be regrettable if the
                                        indemnity provision were to cause a breakdown of the present
                                        negotiations and has inquired whether in order to bring
                                        about a settlement the Soviet Government would if necessary
                                        be prepared to reduce the indemnity figure which <pb facs="0601" n="589" xml:id="pg_589"/> now stands at
                                        $600,000,000 worth of goods spread over five years (this
                                        amount will cover at least 75 percent and possibly 100
                                        percent of the total value of Finnish exports during the
                                        five-year period).</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item>The British Government has given the Soviet Government an
                                        intimation of its concern lest the Soviet demand for goods
                                        from Finland interfere with the supply to Britain of timber,
                                        wood pulp and paper which Britain will badly need both
                                        during the war and the reconstruction period.</item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>The British Government has reserved certain points with
                                        respect to British interests in Finland particularly its
                                        expectation that compensation will be paid to the British
                                        owners of the nickel mine in the Petsamo region should the
                                        territory in which this mine is located be ceded by Finland
                                        to the Soviet Union.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hugh S. Cumming, Jr.</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>