<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. H. F. Arthur Schoenfeld</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d538</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">538</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-06-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-06-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="538"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d538">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">760D.61/6–1344</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. H. F. Arthur
                        Schoenfeld</hi>
                    <note n="27" xml:id="d538fn27">Mr. Schoenfeld, Minister to Finland, had left
                        Finland in December 1942, and did not return, being assigned to the
                        Department of State in Washington.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-06-13">June 13,
                            1944</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Counselor of the Finnish Legation, Mr. Urho Toivola, called at my residence
                    last night and discussed the news of the latest Soviet offensive on the Finnish
                        front.<note n="28" xml:id="d538fn28">Finnish military headquarters announced
                        that on June 9, Soviet forces on the Karelian Isthmus had begun “a general
                        offensive supported by very strong artillery action and by strong air
                        formations.” (740.0011 European War 1939/34594)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Toivola expressed the view that if and when the Russians reach the main
                    Finnish defense line they would require very large masses of troops to break it,
                    perhaps as many as fifty divisions. The marshes and lakes make this line
                    especially defensible in summer. Mr. Toivola was in doubt as to the purpose of
                    the Russian offensive in these circumstances. He suggested that, in view of the
                    effect on other sectors of the Russian–German front of any such large diversion
                    of Russian troops, it might not be the intention of the Russian High Command to
                    force these operations through the main Finnish defense line but rather to bring
                    about a situation of such potential pressure on the Finnish Government that a
                    settlement would become possible without a final military decision.</p>
                <p>He thought, however, that the action was susceptible of still another
                    interpretation, assuming that the present offensive on the Finnish lines was
                    intended to be final. This interpretation is that the Russians desire to
                    establish control over all the areas on their western border formerly in Russian
                    territory in advance of their final all-out assault on the Germans, this on the
                    theory that by resuming possession of all such territory they could present
                    their western Allies with a <hi rend="italic">fait accompli</hi> in respect of
                    these territories and so minimize dissension between the Soviet Union and the
                    western Allies as to the small states in this area.</p>
                <p>Mr. Toivola expressed the view that the occupation of eastern European territory
                    by Russian forces after the victory over Germany <pb facs="0612" n="600"
                        xml:id="pg_600"/> would create a very different state of affairs in
                    territory so occupied from that which would prevail in those European areas
                    which would be occupied by the western Allies following the defeat of Germany;
                    and he had no doubt that all the eastern satellites of Germany would already be
                    out of the war if they were not aware of this difference in their future status
                    as compared with the condition of those European countries which will be
                    occupied by the western Allies.</p>
                <p>Mr. Toivola also expressed the opinion that, following Finland’s rejection of the
                    latest unacceptable Russian peace terms, public feeling in Finland had again
                    hardened into a determination to resist the Soviet Union at any cost. <hi
                        rend="italic">It was now hoped, however, that Finland could hold out on its
                        main defense line until the defeat of Germany, whereafter the western
                        Allies, believed by the Finns to be disposed to maintain Finnish
                        independence, might make such views prevail over Russian plans for the
                        absorption of Finland</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mr. Toivola, speculating on the effects of a possible Russian breakthrough at the
                    main line of Finnish defense, thought that Swedish preparations to receive
                    1,000,000 Finnish refugees, as recently reported from Stockholm, were quite
                    warranted. A mass exodus from Finland to Sweden in the event indicated would
                    certainly take place, provided the Russians did not cut off the sea route over
                    the gulf of Bothnia or the land route around the head of that Gulf. He thought
                    Finnish strategy in this eventuality would involve the defense of a bridgehead
                    on the Gulf of Bothnia of sufficient size to facilitate such an exodus.</p>
                <p>Mr. Toivola alluded to the Department’s recent statement,<note n="29"
                        xml:id="d538fn29">On June 11 the Department issued a statement assailing the
                        ban by the Finnish Government of the newspaper <hi rend="italic">Svenska
                            Pressen</hi> as a pro-German act; see the <hi rend="italic">New York
                            Times</hi>, June 11, 1944, p. 20. In telegram 448, June 6, 1944, the
                        Chargé in Finland reported that the Finnish Government had “decided to
                        forbid until further notice publication of the paper <hi rend="italic"
                            >Svenska Pressen</hi>.” (860d.911/34)</note> following the reported
                    suppression of a newspaper in Helsinki, to the effect that the present Finnish
                    Government is pro-German, and inquired whether this unprecedented statement was
                    the prelude to a rupture in Finnish-American relations. I answered that I had no
                    such information but expressed the personal opinion that a rupture of relations
                    remained a possibility.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">H. F. Arthur Schoenfeld</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
