<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting American Representative to the French Committee of National
                    Liberation at Algiers ( (Chapin) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d605</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">605</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-04-06T15:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-04-06T15:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recewAfM2kfM3rKFJ" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113347"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Retirement</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-06T15:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-06T15:00:00-05:00" n="605"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d605">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.01/3639: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting American Representative to the French Committee of
                        National Liberation at Algiers</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Chapin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-06T22:00:00+02:00"
                            >April 6, 1944—10 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received April 7—8:56 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1149. From Murphy.<note n="52" xml:id="d605fn52">Robert D. Murphy, American
                        Political Adviser, Allied Force Headquarters.</note> On my return to Algiers
                    last evening Duff-Cooper called to discuss the crises arising out of the decree
                    issued by the French Committee of National Liberation which confers on de Gaulle
                    full authority over French military forces. Duff-Cooper as stated by Chapin in
                    his 1104, April 4 confirmed that this decree was issued by the Committee without
                    prior consultation with Giraud, Commander in Chief French forces. Duff-Cooper
                    also stated that he had discussed the matter with Giraud who indicated his
                    intention to resign on the ground that thus stripped of authority his position
                    had become untenable. Duff-Cooper said that he urged Giraud to remain, thus
                    avoiding any appearance of French disunity and also any interpretation of his
                    action as being precipitated by the entry into the French Committee of National
                    Liberation of two Communist members. Duff-Cooper thought that Giraud’s
                    retirement at this time might be so misconstrued. He said that he had also asked
                    Giraud to defer decision until he had discussed the matter with me.</p>
                <p>Later in the evening Giraud called at my residence immediately after a meeting
                    between himself and General de Gaulle during the course of which he said he had
                    expressed to General de Gaulle his dissatisfaction with the action taken by the
                    Committee and his surprise that General de Gaulle without prior consultation
                    with Giraud should have inspired the Committee to clothe de Gaulle with full
                    military powers heretofore enjoyed by Giraud. According to Giraud, de Gaulle
                    made every effort to allay his dissatisfaction suggesting that, after all, the
                    powers that Giraud had enjoyed as Commander in Chief were more apparent than
                    real as all important decisions in this field were taken either by the Allied
                    Commander in Chief or by the Allied generals operating in Italy. He proposed
                    that Giraud accept the position of Inspector General of the Armies. Giraud
                    pointed out that de Gaulle’s present action is in defiance of all republican
                    tradition and said that he recalled to General de Gaulle that under the Third
                    Republic the Vice President of the Superior War Council (for example Foch,
                    Gamelin, et cetera) had in times of peace been Inspectors General of the Armies
                    but in time of war they became Commanders in Chief of the French forces.</p>
                <p>In republican France the combination of civil and military power in one man had
                    never been permitted. In Giraud’s opinion this present action is the first clear
                    cut step toward a personal dictatorship <pb facs="0683" n="671" xml:id="pg_671"
                    /> in France. Under the circumstances he said he preferred to withdraw. He
                    desired to give de Gaulle a reasonable opportunity to amend the decree to
                    provide for the position of Commander in Chief of French forces. If that is not
                    done within a reasonable time, let us say 48 hours, he would withdraw and ask
                    permission to proceed to England. Should that happen what Giraud would hope for
                    is some designation and an appropriate status near the Allied High Command.</p>
                <p>In my opinion we should not only interpose no objection to Giraud’s departure but
                    facilitate it in the event that the decree of April 4 is permitted to stand.
                    Giraud has been associated in the minds of the public with the USA and in fact
                    his French critics have attacked him on the grounds that he is nothing more than
                    an “American agent” or an “American valet”. If these same critics convinced that
                    this is true are permitted to observe that the authority and prestige of Giraud
                    are diminished and changed at will by the de Gaulle faction such a condition of
                    affairs could only be harmful to American prestige in this area. My first
                    impression on return here is that American prestige has suffered a distinct
                    setback in recent months.</p>
                <p>The favorable and happy position which we enjoyed here prior to the November ’42
                        landing<note n="53" xml:id="d605fn53">With regard to the Allied landings in
                        North Africa November 8, 1942, see <ref target="frus1942v02#pg_429">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, pp. 429</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1942v02#pg_432">432</ref>.</note> has largely disappeared.
                    The causes which make for this situation are undoubtedly complex and that
                    certain influences are at work with this objective in mind may be taken for
                    granted. Our position will not be improved it seems to me by continued
                    affiliation with and support of General Giraud if he is not [<hi rend="italic"
                        >sic</hi>] to be the target and victim of continued political maneuver
                    designed to cheapen his prestige and diminish his authority.</p>
                <p>I have discussed the foregoing with Generals Wilson<note n="54" xml:id="d605fn54"
                        >Gen. Sir Henry Maitland Wilson, Supreme Allied Commander, Mediterranean
                        Theater.</note> and Devers who concur. Giraud indicated this morning that he
                    hoped that it might be possible to enable him and his staff to proceed to London
                    in the capacity of Commander in Chief of French forces and resign after his
                    arrival there. It will be indicated to him that this solution would not appear
                    practicable.</p>
                <p>Giraud has stated that if he retires he naturally will avoid any action which
                    might be disturbing to military operations. It is not believed that there would
                    result any violent action either in the army or civilian population although
                    there is evidence that moderate elements are disturbed over the centralization
                    of power. General Wilson informs me that according to his Military Intelligence
                    some French Army elements in Oran and Morocco also manifest dissatisfaction.
                    [Murphy.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Chapin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
