<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting American Representative to the French Committee of National
                    Liberation at Algiers ( (Chapin) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d668</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">668</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-07-25T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-07-25T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-07-25T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-07-25T05:00:00-05:00" n="668"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d668">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">851.01/7–2544: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Acting American Representative to the French Committee of
                        National Liberation at Algiers</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Chapin</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Algiers</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-07-25T12:00:00+02:00"
                            >July 25, 1944—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received July 26—(12:30?)
                        p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2503. Mr. Bullitt,<note n="51" xml:id="d668fn51">William C. Bullitt, former
                        Ambassador to France, serving as foreign correspondent for <hi rend="italic"
                            >Life</hi> magazine 002E</note> who is leaving for Italy tomorrow,
                    informs me that in the course of a long interview which he had the other day
                    with General de Gaulle, the latter expressed the earnest hope that a titular
                    representative of the USA with the rank of Ambassador might be appointed in the
                    near future to the French Committee. The General said that Franco-American
                    relations in the past few months had been handicapped by the absence in Algiers
                    of an official of that authority with whom he might have discussed upon a frank
                    and intimate basis the problems affecting those relations. He added that if a
                    successor to Mr. Wilson<note n="52" xml:id="d668fn52">Edwin C. Wilson, American
                        Representative to the French Committee of National Liberation at Algiers!
                        November 22, 1943, to May 8, 1944.</note> were appointed, he would hope to
                    establish with him just such mutual confidence and reiterated the desirability
                    of immediate action in view of prospective developments in the war. Moreover the
                    General felt it would be helpful to be able to discuss with such a
                    representative the main problems envisaged for the post-war period.</p>
                <p>Mr. Bullitt asked him if existing impulse toward better relations resulting from
                    the successful visit of de Gaulle to the USA might be diminished. While the
                    effect which such a representative might have upon the attitudes and policies of
                    de Gaulle and the French Committee should not be exaggerated, there is little
                    doubt but what the right man, speaking with an authority based on your
                    confidence and that of the President might exert a most beneficial
                    influence.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Chapin</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
