<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-04-29T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-04-29T10:00:00-05:00" n="801" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d801">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">864.01/560: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Portugal</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Norweb</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lisbon</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-04-29T17:00:00+02:00">April
                                        29, 1944—5 p.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 6:34 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1302. Wodianer has received following from Hungarian Minister in
                                Bern, Bessenyei, dated April 26.</p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Final plan of Envoys Committee is that Envoys and Mission Chiefs
                                    who rejected Sztojay Government form a committee regardless of
                                    date on which they took anti-Nazi stand. This committee would be
                                    rallying point of all anti-Nazi Hungarian diplomats, civil
                                    servants and patriots and would serve as an organization of
                                    information and consultation for the United States, Great
                                    Britain and the Allies generally regarding questions affecting
                                    Hungary. It will endeavor to organize military and civil
                                    resistance against German occupation. The committee aims to
                                    assist in the reestablishment of Hungary’s independence and
                                    sovereignty within the framework of constitutional democracy but
                                    it takes no position regarding domestic policy questions and
                                    does not represent any Hungarian political party. To insure
                                    concerted action Barcza agrees to act as coordinator of the
                                    Committee in Europe and Pelenyi will be invited to accept same
                                    task in America. American and British Ministers at Bern have
                                    submitted this plan to their respective Governments which have
                                    taken notice thereof.</p>
                                <p>While it is not intended to make formal announcement of the
                                    committee’s formation it would be useful to give it publicity in
                                    the local press as far as possible.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <p>An identical communication has been sent by Bern to Madrid and
                                Stockholm also. Wodianer here and Ambro at Madrid have accepted the
                                plan; and from Ullein’s last message to Wodianer (see Stockholm’s
                                1437, April 24, midnight, to the Department<note n="50" xml:id="d801fn50">Not printed.</note>) the latter assumes that
                                both Ullein and the Hungarian Minister at Helsinki, now in
                                Stockholm, will also be agreeable.</p>
                            <p>This mission has no indication regarding the Department’s views as to
                                the proposed committee and the information reaching us from Bern and
                                from Stockholm seems to conflict, in that according to Bern we and
                                the British Government have “taken note of” the proposed committee
                                of Envoys, while according to Ullein’s message to Wodianer,
                                transmitted by Johnson, we and the British Government “have
                                approved” Eckhardt’s leadership of a committee of Resistance.
                                Accordingly, the Department’s instructions would be appreciated.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Norweb</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>