<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-01-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-01-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="83" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">811.203/356: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Winant</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-01-07">January 7,
                                        1944</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>181. Foreign Office letter dated November 20 quoted in your 8206,
                                November 24,<note n="39" xml:id="d83fn39">Not printed.</note>
                                requested amplification of statement in Department’s 6748, October
                                    28,<note n="39" xml:id="d83fn38">Not printed.</note> that
                                military and naval authorities would make every effort consistent
                                with law and policy to secure compliance by members of armed forces
                                of United States with judgments of United Kingdom courts in civil
                                case to extent permissible under United States military or naval
                                law.</p>
                            <p>Department is advised as follows by War and Navy Departments:<note n="40" xml:id="d83fn40">The following statements except the last
                                    sentence of the telegram were conveyed in a letter of January 19
                                    (not printed), from the Second Secretary of Embassy in the
                                    United Kingdom to Sir Nevile Butler, Counselor in the British
                                    Foreign Office.</note>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>By the phrase “every effort consistent with law and policy to
                                        secure compliance to the extent permissible in United States
                                        military and naval law”, the following meaning is
                                        intended:</p>
                                    <p>The Army and Navy will give to judgments of British courts
                                        the same effect as that given to judgments of American
                                        courts except as to judgments based on subject matter within
                                        the purview of the Foreign Claims Act.<note n="41" xml:id="d83fn41">Act approved January 2, 1942; 55 Stat.
                                            880.</note>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>The policy of the Army and Navy in regard to invoking
                                        disciplinary action to effect payment of the judgments of
                                        American courts is as follows:</p>
                                    <p>Refusal or failure to satisfy judgments found by courts to be
                                        due to a plaintiff will be proper ground for disciplinary
                                        action when in so refusing or failing to pay such judgment
                                        such personnel have violated Army or Navy standards of honor
                                        by fraud, deceit, evasion, or other dishonorable conduct or
                                        neglect justifying disciplinary action. Mere inability to
                                        pay such a judgment would not justify such disciplinary
                                        action. There must be a willful refusal or failure to make
                                        such payment under circumstances constituting dishonorable
                                        indifference, accompanied by ability to pay.</p>
                                    <p>Refusal or failure to pay a judgment based on a claim within
                                        the purview of the Foreign Claims Act of January 2, 1942, as
                                        amended, would not be a proper basis for such disciplinary
                                        action. Claims within the purview of the Foreign Claims Act
                                        are subject to the jurisdiction of United States foreign
                                        claims commissions whose disposition thereof will be final
                                        and no assistance will be rendered by United States
                                        Authorities to require personnel to pay judgments of British
                                        courts to which claimant has resorted in such cases either
                                        originally or as a means of evasion or appeal from United
                                        States Claim Commissions.</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>