<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-01-12T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-01-12T20:00:00-05:00" n="893" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d893">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00119 EW/1–945: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi>
                                    (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-01-12T21:00:00-04:00">January 12, 1945—9 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>82. ReDeptel 30, January 5. The Department has desired to secure
                                Soviet agreement to our position respecting the second period of the
                                armistice either in Article XVIII or in the protocol containing the
                                ACC statutes. We can accept the present wording of Article XVIII,
                                without making the same reservation as was made in the case of the
                                Bulgarian armistice only if the statutes of the ACC are satisfactory
                                on that point. The employment of the word “concurrence”, as you
                                proposed, would of course meet our position. The word “consultation”
                                does not meet it. If Molotov remains firm on this point, we should
                                prefer to have the paragraph on the second period eliminated
                                entirely from the statutes. We would then be in a position to make a
                                    <pb facs="0983" n="971" xml:id="pg_971"/> clear-cut reservation
                                to Article XVIII along the lines stated in the Department’s 30,
                                January 5, indicating that we consider the organization of the ACC
                                in the second period to be an open question which we may take up at
                                a later date. If Molotov does not consent to eliminate the paragraph
                                from the statutes, you should make clear to him that our acceptance
                                of the statutes and our interpretation of Article IV thereof must be
                                considered in the light of our reservation to Article XVIII.</p>
                            <p>With respect to the first period the Department has always
                                acknowledged the chief responsibility of the Soviet authorities in
                                the conduct of the affairs of the Control Commission (reEmbs 88,
                                January 9), and of course considers that the “consultation” which
                                was proposed in your draft should not be operative in such a way as
                                to prevent the Soviet High Command from taking action which it
                                considers necessary for military reasons. If the term “consultation”
                                seems to the Soviet Government to mean prolonged discussion and to
                                imply an obligation to accept modifications, their objection to the
                                term might be met by the following change in the language of the
                                Soviet text as it appears in the second paragraph of your 75,
                                January 8: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“… shall call meetings and inform the British and American
                                        representatives of policy directives (i.e. directives
                                        involving matters of general principle) prior to the
                                        issuance of such directives to the Hungarian authorities in
                                        the name of the Commission, and take note of such
                                        observations as the British or American representatives may
                                        desire to make.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>We should like you to urge the Soviet Government to agree to this
                                alternative text, failing which you may yield on the point of formal
                                provision for prior consultation in the first period, putting it on
                                record that our chief purpose in seeking a formal agreement on this
                                matter has been to prevent a situation from arising whereby,
                                precisely in matters of policy, the American representative on an
                                Allied Commission should be subjected to a position where he learns,
                                only after their promulgation, of decisions taken in the name of the
                                Allied Governments, and may then be compelled publicly to
                                disassociate his Government from such decisions.</p>
                            <p>We would not hold up the armistice by insistence on the formal
                                provision that our representative should determine the size and
                                composition of his staff, although this seemed to us a thoroughly
                                reasonable provision, and it too was designed to remove occasion for
                                complaints on individual cases as they may arise. We are also
                                willing not to press for detailed stipulations regarding landing
                                rights, entry and exit of staff personnel and travel within Hungary,
                                provided we are given assurances that the Soviet authorities on the
                                spot will be instructed to make prompt and satisfactory arrangements
                                for the needs of our mission.</p>
                            <pb facs="0984" n="972" xml:id="pg_972"/>
                            <p>The British may propose that the statutes provide for the access to
                                the ACC on the part of Czechoslovak and Yugoslav representatives.
                                The Department is willing that such a clause be included.</p>
                            <p>Has anything been heard from Molotov on the question of making
                                available to all three Allied Governments the military information
                                obtained from the Hungarians (reEmbs 14, January 2)? In apprising
                                the Joint Chiefs of Staff of the present state of the negotiations
                                the Department would like to be able to inform them on this
                                point.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Grew</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>