<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-15T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-15T20:00:00-05:00" n="972" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d972">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">865.01/2212a: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                    to the Chargé at Algiers</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Chapin</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-15T21:00:00-04:00">March
                                        15, 1944—9 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>783. For Reinhardt. The following exchange of telegrams has taken
                                place between the President and the Prime Minister on the Italian
                                political situation. You may in your discretion pass this
                                information on to Reber.</p>
                            <p>March 7 from the President to the Prime Minister:<note n="83" xml:id="d972fn83">This message is No. 490, March 7. 1944.</note>
                            </p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“Our advices from Italy indicate that the political situation
                                    there is rapidly deteriorating to our disadvantage and that an
                                    immediate decision in breaking the impasse between the present
                                    Government and the six opposition parties is essential.</p>
                                <p>“General Wilson has had to forbid a strike called by three of the
                                    anti-Fascist parties in the Naples area. I fear we are moving
                                    into a situation in which the Allied authorities will have to
                                    use force against the anti-Fascist leaders and groups. I feel
                                    strongly that our policy should be so designed that it would
                                    never be necessary to suppress these elements by using force
                                    against them.</p>
                                <p>“One of General Wilson’s telegrams of February 29 (Naf 634)
                                    reports that the Government and the opposition are waiting for
                                    an indication of Allied policy with regard to their respective
                                    plans. I would like to give General Wilson an immediate reply.
                                    As you know, we prefer the program put forward by the six
                                    opposition parties which involves the abdication of Victor
                                    Emmanuel and the delegation of the powers of his successor to a
                                    ‘Lieutenant’ of the Realm, acceptable to the six political
                                    parties. Croce has been mentioned as their probable choice.
                                    General Wilson and his advisers have recommended the acceptance
                                    of this proposal and are awaiting our approval. My feeling is
                                    that we should assure at the earliest opportunity the active
                                    cooperation of the liberal political groups by bringing them
                                    into the Italian Government.</p>
                                <p>“If you will send instructions to your Chiefs of Staff here, we
                                    can send an agreed directive to General Wilson in the early Dart
                                    of the week.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <pb facs="1066" n="1054" xml:id="pg_1054"/>
                            <p>March 8 from the Prime Minister to the President:<note n="84" xml:id="d972fn84">This message is No. 610, dated March 8,
                                    1944.</note>
                            </p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“I am concerned about your Number 490. This message is a
                                    departure from your agreement with me of February 11 (your
                                        464<note n="85" xml:id="d972fn85">This telegram is printed
                                        in Winston S. Churchill, <hi rend="italic">The Second World
                                            War: Closing the Ring</hi> (Boston, 1959), p. 497.
                                        President Roosevelt stated that he had directed the
                                        Department of State to take no action toward effecting any
                                        change in the existing Government of Italy “at the present
                                        time”.</note>) which in your Number 483 you kindly
                                    reaffirmed describing the matter as ‘finished business’. I made
                                    my statement to Parliament on the strength of the first
                                    assurances.</p>
                                <p>“I do not find any reason to believe from my advices that any new
                                    facts of importance have arisen or that order cannot be
                                    maintained by the Allied forces in the regions which they occupy
                                    as the result of the Italian ‘unconditional surrender’. I think
                                    it would be a very grievous mistake to yield to agitation
                                    especially when accompanied by threats on the part of groups of
                                    politicians who are seeking office. We should then be liable to
                                    establish in Italy an administration which might not command the
                                    allegiance of the armed forces, but would attempt to make its
                                    position with the Italian people by standing up to the Allies.
                                    In fact we should have another but more intractable version of
                                    the de Gaullist Committee. Meanwhile we are to get rid of the
                                    tame and helpful government of Badoglio and the King in the
                                    midst of a heart-shaking battle, which is trying to aid us and
                                    work its passage.</p>
                                <p>“The course you recommend, I readily admit, would have at least a
                                    transitory success and would be more popular. But it would be
                                    unfortunate, I am sure, for the victorious conquerors to have
                                    their hands forced this way by sections of the defeated
                                    population. The obvious open division between you and me and
                                    between our two Governments would likewise be unfortunate. I
                                    gave loyal and vigorous support over the Darlan affair to you
                                    and the State Department. It was never more necessary than at
                                    the present time to have unity of action between our two
                                    Governments considering the great battles in which we are
                                    engaged and which lie ahead. I am quite willing to discuss with
                                    you now the proposals set forth by General Wilson in his Naf 634
                                    whereby the Crown Prince becomes Lieutenant of the Realm. I
                                    understand from Macmillan that Croce is a dwarf professor about
                                    75 years old who wrote good books about aesthetics and
                                    philosophy. I have no confidence in either Sforza or Croce.
                                    Vyshinsky tried to read these books and found them even duller
                                    than Karl Marx.<note n="86" xml:id="d972fn86">German
                                        philosopher, 1818–1883, co-author of <hi rend="italic">Communist Manifesto</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Das
                                            Kapital</hi>.</note> In his letter to Mr. Berle of
                                    September [19]43,<note n="87" xml:id="d972fn87">Not found in
                                        Department files.</note> Sforza has definitely broken his
                                    undertakings. I hope therefore that we may open discussions with
                                    you on the basis of Eden’s telegram No. 1783 to Halifax.<note n="88" xml:id="d972fn88">See footnote 77, <ref target="#pg_1043">p. 1043</ref>.</note> I repeat that I
                                    am most anxious to have a broad based government assume power in
                                    Italy, but this can certainly be done with far better advantage
                                    when the battle has been gained or, best of all, when Rome is
                                    taken, and ought not to be done under duress by the Allies.
                                    Macmillan is returning immediately.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <pb facs="1067" n="1055" xml:id="pg_1055"/>
                            <p>March 8 to the Prime Minister: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“Your 610. My dispatch No. 490 on the Italian political
                                        situation was sent with the purpose of trying to meet the
                                        difficulties presented in Naf 634 by General Wilson.</p>
                                    <p>“I would appreciate your sending me suggestions as to a way
                                        to remedy the serious situation which will be acceptable to
                                        your Government.</p>
                                    <p>“That you and I should continue to work in complete harmony
                                        in this matter as in all others is my strongest wish. Things
                                        like timing, on which we may differ, can be worked out, and
                                        on the big objectives like self-determination we are in
                                        complete agreement.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p>March 13 to the Prime Minister:<note n="89" xml:id="d972fn89">Presumably this message is No. 498, March 13, 1944.</note>
                            </p>
                            <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“With further reference to your No. 610, I am sorry if my earlier
                                    messages were not clear. I did not at any time intend to convey
                                    to you my agreement that we postpone all political decisions
                                    until after Rome had been taken. The political situation in
                                    Italy has developed rapidly since our earlier messages; the
                                    military situation has not kept pace. The capture of Rome is
                                    still remote and major political decisions must be taken.</p>
                                <p>“I do not like having to use stern measures against our friends
                                    in Italy, except for good reason. In the present situation the
                                    Commander-in-Chief and his political advisers, both British and
                                    American, have recommended that we give immediate support to the
                                    program of the six opposition parties. Thus we have, happily for
                                    once, our political and military considerations entirely in
                                    harmony.</p>
                                <p>“We do not need to intervene beyond informing the Executive Junta
                                    of our support of their program, as described in Naf 622, 624
                                    and 628, and confirm this to the King if necessary. The Italians
                                    can present the solution to the King and work out the program
                                    among themselves.</p>
                                <p>“I cannot for the life of me understand why we should hesitate
                                    any longer in supporting a policy so admirably suited to our
                                    common military and political aims. American public opinion
                                    would never understand our continued tolerance and apparent
                                    support of Victor Emmanuel.”</p>
                            </quote>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>