<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé at Algiers ( (Chapin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1944v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d989</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">989</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-03-24T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-03-24T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97002701"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Military operations</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-03-24T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-03-24T17:00:00-05:00" n="989"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d989">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">865.01/2283a: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé at Algiers</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Chapin</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-03-24T18:00:00-04:00"
                            >March 24, 1944—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>883. For Reinhardt. On March 6 the British Embassy presented an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aide-Mémoire</hi> based on a telegram from Mr. Eden (1783), outlining the
                    British position with respect to the present Italian political situation.</p>
                <p>[Here follows substance of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> printed on
                        <ref target="#pg_1037">page 1037</ref>.]</p>
                <p>In reply, the Department’s note<note n="11" xml:id="d989fn11">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aide-mémoire</hi> to the British Embassy, March 25, not
                        printed.</note> may be summarized briefly as follows: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The British understanding that the American Government has agreed to
                            preserve the status of the present Italian Government and King until
                            after the liberation of Rome is incorrect. In early February the
                            President directed the Department to make no effort to effect any change
                            in the existing Government of Italy at that time and until the military
                            situation in Italy was improved. This decision was influenced by the
                            military situation existing at that time and the military considerations
                            advanced by the Allied Commander-in-Chief. <pb facs="1087" n="1075"
                                xml:id="pg_1075"/> After a visit to Italy and a review of the
                            political situation there, General Wilson, however, decided that
                            political developments would not wait until Rome was reached and
                            recommended in Naf 622, 624, and 628 that he be authorized to support
                            the program presented by the Executive Junta.<note n="12"
                                xml:id="d989fn12">The Executive Junta’s program involved the
                                abdication of King Victor Emmanuel and the delegation of all or some
                                of the powers of his successor to a “Lieutenant” (see memorandum by
                                the Executive Junta, <ref target="#pg_1024">p. 1024</ref>).</note>
                            On March 13 the President sent a letter to the Prime Minister<note
                                n="13" xml:id="d989fn13">See telegram 783, March 15, 9 p.m., to
                                Algiers, <ref target="#pg_1053">p. 1053</ref>.</note> in which he
                            said in part, “I did not at any time intend to convey to you my
                            agreement that we postpone all political decisions until after Rome had
                            been taken.”</p>
                        <p>This Government favors the proposal presented by the Junta involving the
                            abdication of the King and the delegation of all or some of the powers
                            of his successor to a lieutenant. It desires an immediate solution along
                            these lines. However, in view of the recent decisions of the British War
                            Cabinet, the President has agreed that the two Governments should not
                            permit their divergent views to become public knowledge. The American
                            note points out that the mere policy of preserving the <hi rend="italic"
                                >status quo</hi> until after the liberation of Rome is in fact
                            favoring the position of one group of Italians, and that the weight of
                            Allied authority in Italy is such that we cannot avoid the
                            responsibility of supporting one of the various solutions. Furthermore,
                            we are opposed to a policy, in those areas of Italy restored to Italian
                            administration, calculated to suppress normal political activity.</p>
                        <p>Because of the divergence of views between the two Governments and the
                            major political considerations involved, the American note proposes that
                            a solution should be worked out in the Advisory Council. It is held that
                            the Advisory Council is the appropriate place for these considerations
                            and decisions, and the note concludes by informing the British Embassy
                            that the Department will instruct its representative on the Council to
                            initiate discussion in an early meeting of the Council.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>You are accordingly instructed to have placed on the agenda for the next meeting
                    of the Council a general discussion of the solutions presented by the various
                    Italian groups with a view to obtaining an agreed recommendation to the Allied
                    Commander-in-Chief for a solution satisfactory to all members of the Council.
                    You should support the proposal of the Executive Junta described in Naf 622,
                    624, and 628, using the affirmative arguments outlined therein. The Department
                    would like to see a recommendation to the Commander-in-Chief somewhat along the
                    following lines: It is recommended that the Allied Commander-in-Chief secure
                    from the Combined Chiefs of Staff, providing it will not prove harmful to
                    current military operations, authority to notify the six opposition parties that
                    their program as presented by the Executive Junta has his support and that of
                    the interested United Nations. The representatives of the six opposition parties
                    should then inform Victor Emmanuel of their program and they would be free to
                    inform him that it had the support of the Allied military authorities and the
                    United Nations represented on <pb facs="1088" n="1076" xml:id="pg_1076"/> the
                    Advisory Council. The Allied Commander-in-Chief should confirm, if necessary,
                    his support of the opposition program to the King. Undertakings from the
                    opposition parties would have to be secured that they subscribed severally and
                    collectively to all the engagements by the Badoglio Government.</p>
                <p>Sent to Algiers. Repeated to London.<note n="14" xml:id="d989fn14">As telegram
                        2255.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
