<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-03-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="125" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d125">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">893.01 Provisional/70</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Department of
                                        State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">British
                                        Embassy</gloss></hi></head>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Aide-Mémoire</hi></p>
                            <p>Reference is made to the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of the
                                British Embassy of February 14, 1938, in regard to the matter of
                                calls to be paid on the representatives of the Provisional
                                Government at Peiping and on territorial officials. In the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> there was given the substance of
                                instructions which were being sent by the British Government to the
                                British Embassy in China on that subject, and the hope was expressed
                                that this Government might see its way clear to adopting a similar
                                procedure.</p>
                            <p>It will be recalled that on January 21, 1938, during a call at the
                                Department of Mr. Mallet, Counselor of the British Embassy, Mr.
                                Hamilton informed Mr. Mallet of the substance of the Department’s
                                instructions to the American Embassy at Peiping in regard to the
                                question of calls on representatives of the new régime. This
                                Government has given further consideration to this matter, and as a
                                result it has issued to the American Embassy in Peiping
                                supplementary instructions to the effect that informal relations,
                                including exchange of calls, with representatives of the new régime
                                should, so far as is practicable, be restricted to officers acting
                                in their consular capacity. It may be mentioned that three members
                                of the staff of the American Embassy at Peiping have the dual status
                                of diplomatic officer and consular officer.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-03-10">March
                                        10, 1938</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>