<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in China ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d211</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">211</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-07-12T04:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-07-12T04:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="rectoUaG4WerMOwWn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00008430"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rehabilitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-07-12T04:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-07-12T04:00:00-05:00" n="211"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d211">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94119/428: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Hankow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-07-12T17:00:00+08:00"
                            >July 12, 1938—5 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received July 13—10:43 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>352. Donald<note n="98" xml:id="d211fn98">W. H. Donald, Australian adviser to
                        Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek.</note> informed McHugh this morning that a
                    daughter of Tang Shao Yi arrived in Hankow at about the same time as the British
                    Ambassador and called on Generalissimo with a message from her father
                    congratulating him upon his stiff resistance to Japanese. She then visited Wang
                    Ching Wei<note n="99" xml:id="d211fn99">Deputy leader of the Kuomintang
                        (Nationalist Party).</note> and proposed to him that he, Tai Chi Tao<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d211fn1">President of the Chinese Examination Yuan.</note> and
                    Chu Cheng<note n="2" xml:id="d211fn2">President of the Chinese Judicial
                        Yuan.</note> go to Hong Kong to confer with her father with regard to
                    possible mediation and peace. Wang is reported <pb facs="0225" n="221"
                        xml:id="pg_221"/> to have declined the invitation and to have informed
                    Generalissimo of approach. Donald stated that some time before Wang had been
                    approached through some other and unnamed source with the suggestion that he
                    write directly to Prince Konoye to assure him that there would be no enmity
                    between them after hostilities were over. This Wang is said also to have refused
                    to do and to have informed the Generalissimo of approach and of his decision.
                    Donald interpreted the above as efforts by the Japanese to separate some of the
                    leaders in the present Government. Donald stated that Japanese would even be
                    willing now to permit Generalissimo to remain as a power behind the scenes as
                    long as hostilities are over.</p>
                <p>In recent conversations which I have had with British Ambassador who is now in
                    Hankow, I found him interested in the question as to whether the present Chinese
                    Government could hold together after loss of Hankow. Today I had a conversation
                    with Blackburn<note n="3" xml:id="d211fn3">Sir A. D, Blackburn, Chinese
                        Secretary of the British Embassy in China.</note> who arrived yesterday from
                    Shanghai to join British Ambassador. Blackburn, who at Nanking was inclined to
                    criticise his Ambassador for a tendency to spend too much time away from Nanking
                    and the Central Government, seemed now to feel that it was necessary for him to
                    keep his Ambassador from being too enthusiastic about Chinese Government’s
                    chances of success. Blackburn appeared to believe that there was likelihood that
                    Wang Ching Wei and possibly Tar Chi Tao might leave Government to find berths
                    for themselves with Japanese fostered regimes in occupied areas. I inferred that
                    he was informed of Tang Shao Yi’s overtures. I have observed no evidence here of
                    any tendency or likelihood of break up among leaders of Government. I pointed
                    out to Blackburn that I would attach much more significance to efforts to bring
                    leaders like the Generalissimo, Chu Teh, Mao Tse Tung, Li Tsung Jen or Pai Chung
                        Hsi<note n="4" xml:id="d211fn4">Two Communist and two Kwangsi leaders, all
                        generals.</note> over to the Japanese side as the Government always had been
                    embarrassed in its relations with these leaders because of the presence in it of
                    leaders like Wang Ching Wei. I pointed out that while I was by no means
                    confident of the ability of the present Chinese Government to drive the Japanese
                    out of China or even to control the activities of the growing mass of guerrillas
                    throughout the whole occupied areas, I was convinced that resistance would
                    continue for a long time with the Generalissimo growing as a leader and a symbol
                    of Chinese nationalism as opposed to a Japanese controlled China. Blackburn
                    stated that the Chinese leaders were not [<hi rend="italic">now?</hi>] much
                    worried over the danger of the collapse of Chinese currency, saying that this
                    was evidenced by Chinese insistence that China must have financial support
                    through a British or other foreign loan, that the Chinese were worried lest with
                    the collapse <pb facs="0226" n="222" xml:id="pg_222"/> of the currency the
                    Government would not have the wherewithal to pay its troops. I pointed out that
                    while it was natural for the Chinese Government to desire to obtain a loan to
                    assist in maintaining its credit abroad and its currency in foreign exchange I
                    saw less reason for the Chinese Government to be disturbed over the possible
                    collapse of the currency than for the Japanese. I pointed out that a collapse of
                    Chinese currency would be far more disastrous to the Japanese fostered Chinese
                    regimes than it would be to the Central Government which would still be able to
                    pay its soldiers with a currency usable within the areas under its control. I
                    stated that I could not yet see any basis for peace between the Chinese
                    Government and the Japanese, that I believed and feared that the struggle would
                    go on for a long time with disastrous results to everyone’s interests. I agreed
                    that there was no evidence of war weariness in Japan but pointed out that the
                    change in the Japanese Government brought about by the failure of the Hsuchow
                    campaign (loss of advantage of dry spring weather for pushing attack on Lunghai
                    and Hankow), the putting into operation of the mobilization law now, a law
                    obtained by deceiving the Diet, was in my opinion a measure not so much
                    precautionary on the part of the Japanese Government as a measure of
                    desperation, saying that if at the end of a year the Japanese Government had
                    been forced to mobilize its entire strength for a drive on Hankow I wondered
                    what would be left to mobilize for the long haul that must follow the capture of
                    Hankow, the rehabilitation in the occupied areas, et cetera. I report the above
                    as possibly indicating not only that the Japanese are very anxious to find some
                    way of stopping the present hostilities but also as possibly indicating a
                    feeling in the British Embassy that Chinese resistance is about to break up, to
                    be followed by a drift of leaders toward the Japanese controlled regimes, a
                    feeling which I do not share.</p>
                <p>Repeated to Shanghai. Shanghai please repeat to Tokyo.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
