<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-11-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-11-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="377" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d377">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">693.001/514</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 91</seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-11-19">November 19, 1938</date>.<lb/>[Received
                                    February 16, 1939.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose, as of
                                possible interest to the Department, a copy in translation of a
                                leading article<note n="27" xml:id="d377fn27">Not printed.</note>
                                appearing in the <hi rend="italic">Hsin Hua Jih Pao</hi> on November
                                9, 1938, which endeavors to give an assessment of the Anglo-American
                                position in China in the light of Prince Konoye’s announcement of
                                November 3. Briefly, this journal considers that Prince Konoye’s
                                announcement amounts to a negative reply to the American
                                Government’s note of October 6; that it constitutes a threat to
                                American and British interests in the Far East; that the present
                                situation has come about partly as a result of the compromise policy
                                of the present British Government, which is compared unfavorably
                                with what is described as the more positive though hampered policy
                                of the American Government; that the gradual expansion of Japanese
                                activity in the Pacific area will bring Japan into inevitable
                                conflict with the United States and Great Britain; and that,
                                therefore, it is only necessary for China to continue its resistance
                                until such time as succor, produced of Japan’s overweening ambition
                                and pressure exerted by the people of the friendly Powers upon their
                                government, arrives.</p>
                            <p>In this connection, the foregoing views are largely shared by the
                                entire Chinese press of Chungking. Numerous articles have been
                                published which stress the progressive encroachment of the Japanese
                                upon American and European rights and interests in China; which
                                speculate upon the nature of the reaction of the Powers concerned to
                                these Japanese advances; and which urge upon the Powers vitally
                                interested—principally the United States and Great Britain—the
                                necessity of taking prompt and effective steps to safeguard their
                                    <pb facs="0392" n="388" xml:id="pg_388"/> rights and interests
                                in China, either by way of direct assistance to China or by the
                                application of economic sanctions to Japan.</p>
                            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Hsin Hua Jih Pao</hi>, as the Department is
                                aware, is a daily newspaper of the Chinese Communist party, which
                                commenced publication at Hankow in January 1938. Since the fall of
                                Hankow, this newspaper has begun publication in Chungking.</p>
                            <p>It may be well briefly to discuss the policy of this newspaper. In
                                internal affairs, its main consideration is the furthering of the
                                “united front” which it holds to be essential for the final ousting
                                of the Japanese from the Asiatic continent. In consequence, it gives
                                the appearance of supporting the National Government, especially
                                insofar as the prosecution of hostilities is concerned. It
                                constantly praises the person and principles of Sun Yat Sen,
                                professing to see in the latter the fundamentals for the
                                regeneration of the Chinese nation along democratic lines. Through
                                democracy, it hopes to achieve the Communist aim—a socialistic
                                republic. At present, it warmly supports the leadership of General
                                Chiang Kai-shek and is willing apparently to remain under his banner
                                so long as he continues to resist Japan. While it harbors a strong
                                suspicion against the Kuomintang, which it conceives to be following
                                a policy of hampering the activities of the Communist party, “united
                                front” considerations prevent it from adopting a critical attitude
                                toward that political group. Its strongest attacks are directed
                                toward so-called peace advocates, against whom the National
                                Government is urged to take the most drastic measures. It continues
                                to advocate suffrage, freedom of assembly, speech and press, and
                                unrestricted political party activity.</p>
                            <p>In the sphere of foreign affairs, its basic policy is, of course,
                                anti-Japanese and pro-Soviet Russian in the order named. Its thesis
                                is that the Japanese invasion will overreach itself in western China
                                and that prolonged resistance will in the end so exhaust the
                                Japanese that the latter will be driven out of China and off the
                                Asiatic continent. Prolonged resistance is expected to be maintained
                                through the agency of the “united front” and the development of the
                                mass movement and education among the population; negatively, it
                                advocates steps to prevent the Japanese from utilizing the areas
                                which the latter have occupied.</p>
                            <p>This organ maintains a policy of the utmost friendship toward the
                                Soviet Union, hailing it as China’s greatest friend and benefactor
                                in a period of darkest trials and tribulations. News of the Soviet
                                Union, copiously furnished by Tass News Agency, is accorded a
                                premier place in the news columns; while no opportunity is lost to
                                comment favorably upon the aims and policies of the Soviet Union.
                                Its policy toward Great Britain and France has been friendly, though
                                somewhat cool since the Munich agreement, which is held to have
                                constituted <pb facs="0393" n="389" xml:id="pg_389"/> a vital
                                democratic concession to the Berlin–Rome–Tokyo axis. Its attitude
                                toward the United States is studiously cordial, though it has
                                complained about the sale of arms to Japan and the failure of the
                                United States to take a more positive policy in the Far East. It is
                                violently critical of Germany and Italy, holding them to be allies
                                of Japan against China and the Soviet Union. In short, this
                                newspaper pleads for a coalition of the democracies, including China
                                and the Soviet Union, to curb what it terms the “Fascist group.”</p>
                            <p>In the economic field, this organ calls for relief of the peasantry
                                in the form of lower taxes, reduced rents, and reasonable rates of
                                interest. In common with the Kuomintang, it calls for the
                                development of the Northwest and the Southwest as economic bases for
                                future resistance against Japan, and advocates improved
                                communications. Though the Chinese Communist party undoubtedly
                                wishes for the socialization of industry and the redistribution of
                                land, the Communist newspaper has refrained from noticeable comment
                                thereon.</p>
                            <p>It is believed that the views of the <hi rend="italic">Hsin Hua Jih
                                    Pao</hi>, as described above, in general, represent the policy
                                of the leaders of the Chinese Communist party today, a policy which
                                appears to have as its basis the sinking of differences with the
                                Kuomintang, at least temporarily, in order to establish a national
                                unity that can avert Japanese domination of China and of the Chinese
                                people.</p>
                            <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Nelson Trusler
                                    Johnson</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>