<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-12-24T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-12-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="414" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d414">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94119/471: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in China</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Peek</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Chungking</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-12-24T12:00:00+07:00">December 24,
                                        1938—noon.</date><lb/>[Received 11:10 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>618. Central News Agency release of December 23, Chungking, quotes a
                                spokesman of the Chinese Foreign Office as having commented as
                                follows in regard to the statement issued by the Japanese Prime
                                    Minister:<note n="78" xml:id="d414fn78"><ref target="frus1931-41v01#pg_482"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, Japan, 1931–1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 482</ref>.</note>
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“The latest statement by Prince Konoye is in no wise
                                        different from previous declarations made by the Japanese
                                        Government. It thus shows that the basic policy of Japan,
                                        namely, the policy of destroying the independence and
                                        integrity of China and of closing the Open Door in this
                                        country, has remained unchanged.</p>
                                    <p>Prince Konoye professes, on the one hand, the respect of his
                                        Government for the sovereignty of China, but, on the other,
                                        he announces the determination of Japan to continue her
                                        military operations in China, to consolidate the puppet
                                        regimes set up by the Japanese Army, and to force China into
                                        signing an anti-communist pact. His declared objects falsify
                                        the avowed intention of his Government to respect the
                                        sovereignty of China.</p>
                                    <p>While declaring that Japan has no territorial designs on
                                        China, Prince Konoye demands in the same breath the right to
                                        station troops in China and the transformation of inner
                                        Mongolia into a so-called <pb facs="0438" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/> ‘special anti-communist district.’
                                        Such, demands constitute but a disguised attempt at the
                                        political dismemberment of China.</p>
                                    <p>With regard to the so-called rights of domicile and trade in
                                        the interior of China, the Japanese desire may appear to be
                                        harmless on the surface. But if one were to consider the
                                        presence of Japanese troops in China and their domination of
                                        the puppet government, it should not be difficult to
                                        visualize Japan’s true intentions in this country. That is
                                        to say, Japan is intent on using her military forces and the
                                        bogus regimes to push with all her might a comprehensive
                                        scheme of economic penetration covering the whole of China
                                        and exclusively for Japan’s own interest. This line of
                                        action is identical with that followed in her exploitation
                                        of Manchuria.</p>
                                    <p>The declaration that Japan does not wish to monopolize the
                                        economic rights in China now to restrict the economic
                                        interests of third powers, is entirely insincere, being
                                        merely intended to ease the international atmosphere which
                                        has become increasingly unfavorable to her. One needs only
                                        to look at the present condition of the so-called
                                        ‘Manchukuo’ and the recent Japanese economic establishments
                                        in China as well as the extent of destruction of third power
                                        interests to realize that Japan’s declaration is not to be
                                        trusted.”</p>
                                </quote></p>
                            <p>The Chinese press today comments widely and in a similar vein on
                                Prince Konoye’s statement and generally makes the point that China
                                will continue to offer resistance until Japan relinquishes her
                                present policy toward China.</p>
                            <p>Repeated to Peiping for Tokyo.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Peck</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>