<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d488</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">488</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-01-04T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-01-04T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXuFW8WO1tqBrVK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-04T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-04T09:00:00-05:00" n="488"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d488">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94 Advisory Committee/131: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-04T14:00:00+00:00"
                            >January 4, 1938—2 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received January 4—12:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>6. My 3, January 1, 5 p.m. A conversation at the Foreign Office last evening
                    threw some additional light on the rather general statement made to me by the
                    Foreign Secretary on January 1st regarding his conversation with the Chinese
                    Ambassador. It seems that the Chinese Ambassador had spoken to Mr. Eden of the
                    forthcoming meeting of the League Council and had asked for his view regarding
                    the advisability of calling for a meeting of the Advisory Committee of
                    Twenty-three which the delegations, it was said, obviously desired should take
                    place. The Chinese Ambassador had made it sufficiently clear that the object of
                    a meeting of the Advisory Committee in his view was that it should serve as a
                    preclude [<hi rend="italic">prelude?</hi>] to a proposal for imposing sanctions
                    on Japan and specifically sanctions on oil. He evidently hoped for favorable
                    reaction from Mr. Eden. As stated at the Foreign Office, Mr. Eden’s reply to the
                    Ambassador was definitely intended to discourage him from any such idea, for he
                    pointed out to him the impracticability of raising such a question at this time
                    and the serious complications which might result therefrom in Anglo-American,
                    Anglo-French and Anglo-Dutch relations. He also advised the Chinese Ambassador
                    that in his opinion there was no real work which the Advisory Committee could do
                    to good purpose at this time and that before the Ambassador considered such a
                    step as requesting the Committee to convene he should be very sure what the
                    reaction of the principal interested powers would be. It was to this end that
                    Mr. Eden suggested to him that he should, through his colleagues in Washington
                    and Paris, endeavor to ascertain the views of the United States and French
                    Governments.</p>
                <p>I was told also that the Soviet Ambassador recently informed Mr. Eden that his
                    Government has been able to provide a certain amount of war material for China
                    but not very much and that he, the Soviet Ambassador, supposed that Great
                    Britain, France and the United States were doing likewise within certain limits.
                    The Ambassador expressed his opinion that unless aid in war material could reach
                    China from foreign sources, her struggle against Japan was a hopeless one. Mr.
                    Eden, it seems, concurred in this opinion. The Foreign Office pointed out to me,
                    however, that in fact there are no supplies of war material except rifles and a
                    certain number of Lewis guns, which are available for export from this country;
                    that it was impossible for British sources to furnish Chinese requirements in
                    aircraft <pb facs="0494" n="490" xml:id="pg_490"/> or submarines which had been
                    requested by the Chinese Ambassador. The present scale and progress of British
                    rearmament make the prompt supply of any such material impossible.</p>
                <p>The foregoing was given me simply as confidential information which might
                    possibly be of interest to the Department.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
