<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-30T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-30T13:00:00-05:00" n="495" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d495">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">793.94 Advisory Committee/140:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Geneva</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bucknell</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                    <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-30T19:00:00+01:00">January 30, 1938—7
                                p.m.</date><lb/>[Received 7:30 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>26. Department’s telegram No. 6, January 29, 2 [<hi rend="italic">1</hi>]
                            p.m., my telegram No. 23, January 29, 4 [<hi rend="italic">7</hi>] p.m.
                            Stevenson of the British delegation informed me today that the status of
                            the Chinese Council resolution remained unchanged from yesterday. He
                            went on to say that as he had pointed out in our last conversation (see
                            my 22, January 29, 4 p.m.) the Chinese were rather unhappy over the
                            amendment of the last paragraph of the resolution but had referred it to
                            the Chinese Government from which no reply had yet been received. <pb facs="0502" n="498" xml:id="pg_498"/> He hoped and expected that the
                            Chinese would agree to it and would not be so “silly” as to attempt to
                            press an appeal under article 17 which procedure in his opinion would be
                            ill-advised. He continued that in the event a favorable Chinese reply
                            was received in time another Council meeting would probably be held
                            tomorrow afternoon. If the resolution was adopted by the Council he
                            expected that the next step would be for Moscow, London, and Paris to
                            consider what steps they were in a position to take which would most
                            likely be followed by an approach to Washington through diplomatic
                            channels to ascertain whether or not the American Government would join
                            in such steps as had been regarded as possible by the other three
                            governments.</p>
                        <p>Having previously discussed the Department’s 6, January 29, 2 [<hi rend="italic">1</hi>] p.m., with the Minister in Bern, I took
                            advantage of an opportunity during the course of my conversation with
                            others to refer to the Secretary’s conversation with the Chinese
                            Ambassador saying that the Secretary in referring to our attitude toward
                            a further Nine Power Conference had said that he felt that the really
                            important thing was whether any useful purpose would be served by
                            further conferences or meetings and whether the interests of peace in
                            general as well as the interests of China would be thus furthered. I
                            added that the Secretary had pointed out that assembling of conferences
                            or committees with achievement of nothing definite or constructive
                            serves only to harm the cause of peace. Stevenson remarked that this
                            appeared to be a remarkably sound view of the matter.</p>
                        <p>Eden left Geneva last night and Delbos this morning.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to London, Paris. Code copies to Berlin, Rome.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Bucknell</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>