<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-02-03T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-02-03T21:00:00-05:00" n="669" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d669">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">693.002/485a: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-02-03T21:00:00-05:00">February 3, 1938—9
                                p.m.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>37. Shanghai’s 179, February 1, 9 p.m. (which Shanghai has been requested
                            to repeat to you), and Shanghai’s 113, 146, and 170 in regard to
                                Customs.<note n="53" xml:id="d669fn53">Telegram No. 113, January 20,
                                6 p.m., <ref target="#pg_632">p. 632</ref>; No. 146, January 26, 7
                                p.m., <ref target="#pg_635">p. 635</ref>; No. 170, January 29, 4
                                p.m., <ref target="#pg_637">p. 637</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>In the light of your knowledge of the Department’s position in regard to
                            the Chinese Customs, the Department desires that you discreetly bring to
                            the attention of your British and French colleagues, without reference
                            to source, the views expressed in paragraph 3 of Shanghai’s 179; that
                            you frankly discuss with them, on a basis of <pb facs="0650" n="646" xml:id="pg_646"/> expediency and the realities of the situation, the
                            possibility and advisability of concentrating on defensive efforts in
                            regard to the major issues relating to and involving preservation
                            insofar as possible of the administrative machinery of the customs and
                            provision for the servicing of foreign loans and indemnity quotas, as
                            contrasted with effort to preserve the existing situation at all points
                            and in all features; and that you endeavor to obtain favorable
                            consideration of the proposal that approaches be made to the Japanese
                            Government by each of you individually along the following lines:</p>
                        <p>The Department suggests that you acquaint the Japanese Foreign Office
                            with the fact that you have information with regard to the character of
                            the Japanese proposal made at Shanghai to the Commissioner of Customs
                            for a settlement of the Customs problem; that in connection therewith
                            but without indicating approval or disapproval of the proposal you refer
                            in general to the assurances which we have expressed a desire to receive
                            from the Japanese Government (Department’s 339, December 12, 3 p.m.<note n="54" xml:id="d669fn54"><ref target="frus1937v03#pg_900"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1937, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 900</ref>.</note>); and that
                            you express an earnest and emphatic desire to receive from the Japanese
                            Government positive assurances that no action will be taken or
                            countenanced which will disrupt the Chinese customs service or
                            jeopardize the servicing of foreign loan and indemnity quotas from
                            Customs revenues, but that on the contrary in any arrangement reached
                            the administrative machinery and procedure of the Customs will be
                            carefully preserved and the payment on an equitable and unconditional
                            basis of foreign loan and indemnity quotas will be provided for.</p>
                        <p>Please inform the Department and Shanghai of the result of your
                            discussions and approach, if made, to the Japanese Government.</p>
                        <p>Repeated to Shanghai.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>