<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-02-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="97" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">893.0146/633</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Welles</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the French Chargé</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Henry</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-02-14">February 14, 1938</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. Chargé d’Affaires</hi>: In the
                                course of our conversation on February 8, I stated that I would
                                furnish you with information within a few days in response to your
                                inquiries with regard to the reduction and redistribution of
                                American armed forces in north China and with regard to the Chinese
                                customs question.</p>
                            <p>On January 31 Mr. Hornbeck made an oral statement to Mr. Lucet of
                                your Embassy in regard to our decision to withdraw the Fifteenth
                                Regiment, United States Army, from Tientsin, and to transfer to
                                Tientsin a portion of the American marines now stationed at
                                Peiping.</p>
                            <p>The matter of effecting a reduction and redistribution of American
                                armed forces in north China is one to which we had been giving
                                consideration for some time before the fighting broke out in north
                                China last July. The change that is now about to take place is what
                                might have occurred earlier had not the conflict arisen between
                                China and Japan. Our decision now to reduce and redistribute our
                                troops in north China does not involve modification of our treaty
                                position in north China. We are continuing to maintain armed forces
                                in both Peiping and Tientsin in accordance with our rights and
                                responsibilities under the Boxer Protocol of 1901.<note n="34" xml:id="d97fn34"><ref target="frus1901China#pg_312"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1901, Appendix
                                        (Affairs in China), p. 312</ref>.</note></p>
                            <p>The question of the withdrawal of diplomatic representatives and
                                armed forces from north China was raised by the British Government
                                    <pb facs="0091" n="87" xml:id="pg_87"/> in an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> handed to us on December 16 by the British
                                    Embassy.<note n="35" xml:id="d97fn35"><ref target="frus1937v03#pg_814"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1937, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p. 814</ref>.</note> We replied that we felt that
                                it would be premature to take action in the immediate future but
                                stated that the matter should be kept constantly in mind and
                                expressed the desire to continue to keep in close touch with the
                                British Government. In an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of
                                December 27,<note n="36" xml:id="d97fn36"><ref target="frus1937v03#pg_839"><hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p.
                                        839</ref>.</note> the British Embassy informed us of the
                                views of the French Government in regard to the desirability of
                                maintaining diplomatic representation and embassy guards in north
                                China and of the decision of the British Government not to withdraw
                                for the present its diplomatic staff and guards from Peiping and
                                Tientsin. The British Government expressed the hope that the French,
                                British, and American Governments would concert together before
                                taking any action in the matter. We replied that we would be pleased
                                to maintain close touch with the French Government, as well as with
                                the British Government, but that we felt that this expression of
                                attitude should be regarded as relating to exchange of information
                                and consultation rather than as constituting an agreement to act or
                                to refrain from action in concert.</p>
                            <p>With regard to the Chinese customs issue our Ambassador in Tokyo, on
                                February 3, was authorized<note n="37" xml:id="d97fn37">Telegram No.
                                    34, February 3, 5 p.m., <ref target="#pg_65">p. 65</ref>.</note>
                                to consult with his French and British colleagues with a view to
                                taking action along parallel lines to obtain certain assurances from
                                the Japanese Government with regard to the preservation of the
                                integrity of the Chinese customs service. We have now under
                                consideration certain questions raised in an <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> received from the British Embassy and upon
                                completion of that consideration I shall expect to communicate with
                                you further.</p>
                            <p>I am [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Sumner
                                Welles</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>