<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="145" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d145">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">
                        <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        Files: Lot 63D351: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 Series</note>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Report to the National Security Council by the Executive
                            Secretary</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Lay</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-08">December 8,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Annexes to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68/3<note n="1" xml:id="d145fn1">The annexes to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68/3 consist of revised versions of the annexes to
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68/1, September 21, none of
                            which is printed. Annexes 1–7 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            68/3 correspond as to subject to Annexes 1–7 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68/1, although the titles differed slightly. However,
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68/1 was also accompanied by
                            three annexes not included either in original or revised form in the
                            annexes of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68/3. The three were
                            Annex 8, “Long-Term Political and Economic Framework,” prepared in the
                            Economic Cooperation Administration and the Council of Economic Advisers
                            (regarding Annex 8, see Policy Planning Staff study of November 10, and
                            footnote 2 thereto, <ref target="#pg_404">p. 404</ref>); Annex 9,
                            “Organizations for Coordinating National Security Policies and
                            Programs,” prepared in the Bureau of the Budget; and Annex 10, “The
                            Economic Implications of the Proposed Programs: Required Fiscal,
                            Budgetary and other Economic Policies,” prepared in the <gloss target="#t_CEA1">CEA</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            68/1 was also accompanied by an Appendix to Annex 10, “Technical
                            Assumptions and Analysis Underlying the Economic Projections for
                            1950–1955,” also prepared in the <gloss target="#t_CEA1">CEA</gloss>. It
                            should be noted that an undated and much abbreviated version of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68/1, Annex 10, is included in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68/3 as Appendix “B”, <ref target="#pg_427">p. 427</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Objectives and Programs for National
                            Security</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Annex No. 1, The U.S. Military Programs</p>
                    <p>(It is understood that this Annex will be made available by the Department of
                        Defense prior to the Council meeting on Thursday, December 14, 1950)<note n="2" xml:id="d145fn2">See memorandum by Secretary of Defense Marshall
                            to the President and enclosures thereto, December 14, <ref target="#pg_474">p. 474</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Annex No. 2, The Foreign Military and Economic Assistance
                        Programs</p>
                    <p>Part A, Estimates for <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>, Fiscal Years
                        1951 Through 1955 (Prepared by the Department of State, in consultation with
                        the Department of Defense and the Economic Cooperation Administration, and
                        approved interdepartmentally at the <gloss target="#t_FMACC1">FMACC</gloss>
                        level.)</p>
                    <p>Part B, Anticipated U.S. Foreign Grants and Loan Assistance (Prepared by the
                        Department of State and the Economic Cooperation Administration)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Appendix to Annex No. 2, The <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Information Program (Prepared by the Economic Cooperation
                        Administration)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Annex No. 3, The Civil Defense Program<note n="3" xml:id="d145fn3">Not printed.</note> (Prepared by the National Security
                        Resources Board)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Annex No. 4, The United States Stockpile Program (Prepared
                        by the National Security Resources Board)</p>
                    <pb facs="0449" n="433" xml:id="pg_433"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Annex No. 5, The Foreign Information Programs (Prepared by
                        the Department of State)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Annex No. 6, Foreign Intelligence and Related Activities
                        (Prepared by the Central Intelligence Agency, with the concurrence of the
                        Intelligence Advisory Committee)</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">Annex No. 7, The Internal Security Program<note n="4" xml:id="d145fn4">Not printed.</note> (Prepared by the Interdepartmental
                        Intelligence Conference and the Interdepartmental Committee on Internal
                        Security</p>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex No</hi>. 2</head>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">The Foreign Military and Economic Assistance
                                Programs</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">part a. estimates for <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">mdap</gloss>, fiscal years 1951 through 1955</hi><note n="*" xml:id="d145fn5">These estimates cover both aid in the form of
                                armaments, and economic support for the European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries and Western Germany.
                                Economic aid requirements of the other European countries, not
                                members of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss>, are given in Part B
                                Annex No. 2. [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">(Prepared in the Department of State, in consultation
                            with the Department of Defense and the Economic Cooperation
                            Administration, and approved interdepartmentally at the <gloss target="#t_FMACC1">FMACC</gloss> level)</p>
                        <p>1. The estimates of appropriation requirements for military aid to all
                            countries and economic support for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            countries for Fiscal Years 1951, 1952, 1953, 1954 and 1955 include (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the costs of furnishing military equipment,
                            supplies and training to the countries determined to be eligible for
                            grant assistance under the Mutual Defense Assistance Act and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the costs of programs calling for both a
                            vastly expanded European production of military equipment (additional
                            military production program) and the raising of larger forces in the
                            European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries. The estimates
                            given below do not include the costs of certain emergency foreign
                            military assistance programs, such as the cost of equipping and
                            organizing a Korean military establishment. These estimates take into
                            account recent price increases of military equipment. Progress in the
                            technological field will require continuous review of existing programs
                            and the possible adoption of new ones. The approximate amount and
                            distribution of obligations by years for increasing the defensive
                            military strength of selected countries in the free world are indicated
                            in Table 1.<note n="5" xml:id="d145fn6">Not reproduced.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>2. A more detailed breakdown of the estimated costs of meeting the
                            requirements of the Medium Term Defense Plan (MTDP) for the European
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries (and Western Germany)
                            together with the <pb facs="0450" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/> estimated
                            United States assistance needed to meet those requirements is given in
                            Table 2.<note n="6" xml:id="d145fn7">Not reproduced.</note> Estimated
                            total costs of the MTDP requirements for Western Europe are $57.40
                            billion for the four fiscal years 1952–1955, inclusive. As indicated in
                            more detail below, these are United States estimates of requirements
                            costs which will be subject to refinement as the European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries furnish information on their
                            costs of meeting their requirements under the MTDP. The estimated amount
                            of resources which the European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss>
                            countries could mobilize and devote to defense needs is about $45.00
                            billion, assuming the United States continues to furnish general
                            economic support at rates averaging almost $2.0 billion a year. From
                            this total should be deducted about $5.0 billion or more for essential
                            defense expenditures of such countries as the United Kingdom and France
                            in areas outside the North Atlantic Treaty area. In order to close this
                            gap between requirements for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss>
                            defense and available resources which could be devoted to defense in
                            Western Europe, it is estimated that about $25.40 billion of United
                            States assistance is required between fiscal year 1952 and fiscal year
                            1955. The form of this required assistance is flexible within limits. In
                            Table 2, it is estimated that United States assistance in the form of
                            military equipment and training (items 2<hi rend="italic">c</hi> and 6)
                            will be $17.59 billion and in the form of general economic support for
                            European military production and increased forces will be $7.81 million,
                            or roughly in the ratio of 2 to 1. The extent to which the form of
                            United States assistance could and should vary as between armament and
                            economic support depends on a number of political, military and economic
                            factors, including the overriding need for trained and organized
                            European forces, the promptness with which European industry is
                            mobilized for war production, the flexibility and expansibility of the
                            war industries in both the United States and Western Europe, and the
                            extent to which the United States industry can and should be called upon
                            to meet the armament requirements of this country and a major portion of
                            those of the <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> countries. The
                            estimated division given above is believed to be practicable on the
                            basis of present information, but can and should be varied as
                            circumstances require. The basis of the estimates are explained
                            below.</p>
                        <p>3. The estimates of the costs of raising, maintaining and equipping the
                            European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> combat forces are based on
                            the requirements of the Medium Term Defense Plan (MTDP) as developed by
                            the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> Regional Planning Groups and
                            approved by the Defense Committee. The size and composition of the
                            forces required for the defense of the European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> area are those set forth in document 28 of the Defense
                                <pb facs="0451" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/> Committee (dated October
                            28, 1950). The equipment costs were based on these forces equipped in
                            accordance with modified United States standards, after adjustments were
                            made for equipment on hand together with that equipment included in the
                            fiscal year 1950 <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss> Program. This will
                            provide initial armament maintenance parts and ammunition. The equipment
                            costs for capital equipment and maintenance parts and replacement for
                            that capital equipment (items 1(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) and a portion
                            of item 1(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of Table 2) were based upon current
                            United States prices. The gross cost of maintenance and expansion of
                            European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> forces (major portion of
                                1(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of Table 2) was estimated on the basis
                            of current aggregate costs of supporting troops (estimated at a one to
                            one ratio) in the country of recruitment. No allowance was made either
                            for the deployment of forces in countries other than the country of
                            recruitment. The costs of stationing troops outside the North Atlantic
                            area are not included in the estimates of requirements for the European
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries under the MTDP.</p>
                        <p>4. The estimated cost of armament to be furnished from the United States
                            (item 2(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of Table 2) in the form of capital
                            equipment represents about 60 percent of the cost in terms of current
                            United States prices of meeting the aggregate capital equipment
                            deficiencies of the European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> forces
                            of a size and composition called for under the MTDP and equipped
                            according to modified United States standards. It is assumed that the
                            European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries (and Western
                            Germany) would produce or procure about 40 percent of their estimated
                            equipment deficiencies. The estimated cost of maintenance and
                            replacement equipment (item 2(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) of Table 2) was
                            based on the assumption that the United States would furnish 16 percent
                            of the gross maintenance requirements in fiscal year 1952 (item 1(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), Table 2), 14 percent in fiscal year 1953, 12
                            percent in fiscal year 1954 and 10 percent in fiscal year 1955. The 16
                            percent factor for fiscal year 1952 represents about 60 percent of the
                            total rates for maintenance parts and replacement equipment for
                            equipment on hand. Thereafter, it is assumed the armament industry of
                            Western Europe will supply an increasing portion of current maintenance
                            and replacement requirements for the equipment on hand.</p>
                        <p>5. The time-phasing of equipment requirements and of the estimated cost
                            of furnishing armament from the United States was related to estimates
                            of production lead time required to obtain the needed capital equipment
                            from current production both in the United States and in the Western
                            European countries. With respect to the United States, it was assumed
                            that our industrial mobilization base would be broadened to accommodate
                            the procurement by the Department of Defense for the needs of the United
                            States armed forces as well as those of the <pb facs="0452" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss> countries with an over-all
                            shortening of production lead times in fiscal years 1953 and 1954. It is
                            estimated that the capital equipment to be procured in the United States
                            will be produced in time to meet the time-phased force requirements of
                            the European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries. It is
                            assumed that with respect to the balance of European armament
                            requirements, the industry of Western Europe will keep pace with
                            American industry. The estimated costs of supporting European forces
                            (item 1(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>), except for maintenance parts and
                            replacement equipment which are time-phased in relation to armament
                            production) follow the time-phased requirements for the expansion of
                            European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> forces.</p>
                        <p>6. In fiscal and budgetary terms, items 1 and 2 in Table 2 are expressed
                            in and time-phased according to obligations. Actual expenditures,
                            including the call upon available resources in the economy of the United
                            States and Western Europe, would come at a later period. The estimated
                            amount of resources which Western Europe could make available for
                            defense purposes (item 4, Table 2) is on a current or an expenditure
                            basis. Since estimated available resources (mobilizable in Western
                            Europe plus those furnished by the United States) are only slightly in
                            excess of time-phased requirements, an unanticipated peaking of defense
                            expenditures in a given year would run into basic resource shortages.
                            Furthermore, the longer the European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries delay in raising forces and placing contracts
                            for armament, the greater will be the likelihood of losing resources for
                            defense use in the early years of the defense effort and encountering
                            resource shortages in the later years. In addition to the difficulties
                            of measuring the incidence of defense burdens by countries is not known
                            in detail, although the required studies are underway in the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> organization. It is probable that
                            these studies will indicate that assigned defense tasks will not be
                            distributed by countries in accordance with economic and financial
                            capabilities to sustain those tasks. Additional resources will be needed
                            from external sources. Although account has been taken of the
                            possibilities of transfers of resources among European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries, it is expected that
                            unmanageable defense burdens which fall on certain European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries will have to be compensated
                            in part by additional United States assistance. For all these reasons,
                            it has been deemed necessary to anticipate supplementary and justifiable
                            requirements for United States assistance either in the form of
                            armaments or economic aid, in addition to that needed to meet
                            anticipated dollar balance of payments deficits. The amount of aid in
                            other than armaments is $7.81 billion for the four fiscal years (item 7
                            Table 2).</p>
                        <p>7. All United States projected aid to the European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries (and Western Germany) is
                            included in Annex 1. However, certain countries are not directly
                            associated with the defense program for the <pb facs="0453" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> community, but nevertheless will
                            require continued economic aid to sustain their economies. These
                            countries include, at least in fiscal 1952, Austria, Greece, Iceland,
                            Ireland, Sweden, Trieste and Turkey. Aid for this latter group is
                            included in Part B of this annex. United States aid will also be needed
                            in support of European international economic institutions, such as the
                            European Payments Union, the Schuman Plan, and the Program of Trade
                            Liberalization. The total aid figures in Part A and in Part B of this
                            annex for European countries include such funds as may be required for
                            these institutions although the specific amount needed for this purpose
                            has not yet been determined.</p>
                        <p>8. <hi rend="italic">Greece, Turkey</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Iran</hi>,
                            on the southern periphery of the Soviet Bloc, are the recipients of
                            military aid under Title II of the Mutual Defense Assistance Act. The
                            tense international situation requires continuation of measures to
                            maintain and, as practicable, increase the military potential of these
                            countries which are among those likely to be the targets of further
                            Soviet aggression and which are in an area whose security is of vital
                            concern to the security of the United States.</p>
                        <p>9. The danger of satellite states engaging in hostilities against Greece
                            counsels against the reduction of Greek forces under arms as was
                            contemplated at the beginning of fiscal year 1951. Increased military
                            supplies and economic assistance from the United States are essential to
                            maintain these forces and to prepare them with the type of equipment
                            needed to defend themselves.</p>
                        <p>10. Notwithstanding the marked effect of American military aid already
                            rendered, the numerically strong Turkish armed forces still lack
                            adequate military equipment, supplies and training needed to attain the
                            level of combat effectiveness deemed essential for that country. In
                            order to attain combat effectiveness of the Turkish Forces, it is
                            essential that the United States support the establishment and training
                            of a non-commissioned officers corps in the Turkish Forces.</p>
                        <p>11. It is necessary to maintain a steady flow of military supplies to
                            Iran in support of the forces required to maintain internal order in
                            that country and to give the Government and people confidence in their
                            ability to do so. The Iranian Forces should be adequate to discharge
                            delaying action in the event of Soviet aggression in order to permit the
                            withdrawal of the Shah and Government, with some forces, to the southern
                            mountains in accordance with the Iranian military plans and to permit
                            implementation of a demolition program.</p>
                        <p>12. The five-year program recommended under Title II for Greece, Turkey
                            and Iran (in millions) is as follows:</p>
                        <table cols="5" rows="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">1951</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">1952</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">1953</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">1954</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">1955</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>$325.9</cell>
                                <cell>$271.3</cell>
                                <cell>$287.4</cell>
                                <cell>$262.4</cell>
                                <cell>$242.2</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <pb facs="0454" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/>
                        <p>13. The foregoing estimates for Title II are based upon the following
                            assumptions:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the international situation will not appreciably improve
                                during the course of the five-year period, but that actual
                                hostilities, either localized or general, will not commence, or the
                                likelihood of hostilities will not substantially increase. In case
                                of a more imminent danger of conflict, or of hostilities in any form
                                in the general area, the aid requirements would require adjustment
                                in light of circumstances prevailing at the time.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That common-use items for the Greek armed forces will be provided
                                    <hi rend="italic">in toto</hi> from the Greek economy, or, in
                                regard to foreign exchange costs, by funds appropriated for the
                                general economic support of Greece.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the size of the Greek, Turkish and Iranian forces will not be
                                increased appreciably during the period.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>That the achievement of United States objectives in the Near East
                                and South Asia will not require the furnishing of military
                                assistance on a grant basis to countries other than those presently
                                eligible for grant assistance under the Mutual Defense Assistance
                                Act.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>14. <hi rend="italic">The Far East</hi>. The estimated requirements for
                            military assistance on a grant basis to countries in the general area of
                            China, including the Philippines and Formosa but excluding Korea, are
                            given below:</p>
                        <table cols="2" rows="6">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Fiscal Year</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Estimated Requirements</hi> (in million
                                    dollars)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1951</cell>
                                <cell>$375.0</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1952</cell>
                                <cell>560.0</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1953</cell>
                                <cell>467.4</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1954</cell>
                                <cell>383.6</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>1955</cell>
                                <cell>358.7</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>15. <hi rend="italic">Indo-China</hi>. This country is the key to the
                            control of the mainland of Southeast Asia. Its loss would represent a
                            major strategic reversal for the United States and its allies and
                            concurrently a great increase in the political, economic and military
                            power of the enemy. The preservation of Indo-China from Communist
                            encroachment depends upon the success with which the military, economic
                            and political programs are concomitantly prosecuted. The military
                            program will fail unless the political and economic programs are a
                            success and vice versa. The immediate purpose of the political program
                            is to secure for Bao Dai the support of Indo-Chinese nationalists
                            sentiment. Even if this is achieved, Communist-inspired guerrilla
                            operations will continue until a successful military program has been
                            completed.</p>
                        <p>The success of the military operation depends upon the French who must
                            prosecute it successfully. We are confronted by the dilemma between this
                            fact and the fact that the more political concessions the <pb facs="0455" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/> French make the less they have
                            to fight for in Indo-China. They, nevertheless, should receive such aid
                            as the United States and the United Kingdom can contribute.</p>
                        <p>The cardinal point of the United States policy in Southeast Asia is that
                            Indochina must not be permitted to fall before the Communist pressure
                            which is not [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] symbolized internally by Ho
                            Chi Minh’s movement, and externally by Chinese Communist troops on the
                            Tonkin frontier. If Indochina is overrrun by the Communists, all of the
                            Southeast Asian mainland would rapidly succumb. The strategic loss to
                            the West and the resultant gain to the East would certainly make far
                            more difficult our efforts to contain Communism elsewhere in the
                            world.</p>
                        <p>To achieve our objective, it is recognized that a strong nationalist
                            anti-Communist counter-force must be developed in that area. The nucleus
                            of such a movement in Indo-China is represented by the three Associated
                            States of which the State of Vietnam is the largest. These governments
                            must be supported and strengthened in every possible manner,
                            politically, militarily and economically.</p>
                        <p>The United States Military Aid Program for Indo-China is designed to help
                            in the establishment of national armies, national guard and police
                            forces for the three States and to supply American military equipment to
                            the Army of the French Union.</p>
                        <p>The governments of the Associated States are being assisted in their
                            efforts to develop their national armies in order to resist Communist
                            fifth column and terrorist activities from within.</p>
                        <p>16. <hi rend="italic">Korea</hi>. Any projection of probable military
                            assistance requirements for Korea for the post-hostilities period must
                            be based upon factors which cannot yet be assessed. The chief factors
                            determining the amount, character and timing of military assistance to
                            Korea include (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) the extent to which the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> will participate in any program of
                            military assistance to Korea; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) the magnitude
                            of the internal security problem, including guerrilla operations; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) the extent to which the Chinese Communists and
                            the Soviet Union support and abet the guerrilla operations and border
                            incursions; and (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) the necessary size of Korean
                            military forces to insure the internal security and prevent border
                            incursions.</p>
                        <p>17. <hi rend="italic">Formosa</hi>. On June 27, 1950, the President
                            ordered the Seventh Fleet to prevent any attack on Formosa. As a
                            corollary to this action, the President called upon the Chinese
                            Government on Formosa to cease all air and sea operations against the
                            mainland. The President stated that the determination of the future
                            status of Formosa must await the restoration of security in the Pacific,
                            a peace settlement with Japan, or consideration by the United Nations.
                            The implementation <pb facs="0456" n="440" xml:id="pg_440"/> of these
                            directives of the President requires the furnishing of military
                            equipment and training assistance to the Chinese Government forces on
                            Formosa to enable them to defend the island and to assist the Seventh
                            Fleet in rendering the island area secure.</p>
                        <p>18. <hi rend="italic">Thailand</hi>. The objective of United States
                            military assistance to Thailand is to enable that Government to carry
                            through its announced intention to resisting Communist encroachment.
                            Since the threat to Thailand has not yet developed to severe
                            proportions, there is an opportunity to modernize and train the Thai
                            forces to resist Communist encroachment.</p>
                        <p>19. <hi rend="italic">The Philippines</hi>. The United States has a
                            unique responsibility in the Philippines because of a half century of
                            American sovereignty over the islands. In addition, the Philippines
                            furnish important bases and facilities for the United States forces. A
                            serious internal security problem exists in the islands. The solution
                            calls for military and economic assistance as well as political
                            guidance. With respect to military aid, it is recommended that equipment
                            be furnished to equip expanded security forces and to modernize and
                            train the present forces. Greater emphasis is also being given to the
                            training of the Philippine army.</p>
                        <p>20. <hi rend="italic">Indonesia</hi>. The basic objective of the military
                            assistance program for Indonesia is to strengthen the constabulary to
                            enable it to perform effectively its function of maintaining law and
                            order under the authority of the central government. This objective
                            includes the prevention of smuggling activities in Indonesian
                            waters.</p>
                        <p>21. <hi rend="italic">The Other American Republics</hi>. The
                            inter-American community is a source of both immediate and reserve
                            political and economic strength. Its military strength is limited
                            although not negligible. Its military manpower and the equipment
                            presently available are essential to the maintenance of internal
                            security in the other American states. Properly trained and equipped,
                            the manpower of these countries could be used to maintain the security
                            of lines of communication in the inter-American area and possibly to
                            contribute forces to overseas operations. Although a specific estimate
                            of training requirements and urgent equipment needs has not been
                            included in the estimates given above, it is believed that nominal
                            amounts of funds should be made available, when and if circumstances
                            require, to meet training and selected equipment requirements of the
                            other American states in accordance with the policies laid down in
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 56/2.<note n="7" xml:id="d145fn8">Of May 18, <ref target="#pg_628">p.
                                628</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>[Here follow Table 1, “Estimated Costs of Meeting United States
                            Objectives Under the Mutual Defense Assistance Programs,” and Table 2,
                            “Estimated Costs to the United States of Assisting the European <pb facs="0457" n="441" xml:id="pg_441"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> Countries (and Western Germany) to
                            Meet their Requirements under the Medium Term Defense Plan.”]</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">part b. anticipated u.s. foreign grant and loan
                                assistance</hi><note n="†" xml:id="d145fn9">Economic aid
                                requirements for European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss>
                                countries and Western Germany are given in Part A of this annex.
                                [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">(Prepared by the Department of State and the Economic
                            Cooperation Administration)</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The estimates given in table 3<note n="8" xml:id="d145fn10">Not
                                    reproduced herein.</note> below of foreign grant and loan
                                assistance were made on the assumption that we shall not be engaged
                                in a major war, but that the Soviet Union will intensify its efforts
                                to extend the orbit of its influence and control. Our objective in
                                providing economic aid is to create situations of political and
                                economic strength in the free world especially in critical areas
                                whose present weakness may invite Soviet thrusts. However, as a
                                consequence of increased demands on U.S. resources resulting from a
                                military defense program that may require expenditures at a rate of
                                $50 billion a year, claims on U.S. resources for foreign aid have
                                been limited to programs that will meet most urgent and immediate
                                needs. These programs have therefore been restricted to those
                                fulfilling three broad purposes: (1) investment to increase the
                                production and facilitate the distribution of critical materials
                                directly needed for defense, (2) aid to strengthen the defense
                                effort of our allies, and (3) aid to enable governments which are or
                                can be expected to become friendly members of the free world to win
                                the confidence and support of their own peoples as a solid
                                foundation for political stability and national independence. To
                                reduce the drain on U.S. resources, aid programs have been held to
                                the minimum believed necessary to effect these purposes.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The basic task in Europe now is to build up the combined defenses
                                of the European nations without seriously endangering thereby their
                                economic strength. All U.S. military end-item and economic aid to
                                assist in achieving this objective is included in Annex I. However,
                                certain countries are not directly associated with the defense
                                program for the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> community but
                                nevertheless will require continued economic aid to sustain their
                                economies. These include, at least in fiscal 1952 the following
                                countries: Austria, Greece, Iceland, Ireland, Sweden, Trieste and
                                Turkey. Aid for this latter group is included in Annex II. U.S. aid
                                will also be needed in support of European international economic
                                institutions such as the European Payments Union, the Schuman Plan,
                                and the program of trade liberalization. The total aid figures in
                                Annex I and in Annex II for O.E.E.C. countries include such funds as
                                may be required for these institutions although the specific amount
                                needed for this purpose has not yet been determined.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The primary task in other areas is to assist them to make progress
                                    <pb facs="0458" n="442" xml:id="pg_442"/> toward meeting the
                                aspirations and demands of their people for the satisfaction of
                                their basic needs, to enable the governments thereby to command
                                allegiance and support, and to maximize the output of materials
                                essential to the continued strength of the free world.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In determining whether and to what extent to provide U.S.
                                Government assistance in any given area, account has been taken of
                                aid likely to be made available by the <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> and other sources, and of increased dollar
                                earnings that should result from expanded U.S. imports, upward price
                                movements, and U.S. troop expenditures abroad. Aid has been
                                scheduled in the form of U.S. Government loans for development
                                projects normally regarded as bankable where it appears that
                                recipients can carry additional dollar debt. Aid has been scheduled
                                in the form of grants for technical assistance projects, including
                                associated supplies and equipment required to make the technical
                                assistance projects effective. In certain exceptional cases, grant
                                aid has been scheduled for capital investment projects as well. This
                                has been done only in the case of countries of great strategic
                                importance to us, for which loans and investments cannot be
                                contemplated in the near future and which, in the absence of certain
                                capital goods, would experience rapid economic deterioration and
                                political instability.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Making available funds for carrying out the foreign aid programs outlined
                            below will not in and of itself achieve the foreign policy results
                            desired. It will be necessary that the essential supplies, many of which
                            may be in short supply, be assured both for shipment under the aid
                            programs and for shipment for essential purposes where the foreign
                            countries themselves are able to furnish the necessary funds. To
                            accomplish this purpose as well as to minimize the drain on the U.S.
                            economy in the form of non-essential exports careful examination will be
                            necessary of the scope of our export controls and the policies under
                            which they operate.</p>
                        <p>[Here follows Table 3, “Actual and Anticipated U.S. Government Grant and
                            Loan Aid.”]</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">notes</hi><note n="9" xml:id="d145fn11">These notes
                                accompanied Table 3.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Western Europe:</hi> The estimates for Western Europe
                            are still in discussion among <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>, the
                            Department of Defense, and the State Department.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Yugoslavia:</hi> Yugoslavia’s disaffection from the
                            Soviet Bloc has subjected her economy to severe strains because of
                            abruptly severed trade relations with <gloss target="#t_Cominform1">Cominform</gloss> countries, heavy defense expenditures, and the
                            greater need to succeed as a Communist state in rapid industrialization.
                                <pb facs="0459" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/> It is in the U.S. interest
                            that Yugoslavia remain outside the Soviet Bloc and maintain a viable
                            economy.</p>
                        <p>To assist Yugoslavia to overcome the effects of the recent severe
                            drought, grant aid of $64 million will be needed for expenditure in
                            fiscal 1951. However, because certain government agencies are providing
                            immediate food relief for Yugoslavia out of their existing
                            appropriations, Congress will be asked to appropriate only $38 million.
                            It is possible that, in consequence of the drought, further grant funds
                            will be needed in 1952.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_IBRD1">IBRD</gloss> rather than the <gloss target="#t_EximBank1">Eximbank</gloss> is expected to provide
                            further loan funds for Yugoslavia’s economic development.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Latin America:</hi> The program of economic assistance
                            which is projected for Latin America is primarily one of production for
                            defense purposes. The objectives are to increase the availability of
                            critical materials which the U.S. will need for industrial and defense
                            output, to maintain production of food and other items at a level
                            adequate to meet the essential requirements of western Europe from this
                            traditional source of supply, and to develop production which will
                            minimize the dependence of Latin American States on imported food and
                            other essential supplies in case of emergency. In addition, it will be
                            necessary to speed up the construction of the Inter-American Highway.
                            …</p>
                        <p>Increased U.S. procurement and higher raw material prices will increase
                            Latin America’s dollar receipts and her capacity to service further
                            dollar debt. Consequently the major part of U.S. assistance to Latin
                            America is scheduled in the form of loan aid (largely for
                            transportation, fuel and power facilities). It is estimated that Latin
                            America will require foreign capital for investment at a rate of about
                            $350 million a year, of which the International Bank may be able to
                            finance about $125 million a year, leaving about $225 million a year for
                            U.S. Government loans.</p>
                        <p>Grant aid for Latin America includes $64 million over four years for
                            completion of the Inter-American Highway, and about $28 million a year
                            for an expanded technical assistance program, with particular stress on
                            aid to increase indigenous food production.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Japan and the Ryukyus:</hi> The estimates of budgetary
                            requirements for Japan and the Ryukyu Islands represent, for fiscal year
                            1951, funds actually made available for obligation; for fiscal year
                            1952, figures recently submitted by the Department of the Army to the
                            Bureau of the Budget; and for other years, tentative projections by the
                            Department of the Army.</p>
                        <p>The assumptions underlying them, particularly those relating to Japan’s
                            foreign trade prospects, are on the whole conservative. Should her
                            foreign exchange earnings exceed the estimates, however, the <pb facs="0460" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/> more favorable economic
                            position that would result from the projected level of aid in fiscal
                            year 1952 would not be inconsistent with objectives of U.S. policy
                            toward Japan.</p>
                        <p>The Defense Department is considering a partial pay-as-you-go arrangement
                            to begin on July 1, 1951. If that arrangement is established, it would
                            obviate the need for any <gloss target="#t_GARIOA1">GARIOA</gloss>
                            appropriation for economic aid to Japan, although <gloss target="#t_GARIOA1">GARIOA</gloss> funds for administrative expenses
                            and the reorientation program might continue to be needed.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">South East Asia</hi> (<hi rend="italic">including
                                Formosa</hi>)<hi rend="italic">:</hi> The objective of U.S. aid is
                            to strengthen the present moderate and Western-oriented governments in
                            this area, to increase internal support for these governments, and to
                            give effective evidence at the grass roots of U.S. Government
                            constructive interest in the local welfare.</p>
                        <p>The amount of aid actually required will depend on the direction and pace
                            of current political and military developments. The estimates assume
                            that there will be no serious political degeneration in the countries
                            concerned and that those countries which are now suffering military and
                            guerilla operations will become gradually pacified.</p>
                        <p>The grant aid program for <gloss target="#t_STEM1">STEM</gloss> countries
                            is substantially a continuation of the program recommended by the
                            Griffin Mission and recently initiated under <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>. It embraces rehabilitation and development projects
                            with strong emphasis on technical assistance and associated supplies and
                            equipment for direct implementation of technical assistance projects, as
                            well as consumer goods needed to raise local revenues for rehabilitation
                            projects without embarrassment to the fiscal systems of the countries
                            concerned. The projects cover a wide range, but particular emphasis is
                            placed on health, agriculture, and transport.</p>
                        <p>U.S. Government loan assistance is provided for longer-term capital
                            investment projects in Indonesia and Burma which have capacity to
                            service further indebtedness. Thailand’s needs for long-term capital
                            investment will probably be met by the International Bank. Malayan needs
                            should logically be the responsibility of the U.K.</p>
                        <p>The estimates for Formosa are projected on “as is” assumptions regarding
                            Formosa’s membership in the free world, its present status, and its
                            military burden. The general political outlook in the Far East and the
                            fact of U.N. consideration of Formosa’s further status render the latter
                            two of the above assumptions highly speculative. Aid estimates now
                            prepared for Formosa taper off in the later years, reflecting the
                            assumption that increased productivity would enable the island to carry
                            a greater portion of the burden resulting from a high level of Chinese
                            military expenditures.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Korea:</hi> The studies of the damage to and
                            requirements of the Korean economy in consequence of the hostilities
                            have not been completed, <pb facs="0461" n="445" xml:id="pg_445"/> and
                            it will be many months before reliable figures can be obtained.</p>
                        <p>Estimates thus far compiled by <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>
                            indicate that the total cost of foreign aid for reconstructing and
                            restoring the Korean economy would be somewhat less than $1 billion. The
                            capacity of the Korean economy to absorb imports requiring foreign
                            financing is probably limited to $150 million per year. The absorptive
                            capacity would be greater in the initial years, however, since a
                            substantial portion of total requirements is for relief-type goods. The
                            annual costs set forth are projected only through fiscal year 1955, but
                            assistance beyond that date may be required if the country is to become
                            self-sustaining.</p>
                        <p>It is assumed that the U.S. will bear 65 to 70 percent of the costs of a
                            United Nations program.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Philippines:</hi> The payments and expenditures of the
                            United States in the Philippines have supported the economy of that
                            country since liberation from the Japanese forces. Without such
                            assistance the large trade deficit and budgetary deficit would have
                            resulted in a serious economic crisis and inevitable large-scale support
                            of the Communists. However, a substantial part of U.S. aid funds was
                            made available to meet war damage claims and consequently was not used
                            in such a way as to encourage increased production. The program
                            projected above is designed to assist in the development of resources of
                            the Philippines required to achieve viability and stability which are
                            essential if the Philippines are to resist Communist pressure.</p>
                        <p>A minimum program designed to achieve viability will have to be based
                            primarily on agricultural development but some increase in
                            industrialization is justified. Among the principal goals of such a
                            program would be (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) self-sufficiency in rice,
                            corn, fish, vegetables and fruit; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) increased
                            sugar production for export to at least the U.S. quota total level and
                            abaca production to the 1940 level; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)
                            modernization of selected mines and determination of location and extent
                            of mineral resources; (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) expanded facilities for
                            processing ores, wood and agricultural products; (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) expanded hydro-electric power for the production of
                            nitrogen fertilizer and for other purposes; (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)
                            expansion of small-scale industry, and (<hi rend="italic">g</hi>)
                            improvement of general and vocational education and further improvement
                            of public health to the extent required to provide the basis for
                            economic development. In addition, if any economic development program
                            is to proceed with reasonable prospects of success in the Philippines,
                            it will be necessary that (<hi rend="italic">h</hi>) the Government’s
                            budget be balanced by raising revenues substantially, and (<hi rend="italic">i</hi>) that popular support among the agrarian
                            population be enlisted by improving agricultural credit facilities,
                            providing for land resettlement and redistribution, etc.</p>
                        <pb facs="0462" n="446" xml:id="pg_446"/>
                        <p>There is no immediate prospect of any substantial flow of private capital
                            into the Philippines and it would appear that the economy is not strong
                            enough to support loans for the minimum development required to achieve
                            viability. With grant funds available for this purpose over the next few
                            years, it is considered that public loan capital and private equity
                            capital could then start to flow into the Philippines to support the
                            type of development required for long-term stability.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">New Zealand:</hi> New Zealand is not a member of the
                            International Bank and will probably need <gloss target="#t_EximBank1">Eximbank</gloss> assistance to expand productive capacity. Aid to
                            New Zealand is aid in the common defense effort.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Near East:</hi> This area because of its location for
                            international transportation and its oil production is of vital
                            importance to the U.S.</p>
                        <p>Iran is more insistently under the pressure of Soviet proximity and
                            interest than perhaps any other country. There is ferment and unrest in
                            the neighboring Arab States. Immigration into Israel of Jews presently
                            residing in Moslem States continues unabated and with it heavy economic
                            burdens for the State of Israel. In addition there remain several
                            hundreds of thousands of unsettled Arab refugees from the war between
                            the Arab States and Israel.</p>
                        <p>The U.S. is already committed to assist in the resettlement of Arab
                            refugees. In the case of Iran, it is desirable that the U.S. render
                            effective assistance as tangible evidence to the government and the
                            people of American interest in the preservation of the country’s
                            independence and to strengthen both the ability and the will to resist
                            Soviet aggression and communist subversion. It is necessary in the Arab
                            States to provide assistance that will give some forward momentum to
                            these static economies. In the case of Israel, it is in the U.S.
                            interest that this new State receive the technical and financial aid
                            which it will need to cope with its many difficult problems and
                            discharge its international responsibilities.</p>
                        <p>In addition to aid for the settlement of Arab refugees, the grant aid
                            scheduled for this area is intended to cover the cost of an enlarged
                            program of technical assistance and associated supplies and equipment,
                            ranging from specific projects at the village level for the improvement
                            of health, sanitation and education facilities, training in agricultural
                            techniques and the provision of seed, tools and fertilizer, to broad
                            survey and diagnostic missions.</p>
                        <p>Loan assistance is provided for capital investment projects in Israel,
                            Iran, Lebanon, Saudi Arabia and possibly Egypt. (It may become necessary
                            to increase the grant component for the Near East area if Iran is unable
                            to secure loan assistance for necessary development projects.)</p>
                        <pb facs="0463" n="447" xml:id="pg_447"/>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Africa:</hi> The bulk of the assistance for this
                            continent is intended for the African dependent territories. The purpose
                            of both the grant and loan aid is to expand and develop the production
                            of strategic materials and associated improvements in transportation,
                            power and port facilities, as well as indigenous food, fiber and other
                            essential raw material production so as to increase and maintain the
                            internal economic development of the African territories and their
                            contribution to the Western European economies. The program is a
                            continuation and expansion through the years 1952–55 of activities
                            already underway in the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>Western Europe’s 1949 imports from overseas dependencies, largely in
                            Africa, amounted roughly to about $2.5 billion in value. U.S. imports
                            from these areas come to about $400 million in value. Raw material and
                            food exports from these territories included rubber, palm oil, sisal,
                            hemp, hides and skins, cork, copra, vegetables, fruits, cereals, sugar
                            and dairy products.</p>
                        <p>It is anticipated that the aid will be made available through and in
                            cooperation with the European colonial powers. If carefully administered
                            the program should contribute not only to the objectives cited above but
                            should also have the effect of increasing employment, productivity, and
                            economic and political stability throughout Africa.</p>
                        <p>Aid has been scheduled in the form of loans to the extent that loan aid
                            appears feasible.</p>
                        <p>Small amounts of aid have been scheduled for the independent countries of
                            Africa, largely for technical assistance.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">South Asia:</hi> The situation in the Indian
                            Sub-Continent is one involving <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> economic
                            deterioration to date and the prospect of continuing future
                            deterioration as population growth outruns prospective Increases in
                            productivity. Continuing future deterioration appears inescapable unless
                            external aid can be injected to reverse the trends that are now so
                            clearly discernible. Reversal of these trends is an imperative vital
                            interest of the U.S. India and Pakistan are of determinative importance
                            in the pattern of Asian political relations. The present governments of
                            India and Pakistan are moderate in policy and friendly to the West, and
                            they continue to command the support of the wide majority of their
                            people. However, support is giving way to apathy, and organized parties
                            on the extreme right (fanatic religious groups) and the extreme left are
                            gaining strength as economic conditions continue to deteriorate. These
                            adverse political and economic trends might be arrested now by a U.S.
                            aid program, directed primarily toward improvement In agricultural
                            productivity. If these adverse trends are allowed to gain strength,
                            however, a situation might be created which—like that in China—could
                            only be redressed through an effort lying beyond our capabilities. An
                            aid program should also <pb facs="0464" n="448" xml:id="pg_448"/> serve
                            to demonstrate our interest in the welfare and aspirations of the people
                            of this area and thereby tend to align them more closely with us in the
                            face of Communist threats or blandishments.</p>
                        <p>The program proposed is about half of the deficit not covered by other
                            sources envisaged by the countries concerned in connection with the
                            development plans put forward at the Columbo Conference. While it will
                            not support these plans in full, it will give impetus to the process of
                            economic development in those countries.</p>
                        <p>It is not supposed that the aid program as scheduled for this area would
                            of itself bring about significant increases in living standards. It is
                            hoped, however, that beyond the arrest of economic deterioration and
                            consequent political instability during the next few critical years, the
                            recipient countries at the end of such a program would have established
                            an environment that would encourage a maximum utilization of domestic
                            savings and a reasonable flow of outside investment capital for further
                            developmental activities.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Technical Assistance:</hi> The estimates represent the
                            anticipated contribution of Point IV funds to the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Technical Assistance Program, the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> and other international
                            organizations.</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Appendix to Annex No</hi>. 2</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">eca</gloss> information
                                program</hi><note n="‡" xml:id="d145fn12">See also Annex No. 5.
                                [Footnote in the source text.]</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">(Prepared by the Economic Cooperation Administration)</p>
                        <p>The Economic Cooperation Administration has been instructed by Congress
                            (Public Law 535—81st Congress)<note n="10" xml:id="d145fn13">The Foreign
                                Economic Assistance Act of 1950 (64 Stat. 198).</note> “to give full
                            and continuous publicity through the press, radio, and all other
                            available media, so as to inform the peoples of the participating
                            countries regarding the assistance, including its purpose, source and
                            character, furnished by the American taxpayer.”</p>
                        <p>The Economic Cooperation Administration is therefore charged with a
                            direct responsibility for conducting a foreign information program with
                            regard to one specific aspect of the foreign policy of the United
                            States. The great majority of its information work consists of
                            thoroughly informing the people of the Marshall Plan countries of the
                            achievements and objectives of the Plan.</p>
                        <p>While conducting this information program, the Economic Cooperation
                            Administration, in order to promote the success of the Marshall Plan, is
                            involved in many aspects of the international information program
                            carried on by the Department of State. It particularly is involved in
                            information designed:</p>
                        <pb facs="0465" n="449" xml:id="pg_449"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>To promote will and energy on the part of peoples whose
                                governments are recipients of Economic Cooperation Administration’s
                                assistance,</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>To promote understanding of the nature of Soviet Communism and to
                                encourage attitudes hostile to it in the countries involved,</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>To promote through the exploitation of traditions, loyalties,
                                hopes and fears the closer economic association of the nations of
                                Europe,</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                            <item>To promote a sense of urgency and sacrifice for the cooperative
                                and collaborative defense of the free world.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The foreign information program of the Economic Cooperation
                            Administration has been, and still is most vigorously conducted in the
                            sixteen countries of western Europe which are recipients of Economic
                            Cooperation Administration assistance. Foreign information services are
                            being developed in the countries of Southeast Asia where the Economic
                            Cooperation Administration is administering programs.</p>
                        <p>From the beginning, the Economic Cooperation Administration has
                            decentralized the operations of its foreign information program. The
                            largest information operation is in the Office of the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Special Representative in Paris. That
                            office assists the Mission information officers, particularly those in
                            countries without counterpart funds or which are backward in
                            informational media techniques. It also functions on a Western
                            Europe-wide basis to produce, in the various media, materials showing
                            the overall achievements and objectives of the Marshall Plan in all the
                            Western European members.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission in each participating
                            country has an American information officer, generally one or two
                            assistants, and a high-quality local staff composed of nationals
                            (generally ex-newspaper and radio men) of the country concerned.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> has also operated on the
                            principle of vigorous participation by indigenous governments and
                            peoples. It has paid close attention to organized labor in Europe,
                            especially in countries like France and Italy where the Communists still
                            control the largest labor confederations. It has labor information
                            officers in the majority of the Missions.</p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> produces the bulk of its information
                            materials in the country in which it is operating and distributes these
                            through its own facilities, the facilities of the United States
                            Information Service and indigenous channels. It employs all media—press,
                            radio, exhibits, movies, contests, sound and projection trucks, wall
                            posters, toy balloons, leaflets, booklets, games, signs on <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> projects and even troubadours in
                            Sicily.</p>
                        <p>In conformity with <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 59/1,<note n="11" xml:id="d145fn14">
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 59/1, a report by the National
                                Security Council, March 9, 1950, on “The Foreign Information Program
                                and Psychological Warfare Planning,” is not printed.</note> the
                                <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> foreign information program <pb facs="0466" n="450" xml:id="pg_450"/> is coordinated with other
                            foreign information activities of the United States Government in
                            support of national objectives. Policy coordination is assured through
                            the participation of the representative of the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> on the Interdepartmental Foreign Information
                            Organization. It is further assured by the activities of committees set
                            up in the capital of each nation in which the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> is functioning. These committees consist of the Public
                            Affairs Officer, the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Information
                            Officer, the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Labor Information
                            Officer, an administrative officer of the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission and an administrative officer of the Embassy.
                            Their task is to discuss the information activities of <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> in that country and to work out joint projects where
                            possible. Such joint projects are financed with <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> counterpart funds.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Information Officer is required
                            to provide <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Washington with usable
                            material—press and magazine stories, radio programs and movies—which can
                            be circulated on this side so that the American taxpayer may know what
                            becomes of the money he contributes to the Marshall Plan.</p>
                        <p>About fourth-fifths of the cost of <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>’s
                            overseas information program is paid from counterpart funds.</p>
                        <p>[Here follows Annex No. 3, “The Civil Defense Program,” prepared by the
                            National Security Resources Board.]</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex No</hi>. 4<note n="12" xml:id="d145fn15">Dated December 7, 1950.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">The United States Stockpile Program</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">(Prepared by the National Security Resources Board)</p>
                        <p>1. The stockpile program is intended to provide the United States with
                            strategic and critical materials essential for the prosecution of a
                            5-year war. Stockpile objectives are the difference between essential
                            wartime requirements on the one hand and wartime U.S. domestic
                            production and imports from accessible sources on the other.</p>
                        <p>2. These estimates are based on information developed by interagency
                            commodity committees and approved by the Interdepartmental Stockpile
                            Committee on which are represented State, Interior, Commerce,
                            Agriculture, <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_GSA1">GSA</gloss>, and Munitions Board, and to which the
                            Resources Board, Budget, <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>, Army,
                            Navy, Air Force, and <gloss target="#t_RDB1">RDB</gloss> send
                            observers.</p>
                        <p>3. Due to the changes in the current military program and an anticipated
                            acceleration in current military procurement over and above that
                            contemplated in the September version of Annex 1,<note n="13" xml:id="d145fn16">Not printed.</note> although no change is expected
                            in the objectives, it will be necessary to revise the <pb facs="0467" n="451" xml:id="pg_451"/> phasing of stockpile objectives. The
                            stockpiling program as presented here is intended to be kept flexible
                            and can be readily revised as to phasing to reflect changes in current
                            requirements, material on hand, materials available, and strategic
                            assumptions. It should be noted that the actual rate of acquisition of
                            stockpile materials is the subject of constant study and review. Changes
                            may be made in the acquisition rate of various materials from time to
                            time depending upon current availability weighed against demand of the
                            current military and war-supporting requirements.</p>
                        <p>3. [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] In addition, stockpile objectives
                            themselves are undergoing constant review, particularly in the light of
                            such questions as substitution of other less critical materials, tests
                            of necessity, and changes in military specifications. As results of the
                            above studies become available, stockpile objectives themselves are
                            subject to the possibility of change, upward or downward. The program
                            presented here is the best considered opinion of all those concerned of
                            what is essential and required for our defense preparedness.</p>
                        <p>4. Estimated requirements for funds include only those necessary for the
                            acquisition of materials, and do not include expenditures for
                            administration, handling, storage, and rotation. They are based on the
                            following assumptions:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>General war may start at any time. For the sake of planning,
                                however, June 30, 1954 is taken as the date by which minimum
                                stockpiles must be on hand physically within the continental United
                                States. (The more materials stockpiled before 1954, the greater the
                                national security. However, for some few materials, it will be
                                physically impossible to complete stockpiles by 1954.)</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>September 30, 1950 price levels (for purposes of comparison, funds
                                and expenditures on June 30, 1950 levels are also included).</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                            <item>Effective controls as authorized by the Defense Production Act of
                                1950 to channel strategic and critical materials to military
                                programs, essential war-supporting programs, and the national
                                stockpile.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>5. Overall dollar figures are given below, and quantitative details for
                            eleven of the most important materials are in the attached table. About
                            70 materials are being stockpiled.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>The acquisition of minimum stockpile objectives by mid-1954 will
                                require, at September 30, 1950 prices, the appropriation of $4.1
                                billion new obligational authority, in addition to authorizations
                                that have already been enacted. These funds will be obligated and
                                expended in accordance with the following schedule:</item>
                        </list>
                        <table cols="6" rows="4">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>’51</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>’52</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>’53</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">
                                        <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>’54</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">After <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>’54</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell cols="5">(Billions of Dollars—September 30, 1950
                                    prices)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Obligation</cell>
                                <cell>1.8</cell>
                                <cell>1.0</cell>
                                <cell>1.0</cell>
                                <cell>0.3</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Expenditure</cell>
                                <cell>0.2<note n="§" xml:id="d145fn17">See par, below. [Footnote in
                                        the source text.]</note>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>1.6</cell>
                                <cell>1.0</cell>
                                <cell>0.8</cell>
                                <cell>0.5</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <pb facs="0468" n="452" xml:id="pg_452"/>
                        <p>6. At September 30, 1950 prices, and with present authorizations, the
                            stockpile has $2.0 billion worth of materials on hand, $1.5 billion
                            worth financed for delivery after fiscal year 1951.</p>
                        <p>7. At June 30, 1950 prices, and with present authorizations, the
                            stockpile has $1.7 billion worth of materials on hand, $1.3 billion
                            worth financed for delivery in fiscal year 1951, and $0.3 billion worth
                            financed for delivery after fiscal year 1951.</p>
                        <p>[Here follow two tables indicating proposed acquisitions of major items
                            from Fiscal Year 1951 through Fiscal Year 1954 and after.]</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex No</hi>. 5</p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">The Foreign Information Programs</hi><note n="14" xml:id="d145fn18">Additional documentation on this subject is
                                scheduled for publication in volume <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">(Prepared by the Department of State)</p>
                        <p>[Here follow Table A, “The Information and Educational Exchange Program,”
                            and Table B, “Other State Department Information Programs.”]</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Task of Information and Educational
                                Exchange</hi>. The frustration of the design of the Kremlin will
                            result primarily from concrete decisions taken and vigorous measures
                            executed in the political, military and economic fields by the people
                            and the governments of the free world under the leadership of the United
                            States. The task of the United States foreign information and
                            educational exchange programs is to assure that the psychological
                            implications of these actions are, first, fully developed and second,
                            effectively conveyed to the minds and the emotions of groups and
                            individuals who may importantly influence governmental action and
                            popular attitudes in other nations and among other peoples,</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">The Basis of Cooperation and Resistance</hi>.
                            Governmental action and popular attitudes will be influenced along lines
                            favorable to the achievement of United States objectives through
                            recognition of the interests shared by the people and the Government of
                            the United States and other governments and peoples. The Charter of the
                            United Nations reflects these basic interests.</p>
                        <p>Recognition of common interests does not require agreement with regard to
                            religious practices, cultural traditions, social forms, political
                            institutions or economic arrangements. The United States is bound by its
                            principles to respect differences between its own internal arrangements
                            and those of others.</p>
                        <p>The United States and other peoples and nations share common interests
                            which information and exchange programs can cultivate, in:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>National freedom, including both the desire for recognized status
                                in international affairs and the desire to maintain characteristic
                                indigenous cultures. </item>
                            <pb facs="0469" n="453" xml:id="pg_453"/>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Peace and security against external aggression.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Social advancement, economic progress and human welfare, under
                                governments responsive to popular aspirations.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Effective international relationships to serve these ends.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Identity of interest among the nations and peoples of the free world will
                            not be meaningful as an abstraction but only as revealed in the daily
                            life of groups and individuals. It must be regarded as an invigorating
                            and heartening factor in their efforts to achieve freedom, opportunity
                            and security.</p>
                        <p>These shared interests provide a psychological basis both for
                            constructive collaboration among peoples and nations and for creating
                            and maintaining resistance to Soviet Communism.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">The Development of Psychological Resistance</hi>.
                            The development and maintenance of psychological resistance to the
                            design of the Kremlin calls for continuous and highly detailed exposure
                            of the ways in which Soviet Communism threatens the interest shared by
                            other peoples and nations. These may be revealed in the contradiction
                            between the deeds and the words of the Kremlin, between the ideals
                            proclaimed abroad and the conditions of poverty, oppression and terror
                            prevailing within the Soviet Union and its satellites and between the
                            professions of peace and the facts of massive armed force and of
                            imperial aggression. By concrete example of what Soviet Communism has
                            done within its orbit and intends to do wherever its agents seize
                            authority, the myth can be destroyed that it stands for national
                            freedom, international peace, social progress, economic development and
                            human betterment.</p>
                        <p>Exposure of the nature, the intentions and the capabilities of the Soviet
                            Union is part of a program to induce peoples and nations outside its
                            sphere:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To face up to the fact that Soviet Communism is the implacable
                                enemy of all free nations and peoples and of their common
                                aspirations.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To participate in effective actions to deter or, if necessary to
                                repel direct or indirect aggression by the Soviet Union and its
                                satellites.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To sacrifice leisure and comforts in order to resist Soviet
                                Communism.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To maintain efficient governments, stable economies and the
                                disciplines required to support resistance to Soviet
                                Communism.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To prevent the infiltration of agents of Soviet Communism into the
                                armed forces, the government, labor unions, educational
                                institutions, press and radio and other key organizations and to
                                bring about the elimination of those already in such
                                positions.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To cooperate with other nations and peoples in a spirit of
                                accommodation for mutually desired ends.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                            <item>To carry on these actions for as long as necessary to frustrate
                                the design of the Kremlin.</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0470" n="454" xml:id="pg_454"/>
                        <p>The United States will be unrealistic if it expects all peoples and all
                            nations outside the sphere of the Kremlin to respond in the same way and
                            to the same extent to the stimuli of shared interests. Nations and
                            peoples have interests additional to these shared with the United
                            States; these will also shape their attitudes and govern their actions.
                            Propaganda that fails to take account of this diversity in the world
                            will not only misrepresent United States policy but over-reach itself.
                            In some cases, political, economic, and military considerations will
                            require that propaganda endeavor to bring about as full as possible
                            correspondence between the commitments and the actions of another nation
                            or people with the commitments and the actions taken by the United
                            States. In others, the United States can afford to be satisfied if the
                            other nation or people only decline to associate themselves with the
                            Soviet Union.</p>
                        <p>The peoples under the domination of the Soviet Union are potential allies
                            whose hope for ultimate liberation should be nourished . . . . This is
                            particularly true of intellectuals in governments and out, of many in
                            the armed services and of a large part of the peasantry. To the degree
                            to which, while refraining from premature action, they identify their
                            interests with those of the free world, the internal structure of Soviet
                            Communism will be weakened, its controls strained and its aggressive
                            possibilities restricted. Combined with the knowledge that the United
                            States and its associates are building military strength capable of
                            defending the free world against Soviet aggression, the knowledge that
                            the people of the USSR and its satellites are unreliable subjects might
                            incline the Kremlin eventually to choose courses of accommodation that
                            would avoid a war threatening its own power and the security of the
                            motherland.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">The Development of a Sense of Urgency</hi>. In the
                            situation that now exists, the development of psychological resistance
                            must, to contribute effectively to defending wide areas of freedom
                            against aggression and occupation, take place within a relatively short
                            time. To accomplish this, information programs must expose and explain
                            the relationship of Soviet military capabilities to the aggressive
                            nature and intent of Soviet Communism. Careful consideration should be
                            given to making public at an appropriate time the atomic capabilities of
                            the USSR.</p>
                        <p>5. <hi rend="italic">The Development of Confidence and Hope</hi>.
                            Effective psychological resistance to Soviet Communism cannot, however,
                            be expected to grow and to flourish as the result solely of arousing
                            hatred of its intentions and fear of its capabilities. Hatred and fear
                            alone may inspire, not stubborn and active resistance, but a withdrawal
                            into “neutralism” and a resignation to despair. A hardy psychological
                            resistance <pb facs="0471" n="455" xml:id="pg_455"/> must rise from, and
                            constantly refresh, confidence and hope.</p>
                        <p>Confidence and hope in the future will be inspired in other peoples to
                            the degree that they are convinced, emotionally and intellectually,
                            that:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The means of accomplishing a successful military defense against
                                Soviet aggression are or will shortly be at hand.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The frustration of the design of the Kremlin will advance their
                                legitimate aspirations, notably the achievement of national freedom
                                and a large degree of economic independence.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Their right to share in shaping the future will not be measured
                                only by their material capabilities but by recognition of their
                                cultural traditions, indigenous institutions and national
                                character.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>They are regarded as full partners in a common undertaking.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The endeavor to frustrate the design of the Kremlin is not an
                                effort to maintain or to restore a <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi>
                                but is a step in the development of evolutionary arrangements among
                                and between nations giving an enhanced degree of political
                                stability, economic progress, social development and international
                                order.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Although Soviet Communism currently is the greatest threat to the
                            fulfillment of the legitimate aspirations of peoples seeking freedom,
                            many of the conditions against which free nations and peoples are
                            obliged to contend did not originate with any particular system but have
                            been exploited by Soviet Communism for its own advantage.</p>
                        <p>6. <hi rend="italic">The Role of the United States</hi>. The degree to
                            which other peoples and nations develop and maintain confidence in
                            themselves and the free society of which they are or hope to be a part
                            will depend in critical measure upon their confidence in the United
                            States. Circumstances and events have thrust upon the United States
                            leadership in world affairs. The role is difficult and uncomfortable. It
                            requires patience and self-restraint. Its rewards are not invariably
                            understanding, much less gratitude. The United States cannot escape the
                            responsibilities of the role, but it can and should avoid being
                            arbitrary, domineering and condescending. It should endeavor to speak
                            through deeds as well as by words. It should desire that others than
                            itself advertise its virtues. It should seek to exercise authority
                            through willing concurrence rather than enforced compliance.</p>
                        <p>To inspire confidence in its own intentions and capabilities, the United
                            States must convince other peoples and nations that:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>It regards the arming of itself and the free world as the shield
                                behind which it pursues its objectives of safeguarding freedom,
                                maintaining peace, furthering human welfare and bulwarking
                                international order.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>It does not regard war with the Soviet Union as inevitable.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>It is not in its character to wage aggressive or preventive war,
                                although it will resist aggression with vigor, resource and will and
                                with confident assurance of ultimate success. </item>
                            <pb facs="0472" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>All its actions in the international field are in conformity with
                                the principles of the Charter of the United Nations.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</label>
                            <item>The United States always stands ready to consider in appropriate
                                forums concrete proposals put forward by the USSR which contain any
                                promise of diminishing international tension and which do not
                                involve compromise of the basic principles of the United States and
                                the free world. At the same time, the United States believes that
                                general discussions with the USSR will be fruitful to the extent
                                that the United States and the free world possess strength on a
                                scale providing authority and flexibility in negotiations.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">f</hi>.</label>
                            <item>It has the will and the means to make hard decisions and execute
                                necessary plans at sacrifice and cost without creating political or
                                economic instability.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">g</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Notwithstanding necessary partial curtailments of assistance for
                                purely economic purposes, it regards the development of strong
                                indigenous economies in other areas of the world as an indispensable
                                element in its foreign policy.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">h</hi>.</label>
                            <item>It has no imperial ambitions.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">i</hi>.</label>
                            <item>It contemplates the wide distribution of power in the world among
                                peoples and nations, large and small, all responsive to suitable and
                                effective international authority.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">j</hi>.</label>
                            <item>It is determined that in building up its military strength it
                                shall not undermine its basic principles, its respect for individual
                                liberty, its hatred of political oppression, its opposition to
                                totalitarian practices, its love of justice.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The people and the Government of the United States can not fail to be
                            aware that, in the future even more than in the past, their reliability,
                            their character and their devotion to sound principle will be judged not
                            only by what they do directly in the name of foreign policy but also by
                            how they manage their affairs and deal with each other in their domestic
                            relations. Other peoples will not be impressed only by factories put
                            into operation in the United States and armed forces created. They will
                            also be impressed by the quality of the educational system, the support
                            given to cultural institutions, the rise or fall of crime rates, the
                            measure of social justice for various groups and individuals, the degree
                            of self- and group-discipline shown in the pursuit of the national
                            purpose and by other tests of the vigor and scope of the nation’s civic
                            virtue.</p>
                        <p>In order to correct constantly recurring misunderstanding and
                            misconceptions about the United States, which are often more damaging,
                            particularly among basically well-disposed foreign peoples, than the
                            lies of Soviet propagandists, the need continues for making widely known
                            abroad the nature of the people, the history and the institutions of the
                            United States. The objective is not to boast the virtues of the United
                            States or to induce other peoples to adopt its institutions, political,
                            economic or social. The objective rather is to create understanding of
                            how Americans live and work, how richly various is <pb facs="0473" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/> their society, how their institutions
                            function and what are the goals of the national life. Such understanding
                            is an essential basis for the judgment of other peoples of the character
                            of the decisions now taken and the actions flowing from them.</p>
                        <p>The confidence and hope that the United States can communicate to other
                            peoples and nations can only be as great as their confidence in
                            themselves and their hope for their own future. In view of the demands
                            that are now to be made upon them, they are entitled to:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>As full revelation of the facts concerning the peril in which they
                                and the rest of the free world stand as considerations of military
                                security will permit.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>A thorough exposition of the reasoning behind the program for a
                                build-up of strength.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Continuous information concerning the progress of the program and
                                its impact on the world.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Maximum care in the formulation and coordination of official
                                statements so that these contribute neither to confusion at home nor
                                to the propaganda advantage of Soviet Communism abroad.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>7. <hi rend="italic">The Instrumentalities</hi>. Statements by the
                            President, the Secretary of State and other responsible civilian and
                            military authorities, the utterances of congressional leaders and
                            private citizens, declarations by leaders of friendly nations and
                            peoples in the United Nations and elsewhere, together with concrete
                            actions taken in the political, diplomatic, military and economic field
                            will constitute much of the content of the information programs. The
                            wide diffusion, correct understanding and meaningful impact of these
                            statements and actions will require:</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Concentration of effort in the psychological
                            field within nations and among peoples that are</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(1)</label>
                            <item>…,</item>
                            <label>(2)</label>
                            <item>possible targets of forceful aggression by Soviet
                                Communism,</item>
                            <label>(3)</label>
                            <item>under constant harassment by the propaganda and the agents of
                                Soviet Communism,</item>
                            <label>(4)</label>
                            <item>vulnerable strategically and psychologically,</item>
                            <label>(5)</label>
                            <item>sensitive because of internal conditions to communist
                                propaganda.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. Concentration of effort on those groups and
                            individuals having the greatest influence over governmental action and
                            popular attitudes.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. Determination of the media—radio, press,
                            motion pictures, books and the exchange of persons—most effective in
                            reaching these target groups and shaping their use to assure the utmost
                            impact.</p>
                        <p>8. <hi rend="italic">The Target Areas</hi>. Nations and peoples will
                            shift from one category to another as the international situation itself
                            changes. Thirty-seven nations and areas in Europe, the Far East, the
                            Near <pb facs="0474" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/> and Middle East and Latin
                            America are now considered to require urgent attention. Only eight
                            nations, for the most part in the Western Hemisphere, are now considered
                            to require no special attention. The remainder fall into categories
                            between these two.</p>
                        <p>9. <hi rend="italic">The Target Groups</hi>. The groups and individuals
                            deemed to have the greatest influence in these areas vary with
                            prevailing political institutions, social forms, cultural traditions and
                            educational levels. Where governmental power is largely controlled and
                            transmitted by authoritarian devices, intellectuals and governmental
                            officials constitute the most important targets. In areas in which
                            political power has passed largely under popular control, these groups
                            are still important for the influence, disproportionate to their
                            numbers, that they wield in the press, the universities and the council
                            chambers. At the other extreme, the power and influence, if only
                            passive, of the peasantry and the urban proletariat, even in areas where
                            illiteracy is high and popular government does not exist, must be taken
                            into account. A given population will most effectively and most
                            practically be reached through concentration on those elements broadly
                            representative of it. Labor and youth are groups newly emerging in power
                            and influence in many areas; they are also groups whose attitude may
                            determine the character of national action in a time of crisis. They
                            therefore have a special importance, and they represent roughly half of
                            the groups on which especial effort is to be concentrated in all
                            areas.</p>
                        <p>10. <hi rend="italic">The Choice of Methods and Techniques</hi>. The
                            sharp definition of the target areas and target groups calls for equally
                            sharp focusing of the available media—radio, press and publications,
                            motion pictures, books and other cultural materials and the exchange of
                            persons—on those targets.</p>
                        <p>Because radio broadcasting, despite jamming, is the only medium now
                            capable of reaching large audiences inside the Iron Curtain, the rapid
                            construction of relay and transmitting facilities enabling broadcasts to
                            be heard on medium as well as shortwave is essential. In order to reach
                            important segments of the population in critical areas, broadcasting
                            languages will be increased to include tongues and dialects prevalent in
                            the Soviet Union and Central Asia. In addition, small low-cost receiving
                            sets are to be distributed by appropriate agencies behind the Iron
                            Curtain and in areas outside it, notably Korea, where sets are few.</p>
                        <p>The full potentialities of other media will be similarly developed.
                            Emphasis in the field of publications will fall on the production of
                            leaflets, pamphlets, picture books and magazines specifically designed
                            to appeal to youth, labor, community leaders and intellectuals.
                            Filmstrips, posters and pictorial exhibits and displays will be directed
                            at <pb facs="0475" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"/> the same audiences. By
                            arrangement with the motion picture industry, newsreels will be produced
                            for and widely distributed to foreign exhibitors, and equipment will be
                            made available for the wider showing of documentaries produced by the
                            Government. The exchange of persons program involves bringing upwards of
                            three thousand individuals to the United States annually, with heavy
                            emphasis on labor leaders, youth groups, professional and community
                            leaders and public officials. Additional information centers will be
                            established, especially in small communities, and efforts will be made
                            to encourage and to support comparable indigenous centers. The impact of
                            these centers will be increased by the wide distribution of books
                            translated from English, assistance and support given to the teaching of
                            English and the distribution of books and other cultural materials to
                            indigenous institutions.</p>
                        <p>These undertakings will be fully effective only if they are carried out
                            with close regard for local interests, tastes, prejudices and habits.
                            Hence, programming and production will be carried out largely in the
                            field, with the assistance of highly qualified local personnel under
                            competent American supervision. This applies to pamphlets, leaflets and
                            exhibits, to the production of local radio programs, to the local
                            production of films, to the management of information and community
                            centers, to the translation of books and to arrangements for the
                            exchange of persons.</p>
                        <p>No less important is the consideration that a point can quickly be
                            reached at which overt official propaganda becomes self-defeating. Even
                            the friendliest government and people will not welcome or long support a
                            heavy influx of information materials and personnel bearing the label of
                            the United States Government. A basic consideration therefore is that to
                            the maximum possible extent the production and distribution of
                            information materials and the conduct of information activities should
                            be carried out by indigenous personnel and indigenous institutions. This
                            means the maximum utilization of local personnel, the provision of
                            equipment and materials to indigenous organizations, including
                            governments, and the encouragement and support of bi- and multi-national
                            indigenous bodies. It involves full cooperation with and support of the
                            information activities of likeminded governments, of such regional
                            organizations as the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and of the
                            United Nations. In the exchange of persons, it means that maximum
                            cooperation should be sought from labor, business, civic and other
                            community organizations in the United States for the reception and care
                            of foreign visitors.</p>
                        <p>11. <hi rend="italic">Investigation and Research</hi>. The penetration of
                            the Iron Curtain presents a special problem. A group of social and
                            natural scientists <pb facs="0476" n="460" xml:id="pg_460"/> have
                            already been engaged to investigate every possible method of getting
                            information into the Soviet world. This investigation will include every
                            scheme thus far put forward, no matter how unlikely or unprofitable it
                            may appear to be. Included in their tasks, but by no means confined to
                            this one problem, will be a thorough exploration of all possible means
                            to combat the Soviet jamming of <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss>
                            programs.</p>
                        <p>The studies normally carried on concerning the effectiveness of various
                            media and various propaganda themes are to be supplemented by regional
                            investigations involving not only the basic aspirations of other
                            peoples, but also the symbols to which they respond.</p>
                        <p>12. <hi rend="italic">Allocation of Funds</hi>. By far the larger part of
                            the projected appropriations will be utilized for the construction of
                            broadcasting facilities designed to increase the range of the broadcasts
                            and the ease of their reception, the establishment of local production
                            centers and the staffing of them with competent highly qualified local
                            and American supervising personnel and the expansion of <gloss target="#t_USIE1">USIE</gloss> staffs, particularly by the addition
                            of personnel skilled in developing fruitful relationships with priority
                            target groups and of producing materials and programs of special
                            interest to them.</p>
                        <p>The expansion of physical facilities, particularly the relay bases and
                            medium-wave transmitters abroad, will take place on a large scale in
                            1951 and 1952 and will come to its peak early in the fiscal year 1953,
                            at which time the information programs will have at their disposal
                            facilities and equipment capable of meeting the now fore-seen demands
                            upon it. The rate and extent of the development of the information and
                            educational exchange programs to meet the requirements of the existing
                            situation will depend upon the removal of restrictions and conditions
                            that now prevent maximum operational flexibility and the granting of
                            certain additional authority. The radio facilities expansion proposed
                            requires the successful solution of the problems, one, of obtaining
                            necessary frequencies by a review of present and projected facilities;
                            two, of acquisition of sites for overseas relay bases; three, of
                            obtaining within the Government suitable priorities for research and
                            intelligence.</p>
                        <p>13. <hi rend="italic">Coordination Within the Government and with Other
                                Governments</hi>. The effective execution of these programs will
                            require extensive coordination within the Government and with other
                            governments. The organization established within the Department of State
                            pursuant to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 59/1 provides a
                            mechanism for coordination among the Department of State, the Department
                            of Defense, the Joint Chiefs of Staff, the Economic Cooperation
                            Administration and the Central Intelligence Agency in international
                            informational <pb facs="0477" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/> matters.<note n="║" xml:id="d145fn19">See also the Appendix to Annex No. 2, The
                                    <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Information Program.
                                [Footnote in the source text.]</note> The establishment of the
                            information section in the North Atlantic Treaty Council provides the
                            mechanism for close coordination of the international information
                            activities of the nations parties to this treaty. Coordination between
                            the United States and other governments is provided for in an
                            instruction of the Department of State authorizing close coordination
                            with the Government of the United Kingdom, and other governments as may
                            be agreed, in a broad range of information activity.</p>
                        <p>Inasmuch as the success of these coordinated activities will require
                            extensive activity in the international information field by all
                            available resources, and particularly by governments other than that of
                            the United States, other governments need to be encouraged to develop
                            and to maintain vigorous international information activities.</p>
                        <p>Coordination with private agencies in the United States, including a wide
                            range of business, professional, civic, labor and youth organizations
                            and representatives of foreign groups, in the production, utilization
                            and dissemination of materials and in the exchange of persons is carried
                            on in accordance with the provisions of Public Law 402.<note n="15" xml:id="d145fn20">Public Law 402, 80th Cong., 2nd sess., the United
                                States Information and Educational Exchange Act of 1948 (the
                                Smith–Mundt Act) (62 Stat. 6).</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Annex No</hi>. 6<note n="16" xml:id="d145fn21">Dated December 1, 1950.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Intelligence and Related Activities</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">(Prepared by the Central Intelligence Agency, with the
                            concurrence of the Intelligence Advisory Committee)</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>It is axiomatic that the situation appreciated in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 and the policy proposed to meet
                                it require the improvement and intensification of U.S. foreign
                                intelligence and related activities, as a safeguard against
                                political or military surprise, and as essential to the conduct of
                                the affirmative program envisaged.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The Director of Central Intelligence and Intelligence Advisory
                                Committee have taken and are taking action directed toward the
                                improvement and intensification of foreign intelligence and related
                                activities. For reasons of security, the specific programs
                                undertaken and contemplated, and their budgetary requirements, are
                                not set forth here. It has been determined, however, that even the
                                substantially increased budgets now projected would be
                                inconsiderable in relation to the grand total of the other programs
                                projected in this report.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>[Here follows Annex No. 7, “The Internal Security Program,” prepared by
                            the Interdepartmental Intelligence Conference and the Interdepartmental
                            Committee on Internal Security.]</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>