<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-12-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-12-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="155" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d155">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Executive Secretariat
                        Files: Lot 53D244</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-12-27">December 27, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Senator Hickenlooper<note n="1" xml:id="d155fn1">Senator Bourke B.
                            Hickenlooper of Iowa; member of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee
                            and the Joint Committee on Atomic Energy.</note> telephoned me this
                        afternoon to ask whether he could come in for a talk. I said that he could
                        come in immediately or I would make an appointment later at his convenience.
                        He came at once and stayed with me for about half an hour.</p>
                    <pb facs="0504" n="488" xml:id="pg_488"/>
                    <p>The Senator said that he was deeply concerned about the course of events and
                        about positions which he would be called upon to take and would like to tell
                        me some of his worries. He said that he would regard our conversation as
                        wholly confidential and would not repeat it or mention me in any way.</p>
                    <p>The Senator spoke first about the course of events in the Far East. He
                        thought that the misfortunes of the campaign in Korea were undermining our
                        position in Japan, the Philippines and on the continent of Asia and asked
                        whether it was not desirable and necessary to have what he called a
                        diversion in Asia. By this he meant fomenting outbreaks against the
                        Communists in China and possible use of the Army on Formosa to make landings
                        on the mainland. He spoke of a meeting of the Armed Services Committee of
                        the Senate which he had been invited to attend at which General
                            Chennault<note n="2" xml:id="d155fn2">Maj. Gen. Claire L. Chennault
                            (ret.), Adviser to Generalissimo Chiang Kaishek, President of the
                            National Government of the Republic of China, 1937–1941; Commanding
                            General, Fourteenth Air Force, United States Army Air Forces,
                            1943–1945.</note> had talked about the possibility of assisting
                        dissension on the mainland. …</p>
                    <p>The Senator thought that efforts along this line were the most productive
                        open to us. He went on to mention his fears that the defense of Western
                        Europe was impossible and said that General Collins<note n="3" xml:id="d155fn3">General J. Lawton Collins, Chief of Staff, United
                            States Army.</note> in answer to a question from the Senator along these
                        lines at the last meeting of the Committee had left the Senator with the
                        impression that the defense of Western Europe was possible only if
                        everything turned out exactly as we hoped, including efforts by our allies
                        and sufficient time being made available by the Russians. He thought that it
                        was unlikely that this combination of events would occur and was therefore
                        worried that we were wasting our strength.</p>
                    <p>The Senator thought that in the Middle West isolationism was growing. He
                        stated that he did not agree with the isolationist point of view and that he
                        thought the people of the Middle West quickly lost these views when trouble
                        started. He said that the Middle West had the highest record of voluntary
                        enlistments of any section of the country during World Wars I and II.</p>
                    <p>I said to the Senator that in thinking about the matters which he had
                        propounded it seemed to me we must always keep in mind who our principal
                        antagonist was. This was the Soviet Union and not China. Therefore it was
                        important not only to increase our own military strength but do everything
                        possible so that we would have an area from which our strength and that of
                        others could be deployed in case of necessity. This led to the importance of
                        the British Isles, Western Europe and certain areas in the Eastern
                        Mediterranean. If we did not make every effort to strengthen and hold these
                        parts of the world, then it seemed likely not only that we would have no
                        platform from which <pb facs="0505" n="489" xml:id="pg_489"/> to operate if
                        we had to against the Soviet Union, but that we would turn great potential
                        strength to the other side. I said, in response to his reference to the
                        atomic bomb, that the usefulness of this weapon would be minimized if the
                        Russians were not required to concentrate and put on a big effort in order
                        to attack Western Europe. (The Senator, in reply, tended to be pessimistic
                        about the utility of the atomic bomb.)</p>
                    <p>So far as the Far East was concerned, I said that we were not overlooking the
                        possibilities of stirring up trouble in China. I spoke of some of the
                        problems which had to be surmounted and of the fact that this was not a
                        matter which lent itself to public discussion. I spoke of the logistical
                        problems which were raised by his suggestion of using the Nationalist forces
                        for an attack on the mainland while the operations in Korea were going
                        forward.</p>
                    <p>The Senator said that while all that I said was true, it still seemed to him
                        that we were in danger of wasting our strength in Europe and that we should
                        concentrate more in the Far East along the lines he had suggested. I said to
                        him that I thought all these matters required more time for discussion than
                        we had available at the moment and suggested to him that we would be glad to
                        ask him to come down for a few meetings with us at which we could brief him
                        more in detail on particular area problems. He said that he would be glad to
                        do this.</p>
                    <p>The next move is therefore up to us. I suggest that Mr. McFall talk this over
                        with Mr. Webb, Mr. Rusk, and Mr. Perkins and that we consider having further
                        meetings with Senator Hickenlooper. The Senator’s manner was friendly
                        throughout. My impression was that he was sincere in wishing to impart his
                        worries to me for any comfort which I could give him. He did not appear to
                        take much comfort from what I said.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>D[<hi rend="smallcaps">ean</hi>] A[<hi rend="smallcaps">cheson</hi>]</signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>