<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the South African Ambassador ( (Jooste))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d185</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">185</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-08-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recOrZuJ5me6ilcbT" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85141276"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Uranium</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-08-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-08-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="185"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Department of State Atomic Energy Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the South
                        African Ambassador</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Jooste</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>The Secretary of State presents his compliments to His Excellency the Ambassador
                    of the Union of South Africa and has the honor to refer to their conversation of
                    July 12, 1950 during the course of which the Ambassador stated the desire of his
                    Government to associate itself closely with the United States and the United
                    Kingdom in the field of Atomic energy. The Government of the United States
                    previously had been made aware by the Government of the United Kingdom of the
                    interest of the Union of South Africa in being accorded a special position in
                    this field if it becomes an important supplier of uranium.</p>
                <p>The Government of the United States wishes to reassure the Government of the
                    Union of South Africa that its proposals will be given sympathetic consideration
                    in consultation with the Government of the United Kingdom in the light of the
                    principles underlying the existing relationships amongst the United States, the
                    United Kingdom and Canada in the field of atomic energy and other relevant
                    factors.</p>
                <p>The Government of the United States is prepared to discuss this subject at a
                    mutually agreed time and among such representatives as may be designated by the
                    three Governments concerned. In order to provide a framework for expeditious
                    discussion of the matter, it would be most helpful if the Government of the
                    Union of South Africa would define in the near future what sort of cooperation
                    in the field of atomic energy it is interested in establishing with the United
                    States and the United Kingdom.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, it is the earnest desire of the Government of the United States that
                    progress be made as rapidly as circumstances permit toward understandings on
                    technical and commercial matters relating to a contract for uranium between the
                    Combined Development Agency and the South African Atomic Energy Board.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-08-24">August 24,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
