<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs (
                    (Miller) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">209</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-05-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="209"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d209">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">710.5/5–1750</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Inter-American Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Miller</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-17">May 17,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Paper 56—United
                    States Policy Toward Inter-American Military Collaboration</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Problem:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At the National Security Council meeting on Thursday, May 18, the above-mentioned
                    document will be submitted for approval. This <pb facs="0642" n="626"
                        xml:id="pg_626"/> memorandum recommends a position to be taken by the
                    Department at that time.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The present paper represents several months of work to harmonize the views of
                    this Department and the Defense Department on military relations with Latin
                    America. For many years, difficulties have been encountered on this subject as a
                    result of conflicting objectives sometimes pursued by the two Departments. It is
                    the Defense Department’s desire to develop in the Latin American countries small
                    but competent military establishments capable of performing limited defense
                    functions in time of war, in order that United States manpower may not need to
                    be tied up there. Development of such armed forces frequently involves
                    expenditures for armaments by the Latin American countries which they can ill
                    afford. Encouragement of such expenditures runs counter to the Department’s
                    policies of seeking to develop stronger, more productive economies in Latin
                    America, recognizing that the production of raw materials may well be Latin
                    America’s major contribution to hemisphere defense in time of war.</p>
                <p>The present paper has set forth fully the basic considerations of both
                    Departments and suggests methods for harmonizing these views in a basic national
                    policy.</p>
                <p>First, the paper recognizes (paragraph 8) that individual problems cannot be
                    settled on the basis of political, economic or military factors alone, but only
                    by a weighing of United States interests in respect to all three areas of
                    policy. The net result of the paper in this regard is primarily to indicate an
                    approach to problems with perhaps a greater comprehension on the part of each
                    Department of the requirements and interests of the other.</p>
                <p>Second, the paper sets forth a method for developing a clear understanding of the
                    role of each Latin American country in a hemisphere defense plan. On the basis
                    of such roles, this Government will have a better idea of the character and
                    extent of armament which each of the Latin American countries should possess for
                    hemisphere defense.</p>
                <p>The paper at present gives a very elementary indication of the thinking of the
                    Defense Department regarding the role of Latin American countries (paragraph
                        17).<note n="1" xml:id="d209fn1">See footnote 3 to the letter from Mr. Rusk
                        to General Burns, April 25, 1950, <ref target="#pg_624">p. 624</ref>.</note>
                    At various times in the discussion the Defense Department has insisted upon
                    whittling down its references to the strategic roles of other countries. It is
                    believed that <pb facs="0643" n="627" xml:id="pg_627"/> the present reference to
                    this subject represents a bare minimum which should not be reduced any
                    further.</p>
                <p>The paper states the importance of standardization of the armed forces in Latin
                    America on United States lines as a long range objective, but recognizes that
                    standardization cannot be an overriding consideration taking precedence over all
                    other military or political factors. This is a highly important statement in
                    view of the political difficulties facing the standardization policy at this
                        time.<note n="2" xml:id="d209fn2">Further information on views within the
                        Department with regard to arms standardization in the Western Hemisphere is
                        in files 710.5, 720.5, and 720.5 <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> for
                        1950.</note>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is recommended that the paper be approved in its present form.</p>
                <p>It is also recommended that during the discussion the Secretary take an
                    opportunity to express the following points: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The present document is an acceptable statement on military objectives
                            and an outline of the proper steps which should be taken at the
                            appropriate time to reach a clearer understanding of the role of each
                            American republic in hemisphere defense. To be realistic, we must
                            recognize, however, that the successful implementation of this policy
                            paper will encounter many practical difficulties. As the paper itself
                            indicates (paragraph 8), it will be necessary constantly to weigh the
                            various political, economic and military factors which bear upon the
                            desirability, from the viewpoint of the United States, of proceeding
                            with any given step in regard to each country.<note n="3"
                                xml:id="d209fn3">Mr. Dreier’s memorandum of March 20, 1950 to Mr.
                                Barber said in part: “As people in the <gloss target="#t_NME1"
                                    >NME</gloss> have pointed out, it will be some time before the
                                procedure outlined in this paper results in any actual estimates of
                                the amounts and types of armaments required by the armed forces of
                                other American republics. It will, therefore, not for some time be
                                of assistance to the Department in reaching opinions as to whether
                                individual requests for arms should be approved. This fact should
                                not, in my opinion, prevent us from concurring in what is a greatly
                                improved paper, setting forth a policy to which we can willingly
                                subscribe.” (710.5/3–2050)</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The above fact emphasizes the need for continued consultation between
                            the two Departments in regard to the implementation of this program, and
                            the need for full agreement at each stage. It would be highly desirable
                            for this point to be emphasized to the officers of both Departments not
                            only in Washington but also in the field.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward</hi> G. <hi rend="smallcaps">Miller, Jr.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
