<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="217" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d217">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">795B.5/9–1250</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-09-12">12 September
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: I refer to Deputy Under
                        Secretary Matthews’ letter of 9 August 1950,<note n="1" xml:id="d217fn1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>.</note> transmitting a study by the
                        Department of State concerning Latin American participation in the Korean
                        operation.</p>
                    <p>These proposals have been thoroughly reviewed by the Joint Chiefs of Staff,
                        who are in general agreement with the Department of State as to the
                        desirability of Latin American forces joining the unified command, under the
                        United Nations’ aegis, in the war in Korea. They also concur in the view of
                        that Department that positive United States assistance is essential to any
                        effective military contributions from Latin America.</p>
                    <p>In view of the problems involved, the Joint Chiefs of Staff feel that it will
                        be difficult for any existing Latin American army or air combat units to be
                        effectively trained, properly equipped, and transported to the Korean
                        theater in time for participation in the military operations to clear South
                        Korea of the North Koreans. However, in view of the long-range potential
                        benefit to hemisphere relations, the Joint Chiefs of Staff feel that
                        extraordinary efforts should be made by the Department of State without
                        delay to obtain offers and to facilitate the participation of such units.
                        Certain of the larger Latin American nations, furthermore, possess naval
                        vessels which, if immediately proffered, could, in all probability, be used
                        in such combat operations. It is also possible that army, navy, and air
                        units from certain of the Latin American nations could participate in the
                        United Nations occupation in Korea after hostilities have ceased.</p>
                    <p>In the light of the foregoing considerations, the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                        recommend that prompt action be taken by the Department of State to obtain
                        offers of completely organized and, insofar as possible, fully equipped and
                        self-sustaining army, navy, and air units from the Latin American nations as
                        occupation forces in Korea or for combat operations if this proves possible.
                        While it would be highly desirable to have army units of not less than 1,000
                        total strength, and air units of not less than squadron strength, the Joint
                        Chiefs of Staff are willing to accept organized units of smaller size which
                        can operate under the flag of the offering country. The Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff recommend that those Latin American nations which are unable to
                        contribute organized combat military units be encouraged to proffer
                        organized service elements, such as surgical teams, ambulance units,
                        engineer detachments, and port or labor battalions.</p>
                    <pb facs="0666" n="650" xml:id="pg_650"/>
                    <p>For those nations which could not make contributions of battalion size or
                        greater, the Joint Chiefs of Staff would give sympathetic consideration to
                        the organization and employment in the Korean operation of some such units
                        as an Inter-American Force of national units, each under its own flag and
                        preserving its own national identity, providing the plan for such an
                        organization is worked out through the appropriate agency of the
                        Organization of American States, namely the Inter-American Defense Board,
                        and subject to Department of State approval. On the other hand, the Joint
                        Chiefs of Staff are of the opinion that it would be wholly impracticable and
                        militarily unsound for the United States to attempt at present to organize,
                        train, and equip an international unit composed of unorganized volunteers
                        from the several Latin American nations. Furthermore, the Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff have consistently opposed the organization of any United Nations
                        force, other than armed guards, in lieu of the forces to be provided that
                        Organization under Article 43 of the Charter.<note n="2" xml:id="d217fn2">For text of the Charter of the United Nations, signed at San Francisco,
                            June 26, 1945, see Department of State Treaty Series (TS) No. 093, or 59
                            Stat. (pt. 2) 1031.</note> Accordingly, the general recruitment of
                        volunteers under United Nations aegis of an international unit from Latin
                        America is opposed by the Joint Chiefs of Staff, particularly since this
                        would set a precedent. The grouping together of units from an area included
                        in a United Nations security arrangement under the aegis of the Unified
                        Command for the United Nations Forces in Korea would not be inconsistent
                        with previous positions of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.</p>
                    <p>The Joint Chiefs of Staff would welcome offers from Latin American nations
                        possessing troop transports or merchant vessels registered under their flags
                        to provide water transportation for their own contingents and those of other
                        participating countries.</p>
                    <p>The procedures now in effect between our respective Departments, whereby the
                        Joint Chiefs of Staff are consulted in each instance prior to the acceptance
                        of offers of military assistance, should, of course, be followed with
                        respect to offers by Latin American nations. Once the United States
                        Government has accepted a firm offer of assistance from another nation, then
                        the military representatives of that nation will complete negotiations
                        pertaining to the assistance directly with the United States military
                        department concerned.</p>
                    <p>The Department of Defense recognizes that many of the Latin American nations
                        will not be able to reimburse the United States for some of the equipment,
                        supplies and service which will have to be provided by the United States in
                        order to make their contribution of armed forces effective. As you know,
                        with the concurrence of the Departments of State and Treasury, and after
                        approval by the President, <pb facs="0667" n="651" xml:id="pg_651"/> I
                        issued on 1 September 1950 a memorandum<note n="3" xml:id="d217fn3">
                            <p>This memorandum said in part:</p>
                            <p>“The several Services should seek arrangements under which the
                                foreign governments will completely equip and supply their forces.
                                To the extent that such complete support is not practicable but the
                                offer is otherwise desirable, the military departments of the United
                                States will make available necessary supplies or services on a basis
                                of immediate reimbursement in U.S. dollars. To the extent that the
                                foreign Government cannot make prompt reimbursement in U.S. dollars,
                                the U.S. Government and the foreign government will negotiate the
                                terms of settlement.” (795B.5/9–650)</p>
                            <p>In a memorandum of September 14, 1950, to Mr. Merchant, Edward W.
                                Doherty, Officer in Charge of Economic Affairs in the Office of
                                Northeast Asian Affairs, said in part:</p>
                            <p>“. . . Mr. Johnson’s letter of September 12, in the last paragraph
                                but one, expressly states that the acceptance of Latin American
                                units, except on a reimbursable basis, will be contingent upon the
                                conclusion of arrangements among the participating nations for
                                reciprocal aid and reimbursement in kind. This is a gross
                                misconstruction of the purpose and effect of the memorandum of
                                September 1, which was to permit offers of military assistance to be
                                accepted without hindrance from issues involving compensation or
                                reimbursement, but also without prejudice to the ultimate settlement
                                of questions of reimbursement between the U.S. Government and the
                                foreign government.” (795B.5/9–1250)</p>
                            <p>Additional documentation on discussions of this question held between
                                officials of the State, Defense, and Treasury Departments prior to
                                the letter from the Secretary of State to Secretary Marshall,
                                September 27, 1950 (<ref target="#pg_664">p. 664</ref>), is in
                                decimal file 795B.5 for September 1950.</p>
                        </note> to the military departments and the Joint Chiefs of Staff furnishing
                        them interim guidance with respect to this problem, which is of world-wide
                        scope and not confined to the Latin American area. That memorandum does not,
                        however, develop the possibilities of reimbursement in kind or mutual
                        reciprocal aid among the participating nations, which are matters of
                        intergovernmental scope. The Department of Defense would be prepared to
                        assist the Departments of State and Treasury in considering and resolving
                        them. The Joint Chiefs of Staff regard the solution of this broad problem as
                        a matter of great importance, and recommendations for the acceptance of
                        organized Latin American units except on a reimbursable basis will have to
                        be contingent upon its favorable resolution.</p>
                    <p>In closing, I should like to observe that the Joint Chiefs of Staff are
                        convinced that the inability to date of the Latin American nations to
                        furnish immediately adequately equipped and trained combat forces points up
                        the necessity for the prompt implementation of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 56/2.<note n="4" xml:id="d217fn4">Of May 18, 1950, <ref target="#pg_628">p. 628</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Louis Johnson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>