<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="218" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d218">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">720.5621/9–1250</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of Defense</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the
                                <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-09-12">12 September
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: You will recall that a
                        substantial number of patrol, auxiliary and amphibious vessels were sold to
                        various Other <pb facs="0668" n="652" xml:id="pg_652"/> American Republics
                        under the provisions of the Surplus Property Act of 1944. Since the
                        expiration of this Act in 1947, there has been no legal authority for such
                        sales until the passage of the Mutual Defense Assistance Act (Public Law
                        329) in October 1949. However, vessel sales under that law were not
                        practicable because of the “full cost” provisions. Public Law 621, 81st
                        Congress, approved by the President on 26 July 1950, has amended this
                        provision to permit sales at a “fair value as determined by the
                        President.”</p>
                    <p>A plan for hemispheric defense is now being formulated by the Inter-American
                        Defense Board. This plan will reaffirm the need for the standardization of
                        military equipment, training and methods of operation among all countries
                        signatory to the Rio Treaty. It is expected that the principal naval
                        responsibilities assigned by this plan to the Other American Republics will
                        be the protection of their lines of sea communications, over which must pass
                        the major portion of the vast quantities of the strategic materials supplied
                        to us by those countries.</p>
                    <p>Although these countries have indicated their desire to produce a plan of
                        hemispheric defense and agree to it, in most instances they do not have the
                        naval equipment to make such plans effective. The publication of the revised
                        wording of Section 408(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the Mutual Defense
                        Assistance Act<note n="1" xml:id="d218fn1">Public Law 621, approved July 6,
                            1950 (64 Stat. 373).</note> has raised the expectation and hope that, at
                        long last, the purchase of excess U.S. naval vessels required for the
                        implementation of the Inter-American Defense Board’s plans may soon be
                        effected.</p>
                    <p>In light of the above, I recommend that a program of sale of excess U.S.
                        naval vessels to certain of these countries be finalized at the earliest
                        opportunity, and that the countries concerned be informed as to the vessels
                        which we are prepared to sell to them, with the approximate prices. Such a
                        program is set forth on the inclosure.<note n="2" xml:id="d218fn2">
                            <p>In a memorandum of September 7, 1950, to Messrs. Warren and Miller,
                                Duncan A. D. Mackay of the Office of Regional American Affairs said
                                in part he had learned from the Defense Department that Secretary of
                                the Navy Matthews had recommended to Mr. Johnson an allocation as
                                set forth above, except that Mr. Matthews had suggested only one
                                cruiser for Argentina.</p>
                            <p>“It is understood that the Navy made this tentative allocation
                                primarily on the basis of the need of these countries for these
                                ships in their probable role in hemisphere defense; other factors
                                considered were the governments’ traditional friendship to the
                                United States and whether the government had requested this type of
                                ship.</p>
                            <p>Brazil and Chile, as you may know, have made requests for the exact
                                number of cruisers tentatively allocated for them by the Navy, and
                                are most anxious to purchase them. Argentina has requested either
                                one heavy and two light cruisers, or two heavy and two light
                                cruisers, as well as a number more DE’s than are proposed by the
                                Navy be allocated.” (720.562/9750)</p>
                        </note> The prices tabulated in the inclosure represent the total of the
                        following: <pb facs="0669" n="653" xml:id="pg_653"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                            <item>10% of the acquisition cost.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Cost of rehabilitation, including a complete filling of allowances
                                and correction of material deficiencies.</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                            <item>Cost of three weeks’ logistic support during the familiarization
                                and ready-for-sea period.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>I do not consider that the above prices should be inflexibly adhered to
                        during the negotiations, so long as the provisions of the law are adhered
                        to. Price deviations may be necessary for a number of technical reasons,
                        such as the desire of the recipient country for a change in the ammunition
                        allowance, equipage, etc.</p>
                    <p>If you concur in this recommended plan, the Department of Defense will
                        proceed immediately with negotiations with the naval authorities of the
                        countries concerned. When negotiations with a particular country have
                        arrived at mutually satisfactory terms, final consummation of the sale will
                        be carried out in accordance with established Mutual Defense Assistance
                        procedures in effect for Section 408(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) of the
                        Act.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Louis Johnson</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Recommended Sale Program</hi>
                        </head>
                        <table cols="3" rows="11">
                            <row>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Purchasing country</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Ships to be offered for sale</hi>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Approximate sale price to be used for
                                        commencement of negotiations</hi>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Argentina</cell>
                                <cell>2 CL</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$7,935,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>1 DE</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,300,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Brazil</cell>
                                <cell>2 CL</cell>
                                <cell role="num">7,935,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>1 AP, 8 DE<note n="*" xml:id="d218fn3">These vessels are now
                                        held by Brazil under Lend Lease. [Footnote in the source
                                        text.]</note>
                                </cell>
                                <cell><note n="*" xml:id="d218fn4">These vessels are now held by
                                        Brazil under Lend Lease. [Footnote in the source
                                        text.]</note>5,278,300</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Chile</cell>
                                <cell>2 CL</cell>
                                <cell role="num">7,935,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>1 DE</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,300,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Colombia</cell>
                                <cell>1 DE</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,300,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Venezuela</cell>
                                <cell>2 DE</cell>
                                <cell role="num">2,600,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Uruguay</cell>
                                <cell>2 DE</cell>
                                <cell role="num">2,600,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Peru<note n="†" xml:id="d218fn5">Negotiations to commence only
                                        after ratification by Peru of the Treaty of Rio de Janeiro
                                        (1947). [Footnote in the source text. The Peruvian
                                        Government deposited its ratification of the Inter-American
                                        Treaty of Reciprocal Assistance on October 25, 1950.]</note>
                                </cell>
                                <cell>3 DE</cell>
                                <cell role="num"><note n="†" xml:id="d218fn6">Negotiations to
                                        commence only after ratification by Peru of the Treaty of
                                        Rio de Janeiro (1947). [Footnote in the source text. The
                                        Peruvian Government deposited its ratification of the
                                        Inter-American Treaty of Reciprocal Assistance on October
                                        25, 1950.]</note>3,900,000</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>