<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-11-06T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-11-06T19:00:00-05:00" n="259" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d259">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">394.31/11–650: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">United States Delegation to the Fifth Session
                                    of the Contracting Parties</gloss> to <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>, at Torquay</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d259fn1">The
                                Fifth Session of the Contracting Parties of the General Agreement
                                convened at Torquay, England, on November 2. For the composition of
                                the United States Delegation, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, November 6, 1950, p. 747. Winthrop
                                G. Brown, Director, Office of International Trade Policy, was
                                Chairman of the Delegation.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-11-06T19:00:00-05:00">November
                                    6, 1950—7 p. m</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>133. Rowan, Caine, and Burns<note n="2" xml:id="d259fn2">Sir (Thomas)
                                Leslie Rowan was Economic Minister in the British Embassy; Sir
                                Sidney Caine was Head of the United Kingdom Treasury and Supply
                                Delegation, Washington, and Minister in the British Embassy; Robert
                                Burns was British Counselor of Embassy.</note> called on Thorp<note n="3" xml:id="d259fn3">Willard Thorp was Assistant Secretary of
                                State for Economic Affairs.</note> Nov 1 to discuss substantive and
                            procedural points re sterling area consultations at Fifth Session. Brit
                            had previously discussed same range problems with Martin<note n="4" xml:id="d259fn4">William McChesney Martin, Jr., Assistant Secretary
                                of the Treasury, in charge of the Office of International
                                Finance.</note> of Treasury. They indicated full agreement had been
                            reached with other sterling area members on fol UK views and on paper UK
                            is submitting to <gloss target="#t_CP1">CP</gloss>’s in connection
                                consultation.<note n="5" xml:id="d259fn5">A draft of this paper was
                                submitted to the Department of State (and to the Department of the
                                Treasury) about October 25, not printed. It set forth at length the
                                historical background of the sterling area arrangements and recited
                                in detail the financial history of the sterling area for the years
                                1947–1950. (394.31/10–2550)</note> Brit set forth basic position as
                            follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>They consider Fund report reveals basic difference between US
                                    and UK views on merit sterling area arrangements. This presents
                                        <pb facs="0776" n="760" xml:id="pg_760"/> situation clearly
                                    requiring further US–UK discussions. In meantime they wld hope
                                    to avoid airing of differences in <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>. However, UK may feel obliged challenge Fund
                                    report if presented to <gloss target="#t_CP1">CP</gloss>’s
                                    because of their feeling it denies validity sterling area
                                    solidarity on import restrictions and suggests time is ripe for
                                    relaxing such restrictions.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Allege Fund has gone beyond proper scope of consultations in
                                    proposing action based on present fin situation. UK of course
                                    not prepared acquiesce that consultations arranged at Geneva can
                                    properly be extended to period beyond Jul 49. However, Brit
                                    prepared consult <hi rend="italic">de novo</hi> on current
                                    situation after establishing pt indicated above.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Brit main objective seemed to be that of emphasizing above pt’s and
                            eliciting UK [<hi rend="italic">US?</hi>] view on what shld be end
                            result of consultation. We indicated as our present thinking that matter
                            wld be referred by plenary to working party to prepare report along the
                            lines indicated Fund report and our position paper which we sketched in
                            gen terms. Report need not raise explicitly general question validity
                            sterling area arrangements under <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss>.
                            Brit indicated strong preference for Working Party report which set out
                            two positions and reached no conclusions, since they believe that
                            agreement on common conclusion not possible. Dept did not comment on
                            this suggestion. Treas indicated some reservations re feasibility such
                            approach.</p>
                        <p>UK Reps then made fol gen observations: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>No prospect UK or other sterling area members taking major
                                    policy moves now in direction removal discrimination. Consider
                                    dol impact such action might be heavy, since unlikely sterling
                                    area members except UK able limit relaxation to “small amount”
                                    only. They cited recent Commonwealth agreement, presumably
                                    Colombo Conference, to continue strict economy dol expenditures,
                                    maximum dol exports, and build up reserves, as indication
                                    unanimity with which this view held by sterling area members.
                                    Only indication given that any relaxation contemplated was that
                                    maintenance dol imports 75 percent 1948 levels is no longer
                                    controlling and deviations from this rule may be made for
                                    purpose of mtg exigencies particular situations including
                                    specific import requirements for spare parts, etc., rather than
                                    real relaxation. Spoke of more gen relaxation as possibility
                                    only after “period of years”.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Considerable stress laid by Brit on uncertainties present
                                    situation and strong prospect worsening UK’s own dol position in
                                    connection defense programs. Also pointed to such factors as
                                    proposed extension transferable account area to include <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> countries, further progress
                                    towards trade liberalization in Eur, and particularly action
                                    just taken to suspend <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> aid as
                                    prominent in Brit thinking. UK cabinet also mindful unfortunate
                                    developments resulting from convertibility and “slippage” of
                                    import controls during 1947–48.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>In partial reply to Brit views we indicated that we cld not agree that
                            start towards relaxation shld be postponed until specific level of
                            reserves attained. If such moves as extension transferable acct area
                            present <pb facs="0777" n="761" xml:id="pg_761"/> risks to dol position,
                            it wld be appropriate to question justification such steps if end result
                            is failure to relax discrimination. Rowan observed extension
                            transferable acct area might be proper subj US–UK discussions. As for
                            Brit emphasis on basic differences raised by Fund report, we indicated
                            that in our view Brit overstress degree to which Fund has taken issue
                            with basic sterling area arrangements, and we see no reason why validity
                            such arrangements need be subj of controversy at Fifth Session.</p>
                        <p>If Brit challenge Fund conception proper scope of consultations, US Del
                            shld of course support Fund position along lines previously considered.
                            It might be agreed that terms of reference this particular consultation
                            not clearly defined at Geneva. Nevertheless Del should insist that Fund
                            view entirely reasonable common-sense interpretation of request from
                                <gloss target="#t_GATT1">GATT</gloss> for report, as alternative
                            interpretation not consistent with meaningful consultations. If Brit and
                            other sterling area countries indicate willingness to consult
                            individually on current situation <hi rend="italic">de novo</hi> and
                            allow such consultation to reach conclusions, Del might indicate that
                            issue is not substantive in our view. If, however, Brit and others
                            refuse to consult on individual country basis or refuse admit Fund
                            report as pertinent to all phases consultations, we must reject such
                            position.</p>
                        <p>Message will follow on substantive issues raised by Brit.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>