<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Minutes of Meeting No. 147 of the National Advisory Council, Washington,
                    January 23, 1950</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d294</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">294</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjP7nK0m2r7YYXK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-01-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-01-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="294"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d294">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> Files, Lot 60D137, Box 362</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of Meeting No. 147 of the National Advisory Council,
                        Washington, January 23, 1950</hi>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1950-01-23">January 23, 1950</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follow list of persons present (26) and discussion of the European Payments
                    Union question.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Action</hi>. The following action was taken (Action No.
                    383):</p>
                <p>The National Advisory Council advises the Administrator for Economic Cooperation
                    that:</p>
                <pb facs="0838" n="822" xml:id="pg_822"/>
                <p>I. The Council considers that in the establishment of any European clearing union
                    designed to further progess toward the objectives of economic integration and
                    ultimate full convertibility of currencies the following conditions should be
                    met: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The operations of the proposed clearing union shall not conflict with
                            obligations undertaken by the United States and other member governments
                            to the International Monetary Fund;</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The establishment of the clearing union on the regional basis proposed
                            shall not prevent any one participating country from moving as rapidly
                            as possible toward full currency convertibility, nor prevent any group
                            among the participating countries from moving as rapidly as possible
                            toward full currency convertibility and closer integration,
                            independently of the rate of progress evidenced by the other members of
                            the clearing union.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>II. In order to insure fulfillment of the foregoing stipulation, the National
                    Advisory Council recommends with respect to:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">1. <hi rend="italic">Financial Operations of and United States
                        Contribution to a Clearing Union</hi>
                </p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The United States might reasonably concur in any
                    arrangements which the Administrator might work out with the European countries
                    as to the provision of credits by participating countries in local currency
                    which might be used on a multilateral basis.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) Conditional aid dollars might be made available to
                    debtors in specific amounts which might be used multilaterally to cover
                    “structural deficits” with other participants. This money, as present
                    conditional aid, might be supplied by the United States.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) Provision might be made for dollar payments on an
                    “automatic” basis to be made by debtor countries through the clearing union to
                    the creditor countries. Arrangements should be worked out whereby at the
                    earliest practicable date, and not later than June 30, 1952, net dollar payments
                    by debtors to the clearing union are at least equal to any net dollar payments
                    from the clearing union to creditors so that the question of any United States
                    financing would not arise beyond that date. The <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                        >ECA</gloss> would fix a maximum limitation on its obligations for such
                    financing.</p>
                <p>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) The United States should not make any contribution to
                    a fund from which loans would be made by a clearing union to debtors on a
                    non-automatic basis in essentially the same way as International Monetary Fund
                    drawings. <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>The <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> may, however, modify its
                            allocation of aid to individual countries upon the recommendations of a
                            clearing union, to take account of payments positions of such countries
                            relative to the clearing union.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>provided that no action should be taken by <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                                >ECA</gloss> upon any such recommendation involving a question of
                            concern to the International Monetary Fund until the International
                            Monetary Fund has had a reasonable opportunity to reach a judgment and
                            to express its views and they have been considered by the United States
                            Government.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0839" n="823" xml:id="pg_823"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">2. <hi rend="italic">Management of Clearing Union and United
                        States Participation Therein</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In order to avoid any possible United States involvement in conflict of
                    recommendations made by the clearing union on monetary policy and those of the
                    International Monetary Fund, the United States should not participate in the
                    management of the clearing union. This would not preclude a United States
                    observer in the union for the duration of the <gloss target="#t_ERP1"
                        >ERP</gloss> period only; nor would it preclude United States veto power on
                    any use of funds contributed by the United States under 1 above.</p>
                <p>III. With respect to the memorandum of January 12, 1950, from the Managing
                    Director of the International Monetary Fund,<note n="1" xml:id="d294fn1">See
                        footnote 6, <ref target="#pg_818">p. 818</ref>.</note> the National Advisory
                    Council instructs the United States Executive Director to assure the Managing
                    Director that the United States fully recognizes the interest of the
                    International Monetary Fund in any European clearing union and also indicate the
                    hope of the United States that the International Monetary Fund will proceed
                    promptly with consideration of the relationship which ought to be worked out
                    between the International Monetary Fund and any European clearing union. As an
                    immediate first step, the United States will propose that a Fund representative
                    be invited to participate in the meetings of the special committee of the <gloss
                        target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> which is now discussing the clearing union
                    proposal.</p>
                <p>[Here follow discussion and action on another question.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
