<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chairman of the United States Atomic Energy Commission ( (Dean) ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">34</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-09-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-09-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recbcbcHDEt9ge9nZ" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110610"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fissionable material</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recQI8RFLxCFovNr2" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092985"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nuclear fuel</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recdPycISbXW2cCGh" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103582"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Plutonium</term>
                    <term ref="recuR46HFuv1xQrLV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec8cadRUqzOJueqQ" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85059854"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Heavy water</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="reckO9szxNydLBID0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85003956"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Aluminum</term>
                    <term ref="recOrZuJ5me6ilcbT" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85141276"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Uranium</term>
                    <term ref="rec626bb089a1004d2" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons">Atomic
                        weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2qYX3T6ktEaSsg" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85087216"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Moratorium</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="water" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons" subject="nuclear-weapons" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic weapons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-09-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-09-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="34"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d34">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">PM Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chairman of the United States Atomic Energy
                        Commission</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dean</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-09-20">September 20,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: In reply to your letter of August
                    22, 1950, the effects of technical developments on the international control of
                    atomic energy, which were referred to in our letter of June 26, 1950, are
                    discussed in more detail below. These matters are considered under four main
                    headings which we believe cover the points raised in your letter.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">I. <hi rend="italic">Accumulation of Fissionable Material</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Now that the USSR has produced fissionable material, the technical question
                    arises as to how the United States could be sure that the USSR had turned over
                    all fissionable material to an international agency, if such an agency were
                    established in accordance with the United Nations plan for control of atomic
                    energy. The plan states that the international agency would own all nuclear fuel
                    and that nations and persons would be prohibited from producing, possessing,
                    transferring, storing, transporting, handling, or using nuclear fuel, except as
                    authorized <pb facs="0111" n="95" xml:id="pg_95"/> by the international agency.
                    The plan, to the extent that it has been worked out in the various reports of
                    the United Nations Atomic Energy Commission, does not specifically consider the
                    questions of when or how stocks of fissionable material would be turned over to
                    the international agency or what safeguards would apply to prevent or detect the
                    withholding of fissionable material, although it does deal with safeguards
                    against diversion of fissionable material after the plan has gone into effect.
                    Presumably, the transfer of fissionable material to the international agency was
                    left to be considered under the subject of “stages” of transition in putting the
                    plan into operation.</p>
                <p>Whether there exist safeguards against withholding of fissionable material is a
                    crucial matter for any control plan, as indicated in your letter. One approach
                    to this problem is to inquire whether methods are available for the
                    determination of the total past output of facilities for the production of
                    fissionable material.</p>
                <p>With regard to reactors, waste material in the form of radioactive fission
                    products must necessarily be produced in the fuel elements and must be disposed
                    of after extraction of the fissionable material. These fission products would be
                    subject to control by the international agency because of their possible use in
                    radiological warfare. In this country, the fission products are stored in large
                    underground tanks and it would be possible by sampling and analyzing their
                    contents and estimating their volume, to get some idea of the amount of
                    plutonium produced to date and the time when production began. Representative
                    samples and accurate results might be difficult to obtain in this way. In the
                    case of the USSR, if the purpose were to deceive the international agency, the
                    liquid wastes containing fission products might be allowed to run off into the
                    ground without regard to health hazards or, with considerable effort, might be
                    reduced in bulk and scattered, hid, or altered in such a way that significant
                    measurements could not be made. Some of the fission products are gases and
                    escape into the atmosphere during chemical processing of the reactor fuel
                    elements, .... Methods of sampling and analyzing the atmosphere are being
                    investigated. …</p>
                <p>In addition to the fission products, radioactive materials are formed in the
                    moderator, shielding, and structural elements of reactors. Some of those are so
                    short-lived that they could not be used to obtain information on the past
                    history of the reactor, but there are others which may be suitable for that
                    purpose. Where graphite is used as a moderator as at Hanford, carbon-14 with a
                    half-life of 5000 years is produced by absorption of neutrons in ordinary
                    carbon. Measurement of the specific activity of samples of graphite taken from
                    various positions in the reactor would give an indication of the total number
                        <pb facs="0112" n="96" xml:id="pg_96"/> of neutrons which had been released
                    in the reactor and therefore the total fissionable material which could have
                    been produced from the time operation started. Where heavy water is used as a
                    moderator as at Chalk River, tritium with a half-life of 12 years is produced by
                    absorption of neutrons in deuterium. However, it would be possible to replace
                    the heavy water after a certain period of operation, since it is not a
                    structural part of the reactor. Investigation of long-lived activities produced
                    in such materials as steel, concrete, and aluminum may be required.</p>
                <p>With regard to isotope separation plants for the production of U–235, “technical
                    methods for determining total past production do not appear to be nearly as
                    promising as for reactors. The Waste material from isotope separation plants,
                    which contains uranium depleted in U–235, has very little radioactivity and
                    could readily be hidden or otherwise disposed of. The feed material used in the
                    Oak Ridge plant is uranium hexafluoride, which corrodes a number of structural
                    materials. However, the special materials used in the barriers, piping, and
                    pumps and the operational procedures which have been developed make corrosion an
                    inadequate means of determining the age of the plant or the time during which it
                    has been operated. No other specific technical means of obtaining such
                    information from an examination of the plant has been suggested to date, but
                    further study is being given to the matter.</p>
                <p>It is assumed that reliance would not have to be placed on the examination of
                    reactors and isotope separation plants alone, but that the whole range of
                    controls and inspections given in the United Nations plan would be used. This
                    would be necessary in any case to assure that all the facilities for the
                    production of fissionable material had in fact been located. In addition, it
                    would provide cross-checks on what the total production had been and, in
                    particular, might give useful clues as to the time when a particular reactor or
                    isotope separation plant was constructed or began operation. Investigations
                    would have to be made of the mines, mills, and dumps from which source material
                    had been obtained in the past, the facilities for processing and purification of
                    source material, the supply of special equipment and materials such as mass
                    spectrometers, diffusion barriers, pure graphite, and heavy water, and the
                    consumption of large quantities of electricity. Records would have to be
                    examined, personnel interviewed, and ground and aerial surveys made.
                    Considerable effort on the part of the USSR would be necessary to falsify
                    records, remove or alter other evidence, and suborn witnesses in an attempt to
                    withhold large quantities of fissionable material from international
                    control.</p>
                <p>An attempt might be made by the USSR to cover up the withholding of fissionable
                    material by claiming that the missing material had been <pb facs="0113" n="97"
                        xml:id="pg_97"/> consumed in atomic explosions for peaceful purposes or for
                    tests. Methods for detecting atomic explosions would provide a check on such
                    claims, although the quantities of fissionable material used might be difficult
                    to determine in some cases.</p>
                <p>With all the controls and inspections contemplated under the United Nations plan,
                    it would appear that quantitative information could be obtained about the total
                    amount of fissionable material produced in the past. There is still the question
                    of whether such information could be made sufficiently accurate. The Second
                    Report of the United Nations Atomic Energy Commission defines dangerous
                    activities or facilities as those “which are of military significance in the
                    production of atomic weapons,” but does not give a quantitative meaning to
                    “military significance,” leaving this to the international agency to decide.
                    Volume VI of “Scientific Information Transmitted to the United Nations Atomic
                    Energy Commission by the United States Representative” includes the following
                    statement:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“It is difficult to define the amount of activity in the illicit production
                        of atomic weapons which is significant. The illicit construction of a single
                        atomic bomb by means of a decade of successful evasion would not provide an
                        overwhelming advantage, if it can be assumed that it would take another
                        decade to produce a second bomb. But the secret production of one bomb per
                        year would create a definite danger, and the secret production of five or
                        more per year would be disastrous. This report assumes arbitrarily that the
                        minimum unit of noncompliance is the secret production of one atomic bomb
                        per year or of a total of five bombs over any period of time.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>This statement was made at a time when atomic bombs were much scarcer than they
                    are now. As the stocks of fissionable material accumulate in various countries,
                    the difficulties which the international agency would encounter in detecting the
                    withholding of fissionable material for a few bombs become greater. At the same
                    time, weapon development is increasing the energy release which can be obtained
                    from a given quantity of fissionable material, a trend which may reach its
                    culmination in thermonuclear weapons.</p>
                <p>These considerations emphasize the importance of two aspects of the United
                    Nations plan which were never worked out in detail, the stages of transition to
                    full control and the strategic distribution of fissionable material. Before the
                    crucial stage of turning over fissionable material to the international agency
                    was reached, each country would have to assure itself that no other country was
                    withholding significant quantities of fissionable material. Since there will
                    always be the possibility of error or inaccuracy in this determination, the
                    strategic distribution of the bulk of the fissionable material might have to be
                    made in such a way as to override the effects of possible withholding by one or
                    more countries.</p>
                <pb facs="0114" n="98" xml:id="pg_98"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">II. <hi rend="italic">Production of Fissionable Material by
                        Particle Accelerators</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The possibility of producing fissionable material by means of high-energy,
                    high-current particle accelerators was of course not known at the time the
                    United Nations plan was formulated, but seems to be covered by the general
                    language and definitions of the plan. However, there are a number of technical
                    aspects of the plan which may need to be made more explicit.</p>
                <p>Thorium may increase in importance. The First Report of the United Nations Atomic
                    Energy Commission stated that the danger inherent in the diversion of thorium is
                    less immediate than in the case of uranium, because thorium cannot be used by
                    itself for the production of atomic energy. This may no longer be true, since
                    the particle accelerator may provide a means of utilizing thorium alone in the
                    production of U–233. The particle-accelerator development may have the same
                    general effect as a reactor breeding program, in that it may transform U–238 and
                    thorium into fissionable material without being limited by the U–235 content of
                    natural uranium, thus greatly increasing the potential supply of fissionable
                    material. The Specific Proposals of the Second Report made no distinction
                    between the control measures to be applied to thorium and uranium, although it
                    was realized that the control of thorium would be more difficult because of the
                    extent and mode of its occurrence and its use outside of the atomic energy
                    field.</p>
                <p>The particle accelerator may require a smaller inventory of source material for a
                    given rate of production of fissionable material than a reactor, but may be
                    comparable as regards size of installation, cooling and shielding requirements,
                    and chemical processing plant. The requirements for electric power and
                    specialized electrical equipment will be much greater than for a reactor. It
                    would therefore appear that the problems of detection and control would be no
                    more difficult than for a reactor. It should be emphasized that the feasibility
                    of a particle accelerator for production of fissionable material in quantity has
                    not yet been demonstrated.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">III. <hi rend="italic">Prospects for Atomic Power</hi>
                </p>
                <p>At the time the discussions of atomic energy began in the United Nations, there
                    were some persons in this country and elsewhere who were sanguine of the early
                    demonstration both of the practical generation of atomic power and of its
                    economic feasibility. During the course of the discussions, it became apparent
                    that numerous technical and economic problems were involved and that the time
                    scale was a matter of years before atomic power could be demonstrated in a
                    practical way and perhaps decades before atomic power might be utilized on a
                    large <pb facs="0115" n="99" xml:id="pg_99"/> scale, if it should prove to be
                    economically feasible. The production of large stocks of fissionable material by
                    the international agency in anticipation of possible future uses in atomic power
                    plants therefore seemed to be unnecessarily dangerous. There resulted the
                    provision which you quoted from Specific Proposal 12, Chapter 4, of the Second
                    Report, on keeping the production of weapon-level material to a minimum. This
                    provision as written and other provisions in the same chapter would apparently
                    permit work to continue on the development of atomic power, including the
                    construction of pilot plants, and would allow power reactors eventually to be
                    constructed by arrangement between the international agency and the nation
                    concerned. Meanwhile, in the absence of international control, there has been a
                    large accumulation of stocks of weapon-level fissionable material, so that the
                    limitation of Specific Proposal 12 has to some extent been nullified.</p>
                <p>Various proposals have been made for further limitations on dangerous facilities
                    for the production or utilization of fissionable material, such as a moratorium
                    on atomic power. An important question raised by such proposals is the
                    disposition of the large stocks of fissionable material now in existence, which
                    are more dangerous in the sense of the United Nations plan than development or
                    production facilities. This is also an important problem in connection with the
                    United Nations plan itself, and one that has not been worked out in detail. Its
                    seriousness continues to increase as more and more fissionable material is
                    produced.</p>
                <p>The possibility that particle accelerators may be developed for the production of
                    fissionable material from U–238 and thorium without being limited by the U–235
                    content of natural uranium would have an effect on the prospects for atomic
                    power by making fissionable material more readily available for this purpose.
                    The cost of fissionable material produced in this way would be a factor in
                    determining the economics of atomic power.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">IV. <hi rend="italic">Thermonuclear Weapons</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Since thermonuclear weapons would be dependent on the availability of fissionable
                    material and reactors or particle accelerators for the production of tritium,
                    the United Nations plan in its control of fissionable material and facilities
                    for its production would also be controlling thermonuclear weapons. This is also
                    in accordance with the general language and the definitions of the United
                    Nations plan. If an opportunity presented itself at some future time, there are
                    several places where explicit reference could be made to thermonuclear weapons
                    and to the light elements. The provisions for the control of heavy water might
                    also be strengthened. At present, the plan only <pb facs="0116" n="100"
                        xml:id="pg_100"/> calls for periodic reports to the international agency
                    from nations regarding the production, shipment, location, and use of heavy
                    water. Because of the increasing importance of heavy water in production
                    reactors and because of the possible use of deuterium in thermonuclear weapons,
                    it might be desirable for the international agency to own stocks of these
                    materials and to own, operate, and manage facilities for their production.</p>
                <p>One important feature of the increase in energy release which thermonuclear
                    weapons may make possible is that the seriousness of the diversion or
                    withholding of fissionable material together with tritium and deuterium might be
                    intensified and the accuracy required in accounting for such materials might be
                    increased.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Conclusions</hi>. After consideration of the above matters, we
                    arrive at the following conclusions:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                    <item>Effective international control of atomic energy on a current and
                        continuing basis after the United Nations plan went into full operation
                        would be technologically feasible.</item>
                    <label>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                    <item>The detection of the withholding of fissionable material produced prior to
                        the implementation of the United Nations plan would be more difficult, and
                        the amount of fissionable material which might be withheld without detection
                        would increase as the accumulation of fissionable material increases. This
                        difficulty stresses the need for (1) stages of transition to full control of
                        such a nature as to provide opportunities for obtaining assurances against
                        the withholding of significant quantities of fissionable material and (2)
                        strategic distribution of fissionable material in such a way as to minimize
                        the effects of possible withholding.</item>
                </list>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Gordon Dean</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
