<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Study Prepared by the Director of the Policy Planning Staff (
                    (Nitze))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">59</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-02-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-02-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recZ240W8VG9BDJBE" type="compound-subject"
                        category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        >Soviet foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recfgV5j0WMmONcRO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic crisis</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-02-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-02-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="59"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d59">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">661.00/2–850</note>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Study Prepared by the Director of the Policy Planning
                        Staff</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Nitze</hi>)<note n="1" xml:id="d59fn1">In
                        accordance with the instructions delivered by Under Secretary Webb at the
                        Secretary of State’s meeting of February 9, this paper was distributed to
                        the principal officers of the Department (Secretary’s Daily Meetings: Lot
                        58D609).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-02-08">February 8,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Recent Soviet Moves</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">conclusions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I. In seeking to interpret Soviet tactics, it is always useful to remind
                    ourselves that during the course of the war, the Kremlin concluded that the US
                    would emerge as the citadel of the non-Soviet world and therefore the primary
                    enemy against which the USSR would of necessity have to wage a life-and-death
                    struggle. Stalin’s election speech of 1946<note n="2" xml:id="d59fn2">Stalin’s
                        election speech of February 9, 1946, is analyzed in telegram 408 from
                        Moscow, February 12, 1946, in <ref target="frus1946v06#pg_694">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1946, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>, pp. 694</ref>–<ref
                            target="frus1946v06#pg_696">696</ref>.</note> was an open declaration of
                    hostility and since that time the USSR has given every sign that it neither
                    intends to abandon the struggle, other than on its own terms, nor pause in its
                    prosecution. In the choice of tactics, the USSR has shown a willingness to
                    employ at any given moment any maneuver or weapon which holds promise of
                    success. For this reason there appears no reason to assume that the USSR will in
                    the future necessarily make a sharp distinction between “military aggression”
                    and measures short of military aggression. In its decisions, it is guided only
                    by considerations of expediency. As the USSR has already committed itself to the
                    defeat of the US, Soviet policy is guided by the simple consideration of
                    weakening the world power position of the US. This approach, on the one hand,
                    holds out for the USSR the possibility that it can achieve success over the US
                    without ever resorting to an all-out military assault. On the other hand, it
                    leaves open the possibility of a quick Soviet decision to resort to military
                    action, locally or generally.</p>
                <p>II. In the aggregate, recent Soviet moves reflect not only a mounting militancy
                    but suggest a boldness that is essentially new—and borders on recklessness,
                    particularly since in the present international situation great stakes are
                    involved in any USSR move, and any move directly or indirectly affects the US
                    and risks US counter action. Nothing about the moves indicates that Moscow is
                    preparing to launch in the near future an all-out military attack on the West.
                    They do, <pb facs="0162" n="146" xml:id="pg_146"/> however, suggest a greater
                    willingness than in the past to undertake a course of action, including a
                    possible use of force in local areas, which might lead to an accidental outbreak
                    of general military conflict. Thus the chance of war through miscalculation is
                    increased.</p>
                <p>III. The several recent Moscow moves should be interpreted as arising both from
                    Soviet eagerness to exploit the opportunities presented by the expansion of the
                    Soviet empire, particularly in the Far East, and from Soviet anxieties over the
                    problem of imperial control, especially over Communist China. This problem,
                    already pressing, is intensified by the very successes which have been recently
                    achieved. The national deviation of Tito, we know, was a severe reverse for the
                    Kremlin. Nationalist deviation on the part of Communist China would threaten the
                    structure of the Soviet imperialist system. Similarly, national deviation
                    elsewhere would reverse Soviet gains in Eastern Europe, jeopardize Soviet
                    opportunities in Southeast Asia and Moscow’s use of foreign Communist Parties as
                    instruments of Soviet foreign policy.</p>
                <p>Also involved, though less directly and urgently, is Moscow’s continuing concern
                    over Western counter actions in Europe. The immediate effect of these Western
                    actions has been to bar Communist expansion in Western Europe and to commit
                    American power to the defense of Western Europe. Moscow may well discount in
                    part the lasting nature of these effects, but this would not alter Moscow’s
                    over-all concern, particularly in view of its phobia for magnifying dangers. The
                    Kremlin consequently is under constant pressure to counter US moves, real or
                    imagined, as part of the basic maneuvers required in its political warfare with
                    the US.</p>
                <p>IV. In assuming the risks involved in exploiting its present opportunities and in
                    dealing with its imperial problems, Moscow appears to be animated by a general
                    sense of confidence. The Kremlin has good reason for somewhat increased
                    confidence. It has developed an <gloss target="#t_Abomb1">A-bomb</gloss>; it has
                    achieved the prewar level of production and other solid economic successes; it
                    has made progress in consolidating its control over the European satellites; and
                    it has apparently effected an increase in the prestige of the Communist Party
                    among the Russian people. Also contributing is an apparent Moscow belief that an
                    economic crisis is actually in the incipient stage in the West and that this and
                    succeeding crises will contribute to an eventual Soviet triumph. It should be
                    stressed, however, that Soviet actions make clear that Moscow’s faith in the
                    inevitable disintegration of capitalism is not a passive faith in automatic
                    historical evolution. Instead <pb facs="0163" n="147" xml:id="pg_147"/> it is a
                    messianic faith that not only spurs the USSR to assist the transformation of the
                    Marxist blueprint into a reality, but also gives the Soviet leaders a sense of
                    confidence that in whatever particular course they follow they are riding the
                    wave of the future.</p>
                <p>V. With respect to particular objectives, the present pattern of Soviet moves is
                    characterized, on the one hand, by constant attention to consolidation of
                    previous gains and, particularly, the establishment of safeguards against
                    dangers—real or imagined, external or internal—to these gains; and on the other
                    hand, by concentration on soft spots, seizure of every opportunity to move into
                    vacuum areas or to exploit completely the momentum of a successful development.
                    Since the present pattern allows the USSR the same flexibility in the choice of
                    particular tactics that has characterized its postwar strategy generally, it
                    offers no dependable indication as to particular future moves. Thus, for
                    example, the USSR may, without breaking the pattern, either remain in or
                    withdraw from the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, revive the issue of the
                    occupation of Berlin or maintain the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi>, force a
                    break in relations between the satellites and Western states or continue the
                    present precarious arrangements. It can be assumed, however, that in any given
                    situation a course will be adopted in consequence of a careful Kremlin weighing
                    of the opportunities offered as against the deterrents involved. This offers a
                    fairly dependable means of estimating particular steps which may be taken during
                    coming weeks in regard to such areas as Indochina, Berlin, Austria, the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, Korea, etc. Such estimates are in process of
                    being prepared.</p>
                <p>Beyond this the current pattern already seems to indicate with reasonable
                    certainty that:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                    <item>The USSR considers this a favorable and necessary moment for increased
                        political pressure, and, when feasible, taking aggressive political action
                        against all or most soft spots in its periphery;</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                    <item>Every effort will be made to establish and maintain effective Soviet
                        control in China;</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                    <item>Southeast Asia will be a primary area of Soviet-Communist action;</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                    <item>Moscow’s insistence on unquestioning subservience by all Communist Parties
                        will be intensified, regardless of unfavorable local repercussions;</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                    <item>The <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and other media for regular
                        diplomatic contact will be treated with increasing cynicism;</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                    <item>The insulation of the satellites from the West will be further
                        intensified.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
