<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs ( (Barrett)
                    ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">83</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007242"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Defense budget</term>
                    <term ref="recPOhBog0KB3BlCU" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Anti-tank weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-04-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-04-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="83"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Policy Planning Staff Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Assistant Secretary of State for Public
                        Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Barrett</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d83fn1">Transmitted through Under Secretary of State
                        Webb.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-04-06">April 6,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: State–Defense Study Group Papers</p>
                <p>I consider this a magnificent job of analyzing the problem. I have a number of
                    minor suggestions regarding phraseology, which I either have passed along or am
                    passing along to Paul Nitze’s staff.</p>
                <p>Regarding the organization of the paper, the real conclusions seem to me to be at
                    the last of Section 9. If it is anticipated that some of those dealing with this
                    paper will have to read it rather hastily, I suggest that these should be more
                    clearly labeled as the real conclusions, whether by putting them at the end of
                    the paper, or by referring to them more definitely and precisely in Section
                    10.</p>
                <p>My most important point: the whole paper seems to me to point to a gigantic
                    armament race, a huge buildup of conventional arms that quickly become
                    obsolescent, a greatly expanded military establishment in being. I think that,
                    however much we whip up sentiment, we are going to run into vast opposition
                    among informed people to a huge arms race. We will be warned that we are heading
                    toward a “garrison state”. Moreover, even if we should sell the idea, I fear
                    that the U.S. public would rapidly tire of such an effort. In the absence of
                    real and continuing crises, a dictatorship can unquestionably out-last a
                    democracy in a conventional armament race.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, I believe the American public can be sold on programs to build
                    up our strength in those fields in which we have natural superiority. These are: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Economic and technical—as reflected in Point IV and a continuing
                                <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> program;</item>
                        <pb facs="0242" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Psychological, as could be reflected in an information and
                            psychological warfare offensive;<note n="2" xml:id="d83fn2"
                                >Documentation on the United States foreign information program is
                                scheduled for publication in volume <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >iv</hi>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>(and most important) Scientific and technical know-how in the armament
                            field—which should be reflected in a gigantic mobilization of the
                            nation’s scientific brains to launch the greatest new weapons and
                            research program in history.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Only a small portion of the current thirteen billion dollar Defense budget is
                    going into new weapons and research of the type that Vannevar Bush emphasizes in
                    his book.<note n="3" xml:id="d83fn3">Vannevar Bush, <hi rend="italic">Modern
                            Arms and Free Men: A Discussion of the Role of Science in Preserving
                            Democracy</hi> (New York: Simon and Schuster, 1949).</note> Scientists
                    have left the Government since the war and are still leaving the Government. I
                    feel confident that the American people could be sold and be kept sold on a
                    massive program of developing new weapons and the relatively small technical
                    crews needed to man them. Examples are super anti-tank weapons and anti-aircraft
                    guided missiles. I believe a few billion dollars spent in this direction would
                    give the reassurance the rest of the free world needs and would have continuing
                    popular support in this country.</p>
                <p>How this can be embodied in the present paper, I am not sure. I would suggest at
                    least some rephrasing of chapters 9 and 10, to put much more emphasis on these
                    points. I would add that this idea should be given thorough study in connection
                    with the papers which are to follow the current ones.</p>
                <p>This whole plan underscores again the wisdom of the current proposal for a cold
                    war headquarters, probably attached directly to the White House.</p>
                <p>If and when this whole project is approved by the President, the public education
                    campaign must obviously receive the most careful study. I will forward within
                    the next few days some detailed recommendations for this campaign. In the
                    meantime, I would like to point out the following: The first step in the
                    campaign is obviously building up a full public awareness of the problem. This
                    might take three months or it might require no more than ten days. My hunch is
                    that it will be nearer ten days. We must be sure that the Government is in a
                    position to come forward with positive steps to be taken just as soon as the
                    atmosphere is right. It is imperative, for both domestic and overseas reasons,
                    that there should not be too much of a time lag between the creation of a public
                    awareness of the problem and the setting forth of a positive Government program
                    to solve that problem.</p>
                <p>In other words, we should have at least the broad proposals for action well in
                    hand before the psychological “scare campaign” is started.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
