<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by Mr. Hamilton Q. Dearborn of the Council of Economic Advisers to
                    the Executive Secretary of the National Security Council ( (Lay))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d91</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">91</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1950-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recPnftMNhM1QKAYO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Stockpile</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recxTPk6jOc2M2oik" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007242"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Military budget</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recS4xTyl2tDVYfz5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budgets</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec7jSz4IPswgGKPB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic growth</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-05-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="91"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d91">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Policy Planning Staff Files</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Hamilton Q.
                            Dearborn</persName> of the Council of Economic Advisers to the Executive
                        Secretary of the National Security Council</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lay</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-05-08">May 8,
                            1950</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Comments on <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68</p>
                <p>This memorandum is prepared in response to the Committee decision of May 2 that
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 should be further considered at a
                    meeting on May 9, and that written questions and comments should be prepared as
                    a basis therefor.</p>
                <p>Three basic questions are raised by <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68: <list>
                        <label>1)</label>
                        <item>The adequacy of the intelligence data and analysis on which rest the
                            conclusions as to the current status of, and trends in, the relative
                            strength of the United States and the Soviet Union;</item>
                        <label>2)</label>
                        <item>The degree to which the policy conclusions of <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss> 68 are best adapted to remedy the deficiencies
                            disclosed by analysis; and</item>
                        <label>3)</label>
                        <item>The best programs, and their cost and economic significance, for
                            implementing those policy conclusions, or alternative policy
                            conclusions.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Basic Intelligence Data and Analysis</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The major analytical conclusions drawn are the following:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Concerning direct military strength:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. “Unless the military strength of the Western European nations is increased on
                    a much larger scale than under present programs and at an accelerated rate, it
                    is more than likely that those nations will <pb facs="0323" n="307"
                        xml:id="pg_307"/> not be able to oppose even by 1960 the Soviet armed forces
                    in war with any degree of effectiveness.” (<ref target="#pg_19">p. 19</ref>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d91fn1">See <ref target="#pg_250">p. 250</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>2. “At the time the Soviet Union has a substantial atomic stockpile
                        [mid-1954]<note n="2" xml:id="d91fn2">Brackets appear in the source
                        text.</note> and if it is assumed that it will strike a strong surprise blow
                    and if it is assumed further that its atomic attacks will be met with no more
                    effective defense opposition than the United States and its allies have
                    programmed, results of those attacks could include: laying waste to the British
                        Isles…<note n="3" xml:id="d91fn3">Omissions throughout the document are
                        indicated in the source text.</note> destruction of the vital centers and of
                    communications of Western Europe… and delivering devastating attacks on certain
                    vital centers of the United States and Canada.” (<ref target="#pg_20">p.
                        20</ref>
                    <note n="4" xml:id="d91fn4">See <ref target="#pg_251">pp. 251</ref>–<ref
                            target="#pg_252">252</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Concerning economic and military potential:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>3. “… the total economic strength of the U.S.S.R. compares with that of the U.S.
                    as roughly one to four.… Assuming the maintenance of present policies, while a
                    large U.S. advantage is likely to remain, the Soviet Union will be steadily
                    reducing the discrepancy between its over-all economic strength and that of the
                    U.S. by continuing to devote proportionately more to capital investment than the
                    U.S.” (<ref target="#pg_16">pp. 16</ref>, <ref target="#pg_17">17</ref>
                    <note n="5" xml:id="d91fn5">See <ref target="#pg_248">p. 248</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>4. “The military budget of the United States represents 6 to 7 percent of its
                    gross national product (as compared with 13.8 percent for the Soviet Union). Our
                    North Atlantic Treaty allies devoted 4.8 percent of their national product to
                    military purposes in 1949. This difference in emphasis between the two economies
                    means that the readiness of the free world to support a war effort is tending to
                    decline relative to that of the Soviet Union.” (<ref target="#pg_25">p. 25</ref>
                    <note n="6" xml:id="d91fn6">See <ref target="#pg_256">p. 256</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>5. “… a full-scale effort by the U.S. would be capable of precipitately altering
                    this trend. The U.S.S.R. is on a near maximum production basis.… In the U.S., on
                    the other hand, a very rapid absolute expansion could be realized.… Even Western
                    Europe could afford to assign a substantially larger proportion of its resources
                    to defense, if the necessary foundation in public understanding and will could
                    be laid, and if the assistance needed to meet its dollar deficit were provided.”
                        (<ref target="#pg_17">pp. 17</ref>, <ref target="#pg_25">25</ref>
                    <note n="7" xml:id="d91fn7">See <ref target="#pg_249">pp. 249</ref> and <ref
                            target="#pg_249">256</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>It is, of course, outside the competence of the Council of Economic Advisers to
                    appraise the analysis of military strength prepared by the agencies submitting
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68. The Council’s concern is only that
                    the analysis should be in a form most helpful to the work of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee.</p>
                <p>From this standpoint, it would appear desirable that the data on percentage
                    expenditures on defense and investment which are used in <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 68 to illustrate probable trends in military and economic <pb
                        facs="0324" n="308" xml:id="pg_308"/> strength should, to the extent
                    feasible, be supplemented by data showing absolute amounts. The reason for this
                    is that absolute figures tend to be more helpful than percentage figures in
                    determining quantitative objectives. To bring the defense expenditures of
                    European <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NAT</gloss> countries up to the same
                    proportion of national output as in the Soviet Union, for example, would require
                    nearly a three-fold increase in their defense budgets.</p>
                <p>With the proposition that “a very rapid absolute expansion could be realized” in
                        <hi rend="italic">total</hi> United States production of all goods and
                    services there is full agreement. This, in turn, would render more supportable
                    any given level of defense outlays. The size, composition and rate of the
                    expansion in total output that might be achieved with a full effort would be one
                    of the major considerations governing program formulation under <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68. On them would depend the extent to which
                    any major new programs adopted would require a reduction in consumption, the
                    imposition of selective or general price and allocation controls, cutbacks in
                    expenditure programs other than for defense and foreign aid, or increases in
                    taxes.</p>
                <p>For these reasons the Council considers that a careful analysis of the productive
                    potentialities of the United States economy must be a central feature of the
                    analytical framework supporting program recommendations that may be reached
                    under <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68. Such an analysis is important from
                    the standpoint of general economic policy regardless of whether new programs
                    recommended may be of large or moderate dimensions.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Policy Conclusions of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        68</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The basic policy conclusion reached by <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 is
                    as follows:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“In the light of present and prospective Soviet atomic capabilities, the
                        action which can be taken under present programs and plans… becomes
                        dangerously inadequate, in both timing and scope, to accomplish the rapid
                        progress toward the attainment of the United States political, economic, and
                        military objectives which is now imperative. A continuation of present
                        trends would result in a serious decline in the strength of the free world
                        relative to the Soviet Union and its satellites.… It is imperative that this
                        trend be reversed by a much more rapid and concerted build-up of the actual
                        strength of both the United States and the other nations of the free world.”
                            (<ref target="#pg_63">pp. 63</ref>, <ref target="#pg_64">64</ref>
                        <note n="8" xml:id="d91fn8">See <ref target="#pg_290">p.
                        290</ref>.</note>)</p>
                </quote>
                <p>It is stated that “a comprehensive and decisive program… would probably involve: <list>
                        <item>“1. The development of an adequate political and economic framework
                            for the achievement of our long-range objectives.</item>
                        <pb facs="0325" n="309" xml:id="pg_309"/>
                        <item>“2. A substantial increase in expenditures for military
                            purposes.…</item>
                        <item>“3. A substantial increase in military assistance programs.…</item>
                        <item>“4. Some increase in economic assistance programs and recognition of
                            the need to continue these programs until their purposes have been
                            accomplished.</item>
                        <item>“5. A concerted attack on the problem of the United States balance of
                            payments.…</item>
                        <item>“6. Development of programs designed to build and maintain confidence
                            among other peoples in our strength and resolution, and to wage overt
                            psychological warfare.…</item>
                        <item>“7. Intensification of… operations by covert means.…</item>
                        <item>“8. Development of internal security and civilian defense
                            programs.</item>
                        <item>“9. Improvement and intensification of intelligence activities.</item>
                        <item>“10. Reduction of Federal expenditures for purposes other than defense
                            and foreign assistance, if necessary by the deferment of certain
                            desirable programs.</item>
                        <item>“11. Increased taxes.” (<ref target="#pg_56">pp. 56</ref>, <ref
                                target="#pg_54">57</ref>
                            <note n="9" xml:id="d91fn9">See <ref target="#pg_285">p.
                                285</ref>.</note>)</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Again, the Council is in no position to appraise those policy conclusions
                    relating to the basic military security and foreign policy of the United States.
                    The Council’s concern is that the conclusions and program recommendations that
                    may be approved both reflect and contribute to our basic economic strength.</p>
                <p>From this standpoint, “the development of an adequate political and economic
                    framework for the achievement of our long-range objectives” would appear to be
                    the governing concept which embraces all the specific areas of activity listed
                    in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68, and in the light of which specific
                    programs must be appraised. It embraces not only ponderable elements of economic
                    and military strength, but also the imponderables of political faith and action.
                    It embraces not only the conduct of our foreign policy, but also the conduct of
                    our domestic policy.</p>
                <p>It would seem of the highest importance that the development of a broad policy
                    framework be regarded as central in the work of the <hi rend="italic">Ad
                        Hoc</hi> Committee, rather than as an ancillary project for continuing
                    study. Only such a framework can give adequate guidance in approaching such
                    problems as how, over a considerable period of years, economic and social
                    resources can be devoted to military ends with maximum emphasis upon the
                    productive economic strength of the whole economy; or the way in which the
                    structure of taxation and incentives in our economy might best be used to ensure
                    the full achievement of our potential.</p>
                <p>Viewed in this light, there appears to be a need for an expansion of the areas of
                    specific action which are listed in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68. The
                    inclusion <pb facs="0326" n="310" xml:id="pg_310"/> of additional areas where
                    policy recommendations may be required will depend in considerable measure on
                    the size of new programs that are likely to come under consideration by the
                    Committee, but the following tentative listing is suggested: <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Measures to increase capacity in strategic areas of the economy. These
                            might involve tax measures, credit measures, price support programs or
                            market guarantees (as in the case of agriculture), etc. In some cases,
                            clear identification of needed goals and the reasons for them might be
                            enough to lift voluntary effort to the required levels.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Measures to promote an efficient and equitable allocation of
                            resources. Depending on the size of new programs, such measures might,
                            if needed, range from voluntary allocation agreements in selected fields
                            to more general types of allocation policies.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Measures to promote a stable and equitable distribution of purchasing
                            power. Again depending on the size of new programs recommended, such
                            measures, if needed, might range from purely voluntary programs in
                            selected areas to more general types of price-wage policies, tax
                            policies, etc.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                        <item>Finally, to the extent which seems desirable in the light of a
                            balanced assessment of other program recommendations and of general
                            economic developments, a general program designed to promote the full
                            utilization of the United States potential for economic growth. <gloss
                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68, in the Council’s view rightly,
                            stresses the serious risks to the achievement of our broad policy
                            objectives which would arise from economic instability, and the crucial
                            importance to those objectives of a stable and expanding economy.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The immediately foregoing points make clear the high relevance to <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 of the target studies for the general
                    economy which the Council of Economic Advisers has had continuously under way.
                    These studies need to be expedited, amplified, and more closely articulated with
                    the problems raised by <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68.</p>
                <p>It will have been observed that the above listing is framed more in terms of
                    policy aims than of specific fields of action, and that it embraces the two
                    final points in the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 listing, namely,
                    “reduction of Federal expenditures for purposes other than defense and foreign
                    assistance”, and “increased taxes”. This approach appears desirable in order to
                    avoid pre-judgment. A major program to expand our economic and military
                    potential might well require some selective increases in expenditures outside
                    the areas of direct defense and foreign aid. It might also be found that certain
                    tax concessions, as well as tax increases, might be an important element in such
                    a general program. It may also appear that if we take up the slack in total
                    output and employment which has developed since the end of 1948, every expansion
                    of defense will not require contraction elsewhere.</p>
                <pb facs="0327" n="311" xml:id="pg_311"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Programs and Costs; the Broad Implications of <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The preparation and appraisal of programs to carry out the objectives of <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68, as they may be approved, is a major task of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Ad Hoc</hi> Committee. Until some notions of magnitude and
                    duration are available, it is difficult to appraise the implications of <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 in even the most preliminary way. Certain
                    broad comments may, however, be put forward.</p>
                <p>In the Council’s view, the United States economy’s capacity for growth is such
                    that substantial new programs could be undertaken without serious threat to our
                    standards of living, and without risking a transformation of the free character
                    of our economy. Yet the adoption of such programs would create major problems of
                    economic and social policy. Unless carefully and imaginatively prepared, their
                    adoption could create concerns on the part of the Congress and the public which
                    could ultimately threaten their success.</p>
                <p>These problems and concerns stem in large measure from an inadequate appreciation
                    of our capacity for growth. They stem from a conviction that increased defense
                    must mean equivalently lowered living standards, higher taxes and a
                    proliferation of controls.</p>
                <p>In some measure, these apprehensions can be reduced by education and persuasion.
                    In some measure they can be offset by appeal to the people’s basic willingness
                    to sacrifice in the interests of a free society. But in considerable measure
                    they will remain, and will strongly influence both the magnitude and the
                    character of new programs that can be realistically put forward.</p>
                <p>This means that programs cannot be framed solely, or even predominantly, in terms
                    of our physical capacities. It means that there will be limitations of a
                    non-economic character on increases in expenditures, and pressures of like
                    character toward reducing expenditures in non-defense areas and revising our tax
                    structure. These limitations and pressures must be taken into account. From the
                    Council’s standpoint, the basic problem will be to contribute to the development
                    of recommendations which can make a maximum contribution to our economic and
                    military strength within this framework.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hamilton</hi> Q. <hi rend="smallcaps">Dearborn</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/> Approved: <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Leon</hi> H. <hi rend="smallcaps">Keyserling</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
