<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-06-06T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1950-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="97" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d97">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">711.59/6–650</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Director of the
                            Executive Secretariat of the Department of State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">McWilliams</hi>)</head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1950-06-06">June 6, 1950</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Meeting of Advisory Committee</hi>,<note n="1" xml:id="d97fn1">The Under Secretary’s Advisory Committee, consisting of
                            certain principal officers of the Department other than the Assistant
                            Secretaries for geographic areas, first met on May 9. The consensus of
                            that meeting was that the Committee should be used to provide high-level
                            policy guidance on major foreign policy problems. It was agreed that
                            aspects of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 should be discussed at
                            future meetings. (611.00/5–1050)</note>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 6</p>
                    <table>
                        <row>
                            <cell rendition="#nowrap">Participants:</cell>
                            <cell>Mr. Webb</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. Jessup</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. Barrett</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. Fisher</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. Nitze</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell>Mr. McWilliams</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Mr. Nitze summarized the paper for discussion—a statement of differences in
                        planning assumptions with respect to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68
                        between the <gloss target="#t_NSRB1">NSRB</gloss> and the Department.<note n="2" xml:id="d97fn2">Reference is to document AC D–1, June 5,
                            “Differences in Planning Assumptions in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68,” not printed.</note> The <gloss target="#t_NSRB1">NSRB</gloss> has put forward a maximum program of civil defense which
                        essentially is designed to care for the civilian population after a war has
                        started. The Department believes that we can not do everything under the
                        guise of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 68 and that we should
                        concentrate on the things we can do which we feel will help prevent a
                        possible war rather than to proceed on the assumption that a war will occur
                        in the near future and to plan what should be done then.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Fisher pointed out that he asked to have this subject put on the agenda
                        because this is the first time we are meeting this argument which will be
                        presented many more times in the future. He pointed out that by indicating
                        the necessity of building up forces you automatically create a frame of mind
                        which considers that war is immediate and this in turn makes it impossible
                        to achieve our objective which is preventing a war.</p>
                    <pb facs="0340" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/>
                    <p>Mr. Webb agreed that this is so and pointed out that the President and the
                        Bureau of the Budget would be subjected to all sorts of pressure for
                        expanding programs. He pointed out that the power people would want to
                        expand and would need a greater amount of money and likewise the public
                        roads people would say that we must have more and better roads and every
                        other agency would press for more money to expand their programs. It was
                        agreed that this sort of thing must be headed off—that it required firm
                        leadership to sort out the things which are important to be done and not
                        agree to programs such as these mentioned above which do not contribute to
                        the primary objective of preventing war.</p>
                    <p>The consensus of the group was that the position we should take with <gloss target="#t_NSRB1">NSRB</gloss>, and also in the future in regard to this
                        issue, is that we must concentrate on the political, psychological and
                        defensive mechanism to prevent dropping of bombs and an out-break of war. We
                        must proceed with the assumption that we can not do everything and we should
                        concentrate only on those things which set the above pattern. We must reject
                        the idea that we are fighting a war tomorrow because, when planning is done
                        with that assumption, the inevitable result will be to make the assumption
                        come true.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>W. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">McWilliams</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>