<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-10-17T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-10-17T10:00:00-05:00" n="115" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                        <head>115. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d115fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, POL 17
                                HUNG–US. Confidential. Drafted by Tihany. The conversation was held
                                in <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName>’s office.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1968-10-17T11:00:00-04:00">October 17, 1968, 11
                                    a.m.</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Introductory Call of Hungarian Ambassador
                                    <persName>Nagy</persName> on Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Janos Nagy</persName>, Hungarian
                                Ambassador</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">John M. Leddy</persName>, Assistant
                                Secretary for European Affairs</item>
                            <item>Leslie C. Tihany, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>, Hungarian Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nagy</persName>’s introductory call
                            on Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> lasted 12 minutes.
                            In order to avoid a repetition of the tactic used by the Ambassador
                            during his call on Mr. Lisle (see Lisle-<persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nagy</persName> memcon dated October 15, 1968),<note n="2" xml:id="d115fn2">Not printed. (Ibid., POL 17 HUNG–US)</note> which
                            was to blur the issue by introducing Viet-Nam in response to our opening
                            expression of disapproval regarding Warsaw Pact action in
                            Czechoslovakia, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> took
                            the initiative by first mentioning Viet-Nam and then proceeding to
                            Czechoslovakia. He told the Ambassador that, because of his wearisome
                            conversation with Deputy Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SB1">Szilagyi</persName> in Budapest a year ago,<note n="3" xml:id="d115fn3">See <ref target="#d111">Document 111</ref>.</note>
                            he was familiar and also in disagreement with the Hungarian Government’s
                            views on Viet-Nam. Next focussing on the events of last August, Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> tersely explained that
                            our efforts toward détente with Bloc countries, including Hungary, which
                            have borne some fruit in the case of the Soviet Union, would now have to
                            proceed more slowly and with more difficulty owing to
                            Czechoslovakia.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said he realized that his arrival in Washington occurred
                            in a situation marked by difficulties but that his efforts would be
                            directed toward contributing to an improvement rather than to a
                            deterioration of the situation. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> expressed approval of this intent and mentioned
                            that among the various bilateral problems awaiting solution that of the
                            mission personnel ceilings, in Washington and Budapest, could probably
                            be handled most rapidly. We were interested for security reasons, he
                            added, in assigning five Marines to our Embassy at Budapest.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nagy</persName> agreed that the
                            matter of personnel ceilings posed a problem easy to handle. He
                            continued to say that his Government did not tie in this problem with
                            any other outstanding issue. “My <pb facs="0352" n="324" xml:id="pg_324"/> need for increased staffing,” he added, “is not in Washington but
                            beyond the capital city.”</p>
                        <p>This oblique reference to the Hungarian desire to open consulates in New
                            York and Cleveland (see Lisle-<persName corresp="#p_NJ1">Nagy</persName>
                            memcon dated October 15, 1968)<note n="4" xml:id="d115fn4">Not printed.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, POL 17 HUNG–US)</note> drew the
                            comment from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> that “this
                            was not our case.” On the other hand, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> continued, we were concerned about two protection
                            cases in Hungary, those of Andrew Csala and Henrietta Blueye. Release of
                            these imprisoned Americans would mark progress toward improved
                            relations, he said.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador promptly replied that Mr. Csala would be released the
                            following day (October 18) and that our Embassy at Budapest was so
                            informed today. He was not familiar with the Blueye case but felt
                            hopeful as to its outcome as well.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> said that Csala’s
                            imminent release was good news, indeed, and expressed his appreciation.
                            When the Ambassador next took up the subject of US-Hungarian trade, Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> agreed that our
                            inability to grant <gloss target="#t_MFN1">MFN</gloss> should not
                            prevent some expansion of trade through promotional activities. He
                            mentioned, as an example, the Bulgarian Embassy’s current drive to
                            popularize Bulgarian wines in this country. The Ambassador appeared
                            interested.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> terminated the
                            conversation by wishing the Ambassador well in his new assignment.</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>