<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>158. Airgram From the Embassy in Romania to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d158</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">158</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-01-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recqDYPNCT9Q6HQio" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85039557"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Drilling</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec9i482eX195qnGX" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic reform</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec8PCbWGrkAaOOXZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001000124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developed countries</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                    <term ref="recJFd5tAUUdqBj9H" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">East-West relations</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recQZHNztoaX0AXIm" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military exercise</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-01-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="158"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d158">
                <head>158. Airgram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Romania</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d158fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL 1 ROM. Confidential. Drafted by deMartino. Repeated to Belgrade,
                        Berlin, Bonn, Budapest, London, Moscow, Munich, Paris, Prague, Rome, Sofia,
                        and Warsaw.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">A–181</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Bucharest</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-01-19">January 19, 1968</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Romanian Foreign Policy in 1968</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>
                </p>
                <p>A review of Romanian foreign policy suggests that the Romanians will continue
                    along well established lines, although they may make some concessions—more of a
                    formal than a substantive nature—to Moscow.</p>
                <p>Will Romanian foreign policy in 1968 be more cautious than in 1967? The question
                    is valid in view of the developments of the past year.</p>
                <p>Very recently, reliable information came to light that Moscow and other bloc
                    countries have been exerting economic pressure on Romania (Bucharest 901).<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d158fn2">Telegram 901, December 22, 1967, reported on Soviet
                        economic pressures on Romania. (Ibid., E 1 RUM–USSR)</note> To the extent
                    that these pressures include a Soviet refusal to buy Romanian oil drilling rigs,
                    the materials published here on the 1968 Romanian-Soviet trade protocol (signed
                    December 30, 1967) do not indicate that the pressure is off. We had long assumed
                    that Romania was under strong pressure, but the only evidence was indirect and
                    circumstantial: the logic of the situation (Romania’s defiance of Moscow in
                    establishing diplomatic relations with West Germany, staying away from the
                    conference of European Communist Parties at Karlovy Vary, and refusing to join
                    in the bloc position on the Middle East), Romanian accusations or intimations of
                    interference in internal affairs by unidentified parties (in particular,
                    Ceausescu’s article in <gloss target="#t_RCP1">RCP</gloss> Central Committee
                    daily <hi rend="italic">Scinteia</hi> of May 7), and the evident irritation of
                    Moscow and other bloc countries toward Romania (as reflected, inter alia, in the
                    propaganda against nationalism).</p>
                <p>In addition, Romanian internal policy is perhaps a complicating factor for its
                    foreign policy. The changes approved by the <gloss target="#t_RCP1">RCP</gloss>
                    National Conference imply a broad personnel reshuffle in the central and local
                    Party and State apparatus. They also imply a reduction in the size of this
                    apparatus. While some will be promoted, many will lose out in the process. The
                    prospect of such changes presumably is a dismal one for many if not most of the
                    Party apparatchiks. And the need to grapple with this <pb facs="0465" n="437"
                        xml:id="pg_437"/> problem is perhaps responsible for the evident caution of
                    the leadership in moving ahead on the economic reform, witness the introduction
                    of a slow schedule of implementation at the <gloss target="#t_RCP1">RCP</gloss>
                    National Conference, the blurring of responsibilities for economic activities at
                    the local level, and the carte blanche enabling law passed by the Grand National
                    Assembly. In passing, it is perhaps worth noting that none of the measures
                    approved by the Conference are likely to stir up any compensating popular
                    enthusiasm.</p>
                <p>Whether Moscow and its allies can or will try to capitalize on the
                    dissatisfaction which presumably will develop in the ranks of the Romanian
                    Communist Party remains to be seen. (In theory they could take advantage of the
                    vast number of contacts with Romanians which constantly take place—exchanges of
                    Party, State, and mass organization delegations—to strengthen such
                    dissatisfaction.) All that is said here is that, notwithstanding the show of
                    unity toward Moscow implicit in the continued presence of the “old guard”
                    leaders in the top Party organs, Romania will be more vulnerable to outside
                    pressure than before.</p>
                <p>To a degree, Romania’s foreign policy in 1968 will depend upon the foreign policy
                    initiatives of the Soviet Union. But only to a degree. Regardless of what the
                    Soviets do or do not do, the Romanians are busy steadily decreasing their
                    economic and political dependence on Moscow and its allies. In the communist
                    world, they have done their best to maintain a facade of cordial relations with
                    Communist China and Albania and they have assiduously cultivated other countries
                    and parties which tend to assert their independence from Moscow. Cuba is a
                    recent case in point. A more long-standing example is Yugoslavia. The Romanians
                    have been very active in trying to restore the excellent rapport which existed
                    between them and the Yugoslavs before <persName corresp="#p_CN1"
                        >Ceausescu</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TJB1">Tito</persName> fell
                    out on the Middle East question. At the same time, the Romanians have expanded
                    their ties with the West and with the less-developed countries of Asia, Africa,
                    and Latin America. They have also made the most of international forums (notably
                    the UN) and regional groupings (e.g., the Group of Nine and the Balkans). Since
                    these activities are vital to the consolidation of their independence, the
                    Romanians will surely continue along these lines in 1968.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Union, for its part, seems determined to press ahead with a variety of
                    policies the Romanians abhor: attacking “Mao and his clique“, isolating West
                    Germany from Eastern Europe, siding with the Arab countries against Israel,
                    promoting conferences of communist parties, and, perhaps, “strengthening” the
                    Warsaw Pact. The presumed Soviet interest in renewing the Soviet-Romanian Treaty
                    of Friendship, <pb facs="0466" n="438" xml:id="pg_438"/> Cooperation, and Mutual
                        Assistance<note n="3" xml:id="d158fn3">For text, see 48 UNTS 189.</note> and
                    concluding a non-proliferation treaty also present difficulties for the
                    Romanians.</p>
                <p>Barring a substantial deterioration in East-West relations, the Romanians will
                    not allow Moscow to impair their relations with third parties. They will not
                    attack Communist China nor will they join in any condemnation of West Germany or
                    Israel. (Romanian participation in the December 19–21 meeting of Eastern
                    European foreign ministers on the Middle East does not reflect a change in the
                    Romanian position. Evidently, the price of Romanian participation was a
                    communiqué consistent with the line taken in Romania’s formal statements on the
                    subject.) The Romanians could not afford to follow Moscow in these matters.</p>
                <p>On the other questions, however, there is more room for maneuver. Unquestionably,
                    the Romanians would prefer to stay away from the Budapest consultative
                    conference of communist parties.<note n="4" xml:id="d158fn4">The conference was
                        held February 26–March 5.</note> By implication at least, the proceedings
                    will have a pro-Moscow, anti-Peking flavor.</p>
                <p>Since it is only a preparatory conference, however—and hence presumably will not
                    produce “binding documents”—the Romanians may find it hard to stay away. If they
                    attend (and the Yugoslav Embassy in Bucharest seems to think that they will),
                    the Romanians presumably will use the occasion to reassert their well known
                    views about the conditions under which communist conferences are desirable
                    (along the lines of the Scinteia article of February 28, 1967).</p>
                <p>In connection with the Treaty of Friendship, Cooperation, and Mutual Assistance
                    with the Soviet Union, it is not clear whether the Romanians would prefer no
                    treaty at all, an automatic five-year renewal of the treaty, or a new treaty.
                    Whatever their motives, they seem to have decided to negotiate a new 20-year
                    treaty. In so doing, one can assume that they will insist on acceptable wording
                    and that the new treaty will neither heap abuse on the West Germans nor speak of
                    the desirability of arriving at joint positions on international problems. This
                    could be read as a further example of the determination of the Romanians to
                    “stick to their guns“, especially if the new treaty is not signed before the end
                    of the first 20-year period, on February 4, 1968. The failure of the Romanians
                    and Bulgarians to renew a similar treaty before the expiration of the first
                    20-year period on January 16, 1968 indicates that the Romanians are probably
                    taking a firm position in their negotiations with Moscow.</p>
                <p>As regards <gloss target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss>, it is difficult to tell just how
                    seriously the Romanians view their own objections to it. Although <gloss
                        target="#t_NPT1">NPT</gloss> presents the same type of problems for Romania
                    as for other non-nuclear countries, it is very likely that the purpose of
                    surfacing their objections was to show <pb facs="0467" n="439" xml:id="pg_439"/>
                    Moscow that Bucharest must be consulted on such matters. If so, their signature
                    of a non-proliferation treaty would not be as much of a concession as it might
                    appear at first glance. As a matter of fact, we would not be surprised to see
                    them end up by signing a non-proliferation treaty, particularly if many of the
                    other non-nuclear powers are willing to sign it.</p>
                <p>As for the Warsaw Pact, it is not at all certain that we are in for another
                    Soviet offensive directed toward “strengthening” the Warsaw Pact, although the
                    latest Soviet communiqués with the East Germans and Romanians suggest that this
                    may be the case. If so, the participation of Romania in the August 21–27 Warsaw
                    Pact maneuvers in Bulgaria and the statement about strengthening the Warsaw Pact
                    Organization in the joint communiqué with the Soviets would seem to imply a
                    co-operative attitude on the part of the Romanians. On the other hand, some of
                    their other activities seem to have the opposite implication. In 1967, the
                    Romanian leadership emphasized the need for less reliance on traditional sources
                    of arms supplies. The Romanians also organized a military exercise of their own
                    on October 12–13 to which no Warsaw Pact observers were invited and sent
                    lower-ranking delegates than those of other countries to the October 13–17
                    Warsaw Pact meeting in East Germany. On balance, we would judge that the
                    Romanians would not be willing to go along with any Soviet proposal which, in
                    substance, would increase Romanian involvement in Warsaw Pact affairs.</p>
                <p>We doubt very much that the Romanian willingness to compromise with the Soviets
                    would go beyond the framework discussed above. At the most, in our judgment, the
                    Romanians might make certain concessions which are more of a formal than a
                    substantive nature—e.g., attendance at the Budapest conference, and, if this can
                    be considered a concession, renewal of the bilateral treaty with the Soviet
                    Union—while continuing to defend their national interests in dealing with Moscow
                    and steadily building up the material and political basis of their independence.
                    The determination to continue along well established lines was reflected in the
                    joint communiqué signed with the Soviets on December 15 and, external pressures
                    and internal uncertainties aside, would be the logical consequence of the fact
                    that <persName corresp="#p_CN1">Ceausescu</persName> and his team have emerged
                    stronger than ever from the <gloss target="#t_RCP1">RCP</gloss> National
                    Conference.</p>
                <p>Nonetheless, the extent of the Romanian willingness to compose [<hi rend="italic"
                        >compromise</hi>?] with the Soviets will bear close watching. In formulating
                    policy in the future, the Romanians will no doubt take account of the reactions
                    of Moscow and its allies to Romania’s rather dramatic assertion of independence
                    in 1967. Presumably, they will also consider whether far-reaching internal
                    changes should incite them to greater prudence in international affairs. Under
                    these circumstances, more than ever the <pb facs="0468" n="440" xml:id="pg_440"
                    /> Romanians will be looking for signs that the West, and particularly the
                    United States, is willing to expand its economic and political relationship with
                    them.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Neubert</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
