<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1967-07-15T06:44:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1967-07-15T06:44:00-05:00" n="185" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                        <head>185. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in
                                Yugoslavia</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d185fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, POL US–YUGO. Confidential.
                                Repeated to Zagreb.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Belgrade</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1967-07-15T11:44:00+00:00">July 15, 1967,
                                1144Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>146. 1. During meeting with FonMin <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Nikezic</persName> yesterday, I raised question of our bilateral
                            relations. In much the same vein as conversation with Amb Crnobrnja day
                            before (Belgrade’s 140)<note n="2" xml:id="d185fn2">Dated July 14.
                                (Ibid.)</note> I referred to atmosphere of mistrust and apprehension
                            which seemed to permeate Yugoslav officialdom and press and increasing
                            tendency to regard <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> as deus ex
                            machina responsible for world events which seem to have raised so much
                            alarm here. <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> had shown in many ways
                            its desire to maintain good relations with Yugoslavia and I was
                            constantly being assured here that <gloss target="#t_GOY1">GOY</gloss>
                            was similarly interested in good relations. Repetition of charges re “US
                            aggression” and “US imperialism” in official utterances and press,
                            however, could hardly advance this objective. I pointed to history of
                            US-Yugoslav relations since 1948 which should have convinced Yugoslavs
                            of sincerity of our intentions. US public cannot fail to be aware <pb facs="0526" n="498" xml:id="pg_498"/> of present Yugoslav attitude
                            toward US and this in turn could affect whole scale of our
                            relations.</p>
                        <p>2. Nicezic said that many factors were involved in formulation of public
                            and official opinion which in turn affect conduct of foreign policy. He
                            was fully aware of points I had made and said <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> frequently found itself in position of trying to
                            moderate government’s views in much the same way as State Dept is
                            required to do from time to time. Recent events in world, culminating in
                            Greek coup d’etat and ME crisis had alarmed many people in Yugoslavia,
                            however, and caused conclusions to be drawn which may or may not be
                            fully justified. He spoke about Greece particularly, noting that new
                            Greek Govt is noisily anti-Communist and has indulged in various actions
                            which would not indicate any desire to maintain good relations with
                            Yugoslavia. <gloss target="#t_GOY1">GOY</gloss> on other hand wished to
                            maintain good relations with all neighboring states. It is assumed here
                            therefore that for reasons intimately connected with its effort to
                            remain in power Greek Govt deliberately fosters illusion of threat from
                            Communist neighbors. Over and above this there is some reason to suspect
                            that Greece might have designs on Albania which, of course, would be of
                            vital interest to Yugoslavia. I tried to dissuade him from this line of
                            thinking, observing that preoccupation with internal affairs should make
                            it obvious that Greece is in no position or mood to carry out foolhardy
                            military adventures.</p>
                        <p>3. <persName corresp="#p_NM1">Nikezic</persName> was very affable and
                            frank throughout our conversation. He said present atmosphere which I
                            had commented on and which he also deplored as affecting adversely
                            relations with the US would doubtless begin to be dispelled with
                            settlement of Middle Eastern problem. He expressed an interest in seeing
                            me again before I leave for Washington and before he departs on a
                            month’s holiday.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_ECB1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Elbrick</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>