<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>198. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d198</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">198</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-11-29T11:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1965-11-29T11:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recCxu7bJCFQ4pEdg" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rechJJ62r5nmf4KiI" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Cultural exchanges</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recFM9KfbcgtFmFBN" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1965-11-29T11:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-11-29T11:30:00-05:00" n="198"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d198">
                <head>198. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d198fn1"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, POL 2 <gloss target="#t_EUR1"
                            >EUR</gloss> E. Confidential. Drafted by Foley, on December 12. The
                        meeting was held at the Department of State. <persName corresp="#p_KJ2"
                            >Klaus</persName> visited Washington November 28–29. Memoranda of his
                        conversation with <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> on November 29,
                        dealing with peace efforts, the Asian Development Bank, and Austria’s
                        foreign policy, are ibid., POL AUS–US. A memorandum of his conversation with
                        Vice President Humphrey on November 29, dealing with the <gloss
                            target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> and East Europe, is ibid., Presidential
                        Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 70 D 217, VP/Memcon.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1965-11-29T11:30:00-05:00"
                            >November 29, 1965, 11:30 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Developments in Eastern Europe</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Austria</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJ2">Josef Klaus</persName>—Federal
                                Chancellor of Austria</item>
                            <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_LE1">Ernst Lemberger</persName>—Austrian
                                Ambassador to the United States</item>
                            <item>Dr. Franz Karasek—Chief of the Federal Chancellery</item>
                            <item>Dr. Gerald Hinteregger—Counselor of the Austrian Embassy,
                                Washington</item>
                            <item>Dr. Thomas Klestil—Economic and Scientific Secretary of the
                                Austrian Embassy, Washington</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">John M. Leddy</persName>—Assistant
                                Secretary of State for European Affairs</item>
                            <item>Mr. LeRoy F. Percival—Deputy Director, Office of Atlantic
                                Political-Economic Affairs</item>
                            <item>Mr. David Popper—Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for
                                International Organization Affairs</item>
                            <item>Mr. Raymond E. Lisle—Director, Office of Eastern European
                                Affairs</item>
                            <item>Mr. Julius Katz—Director, Office of International Trade</item>
                            <item>Mr. Edgar J. Beigel—Acting Director, Office of Western European
                                Affairs</item>
                            <item>Mr. Arthur D. Foley—Officer in Charge of Austrian-Swiss
                                Affairs</item>
                            <item>Mr. Herbert Spielman—Economic Officer for Italian-Austrian
                                Affairs</item>
                            <item>Mr. Harry Obst—Office of Language Services</item>
                            <item>Mr. William Krimer—Office of Language Services</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName> asked how the Chancellor sees
                    recent developments in Eastern Europe. Development of U.S. relations with the
                    Soviets, he said, are somewhat impeded by the Vietnam war. The U.S. would like
                    to continue normal exchanges with the Soviets but we are meeting with a
                    difficult attitude. This attitude is reflected only in part in Eastern Europe
                    and differs from country to country. The U.S. would like to relax tensions and
                    improve trade relations with Eastern Europe.</p>
                <pb facs="0555" n="527" xml:id="pg_527"/>
                <p>Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_KJ2">Klaus</persName> stated that this is a most
                    important subject for Austria. Austria conducts an active Eastern European
                    policy, particularly since the normalization of its relations with Eastern
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>Seen from Austria, the Chancellor continued, those countries of Eastern Europe,
                    which in 1945 turned completely toward the East, are now turning back toward
                    Western Europe as toward an old family. The governments are permitting more
                    liberalization but, he noted, the government leaders are in no way turning from
                    Communism. However, a healthy climate is being created and Austria wishes to
                    take advantage of it. Austrians find that old traditional relations with the
                    former members of the Hapsburg Empire permit them a special entree. Austrian
                    administration in these lands is well remembered, and this makes discussions for
                    the Austrians easier.</p>
                <p>Human contacts between Austrians and other Eastern Europeans are increasing, the
                    Chancellor said. 100,000 Austrians have friends or families in Eastern Europe.
                    Crossing the borders is made easier and real human contacts can be made.
                    Austrians now go to Yugoslavia on vacation and many thousands of Austrians go to
                    Hungary and many Hungarians now visit Austria. The Chancellor said that on
                    summer evenings in some parts of Vienna one can hear more Eastern European
                    languages being spoken than German. The Chancellor noted that cultural exchanges
                    in things German are easier through Austria for the Eastern Europeans than
                    directly with Germany.</p>
                <p>The Chancellor said that economic relations with Eastern Europe are making
                    progress. Austrian-Rumanian trade has quadrupled in recent years. The Austrian
                    Government realizes that this does not necessarily improve relations; politics
                    for the communist countries comes before trade and Austria cannot become
                    dependent on Eastern European trade.</p>
                <p>Austria actively cultivates official exchanges with Eastern Europe, the
                    Chancellor said. He said he had invited this year to Austria the prime ministers
                    of Poland and Rumania and he himself had had an interesting visit to Yugoslavia.
                    For the time being, he is not accepting invitations to the other Eastern
                    European countries since he wants the officials of those lands to come to
                    Austria first.</p>
                <p>In response to a question from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM1">Leddy</persName>
                    about Czechoslovakia, the Chancellor said that relations here are difficult.
                    Austria first normalized its relations with Yugoslavia, reached an agreement on
                    Carinthia, then the Government reached property agreements with Rumania,
                    Bulgaria, Yugoslavia and Hungary. However, no property agreement has been
                    reached with Czechoslovakia. He explained that since the days of the Hapsburg
                    monarchy, Austria-Czechoslovakian property has been closely intertwined and that
                    large sums of money are involved. This, he said, makes reaching an agreement
                    difficult.</p>
                <pb facs="0556" n="528" xml:id="pg_528"/>
                <p>As regards Poland, the Chancellor said Austria has no difficulties. A large
                    Austrian cultural institute has been established in Poland and cultural
                    exchanges are going on, as well as increased trade.</p>
                <p>Mr. Lisle asked for the Chancellor’s assessment of the status of the Catholic
                    Church in Eastern Europe and relations with the Vatican.</p>
                <p>The Chancellor said that status of the Catholic Church differs from country to
                    country. In Poland improvement of relations with the Vatican has come the
                    farthest. Relations with Yugoslavia are somewhat tense but an agreement is being
                    negotiated. The Chancellor said he had visited the Archbishop in Belgrade but
                    had not seen the Cardinal in Zagreb. Vatican relations with Czechoslovakia are
                    normalizing and in Hungary Cardinal <persName corresp="#p_MCJ1"
                        >Mindszenty</persName> is the only remaining problem. Rumania, the
                    government which has in many respects gone further in normalizing other things,
                    has been the most difficult for the Catholic Church. Four bishops have died in
                    prison and one is now under house arrest. The Chancellor said that Austrian
                    Cardinal Koenig has attempted to establish relations with the Catholic hierarchy
                    in each of the Eastern European countries. He has had good relations with them
                    at the Ecumenical Council.</p>
                <p>Mr. Lisle asked about the newspaper reports that Rumania wants to act as a
                    mediator in Vietnam. Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_KJ2">Klaus</persName> said
                    that in the four hours of his discussions with <persName corresp="#p_MI1"
                        >Maurer</persName> the question of mediation was not mentioned. He said
                    apparently <persName corresp="#p_MI1">Maurer</persName> mentioned this only
                    while traveling in Western Austria. There is no question, <persName
                        corresp="#p_KJ2">Klaus</persName> said, of either Austria or Rumania acting
                    as mediator. <persName corresp="#p_MI1">Maurer</persName> did criticize
                    U.S.-Vietnam policy. The Chancellor said that Austria has stated that it is
                    interested in securing peace but he noted that Foreign Minister Kreisky had said
                    that no solution to Vietnam is possible without U.S. prestige being
                    protected.</p>
                <p>Mr. Karasek said that so as not to create a false impression he wished to
                    emphasize that the Austrian Government had not discussed mediation in Vietnam
                    with the Rumanians. He has tried to check the source of these reports of
                        <persName corresp="#p_MI1">Maurer</persName>’s alleged statements. The
                    reports seemed to have been the conclusions of a reporter who had heard several
                    of <persName corresp="#p_MI1">Maurer</persName>’s statements on Vietnam. Other
                    reporters who had heard Maurer on the same occasions had not confirmed this
                    conclusion.</p>
                <p>Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_KJ2">Klaus</persName> said that there can be no
                    mediation unless both sides request it. He added that visitors to the West from
                    the East have repeatedly tried to get the Austrian Government to denounce
                    U.S.-Vietnam policies and the Austrians have at all times rejected this.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
