<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="204" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d204">
                        <head>204. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d204fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, POL
                                    <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> E–USSR. Secret. Drafted by
                                Crump and approved in <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss> on October 24.
                                The meeting was held in Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>’s office. <persName corresp="#p_WK1">Waldheim</persName> was in the United States attending the U.N.
                                General Assembly.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1968-10-21">October
                                    21, 1968</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Eastern European Situation</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Austrian</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>His Excellency Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WK1">Kurt
                                            Waldheim</persName>, Federal Minister of Foreign
                                        Affairs</item>
                                    <item>His Excellency Dr. <persName corresp="#p_LE1">Ernst
                                            Lemberger</persName>, Austrian Ambassador</item>
                                    <item>His Excellency Dr. Arno Halusa, Director General of
                                        Political Affairs</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                                <list>
                                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                                    <item>Mr. John E. Crump, Desk Officer,
                                        Austria-Switzerland</item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Czechoslovakia</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Minister <persName corresp="#p_WK1">Waldheim</persName> emphasized that,
                            contrary to the impression created by Austrian newspapers, there had not
                            been a sense of panic among the Austrians and there had never been a
                            fear of Soviet invasion, although there had been and still remains
                            serious concern. He admitted that the Austrian military establishment
                            had contributed to the sense of nervousness by its prediction of Soviet
                            action against Austria. This fear had been based upon the large numbers
                            of Soviet troops in Czechoslovakia,<note n="2" xml:id="d204fn2">Soviet
                                troops held maneuvers in Czechoslovakia June 19–30.</note> illegal
                            over-flights over Austrian territory and a three-day period when Soviet
                            leaders were not available to the Austrian Ambassador in Moscow. The
                            current feeling is that the Soviets will not undertake direct action
                            against Austria because to do so would bring on a direct confrontation
                            with the West. It is difficult to see into the future but Austria
                            expects no action by Warsaw Pact powers against Yugoslavia or
                            Austria.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary replied that in August we had considered the chances of an
                            intervention in Czechoslovakia to be 51/49. We had the impression from
                            the Soviet Ambassador and others that developments in Prague represented
                            a fundamental threat to the Soviet Union and that possible Czech
                            defection from the Communist Bloc had been raised. In addition, the
                            Czechs themselves had raised questions regarding the fundamental
                            governing position of the Communist Party.</p>
                        <p>The question which now remains is the presence of Soviet forces near the
                            Bavarian border. This is a problem for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and certain steps will be taken—these steps are a
                            matter of prudence rather than steps arising from a fear of immediate
                            attack.</p>
                        <pb facs="0569" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Possible Future Soviet Actions</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Secretary outlined possible actions which might be taken by Warsaw
                            Pact powers in a descending order of gravity.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Action against Berlin; this would clearly mean war.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>At almost the same level, any Soviet move against Austria would
                                surely involve a confrontation with the West. The U.S., France and
                                Great Britain have an interest in Austrian independence arising from
                                the State Treaty and if Austria were to call on the signatories of
                                the Treaty to help her preserve her independence, this would surely
                                precipitate a crisis.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Soviet action against Yugoslavia would produce a far more
                                formidable crisis than Czechoslovakia. We cannot look calmly at
                                Soviet actions aimed at the Adriatic area. The question arises
                                whether Yugoslavia is still considered a member of the Socialist
                                commonwealth. In this regard, the Secretary mentioned a press
                                briefing recently at the Soviet Embassy which indicated that the
                                Soviets do not consider Yugoslavia to be a member of the Socialist
                                Bloc.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>An attack on Romania would have different motivations because
                                there is no question there of the monopoly of the Communist Party.
                                The question regarding possible intervention in Romania was put
                                directly to Soviet Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> who replied categorically that the Soviet
                                Union is not planning action against that country.<note n="3" xml:id="d204fn3">See <ref target="#d167">Document
                                    167</ref>.</note> While it is questionable what value should be
                                given to that response, we do not see the threat of military action
                                against Romania nor any of the other three areas at the present
                                time.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>This can obviously change very quickly. We are concerned about the recent
                                <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> article which apparently set forth a
                            new doctrine of the “Socialist commonwealth.”<note n="4" xml:id="d204fn4">Reference is to the “<persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> Doctrine.” See <ref target="#d23fn4">footnote 4, Document 23</ref>.</note> It may be that this is an
                            explanation of the Soviet intervention in Czechoslovakia to those
                            persons in the Soviet Union and elsewhere who require such an
                            explanation. On the other hand, the Soviets may have indeed evolved this
                            new theory which may be used to explain further military moves.</p>
                        <p>In summary, we doubt the likelihood of further military moves at the
                            present, although the situation remains one of utmost gravity. An attack
                            against West Berlin, a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> country or
                            Austria would present an extremely grave situation; Soviet moves in
                            other areas would be less serious but still grave.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Western Responses</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Minister <persName corresp="#p_WK1">Waldheim</persName> said that it was
                            of great importance to make clear to the Soviet Union that an act
                            against a neutral European country <pb facs="0570" n="542" xml:id="pg_542"/> would lead to counter-action. The Secretary
                            replied that the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Ministerial
                            meeting in mid-November will show a clear response on the part of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.<note n="5" xml:id="d204fn5">The
                                    <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> Ministerial Meeting was held
                                in Brussels November 15–16. For text of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> declaration, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, December 9, 1968, pp.
                                595–597.</note> It is important that all Western countries move
                            together and the days of a response by the U.S. alone are over. For
                            example, during the 1961 Berlin crisis the U.S. added $6 billion to its
                            defense budget, called up reserves and took actions which were not taken
                            by any other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> country. Similarly,
                            we were alone in some actions following the Czechoslovak invasion.
                            Europe cannot say that it is up to the U.S. alone to respond to
                            Czechoslovakia.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he would hope that if the Austrians receive any
                            information or indications of Soviet pressure, they would immediately
                            inform the U.S., Great Britain and France so that we can make clear to
                            the Soviet Union our reaction. In the case of Romania we had felt it
                            necessary to make a public statement<note n="6" xml:id="d204fn6">Apparently a reference to President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s August 30 address at San Antonio, Texas.
                                For text, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers of the Presidents of
                                    the United States: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B.
                                        Johnson</persName>, 1968–69</hi>, Book II, pp.
                                917–920.</note> and to call in the Soviet Ambassador;<note n="7" xml:id="d204fn7">See <ref target="#d165">Document 165</ref>.</note>
                            we would need as much advance warning as possible if similar actions
                            were to be undertaken regarding Austria.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Soviet Internal Reaction</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Secretary noted that the Soviets certainly could have predicted the
                            disadvantages which would accrue from their intervention in
                            Czechoslovakia—unfavorable publicity in Czechoslovakia, division among
                            the Eastern Europeans, splits in Western Communist parties. They were
                            willing to pay this price and this may indicate a willingness to move
                            back to the cold war days in the Kremlin. Another explanation may lie in
                            the fact that committee actions, such as are required within the present
                            Soviet Government, make it difficult for an individual to oppose the
                            majority view and this may have a bearing on future moves. It is clear
                            that the Soviets have become afraid of peaceful co-existence.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary added that the Soviet Government may now realize that its
                            intervention in Czechoslovakia has developed badly and cannot survive
                            without far reaching changes. The Soviets face problems with their youth
                            and with minority national groups. They must continually deal with
                            nostalgia in Eastern European countries for ties to the West. These
                            factors have created a difficult situation and their awareness of the
                            situation causes them to be nervous and afraid and they are therefore
                            dangerous.</p>
                        <pb facs="0571" n="543" xml:id="pg_543"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Austrian Views</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Minister <persName corresp="#p_WK1">Waldheim</persName> responded that
                            the Austrian judgment of the present situation is similar. However,
                            while the Austrians see no danger in the immediate future, they are
                            concerned about long-run developments, particularly in connection with
                            hostilities in the Middle East. If war breaks out again in the Middle
                            East the Soviets can be expected to make further moves in Eastern
                            Europe.</p>
                        <p>He agreed that it was necessary for the U.S. and Austria to keep in close
                            touch regarding any increases in Soviet pressures against Austria. He
                            said that he had been asked about guarantees of Austrian neutrality and
                            had responded that the obligations in the State Treaty are sufficient
                            for that purpose. It is clear to the Soviet Union that an action against
                            Austria would bring on a new war and there is therefore no necessity for
                            any further guarantee.</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>