<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>65. Telegram From the Embassy in the Soviet Union to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v17</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d65</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">65</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1968-07-11T10:20:00-05:00" notAfter="1968-07-11T10:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rect4tQQCzcqVqdpO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98003467"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democratization</term>
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                    <term ref="rec26FVg4SV48wXxH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85124118"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Socialism</term>
                    <term ref="receKRNx87Ug7K5bW" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106111"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Pravda</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1968-07-11T10:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1968-07-11T10:20:00-05:00" n="65"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d65">
                <head>65. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in the Soviet Union</gloss>
                    to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d65fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, POL CZECH. Confidential. Repeated to Budapest, Warsaw, Sofia, London,
                        Berlin, Bucharest, Bonn, USNATO, Prague, Belgrade, Paris, and Munich.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Moscow</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1968-07-11T15:20:00+00:00">July 11, 1968, 1520Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>4614. Subj: USSR-Czechoslovakia.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Summary. As Czech <gloss target="#t_CP1">CP</gloss> Congress approaches,
                        Soviets apparently increasing pressure on Dubcek leadership to contain
                        “democratization.” This reflects growing concern not only over danger of
                        contamination other <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>s with resultant
                        adverse effects on their foreign as well as domestic policies, but also over
                        possible reverberations in USSR itself.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Despite reported <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s tearful
                        protestations to Smrkovsky’s delegation<note n="2" xml:id="d65fn2">The
                            Chairman of the Czech National Assembly led a parliamentary delegation
                            to Moscow June 4–15. He met with <persName corresp="#p_BLI1"
                                >Brezhnev</persName> on June 14.</note> that Soviets did not even
                        think of interfering in Czech internal affairs, they obviously attempting to
                        do just that. Most dramatic evidence this effort are, of course, delay in
                        departure Soviet troops after Warsaw Pact exercise and recent letters to
                        CPCS from Soviet, East German, Polish, Hungarian, and Bulgarian <gloss
                            target="#t_CP1">CP</gloss>s. After brief lull in press polemic with
                        Czechs following Kosygin’s “rest and cure” at Karlovy Vary, Soviets have
                        also intensified their public campaign against proponents <pb facs="0230"
                            n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/> of liberalization in Czechoslovakia, with
                        implied threat they would come to support true defenders of
                        socialism.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Following their attack on Cisar (Moscow 4268),<note n="3" xml:id="d65fn3"
                            >Apparently an incorrect reference. Telegram 4268 from Moscow, June 14,
                            reported on the makeup of a Soviet scientific delegation. (Department of
                            State, Central Files, SCI 40–3 IAEA)</note> Soviets seized upon letter
                        Czech People’s Militia to Soviet Ambassador Prague as pretext for
                        well-publicized meetings throughout USSR expressing support for defenders of
                        socialism and condemning “anti-socialist” elements in Czechoslovakia. This
                        campaign included July 7 <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> denunciation of <hi
                            rend="italic">Mlada Fronta’s</hi> reaction to meetings, which ended with
                        statement that “our Czech class brothers can always count on full
                        understanding and support Soviet people.” Czech Embassy here also receiving
                        from one to two hundred letters a day from Soviet citizenry endorsing Czech
                        militia letter, and even Koucky expressed to British Ambassador his
                        annoyance at action Soviet Government in stimulating such letters.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Continuing Soviet attacks on Czech liberals, yesterday’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Literaturnaya Gazeta</hi> carried extremely sharp attack on Vaculik and
                        his “2000 Words” declaration.<note n="4" xml:id="d65fn4">A June 27 manifesto
                            written by Ludvik Vaculik and signed by 70 prominent Czech intellectuals
                            calling for a speed-up in democratization and denouncing party rule
                            under the <persName>Novotny</persName> regime. For text, see Times
                            Literary Supplement, July 18, 1968.</note> Article accuses Vaculik of
                        attempting promote “hot summer” of chaos and disorganization in
                        Czechoslovakia, of hating Communist Party and “truly popular democracy,” and
                        of seeking establish “pure democracy” designed deprive CPCS of power. “2000
                        Words” labeled as provocative, anti-Communist, and counter-revolutionary
                        program. Echoing Kirilenko’s remark in Bologna that “no one has right close
                        his eyes” to danger caused by imperialist attempts subvert socialist
                        countries from within, article states “watershed” between “healthy” and
                        “anti-socialist, in essence counter-revolutionary” forces increasingly
                        evident in Czechoslovakia, and expresses bewilderment “2000 Words” published
                        by four Prague papers and in effect supported by National Front President
                        Kriegel on TV June 28.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>While <hi rend="italic">Literaturnaya Gazeta</hi> focused its attack on
                            Vaculik personally, and in fact suggested he had had some difficulty in
                            finding signers for declaration, today’s Pravda article by Aleksandrov
                            states “2000 Words” not isolated phenomenon but evidence growing
                            activity rightists and outright counter-revolutionary forces in
                            Czechoslovakia. Indeed, in asserting tactics used by these forces
                            similar to and even more devious than those employed by Hungarian
                            counter-revolutionaries in 1956, article implies Czechoslovakia on verge
                            of anti-Communist revolt. Although Aleksandrov notes that “healthy”
                            forces in CPCS regard “2000 Words” as open attack against socialist
                            system, against leading role CPCS, and against friendship between
                            Czechoslovakia and USSR, as <pb facs="0231" n="203" xml:id="pg_203"/>
                            well as other socialist countries, he also deplores “equivocal” stand
                            taken by some of Czech leaders and attacks Prace, Zemedelske Noviny,
                            Mlada Fronta, and Prague radio and TV for influencing public opinion in
                            favor declaration. Pointing out other socialist countries closely
                            watching Czech developments, Aleksandrov refers to Soviet meetings in
                            support Czech Militia’s letter, and cites criticism of “2000 Words”
                            voiced by Rabotincheka Delo and Nepsabadszag.</p>
                        <p>In what sounds like strong warning to <persName corresp="#p_DA1"
                                >Dubcek</persName> leadership, article expresses “confidence” Czech
                            Communists will be able give resolute rebuff to reactionary,
                            anti-socialist forces and ensure further development of country on road
                            of socialism and friendship with all socialist states. Similar to Pravda
                            July 7 denunciation of Mlada Fronta, it ends with ominous statement that
                            in their struggle for strengthening socialism “working class and all
                            working people of Czechoslovakia can always count on understanding and
                            full support Soviet people.”</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Another device used by Soviet press in criticizing Czech developments is
                        to identify <gloss target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss> with objectives pursued by
                        Czech liberals. Latest piece along such lines, perhaps prompted by Ziak’s
                        suggestion Brandt visit Prague (Bonn 14142),<note n="5" xml:id="d65fn5"
                            >Telegram 14142 from Bonn, July 5, reported that the Czech Vice Foreign
                            Minister had expressed a desire for a visit by Willy Brandt to
                            Czechoslovakia. (Department of State, Central Files, POL 7 GER W)</note>
                        was July 5 <hi rend="italic">Izvestiya</hi> article accusing Bonn of seeking
                        spread deviously falsified interpretations of Marxism in effort split <gloss
                            target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>’s among themselves and from USSR.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Last, but not least, Soviets’ concern about Czech situation and their
                        effort put pressure on <persName corresp="#p_DA1">Dubcek</persName> evident
                        from <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s speeches on occasion
                            <persName>Kadar</persName> visit and at reception military academies
                        graduates July 8. Soviets probably do not hope be able turn clock back in
                        Czechoslovakia, but they clearly making every effort stop it.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Thompson</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
