<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">124</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="124"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d124">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.4731/328</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="32a" xml:id="d124fn32a">Delivered to the Department by Mr. Keith
                        Officer, Australian Counselor of the British Embassy; the first-person
                        references in this document are to Mr. Officer.</note>
                </head>
                <p>His Majesty’s Government in the Commonwealth of Australia have given careful
                    consideration to the memorandum handed to me at the State Department on June
                    13th and the list of probable concessions<note n="33" xml:id="d124fn33">List not
                        printed.</note> received from the State Department on the 20th June.</p>
                <pb facs="0159" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/>
                <p>They wish me to communicate to you the attached list<note n="33a"
                        xml:id="d124fn33a">Not printed.</note> of formal requests made by the
                    Commonwealth Government: this list would have been supplied before had the
                    Commonwealth Government thought that the United States Government wished and
                    were in a position to proceed to detailed discussions.</p>
                <p>The Commonwealth Government desire me to say that whilst they are anxious to
                    negotiate with the United States of America a mutually satisfactory trade
                    agreement, such an agreement naturally must have regard to the circumstances of
                    both countries and, in the case of Australia, to the great need for an expansion
                    of its exports to the United States of America, particularly in such commodities
                    as wool, beef, mutton and lamb. In their opinion the offer the United States
                    Government have made falls very far short of constituting a reasonable basis for
                    negotiations, and they hope that the United States Government will be able to
                    accept as a basis the list they are now submitting.</p>
                <p>In explanation of the above, I should say that the Commonwealth Government are
                    preparing to consider only an agreement which is of real value to both parties.
                    To be of value to Australia an agreement must promise a more even balance in
                    trade between the two countries and contain concessions which will make possible
                    some expansion of the Australian Export Trade to the United States of America,
                    for the Commonwealth Government cannot contemplate a continuance indefinitely of
                    anything approaching the figure of the present annual adverse balance. But
                    whilst the requests submitted by the United States Government would expand to a
                    very considerable extent United States exports to Australia the concessions
                    offered by the United States of America promise no expansion of Australian trade
                    and so actually threaten to increase Australia’s adverse balance of trade. For
                    these reasons the Commonwealth Government are seeking such further concessions
                    as would promise some increase in their exports and so a more equitable and
                    mutually satisfactory distribution of trade.</p>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-06-28">June 28,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
