<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="279" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d279">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">862.00 P.R./237</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Political Report of the Chargé in Germany</hi>
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Gilbert</hi>)<note n="2" xml:id="d279fn2">Transmitted to the Department by the Chargé in Germany in his
                                    despatch No. 3832, January 17, 1938; received February
                                5.</note></head>
                            <dateline>
                                <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-17">undated</date>
                            </dateline>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Extract]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                            <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Anti-Semitic Action</hi>. The tendency toward
                                the exclusion of Jews from German economic and professional life
                                which moves forward in periodic waves received a new impetus with
                                the announcement on January 5 that doctors of Jewish race, as
                                defined by the 1935 Nuremberg Laws,<note n="3" xml:id="d279fn3">For
                                    Citizenship Law of September 15, 1935, see <ref target="frus1935v02#pg_406"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1935, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>,
                                        p. 406</ref>.</note> had been forbidden, as from the
                                beginning of the year, to treat patients belonging to the employees
                                sickness insurance system. This system, to which its members pay a
                                slightly higher contribution and thereby possess a wider choice of
                                doctors than those enrolled with the ordinary compulsory sickness
                                insurance fund, comprises about three million patients. The German
                                press has indicated that the order will affect between 3,000 and
                                9,000 Jewish doctors throughout Germany, 900 of whom reside in
                                Berlin. A further order published January 16 forbade Jewish
                                dentists, as from the twentieth of the month, from treating patients
                                enrolled with the Ersatzkrankenkassen, or various insurance systems,
                                including that for employees, which serve as substitutes for the
                                compulsory system. For the present, Jewish doctors are to remain
                                with the ordinary government compulsory insurance system, or
                                Ortskrankenkassen, a circumstance which is ascribed to the current
                                shortage of doctors in Germany.</p>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>