<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Germany ( (Wilson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">377</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9yKWGNvCFmqmdD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recwiCYrBEGX9Z5wr" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Naturalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="377"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d377">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.624/26</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Germany</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Wilson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 125</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-10-11">October 11,
                            1938</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department has received your despatch No. 120
                    of April 30, 1938, referring to the case of Ransom Otto Theodore Rupprecht, <pb
                        facs="0484" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/> and concerning the attitude of the
                    German Government with respect to the provisions of Article 278 of the Treaty of
                    Versailles, which was incorporated in the treaty of August 25, 1921, between the
                    United States and Germany restoring friendly relations. The Department has
                    observed that in its note to the Embassy of April 11, 1938, the German Foreign
                    Office takes the position that Article 278 of the Treaty of Versailles is not
                    intended to declare a loss of German citizenship but to extend regulations
                    regarding protection which are laid down in the preceding Articles, 276 and 277,
                    in favor of citizens of the former Allied and Associated Powers on German
                    territory, to apply to the new citizens of those Powers, and in particular to
                    exempt them from those German taxes which are levied only on Germans. It is
                    argued that the German view is inferred from the fact that Article 278 is not in
                    Part III of the Treaty of Versailles containing the provisions as to
                    citizenship, but in Part X, entitled “Economic Clauses” and in Chapter IV of
                    such Part under the heading “Treatment of Nationals of Allied and Associated
                    Powers”. It is observed further that whenever the view has been taken that under
                    Article 278 the acquisition of citizenship in one of the Allied and Associated
                    Powers results in the loss of German citizenship the view has always been held
                    in Germany that the Article can only be intended to apply to new citizenship
                    acquired through the transfer of territory provided in the Treaty of Versailles,
                    or through the treaties concluded to carry out the Treaty of Versailles, or, in
                    other words, only in consequence of the operation of the provisions of the
                    Treaty of Versailles.</p>
                <p>The Department has very carefully considered the arguments contained in the note
                    of the German Foreign Office. It considers that these arguments are illogical
                    and untenable. The principal argument seems to be that because Article 278 is
                    contained in Part X of the Treaty of Versailles, which is entitled “Economic
                    Clauses” and not in Part III which is entitled “Political Clauses for Europe”,
                    which contains provisions as to citizenship, Article 278 is not intended to
                    declare a loss of German citizenship but to extend regulations regarding
                    protection to the new citizens of the Allied and Associated Powers resulting
                    from the Treaty of Versailles, and in particular to exempt them from German
                    taxation. The Department is of the opinion that it is illogical to draw any
                    inference from the fact that the provisions of Article 278 are contained in Part
                    X rather than Part III of the Treaty. There is no reason why such a provision
                    should have been contained in Part III. An examination of Part III of the Treaty
                    indicates that citizenship is treated specifically in connection with the
                    provisions concerning each of the various territories, sovereignty over which
                    was transferred to another state or to a new state or concerning which a
                    plebiscite was to be held. Thus having dealt specifically with <pb facs="0485"
                        n="477" xml:id="pg_477"/> citizenship in each situation, there would have
                    been no purpose in placing such a provision as Article 278 in Part III. It seems
                    particularly appropriate, however, that the provisions of Article 278 be
                    contained in Part X, Chapter IV, under the heading “Treatment of Nationals of
                    Allied and Associated Powers”. Under Articles 276 and 277 contained under such
                    heading Germany made certain undertakings with regard to nationals of the Allied
                    and Associated Powers. It was particularly appropriate that under such Chapter a
                    provision should have been made under which the question whether a person was a
                    national of an Allied and Associated Power could easily be determined. The
                    provision is clear and unequivocal. It has no relation to the question of the
                    mere right of a person to be protected in Germany as a national of one of the
                    Allied and Associated Powers. Under it Germany specifically undertakes to
                    recognize any new nationality which has been or may be acquired by her nationals
                    under the laws of the Allied and Associated Powers or under treaty stipulations,
                    and further, it specifically undertakes to regard such persons as having in all
                    respects severed their allegiance to Germany. The provision is unambiguous. It
                    is not limited as to time.</p>
                <p>With regard to the second argument of the German Foreign Office that whenever the
                    view has been taken in Germany that under Article 278 the acquisition of the
                    citizenship of a person of German origin in one of the Allied and Associated
                    Powers results in the loss of German citizenship the Article can only be
                    intended to apply to new citizenship acquired through the transfer of territory
                    provided in the Treaty of Versailles or through the treaties concluded to carry
                    out the provisions of such Treaty, or, in other words, only in consequence of
                    the operation of the provisions of these treaties, the Department considers
                    again that the argument is illogical and untenable. It apparently has been
                    overlooked that under Article 278 Germany undertook to recognize any new
                    nationality which had been or may be acquired by her nationals under the laws of
                    the Allied and Associated Powers and in accordance with the decisions of the
                    competent authorities of these Powers pursuant to naturalization laws or under
                    treaty stipulations and to regard such persons as having in all respects severed
                    their allegiance to Germany. Under this provision Germany specifically undertook
                    not only to recognize a new nationality acquired in consequence of the operation
                    of the provisions of the Treaty of Versailles but also any new nationality
                    acquired “in accordance with the decisions of the competent authorities of these
                    Powers pursuant to naturalization laws”.</p>
                <p>While the Department considers that the arguments of the German Foreign Office
                    are both illogical and untenable, it may be stated that when considering the
                    provisions to be incorporated in the treaty which <pb facs="0486" n="478"
                        xml:id="pg_478"/> was finally signed on August 25, 1921, restoring friendly
                    relations between the United States and Germany, the Department gave very
                    careful consideration to those provisions of the Treaty of Versailles under
                    which rights, privileges, indemnities, reparations, or advantages were given to
                    the United States as one of the principal Allied and Associated Powers. During
                    the course of the negotiations resulting in the treaty of August 25, 1921, it
                    was made clear to the German authorities that the Peace Resolution of July 2,
                    1921, portions of which were incorporated in the treaty of August 25, 1921,
                    indicated clearly the views of the Congress that the rights, privileges,
                    indemnities, reparations, and advantages, accorded the United States under the
                    Treaty of Versailles should be secured to the United States and that this
                    Government would not enter into any treaty which failed to secure them. Among
                    other things the Department considered the provisions of Article 278 of the
                    Treaty of Versailles. While it was considered that the provision of this Article
                    obligating Germany to recognize any new nationality acquired by her nationals
                    under the laws of the Allied and Associated Powers is unilateral, in explicit
                    terms and eliminated all questions of dual nationality of persons of German
                    extraction who acquired the nationality of one of the Allied and Associated
                    Powers, it regarded Article 278 as a substitute for a naturalization treaty. As
                    indicated, the Article is unilateral but under the laws of the United States the
                    right of expatriation is freely recognized; hence, any American citizen who is
                    naturalized as a German citizen loses his citizenship in the United States as a
                    result of such German naturalization. No question was raised by the German
                    authorities at the time negotiations were being carried on as to the view of the
                    German Government with regard to the meaning of Article 278 of the Treaty of
                    Versailles, nor had it even been intimated up to the time when the case of Mr.
                    Rupprecht arose that the German Government took a view as to the meaning of the
                    provisions of Article 278 other than what its unambiguous and specific terms
                    indicate, that is, that Germany would recognize any new nationality which had
                    been or may be acquired by her nationals under the laws of the Allied and
                    Associated Powers and in accordance with the decisions of the competent
                    authorities of these Powers pursuant to naturalization laws and to regard such
                    persons as having in consequence of the acquisition of such new nationality in
                    all respects severed their allegiance to Germany. The Department considers that
                    Article 278 of the Treaty of Versailles has been incorporated as a part of the
                    treaty of August 25, 1921, and that under it Germany is obligated to recognize
                    the naturalization of a German citizen in the United States as resulting in the
                    loss of German nationality.</p>
                <p>It is suggested that you communicate the foregoing views to the appropriate
                    German authorities and express the hope that Ransom Otto Theodore Rupprecht will
                    not only be recognized as having been <pb facs="0487" n="479" xml:id="pg_479"/>
                    naturalized as a citizen of the United States under the laws of this country and
                    in accordance with the decision of the competent authorities of this Government
                    as previously conveyed to the German authorities but that in accordance with the
                    provisions of Article 278 of the Treaty of Versailles he will be regarded as
                    having in consequence of the acquisition of citizenship in the United States in
                    all respects severed his allegiance to Germany.</p>
                <p>Very truly yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Secretary of State:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">R. Walton Moore</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[In despatch No. 1034, June 21, 1939 (711.624/28), the Chargé in Germany
                        reported that the Department’s views as given in instruction No. 125,
                        October 11, 1938, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>, were embodied in a note sent
                        to the German Foreign Office on January 9, 1939, and that in a reply dated
                        June 13, 1939, the German Foreign Office stated that the German Government
                        after careful study upheld its position as explained in its note of April
                        11, 1938, quoted in despatch No. 120, April 30, printed on <ref
                            target="#pg_472">page 472</ref>. In reply, the Department in instruction
                        No. 415, November 14, 1939, directed the Embassy to postpone indefinitely
                        the presentation of the draft treaty to the German Government
                        (711.624/28).]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
