<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Liberia ( (Walton) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d689</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">689</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-12-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-12-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="689"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d689">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">882.635 Neep/134</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Liberia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Walton</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 243</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Monrovia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-12-12">December 12,
                            1938</date>.<lb/>[Received January 12, 1939.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to my telegram No. 95,
                    December 9, 3 p.m., and to report that there appeared in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Weekly Mirror</hi> of November 25, 1938 the following article: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Arriving by the S. S. <hi rend="italic">Maaskerk</hi> on the 19th
                            instant was Mr. D. Caffe, who represents the financial group seeking to
                            exploit the iron resources of the Republic. Iron has played such an
                            important part in the progress of nations and the history of
                            civilization, that Mr. Caffe’s mission in Liberia has seemed somewhat
                            providentially timed. The new program of advancement needs the strength
                            and endurance of the “Iron Horse.” Liberia has waited long for this day,
                            and the opportunity that it offers may not come again soon. Seized now
                            it will lead inevitably to progressive development, omitted Liberia may
                            flounder another century in the toils of a poor and unbalanced economy.
                            We welcome Mr. Caffe back to Liberia and wish for his mission the
                            success it seems to deserve.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Publication of the foregoing occasioned no little comment among Liberians and
                    other nationals at this capital and was particularly disturbing to Mr. W. W. J.
                    Croze, the representative of the United States Steel Corporation, who is heading
                    a party of geologists and engineers in making a survey of the iron deposits in
                    this country.</p>
                <p>Mr. Croze had previously called at the American Legation and made reference to
                    the presence of Mr. Caffe in Monrovia. In all probability Mr. Croze had heard
                    some comment on Mr. Caffe’s intention to reopen conversations with the Liberian
                    Government relative to granting Neep <pb facs="0824" n="816" xml:id="pg_816"/>
                    an iron concession. Mr. Caffe had been absent from the capital since June.</p>
                <p>In the late afternoon of December [<hi rend="italic">November?</hi>] 26,
                    Secretary of State Simpson paid me a social call. I showed him a copy of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Weekly Mirror</hi> containing the article concerning Mr.
                    Caffe, which he had not seen. Both of us were of the opinion that the article
                    had been subtly written to give the members of the Legislature and the public in
                    general a wrong impression as to the real status of the Neep application and why
                    President Barclay no longer favored granting the company a concession.</p>
                <p>As the <hi rend="italic">Weekly Mirror</hi> is subsidized by the Liberian
                    Government, Secretary Simpson and I surmised, and correctly so, that the article
                    had been inserted without the editor having given serious consideration as to
                    the probable unfavorable reactions it might provoke. Assurance was given me by
                    Secretary Simpson that he would see both the President and the publisher about
                    the article.</p>
                <p>That evening I attended a social affair in Monrovia at which Mr. Croze was
                    present. So was Mr. Caffe. For fully half an hour they were engaged in earnest
                    conversation. After Mr. Caffe had left, Mr. Croze obviously perturbed,
                    approached me and related conversation he had had with Mr. Caffe. Mr. Caffe is
                    quoted as having said that the Liberian Government had given him “a dirty deal.”
                    Mr. Croze informed me that he was transmitting via air mail a copy of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Weekly Mirror</hi> to the United States Steel Corporation
                    officials in the United States. He thought something should be done to clear up
                    what he considered a delicate situation, and expressed the hope that the United
                    States Steel Corporation would not encounter a similar experience with the
                    Liberian Government.</p>
                <p>Earlier in the week I had sought to assure Mr. Croze that the status of the
                    United States Steel Corporation was not analogous to that of Neep; and that the
                    Liberian Government had taken the position that Neep was seeking to secure the
                    concession to peddle, while United States Steel Corporation had sufficient
                    capital to exploit the Liberian iron deposits, if the survey measured up to
                    their expectations. In a similar vein I talked with Mr. Croze on the evening in
                    question.</p>
                <p>On November 30, I conferred with President Barclay, who had discussed the article
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Weekly Mirror</hi> with Secretary Simpson. The latter
                    had also reported a conversation he had held with Mr. Caffe, who had called at
                    the foreign office to register a protest against the position taken by the
                    Government toward Neep and had complained that President Barclay had not seen
                    fit to give him an audience. In the course of his talk Mr. Caffe is supposed to
                    have said: “Neep cannot successfully cope with the United States Government nor
                    the United States Steel Corporation, but we can voice our dissatisfaction
                    through diplomatic channels.”</p>
                <pb facs="0825" n="817" xml:id="pg_817"/>
                <p>Secretary Simpson is reported to have told Mr. Caffe that as the Liberian
                    Government had not granted Neep a concession, he did not see how it would be
                    possible for Neep to precipitate a diplomatic incident between the Liberian
                    Government and the Netherlands.</p>
                <p>President Barclay informed me on the evening of November 30, he had invited the
                    members of the Legislature, Cabinet and other prominent members of the True Whig
                    Party to an informal social gathering at the Executive Mansion, which he was
                    giving for the express purpose of creating an opportunity to discuss fully and
                    frankly every stage of the negotiations between the Liberian Government and
                    Neep. This he did, confidentially reading important communications and records
                    bearing on the subject. I am advised that when the gathering broke up the
                    Legislators assured the President they had a clearer picture of the situation
                    and that the course he had pursued was the proper one.</p>
                <p>Subsequently, President Barclay sent a special message to the Legislature
                    recommending the disapproval of suggested modifications which were to have been
                    a basis of acceptance for granting of Neep concession, and the repeal of the
                    initialed memorandum. These recommendations have been favorably acted upon by
                    the Legislature.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Lester A. Walton</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
