<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Chargé in the United Kingdom (
                    (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d715</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">715</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-01-12T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-01-12T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-01-12T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-01-12T17:00:00-05:00" n="715"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d715">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">781.003/65: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-01-12T17:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 12, 1938—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>14. Your 810, December 29, 8 p.m.<note n="2" xml:id="d715fn2">
                        <ref target="frus1937v02#pg_879">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, p. 879</ref>.</note> The Department is
                    gratified to observe that the principles set forth in its confidential
                        memorandum<note n="3" xml:id="d715fn3">See telegram No. 485, December 11,
                        1937, 3 p.m., to the Chargé in the United Kingdom, <ref
                            target="frus1937v02#pg_874">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 874</ref>.</note> meet in general with
                    the concurrence of the Foreign Office. The Department shares the opinion of the
                    Foreign Office that it might be advantageous to inform the French Government of
                    our views regarding economic equality in Morocco, but it is inclined to believe
                    that mutual American and British interests might be best served if we
                    communicated our views direct to the French Government through our Embassy at
                    Paris.</p>
                <p>It would be helpful to the Department in considering this matter if it could be
                    informed whether the British views on economic equality and the establishment of
                    quotas in relation to Moroccan trade conform substantially with our views and,
                    if not, in what specific particulars they differ.</p>
                <p>In this connection the Department is particularly desirous of ascertaining the
                    views of the Foreign Office as to “whether the establishment of different
                    representative periods for the quotas of different commodities entering into
                    Moroccan trade might not better serve the interests of the countries most
                    concerned than the establishment of a single representative period for all
                    commodities in respect of which quotas may be contemplated.”</p>
                <p>Please seek an early opportunity to discuss in detail our confidential memorandum
                    with the Foreign Office and report the result of your discussion by
                    telegraph.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
