<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-10-11T14:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-10-11T14:00:00-05:00" n="779" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d779">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">867N.01/1161: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi>
                                    (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-10-11T19:00:00+00:00">October 11, 1938—7
                                        p.m.</date><lb/>[Received October 11—4 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1161. Your 614, October 10, 6 p.m. The Foreign Office confirms your
                                understanding that no final decision respecting the future of
                                Palestine is to be made before the report of the Woodhead Commission
                                is in the hands of the Government. The report has not yet been
                                signed and the Foreign Office states that it is not expected to be
                                completed until the latter part of October.</p>
                            <p>Mr. MacDonald was very explicit in the House of Commons on October 6
                                last regarding the Government’s intentions in this respect. He
                                referred to the fact that the Woodhead Commission’s report would not
                                be in his hands until towards the end of October and that he did not
                                anticipate that the Government would be able to reach conclusions
                                before the House of Commons reassembled on November 1st. In reply to
                                a further question he confirmed that the House of Commons <pb facs="0960" n="952" xml:id="pg_952"/> would not be put in a
                                position of having to confirm or reject a decision already taken and
                                put into operation, but would have an opportunity of considering the
                                policy before it was adopted and put into operation by the
                                Government.</p>
                            <p>The press attributes to the Iraqi Foreign Minister who has recently
                                visited London a plan whereby Palestine would be converted from a
                                mandatory to an independent state allied by treaty to Great Britain
                                and governed under a constitution which would embody guarantees of
                                full civil and religious rights to all communities and which would
                                permit no further Jewish immigration.</p>
                            <p>An official of the Foreign Office states that the Iraqi Foreign
                                Minister’s visit was arranged as long ago as last July. He added
                                that the Palestine situation was discussed with him but that there
                                were “no negotiations”.</p>
                            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Daily Telegraph</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Morning Post</hi> of October 5 stated that it is expected that
                                an extraordinary meeting of the League Council will be summoned
                                toward the end of the year to approve the British Government’s
                                eventual policy with regard to Palestine.</p>
                            <p>I shall revert to the last paragraph of your telegram at an early
                                date.</p>
                            <p>Copy by mail Jerusalem.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Kennedy</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>