<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Turkey ( (MacMurray) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1938v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d872</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">872</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1938-06-30T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1938-06-30T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recbfb6dc62c599a48" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recZJL0JHE1yyaPgZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028962"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade agreement</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1938-06-30T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1938-06-30T12:00:00-05:00" n="872"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d872">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">611.6731/403: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Turkey</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">MacMurray</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ankara</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1938-06-30T19:00:00+02:00"
                            >June 30, 1938—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received July 2—7:15 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>49. From Trade Delegation. Department’s telegram No. 15, June 25, 2 p.m.</p>
                <p>1. Referring to last paragraph Department’s telegram, an investigation and
                    analysis of Turkish commodity export statistics to the United States for first 3
                    months indicates that the sharp decline in exports is accounted for by decreased
                    shipments chiefly of tobacco, and secondarily of skins and furs, sheep casings,
                    walnuts, valonia, valonia extract and emery.</p>
                <p>2. In order that the delegation may be in a position to proceed with negotiations
                    on tariff concessions, in accordance with the Department’s instructions,
                    delegation requests that decisions be reached as to reclassification of oriental
                    rugs and as to reduction which may be offered to Turkey.</p>
                <p>Delegation suggests that consideration be given to following possible
                    reclassifications: (1) “carpets, rugs and mats of the Turkish type, not made on
                    a power driven loom, et cetera”; (2) substitution of “Anatolian” for “Turkish”;
                    (3) substitution of “Sivas,” Isparta, Smyrna, Kaysereri, Ouschak, Gordes,
                    Bergama” for “Turkish.”</p>
                <p>With regard to possible reclassification (1) delegation desires to point out that
                    Turkish is a term generally used in rug trade to designate <pb facs="1076"
                        n="1068" xml:id="pg_1068"/> a distinctive type of rug, distinct from other
                    types such as Persian, Caucasian, Turcoman, et cetera. It is believed that
                    either (1) or (2) would be satisfactory to Turkey and that (3) would probably be
                    acceptable.</p>
                <p>3. Delegation perceives no objection to exploring possibility of a solution of
                    the question of the consolidation of tariff reductions and other similar taxes
                    and charges, et cetera, along lines indicated in your paragraphs 1, 2 (<hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>) and 2 (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>). It is of the opinion
                    that the exchange formula proposed by the Department is not feasible because, on
                    account of the impossibility of forecasting with reasonable accuracy Turkey’s
                    total imports from all countries and Turkey’s exports to the United States, it
                    is not possible to fix a percentage for United States share of Turkey’s total
                    imports from all countries which would reasonably assure the fulfillment of both
                    of the conditions laid down by the Department, namely (1) insure Turkey a
                    surplus of dollar exchange over and above amounts required to pay for
                    merchandise imports from the United States and (2) assure for payment of
                    American goods an amount of exchange not less than that which would be available
                    in the absence of a trade agreement. Whatever percentage be selected, any
                    unforeseen increase in Turkey’s total imports or unforeseen decrease in Turkey’s
                    exports to the United States would reduce or eliminate Turkey’s surplus of
                    dollar exchange and might even make it impossible for Turkey to supply the
                    amount of exchange required by the formula; and any unforeseen decrease in
                    Turkey’s total imports or unforeseen increase in Turkey’s exports to the United
                    States would result in the United States obtaining less favorable treatment
                    under Department’s formula than Turkey would contemplate in the absence of a
                    trade agreement.</p>
                <p>In view of the foregoing the delegation desires to submit for the Department’s
                    consideration the following alternative suggestions with regard to exchange
                    control provision.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                    <item>Standard general provision on exchange control with insertion at the end
                        of subparagraph (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) of a sentence to the following
                        effect “the foregoing however does not preclude such delay as may be
                        incidental to Turkey’s refraining from making available for commercial
                        payments exchange required for essential needs of the State”.</item>
                    <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                    <item>Provision to the effect that in respect to all aspects of foreign exchange
                        control the United States shall be accorded treatment no less favorable than
                        that which it received in a specified period, say 1935–1937, and in any
                        event no less favorable than that accorded the most favored nation.</item>
                </list>
                <p>It does not seem possible to draft a provision imposing precise obligations on
                    Turkey in respect to making exchange available for payment <pb facs="1077"
                        n="1069" xml:id="pg_1069"/> of imports from the United States which would
                    fulfill the two requirements set forth by the Department in regard to this
                    matter. A provision based upon either of the above suggestions would afford a
                    base for our obtaining as favorable treatment as is possible under the present
                    circumstances. Such a provision would permit Turkey to reserve a portion of
                    dollar exchange for requirements other than commercial payments, and would not
                    set up a formula under which Turkey would have the right to accord us treatment
                    less favorable than it contemplates in the absence of a trade agreement.</p>
                <p>4. As the Prime Minister is leaving Ankara tomorrow and has indicated an interest
                    in the tenor of Department’s latest instructions, Acting Secretary General of
                    Foreign Office was informed today that our Government was prepared to explore
                    every possibility with a view to finding a solution for the difficulties
                    confronting the Turkish Government in connection with our proposals, especially
                    with respect to the questions of the consolidation of tariff rates, et cetera,
                    and exchange control. A solution to question of tariff reductions along the
                    lines outlined in the Department’s paragraphs 1 and 2 was submitted to him.</p>
                <p>With regard to question of exchange control, Secretary General was informed that
                    the United States Government recognizes Turkey’s exchange difficulties and is
                    disposed to agree to a limitation of Turkey’s obligation to make exchange
                    available for payment of commercial imports from the United States, but that it
                    could not accept the particular form of limitation contained in the Turkish 80%
                    exchange clause. He was informed that the American delegation was prepared to
                    cooperate with the Turkish delegation in working out a formula which would meet
                    the needs of Turkey’s position and which would not be in conflict with our
                    policy.</p>
                <p>Acting Secretary General stated that he would immediately consult with
                    appropriate officials and let us know by the middle of next week Turkish
                    Government’s attitude with regard to our suggestions. [Trade Delegation.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacMurray</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
