<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>109. Telegram From the Embassy in Vietnam to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-05-06T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-05-06T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec0NGmogdkmVrqib" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022963"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemicals</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recJdNN8BhT6m6iw4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-05-06T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-05-06T06:00:00-05:00" n="109"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d109">
                <head>109. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d109fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27-14 <gloss target="#t_S1"
                            >S</gloss> VIET Secret. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1"
                            >CINCPAC</gloss>, London, New Delhi, and Ottawa.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1963-05-06T19:00:00+08:00">May 6, 1963, 7 p.m.</date>
                        </hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>987. <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1"
                        >POLAD</gloss> and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_NFEJ1"
                        >Nolting</persName>. <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL1">Deptel</gloss> 951, Emb
                        A-651.<note n="2" xml:id="d109fn2">In telegram 951 to Saigon, April 12, the
                        Department concurred in the Embassy’s proposal to encourage the Government
                        of Vietnam to limit the response to the North Vietnamese charges to a
                        denial. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,<gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                        27-10 <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss> VIET) Airgram A-651 from Saigon, April
                        23, transmitted a copy of the April 8 letter from the <gloss
                            target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> to the Government of Vietnam requesting a
                        response to North Vietnamese charges that noxious chemicals had been used to
                        carry out “collective reprisals” against the people of South Vietnam. (<hi
                            rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27 <gloss
                            target="#t_S1">S</gloss> VIET)</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> replied May 4 to <gloss target="#t_ICC1"
                        >ICC</gloss> concerning <gloss target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> charges on
                    “noxious chemicals” (copies being pouched). Reply asserts charges completely
                    without foundation, explains purpose defoliation operations in <gloss
                        target="#t_RVN1">RVN</gloss>; claims no chemical product other than 2,4-D
                    2,4,5-T <pb facs="0299" n="273" xml:id="pg_273"/> has “ever” been used,
                    particularly arsenites and others alleged by Hanoi. Letter says <gloss
                        target="#t_DRV1">DRV</gloss> charges constitute inadmissible interference in
                    internal affairs of <gloss target="#t_RVN1">RVN</gloss>; notes Communist
                    propaganda effort aims at diverting international attention from <gloss
                        target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> aggressive acts (it mentions particularly <gloss
                        target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> arsonists in Saigon) in face realization that
                        <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> people: turning away from Communist
                    propaganda (Strategic Hamlet and Chieu Hoi programs are cited). <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> letter also encloses text President <persName
                        corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName>’s <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss>
                    interview (Emb A-552)<note n="3" xml:id="d109fn3">In the interview, which was
                        conducted by the Voice of America on March 17, <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1"
                            >Diem</persName> characterized the North Vietnamese charges as “a pure
                        fabrication”. (Airgram A-552 from Saigon, March 26; <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid.</hi>, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27-10 <gloss
                            target="#t_S1">S</gloss> VIET)</note> and Professor <persName
                        corresp="#p_BH1">Buu Hoi</persName>’s April 15 press conference this subject
                    (Emb A-628).<note n="4" xml:id="d109fn4">On April 15, Professor <persName
                            corresp="#p_BH1">Buu Hoi</persName>, Director of the Vietnamese Atomic
                        Energy Office, held a press conference in Saigon to explain that defoliants
                        and herbicides were not harmful to humans or animals and could have
                        beneficial effects. (Airgram A-628 from Saigon, April 18; <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid.</hi>)</note> Finally, letter says in event “some” members <gloss
                        target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> wish to form “personal opinion” <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> mission will arrange with local authorities for
                    them to go to provinces where <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> propaganda
                    alleges defoliation caused damage or claimed victims.</p>
                <p>We consider letter generally good (although claim that no other chemicals than
                    2,4-D and 2,4,5-T used is not true and no mention made of crop destruction) but
                    final reference to visit more forthcoming than we would have preferred. Colonel
                    An, Chief <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> Mission to <gloss target="#t_ICC1"
                        >ICC</gloss>, explained to Embassy officer wording of this paragraph had
                    been changed from “invitation” to offer to “arrange if requested” in light
                    Embassy’s views; draft had then been discussed with Foreign Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_MAU1">Mau</persName> and President <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1"
                        >Diem</persName> who “instructed” An leave offer in. An requested our
                    assistance in obtaining British and Canadian support for position outlined in
                    letter.</p>
                <p>[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (5 lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>It continues our strong conviction (with which Colonel An [<hi rend="italic">less
                        than 1 line not declassified</hi>] agree) <gloss target="#t_ICC1"
                        >ICC</gloss> investigation would be counterproductive and latest offer to
                    arrange visit should not be permitted provide opening wedge such investigation.
                    Would be helpful if New Delhi, Ottawa, London, and Department would continue use
                    appropriate opportunities emphasize this position. We plan continue taking this
                    position here with Canadians, British and <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                    >GVN</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Concerning New Delhi’s 4123<note n="5" xml:id="d109fn5">In telegram 4123 from New
                        Delhi, April 23, the Embassy noted that Indian officials inclined to the
                        view that it might be better if the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>
                        investigated the North Vietnamese charges and refuted them rather than
                        dismiss them and leave the question open for further exploitation by the
                        North Vietnamese. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>)</note> to Department,
                    Embassy fully agrees first pare <gloss target="#t_DEPTEL1">Deptel</gloss>
                        1000.<note n="6" xml:id="d109fn6">The first paragraph of telegram 1000 to
                        Saigon, April 25, outlined the Department of State’s conviction that given
                        Polish membership, the <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> was unlikely to
                        clear the Government of Vietnam rapidly of the noxious chemical charges.
                        Rather, the investigation would probably be prolonged with continued
                        propaganda exploitation by the North Vietnamese. (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid.</hi>)</note> On question legal committee report,<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d109fn7">Not further identified.</note>
                    <pb facs="0300" n="274" xml:id="pg_274"/> believe its release would have
                    considerable exploitable value to us even though information old and we should
                    seek avoid quid pro quo between non-publication of report and <gloss
                        target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss> decision not to investigate chemicals charges.
                    In view immediate necessity preventing <gloss target="#t_ICC1">ICC</gloss>
                    investigation, however, and fact our views on legal report recently conveyed
                    Indians, believe we should concentrate on “noxious chemicals” charges and not
                    add to potential linkup those charges with legal report by pressing for latter
                    at this time.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MML1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Manfull</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
