<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-05-21T09:48:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-05-21T09:48:00-05:00" n="130" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d130">
                        <head>130. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d130fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, PR 11 Saigon. Confidential; Routine. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HTJ1">Heavner</persName> and cleared by Manell,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HR1">Hilsman</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MRJ1">Manning</persName>, and with Defense and
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>. Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-05-21T10:48:00-04:00">May
                                        21, 1963, 10:48 a.m.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1111. Re press policy. Primary purpose this message is to recapitulate
                            our basic approach and policy on press relations Viet-Nam.</p>
                        <p>In line with policy laid down at outset increase US assistance effort,
                            first principle press relations Viet-Nam must continue be to provide
                            fullest possible cooperation to press in order make available to newsmen
                            complete picture complicated Viet-Nam situation and US role. US public
                            must have accurate story our Viet-Nam program if we are to justify our
                            large human and material investment there. Assistance to press thus
                            commands very high priority.</p>
                        <p>We aware mission has made extraordinary efforts assist press and
                            encourage <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> adopt liberal and
                            generally helpful press policy. Believe however that wherever possible
                            we should take reporters further into our confidence in order to be
                            certain their background understanding of situation is more
                            complete.</p>
                        <p>We also have in mind more frequent pre-operations briefings. While
                            considerations of military security must naturally come first, believe
                            it might be possible to do more such briefings without endangering war
                            effort.</p>
                        <p>You should also continue your efforts persuade <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> cooperate more fully with US press. Primary
                            responsibility for access to news is theirs and hence primary effort get
                            Viet-Nam story fully told should be Vietnamese also.</p>
                        <p>We understand difficulties your situation and fully appreciate your
                            efforts. Department also confident press accounts Viet-Nam situation are
                            bound to reflect overall improvement situation as progress against
                                <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> becomes more evident. Foregoing
                            intended only to reiterate standing policy and suggest what may be done
                            to further implement that policy.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BGW1"><hi rend="strong">Ball</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>