<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-07-05T22:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-07-03T23:00:00-05:00" n="207" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d207">
                        <head>207. Report by the Joint Chiefs of Staff’s Special Assistant for
                            Counterinsurgency and Special Activities (<persName corresp="#p_KMGVH1">Krulak</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d207fn1">Source: Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_OASD1">OASD</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 67 A 4564, Vietnam 1963. Secret. Attached to a
                                brief transmittal memorandum sent on July 5 by General <persName corresp="#p_TGMD1">Taylor</persName> to Secretary of Defense
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>. A handwritten
                                note on the covering memorandum indicates that Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> saw the report. On July
                                9, <persName corresp="#p_FMV1">Michael Forrestal</persName> sent a
                                copy of the report to <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                                    Bundy</persName> for the President. <persName corresp="#p_FMV1">Forrestal</persName> indicated, in his covering memorandum,
                                that he felt the report gave “a fair and soundly optimistic picture
                                of the part of the iceberg which is under water, i.e. the war
                                against the Viet Cong.” A note on the covering memorandum indicates
                                that the report was placed in the President’s weekend reading file.
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_KJE1">Kennedy</persName> Library,
                                National Security Files, Vietnam Country Series,
                                7/1/63-7/20/63)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1961-07-05T23:59:59-04:00" notBefore="1961-07-04T00:00:00-04:00">undated</date>.</hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">VISIT TO VIETNAM</p>
                        <p>This reports on a visit to Vietnam, made during the period 25 June to 1
                            July 1963, to review progress in the counterinsurgency campaign.</p>
                        <pb facs="0482" n="456" xml:id="pg_456"/>
                        <p>Time was spent mainly in the provinces, where affairs, within their
                            purview, were discussed with United States and Vietnamese military and
                            civilian personnel, at the various levels of authority. Places visited
                            are portrayed on the facing page.<note n="2" xml:id="d207fn2">The
                                attached map, which details the 15 places visited by <persName corresp="#p_KMGVH1">Krulak</persName> in South Vietnam, is not
                                printed.</note></p>
                        <p>As a supplement to the practical part of the visit, a series of specific
                            questions were presented to the Military Assistance Command. The
                            responses to those questions are appended.<note n="3" xml:id="d207fn3">Not found attached.</note> They, coupled with the field visits and
                            personal conversations, and reflected against the backdrop of two
                            previous visits at five month intervals, formed the basis for these
                            conclusions: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p><hi rend="italic">The counterinsurgency campaign is moving
                                        forward on the military and economic fronts. There is reason
                                        for optimism in both of these areas.</hi></p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">The strategic hamlet program, correctly
                                        characterized as the heart of the campaign, has acquired
                                        both momentum and balance. Its impact is most
                                        favorable.</hi></p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Offensive operations against the Viet Cong are
                                        widespread and varied, and are growing steadily in
                                        intensity. While not always of high quality, their general
                                        effect has been to place the Viet Cong on the
                                        defensive.</hi></p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">The Buddhist issue is alive, serious and
                                        enmeshed with politics. It has not as yet affected adversely
                                        the essential operational programs.</hi></p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">The “Open Arms” amnesty program is effective,
                                        both as an index to progress achieved and as a weapon
                                        against the Viet Cong.</hi></p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">The operating relationship between US advisors
                                        and their counterparts is efficient and mutually respectful.
                                        It continues to be an essential to successful prosecution of
                                        the war.</hi></p>
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Events in Laos are a source of growing concern
                                        to those charged directly with the conduct of the war in
                                        South Vietnam.</hi></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p rend="center">Field Visits</p>
                        <p>Field visits were conducted to: (a) Observe the evolution of the province
                            rehabilitation program; (b) Note changes in the professional quality of
                            the Vietnamese military, by observing units in actual operations; (c)
                            Appraise the advisor/advisee relationship in action; and (d) Obtain low
                            level views as to the progress of the war. The itinerary followed during
                            the visit responded to these purposes.</p>
                        <pb facs="0483" n="457" xml:id="pg_457"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The Province Rehabilitation
                                Program</hi></p>
                        <p>The constantly repeated assertion, heard over the past year and a half,
                            that the strategic hamlet is the heart of the counterinsurgency
                            strategy, is acquiring growing validation. Binh Duong Province-one in
                            which province rehabilitation has lagged because of much hard core Viet
                            Cong activity was first selected for a physical inspection. This is the
                            province in which President <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName>, against the counsel of others, launched the Sunrise
                            strategic hamlet operation in 1962, at a time when the bulk of the
                            population in the area was under Viet Cong control.</p>
                        <p>When the Secretary of Defense visited the Sunrise project in May of 1962,
                            and despite the Vietnamese effort to conceal the fact, it was plainly
                            far from a success. The only strategic hamlet in the province, its
                            organization did not really extend far beyond a system of strong
                            physical defenses. The inhabitants were there under duress. Combat
                            capable men were conspicuous by their absence.</p>
                        <p>Fourteen months have seen a great change. There are now 92 strategic
                            hamlets completed in the province, out of a programmed total of 302.
                            Many have been carved out of areas wholly dominated by the Viet Cong for
                            ten years or more. These, moreover, are now more than barbed wire
                            enclosures into which women, children and aged men have been herded
                            against their will, as was the case in Sunrise. The people have come
                            willingly—in some cases having actually sent deputations to request the
                            development of a hamlet. Economic and political developments have moved
                            ahead in train with the defensive preparations. Two new hamlets
                            visited—Bung Dia and Cau Dinh—had programs underway for pig raising,
                            seed and fertilizer distribution, fruit tree planting, well digging and
                            education. The people, unprepared for the visit, seemed enthusiastic.
                            The hamlet chiefs had both been elected by the villagers. Neither had
                            ever held any office before; both had just completed a province-run
                            course in hamlet administration. These hamlets were impressive in every
                            sense.</p>
                        <p>In Quang Ngai Province, also visited because of its long history of heavy
                            Viet Cong infestation, progress was equally impressive. A year ago the
                            province had no strategic hamlets deserving of the name. Today there are
                            273 completed and 125 more under construction, out of a total program of
                            419. Over two thirds of the people in the province are in hamlets, and
                            the entire program is scheduled for completion by the end of this year.
                            Here, as in Binh Duong Province, the people and the land have had to be
                            wrested from the Viet Cong. The hamlet of Vinh Tuy, one of those visited
                            in this province, rests on ground which only fell to Vietnamese forces
                            after three attacks, in February of this year. It is still pretty crude,
                            but the people in it, who <pb facs="0484" n="458" xml:id="pg_458"/> were
                            actually under Viet Cong control six months ago, seemed cheerful and
                            busy. Most important, there was a reasonable percentage of young men of
                            military age in evidence.</p>
                        <p>For contrast, a visit was also paid to Ninh <persName corresp="#p_THUAN1">Thuan</persName> Province, one of the two in which the strategic
                            hamlet program is already fully completed. Here, 127 hamlets are in
                            being, housing 97% of the people of the province. The hamlets differ
                            greatly in quality and in physical character, being designed to suit the
                            peculiarities of the varied population—which includes Vietnamese, Cham
                            tribesmen and Montagnards. In several respects, however, they are
                            similar. The all reflect a unified effort at training and equipping a
                            hamlet militia contingent. They all are active in the radio warning
                            system; and they all exhibit progress in the US/Vietnamese economic
                            assistance program.</p>
                        <p>In fact, this province finds its problems now largely shifted from
                            military matters to economic development. The area is tranquil-will
                            probably soon be declared officially “white”. There are no regular
                            military forces remaining in the province and the peoples’ concerns have
                            now turned from the Viet Cong to an ambitious irrigation program and the
                            development of rural power. The province, hopefully, is a foretaste of
                            the future.</p>
                        <p>Throughout the visit to the central and northern parts of the country
                            progress was noted in bringing together the US military and economic
                            assistance programs. Every major military briefing attended in these
                            regions included a presentation by a civilian member of the US Overseas
                            Mission, and every discussion on strategic hamlets dwelt upon the
                            indissoluble nature of our military/economic programs. This coordinated
                            approach may have been in effect 15 months ago. If so, it was not nearly
                            so obvious as today.</p>
                        <p>In the Delta, this degree of coordinated progress apparently has not yet
                            been achieved. In Vinh Long Province, although the hamlet program is
                            well along (206 out of 247) our economic participation is less in
                            evidence. This may derive from the fact that there is not so much
                            poverty in the Delta, or because the premium on security is still much
                            greater than on economic improvement.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Military Operations</hi></p>
                        <p>The Operational Phase of the National Campaign, directed to begin on 1
                            July, was actually in progress before that date. Over 1,000 assorted
                            offensive operations are now conducted per month, over twice the level
                            of a year ago. Not all are effectively executed, nor are all successful.
                            In sum, however, they are putting great pressure on the Viet Cong,
                            causing him casualties, degrading his resources and keeping him on the
                            defensive.</p>
                        <pb facs="0485" n="459" xml:id="pg_459"/>
                        <p>In the forthcoming phase of the National Campaign, it is prescribed that
                            every tactical unit-Regular, Civil Guard and Self Defense Corps—shall be
                            offensively engaged in the field for twenty days per month. While
                            somewhat unrealistic, the directive still promises even further
                            intensification of operations and even greater stress on the Viet
                            Cong.</p>
                        <p>Tactical operations of varying sizes were visited in the field. They
                            varied in quality, from extremely impressive to just fair.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item><p>The 25th Division, in Quang Ngai has been in existence for
                                    exactly one year. During that period it has succeeded in driving
                                    the Viet Cong from the coastal plain into the mountains of the
                                    Annamite Chain, where they are now largely on the defensive. At
                                    the time of this visit all three regiments of the division were
                                    in the field, and some 50 small ambush type patrols were in
                                    progress. This effort has made the Viet Cong’s food problem a
                                    grave one, has rendered the kidnapping of conscripts most
                                    difficult, is the cause of continued defections, and diminishes
                                    the enemy’s capacity for coordinated offensive operations.</p>
                                <p>The division commander has the taste of blood and is convinced
                                    that he can destroy the Viet Cong forces in his province—or
                                    drive them elsewhere—by the end of the year.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><p>The 23d Division, in Khanh Hoa Province is engaged in a similar
                                    campaign. At the time it was visited the division had two
                                    battalions, broken down into their small component units,
                                    patrolling in the mountainous area in the western part of the
                                    province. They had been continuously at this task for the
                                    preceding 26 days, concentrating on harrying the Viet Cong,
                                    making him move and destroying his resources. It is a well
                                    conceived and fruitfully executed effort. In the 26 day period
                                    they had seized sizeable grain stocks (120 tons), destroyed
                                    crops, bivouac areas and crude weapons shops. They had freed 293
                                    persons from Viet Cong control-people who have hitherto been
                                    terrorized into tilling the Viet Cong fields and bearing their
                                    loads.</p>
                                <p>In all of this, only 26 Viet Cong had so far been killed and six
                                    captured, which seems somewhat disappointing until it is
                                    recalled that the total number of Viet Cong involved is probably
                                    small, and the task of bringing them to bay in the mountains
                                    very difficult. More important, by far, is that patrol and
                                    attack efforts of this type deprive the Viet Cong of his
                                    initiative. So long as he is on the defensive, it is plain that
                                    he cannot attack anyone.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>A similar conclusion was reached concerning an operation in the
                                Delta, where elements of five battalions combed an area where about
                                200 Viet Cong were supposed to be bivouacked. Some 60 were killed,
                                and the disruption created by the operation certainly diminished
                                greatly the capability of those who escaped to do anything offensive
                                for some time to come.</item>
                            <pb facs="0486" n="460" xml:id="pg_460"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>A patrol type operation by an M-113 detachment into hard core Viet
                                Cong territory adjacent to Zone D was a disappointment. By moving
                                into the Viet Cong enclave, the unit struck a raw nerve. It was
                                taking casualties from both mines and snipers, yet little was being
                                done to develop the situation aggressively. At three o’clock on a
                                bright afternoon the troops were already beginning to settle down
                                for the evening, with the soldiers keeping very near to their
                                vehicles-which they clearly regarded more as mobile redoubts than
                                offensive conveyances Despite the demonstrated proximity of the
                                enemy, there were no patrols; no aggressive activity. It will be
                                remarkable if much comes of the operation, other than casualties.
                                The unit commander (a captain) and his US advisor (a captain) had
                                little to say, when questioned, beyond frustrated observations on
                                the elusiveness of the Viet Cong.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The Buddhist Problem</hi></p>
                        <p>The Buddhist matter seems to break cleanly into two separate problems—the
                            question of the metropolitan political maneuverings in Saigon, Hue, etc.
                            and the influence of the Buddhist issue on the actual counterinsurgency
                            campaign.</p>
                        <p>This being essentially a military report, it will be pertinent, in
                            connection with the first element, to state only that the issue is
                            serving as nourishment for all varieties of dissidents, malcontents,
                            king makers and coup plotters, and that some of the most articulate
                            Buddhist Bonzes are probably motivated more by politics than by
                            religious conviction. On this basis it is not likely that the problem
                            will be allowed to reach an early or an agreeable end. The anti-Diemists
                            will not relinquish lightly this Buddha-sent opportunity to attack
                                <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName>’s position.</p>
                        <p>As to whether the affair has affected the war itself, Americans and
                            Vietnamese of all stations were queried, and the nearer to the battle,
                            the less gravely the problem was regarded. There appeared no evidence
                            that the front line counterinsurgency effort has yet been impeded or
                            decelerated at all by the crisis.</p>
                        <p>In Quang Ngai, for instance, the Province Chief-himself a
                            Catholic-handled a group of demonstrators in the capital by inviting
                            them to a free meal. The demonstration collapsed. In Binh Dinh, the
                            commander of the 9th Division (a Buddhist) characterized the problem as
                            regrettable, but one which time would solve.</p>
                        <p>At the same time, several Americans stated that this attitude of
                            detachment in the field could not persist indefinitely; that sooner or
                            later, if the matter is not resolved, the mid-rank military of Buddhist
                            persuasion will begin to worry as to just what they would do if their
                            unit were told to take military action against Buddhist
                            demonstrators.</p>
                        <pb facs="0487" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/>
                        <p>A significant point in this unfortunate matter is that the religious
                            aspect of the issue has a narrower base than public reports might
                            suggest, since the true percentage of practicing Buddhists is smaller
                            than generally represented. These is a tendency to classify all
                            non-Christians as Buddhists. IN fact, many are simple ancestor
                            worshippers in the Chinese tradition, while other major religions are
                            also represented in the country—including Confucianists, Taoists and
                            Moslems. Finally, there 7,000,000 Montagnards, of whom many are
                            animists.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">“Open Arms”—The Amnesty Program<note n="4" xml:id="d207fn4">See <ref target="#d92">Document
                                    92</ref>.</note></hi></p>
                        <p>First thoughts on the amnesty program are usually, “Can the Vietnamese
                            really distinguish between simple refugees and genuine returning Viet
                            Cong Sympathizers?” and “What assurance is there that the returnees will
                            not re-defect to the Communists?”</p>
                        <p>A hint of an answer was found at the Chieu Hoi reindoctrination camp at
                            Than Xa, Quang Ngai Province, where 115 returnees were observed
                            undergoing reindoctrination.</p>
                        <p>The group was mostly men. They had come in voluntarily; some bringing
                            weapons; all bringing intelligence which ultimately they transmitted to
                            our side.</p>
                        <p>About a quarter were hard core Viet Cong. Another quarter were political
                            cadre. The remainder were people who willingly followed the Viet Cong
                            when the hamlet program and widespread military attacks caused the Viet
                            Cong to retire westward from the plains to the mountains.</p>
                        <p>Most of this group were described by the US Sector Advisor as politically
                            astute. They show evidence of having had careful Communist
                            indoctrination. Some are sufficiently articulate to confirm that they
                            were political instructors themselves. There seemed little reason to
                            doubt the word of the Province Chief when he said that these were truly
                            Viet Cong sympathizers and not refugees.</p>
                        <p>There are many reasons given for accepting the amnesty offer (usually
                            received through leaflets), but they are generally polarized around one
                            abstract attitude—disillusionment, and one concrete reality—hunger. In
                            the north, hunger probably leads all the rest, although this is not true
                            in the more fruitful south. Every one of the returnees queried during
                            the visit to the Quang Ngai center got around to talking about food very
                            quickly. They looked hungry, and are in poor physical shape.</p>
                        <p>It is too early to address the second question—whether the returnees will
                            redefect. When asked this question, the tactical zone commander
                            responded in this fashion. The program in Quang Ngai was <pb facs="0488" n="462" xml:id="pg_462"/> begun on 17 December 1962. Since that time
                            823 people have passed through the rehabilitation center and thence
                            returned to their own villages. A check is kept on all of them; none
                            have yet gone back to the Communists.</p>
                        <p>The total number of “Open Arms” returnees—country wide, stands at 11,700.
                            While more surrendered in June than in the preceding two months put
                            together, it is not likely that there will be any vast domino effect.
                            The base is too small. Over 60% of the population are already in
                            strategic hamlets. In a few months the figure will be much higher. So
                            there will actually not be a very great number of people available for
                            the amnesty program to attract.</p>
                        <p>Nevertheless, those who have rallied to the government have already cut
                            in to the Viet Cong logistic support structure, in areas where it badly
                            hurts—food production, porterage and probably most important, native
                            intelligence.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The US Advisory Presence</hi></p>
                        <p>Forty-eight US advisors, from the Saigon level to enlisted men with
                            tactical units, were asked to comment on the US/Vietnamese relationship.
                            Their answers were singularly similar: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“There may be troubles, in this regard, elsewhere; but I have
                                    never had any difficulty at all.”</p>
                                <p>“My counterpart wants me here, and says so often. He takes my
                                    advice.”</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>“We have had our disagreements as to ways and means. Sometimes it takes a
                            week for my advice to sink in; but we have come to understand one
                            another.”</p>
                        <p>Of the forty-eight, none could recall any change in attitude since the
                            subject was raised by Counsellor <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu</persName> two months ago. Several have discussed it candidly
                            with their Vietnamese counterparts. Among these, the general reaction
                            obtained seems to be that the attitude of Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu</persName> is remote from the realities of the
                            war. Apart from this, the warm and respectful advisor/advisee
                            relationship is quite evident. General <persName corresp="#p_HGPD1">Harkins</persName>, in this regard, lays the bulk of the
                            trouble-making proclivity at <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu’s</persName> door; considers <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> not to be an active participant.</p>
                        <p>One point noted frequently by the US advisors relates to language. The
                            more senior Vietnamese commanders speak French, and some have fair
                            English. The junior ones speak only Vietnamese, and struggle with
                            English. Thus, ideally, they point out that we should send senior
                            advisors with skill in French, while the lower ranking advisory
                            personnel should have a basic grounding in Vietnamese before they
                            come.</p>
                        <pb facs="0489" n="463" xml:id="pg_463"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Laos</hi></p>
                        <p>It is not difficult to synthesize the views of US/Vietnamese officialdom
                            in Vietnam on the matter of Laos. They are all agreed on one point’
                            there is a direct and pressing relationship between affairs in the two
                            countries and the worse things go in Laos, the more difficult matters
                            will be in Vietnam.</p>
                        <p>Their viewpoints differ only as to degree. The Saigon <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> representative is unequivocal in his
                            conviction that if Laos falls to the Communists the loss of Vietnam must
                            inevitably follow. General <persName corresp="#p_HGPD1">Harkins</persName> believes that the loss of Laos would render our
                            problem in Vietnam more difficult, but that it would not make a
                            favorable conclusion impossible.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, Vietnamese commanders at all levels speak with feeling of the
                            flow of warlike essentials and key personnel into their country via the
                                <persName corresp="#p_HCM1">Ho Chi Minh</persName> Trail. While
                            generally unable to produce abundant hard evidence of the fact, they
                            still, in recounting their day to day combat experiences, underscore
                            that external influence on the battle—actual and potential—must form a
                            part of every calculation. Certainly, the material flow could be greatly
                            increased, should the Communists choose to do so, particularly were
                            Tchepone, Attopeu and Saravane to come wholly under their control. It is
                            for this reason that there is strong sentiment, on both the US and
                            Vietnamese sides for more covert pressure on the Laos corridor and on
                            North Vietnam.</p>
                        <p rend="center">Miscellaneous Observations</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Visit with the Minister of
                                Defense</hi></p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_THUAN1">Thuan</persName> expressed satisfaction
                            with the growth of offensive military activity, and enthusiasm with
                            President <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName>’s formal approval
                            of 1 July as the beginning of Phase II of the National Campaign.</p>
                        <p>In response to a question as to how the Viet Cong would react to this
                            intensified effort, he responded that, in his judgment, they are already
                            reacting—steadily acquiring forces and material in southern Laos. These,
                            he says, will be used in a powerful attack in the highlands or Quang
                            Ngai, to deal the Vietnamese military a hard blow, which can then be
                            publicized as a basis for seeking a negotiated peace.</p>
                        <p>In this regard, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_THUAN1">Thuan</persName> is
                            quite as alert as any interested American regarding the unfavorable
                            image of the Vietnam war in the US press, and the necessity for getting
                            what he called “the correct story” before the US Congress. Also, like
                            the interested Americans, he was not prepared to offer any dramatic
                            suggestions as to just how to achieve this purpose.</p>
                        <pb facs="0490" n="464" xml:id="pg_464"/>
                        <p>When asked what, in his view, most needed doing to get the National
                            Campaign forward effectively, he responded with three specifics: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Settle the Buddhist problem quickly and completely. (On this
                                    he expressed great determination and at best, restrained
                                    optimism.)</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Undertake numerous small scale incursions into Southern Laos,
                                    for intelligence purposes and to disrupt development of the Viet
                                    Cong logistic mechanism.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>Increase greatly our sabotage, harassment, intelligence and
                                    subversive activities in North Vietnam.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The Vietnamese Organization for
                                Counterinsurgency</hi></p>
                        <p>The Vietnamese have a Special Group (Counterinsurgency) too. They call it
                            the “Interministerial Committee on Strategic Hamlets”. It is chaired by
                            Counsellor <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu</persName>, and includes the
                            heads of all the civil ministries, the Chief of the Joint General Staff
                            and the four Corps Tactical Zone commanders. It has much authority, in
                            both the approval of plans for clear and hold operations and for hamlet
                            development. It supervises execution closely through on-site observation
                            and periodic progress reports.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The Continuity of Viet Cong
                                Strength</hi></p>
                        <p>The intensity of offensive operations is growing steadily, at a cost to
                            the Viet Cong of over 2,000 battle casualties per month. Defections are
                            increasing rapidly—from 200 per month in January to 450 in June. Over
                            60% of the Vietnamese rural population is in strategic hamlets, with a
                            consequent narrowing of the Viet Cong recruitment base. Finally, the
                            “Open Arms” amnesty program is beginning to diminish the number of
                            active Viet Cong sympathizers and supporters.</p>
                        <p>Against this background, it is not surprising to find the Advisory
                            Command’s best estimate of Viet Cong irregular strength to have
                            dropped—from a high of 100,000 to 80,000. The Viet Cong now have less to
                            offer the Vietnamese youth and, to the extent that they must rely on
                            kidnapping to procure replacements, their problem is greatly complicated
                            by the personal security afforded by the strategic hamlet.</p>
                        <p>Regular Viet Cong strength, on the other hand, remains about constant at
                            22,000-25,000. Both the Vietnamese and US authorities questioned were
                            convinced that this strength is maintained largely by infiltration,
                            supplemented by intensive training of selected local cadres.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Reduction in US Forces</hi></p>
                        <p>It was not possible, in this brief visit, to do more than observe and to
                            sample opinion on the subject, at various levels of authority.</p>
                        <p>Observation underscored these realities: <pb facs="0491" n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/>
                            <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>The shooting part of the war is moving to a climax. Our help
                                    for the Vietnamese in logistic and tactical support is thus
                                    probably not susceptible of much reduction in the immediate
                                    future.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>On the other hand, the training effort has passed its climax.
                                    All divisions are organized and re rapidly being trained. The
                                    Civil Guard and Self Defense Corps training programs are also
                                    well advanced; and training of strike forces and similar
                                    paramilitary elements is maturing rapidly. A reduction in the
                                    advisory area is thus a logical prospect.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Discussion of the problem with responsible officers elicited the general
                            reaction that reduction is feasible in both advisory personnel and in
                            the various US staff and administrative support forces. General
                                <persName corresp="#p_HGPD1">Harkins</persName> considers that a
                            reduction of 1,000 men could be accomplished now, without affecting
                            adversely the conduct of the war. About half of the positions vacated,
                            as he sees it, would come as a result of the Vietnamese achieving
                            greater self-sufficiency in training and command matters, with the other
                            half coming from a withdrawal or replacement of US units.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">The Press</hi></p>
                        <p>Very little observed during this visit had any real sensitivity or
                            secrecy. Almost anyone could see it without violating security.</p>
                        <p>This gave rise to the thought that what is needed is a few venturesome
                            newsmen who are willing to forego the comforts of the city, and endure a
                            little mud and discomfort. Those so inclined would be rewarded with a
                            picture of resolution and progress which they would not quickly
                            forget.</p>
                        <p rend="center">Conclusion</p>
                        <p>Almost the whole of this visit was concentrated in the field, observing
                            the people—military and civilian, US and Vietnamese—who are carrying the
                            front line burden. From them the sounds of confidence, achievement and
                            cautious optimism can be plainly heard, and with growing resonance.</p>
                        <p>Military operations are more effective; rural economic progress is
                            manifest; US/Vietnamese coordination is heartening; and the morale of US
                            military forces is classic.</p>
                        <p>Acknowledging that this trip dwelt mainly upon the rural sector;
                            acknowledging further the potential gravity of the political vibrations
                            in Saigon; and recognizing the rapidity with which the situation could
                            be worsened by adverse developments in Laos, the visit still added
                            substance to the view that we are indeed winning the war, that our
                            present course is sound and that, resolutely pursued, it will see the
                            job done.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>