<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-08-27T04:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-08-27T04:00:00-05:00" n="298" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                        <head>298. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Vietnam</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d298fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 15 <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss> VIET-US. Secret; Eyes Only; Limit Distribution.
                                Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss>. Received at
                                11:30 a.m. and relayed to the White House, Office of the Secretary
                                of Defense, and <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> exclusive for
                                principal officers there.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Saigon</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-08-27T17:00:00+08:00">August 27, 1963, 5
                                        p.m.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                        <p>346. <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>. Report of one hour meeting with
                                <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu</persName>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>After exchange of amenities, he called attention to the comment by
                                the Department of State Spokesman on the <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> broadcast<note n="2" xml:id="d298fn2">Apparent
                                    reference to a reply by the Department of State’s Spokesman,
                                    Richard 1. Phillips, to a question posed at a press and radio
                                    news briefing, August 26. <persName corresp="#p_PRC1">Phillips</persName> amplified the <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> broadcast of August 26, Document 287, but
                                    without any reference to U.S. aid being cut off. For text, see
                                        <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current
                                        Documents</hi>, 1963, p. 865.</note> and said that such
                                statements from Washington should stop. He used the French phrase
                                “doivent s’arreter”, which could be translated “must stop”. U.S.
                                statements about Vietnam were accepted at face value by many other
                                governments and U.S. was therefore injuring Vietnam’s standing with
                                foreign countries. He said that Washington should await <pb facs="0678" n="652" xml:id="pg_652"/> my report before making
                                any further comment. Moreover the Washington statement was wholly
                                false as regards the facts, inasmuch as it was the Generals
                                themselves who had specifically demanded the action which had been
                                taken. He thought that the U.S. people talked too much, whereas in
                                Vietnam they did not talk enough.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I said that I did not know the details of the statement, but that
                                there were some things that were very real to me as a man who had
                                spent many years in public life and one of them was that no long
                                range foreign policy could be carried out by the U.S. Government
                                without the support of Congress and public opinion. I said that
                                public opinion in the U.S. was much distressed by the treatment of
                                the Buddhists and statements made in connection therewith. These
                                have greatly complicated the job of the Executive branch of the U.S.
                                Government in aiding Vietnam and that frankly I sympathized with
                                whatever efforts the Executive branch might make to make clear to
                                U.S. public opinion that our Vietnam policy did not involve
                                stultifying ourselves-which would definitely be the case if we
                                underwrote some of <persName corresp="#p_NDNM1">Madame
                                    Nhu’s</persName> statements like “barbecuing the Buddhists” and
                                her last interview with Life which proposed total destruction of
                                    Buddhists.<note n="3" xml:id="d298fn3">For text of the
                                    interview, see Life, August 16, 1963, p. 31.</note> I said I was
                                receiving letters about these statements and asked whether I should
                                say in reply that <persName corresp="#p_NDNM1">Madame Nhu</persName>
                                was not an official person and was speaking only for herself, to
                                which he said that she was a member of the Assembly and was
                                therefore a public person.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>All of this took place in a pleasant conversational tone on both
                                sides.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Other points made by <persName corresp="#p_NHU1">Nhu</persName>:</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>35 percent of the population were not in first class Strategic
                                Hamlets. All of the people would be in Strategic Hamlets of some
                                kind by the end of the year and the guerrilla war would then be
                                over. Perhaps there would then be a conventional war.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>There have been no more suicides since July 20. [?] This was
                                because of the initiative which he had taken. Occidental people
                                should understand that these suicides are brought about within the
                                pagoda where in an atmosphere filled with incense and incantation,
                                an individual is hypnotized, intoxicated and intimidated. This is
                                how suicides are organized. That there have been no more suicides is
                                proof that the measures that have been taken have had effect. He
                                said he had wanted to clear up the matter before my arrival which,
                                he thought, would be on August 26.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>I said it would be very helpful in the U.S. if there could be some
                                dramatic gesture here regarding the liberation of Buddhist
                                prisoners.</item>
                            <pb facs="0679" n="653" xml:id="pg_653"/>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>He said it was now a fact that all the Buddhist prisoners were
                                being released but he wanted this done quietly with the bonze in
                                each area handling this himself and he could not make a dramatic
                                gesture out of it.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>He stressed the importance of winning the guerrilla war in terms
                                of worldwide communist objectives and stressed the fact that he had
                                invented personally the concept of the strategic hamlet.</item>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>When he accompanied me to the door to say goodbye, he said he
                                hoped there would be no more statements out of Washington and I said
                                I hoped there would be no more inflammatory speeches out of
                                Vietnam.</item>
                            <label>11.</label>
                            <item>This is a highly intelligent and effective man, and would be so
                                considered in any country. My guess is that he is ruthless, not
                                wholly rational by our standards and that he is interested above all
                                in survival of himself and family.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1"><hi rend="strong">Lodge</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>