<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-04-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="94" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d94">
                        <head>94. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d94fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> Files. Secret;
                                Controlled Dissem. According to a note on the cover sheet: “The
                                following intelligence organizations participated in the preparation
                                of this estimate: The Central Intelligence Agency and the
                                intelligence organizations of the Departments of State, Defense, the
                                Army, the Navy, the Air Force, and <gloss target="#t_NSA1">NSA</gloss>.” All members of the U.S. Intelligence Board
                                concurred in this estimate on April 17, except the Atomic Energy
                                Commission Representative and the Assistant Director of the Federal
                                Bureau of Investigation, who abstained on the grounds that the
                                subject was outside their jurisdiction. The statement of the problem
                                and the conclusions are also printed in United States-Vietnam
                                Relations, 1945-1967, Book 12, pp. 522-524.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left"><gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 53-63</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-04-17">April 17,
                                    1963</date></hi>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">PROSPECTS IN SOUTH VIETNAM</p>
                        <p rend="center">The Problem</p>
                        <p>To assess the situation and prospects in South Vietnam, with special
                            emphasis upon the military and political factors most likely to affect
                            the counterinsurgency effort.</p>
                        <pb facs="0259" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/>
                        <p rend="center">Conclusions</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>We believe that Communist progress has been blunted and that the
                                situation is improving. Strengthened South Vietnamese capabilities
                                and effectiveness, and particularly US involvement, are causing the
                                Viet Cong increased difficulty, although there are as yet no
                                persuasive indications that the Communists have been grievously
                                hurt. (Paras. 27-28)</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>We believe the Communists will continue to wage a war of
                                attrition, hoping for some break in the situation which will lead to
                                victory. They evidently hope that a combination of military pressure
                                and political deterioration will in time create favorable
                                circumstances either for delivering a coup de grace or for a
                                political settlement which will enable them to continue the struggle
                                on more favorable terms. We believe it unlikely, especially in view
                                of the open US commitment, that the North Vietnamese regime will
                                either resort to overt military attack or introduce acknowledged
                                North Vietnamese military units into the south in an effort to win a
                                quick victory. (Paras. 29-31)</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Assuming no great increase in external support to the Viet Cong,
                                changes and improvements which have occurred during the past year
                                now indicate that the Viet Cong can be contained militarily and that
                                further progress can be made in expanding the area of government
                                control and in creating greater security in the countryside.
                                However, we do not believe that it is possible at this time to
                                project the future course of the war with any <pb facs="0260" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/> confidence. Decisive campaigns have
                                yet to be fought and no quick and easy end to the war is in sight.
                                Despite South Vietnamese progress, the situation remains fragile.
                                (Para. 32)</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>Developments during the last year or two also show some promise of
                                resolving the political weaknesses, particularly that of insecurity
                                in the countryside, upon which the insurgency has fed. However, the
                                government’s capacity to embark upon the broader measures required
                                to translate military success into lasting political stability is
                                questionable. (Paras. 33-35)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>[Here follow 11 pages of discussion of the conclusions outlined
                            above.]</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>32.</label>
                            <item><hi rend="italic">The Outlook</hi>. Whether the Communists are
                                correct in their appraisal will, of course, depend in some measure
                                upon the extent and nature of US involvement, but primarily upon the
                                South Vietnamese response to the developing situation. We do not
                                believe that it is possible at this time to project the future
                                course of the war with any confidence. Despite <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> progress, the situation remains
                                fragile. A series of major Viet Cong successes, should they occur,
                                might have a shattering psychological effect. Nevertheless, the
                                heavy US involvement and close working relationships between US and
                                Vietnamese personnel have fundamentally altered the outlook. Changes
                                and improvements have occurred during the past year which for the
                                first time indicate that the Viet Cong can be contained militarily
                                and that further progress can be made in expanding the area of
                                government control and in creating security in the countryside.
                                However, some areas of Viet Cong control, such as the Mekong delta,
                                will be very difficult to pacify, decisive campaigns have yet to be
                                fought, and no quick and easy end to the war is in sight.</item>
                            <label>33.</label>
                            <item>Developments in the last year or two have also gone some distance
                                in establishing a basis for winning over the peasantry and in
                                improving the efficiency of the military establishment and the
                                civilian bureaucracy. It can, of course, be argued that only a
                                highly centralized regime, single-mindedly dedicated to
                                independence, and placing a heavy emphasis on personal loyalty can
                                cope with the problems of guerrilla warfare. However, we believe
                                that a greater willingness on the part of the regime to enlist the
                                active support of those who have become disaffected or discouraged
                                in the face of <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName>’s
                                techniques of government would considerably speed the reduction of
                                the Viet Cong insurgency.</item>
                            <label>34.</label>
                            <item>Substantial reduction of Viet Cong military power, however, would
                                probably intensify rather than reduce the need for changes in the
                                philosophy and practice of the <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> regime, if revived insurgency were to be
                                precluded and military victory translated into political
                                consolidation. The achievement of physical security in the
                                countryside would in itself satisfy a major political requirement in
                                convincing the peasants of the government’s ability to protect them.
                                But the government must be both willing and able to expand its
                                efforts to bring social, political, and economic improvements to the
                                countryside if the peasant is to recognize a stake in the survival
                                of the government and to be fortified against Communist
                                blandishments. Effective action in this and other fields,
                                particularly with the removal of a substantial US presence at all
                                levels of the government, would almost certainly require a wider
                                participation in the development and implementation of policy and a
                                considerable reduction in the tight, personal control of the
                                bureaucracy.</item>
                            <label>35.</label>
                            <item>On the basis of its past performance, the ability of the <persName corresp="#p_DIEM1">Diem</persName> regime to move willingly and
                                effectively in these directions is questionable, and may become even
                                more so should military victory come within sight. With the removal
                                of the inhibiting effects of an immediate and overwhelming military
                                danger, political stability would be <pb facs="0261" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> greatly threatened if disappointment with the
                                regime’s performance mounted among important sectors of the
                                population and the conviction deepened that legal avenues to change
                                remained blocked.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>[Here follows a map of South Vietnam highlighting principal. areas of
                            insurgency and counterinsurgency activity.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>