<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to  to Mr.
                                Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">132</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-03-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-03-27T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recoA56uMzqjuuRYx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85145447" lcsh-match="exact">Water</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="labor" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091" lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856" lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="neutrality" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195" lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871" lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302" lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-03-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-03-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="132" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 356.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-03-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 27, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I am now to report the result of my
                            conference with Lord Russell at three o’clock yesterday.</p>
                <p>I began by expressing my regret that circumstances seemed to be once more
                            conspiring to embarrass the friendly relations between the two
                            governments. It had been my constant effort ever since I came, so far as
                            I could, to defeat the <pb facs="0223" n="181" xml:id="pg_181"/>
                            machinations of those ill-disposed people whose object had been from the
                            first to sow strife. But late events led me to fear that at last they
                            might gain their point. Of the nature of the present danger I did not
                            know that I could give his lordship a better idea than by laying before
                            him a copy of a letter which had been transmitted to me by one of many
                            active friends of peace in this country as having been lately received
                            by him from a responsible person in London. This would serve to show the
                            nature of the means upon which these desperate rebel conspirators
                            counted to inflame animosities between us.</p>
                <p>I then read the letter, a copy of which I send you with this
                            despatch.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>The object of asking the interview I then explained to be an earnest
                            desire to obtain the active co-operation of her Majesty’s government to
                            prevent the danger growing out of these machinations. Without such
                            action I very much feared they might succeed; for I was now charged with
                            the duty of laying before his lordship a frank statement of the
                            difficulties under which my government labored in consequence of the
                            increasing irritation of the people by reason of the successive accounts
                            of the depredations committed by the two gunboats fitted out from here.
                            My best course, I thought, would be to read to him for his information
                            the despatch on the subject which I had just received, though I was not
                            instructed to do so, nor to leave a copy of it. I then, with his assent,
                            read your No. 505. After I had finished it, I added an expression of my
                            own strong conviction that the measure of issuing letters of marque
                            therein referred to was one very distasteful to the government. I had
                            myself great doubt of its efficacy, not less than of its expediency. In
                            my view it Would rather be like playing into the hands of the common
                            enemy of both countries. But still it was not to be denied that the
                            people in America felt as if they were now suffering from all the
                            effects of war waged from this side of the water whilst their own hands
                            were tied behind them. They very naturally argued that if such
                            operations were to be carried on without any effectual labor to prevent
                            them on the part of the government here, it was about as well to let the
                            game be opened to both sides. I did not give this as conveying my own
                            opinions, but simply to put his lordship in possession of the views held
                            at home. And unless the government and those of us who were disposed to
                            preserve amicable relations were furnished with some evidence of action
                            to prove the determination of her Majesty’s government to exert its
                            power to protect us from the effects of this misconduct of a portion of
                            her own subjects, it seemed impossible to resist the force of this
                            popular reasoning.</p>
                <p>His lordship then went over much of the same ground heretofore taken by
                            him on the nature of the contest and the desire of Great Britain to
                            remain perfectly neutral. He adverted to the action of certain people at
                            Liverpool as of a kind which he had always disapproved, to convince me
                            of which he referred to his letter of last year, which had, he said,
                            excited much dissatisfaction among them. I replied by reminding his
                            lordship of the fact, as shown in the published diplomatic
                            correspondence, that I had endeavored to give full credit at home to
                            that letter. But the difficulty now was that we needed something more
                            like evidence of efforts to prevent threatened evils.</p>
                <p>His lordship said that the government was sincerely desirous to do all it
                            could. Any attempt to go beyond the law would only end in
                            disappointment. They had carefully consulted on the matter, had examined
                            their powers, and were ready to exert them to the utmost. He had made
                            some explanation of his. views in the speech he had made on Monday
                            evening. He had since received a note from Lord Palmerston expressing
                            his approbation of every word of that speech.</p>
                <p>I said that I also had been much gratified in reading that speech. It
                            would be regarded in America as altogether the most friendly which
                            emanated from his lordship since the beginning of the troubles. Had the
                            same sentiments been <pb facs="0224" n="182" xml:id="pg_182"/> expressed
                            then we should not have been where we now are. I must also add that I
                            should be highly gratified in writing home the substance of what he had
                            said of Lord Palmerston.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>What was much needed in America was not solely evidence of action to
                            prevent these armaments. It was the moral power that might be extended
                            by the ministry in signifying its utter disapproval of all the
                            machinations of the conspirators against the public peace. Hitherto the
                            impression was quite general, as well in America as in this country,
                            that the ministry held no common sentiment, and were quite disposed to
                            be tolerant of all the labors of these people, if not indifferent to
                            them. Here they were absolutely sustaining the rebels in the prosecution
                            of the war, by the advance of money, of ships, and of all the
                            necessaries with which to carry it on as well by sea as on the land; and
                            upon such notorious offences ministers had never yet given out any other
                            than an uncertain sound. The effect of this must be obvious. It
                            encouraged the operations of British instigators of the trouble on this
                            side, who believed that they were connived at, and so believing carried
                            on their schemes with new vigor; whilst, on the other, it confirmed the
                            popular impression in America that the government policy was really at
                            heart hostile, and therefore should be met in a corresponding spirit.
                            These were the views commonly held as they appeared to me from the
                            calmest consideration I could give to the whole subject. I regretted
                            them the more that I believed they were founded in a mistake, which
                            might lead to very bad consequences. I should do what I could in
                            deprecating any present resort to so doubtful a remedy as that of
                            issuing letters of marque.</p>
                <p>There was a strong and a growing popular sentiment throughout the kingdom
                            which might be relied upon partially to counteract the dangers which I
                            feared. But I could not too earnestly beg his lordship at this crisis to
                            think of the value that would in this sense attach to any unequivocal
                            expression by persons in high authority of their condemnation of all
                            enterprises in violation of the neutrality of this kingdom, now
                            projected or in process of execution, within it limits.</p>
                <p>His lordship’s tone throughout this conversation was unequivocally
                            friendly, and I thought him not unimpressed by the earnestness of my
                            representations. He went so far at one time as to express regret at the
                            failure to prevent the departure of the two privateers. But he evidently
                            considered it as a misfortune rather than a fault, which should be now
                            repaired by us through the application of our “vast resources” to the
                            capture of the offenders, He wondered that we had not done so. I replied
                            that it was not for want of effort. But it should be remembered that
                            this was a somewhat novel kind of warfare on the ocean. It consisted of
                            depredation on the innocent and the unarmed, and running away from the
                            strong and those prepared for defence.</p>
                <p>The gunboats were known to be very fast vessels. The great improvement
                            made in steam navigation had given facilities for this kind of piracy
                            never before known, especially in favor of those who had nothing to
                            lose, and against those who had commerce spread over every sea. I then
                            gently reminded him that no nation would take more chances against
                            itself by tolerating such a practice than Great Britain. A concentrated
                            effort made to surprise its navigation in remote portions of the globe
                            might sweep half of it away before it had time to turn round and lay its
                            hand on the right instruments to use for prevention, and then it would
                            have the task before it of a wide and long chase after an offender swift
                            to escape his punishment.</p>
                <p>Having disposed of this matter, I next turned to the subject of the joint
                            resolutions of Congress on foreign intervention, and agreeably to your
                            instructions, contained in the printed circular of the 9th March. I
                            offered to read them to his lordship, or to leave a copy, as he might
                            prefer. He said that Lord Lyons had already sent a copy of them, which
                            he had read. His opinion on that subject was sufficiently known. He
                            would, therefore, take a copy, which I accordingly <pb facs="0225" n="183" xml:id="pg_183"/> put into his hands. Lastly, I alluded to a
                            letter which had been sent to me from a respectable person at Liverpool,
                            an earnest friend of peace and good will, urging me to suggest the
                            propriety of prosecuting the parties known to have been connected with
                            the outfit of the gunboats in Liverpool.</p>
                <p>I said that I should not be unwilling to recommend my government to
                            initiate any suitable form of proceedings if necessary, and if with the
                            slightest hope of success in procuring conviction. I thought it no more
                            than proper to present the subject to his lordship’s consideration. He
                            said he would think of it, and take advice. Should it appear that
                            anything effectual could be done he would let me know.</p>
                <p>I have by no means reported the whole of this conversation, which lasted
                            more than an hour. The conclusion which I draw from it is, that the
                            government is really better disposed to exertion, and feels itself
                            better sustained for action by the popular sentiment than ever before. *
                            * * *</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-03-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">March</hi>
                                    20</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> You are doubtless aware that the money
                                received from the confederate loan is to be applied to the payment
                                of sundry vessels building for the confederate government at sundry
                                English ports, which vessels are to be got to sea at any cost, the
                                south believing that the irritation caused by the depredations of
                                the Alabama, increased by the departure of other vessels under
                                similar circumstances, will force on a war between Great Britain and
                                the United States, and thus secure independence to the south, and to
                                the subscribers to the loan their cotton.</p>
                    <p>I have this view, in writing, from one who says he was the party who
                                first suggested to Messrs J. H. Schneder &amp; Co. to take up the
                                loan, (all of which I mention to you in confidence,) seeing the tone
                                and style lately adopted by Earl Russell on the American question,
                                and particularly in his correspondence with Mr. Adams, and the
                                apparent apathy of our government and people. I must own I firmly
                                believe that we shall drift into a war with the United States. A
                                further departure of Alabamas from our ports would, I believe, fan
                                irritation into a flame, and <hi rend="italic">they will</hi>
                                depart, and <hi rend="italic">very</hi> soon, unless the most
                                determined and energetic action is <hi rend="italic">at once</hi>
                                adopted by our government. I say so advisedly.</p>
                    <p>Can you not take measures to have the subject <hi rend="italic">continually, importunately</hi> ventilated in Parliament. As
                                the friend of the slave, as the advocate of constitutional liberty,
                                as a lover of your own country, I, a stranger, venture to call your
                                immediate attention to this subject. I know more than I can in honor
                                tell.</p>
                    <p>Begging to apologize for troubling you with this communication, I am,
                                yours faithfully,</p>
                    <p rend="right">—— ——.</p>
                    <p>I beg you, if you make any use, in any way, of this communication to
                                withhold my name, as my social relations with many confederate
                                gentlemen have been of years standing.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
