<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-07-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-07-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="236" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d236">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Adams</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 655.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-07-14"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 14, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> We have advices from Port Hudson of the 3d
                            of July. The siege was then vigorously maintained, and there is reason
                            to believe that re-enforcements, if thought necessary, have since been
                            supplied by General Grant. The 8th of July gave us our last intelligence
                            from Vicksburg, and it enables me to correct some of the details of the
                            results of the capitulation contained in my recent telegram. More than
                            twenty-seven thousand (27,000) prisoners had already then been paroled,
                            and the task was not yet completed. There were found in various parts of
                            the city, concealed and otherwise, sixty-six thousand (66,000) stands of
                            small arms, and still new searches discovered new deposits of the same
                            sort. The whole amount of ordnance captured, including siege and sea
                            coast guns, exceeded two hundred (200.) The supply of ammunition
                            surpasses belief. It would have sufficed for six years of defence, if
                            used at the rate that it was consumed during the siege. The military
                            stores, chiefly clothing for soldiers, is estimated at five millions of
                            dollars, insurrectionary currency. General Sherman was in hot pursuit of
                            Johnson’s forces.</p>
                        <p>The insurgent army, under Bragg, has been driven out of Tennessee into
                            Alabama.</p>
                        <p>Rear-Admiral Dahlgren was expected to assault Morris island, which is one
                            of the defences of Charleston, on the 9th.</p>
                        <p>Lee’s insurgent army has retreated before General Meade, and is now under
                            stood to be compactly posted near the fords of the Potomac, and wholly
                            lies between the banks of that river and the Union army. Lee’s losses in
                            the late battles are believed to have been thirty-three thousand
                            (33,000) men. A solution of the problem of invasion is expected hourly,
                            and therefore I refrain from conjecture concerning it.</p>
                        <p>There is some popular disturbance at New York arising out of the draft.
                            The journals of that city, going out by to-morrow’s steamer, will give
                            you, probably, the full development of the movement. At present it does
                            not seem to be formidable, although the occurrence of it is a subject of
                            much regret.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams</hi>, Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>