<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-08-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-08-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="275" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d275">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Adams</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 688.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-08-31"><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 31, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have just returned to this city from an
                            excursion through the State of New York, in company with a large number
                            of the foreign representatives residing near this government. The
                            recreation thus obtained was as needful to myself as to them. The
                            immediate departure of the mails prevents special acknowledgments of
                            such despatches received during my absence, as were thought deserving of
                            my personal attention.</p>
                        <p>The siege of Charleston is proceeding with apparent success. The
                            movements of General Rosecrans and General Burnside, in their operations
                            with regard to East Tennessee, are as difficult as they are important.
                            Our information from them is satisfactory. The interests of the Union in
                            Texas are not overlooked.</p>
                        <p>You will have already learned that the expectations of the insurgents
                            which were built on a riot in New York, such as often happens in all
                            great cities, have been disappointed. The re-enforcement of the army and
                            the increase of the navy are going on with all reasonable success. The
                            riot proceeded upon a false assumption of interested persons that the
                            country was wearied and exhausted by this unfortunate civil war. It is
                            now perceived that it as prosperous and as strong as it has been at any
                            former period of its history. It desires peace, but not
                            immoderately.</p>
                        <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Francis Adams</hi>, Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c</hi>.</p>
                            <p>Same to Messrs. Dayton, Clay, Pike, and Koerner.</p>
                        </postscript>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>