<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-09-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="287" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d287">
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Extracts.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>.</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#left">No. 492.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,
                                        <hi rend="italic">London</hi>,</placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-09-08"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 8, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> At the last moment on Saturday I sent you
                            a despatch by the ordinary mail, containing a copy of Lord Russell’s
                            note to me of the 4th instant, just then put into my hands, signifying
                            that the decision of the government, announced in his previous note of
                            the 1st instant, had, under the effect of my notes of the 3d instant,
                            and former dates, been subjected to a reconsideration. It is proper now
                            to add, that just before the reception of this I had prepared and
                            despatched another one in reply to the previous note of the 1st instant,
                            which I then supposed to be final. A copy of this, which there was no
                            time to make on Saturday, I now transmit. I need not say, that had I
                            known of the latter course of the government in season, I should have
                            held it back. Feeling as I do the heavy responsibility that must devolve
                            upon me in the conduct of this critical transaction, it is not my
                            disposition to say or do the least thing that may add to the
                            difficulties inevitably growing out of it between the countries. * * * *
                            Considering the grave nature of the issue, I have <pb facs="0460" n="418" xml:id="pg_418"/> thought it wiser not to give any handle to
                            the pretence that resort to intimidation had been attempted. At the same
                            time, I have endeavored to convey, in its full sense, what I believe to
                            be the feeling excited in both the government and people of the United
                            States, by the extraordinary and unjustifiable violations of neutrality
                            continually permitted in this kingdom, of which the latest is the
                            crowning instance</p>
                        <p>In regard to the allegations made in the public prints, to which the
                            crown lawyers seem to have been disposed to attach consequence, of
                            possible ownership of these vessels either by France or Egypt, I ought,
                            perhaps, to have mentioned, that on application through Mr. Dayton, in
                            Paris, and to Mr. Musums, the Turkish ambassador at this court, I had
                            obtained satisfactory evidence of their falsehood.</p>
                        <p>Since commencing this despatch I have received a note from Lord Russell,
                            a copy of which, as also of my reply, is transmitted. I had been
                            somewhat prepared for the intelligence it conveys by the appearance in
                            the <hi rend="italic">Post</hi> of this morning of an article bearing an
                            official aspect, to the same effect. Under the peculiar circumstances
                            attending the case, and the heavy responsibility which the ministry has
                            assumed in taking this course, I trust I may be pardoned for suggesting
                            the expediency of as much caution and forbearance as possible in the
                            treatment of the subject in America.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Earl Russell</persName>.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States</hi>, <hi rend="italic">London</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-09-05"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 5, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: At this moment, when one of the
                                iron-clad vessels is on the point of departure from this kingdom, on
                                its hostile errand against the United States, I am honored with the
                                reply of your lordship to my notes of the 11th, 16th and 25th of
                                July, and of the 14th of August. I trust I need not express how
                                profound is my regret at the conclusion to which her Majesty’s
                                government have arrived. I can regard it no otherwise than as
                                practically opening to the insurgents free liberty in this kingdom
                                to execute a policy described in one of their late publications in
                                the following language:</p>
                            <p>“In the present state of the harbor defences of New York, Boston,
                                Portland, and smaller northern cities, such a vessel as the Warrior
                                would have little difficulty in entering any of these ports and
                                inflicting a vital blow upon the enemy. The destruction of Boston
                                alone would be worth a hundred victories in the field. It would
                                bring such a terror to the ‘blue-noses,’ as to cause them to wish
                                eagerly for peace, despite their overweening love of gain which has
                                been so freely administered to since the opening of this war.
                                Vessels of the Warrior class would promptly raise the blockade of
                                our ports, and would even, in this respect, confer advantages which
                                would soon repay the cost of their construction.”</p>
                            <p>It would be superfluous in me to point out to your lordship that this
                                is war. No matter what may be the theory adopted of neutrality in a
                                struggle, when this process is carried on in the manner indicated,
                                from a territory and with the aid of the subjects of a. third party,
                                that third party to all intents and purposes ceases to be neutral.
                                Neither is it necessary to show, that any government which suffers
                                it to be done fails in enforcing the essential conditions of
                                international amity towards the country against whom the hostility
                                is directed. In <pb facs="0461" n="419" xml:id="pg_419"/> my belief
                                it is impossible that any nation, retaining a proper degree of
                                self-respect, could tamely submit to a continuance of relations so
                                utterly deficient in reciprocity. I have no idea that Great Britain
                                would do so for a moment.</p>
                            <p>After a careful examination of the full instructions with which I
                                have been furnished, in preparation for such an emergency, I deem it
                                inexpedient for me to attempt any recurrence to arguments for
                                effective interposition in the present case Under these
                                circumstances, I prefer to desist from communicating to your
                                lordship even such further portions of my existing instructions as
                                are suited to the case, lest I should contribute to aggravate
                                difficulties already far too serious. I therefore content myself
                                with informing your lordship that I transmit, by the present
                                steamer, a copy of your note for the consideration of my government,
                                and shall await the more specific directions that will be contained
                                in the reply.</p>
                            <p>I seize this opportunity to pray permission of your lordship to
                                correct a clerical error inadvertently made in my note of the 3d
                                instant, in inserting the date of two notes of mine as having
                                received the express approbation of my government. The intention was
                                to specify only one, that of the 11th of July. The correction is not
                                material, excepting as it conforms more strictly to the truth.</p>
                            <p>I pray your lordship to accept the assurances of the highest
                                consideration with which I have the honor to be, my lord, your most
                                obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Right Honorable <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl Russell</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Earl Russell</persName>.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United
                                            States</hi>, <hi rend="italic">London</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-09-09"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 9, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge
                                the reception of your lordship’s note of yesterday, announcing the
                                determination of her Majesty’s government to prevent the departure
                                of the war vessels now fitting out at Liverpool. I shall take great
                                pleasure in transmitting a copy for the information of my
                                government.</p>
                            <p>I have the honor to be, my lord, your most obedient servant,</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>CHAELES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>The Right Honorable <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl Russell</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi></p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Earl Russell</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Adams</persName>.</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Foreign Office</hi>,</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-09-08"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 8, 1863.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p>Lord Russell presents his compliments to Mr. Adams, and has the honor
                                to inform him that instructions have been issued which will prevent
                                the departure of the two iron-clad vessels from Liverpool.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#center">[From the Morning Post of <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-09-08">September
                                    8</date>.]</dateline></opener>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">El Toussoun and El Monassir.</hi></head>
                            <p>“The first exploit of these two vessels of war, which have now almost
                                arrived at completion in Mr. Laird’s building yard, will be to run
                                the home blockade of legal difficulties before they are allowed to
                                proceed on their destined career, whatever that may be. Whether they
                                can successfully navigate the channel <pb facs="0462" n="420" xml:id="pg_420"/> beset with shoals and rocks through which the
                                Alexandra was steered remains to be seen. There is now, we believe,
                                little doubt that, under the terms of the foreign enlistment act,
                                they are to be detained by government. The allegation against them
                                is that they are fitted out for the purpose of carrying on
                                hostilities against the United States. On the other hand, it is
                                contended that they were built by order of a French house for the
                                late Pasha of Egypt, who gave the firm a commission for the coinage
                                of a large sum of money in France, and for the construction of two
                                steam-rams in England. The money was duly coined and received in
                                Egypt. The vessels were in course of construction when the Pasha
                                died, and his successor repudiated that part of the contract. What
                                the French house intends to do with them is not known. The
                                accusation is, that they are destined for war with a friendly power.
                                They will consequently be detained, and a court of law will
                                determine whether, under the terms of the foreign enlistment act,
                                the detention is legal, or whether the owners can recover them from
                                the hands of the government.”</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>