<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lord Lyons to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d399</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">399</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-02-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-02-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-02-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-02-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="399"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d399">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Lord Lyons</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-02-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 21, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to call your attention to the
                    enclosed copy of a letter addressed to me on the 12 instant by Mr. J. M. Vernon.
                    I received a copy of the letter from her Majesty’s consul at New York the day
                    before yesterday, but the original has not yet reached me.</p>
                <p>Mr. Vernon states that he is a British subject; that he was a passenger on board
                    the steamer Huntress, bound for Nassau, which was burned at sea, thirty miles
                    from Charleston harbor; that he, with the crew of the Huntress, took to their
                    boats, and that they were picked up at sea by the United States ship Quaker City
                    on the 18th of January last; that he himself was afterwards detained on board
                    various United States vessels, and that he has finally been sent as a prisoner
                    to Fort Lafayette. He demands that his case be investigated, if there be any
                    charge against him, or that he be immediately set at liberty.</p>
                <p>Her Majesty’s consul at New York informs me that he finds, on inquiry, that Mr.
                    Vernon is a British subject, born at Liverpool, and not naturalized in the
                    United States. I therefore deem it my duty to recommend the case to your
                    immediate consideration.</p>
                <p>I have the honor, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>LYONS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <pb facs="0556" n="514" xml:id="pg_514"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Vernon</persName> to <persName type="to">Lord
                            Lyons</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Fort Lafayette</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-02-12">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 12, 1863.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: I beg leave to place before your lordship
                        the facts pertaining to my incarceration, and would most respectfully ask
                        your lordship, as United States minister of her Britannic Majesty, to have
                        the matter investigated, and that I may be set at liberty.</p>
                    <p>I am a subject of Great Britain, and have commercial relations and personal
                        interests in New Orleans, Memphis, and the State of Georgia. I have been in
                        England and the continent (except about three months) from 1858 to 1861. I
                        returned to this country to protect my interests, and pursue my legitimate
                        busi-of importing and exporting, and to protect my interest. My business and
                        interests called me to London, and I took passage in the steamer Huntress,
                        (bound for Nassau,) which was burned at sea, thirty miles off Charleston
                        harbor. It was blowing almost a gale when we took to our boats, saving
                        nothing but the clothes on our backs. We were four hours in the boats, and
                        we were picked up as castaways at sea, on the 18th of January last, by the
                        Quaker City, United States navy. We were detained on board this ship and the
                        Powhattan until the 26th of January, when we were transferred to the Vermont
                        at Helen Head, and then to the United States steamship Circassian, of United
                        States navy, bound for New York. We were detained at Helen Head six days,
                        and arrived at Fortress Monroe on the 2d of February, at which place I wrote
                        to your lordship, and also demanded my release, or to be sent to Washington,
                        which was refused.</p>
                    <p>We arrived in New York on the 8th instant; was detained on board until the
                        10th instant. I was then taken before the United States marshal, who asked
                        me “who I was, and where born;” who peremptorily ordered me to the “house of
                        detention.” On the 11th instant a gentleman called for me, then asked my
                        name, age, nationality, &amp;c. When given, I told him I had written to the
                        marshal, and requested that I be taken before the British consul; that I was
                        a British subject, and had been deprived of my liberty long enough; and that
                        if the United States government had anything against me, I desired to know,
                        and have the matter investigated. He told me all that would have his
                        attention, and that he had a special despatch from Washington in relation to
                        me. I learned afterwards that this was Mr. Murray, United States marshal.
                        About an hour after this interview officers arrived and took me to this
                        fort, with a fellow passenger, the captain of steamer, and three
                        engineers.</p>
                    <p>I am here without any clothing save what I have worn since my capture.</p>
                    <p>I am confined, for what offence I know not, being picked up in an open boat,
                        struggling for life as an outcast at sea, saved as a case of humanity, and
                        now treated as a condemned prisoner in a United States fortress, without any
                        trial whatsoever,</p>
                    <p>As a non-combatant, pursuing my own legitimate business, and owing to neither
                        belligerents any allegiance whatever, I have been by force deprived of
                        liberty, and even the necessary commodities pertaining to the wardrobe of a
                        gentleman.</p>
                    <p>I do sincerely ask your lordship that this matter may be placed before the
                        honorable Secretary of State at Washington, and that I be removed to
                        Washington for investigation, should the United States government have any
                        charges to prefer against me, or that I be immediately set at liberty.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>J. M. VERNON.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Lyons.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>P. S.—I would also state that I am the commercial and financial
                            correspondent of the <hi rend="italic">Times, Telegraph</hi> and <hi
                                rend="italic">Economist</hi>, London.</p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
