<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lord Lyons to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d481</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">481</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-04-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-04-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-04-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="481"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d481">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Lord Lyons</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-04-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 27, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    the note dated the day before yesterday, in which, in answer to my inquiries
                    respecting the British steamship Granite City, you have done me the honor to
                    inform me that that ship has <pb facs="0621" n="579" xml:id="pg_579"/> been
                    transferred to the United States navy, pursuant to an offer of the head of the
                    Navy Department to receive her at a valuation of fifty-five thousand
                    dollars.</p>
                <p>With regard to the general principles involved in this transaction, I will at
                    this moment content myself with referring you to the note which I had the honor
                    to address you on the 31st December last, and, waiving for the present any
                    further discussion of those principles, will now merely ask you for some
                    additional information respecting the proceedings in the case of the Granite
                    City.</p>
                <p>It would seem from the papers before me, that the ship was transferred to the
                    Navy Department by the court, as a matter of course, on the motion of the United
                    States district attorney. It does not appear whether the representatives of the
                    owners were heard, either on the question of making the transfer, or on that of
                    fixing the value of the vessel; nor, indeed, whether in any stage of the
                    proceedings, an opportunity was offered for defending the interests of the
                    owners. I shall, therefore, be very much obliged if you will do me the honor to
                    furnish me with information on these points.</p>
                <p>I desire, as I have already intimated, to avoid entering in the present note upon
                    a discussion of general principles; but my earnest desire to guard beforehand
                    against everything likely to lead to difficulty, or irritating questions,
                    induces me to take this opportunity of begging you to consider the unfavorable
                    impression which must, especially in important cases, be produced, if captured
                    vessels, not condemned by any prize court, be appropriated by the Navy
                    Department, without regard to the interests of the owners, and solely on the
                    ground that they are suited to the naval service of the United States.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, you most obedient,
                    humble servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>LYONS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
