<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lord Lyons to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d485</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">485</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-04-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recXXD3sj2iBEhNCv" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-04-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-04-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="485"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d485">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Lord Lyons</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>,</placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-04-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 29, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I think it right to submit to the government of
                    the United States the authenticated copy, which I enclose herewith, of a protest
                    made before her Majesty’s acting consul-general at Havana, by the master, the
                    mate, the chief engineer, and the purser, of the British steamship Dolphin,
                    which appears to have been captured by the United States ship Wachusetts, in a
                    voyage from Liverpool to Nassau.</p>
                <p>There is much in the protest that seems to call for your serious consideration.
                    Among the points to which I will ask your particular attention is the allegation
                    that the chief engineer was put in irons for more than twenty-four hours by
                    order of the prize officer.</p>
                <p>I beg you to be so good as to send me back the authenticated copy of this
                    protest.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, you most obedient,
                    humble servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>LYONS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Secretary
                            of State, &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>{<hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate Seal, Cuba</hi>.}</head>
                    <p>Know all men by this public instrument of protest, that on the 1st day of
                        April, A. D. 1863, at the office of the British consulate at Havana, before
                        me, John Vincent Crawford, esquire, her Britannic Majesty’s acting
                        consul-general in Cuba, <pb facs="0623" n="581" xml:id="pg_581"/> presonally
                        appeared Richard H. Eustice, the master; Vincent Lazzole, the mate; William
                        Jenkinson, chief engineer; and Frederick Joseph Banning, the purser; all of
                        and belonging to the steamship Dolphin, of Liverpool, official number 3,150,
                        and being severally sworn upon the Holy Evangelists of Almighty God,
                        declared that they, on board the said vessel, she then being tight, staunch,
                        and strong, well fitted and provisioned, and being in every respect complete
                        for their then intended voyage, and being laden with a cargo of general
                        merchandise, got up steam and departed from Liverpool on the 10th day of
                        February last, and proceeded on their voyage towards Nassau, New Providence,
                        via Madeira and St. Thomas, at which places they were to call for a supply
                        of coal. That nothing particular occurred until their departure from St.
                        Thomas, on the 24th March. Next morning at daylight, when in sight of Porto
                        Rico, they saw a steamer on the starboard bow bearing down upon them. They
                        immediately hoisted their ensign. Shortly afterwards a shot was observed to
                        fall near the starboard side, although no report was heard. The engines were
                        instantly stopped, several shots being fired by the stranger. Upon her
                        coming close to, they observed that she was a vessel-of-war of the United
                        States, and they were then boarded by an armed boat from the said vessel,
                        which proved to be the Wachusetts. The boarding officer demanded the ship’s
                        papers, which were given to him immediately, and after examining them he
                        mustered the crew, in spite of Captain Eustice’s protest. He then went to
                        the Wachusetts, and returned with an armed force, which took possession of
                        the ship, and forcibly sent ten of the crew into his boat, arresting Captain
                        Eustice, and obliging him to go with the ten men on board the Wachusetts,
                        simultaneously hauling down the British flag and hoisting that of the United
                        States in its place. In about three quarters of an hour afterwards Captain
                        Eustice was brought back to the ship, accompanied by an officer and about
                        twenty men. The Dolphin’s crew was again mustered, and ordered on board the
                        Wachusetts, with the exception of the master, the chief mate, the purser,
                        chief engineer, the steward, the cook, and the leading fireman. The
                        Wachusetts then left them, and the Dolphin was taken charge of by Mr.
                        Muldam, the prize officer, and proceeded towards Key West; an order being
                        issued prohibiting any of the Dolphin’s people from going to the compass,
                        under penalty of being shot. At 8 a.m., on the 26th March, Captain Eustice
                        discovered that his charts and chronometer were missing. It was also
                        discovered that during the night the fore hold had been broken into, and a
                        quantity of champagne, being part of the cargo, taken and consumed. On the
                        28th March, about 6 a.m., Jenkinson, the chief engineer, was put in double
                        irons, by order of the prize officer, no reason being given, and in spite of
                        Captain Eustice protesting against such violence. At 11 a.m., on the 29th,
                        the irons were taken off Mr. Jenkinson. At 7 p.m. he was locked up a
                        prisoner, in his room, for the night. The vessel having run short of fuel,
                        put into this port this morning, the master immediately reporting the
                        circumstances of this unwarrantable seizure of his vessel at this office,
                        and requesting to enter his protest. And whereas the said steamship Dolphin
                        was legally cleared at Liverpool for Nassau, and was bound upon her
                        legitimate voyage to that port when fallen in with, boarded and seized, in
                        the manner aforesaid, by the said Wachusetts, in direct contravention of the
                        laws of nations and the rights of neutrals :</p>
                    <p>Therefore, the said appearers desire to protest, and by these presents do
                        most solemnly protest, against the captain, officers, and crew of the United
                        States ship-of-war Wachusetts, and against the government of the United
                        States of America, under whose orders the said captain, officers, and crew
                        are acting, for the unjust, arbitrary, and piratical detention and seizure
                        of their vessel, the Dolphin, and her cargo, whilst on the prosecution of
                        her legitimate voyage from one neutral port to another, and for all losses,
                        damages, and averages, which may be consequent thereon, for these appearers
                        swear that all such is owing to the unjustifiable <pb facs="0624" n="582"
                            xml:id="pg_582"/> seizure and detention as aforesaid, not by reason of
                        any defect or insufficiency of the said ship Dolphin, or neglect or
                        impropriety of the master or crew.</p>
                    <p rend="right">R. H. EUSTICE, <hi rend="italic">Master.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="right">VINCENT LAZZOLE, <hi rend="italic">Mate.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="right">WILLIAM JENKINSON, <hi rend="italic">Chief Engineer.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="right">F. J. BANNING, <hi rend="italic">Purser.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Signed and sworn to before me,</p>
                    <p rend="right">JOHN V. CRAWFORD, <hi rend="italic">Acting Consul-general,
                            Cuba.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>A true copy.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN V. CRAWFORD.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
