<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Lord Lyons..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d582</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">582</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recHw6HPyWWByz7Kd" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046277"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Execution</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                    <term ref="reccab053b473a4a56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="world-war-i" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148236" lcsh-match="exact">Munitions of war</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="582"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d582">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Lord
                        Lyons</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-07-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 1, 1863.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: Adverting to your note of the 24th ultimo, in
                    which, to the refusal of the custom-house authorities at New York to grant a
                    clearance to the brig John Freeman, with cattle on board, you ask for
                    information as to the grounds of the prohibition of the exportation of cattle. I
                    have the honor to enclose you the copy of a communication of yesterday,
                    addressed to this department by the Secretary of the Treasury.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be your very obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Right Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord Lyons.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Chase</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Seward</persName>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Treasury Department,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-06-30">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 30, 1863.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have received your note of the 26th
                        instant, inviting my attention to an enclosed copy of a communication of the
                        24th instant, from Lord Lyons, in relation to the refusal of a clearance for
                        the brig John Freeman, with cattle on board, and for information as to the
                        grounds of the prohibition of the exportation of cattle.</p>
                    <pb facs="0701" n="659" xml:id="pg_659"/>
                    <p>In reply, I beg leave to transmit copies of an order made by the President of
                        the United States in relation to the exportation of arms, ammunition, and
                        munitions of war, and of a communication from the Secretary of War, from
                        which it appears that the prohibition extended to the exportation of live
                        stock. I also enclose a copy of a letter from me to the Secretary of War in
                        relation to proposed exceptions from the operation of the order.</p>
                    <p>Lord Lyons correctly states that the refusal to clear the John Freeman has
                        been the subject of some informal correspondence between him and myself, and
                        it is proper to say that I conferred, also informally, with the President in
                        respect to permitting the clearance desired, and that the President, after
                        consulting with the Secretary of War, declined to grant such permission.</p>
                    <p>The clearance referred to was refused in obedience to this prohibition. For
                        the grounds of it I respectfully refer you to the President and Secretary of
                        War.</p>
                    <p>With great respect,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>S. P. CHASE, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Treasury.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">A.</note>
                        <head>
                            <persName type="from">Mr. Stanton</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Chase</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">War Department,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington City, D. C.</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-20">
                                    <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 20, 1863.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to enclose herewith a
                            copy of an executive order made by the President this day, and filed in
                            this department, and would request you to give such orders as may
                            prevent the prohibited clearances at New York and elsewhere.</p>
                        <p>Yours, truly,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>EDWIN M. STANTON, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of War.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">S. P. Chase,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Treasury.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Executive Mansion,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington City,</hi>
                                </placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1862-11-20">
                                    <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 20, 1862.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">Ordered,</hi> That no arms, ammunition, or munitions
                            of war be cleared or allowed to be exported from the United States until
                            further order; that any clearances for arms, ammunition, or munitions of
                            war, issued heretofore by the Treasury Department, be vacated, if the
                            articles have not passed without the United States, and the articles
                            stopped; that the Secretary of War hold possession of the arms recently
                            seized by his order at Rouse’s Point, bound for Canada.</p>
                        <p rend="right">ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
                        <p>The foregoing is a true copy of an executive order this day filed by the
                            President in the War Department.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>EDWIN M. STANTON, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of War.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <pb facs="0702" n="660" xml:id="pg_660"/>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">B.</note>
                        <head>
                            <persName type="from">Mr. Stanton</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Chase</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">War Department,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington City, D. C.</hi>
                                </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-05-19">
                                    <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 19,1863.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to enclose herewith a
                            copy of an order of this department, designed to enforce the executive
                            order of November 21, 1862, against sundry persons engaged in purchasing
                            horses and mules for exportation.</p>
                        <p>I would respectfully request the co-operation of your department.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, very respectfully, your obedient servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>EDWIN M. STANTON, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of War.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">S. P. Chase,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Treasury.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>
                            <persName type="from">Mr. Stanton</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Chase</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">War Department,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Washington City, D. C.,</hi>
                                </placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-05-13">
                                    <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 13, 1863.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Information has been received by this department that sundry persons are
                            purchasing horses and mules within the United States for exportation,
                            contrary to the executive order of. November 21, 1862. To the end that
                            during the present war the military resources of this government should
                            not be withdrawn from the country, the commandants of departments are
                            directed to prohibit the purchase and sale of all horses and mules,
                            within the limits of their respective commands, to be exported from the
                            United States, and to take and appropriate to the use of the government
                            any horses, mules, and live stock designed for exportation, causing the
                            value thereof to be appraised and reported to the quartermaster general;
                            and they are enjoined vigilantly to enforce the executive order of
                            November 21, 1862, prohibiting the exportation of arms, ammunition, or
                            munitions of war.</p>
                        <p>Claims for property taken under this order will be presented to the
                            quartermaster general for adjustment.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>EDWIN M. STANTON, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of War.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">S. P. Chase.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <head>
                            <persName type="from">Mr. Chase</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Stanton</persName>.</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Treasury Department,</hi>
                                </placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-06-02">
                                    <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 2, 1863.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have received your letter of the 25th
                            ultimo, returning to this department the application of Messrs.
                            Stetheimer and Altman for permission to export certain rifled muskets to
                            Hamburg, and suggesting that, while the President’s order of November
                            21, 1862, continued in force, it is not competent for the War
                            Department, any more than for the Treasury Department, to grant permits
                            for the exportation of prohibited articles, and that it is unnecessary
                            for the Treasury Department to transmit applications like those referred
                            to for the decision of the Secretary of War.</p>
                        <p>I have also received your letter of the 29th ultimo, returning to this
                            department the inquiry of the collector of Boston in relation to
                            permission of the <pb facs="0703" n="661" xml:id="pg_661"/> shipment of
                            a pair of carriage horses to Hayti, and have observed your remark, that
                            you are not aware that this (the war) department has any power not
                            possessed by the Treasury Department to permit the exportation of
                            articles prohibited by the President’s order.</p>
                        <p>The President’s order of November 21, 1862, as construed by the order of
                            the War Department of May 13, 1863, which enjoins the application of its
                            prohibition to the exportation of horses, mules, and live stock, has
                            governed the action of this department. Indeed, immediately on receiving
                            your letter transmitting the last-named order, directions were forthwith
                            and on the same day issued by me to the officers of this department,
                            enjoining vigilance in enforcing its execution.</p>
                        <p>Necessarily, however, many cases have occurred, and must occur, which the
                            interested parties or officers of this department regard as not embraced
                            within the spirit of the rule, though covered by its lefter; and these
                            cases have, in regular course of business, been sent to me. As the whole
                            action of this department has only been auxiliary to yours in this
                            business, I have thought it my duty to transmit these applications for
                            dispensation from the rule to you for consideration. In some cases the
                            dispensation has been allowed, and in others refused; and your decision
                            has governed the action of this department.</p>
                        <p>I now understand you as refusing to entertain any further applications of
                            this character, and shall, of course, refer no more to you. There must,
                            however, be questions touching the scope and permanency of the orders
                            which will need to be settled by some authority. These will be referred
                            directly to the President until further advice from him or yourself.</p>
                        <p>It is my earnest desire, in the administration of this department, to
                            cause no unavoidable inconvience, and to render every possible support
                            to the others, and especially to yours, the vast responsibility and
                            labors of which I understand and appreciate.</p>
                        <p>With great respect,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>S. P. CHASE, <hi rend="italic">Secretary of the Treasury.</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Edwin M. Stanton,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Secretary of War.</hi>
                            </p>
                        </postscript>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
