<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Adams to to Mr. Seward..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1863p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d657</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">657</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1863-11-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1863-11-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85117158"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Sanction</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1863-11-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1863-11-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="657"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d657">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Adams</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 532.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">London,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 6, 1863</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to transmit copies of the
                    Morning Post which contain reports of the proceedings thus far, in the court of
                    exchequer, on the case of the Alexandra, on the question of an appeal from the
                    ruling of the chief baron, at the trial held last spring. It now appears that
                    the chief Baron declines to sign a bill of exceptions because it imputes to him
                    certain legal declarations which he never made, and objects to him that he did
                    not give instructions which he avers were the very ones he did give. As a
                    consequence, a technical barrier was at once raised against further operations,
                    which proved so difficult to remove, that resort was finally had to the
                    extraordinary step of creating a new rule for the purpose of admitting a motion
                    on the part of the government. Thus far the new attorney general seems to have
                    succeeded in forcing his way out of this court. But he has yet some further
                    difficulties to overcome before he can get into the exchequer chamber which,
                    from the intimations made at the opening, would seem to be fully prepared to
                    receive him.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * *</p>
                <p>I am now rather hopeful of a better final result than I was in the spring. There
                    has been a marked alteration in the tone of the leading newspapers, which will
                    not fail to produce its effect on the classes which they reach. A copy of the
                    Globe of the 4th instant, containing a leader on the subject, is herewith
                    transmitted.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CHARLES FRANCIS ADAMS.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington, D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">[<hi rend="italic">From the Morning Post
                                of</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 4, 1863</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <p rend="center">COURT OF EXCHEQUER.—Nov. 3.</p>
                    <p>Sittings in Banco in Michaelmas Term.—Before Lord Chief Baron Pollock, and
                        Barons Bramwell, Channell, and Pigott.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron, on taking his seat on the bench, said: The ordinary
                        practice is to take, first of all, the peremptory paper in the first two
                        days of term; but, Mr. Attorney General, as I presume you are in attendance
                        on the business of her Majesty, you are entitled to pre-audience.</p>
                    <p rend="center">THE ATTORNEY GENERAL <hi rend="italic">vs.</hi> SILLIM.—THE
                        CASE OF THE ALEXANDRA.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. My lord, I came here to apply to your lordships not at
                        present to go into any motion which will involve any lengthened discussion
                        or argument, but to give me longer than the ordinary time appointed to us
                        for the purpose of making, if it should become eventually necessary, a
                        motion for a new trial in the case of the “Attorney General vs. Sillim,”
                        which was tried before your lordship at the last sittings after term, and
                        concerned the forfeiture of the ship Alexandra. It will be in your
                        lordship’s recollection that your lordship on that occasion laid down the
                        views which you thought ought to govern the jury as to the construction of
                        the foreign enlistment act. Your lordship did so in a manner which we
                        thought perfectly clear and intelligible to all persons. There was no
                        difference whatever in the understanding of your lordship’s ruling on the
                        part of the counsel for the crown, and we have no reason to suppose it <pb
                            facs="0789" n="XLI" xml:id="pg_XLI"/> was otherwise as regards the
                        counsel for the defendants, or that it was generally understood in any other
                        sense than that in which we understood it. At the end of the trial we
                        expressed a wish to offer, in the usual manner and form, exceptions to that
                        ruling, and we were told that it was not necessary at all to stand upon
                        form. His lordship said, “I will accept any bill of exceptions you wish to
                        tender,” and accordingly after the verdict we wrote out the principal points
                        which we understood he had laid down; but his lordship said we were not to
                        he bound by what passed on that occasion, and that the matter could be
                        easily settled. Of course we were in hope that there would be no difficulty
                        at all in consenting to a bill of exceptions. The case involved a point of
                        very great importance, most fit for exceptions to the solemnly tendered for,
                        in order that it might go to a court of error, and, if necessary, to the
                        last court of appeal. We are most anxious that the question should be so
                        raised and determined, and we have no reason to doubt that the other side is
                        equally so, but hitherto there have been difficulties in arriving at any
                        form of exception which we can rely upon as certain to receive the signature
                        of his lordship. We hope that these difficulties may be overcome. We are in
                        communication with the counsel on the other side, who have in their
                        possession the form of exceptions we propose, and we trust that an agreement
                        in writing may be arrived at with them; or if that should not happen, that
                        his lordship, on being applied to at chambers in the usual manner, will be
                        able to settle such a form of bill of exceptions as will raise the real
                        question, to be determined in a way satisfactory to both parties and useful
                        to the public.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. I think it right to state that I see no prospect
                        whatever of any change in the view I took as to my duty in deciding upon the
                        bill of exceptions. A correspondence has passed between me and the late
                        attorney general, which probably you may have seen; you were not present at
                        the whole of the trial. So far from my laying down the law, as the bill of
                        exceptions tendered to me assumed, I took particular pains to avoid anything
                        of the kind. I had originally during that argument of Sir H. Cairns
                        undoubtedly entertained an impression—I called it no more—that all the
                        expressions in that act, “equipping,” “fitting out,” and so on, probably
                        meant the same thing, and were to be referred to the verbiage of an act of
                        Parliament, just in the same way as the words “ship or vessel,” which are
                        commonly used in statutes, and no doubt are intended to mean the same thing.
                        But the late attorney general, in his address, referred to a case of an
                        American court with an appeal to a superior court, where the decision below
                        was affirmed. It was a case where the vessel was completely prepared in
                        every respect with the exception of being armed. When I came to sum up, I
                        mentioned that case to the jury, and commended it so far as to say I adopted
                        it. I left it to them, and pointed out what had apparently fallen from the
                        counsel as to the law on the subject, not what I considered was the law. I
                        then finally left the question to them in the alternative, using the very
                        words of the act of Parliament. “If you think,” I said, “this vessel was
                        armed, or equipped, or fitted out, or intended to be armed, or fitted out,
                        or equipped, your verdict must be for the crown. If not, it must be for the
                        defendants.” Now, the attorney general presented to me a bill of exceptions
                        by which I was said to have told the jury that the vessel must be armed, and
                        that if it was not armed there was no offence. I not only did not tell the
                        jury so, but if you read the shorthand writer’s notes, I think you will say
                        no person can have any doubt that I left the question as I have just stated.
                        But probably, Mr. Attorney General, the object you have in view may be
                        attained by a motion without reference to a bill of exceptions. It is true
                        no point was reserved at the trial so as to give you a right of appeal in
                        the event of the rest of the court concurring with me in the direction I
                        gave to the jury. But this is a matter of so much importance—I do not know
                        whether I can pledge the whole court in this respect—but certainly it would
                        be very much to be lamented, however unanimous <pb facs="0790" n="XLII"
                            xml:id="pg_XLII"/> this court might be, if we did not give you what we
                        have the power of doing—an appeal to a superior court.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. I understand you have no power by act of Parliament to
                        give an appeal unless there be a difference of opinion among your
                        lordships.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. That is not so.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said he had misunderstood his learned friend, Mr. Jones,
                        on that point.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. We have the power of granting an appeal, and I must
                        say, as far as I am concerned—however unanimous and strong the court may be
                        upon the point of law—if you wish an appeal you will certainly have my voice
                        in favor of granting it.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell. I understand the difficulty to be that the common law
                        procedure act does not apply to a case of this kind.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. Mr. Jones has carefully considered the matter, and he
                        is strongly of opinion that the act does not meet the case.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell. You are apprehensive that the lord chief baron will
                        decline to sign the bill of exceptions in the form in which you have
                        tendered it, and if you move for a new trial on the ground that he directed
                        the jury wrongly, and he reports that he did not so direct them, of course
                        we could not grant a rule for a new trial under those circumstances. That is
                        the sort of difficulty in which you are placed.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. We have merely in the bill of exceptions adopted the
                            <hi rend="italic">litera scripta</hi> which we have here. I am not aware
                        that even a learned judge is able to interpret his own words, in an
                        application for a new trial, in a sense, different from that which they
                        really mean.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell. We ought not to depart from the ordinary practice of
                        taking the judge’s interpretation of the words in which he directed the
                        jury.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. I will read the shorthand writer’s notes as to what I
                        left to the jury. “The question is,” I said, “was there any intention in the
                        port of Liverpool, or any other port, that the ship should be, in the
                        language of the act of Parliament, equipped, fitted out, or armed, with the
                        object of taking part in any contest.” I also said, “If you think that the
                        object was to equip, furnish, fit out, or arm that vessel at Liverpool, then
                        there is sufficient matter for your consideration; but if you think the
                        object really was to build a vessel in obedience to orders and in compliance
                        with a contract, leaving it to those who bought it to make what use they
                        thought fit of it, then it appears to me that the foreign enlistment act has
                        not in any degree been broken. I leave you to find that by your
                        verdict.”</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said his lordship stated, at the conclusion of the
                        trial, that he would not bind the attorney general to what passed on that
                        occasion; that he could not alter the thing then, but that he had no doubt
                        the learned gentleman had a very accurate note of what he had said. His
                        lordship did not contradict the version which his learned friend gave at
                        that time of his direction to the jury.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. The question, however, now is, what course can we take
                        consistent with the rules of the court. If you wish to move for a new trial
                        on the ground that the jury ought not to have found the verdict they did,
                        the court will entertain that application; but if you mean to reserve to
                        yourself the power of making a motion for a new trial on a point of law,
                        having tendered a bill of exceptions containing that or some other point, I
                        do not think the court would consent to that course.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. My application is now simply to have the time for
                        moving for a new trial enlarged, so that both sides may agree as to what
                        your lordships said to the jury as to the interpretation of the statute. We
                        believe <pb facs="0791" n="XLIII" xml:id="pg_XLIII"/> that the jury returned
                        a verdict upon your lordship’s interpretation of the statute.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. Nothing of the kind occurred.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. Then both sides are under a misapprehension, and it is
                        their common wish to raise the point by a bill of exceptions if possible. We
                        ask you to enlarge the time for moving beyond the four days; and if, in the
                        mean time, we do not get your lordship’s signature to the bill of
                        exceptions, I will move for a new trial.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell. We have no power under the act to allow more than four
                        days, except by your making the motion for a new trial, and then adjourning
                        it, but that would not answer your purpose.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said this was the second day allowed for moving, and by
                        the fourth they would consider whether the case could be brought under the
                        common law procedure act.</p>
                    <p>It was then understood that the case should be mentioned again before the
                        four days expired.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">EXCHEQUER CHAMBER.—Nov. 3.</note>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <p rend="center">Sittings in error.</p>
                    <p rend="center">THE ALEXANDRA CASE.</p>
                    <p>The judges sat in the court of exchequer this morning for the purpose of
                        appointing the days for sittings in error in the exchequer chamber.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice Erle said the court had appointed the following days: For
                        errors from the Queen’s bench, Thursday, the 26th, and Friday, the 27th
                        November; for errors from the common pleas, Saturday, the 28th November, and
                        Monday, the 30th; and for errors from the exchequer, Tuesday, 1st December,
                        and Wednesday, 2d December. His lordship added, that with regard to the
                        errors from the exchequer, the arrangement was conditional, and was subject
                        to any alteration which might be necessary for the interests of public
                        justice. There was one case (the case of the Alexandra,) which he believed
                        would probably go to the exchequer chamber, which was of very great public
                        importance. If more time happened to be required for that case the court
                        would be glad to give it, and also to make arrangements for having it heard
                        before a full court.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said it was the desire of both parties to take the case
                        to the exchequer chamber, but as the lord chief baron has declined to sign a
                        bill of exceptions raising the question involved in it that might not
                        happen.</p>
                    <p>Lord Chief Justice Erle. We, however, wish it to be understood that we
                        reserve to ourselves the right to make any fresh arrangement.</p>
                    <p>Their lordships then rose.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">[<hi rend="italic">From the Morning Post
                                of</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-05">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 5, 1863</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">COURT OF EXCHEQUER.—Nov. 4.</note>
                    <p>Sittings in Banco.—Before Lord Chief Baron Pollock, and Barons Bramwell,
                        Channell, and Pigott.</p>
                    <p rend="center">THE ATTORNEY GENERAL <hi rend="italic">vs.</hi> SILLIM.—THE
                        CASE OF THE ALEXANDRA.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general (with whom was the solicitor general and Mr. T. Jones)
                        said he attended their lordships this morning, in consequence of a
                        suggestion thrown out by them yesterday, which had received the careful
                        attention of the <pb facs="0792" n="XLIV" xml:id="pg_XLIV"/> counsel for the
                        crown. They found that it was in their lordships’ power, if they thought fit
                        to exercise it, by an act to be done this day, to so apply the common law
                        procedure act as to give an appeal in a case of this description on the
                        revenue side of the court. The 26th section of the Queen’s remembrancer, act
                        22 and 23 Vic, said it should be lawful for the lord chief baron and two or
                        more barons of the exchequer, from time to time, to make rules and orders as
                        to process, practice, and pleading on the revenue side of the court, as
                        might seem to them necessary, and also by such rules and orders to adopt any
                        of the provisions of the common law procedure act, and any rules of pleading
                        and practice on the plea side to the revenue side of the court, as might
                        seem to them expedient for making the process, &amp;c, on both sides, as
                        nearly as might be, uniform. The learned counsel said he thought that their
                        lordships could under that section make an order which would meet the
                        present case.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. Why cannot your motion be made to-morrow, or, indeed,
                        at any time?</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said it occurred to him that it might possibly be too
                        late to-morrow.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. I am inclined to think that under that section the
                        court could make such an order, as you suggest, at any time.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell said the revenue rules made under the section in question
                        were originally proposed in the Queen’s remembrancer’s office, and he had
                        himself a good deal to do with them. The omission of the right of appeal in
                        revenue cases was intentional on the part of those who prepared the rules,
                        who thought it was not expedient to give such power. He was, however, not
                        aware of the omission at the time, as his attention was not called to it,
                        but he now thought that what was a good rule in an ordinary civil case must
                        also be a good rule in cases on the revenue side of the court. If, however,
                        they thought such a rule should be inserted, they should not adopt it
                        without consideration and on the spur of the moment, lest in doing so they
                        might reverse something which had been previously done by the court.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said it had, of course, been his duty to consider
                        whether any public inconvenience would arise in other cases by making such a
                        rule, and his strong impression was that there was not, and that the rule
                        was very desirable.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. I quite agree with you, and on the present occasion I
                        should be disposed to concur in any mode, short of a violation of principle,
                        which would give effect to your desire for an appeal. I own, after the
                        experience I have had in this court, that I see no reason why there should
                        not be an appeal in a revenue case, as in other cases. At all events, there
                        ought to be power in the court to grant an appeal if applied for, and they
                        thought fit it should be given.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Pigott entirely concurred in the view taken by his lordship, which
                        he thought consonant with the spirit of modern legislation, which gave the
                        petition of right and costs against the crown.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron said, as the court entirely concurred in the view of the
                        learned counsel, he thought the better course would be for the court to
                        adjourn earlier than usual, for the purpose of seeing whether the rule
                        should be made. As his learned brother said, the matter ought not to be
                        decided in a hurry; and if the learned counsel attended to-morrow morning,
                        they would tell him whether the alteration in the rules would be made. He
                        presumed that if they granted the application, the attorney general would
                        simply move for a new trial on all the grounds which might occur to him.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. If your lordships make the rule proposed, no doubt I
                        shall do so.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. I think that would be the better course to adopt,
                        because it will enable you to make every objection which can reasonably be
                        urged to what passed at the trial, and to whatever it may be thought had
                        misled the jury.</p>
                    <pb facs="0793" n="XLV" xml:id="pg_XLV"/>
                    <p>The attorney general. I am much obliged to your lordship.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. Unfortunately I was in communication with the late
                        attorney general alone on this subject, and with no other law officer of the
                        crown; and if he had not resigned, I had some intention of suggesting to him
                        the propriety of abandoning the bill of exceptions, and moving on any point
                        which he thought presented a fair ground for a motion. Now that the
                        impediment is likely to be removed, and a revenue case placed on the same
                        footing as any other proceeding, undoubtedly a motion for a new trial would
                        be far better than a bill of exceptions which covers various old
                        technicalities, which under a better and more enlightened system may be got
                        rid of.</p>
                    <p>The court then deferred their decision until to-morrow morning, when, if they
                        made the alteration proposed, it was understood the attorney general would
                        make a motion for a new trial raising all the points in the case.</p>
                    <p rend="center">IN RE ALFRED LEIGH, AN ATTORNEY.</p>
                    <p>When this case was called on—</p>
                    <p>Mr. J. A. Russel said he appeared on the part of the person who had obtained
                        the rule, and he understood that no cause would be shown on the other side.
                        He then asked the court to make the rule absolute, calling upon the attorney
                        to answer the matters in the affidavit, and in default to issue an
                        attachment, and to strike him off the rolls.</p>
                    <p>Rule absolute accordingly.</p>
                    <p rend="center">THE ALEXANDRA.</p>
                    <p>The learned barons retired from the court shortly before 3 o’clock, and after
                        being absent a short time, again took their seats on the bench, when Mr.
                        Walton, the senior master of the court and the Queen’s remembrancer, read,
                        by the direction of the chief baron, a new rule which they had framed under
                        the 22d and 23d Vict., c. 21, sec. 26, extending the provisions of the
                        common law procedure act to the revenue side of the court, so as to give an
                        appeal in revenue cases. This will meet the case of the Alexandra, and
                        enable the crown to obtain the appeal which the attorney general has
                        sought.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">[<hi rend="italic">From the Morning Post
                                of</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-06">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 6, 1863</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <p rend="center">COURT OF EXCHEQUER.—Nov. 5.</p>
                    <p>Sittings in Banco.—Before Lord Chief Baron Pollock and Barons Bramwell,
                        Channell, d Pigott.</p>
                    <p rend="center">THE ATTORNEY GENERAL <hi rend="italic">VS.</hi> SILLIM AND
                        OTHERS.—THE SEIZURE OP THE ALEXANDRA.</p>
                    <p>At the sitting of the court this morning there was an unusually large
                        attendance of the bar and of the public.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said that in the case of the Alexandra, which was an
                        information arising out of the seizure of the ship Alexandra on the 5th of
                        April last, by the crown, for the violation of the foreign enlistment act,
                        he had humbly to move their lordships for a rule to show cause why there
                        should not be a new trial on the ground of misdirection by the learned
                        judge, and also on the ground that the verdict was against the evidence.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell. In order that there may be no mistake, let it be clearly
                        understood that you move on the ground of the verdict being against the
                        evidence and misdirection, and that the bill of exceptions is abandoned.</p>
                    <pb facs="0794" n="XLVI" xml:id="pg_XLVI"/>
                    <p>The attorney general. Yes.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell. Let it be further understood that we must take my lord’s
                        report of his direction to the jury.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. I understand that, my lord.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell. And further, supposing that for any reason we, in our
                        discretion, grant or refuse a rule, let it be understood that no appeal will
                        lie from us under the rule we pronounced yesterday.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. Unless your lordships think fit to grant one.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Bramwell. Nay, there will be no appeal, except on a matter of law.
                        If we should be of opinion that there was no misdirection, but,
                        nevertheless, that the jury acted upon some wrong opinion, and we grant a
                        new trial on that ground, it would not be competent for the defendants to
                        appeal. On the other hand, if we should be of a different opinion and refuse
                        a rule, and you desire to take the opinion of the exchequer chamber on the
                        question, it would not be open to you to do so. I wish for my part, and I
                        believe I express the feeling of the rest of the court, that these three
                        matters should be clearly understood, viz: first, that the bill of
                        exceptions was abandoned; secondly, that the court would take his lordship’s
                        report of his direction to the jury; and thirdly, that there would be no
                        appeal from their decision by either side, except on a matter of law.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said that when he spoke of misdirection he must be
                        understood to include in that the omission to give a proper direction, and
                        also giving a direction which might in one sense be justified, but had a
                        tendency to mislead and might have misled the jury. The learned gentleman
                        then stated that the information was filed by the crown on the 25th of May
                        last, on the seizure of the vessel, which took place in the yard of Messrs.
                        Miller &amp; Son, shipbuilders at Liverpool. There were ninety-eight counts
                        in the information, that number being rendered necessary by the rather
                        complicated structure of the clause of the act of Parliament on which the
                        information was founded. In substance, it charged the persons whom he would
                        mention with various acts against a certain section of the foreign
                        enlistment act. The persons charged in the record were these: the members of
                        the firm of Miller &amp; Sons, the builders of the vessel, and in whose yard
                        she was when she was seized; the firm of Fawcett &amp; Co., manufacturers of
                        machinery at Liverpool, who came forward as the claimants of the vessel; the
                        firm of Frazer, Trenholm &amp; Co., who were proved to be the general agents
                        for the business of the confederate States, at Liverpool; a person named
                        Captain Bullock, the special agent for the business of those States; and a
                        person named Tessier, who was also employed in that business. Those persons,
                        together with others not known, were charged in every count of the
                        information with different acts in violation of the foreign enlistment act.
                        The separate counts were founded on the language of the seventh section,
                        which was directed against the “equipping, furnishing, fitting out, or
                        arming” of a ship or vessel, or attempting to do so, with the intent of
                        employing such ship or vessel in the belligerent service of a foreign people
                        or state against persons with whom her Majesty was not at war. The learned
                        counsel then pointed out that the words “equipping,” “furnishing,” &amp;c,
                        were employed in the disjunctive sense, and observed that the crown did not
                        charge “arming” in the information.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron said his impression was that arming was not charged, but
                        he was not quite certain upon the point.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said that “equipping,” “furnishing,” and “fitting out”
                        were separately charged; and in like manner were separately charged the
                        “attempting” and “endeavoring” to equip, furnish, and fit out, and the
                        “procuring” and “knowingly aiding, assisting, or being concerned in the
                        equipping, furnishing, or fitting out of a vessel,” which were all distinct
                        and separate offences under the statute. The learned counsel then said that
                        when their lordships came to hear the summing up, he thought they would be
                        of opinion that the jury had no opportunity whatever of giving a verdict on
                        the effect of the <pb facs="0795" n="XLVII" xml:id="pg_XLVII"/> evidence in
                        reference to the view of the act which was taken by the crown. In fact, the
                        case was left to them so as to preclude their judgment on the true question
                        to be determined. The case divided itself substantially into two points— the
                        equipping, furnishing, and fitting out; and secondly, the attempting to do
                        so with the intent of employing the ship in the manner against which the act
                        was directed; and upon both those points the evidence given on the part of
                        the crown was wholly uncontradicted. The learned judge, in his direction to
                        the jury, seemed to have overlooked the provisions as to attempting and
                        endeavoring, and addressed himself to the complete equipment and fitting out
                        in the sense which his lordship considered those words ought to bear. The
                        seventh clause substantially divided itself into two points—the equipping,
                        furnishing, fitting out or arming, and the attempting and endeavoring with
                        intent, &amp;c; and upon both these points the material evidence at the
                        trial was uncontradicted. He would first refer to the evidence as to the
                        character and condition of the vessel, and the preparations and equipments
                        on the 5th April, when she was seized. The custom-house officer, Morgan,
                        said she was incomplete, but had three masts up, with lightning conductors,
                        as well as her machinery and other fittings on board. There was also
                        evidence to prove that she was built as and for a gunboat; that she had
                        bulwarks and a rudder adapted to and peculiarly fit for the purposes of war;
                        that she was unfit for any mercantile purpose whatever; and that though she
                        might possibly be used for a yacht, and had no fittings actually placed on
                        board to enable her to receive guns, yet she could with the greatest
                        facility be adapted to receive two or three pivot guns—the proper number—
                        which would sweep over her bulwarks and make her serviceable as a gunboat.
                        So much with respect to the character of the vessel. Then as to the fitting
                        out, equipping, and furnishing, there was further evidence to show that the
                        machinery, engine, and boiler, were either on board or in progress of being
                        put, and that there were preparations for hammock nettings and guns and gun
                        carriages. Barnes, an engine driver in the employment of Messrs. Miller,
                        said he had been concerned in the yard in building three gunboats—the Oreto,
                        the Penguin, and the Steady—which were for the government. He also said he
                        recollected the screw steamer Alexandra, and she was like the other
                        gunboats, only smaller. Then there was Mr. Spears, foreman to claimants of;
                        the vessel, who received orders to take the machinery to the gunboat. Black,
                        a ship carpenter, and Green, a shipbuilder, gave evidence showing that the
                        bulwarks of the Alexandra were not those of a merchant vessel, on account of
                        their extraordinary strength, and that they would be useless except for a
                        ship-of-war. They further stated that she had pitch-pine decks, a wood which
                        was chiefly used for war-vessels. Again, there was Captain Engledue, who
                        said the Alexandra had only stowage room sufficient for her crew, supposing
                        it to consist of 32 men; that she was not fit for mercantile purposes, and
                        could be easily adapted to the uses of a war-vessel. That was the evidence
                        as to the construction of the ship, and he would now turn to that part of
                        the case which related to the fitting out, furnishing, and equipping, as
                        distinct from the structure. He submitted that it was utterly unimportant
                        whether those equipments were of a warlike character or not, and that if he
                        proved she was intended for warlike purposes, any equipment whatever for
                        such purposes was sufficient to constitute a violation of the statute. He
                        thought that a great fallacy had run through the arguments, and that any
                        kind or description of fitting out or furnishing was against the statute,
                        provided always the intent and purpose was proved. The learned counsel then
                        read extracts from the evidence of different witnesses, with reference to
                        the equipments, &amp;c, which he contended were essentially of a warlike
                        character, and to the cotemporaneous preparation under the superintendence
                        of Messrs. Fawcett, the claimants of the vessel, of gun-carriages just of
                        the kind which it would be natural and safe to place on board the ship. He
                        next passed to the evidence as to the intent and purpose, and argued that
                        the clause clearly and distinctly laid down <pb facs="0796" n="XLVIII"
                            xml:id="pg_XLVIII"/> that any species whatsoever of furnishing, fitting
                        out, or equipping was against the act if it was with intent or in order that
                        the ship should be employed in the belligerent service of a foreign people
                        or state against persons with whom her Majesty was not at war. He then said
                        it had been proved in a manner beyond the possibility of a doubt, and was
                        wholly uncontradicted, that these things were done under the superintendence
                        and with the interference of persons who were proved to have been the agents
                        of the Confederate States for the purposes of their war service. There was
                        Captain Bullock, who was specially sent to this country to organize the
                        means of carrying on the war on the seas as servant and officer of the
                        Confederate States; there was Mr. Hamilton, another servant and officer of
                        those States, who was obviously employed for a like purpose; and there was
                        the firm of Frazer, Trenholm &amp; Co., who were named in the information as
                        interfering with the construction of the ship by their agent, and at whose
                        office was the seat of the agency of the Confederate States who conducted
                        their pecuniary business, and through whom they ordered their paymaster to
                        pay the persons who were employed on board the Alabama and the other
                        war-ships which they had constructed in this country. Then there was the
                        active superintendence of Captain Tessier over the work-people in both
                        Miller’s yard and Fawcett’s works; and in addition, the direct admission of
                        Miller, the builder, that the vessel was being built for the Confederate
                        States, under contract entered into with Frazer, Trenholm &amp; Co., and was
                        to be employed in the service of those States. The learned counsel then
                        referred to the evidence of Clarence Randolph Young, acting assistant
                        paymaster of the Confederate States navy, who deposed that he made payments
                        in Liverpool to persons in the service of those States; that he derived his
                        authority from Captain Bullock, commander of the Confederate States navy;
                        that he made requisitions to Captain Bullock for the amounts of money he
                        required, and that the captain gave him orders upon Messrs. Frazer, Trenholm
                        &amp; Co., from whom he received checks. This witness was severely
                        cross-examined, and it appeared that his morality was not quite
                        unimpeachable, but his evidence was confirmed by documentary and other
                        evidence, which could not be gainsaid. It seemed that while at Liverpool he
                        formed a connexion with and married a black woman, and afterwards deserted
                        her under circumstances which could not be justified. This woman had a black
                        boy, and the man Young, who said he was “raised” in Georgia, suggested that
                        a little money might be made by selling the black boy, and that he might be
                        sold. It was very far from his intention, as had been alleged by the lord
                        chief baron of the late attorney general, to attempt to whitewash Clarence
                        Randolph Young, but he spoke of his evidence as it bore upon the res gestae
                        of the case, and as it was corroborated by the litera scripta and the
                        documentary evidence, to which no objection at the time was made. In England
                        we were accustomed to liberty, and did not sell either white or black men,
                        but the witness Young came from a country where that was common, and a man
                        bred in an atmosphere of slavery, and engaged in the service of burning and
                        destroying merchant vessels on the wide ocean, was not likely to feel as we
                        did, or to be a man of very tender feelings. In the Confederate States this
                        man would have been a perfectly good witness notwithstanding his black boy,
                        for in that country they did not allow either a black boy or a black man or
                        woman to enter the witness-box, whatever might be the extent of the evil
                        complained of. All the remarks made about him were mere claptrap, and had no
                        bearing on the question as to the agency of Bullock, which he was called
                        solely to prove. The eloquent vituperation of Sir H. Cairns was, therefore,
                        perfectly irrelevant and beside the mark, and did not tend to discredit the
                        testimony of Young. The learned counsel next examined the evidence of
                        Chapman, who went to the office, of Frazer, Trenholm and Co. under false
                        colors, pretending to have southern sympathies, whereas he was in favor of
                        the northern States—a course which he did not for a moment justify; but this
                        witness, he said, proved certain transactions with Bullock and others which
                        had <pb facs="0797" n="XLIX" xml:id="pg_XLIX"/> not been disputed, and which
                        proved that they were agents for the belligerent service of the Confederate
                        States. After referring to other witnesses he contended, that upon this
                        uncontradicted state of things, unless explained by their having been
                        improperly directed, the jury could not but find a verdict for the crown.
                        When, however, he came to read the summing up, the matter was made perfectly
                        plain, because the jury had no option but to find as they did, whereas the
                        evidence clearly entitled the crown to a verdict. The learned counsel then
                        dwelt upon the object and provisions of the foreign enlistment act and its
                        application to the present case.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron said one of the objects of the act was to prevent any
                        hostile vessel being fitted out so as to make a port of this country the
                        point of discharge.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general did not think that was the view of the lord chief baron,
                        as shown by the short-hand writer’s notes. His lordship seemed to imply that
                        a vessel might be constructed in one yard for the federals, and another in a
                        different yard for the confederates, and that as soon as they got out they
                        might come in collision and endanger the public peace.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. That might be one of the mischiefs which would
                        arise.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general thought that such a thing never entered the mind of any
                        human being.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. It is not only not impossible, but it is a fact—it is
                        true.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Baron Pigott. Did not this happen at Southampton, where a federal and
                        confederate vessel met, and where one was detained by us for several hours
                        to prevent it overtaking the other?</p>
                    <p>The attorney general said that occurrence had nothing to do with the foreign
                        enlistment act. The statute aimed at prevention; its object was to stop
                        these things in limine, and not to punish them when done; and therefore the
                        act said that any attempt to do any of these things was a violation of its
                        provisions. Unless their lordships sat there to make laws, they must say
                        that any ships fitting out for warlike purposes, the intent being proved,
                        came within the act. This was a case which the 7th section directly touched,
                        and if it were ruled otherwise they might as well at once strike the act out
                        of the statute-book.</p>
                    <p>At this stage of the proceedings their lordships adjourned; and upon their
                        return,</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron said the court had availed themselves of the adjournment
                        to consider the matters which the attorney general had brought before them,
                        and without in the least saying what the opinion of any member of the court
                        was as to the ultimate fate of the rule; they all thought that what he had
                        stated was unquestionably matter fit to be discussed. If the learned
                        gentlemen were content, therefore, to take a rule to show cause why the
                        verdict should not be set aside as contrary to evidence, or as not being
                        warranted by the evidence, and on the ground of misdirection by the judge at
                        the trial, or on the ground that though there might be no positive
                        misdirection, there was a want of information furnished to the jury to
                        enable them to discharge their duty fairly—if he were content to take a rule
                        on those two grounds, dividing the second ground into positive misdirection
                        or imperfect misdirection, he might take a rule to show cause at once.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. I thank your lordship. That is what I have been asking
                        your lordship for, and I have no more to say.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. I may state that I took pains to lay down the law as I
                        understood it to have been laid down by the highest possible authority in
                        another place.</p>
                    <p>The attorney general. Any such authority is incapable of vindicating himself
                        here.</p>
                    <p>The lord chief baron. I thought I was remarkably safe in taking that course,
                        but I may have been mistaken.</p>
                    <p>Rule nisi granted.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0798" n="L" xml:id="pg_L"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">
                            <hi rend="italic">[From the Globe and Traveller
                                    (<placeName>London</placeName>) of</hi>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1863-11-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 4, 1863</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <head ana="#head_untitled-missing-head-in-printed-volume">[Untitled]</head>
                    <p>Whatever may be the upshot of the questions arising under the foreign
                        enlistment act, there is one thing that all must desire. We mean a full and
                        solemn interpretation by the highest judicial authorities of the real intent
                        and effective operation of the statute. Is it or is it not a dead letter?
                        Can any one, either for the sake of profit, or for the gratification of
                        personal sympathies, or with a view of bringing about a state of
                        ill-feeling, if not war, between this country and another, drive a coach and
                        six through this unlucky act of Parliament every month in the year, and
                        every day in the week? For many years it has been supposed that there was a
                        statute in existence which would enable the government to prevent private
                        persons from thwarting state policy. It now appears that great doubts are
                        entertained on this head. Attempts, some of them successful, have been made
                        to evade the act. Doubts are thrown on the powers of the government, and
                        while no one alleges any moral doubt respecting the actual evasion of the
                        statute, many set up legal doubts. Under these circumstances it is of the
                        highest moment that the questions raised and the full scope of the act
                        should be determined by the highest available judicial tribunal. As the
                        matters in dispute are pending, we wish to express no opinion whatever on
                        the merits of the particular questions at issue in a particular case. But we
                        do feel that, for the sake of the national welfare, no mere technical
                        obstacles of any sort should be allowed to obstruct a final and complete
                        examination of the whole law. We ought to know how far the law officers of
                        the crown can rely on the means placed by the legislature at their disposal
                        to give effect to the intention with which those means were
                        sanctioned—namely, the preservation in the hands of the government of the
                        direction of the national policy.</p>
                    <p>As regards the point raised yesterday before the court of exchequer, we, in
                        common with everybody else, did understand that the lord chief baron had set
                        forth in his charge to the jury that arming, equipping, furnishing, fitting
                        out, were the mere verbiage of an act of Parliament, and that, in his
                        opinion, these terms did all mean the same thing, namely, arming. The
                        counsel for the crown so understood him. It is assumed that the jury so
                        understood him. They and we and all the world, it seems, were in error. He
                        tells us he did not say so, or imply so. We are, as Mr. Justice Bramwell
                        reminds us, bound to take the judge’s interpretation of the words in which
                        he directed the jury. We do so; but it is the most remarkable
                        misapprehension on the part of all those who heard and read those words that
                        we remember ever to have met with. And here we must regret that the usual
                        practice of framing and tendering a bill of exceptions before the jury gave
                        their verdict was not followed. At the end of the trial, and before the
                        verdict, the counsel for the crown expressed a wish to offer exceptions to
                        the ruling of the lord chief baron. They were told by him that it was not
                        necessary to stand upon the usual forms, and they did not stand upon them,
                        especially as the lord chief baron said, “I will accept any bill of
                        exceptions you may choose to tender.” But when the bill was drawn up, the
                        lord chief baron objected that it did not correctly set forth the nature of
                        his ruling. Now, had exception been taken at the time; had the common
                        opinion respecting the drift and bearing of that ruling been distinctly
                        expounded, the error, into which it seems we all fell—counsel, jury,
                        public—could have been there and then dispelled by a simple restatement by
                        the judge of what he did mean to say and did say. It was even stated
                        yesterday that the version which the then attorney general had given at the
                        time of the lord chief baron’s ruling was not contradicted. The answer
                        was—the question is, what course can now be taken consistent with the views
                        of the court. This shows that an error was committed in not fixing at once
                        the impression made by the language of the lord chief baron. But the state
                        of the matter, as disclosed by the proceedings of yesterday, is an <pb
                            facs="0799" n="LI" xml:id="pg_LI"/> additional reason why some
                        unquestionable decision should be obtained on this momentous point.</p>
                    <p>For our parts, we do not pretend to lay down the law. Whatever the law is,
                        let us know it; and if it be found incompatible with the object for which it
                        was devised, then we can say whether we will be content with an useless
                        statute, whether we will have any statute at all, or whether we will have an
                        efficient one.</p>
                    <p>It has been asked why, when guns and amunition and small arms can be supplied
                        by a neutral to a belligerent, “why object to ships?” It may be difficult to
                        set forth convincing reasons why ships should be stopped and arms and shells
                        allowed to go free. But to us there seems to be one plain reason. If you
                        export to the ports of a belligerent any quantity of destructive arms and
                        missiles, no one can furnish proof that they have been used with effect
                        against the other belligerent. But if you export a ship, the doings of that
                        ship can be tracked over the sea by the fires she leaves behind, or by the
                        prizes she brings into port. You cannot charge an Armstrong gun with killing
                        and slaying, and identify the gun with damage and slaughter. You can charge
                        a ship with capturing prizes from a friendly power, and prove the charge.
                        There is an identity about a ship which there is not about a gun. But we may
                        be asked, if a fighting machine, like a ship, may be exported to strike at a
                        friendly power, why not a battalion, or a battery, or a regiment of horse? A
                        ship, even without guns, is equivalent to a trained battalion without arms,
                        or a body of artillerymen without guns, or a trained regiment of horsemen
                        without horses. It is obviously within the power of the crown to say with
                        whom it will and with whom it will not make war; and every act which tends
                        to weaken that power and thwart the intention of the crown is an act which,
                        on the assumption that we are to have a government at all, the crown should
                        have power to prevent. We believe the sensible men of all parties take this
                        view, and will not sanction any proceedings which restrict the power of the
                        crown in so important a matter of state policy, or which tend to injure the
                        maritime power of England.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
