<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Uruguay ( (Dawson) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1131</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1131</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-02-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="1131"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1131">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">833.20 Missions/2–1345</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 5459</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-13">February 13,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received February 21.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt (on
                    February 12) of the Department’s secret airgram no. 40 of February 3, 1945,
                    requesting a report on any recent developments which might indicate Uruguayan
                    willingness to request an American military mission.</p>
                <p>It is presumed that the Department had not yet received my despatch no. 5335 of
                    January 23,<note n="30" xml:id="d1131fn30">Not printed.</note> in which I
                    commented at some length on the outlook for military missions in Uruguay.</p>
                <pb facs="1390" n="1376" xml:id="pg_1376"/>
                <p>In the meantime, I have had the advantage of discussing the matter with Major
                    General Ralph H. Wooten<note n="35" xml:id="d1131fn35">Commanding General,
                        United States Army Forces, South Atlantic.</note> on the occasion of the
                    latter’s recent visit to Montevideo (see my despatch no. 5435, February 9,
                        1945<note n="36" xml:id="d1131fn36">Not printed.</note>). On February 8
                    there was held at the Embassy a conference attended by General Wooten, the
                    Military and Naval Attachés, Mr. Sparks,<note n="37" xml:id="d1131fn37">Edward
                        J. Sparks, First Secretary of Embassy.</note> and myself. General Wooten
                    gave us certain background information concerning staff conferences with Brazil
                    and informed us that he and Vice Admiral Munroe<note n="38" xml:id="d1131fn38"
                        >Vice Adm. William R. Munroe, Commander of the Fourth Fleet.</note> would be
                    glad to initiate conferences with Uruguay in March.</p>
                <p>General Wooten informed us in particular that in Brazil<note n="39"
                        xml:id="d1131fn39">For documentation on staff conversations between
                        Brazilian and United States military authorities, see <ref target="#pg_600"
                            >pp. 600</ref> ff.</note> there was certain opposition to formal
                    military missions and that indications were that in lieu of such missions
                    arrangements would be made under which we would furnish instructors as needed
                    for limited periods and limited objectives.</p>
                <p>All those present at our conference agreed that the situation in Uruguay is very
                    similar to that in Brazil as explained by General Wooten. As has been pointed
                    out by the Embassy we feel that the Uruguayan Government will be disinclined to
                    request formal military or naval missions or to contract for the services of
                    such missions. We believe the outlook much brighter for requests for furnishing
                    small groups of officers (not to be called missions) to be sent for limited
                    periods and limited purposes with particular reference to instruction and
                    training in the use of Lend-Lease matériel.</p>
                <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William Dawson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
