<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-04-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="1146" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1146">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">862.20233/4–3045</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Uruguay</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Dawson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#center">[Extracts]</seg>
                        </opener>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 5764</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Montevideo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-04-30">April 30,
                                1945</date>.<lb/>[Received June 6.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to furnish herewith such
                            details as have appeared in the Montevideo press describing how the
                            Uruguayan authorities, with the assistance of a lead received from the
                            British Intelligence Service, carried out a series of raids early this
                            month and after interrogating some twenty people released all but the
                            following three individuals, who have been remanded to prison to stand
                            trial for carrying on Nazi espionage activities: Fritz A. Rabe
                                (PL),<note n="86" xml:id="d1146fn1">Proclaimed List.</note> his
                            brother, Hans J. Rabe (PL) and José Vendemia.</p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>It appears that the authorities have discovered from their interrogations
                            of the above individuals and the evidence received from other sources
                            that the Rabe brothers and José Vendemia were engaged in obtaining and
                            forwarding information on Allied shipping to a Nazi group in Rio de
                            Janeiro. These three individuals have now been committed for trial and,
                            as stated, have been placed under arrest. On April 11 it was announced
                            in the press that Fritz Rabe had been provisionally suspended as a
                            member of the National Chamber of Commerce and also as a qualified stock
                            exchange broker.</p>
                        <p>While the recent success of the local authorities in uncovering
                            additional Nazi agents naturally attracted attention and produced
                            expressions of alarm from various newspapers, coinciding as it did with
                            the appearance of press reports of the discovery of an Axis sabotage
                            ring in Chile and with publication of the more sensational findings of
                            the Uruguayan and Argentine authorities who had been jointly
                            investigating Axis subversive activities in the River Plate (see
                            Embassy’s despatches no. 5561 of March 21 [<hi rend="italic">12</hi>]
                            and no. 5683 of April 10, 1945),<note n="87" xml:id="d1146fn2">Neither
                                printed.</note> this case failed to arouse the excitement provoked
                            by the discovery three months before of the local Nazi spy ring
                            involving Juan Alberto Bove Trabal (see Embassy’s despatches no. 5270 of
                            January 10 and no. 5339 of January 23, 1945<note n="87" xml:id="d1146fn3">Neither printed.</note>).</p>
                        <p>Upon completion of the report now being prepared by the Legal Attaché
                            about this case, a copy will be promptly forwarded to the
                            Department.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>For the Ambassador: <lb/>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Reginald Bragonier</hi>
                            </signed>
                            <lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Second Secretary</hi>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>