<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Acting Chief, Commodities Division ( (Cale))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recfIX2Uumy8inHEq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85144526"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wages</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-03-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-03-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="233"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d233">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">561.333D3/3–1945</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Acting Chief, Commodities Division</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">Cale</hi>)<note n="9" xml:id="d233fn1">Addressed to Assistant
                        Secretary Clayton and to his Deputy, Edward S. Mason.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-03-19">March 19,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The following is a summary of a somewhat longer memorandum I prepared over the
                    weekend concerning some of the factors that should be considered in connection
                    with the request of the coffee producing countries for an increase in coffee
                    ceiling prices: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Our coffee supply situation is now so grave that we may not be able to
                            avoid a return to coffee rationing, regardless of the decision on <pb
                                facs="0368" n="354" xml:id="pg_354"/> coffee prices. Granting the
                            increase would to some extent improve our chances of avoiding rationing.
                            Granting the increase without obtaining some assurance from the
                            Governments of the producing countries that supplies will continue to be
                            forthcoming at those prices would probably give only temporary relief
                            from our supply difficulties. There are reasons for believing that the
                            Governments of Brazil and Colombia may be in a position to assure
                            supplies for one or two years at new prices mutually agreed upon.
                            Whether or not they are prepared to do so and whether they would be able
                            to act with the required degree of toughness to fulfill the commitment,
                            if made, are questions the answers to which are uncertain.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Although the Office of Price Administration is in a better position
                            than I to judge the possible harmful effect of an increase in coffee
                            ceiling prices on the stabilization program, the following are reasons
                            for believing that officers of that agency may have over-emphasized the
                            danger: <list>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The cost of coffee is an almost insignificant item in the cost
                                    of living, its weight in the cost of living index being .6 of 1
                                    percent.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The stabilization program is still considered to be reasonably
                                    well intact in spite of substantial increases in the prices of
                                    domestically-produced agricultural and other products and of
                                    various adjustments that have been made in certain types of
                                    wages.</item>
                                <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>The list of items for which an increase in coffee prices is
                                    most likely to set a precedent is believed to be relatively
                                    small. It consists of staple agricultural commodities which are
                                    not produced in the United States but which are imported from
                                    countries that have been less successful than the United States
                                    in controlling inflation. It is believed to be the area in which
                                    we have most rigidly applied price control and our policy with
                                    respect to the prices of such products should perhaps be
                                    reexamined anyway.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>It is impossible to obtain accurate figures on the cost of producing
                            agricultural products in the other American republics. The Office of
                            Price Administration would in any event be forced to refuse to increase
                            its maximum prices on the sole basis of increased production costs in
                            foreign countries, since many of them do not adequately control prices.
                            Coffee production is perhaps still carried on in most countries on a
                            basis that does not involve plantation owners and small farmers in a
                            loss. However, the former are perhaps not now able to pay wages as high
                            as those paid in certain other industries whereas money wages and money
                            costs of production have little meaning to the latter since they would
                            find it difficult to shift to any other industry and since they and the
                            members of their families generally furnish most of the labor used in
                            the growing of coffee.</item>
                        <pb facs="0369" n="355" xml:id="pg_355"/>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>As a result largely of inflation in the coffee producing countries
                            real income from coffee production is now much lower than when the
                            present coffee price ceilings were established. A memorandum recently
                            received from the Colombian Foreign Office claims, on the basis of
                            statistical information it contains, that the real income of Colombian
                            coffee growers is now lower than at the time the Inter-American Coffee
                            Agreement was negotiated in 1940.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Although unprofitable prices extending over a long period of years
                            could reduce future coffee production and eventually result in very high
                            prices, the argument of the producing countries that present ceiling
                            prices are in fact now impairing future production is believed to be
                            greatly over-emphasized. In this connection it should be remembered that
                            from five to seven years must elapse between the time new trees are
                            planted and the time they begin to bear, that they do not reach maximum
                            production until the 12th to 15th year, that they usually continue
                            bearing for many years more, and that coffee prices up until a year or
                            so ago undoubtedly were profitable.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Parity for Santos 4 coffee is 22.13 cents per pound, using the 1909 to
                            1914 base, as compared with a ceiling price of 13.375. Prices of
                            agricultural commodities in this country have, on the average, increased
                            by 39 percent since coffee prices were frozen in December 1941.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Coffee prices for Africa coffee, which is now used to supply the
                            European market, are much above the equivalent of the United States
                            ceilings for such coffee. For example, Ethiopian coffee is now selling
                            for 7 or 8 cents per pound above the ceiling established for it by the
                                OPA<note n="10" xml:id="d233fn2">Office of Price
                                Administration</note> in 1941.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>European countries appear in a few isolated cases to have paid more
                            than our ceilings for small quantities of coffee in Latin America. If we
                            continue to maintain our ceilings and the producers continue to refuse
                            to sell at those prices, it is likely that such cases will become more
                            numerous.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>The outlook is for more than enough coffee to supply world
                            requirements for the next five years, even allowing for a reasonably
                            rapid restoration of European consumption and even assuming the
                            continuation of the very low level of Brazilian production of the past
                            four years. The probability is that the present stock of 27,000,000 bags
                            of Brazilian coffee (not counting the current crop) will be
                            increased.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>The Brazilian Government has just announced a plan for subsidizing the
                            exportation of coffee as is stated in the following telegram <pb
                                facs="0370" n="356" xml:id="pg_356"/> of March 17 (No. 855)<note
                                n="11" xml:id="d233fn3">Not printed.</note> from the American
                            Embassy in Rio de Janeiro: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>Among measures approved by recent Interstate Coffee
                                        Conference<note n="12" xml:id="d233fn4">The Brazilian
                                        Interstate Coffee Convention which met in February and
                                        March, 1945, and indicated support for government subsidies
                                        and interest-free loans for the coffee industry.</note> (re
                                    Embassy’s telegram No. 846 of March 16<note n="11"
                                        xml:id="d233fn5">Not printed.</note>) was subsidy on coffees
                                    of 1944–45 crop ranging from 65 cruzeiros per bag on São Paulo
                                    and nearby coffees down to 15 cruzeiros for Bahias and
                                    Pernambucos; parallel bonus for coming 1945–46 crop; and export
                                    bonus ranging from 36 to 18 cruzeiros on past crop coffees. Also
                                    one year loan to growers without interest in amount of 60
                                    centavos per tree. Full text of agreements reached being
                                    forwarded air mail.<note n="13" xml:id="d233fn6">Embassy report
                                        181, March 19, 1945, not printed.</note>
                                </p>
                                <p>Santos market easier, 27,000 bags registered March 15, and good
                                    prospects for early handling of prospective army business.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>In view of the foregoing, particularly item 10, it is doubted that the Department
                    will wish at this time to urge an increase in coffee ceiling prices. If the
                    agencies of the Government in charge of procurement activities wish to have
                    prices increased as a means to obtaining supplies we should, of course, not
                    object. It is believed that we should, in any event, explore fully the
                    possiblity of working out with the interested agencies of the Government a
                    program with respect to a ceiling for coffee and for other imported agricultural
                    commodities that is in so far as possible in keeping with Resolution XV of the
                    Mexico City Conference.<note n="14" xml:id="d233fn7">For documentation
                        concerning this Conference, see <ref target="#pg_1">pp. 1</ref> ff. For text
                        of Resolution XV, see Pan American Union, <hi rend="italic">Final Act of the
                            Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace, Mexico City,
                            February–March, 1945</hi>, pp. 52–53. In this Resolution the Conference
                        approved a statement that criteria analogous to those applied to ceiling
                        prices of products of domestic industries should be applied to the products
                        of the American nations, and that price ceilings should bear an appropriate
                        relationship to costs of production.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward G. Cale</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
