<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Secretary of State to the
                        United States Political Adviser for Germany (
                        Murphy
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d353</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">353</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-11-29T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-11-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-11-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="353" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d353">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">862.20235/11–2945: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        United States Political Adviser for Germany</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Murphy</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-11-29">November 29,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–239. For Griswold.<note n="84" xml:id="d353fn84">Richard W. Griswold, Economic
                        Analyst, Office of the United States Political Adviser on German
                        Affairs.</note> By order of the Secretary a special <hi rend="italic">ad
                        hoc</hi> unit has been organized under Assistant Secretary Braden to collate
                    with the greatest possible speed all evidence of Axis activities in Argentina
                    and especially complicity of the present Argentine regime. Success of this
                    project depends largely on obtaining additional evidence from sources within
                    Germany. Material already received from you is very valuable for this purpose,
                    but much more is needed, especially in the form of interrogation of German
                    personnel. In view of the extreme urgency you are requested to transmit
                    hereafter by airgram full description of important material discovered
                    hereafter, following up with expeditious transmission of photographs of
                    documents and other full reports. War and Treasury Departments are cooperating
                    in this project. Griswold should therefore communicate with proper Army
                    authorities in Germany to ascertain who has been charged with this work in
                    Germany for the Army. It is recognized that additional personnel will be needed
                    in Germany for this project, especially interrogators. Griswold should use all
                    available personnel for this purpose and arrange for the use of qualified Army
                    personnel to the extent necessary. In this connection reference is made to War
                    Department cable no. 84395 dated November 14, 1945 instructing War Department
                    personnel to give priority for the purpose of this project. Griswold should also
                    inform himself on the progress and coordination of investigation of German
                    commercial and industrial enterprises in this field by Cartels and External
                    Assets Investigation Division and report developments currently.</p>
                <p>Information needed from you (unless already transmitted in the material en route)
                    is as follows: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Ascertain for purposes of interrogation whereabouts of Foreign Office
                            personnel who handled Argentine matters in recent years, including
                            subordinate assistants and clerical help. Information available here
                            indicates that Reinebeck was in charge of Latin American <pb facs="0505" n="491" xml:id="pg_491"/> political matters and Beye was in charge
                            of Latin American commercial and economic matters. Therefore, these two
                            may be sources of information on this subject.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Special and detailed interrogation should be made of all such
                            personnel along the following lines (in addition to such others as may
                            occur to the interrogator). <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Where is the Argentine correspondence and file material not
                                    discovered by you in existing Foreign Office files at
                                    Marburg?</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Where are other communications and file material on subject of
                                    Argentina not filed with Foreign Office, such as Abwehr,<note n="85" xml:id="d353fn85">Information agency of the German
                                        High Command.</note> SD,<note n="86" xml:id="d353fn86">Sicherheitsdienst, Nazi Security Service; intelligence and
                                        counterintelligence agency headed by Heinrich
                                        Himmler.</note> cultural activities not under Foreign
                                    Office, etc.?</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                <item>What are names and whereabouts of other individuals than
                                    Foreign Office personnel involved in the handling of Argentine
                                    matters within the German Government, both at the German end and
                                    the Argentine end?</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi>)</label>
                                <item>What were the plans (completed, projected, or otherwise) for
                                    the use of Argentina for German purposes? Are documents
                                    available in which such subjects are discussed? If so, the
                                    documents should be obtained and promptly transmitted. It should
                                    be borne in mind in this connection that we are concerned with
                                    the participation of the present Argentine regime in any German
                                    plan as well as the use of Argentina by Germany as a base for
                                    penetration elsewhere in this hemisphere (such as Bolivia,
                                    Brazil, Paraguay, Uruguay, and Chile) and any German plan to
                                    dominate Argentina.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">e</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Obtain full story on conspiracy and cooperation with leaders
                                    of the Argentine ruling regime, including financial aid to the
                                    officials of the present regime, plans for armed aid, bribes,
                                    subsidies, technical military assistance, use of other
                                    intermediaries (such as Spanish) both before and after the
                                    Argentine Revolution of June 4, 1943. In this connection
                                    specific information should be sought on Argentine leaders,
                                    particularly Colonel Juan D. Perón and General Edelmiro Farrell.
                                    Also ascertain the part played by such German agents as Ludwig
                                    Freude, important in Argentine construction industry and German
                                    community, and SD representatives Becker and Harnisch.<note n="87" xml:id="d353fn87">Hans Harnisch was a key secret
                                        agent of the German military intelligence service
                                        (Abwehr).</note> All files involving Freude, Becker, and
                                    Harnisch mentioned above should be photographed and transmitted
                                    with greatest dispatch.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">f</hi>)</label>
                                <item>Obtain details of German participation in Helmuth case, with
                                    which Blancke is familiar.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>You should also conduct investigation of Ibero Amerikanisches Institut
                            along same lines as foregoing.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>It is expected that you will be sent additional lines of specific inquiry as may
                    be indicated by further developments.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
