<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Argentina ( (Braden) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">366</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="366"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d366">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">835.918/6–645</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Braden</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 109</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos Aires</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-06">June 6,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received June 18.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit the texts of two
                    dispatches received by the Associated Press dated June 1 and June 2<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d366fn7">Neither printed.</note> which were not allowed to be
                    released to local newspapers by the Censorship Division of the Argentine Post
                    Office (Oficina Centralizadora de Control).</p>
                <p>Employees of the Post Office are assigned to both the Associated Press and the
                    United Press in the city throughout the hours that wireless messages are
                    received from the United States. They review each incoming dispatch as it is
                    received and immediately report any passage or detail which they consider
                    unfavorable to the Argentine Government. Certain passages are ordered deleted
                    almost every day, and a number of complete dispatches have been held up each
                    week, for months past. The order is usually received from the Post Office by
                    telephone, only a few minutes after the dispatch has been received. In cases of
                    unusual importance the newspapers are notified separately that they must not
                    print a certain item, if it should be received. This order is usually given by
                    telephone also.</p>
                <p>Both the A.P. and the U.P. state that they were bothered less frequently by such
                    “censorship” during the week or ten days following Ambassador Warren’s
                        visit,<note n="8" xml:id="d366fn8">For information on Avra M. Warren’s visit
                        to Buenos Aires, see circular telegram of April 23, 3 p.m., to diplomatic
                        representatives in certain American Republics, <ref target="#pg_378">p.
                            378</ref>. Mr. Warren was Chairman of the State-War-Navy Subcommittee on
                        Latin America.</note> but that the situation is worse now than at any
                    previous time.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward L. Reed</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Counselor of Embassy</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
