<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Guatemala (
                        Long
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d45</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">45</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-02-14T19:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-02-14T19:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-14T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-14T19:00:00-05:00" n="45" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d45">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">710 Conference W &amp; PW/2–1445: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Guatemala</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Long</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-14T18:00:00-06:00">February 14, 1945—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received February 15—1 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>108. The Guatemalan Foreign Minister told me today that it is again uncertain
                    that Guatemala will send a delegation to the conference at Mexico City because
                    he heard this morning from the Guatemalan Ambassador in Mexico that the Aguirre
                    government in El Salvador <pb facs="0052" n="38" xml:id="pg_38"/> was going to
                    be recognized tomorrow by the majority of the American Republics. He said again
                    that the Guatemalan concern is that if Aguirre is recognized he will not turn
                    over the government to Castañeda.</p>
                <p>After some discussion the Minister said that a Guatemalan delegation would attend
                    the conference if the Salvadoran delegation are present only as observers and as
                    representatives of the Salvadoran people and President-elect Castañeda until
                    Castañeda takes office when they would receive full powers. Guatemala would
                    attend under these circumstances even if one or two governments were to
                    recognize Aguirre and even if Aguirre as a technicality commissioned the
                    observers. The Minister said he was telephoning the Guatemalan Ambassador in
                    Washington to try to obtain a clarification of the status of proposed
                    recognition and the status of a proposed delegation from Salvador. He is very
                    anxious to clarify the uncertainty. If Aguirre is recognized, the Minister said
                    arrangements might be made for the Guatemalan Ambassador to Mexico to act as an
                    observer at the conference.</p>
                <p>The Minister said that if Guatemala sends a delegation to the conference it will
                    have two or three “initiatives” which he considers it premature to mention now
                    but that he could say it would be the particular desire of the Guatemalan
                    delegation to cooperate in every possible way with the United States delegation
                    and specifically in the Argentine matter.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Long</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
