<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Brazil (
                        Berle
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d517</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">517</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-05T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="517" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d517">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.32112 RP/10–545</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 3053</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-05">October 5,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received October 12.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Supplementing Embassy confidential telegram no.
                    3044, October 3, 1945, 3 p.m.,<note n="20" xml:id="d517fn1">Not printed.</note>
                    I have the honor to transmit herewith a memorandum<note n="20" xml:id="d517fn2">Not printed.</note> covering a conference held at the Ministry of Foreign
                    Affairs on September 26, 1945, with the Ministers of Finance and Foreign
                    Affairs, the Director of Exchange of the Banco do Brasil S.A. and other
                    representatives of the Brazilian Government, with a view to ascertaining the
                    intentions of the Brazilian authorities as to the completion of the program for
                    the nationalization or liquidation of Axis enterprises in Brazil. As a result of
                    the views expressed at that conference, I hereby confirm the recommendation made
                    in my telegram above mentioned that the approved “intermediate group” names for
                    Brazil be removed from the Proclaimed List of Certain Blocked Nationals during
                    the current month, rather than to postpone such action until the general
                    reduction of the Proclaimed List to the “hard core” in November, or later, under
                    the program indicated in the Department’s telegram no. 2302, September 21, 1945,
                    8 p.m.<note n="20" xml:id="d517fn3">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In this connection, I desire to refer to the Department’s instruction no. 7152,
                    dated May 15, 1945, which outlined the policies to obtain with respect to the
                    continuance of the Proclaimed List in the post-hostilities period and set forth
                    recommendations of the Interdepartmental Committee on Proclaimed List with
                    respect to the reduction and ultimate withdrawal of the Proclaimed List in
                    Brazil. The Embassy was directed to approach the Brazilian Government in
                    accordance with the recommendations contained in the “country memorandum” <pb facs="0687" n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/> transmitted with that instruction and,
                    in its discussions with the Brazilian authorities, to stress the importance of
                    eliminating the remaining Axis spearhead enterprises in this country. The
                    recommendations in the “country memorandum” included the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“3. (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) The Brazilian Government should be
                            informed that this Government had hoped that by V–E day the elimination
                            of Axis Spearheads would have progressed to a point where the Proclaimed
                            List for Brazil, with the exception of Japanese names, could have been
                            completely withdrawn. The Brazilian Government should be asked
                            immediately what its plans are with respect to the elimination of the
                            remaining Spearheads. If feasible, assurances should be obtained from
                            the Brazilian Government that elimination will occur in the near future,
                            and the Brazilian Government should be informed that this Government
                            proposes to withdraw the Proclaimed List for Brazil with the exception
                            of a “hard core” list as defined in the preceding paragraph in the June
                            8 supplement.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">Reference is also made to the Department’s restricted telegram
                    no. 1695, July 7, 1945, 2 p.m.,<note n="21" xml:id="d517fn4">Not printed.</note>
                    emphasizing the importance of ascertaining at an early date the intentions of
                    the Brazilian Government as to the completion of the balance of the Axis
                    replacement program in order to permit establishing arrangements for the
                    reduction of the Proclaimed List to the “hard core” in Brazil and other
                    countries.</p>
                <p>It is felt, and it is understood that the interested authorities in Washington
                    consider, that the performance of Brazil in the field of economic warfare
                    against the Axis has been more satisfactory than that of almost any other
                    Latin-American country. Now that assurances have been received from the
                    Brazilian authorities that it is their intention to complete the nationalization
                    or liquidation of the remaining enterprises in Brazil which are clearly subject
                    to majority control from enemy territory, it is believed that it would be only
                    just to accord a measure of recognition to Brazil’s excellent cooperation by
                    reducing the Proclaimed List in this country to a “hard core” prior to the
                    taking of like action in other countries, many of which have much less favorable
                    records.</p>
                <p>The Embassy has heretofore opposed the proposals to delete any substantial number
                    of the so-called less serious offenders from, the Proclaimed List for Brazil
                    because of the fact that, during the earlier part of this year, the progress
                    being made in the Axis replacement program was far from satisfactory, both
                    because few concerns were being effectively nationalized and because there were
                    indications that certain sectors of the Brazilian Government appeared to be
                    favoring, or at least considering, the reversal of action previously taken in
                    certain important cases, such as Fábrica Nacional de Tambores Ltda. and Hermann
                    Stoltz e Cia. It was felt, rightly or wrongly, that a substantial <pb facs="0688" n="674" xml:id="pg_674"/> reduction in the Proclaimed List would
                    be interpreted as a lack of interest on our part in the completion of the
                    replacement program and further discourage the Director of Exchange, who is a
                    key figure in the administration of the Brazilian controls and whose cooperation
                    with the Embassy has been outstanding.</p>
                <p>During the last few months, in addition to the Embassy’s efforts directed
                    especially to eliciting a statement of the intentions of the Brazilian
                    Government as to the completion of the replacement program, as a part of which
                    there was presented to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs the memorandum of July
                    25, 1945 (a copy of which in translation was transmitted to the Department under
                    cover of Embassy despatch no. 2235 of July 31, 1945<note n="22" xml:id="d517fn5">Neither printed.</note>), the Embassy has delivered several memoranda or
                    notes, as indicated below, in the endeavor to prevent, or to obtain more careful
                    consideration of, certain action which appeared likely to conflict with the
                    objectives of the replacement program.</p>
                <p>[Here follow descriptions of three communications addressed to the Brazilian
                    Government, together with comments regarding various business firms in
                    Brazil.]</p>
                <p>… Therefore, the solution suggested by the Minister of Finance, namely, of
                    eliminating the interests in these Brazilian enterprises owned by German
                    nationals residing in Germany and thereafter maintaining the enterprises under
                    continuing surveillance by the Brazilian authorities, with the cooperation of
                    the Embassy, may be the best practicable solution, taking into account the fact
                    that, as the Minister observed, these enterprises are considered of interest to
                    the economic welfare of Brazil and should be preserved.</p>
                <p>An early expression of views of the Department with reference to the handling of
                    these cases proposed by the Minister of Finance, as outlined herein and in the
                    accompanying memorandum of conversation, will be appreciated. It will of course
                    be incumbent upon the Embassy to give some definite and clear-cut response to
                    his suggestion in the near future.</p>
                <p>It is requested also that the Embassy be notified as promptly as possible of the
                    decision reached on my present recommendation for the elimination of the
                    “intermediate group” names from the Proclaimed List for Brazil during
                        October<note n="23" xml:id="d517fn6">In instructions 7551 and 7552, October
                        5, 1945, the Department indicated removal from the Proclaimed List of this
                        “intermediate group” of names (740.32112A/8–3045, /8–645).</note> and, if
                    such recommendation is approved, of the date on which such elimination will be
                    effected. In the event that there is any uncertainty on the Department’s records
                    as to the names which the Embassy believes should be removed at this time, the
                    Department’s early advices are requested.</p>
                <pb facs="0689" n="675" xml:id="pg_675"/>
                <p>It may be mentioned that the number of petitions for deletion being received from
                    firms and individuals included in the list of less serious offenders is steadily
                    increasing and demands a disproportionate amount of time from the present
                    reduced staff of the Economic Warfare Section, thereby distracting attention
                    from the more important matters. The number of inquiries received from the
                    Brazilian Foreign Office on cases of this nature has also increased noticeably
                    within the last two or three months. It should be borne in mind that some of the
                    “intermediate group” names undoubtedly would have been recommended for
                    individual deletion before now, except for the belief that the reduction to the
                    “hard core” in Brazil would be effected at the latest in September or early
                    October of this year.</p>
                <p>As was stated in my telegram no. 3044, the Ministers of Finance and Foreign
                    Affairs have indicated that they feel it would be desirable and proper to remove
                    from the Proclaimed List at this time the names of the less serious offenders
                    not involved in the replacement program. Furthermore, as was reported in my
                    despatch no. 2338 of August 6, 1945,<note n="24" xml:id="d517fn7">Not
                        printed.</note> Dr. Santos Filho and the Agencia Especial de Defesa
                    Economica have heretofore cleared by far the greater number of the names
                    recommended by the Embassy and approved by the Interdepartmental Committee for
                    removal from the Proclaimed List in the “intermediate group”.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>For the Ambassador: <lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">DuWayne G. Clark</hi>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Commercial Attaché</hi>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
