<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in Brazil ( (Berle))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d562</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">562</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-12-05T17:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-05T17:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recUInGVZ0Y3MeuOS" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-05T17:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-05T17:00:00-05:00" n="562"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d562">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">832.24/12–545: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Berle</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-05T17:00:00-05:00"
                            >December 5, 1945—5 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2711. ReEmb’s 3558, November 30.<note n="96" xml:id="d562fn96">Not
                        printed.</note> Dept is concerned that negotiations of Brazil to secure
                    wheat from Argentina have reached impasse in view of fact emphasized in Dept’s
                    2450 of October 15<note n="97" xml:id="d562fn97">Not printed; in it the
                        Department indicated that United States wheat should be shipped to Brazil
                        only as a last resort (832.24/10–1245).</note> that wheat sent to Brazil
                    from US would have to be subtracted from amounts programmed to liberated areas.
                    Oil and coal are now going to Argentina in considerable amounts and Dept has
                    under consideration means for making available as speedily as possible truck
                    tires without provision of which Emb Buenos Aires declares wheat stocks in
                    Argentina “literally cannot be moved”. Since it is expected provision of these
                    tires will make possible export of wheat from Argentina, it does not appear
                    realistic to make any specific determination at this time regarding shipments of
                    wheat to be made 1946. Furthermore programming is on month to month basis.
                    Program of shipment for December has already been worked out but that for
                    January will be considered at a later date when attention will be given to needs
                    of Brazil along with those of other claimants.</p>
                <p>With regard urgent need for flour to be shipped in December for consumption in
                    Brazil during January, attention of Emb is called to fact reported by Agri that
                    Brazilian purchases of US wheat flour during November alone totalled 911,800
                    cwt. (45,590 short tons) or almost 50 percent more than sum of purchases made 6
                    months May to October. In addition Brazil has been purchasing considerable
                    amounts of flour milled from other than US wheat (i.e. Canadian) for shipment
                    from US and presumably also for shipment from Canada. Precise information
                    concerning amounts already shipped Brazil being sought from Trade. WSA<note
                        n="98" xml:id="d562fn98">War Shipping Administration.</note> reports flour
                    to Brazil being lifted slowly and is quite clear therefore that amounts already
                    purchased and still outstanding for shipment to Brazil are of magnitude to go
                    far toward meeting requirement as given by Emb for shipping in December and
                    consumption in January. 17,000 tons wheat purchased by Brazil for shipment from
                    Galveston reported by WSA to be shipped second week December.</p>
                <pb facs="0728" n="714" xml:id="pg_714"/>
                <p>Immediate problem one of shipping of flour, since export licenses are not
                    required. United Maritime Authority optimistic regarding possibility prompt
                    assignment additional space flour Brazil but states accepted procedure requires
                    representation by Brazilian Government directly to UMA. Brazilian Emb Washington
                    has been so advised by Dept and will presumably present a statement emphasizing
                    need for assigning additional shipping from pool to carry flour Brazil
                        December.<note n="99" xml:id="d562fn99">In a communication dated December
                        14, 1945, from the Office of the Brazilian Commercial Counselor in
                        Washington, the intercession of the Department of State was sought to
                        restore the previous level of Argentine wheat to Brazil; for its part,
                        Brazil would offer 10,000 tires to Argentina to relieve transportation
                        stringencies (832.61311/12–1445).</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Byrnes</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
