<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Mexico (
                        Messersmith
                    ) to the Assistant Secretary of State
                        (
                        Rockefeller
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d65</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">65</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-02-05T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="65" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d65">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">710 Conference W and PW/2–545</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Rockefeller</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi>, D. F.</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-05">February 5,
                        1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Nelson</hi>: I had a talk with Padilla on Friday
                    evening in which we covered a number of things, and I need not tell you that
                    Padilla is exceedingly anxious to do everything in his power to make the
                    February meeting a success. He realizes that while some of the other countries
                    will be making sporadic preparations, or rather, incomplete preparations, that
                    we and Mexico are really the only two countries that will be giving considered
                    thought to all phases of the meeting.</p>
                <p>For this reason, he is naturally very pleased that Bohan and Sanders are here
                    because this will be very helpful. Machold<note n="50a" xml:id="d65fn50a">William F. Machold, Special Representative, Mexican-American Commission for
                        Economic Cooperation; a Technical Officer at the Mexico City
                        Conference.</note> too is going to remain here and I think this is a good
                    thing, and I am going to have Bohan, Sanders and Machold work as a team and with
                    me on all matters affecting the conference.</p>
                <p>Padilla, as you will know from my previous letters, feels so strongly that so
                    much of the success of the meeting will depend on preparation, and there isn’t
                    any doubt but what he and some of the people on the Mexican group are working
                    very hard. The whole attitude of the Mexicans is that they want to work with us
                    because they realize what responsibility rests on us in the inter-American and
                    in the world picture. I don’t think they want to raise any question that is
                    going to make trouble, and I think so far as possible they want to fit their
                    attitude in with ours, to the extent that this is humanly possible, on all the
                    major questions which will be considered.</p>
                <p>Padilla said with regard to Dumbarton Oaks that we ought to have a very complete
                    understanding, that is, the Department and the Ministry here, before the
                    meeting, and if possible, well before the meeting. He says that most of the
                    Latin American countries have very definite views with regard to Dumbarton Oaks.
                    He says that they will want to give expression to these, although some of them
                    have done so in memoranda. He says, as he sees it our attitude could be only one
                    of three. We could accept these suggestions, which he doubts whether we could;
                    we could reject them, which he doubts we should do; or we could indicate that we
                    were taking them into account for background in connection with further
                    conversations in the formulation of the final agreement on world security
                    organization among the big three. He said this was a very rough way of putting
                    it, but he said we would have to work out some way of meeting this point of view
                    of the Latin American States with regard to the proposals as they now stand. <pb facs="0100" n="86" xml:id="pg_86"/> The important thing is that so far as
                    Padilla is concerned, he is ready, I believe, to accommodate the Mexican
                    attitude into the realities of the situation and he knows enough about the big
                    picture to know how difficult our position is and that there are certain things
                    which we can’t say or do now, and that there are certain suggestions with which
                    we can’t agree at this meeting, even though we might be fundamentally in accord
                    with them. Padilla’s view I think is that the most important thing is that we
                    have an understanding of what can be done eventually. I think he has in mind
                    that some of these Foreign Ministers are going to be here perhaps as much as a
                    week before the meeting, or at least three or four days before the meeting, and
                    they will be bound to have conversations with him and perhaps with the President
                    of Mexico,<note n="51" xml:id="d65fn51">Manuel Avila Camacho.</note> and he
                    wants to be sure that before he talks with any of these people before the
                    meeting, he will know pretty well what we have in mind, what we could go along
                    with, and what would be constructive from our point of view.</p>
                <p>The foregoing is a very poor way of stating this problem, but I am going to ask
                    Sanders to write more fully on this matter. You will appreciate, however, what
                    the situation is and what Padilla has in mind, and that all he is thinking of is
                    to be helpful.</p>
                <p>Similarly, Padilla says it will be very important for Mexico and us to know just
                    what each thinks about how this Argentine question is to be handled. Padilla of
                    course is very definitely of the opinion that it can’t come up until the very
                    end of the meeting, if it does come up at all. He believes that there will be
                    several countries which may try to bring it up at the beginning, but that this
                    must be stopped at the outset. Parenthetically here I may say that I think the
                    chances are more that Cuba will be recalcitrant than even Colombia, Venezuela or
                    Ecuador. I think that if we are prepared to make adequate distinction between
                    the Argentine people and the present Argentine regime, which of course we are,
                    we can get an understanding attitude from the Colombians and Venezuelans on this
                    matter.</p>
                <p>Padilla is of the opinion that it will be very difficult to keep from some
                    discussion of the Argentine question at the end of the meeting. He thinks some
                    of the countries will be insistent on that. He doesn’t like the idea but I think
                    he is right when he thinks it has to be done. The form he thinks should be
                    determined by the principal delegates, if possible, very early in the session.
                    Certainly at their first meeting they should decide that at no time during the
                    meeting can the Argentine question be raised until the very end of the regular
                    agenda has been disposed of. He says however he would like to know now what our
                    own thoughts are as to how it can be handled if and when it is <pb facs="0101" n="87" xml:id="pg_87"/> handled at the end of the meeting. His thought is
                    that if it is handled in any way, we are going to come with such overwhelming
                    evidence that there will be no question of an Argentine appearing because even
                    those who may be friendly to the Argentine would realize how useless this would
                    be. I understand that Carl Spaeth is working on the Argentine case and briefing
                    it, and I think this is most important.</p>
                <p>Padilla said he had no idea of a specific character but he did think that one of
                    the things which could be done was for the principal delegates to agree that a
                    permanent committee be set up composed of a certain number of States, to deal
                    with the developments in this Argentine situation and to report to the other
                    American States any developments in that situation of interest, so that if there
                    are developments in the Argentine with respect to the regime or a change of
                    regime which would make any change of attitude on the part of the other American
                    Republics possible, such a change could be considered. He said this was only a
                    very rough thought that he had not developed, but it was one of the things which
                    he thought might be possible.</p>
                <p>He is very sorry that you were not able to come down for the closing meeting of
                    the Joint Economic Commission,<note n="52" xml:id="d65fn52">For documentation
                        concerning this Commission, see <ref target="frus1944v07#pg_1198">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1944, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, pp. 1198</ref> ff.</note> as he hoped to
                    have this opportunity to exchange views with you. Dudley Bonsal has informed me
                    that the Department is sending us as rapidly as it can, drafts and thoughts of
                    ours in the economic and political field, even though they are not final, and
                    this of course, is going to be helpful. Padilla has expressed strongly how much
                    he feels the need of discussing these matters with us and having some common
                    point of view if possible before the Foreign Ministers and delegates and
                    advisors begin to arrive. Of course this does not mean that he has in mind that
                    we are going to set the stage between ourselves, because that would be
                    inadvisable, but I think he is very sound in his thought that, so far as
                    possible, we should have a complete exchange of views in as frank a way as
                    possible and try to reach as common a basis as we can on some of the major
                    matters, at least six or seven days before the meeting. His whole thought of
                    course is to be helpful.</p>
                <p>I should be glad to have your reactions to any of the foregoing.</p>
                <p>With all good wishes [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Messersmith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>[Here follows a postscript in which the Ambassador indicated certain factors
                        in Cuban-United States relations that might affect adversely the interests
                        of the United States at the Conference.]</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
