<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-05-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-05-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="672" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d672">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">625.113/5–945</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 12,078</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-05-09">May 9,
                                1945</date>.<lb/>[Received May 20.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>The Ambassador has the honor to transmit herewith<note n="89" xml:id="d672fn1">Enclosures not printed.</note> copy of a proposal
                            by the Chilean Government to grant the United States, for a period of
                            one year or until a new trade agreement between the two countries may be
                            consummated, a number of tariff concessions formerly granted by Chile to
                            France. The proposal was received by the Embassy on April 21 but its
                            transmission to the Department has been unavoidably delayed by the
                            difficulties in obtaining data on Chile’s imports for periods subsequent
                            to 1942 showing the extent to which exports from the United States and
                            other countries would benefit from the proposed concessions.</p>
                        <p>It will be observed that the Chilean Government declares that it desires
                            to adopt measures designed to expand trade with the United States and
                            other Allied nations in accordance with a policy of mutual concessions
                            and close cooperation and thereby effectively implement the principles
                            sponsored by the United Nations and the economic objectives of both the
                            Atlantic Charter<note n="90" xml:id="d672fn2">For text, see <ref target="frus1941v01#pg_367">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1941, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 367</ref>.</note> and the recent
                            Mexico City Conference.</p>
                        <p>It will be further observed that Chile, ostensibly as a gesture of
                            appreciation of the frank and loyal cooperation manifested by the
                            American delegation in connection with the agreements concluded at
                            Mexico City, states that it is disposed at this time to grant import
                            duty reductions without seeking any concessions in return.</p>
                        <p>Without any thought of questioning the reasons advanced by Chile for
                            proposing duty reductions at this juncture, the Embassy feels that it
                            should point out that the abrogation of the Franco-Chilean Commercial
                                <pb facs="0844" n="830" xml:id="pg_830"/> Convention<note n="92" xml:id="d672fn3">
                                <hi rend="italic">British and Foreign State Papers</hi>, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">cxxxv</hi>, p. 1.</note> in February of this
                            year combined with the increased gold customs surcharge on imports,
                            which became effective at the beginning of 1945, have resulted in the
                            Government being roundly criticized by the press and various influential
                            organizations for raising the cost of merchandise on one hand while on
                            the other it is allegedly making every effort to control and reduce
                            prices within the country. In addition, the Government has been subject
                            to strong pressures by persons in private and commercial life to adopt
                            measures of relief. Importers of the products formerly favored by the
                            preferential duties of the Franco-Chilean Commercial Convention, have
                            threatened not to clear their shipments from the customs claiming they
                            would rather abandon the merchandise or return it to the country of
                            origin than pay the higher imposts.<note n="*" xml:id="d672fn4">See
                                Embassy’s Despatch No. 11,976 of March 15, 1945, entitled
                                “Additional data on effects of cancellation of French-Chilean
                                Commercial Convention and increase in customs surcharge”, file No.
                                631/630. [Footnote in the original. Despatch 11,976 not
                                printed.]</note> The Government, consequently, is faced with a loss
                            of customs revenues. These considerations, the Embassy is convinced,
                            have strongly influenced the decision to propose reductions in certain
                            import duties.</p>
                        <p>For the information and guidance of the Department, there is enclosed
                            such statistical material as the Embassy has been able to compile from
                            official sources on the products imported into Chile in 1943 under 76 of
                            the 82 tariff items which would be subject to lower rates. No figures
                            have been obtainable on six items, namely, numerals 371, 378, 379, 380,
                            381 and 383, all covering cotton textiles. There is no detailed
                            statistical information on the 82 tariff items for 1944.</p>
                        <p>The total value in gold pesos of the imports corresponding to the 76
                            tariff items is 34,603,286 gold pesos. The leading supplier was Great
                            Britain with 15,351,285 gold pesos followed respectively by the United
                            States with 7,525,419 gold pesos, Brazil with 6,022,767 gold pesos, and
                            Argentina with 4,349,515 gold pesos. All other countries account for
                            only 1,355,300 gold pesos. Brazil followed by Great Britain were the
                            principal suppliers of the cotton textile items on which no figures have
                            been obtainable. If statistical information for 1943 were available for
                            all 82 tariff items it would no doubt show the position of the suppliers
                            to be Great Britain first with Brazil a close second, followed by the
                            United States in third place and Argentina holding fourth place.</p>
                        <p>An agreement in force between Chile and Great Britain, and treaties
                            between Chile and Brazil and Argentina give these countries most <pb facs="0845" n="831" xml:id="pg_831"/> favored nation treatment.
                            Assuming that during the next 12 months they retain the positions held
                            in 1943 as Chile’s suppliers of the tariff items subject to concessions
                            then the proposed Chilean duty reductions would prove to be more
                            important to British and Brazilian trade than to the commerce of the
                            United States.</p>
                        <p>It will be observed that the Chilean Government states that a note in
                            acknowledgment of the note containing its proposal would constitute an
                            agreement in the matter, and that the agreement would be construed as
                            broadening the existing <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>After the Department has had the opportunity to consider the Chilean
                            proposition, the Embassy would appreciate receiving its views and a
                            draft text of a note of acceptance of the Chilean proposal in the event
                            it is believed that an agreement can be consummated in the manner that
                            has been suggested.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>