<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Mexico (
                        Messersmith
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d73</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">73</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-02-13T21:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-02-13T21:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-13T21:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-13T21:00:00-05:00" n="73" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d73">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">710 Conference W and PW/2–1345: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico City</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-13T20:00:00-06:00">February 13, 1945—8 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received February 14—5:45 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>175. I have just had a talk with the Department’s representatives who are here
                    and who have been having conversations with our Mexican friends during the last
                    days. While we have been hampered by our inability to indicate the thinking of
                    our Government, our Mexican friends have been quite free in the expression of
                    their views. In view of the frequent delays in the airmail, also that we are not
                    yet altogether sure of the secrecy of our direct wire, I have asked Bohan, in
                    view of the importance of Department’s having this information without delay,
                        <pb facs="0125" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/> to transmit over the telephone the
                    views expressed to us by our Mexican friends in the last few days without his
                    commenting thereon.</p>
                <p>We can secure the reaffirmation of liberal trade policies at the coming
                    conference. This is important since it sets the objectives to be achieved, but
                    if nothing further is offered by way of a program, it will cause the keenest
                    disillusionment since the road by which we propose to reach those objectives is
                    of primary interest to Latin America. To disregard implementation will actually
                    jeopardize the ultimate and real acceptance of the principles underlying the
                    objectives. The Mexicans are convinced that continuance of many controls,
                    including tariffs, is essential to their protection and development for many
                    years to come, and as these same opinions are widespread throughout Latin
                    America, no real progress can be made unless we are prepared to present a
                    program which is more effective in meeting transition and postwar problems than
                    present unilateral control systems. Hence our thinking must be less adamant and
                    we must realize that some form of protection is required to promote even
                    economic industrialization, international agreements may be required to protect
                    living standards and efficient utilization of exchange balances is not to be
                    condemned per se.</p>
                <p>Without offering constructive solutions for immediate and long term problems we
                    are not only retarding implementation of liberal trade principles but almost
                    certainly creating a situation on which the conference may be founded [<hi rend="italic">founder?</hi>].</p>
                <p>As we have continuously indicated from here, the probabilities are that the
                    political problems before the meeting can be resolved without difficulty
                    provided an adequately favorable atmosphere is created by the approach to
                    economic problems.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Messersmith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
