<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Cuba (
                        Norweb
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d773</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">773</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-11T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="773" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d773">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">837.5017/10–1145: Airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Norweb</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-11">October 11,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received October 15—6 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>A–1944. Embassy desires to submit following comments with respect to Cuban price
                    stabilization activities, in case Cuban delegation in 1946–crop sugar
                    negotiations asks for re-establishment of price stabilization concessions for
                    shipments of United States rice wheat flour, and lard: <list>
                        <label>(1)</label>
                        <item>Cuban Office of Price Regulation and Supply at present is not
                            enforcing effectively any ceiling prices for foodstuffs. Its activities
                            have a restraining influence on inflationary price advances only insofar
                            as a few large wholesalers, mainly affiliates of United States
                            companies, observe ceiling prices because they would be vulnerable to
                            discriminatory attack if they participated in the general
                            noncompliance.</item>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>The ORPA because of internal dissension and public indifference is
                            growing progressively weaker and prospects are negligible for its
                            rehabilitation. Price ceilings for most foodstuffs probably <pb facs="0955" n="941" xml:id="pg_941"/> will be continued in 1946 only
                            as a matter of general policy with little actual enforcement if faced
                            with inflationary pressure.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>Any price concessions on our part, such as another special subsidy on
                            wheat flour, will have negligible effect on the Cuban Government’s price
                            policy or on the trend in cost of living.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>It appears desirable therefore to omit price stabilization concessions in
                    negotiating for the 1946 sugar crop. Presumably the above factors are
                    supplemented also by changes in United States stabilization policies as a result
                    of the war’s end.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Norweb</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
