<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the Dominican Republic ( (Scherer) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d807</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">807</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1945-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec12oVQ7f61LEbi0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Domestic politics</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="807"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d807">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">839.00/12–1145</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Dominican Republic</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Scherer</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 527</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Ciudad Trujillo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-11">December 11,
                            1945</date>.<lb/>[Received January 2, 1946.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Embassy’s
                    telegram no. 475 of December 8, 1945<note n="32" xml:id="d807fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> with reference to an interview with President Trujillo and
                    others at the National Palace on December 7 concerning the President’s request
                    to certain American sugar companies operating in the Dominican Republic to
                    engage in informational activities.</p>
                <p>On receipt of the Department’s telegram no. 362 of December 5, 1945<note n="32"
                        xml:id="d807fn2">Not printed.</note> an appointment was made at my request
                    to See President Trujillo at noon on December 7. When I arrived at the Palace,
                    Mr. E. I. Kilbourne, of the West Indies Sugar Company, was in the President’s
                    waiting room and he remained there during the early part of the conversation
                    between the President, Foreign Minister Peña Batlle and myself.</p>
                <p>I recalled to the President our meeting of November 17 in his office, at which
                    time I outlined the Department’s policy concerning noninterference in local
                    political affairs of other countries by American individuals or companies. I
                    added that the Department of State had instructed the Embassy to address letters
                    restating this policy to the three sugar companies whose representatives had
                    attended the previous meeting and I wished to have the President know of that
                    action. I then reviewed in brief the contents of the identical letters which
                    have been sent to Messrs. Fox, Kilbourne and Hennessey (copy enclosed<note
                        n="32" xml:id="d807fn3">Not printed.</note>). The President said that he had
                    no idea of asking American <pb facs="1006" n="992" xml:id="pg_992"/> interests
                    to become involved in Dominican politics; in fact, his two basic policies in
                    this connection with American companies are (1) to keep them from engaging in
                    local Dominican politics and (2) to assist them to operate successfully as far
                    as he can.</p>
                <p>The President continued that his request of November 17 to the sugar companies
                    was merely for the purpose of obtaining information as to any interruption of
                    work to which they might become subject. He then called Mr. Kilbourne, who had
                    obviously been informed of the meeting in advance. Mr. Kilbourne stated that he
                    would be glad to get such a letter from the Embassy as it would enable him and
                    his associates to clarify the situation. He said that his company has not
                    engaged in political activities in the Dominican Republic, nor does he know of a
                    single instance of any American company’s making any campaign contribution here.
                    He stated that his company’s policy is to support the administration in power,
                    whatever it may be.</p>
                <p>Up to this point no one had mentioned the fear of Communism which had played such
                    an important part in the meeting of November 17. Consequently, I stated to the
                    President that it was his mention of Communism then which led me to restate the
                    Department’s policy on political interference by American companies. The
                    President brushed my statement aside by saying that he did not intend to specify
                    communists only in connection with the interruption of work at sugar Centrals.
                    He is interested in learning of such interruptions, whatever the cause may
                    be.</p>
                <p>Peña Batlle then spoke up, saying that the Government would make every possible
                    effort to see that the sugar crop is ground since Government finances depend to
                    such a large extent on revenues from sugar operations. In fact, without these
                    revenues the Foreign Minister said the Trujillo government would fall.</p>
                <p>At the end of the conversation President Trujillo reiterated his two basic
                    points, that of non-interference in domestic politics by American interests, and
                    his firm support of them in carrying on their activities. It appears certain to
                    me now that both the Dominican Government and the American sugar companies
                    operating here well understand the view of the United States Government in this
                    connection. There is still room for doubt, however, as to what the American
                    companies will do. After the meeting at the palace, Mr. Kilbourne came to the
                    Embassy and among other things said he had not had <pb facs="1007" n="993"
                        xml:id="pg_993"/> to report any individuals to the President so far. He
                    stated that he would follow all proper requests of the Trujillo government as
                    long as it is in power. Mr. Kilbourne explained that his company’s policy of
                    supporting the Government consisted of obeying its laws, but the Embassy
                    strongly suspects that at times the support takes on a more positive form. He
                    said he would study with great interest the Embassy’s letter and would present
                    his reply in person.</p>
                <p>The Embassy will endeavor to keep close watch over developments and inform the
                    Department promptly.</p>
                <p>Although I have had only two interviews with the President, I was impressed by
                    his equanimity. If he is apprehensive as to his future, he has given me no sign
                    whatsoever. He appears to be confident, serene and smiling. His associates are
                    not so composed, however, and both Peña Batlle and Emilio Garcia Godoy, the
                    Dominican Ambassador at Washington, appear to be nervous and concerned.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">George E. Scherer</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
