<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-02-26T01:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-02-26T01:00:00-05:00" n="83" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d83">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">710 Conference (W &amp; PW)/2–2645:
                                Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">American Delegation</gloss>
                                    to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico City</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-02-26T00:00:00-06:00">February 26, 1945—midnight</date>.<lb/>[Received February
                                    27—11:55 a.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>256. From the Secretary. Members of the United States delegation met
                                at 9 a.m., February 24th. General Embick announced that joint
                                Chiefs-of-Staff were in agreement that the Colombian resolution
                                regarding non-aggression was entirely satisfactory in that if
                                approved it would constitute a regional pact which could be
                                integrated into the world security system. General Embick will
                                consult with the Secretary at the earliest opportunity concerning
                                this matter.</p>
                            <p>Mr. Rockefeller reported that Argentine influence seeking to break up
                                the solidarity with which the principal American Governments view
                                the Argentine Government was meeting with no success. United States
                                Steering Committee met at Reforma Hotel 2 p.m., February 24
                                discussing fully topics of Inter-American solidarity. General
                                Embick, Dr. Pasvolsky and Judge Hackworth joined in free discussion
                                outlining respectively the importance of this subject from a
                                military, political and economic viewpoint. It was determined that
                                the solidarity of the Americas is essential to the defense of the
                                United States.</p>
                            <p>There followed a discussion concerning the feasibility of accepting
                                the Uruguayan and Colombian proposals. The Colombian proposal
                                provides for collaboration of the American Republics against any
                                active aggression; and a saving clause encompasses modification upon
                                the creation of a world organization. Ambassador Berle and Judge
                                Hackworth will consult between themselves and with Dr. Pasvolsky on
                                the matter of immediate application of the Colombian resolution,
                                which provides for joint alternative action against an aggressor
                                following consultation.</p>
                            <p>Resolution regarding military cooperation also was approved by this
                                Committee.</p>
                            <p>1. Sub-committee of Committee III (Inter-American system) dealing
                                with matters pertaining to Inter-American organization conducted a
                                discussion concerning the proposals relating to Inter-American
                                solidarity against aggression made by Uruguay, Brazil and Colombia.
                                A sub-committee composed of representatives of Colombia, Uruguay,
                                Brazil, Mexico and the United States was appointed to consider these
                                proposals.</p>
                            <p>Committees IV and V on postwar economic and social problems of the
                                war and transitional period were instructed to continue their
                                discussion of economic topics, and Mr. Clayton will on Tuesday
                                February 27 make a statement of principles underlying Inter-American
                                economic relations.</p>
                            <pb facs="0143" n="129" xml:id="pg_129"/>
                            <p>At a meeting of the Steering Committee of the Conference held at
                                10:30 a.m., February 26 Dr. Padilla, the Chairman, announced that
                                certain groups are exerting considerable pressure to the end that
                                the Conference resolve upon a break with Spain. He said that Mexico
                                would not be involved in such a contingency since his country
                                maintains no diplomatic relations with the Spanish Government. He
                                added his opinion that the matter might possibly be satisfactorily
                                disposed of by a statement that the Conference does not deal with
                                matters in which this Continent is not involved. The Uruguayan
                                delegate held that the Conference should pass a resolution welcoming
                                the establishment of a democratic system in Spain, alleging that
                                this would be desirable because of the interest in Spanish affairs
                                of the American nations who are actively engaged in the war, and in
                                view of Spain’s proximity to a theater of the war but he expressed
                                the belief that any country regardless of its location has a full
                                right to oppose the establishment or continuation of a Nazi or
                                Fascist Government wherever this might be. He preferred to use the
                                term “Democratic system” rather than “Republican”, since it would
                                permit Spain to establish a constitutional monarchy if that is what
                                it desires. A full discussion resulted in the unanimous adoption of
                                Dr. Padilla’s suggestion, and the Uruguayan delegate withdrew his
                                views.</p>
                            <p>Please repeat essence of this and future summaries to President.
                                Also, I suggest if not already done that this summary and previous
                                and future ones be turned over to information committee for
                                preparation of appropriate circular information telegrams to our
                                missions in the American Republics. [Stettinius.]</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>