<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by the Ambassador to Ecuador (Scotten), Temporarily in Washington, of
                        a Conversation With the Ecuadoran Ambassador (Galo
                        Plaza)</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d838</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">838</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-08T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="838" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d838">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24532/10–845</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador to Ecuador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Scotten</hi>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily in Washington, of
                        a Conversation With the Ecuadoran Ambassador</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Galo
                        Plaza</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-08">October 8,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Galápagos matters arose in conversation with Galo Plaza at luncheon today. I
                    stated that I had not seen Wayne Taylor and had only discussed the matter in a
                    general way at the Department but that what I was puzzled about was what was the
                    Ecuadoran understanding as to the amount that the United States would set aside
                    for the use of the base as provided in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    which the Minister of Foreign Affairs and I had signed. He stated that the
                    Ecuadoran understanding was that the full amount of $20,000,000 would be set
                    aside and used to liquidate the $20,000,000 loan. He stated that nothing
                    specific had been said in the memorandum, although Nelson Rockefeller’s
                        letter<note n="56" xml:id="d838fn56">Letter of August 7, 1945, to the
                        Ecuadoran Ambassador, not printed.</note> mentioned the sum of $20,000,000.
                    I inquired, as a hypothetical question, whether if the United States should set
                    aside a lesser sum, let us say $10,000,000, the Ecuadorans would be <pb facs="1037" n="1023" xml:id="pg_1023"/> prepared to reimburse the Bank for
                    the remaining $10,000,000. He stated that it is the feeling of the President and
                    the Minister of Foreign Affairs that unless the entire $20,000,000 were set
                    aside to liquidate the loan, Ecuador should simply leave the United States in
                    possession of the bases with no question of compensation being mentioned. In
                    other words, he created the impression that Ecuador realized it would have to
                    yield to <hi rend="italic">force majeure</hi> and allow us to remain in the
                    Galápagos, but that the Government felt that for internal political reasons it
                    could not actually agree to a lesser amount than the $20,000,000. He stated that
                    this was understood by Messrs. Rockefeller and Avra Warren<note n="57" xml:id="d838fn57">Chairman, State-War-Navy Subcommittee on Latin
                        America.</note> and they could probably explain this to the Department.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert M. Scotten</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
