<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Henry Dearborn of the
                        Division of North and West Coast Affairs</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d839</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">839</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-16T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="839" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d839">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24522/10–1645</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by Mr. Henry Dearborn of the
                        Division of North and West Coast Affairs</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-16">October 16,
                            1945</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#nowrap #top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Export-Import Bank: Mr. Taylor, Mr. Machold, Mr.
                            Chase</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Embassy of Ecuador: Ambassador Plaza, Dr.
                            Laso</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Department of State: Ambassador Scotten, Mr.
                            Briggs, Mr. Flack, Mr. Stenger, Mr. Dearborn</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>A meeting was held today in Mr. Taylor’s office for the purpose of making certain
                    that the United States and Ecuadoran Governments entertained a similar
                    understanding of matters relating to the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>
                    signed by representatives of the two Governments in Quito on September 1, 1945.
                    There had been reason to suppose that these matters required clarification in
                    view of statements which Ambassador Plaza made during his recent trip to
                    Ecuador.</p>
                <p>The first subject discussed was “dollar requirements”. Mr. Taylor explained that
                    this expression as used in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> indicated
                    that the Bank was only laying the basis for a loan to cover those expenditures
                    under the Ecuadoran development program which were to be made in dollars. He
                    explained that the loan would not be applicable to sucre expenditures for local
                    labor or local materials. Ambassador Plaza stated that he had not understood
                    this previously and added that if this were the case his Government would not
                    have sufficient funds to carry out the projects recommended by the preliminary
                    studies mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>. He said that the
                    sucre requirements <pb facs="1038" n="1024" xml:id="pg_1024"/> would be beyond
                    the means of Ecuador. Mr. Taylor replied that the Bank necessarily followed this
                    policy in respect to practically all of its loans to foreign countries and that
                    it could not very well make an exception in the case of Ecuador. The Bank would,
                    he emphasized, be in an impossible situation if it undertook to finance the
                    deficits of foreign Governments. Ambassador Plaza said that he understood this.
                    He inquired as to whether the Bank could not find some way to finance a part of
                    the sucre requirements as it had in some cases in the past, but to this Mr.
                    Taylor remarked that the war was over and no such practice would be continued.
                    Ambassador Scotten asked if there might not be some way around the difficulty
                    which the Ecuadorans faced in view of the Bank’s policy. Dr. Laso suggested that
                    the sucre requirements of the development program might be included in the
                    Ecuadoran appropriations for the Ministry of Public Works so that these
                    requirements could be arranged for when the yearly national budget was drawn up.
                    Mr. Taylor replied that it was in just such a way that he anticipated sucre
                    requirements would be taken care of.</p>
                <p>At this point Mr. Taylor suggested that it was useless to discuss details as to
                    the money to be used for the construction of the projects themselves since,
                    until the preliminary surveys were completed, no one knew what the projects
                    would be. He stressed that the Bank had agreed to make one million dollars
                    available for the preliminary surveys, that only dollar requirements were
                    concerned therewith, and that a considerable period would elapse before there
                    would be any question of sucres; the selection of an engineering firm and the
                    receipt of its report would be time-consuming factors. Mr. Briggs asked how long
                    it would be before the survey was completed. It was Ambassador Plaza’s opinion
                    that the whole preliminary work might take two years but that some parts of it
                    could be completed within six months. He said he was basing his opinion on talks
                    with prospective engineering firms. Ambassador Plaza was further of the opinion
                    that work could be begun after particular studies were terminated without
                    waiting for the completion of the countrywide survey.</p>
                <p>The question of the amount of the loan came up. It was clear that every one
                    present understood that $20,000,000 was a ceiling figure beyond which the credit
                    mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> would not be expected to
                    go. It was equally clear that the Eximbank had not committed itself to lend
                    Ecuador a total of $20,000,000. The way was open up to that amount if Ecuador
                    offered adequate security to satisfy the Bank.</p>
                <p>Security for the loan led to a discussion of the tie-up between the loan and the
                    Galápagos base treaty. Ambassador Plaza said that he understood <pb facs="1039" n="1025" xml:id="pg_1025"/> that Ecuador had not been promised $20,000,000
                    in return for permitting the United States to operate a Galápagos base. He
                    reviewed, accurately, the loan and base negotiations since the Estrada mission
                    of September 1944<note n="58" xml:id="d839fn58">Victor Emilio Estrada visited
                        Washington to discuss financial matters as a personal representative of the
                        Ecuadoran President.</note> and pointed out that he and Mr. Estrada had been
                    told at that time that no discussion of a loan could take place until the matter
                    of a military base was settled. He recalled that Estrada had been seeking a
                    $20,000,000 loan, that that figure had been mentioned upon numerous occasions
                    since Estrada’s visit, and that in consequence of this chain of events the
                    Ecuadoran people had come to think of the Galápagos base as being worth
                    $20,000,000. Ambassador Plaza correctly said that his Government had been asked
                    several months ago by us to say how much it wished to receive in return for
                    permitting us to operate a Galápagos base but that his Government had not been
                    able to make a suggestion. He added that he understood that the State Department
                    had not been able to obtain a definite figure from the War and Navy Departments.
                    (It was evident that Ambassador Plaza understood the situation very well and
                    that he realized that the Department of State was still seeking an answer to the
                    question: how much will the United States pay for a Galápagos base?)</p>
                <p>As for the minimum amount Ecuador would accept for permitting us to operate a
                    base, Ambassador Plaza had no clear conception. He did say that if his country
                    were offered seven, eight or nine million dollars he believed it would simply
                    leave the United States in the Archipelago without a treaty. However, he
                    expressed his confidence that there would not be a “shot-gun wedding” and that
                    some agreement would be reached.</p>
                <p>Ambassador Plaza brought up the question of the draft treaty pertaining to the
                    Galápagos base. He explained how no reference to payment had been mentioned
                    therein so that the Department of State and the Government of Ecuador could
                    complete a draft for the use of the base while the matter of payment was being
                    held up pending a decision as to the amount. He said that he had discussed the
                    draft with his Government during his recent visit to Ecuador and that a number
                    of changes had been suggested. He was prepared to bring the altered draft in for
                    discussion with Mr. Braden as soon as Mr. Braden was ready to discuss the
                    matter. The Department would, he hoped, have present the necessary military
                    personnel so that he would not have to repeat his remarks in further
                    meetings.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
