<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Ecuador (
                        Scotten
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d849</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">849</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-12-08T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-12-08T16:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-08T16:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-08T16:00:00-05:00" n="849" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d849">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.24522/12–845: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Ecuador</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Scotten</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Quito</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-08T16:00:00-05:00">December 8, 1945—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 11:12 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>861. When the Minister Foreign Office handed me this morning note 298 transmitted
                    to the Dept in my 860, Dec 8, 1945,<note n="72" xml:id="d849fn72">Not
                        printed.</note> he stated that the President urgently requests for the sake
                    of public opinion here that the War Dept announce immediately a definite date
                    for the return of the Salinas base. The Minister explained that he regretted to
                    be so urgent about this matter and that any date in the near future would be
                    satisfactory, but what the President desired, was to be able to inform Congress
                    of a definite date before Congress adjourns next Tuesday.<note n="73" xml:id="d849fn73">In telegram 715, December 10, 1945, the Department
                        informed the Embassy that the War Department had indicated that the Salinas
                        base would be turned over on or before February l, 1946
                        (811.24522/12–845).</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="1047" n="1033" xml:id="pg_1033"/>
                <p>The Minister further informed me that while his Govt is entirely exposed [<hi rend="italic">disposed</hi>] to permit transit rights for our airplanes
                    after the base is turned back to Ecuador, the President prefers to make this
                    arrangement after the base is returned instead of making it appear to the public
                    here that the granting of these rights is a condition which we have imposed for
                    securing the return of the base.</p>
                <p>The Minister further explained that it would be more acceptable to public opinion
                    for the American technicians which remain here to be under the direct control of
                    our Aviation Mission than for these technicians to be under the control of the
                    Caribbean Defense Command. He explained that should the technicians remain under
                    the control of the Caribbean Defense Command, it would create the impression
                    that we were actually maintaining an American base at Salinas, whereas, if they
                    are placed under the control of the Air Mission no such impression will
                    exist.</p>
                <p>In general, I perceive no serious objection to the Ecuadoran position as set
                    forth above and I believe that no trouble will be experienced in obtaining
                    transit rights, etc. Furthermore, as the maintenance of the small group of
                    technicians was actually suggested to me by Major General Walsh as being in our
                    own interests I am hoping that this group can be attached to our Air Mission
                    without expense to the Ecuadoran Govt. Reference my 841, Dec 4, noon.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotten</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
