<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Mexico (
                        Messersmith
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d941</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">941</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-06-22T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-06-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-06-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="941" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d941">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">812.51/6–2245</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Messersmith</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 24,997</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">México</hi>, D. F.</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-06-22">June 22,
                        1945</date>.<lb/>[Received June 26.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to refer to conversations which I have had
                    during the course of this year with the Department and with the Export-Import
                    Bank with reference to loans desired by the Mexican Government. I do not make
                    reference to the specific despatches in the Department on this matter as they
                    are readily available in its files.</p>
                <p>The Department is aware that as a result of conversations which I had with the
                    President of Mexico and with the Foreign Office and later with the late
                    President Roosevelt, Secretary Stettinius, and officers of the Department, and
                    with the Export-Import Bank, the requests of the Mexican Government for loans
                    were fully set forth. A loan was desired for the purchase of railway equipment
                    in the United States for the Mexican National Lines; a further loan for road
                    construction; and a loan for rural electrification.</p>
                <p>The Mexican Government expressed a preference that the loan for railway equipment
                    to be purchased in the United States be considered first. As a result of
                    conversations in Washington between the Minister of Hacienda of Mexico,
                    Licenciado Suárez, and Mr. Espinosa de los Monteros of the Nacional Financiera,
                    with the Export-Import Bank a credit of 15,000,000 dollars was extended to the
                    Mexican Government through the Nacional Financiera, the proceeds to be used for
                    the purchase of new equipment in the United States for the National Railway
                    Lines of Mexico. This loan has been completed and the credit is available to the
                    Mexican Government. I may say that this Embassy considers this loan as a sound
                    loan in every respect and a wise one for our Government to extend through the
                    Export-Import Bank.</p>
                <p>The Mexican Government indicated that next in preference for consideration was
                    the road loan. It will be recalled in this connection that in 1941, the
                    Export-Import Bank had extended a credit to the Mexican Government in the amount
                    of 30,000,000 dollars to be used at the rate of not more than 10,000,000 dollars
                    a year. The Mexican Government has used 10,000,000 dollars of this credit. Owing
                    to the more favorable position of the Mexican Treasury, the very extensive
                    road-building program of Mexico was carried forward without calling beyond these
                    10,000,000 dollars on the above-mentioned credit. It may be said in this
                    connection that Mexico has in the meantime carried forward a very well planned
                    road construction program. The roads are well built, at reasonable cost, and the
                    whole program has been very carefully and soundly worked out. It is to the
                    credit of the Mexican <pb facs="1185" n="1171" xml:id="pg_1171"/> Government
                    that, although it had these 20,000,000 dollars available with the Export-Import
                    Bank, it continued this road construction program out of its own resources.</p>
                <p>In view of the less favorable prospect for receipts by the Treasury due to the
                    diminishing of the purchase program of strategic materials, and for other
                    reasons which it is not necessary to go into here, the Mexican Government has
                    found it necessary to have this recourse to further credits. It has, therefore,
                    requested the extension of the 20,000,000 dollar unused credit and an additional
                    10,000,000 dollars. This Embassy gave its strong approval to favorable
                    consideration by our Government and of the Export-Import Bank to the granting of
                    these credits. I am now in receipt of a letter from Mr. Wayne Taylor, the
                    President of the Export-Import Bank, dated June 16, of which a copy is attached
                    hereto (Enclosure 1).<note n="84" xml:id="d941fn84">Not printed.</note> In this
                    letter Mr. Taylor states that the Export-Import Bank has decided to renew the
                    20,000,000 dollar unused credit making it available until December 31, 1946. Mr.
                    Taylor states that the Bank has also approved an additional credit of 10,000,000
                    dollars, the proceeds of which are to be used for the purchase of road-building
                    equipment and machinery and supplies in the United States.</p>
                <p>During a conversation with the President of Mexico on June 20, 1 informed him of
                    the substance of Mr. Taylor’s letter of June 16, and he expressed his very real
                    appreciation of the consideration given this matter by our Government and the
                    Export-Import Bank. He expressed full appreciation of the fact that the
                    10,000,000 dollar additional credit is extended by the Bank for the purchase of
                    road-building equipment, etc., in the United States. I also explained to him the
                    reasons why the rate of interest was now increased from 3.6% to 4%. The
                    President was particularly appreciative that no restrictions were placed upon
                    the 20,000,000 dollars which represent the renewed credit. I should like to say
                    in this connection that I think the action of the Export-Import Bank in renewing
                    the 20,000,000 dollar credit without restriction was wise and sound and will
                    find its understanding in a favorable reflection in our relationships with
                    Mexico.</p>
                <p>[Here follows report on arrangements for signing road-credit loan agreement with
                    Export-Import Bank in Washington and comment by the Ambassador on additional,
                    later loan for rural electrification.]</p>
                <p>I wish to express to the Department and to the Export-Import Bank the
                    appreciation of this Embassy for the sympathetic and understanding manner in
                    which the credit for railway equipment and for road construction has been
                    considered. I consider that the action of the Department and of the Bank is a
                    further measure in the consolidation of our relationships with Mexico. The
                    understanding and <pb facs="1186" n="1172" xml:id="pg_1172"/> sympathetic manner
                    in which the Bank has handled these requests is deserved by the performance of
                    Mexico in recent years in reestablishing her credit and her financial situation,
                    and we have gone a long way in consolidating our situation by our action. The
                    Export-Import Bank has been and is, I believe, going to be one of the most
                    effective instruments which we have to implement and consolidate a constructive
                    foreign policy, and the constructive and sympathetic manner in which the Bank
                    has handled its operations with Mexico has strengthened the prestige of our
                    country in many ways.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">George S. Messersmith</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
