<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The President of Nicaragua ( (Somoza) ) to President Roosevelt</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d950</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">950</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1944-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1944-12-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1944-12-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1944-12-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="950"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d950">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">817.24/4–745</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The President of Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Somoza</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to"
                            >Roosevelt</persName>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Managua</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1944-12-23">December 23,
                            1944</date>.<note n="1" xml:id="d950fn1">This message did not reach
                            President Roosevelt until April 7, 1945. It was delivered on March 30 by
                            Nicaraguan Ambassador Guillermo Sevilla-Sacasa to Acting Secretary of
                            State Grew, who in turn transmitted it to President Roosevelt at Warm
                            Springs, Georgia.</note>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Very Esteemed Friend</hi>: A request of my Government for
                    ten thousand Springfield rifles and the necessary cartridges for them is pending
                    in the Department of War of the United States; and I have thought that the
                    reasons which may be responsible for the failure to reach a prompt decision, or
                    which may be alleged for not taking favorable action, must be the recent
                    developments which have taken place in certain Central American Republics or the
                    idea that the purpose is to increase the armament of the National Guard.</p>
                <p>With this in mind I am addressing you directly to request your timely
                    intervention, which would add to the many reasons for gratitude to you which my
                    Government has.</p>
                <p>The case of Nicaragua, Mr. President, is very distinct from the other countries
                    of Central America. The reign of internal peace continues unchanged in
                    Nicaragua, and its conduct continues to be closely linked—as it will be in all
                    circumstances—to the interests which the United States is defending in the war
                    and to all the pacts and exigencies to which it is obligated as a United
                    Nation.</p>
                <p>You may have the most absolute security that the arms in the hands of the
                    National Guard organized by officers of the American Army are in friendly hands
                    which will do honor to the cause of democracy.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, there is no intent to increase the arsenal, but rather one to
                    change old rifles for new ones; and this matter has become so urgent that at
                    least five thousand rifles are absolutely indispensable to us. This is so to the
                    degree that my Government would return an equal number, in as much as it is
                    interested only in the quality and not in the quantity of this type of arm.</p>
                <pb facs="1208" n="1194" xml:id="pg_1194"/>
                <p>The disturbed history of Central America gives testimony to the constant purpose
                    of Mexico to exercise a direct influence in the life of these countries and in
                    the organization of their Governments as a means of separating them from the
                    United States. There has been a recrudescence of this purpose in these last
                    years with certain new factors involved.</p>
                <p>This purpose of Mexico, which does not hide its repugnance for the United States,
                    has encountered and will continue to encounter my opposition and that of
                    Nicaragua, (which has) become a stronghold for the closest collaboration and
                    friendship with your nation on the worthy basis of Good Neighborship.</p>
                <p>Nicaragua is likewise a stronghold and breakwater against the communism which
                    diligently seeks to infiltrate into Central America as an aspect of Mexican
                    policy and as a disquieting problem for the future.</p>
                <p>It does not escape my thoughts that sooner or later our continent will have to
                    face the influence of Russia, and that the United States will take the
                    leadership—as today—with the same courage and vision devoted to the defense of
                    our future. But logically it will have to count on the cooperation of other
                    countries, which will be in the same trench and which will share in every way
                    its struggle and its fate.</p>
                <p>There are thus reasons of a different nature from internal needs properly
                    speaking, which militate in favor of the request made in this letter and which
                    excuse yet more the calling of your attention when it is occupied with knotty
                    problems. The National Guard, as an army watchful over the destiny of America,
                    should without losing a sense of proportions be maintained with efficient
                    equipment which would never be used in an inappropriate manner. It is my most
                    earnest desire to standardize the arms of Nicaragua with those of the United
                    States, in as much as we have the same tactics. It is to be hoped that in the
                    future all the nations of the American continent may have the same tactics and a
                    single type of arms in order that they may be in every sense a continental
                    block.</p>
                <p>I am acquainted with the fact that both General Brett of the Canal Zone of Panama
                    and General Bartlett, Chief of the Military Mission in Nicaragua, to whom I have
                    shown our war equipment in order that they may see for themselves the scanty
                    material which Nicaragua has, have recommended to the War Department that the
                    above-mentioned rifles and materials be not refused. They know that not a single
                    rifle is in good order.</p>
                <p>I wish to reiterate the assurances of the sincere devotion of the Nicaraguan
                    Government and people to democracy and Pan Americanism <pb facs="1209" n="1195"
                        xml:id="pg_1195"/> and repeat to you the feelings of friendship and
                    admiration which bind them to you and your great nation.</p>
                <p>With renewed expressions of my personal devotion I sign myself your warm
                    friend.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Somoza</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
