<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Nicaragua (
                        Warren
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1945v09</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d975</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">975</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1945-10-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1945-10-23T00:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-10-23T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-10-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="975" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d975">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">817.00/10–2245: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Nicaragua</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Warren</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Managua</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-10-22T23:00:00-06:00">October 22, 1945—11 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received October 23—11 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>622. At 8 p.m. I saw the President at the end of a long hot day to tell him of my
                    trip to the US.<note n="45" xml:id="d975fn45">Ambassador Warren arrived in
                        Washington for consultation on October 14 and resumed his duties in
                        Nicaragua on October 21.</note> He appeared tired, a bit nervous and
                    somewhat harried.</p>
                <p>[Here follow several paragraphs concerning a local strike, student unrest at the
                    Central University, suspension of the newspaper <hi rend="italic">Flecha</hi>
                    and the results of a recently-held, nationwide Liberal plebiscite.]</p>
                <p>I asked the President when the Liberal convention would be held. He replied that
                    the Junta Directiva Nacional y Legal of the Liberal Party, the highest Liberal
                    authority, would call the election. He expects that the convention will be
                    called to meet in the next month or so. He said it might select him as its
                    candidate.</p>
                <p>Having in mind the President’s promise to Mr. Rockefeller and to me not to be a
                    candidate, I inquired whether he had thought of his plans beyond the convention.
                    He replied that he had. They are as follows: He will go to the U.S. in June of
                    1946 to see his son graduated from West Point. Before going he will, in
                    accordance with Constitution, deposit the executive power in one of the
                    designated members of <pb facs="1234" n="1220" xml:id="pg_1220"/> the Senate or
                    the House. He will also before going turn over command of the Guardia Nacional
                    to a new chief. The President will remain in the U.S. until after the elections
                    of February 1947. During that period he would confer with the Department of
                    State and on the basis of what he says and what the Dept observes from events
                    transpiring in Nicaragua, it will be decided whether he is to be a candidate for
                    the Presidency. (It was evident that he felt that events in Nicaragua would be
                    such that the Dept of State would want him to be a candidate.)</p>
                <p>The following must be borne in mind: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>President Somoza sincerely believes that he is the only man in
                            Nicaragua today capable of keeping order and the peace.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>He says he has spent sleepless nights trying to think of someone
                            capable of taking his place.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>He has convinced himself that it is his duty to Nicaragua and the
                            Nicaraguan people to be reelected President for the next term.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>He feels intensely that democracy in Nicaragua calls for different
                            expression and different processes from that obtaining in the US.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>He has contempt for the independent Liberals because most of them have
                            been his supporters and beneficiaries of his favors at one time or
                            another.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>He has a sincere belief that ultimately Chamorro<note n="46" xml:id="d975fn46">Gen. Emiliano Chamorra, former President of the
                                Republic and Minister to the United States, leader of the
                                Traditionalist Conservative Party.</note> and the Conservatives will
                            be the gainers if he disappears from the political scene.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Briefly, it may be said that the President sincerely believes that he is the only
                    man in Nicaragua today capable of governing the Republic and that without him
                    chaos will result.</p>
                <p>In the final seconds of the conversation, I gained the impression that although
                    the ideas mentioned above represent the present thinking of the President, they
                    are not necessarily his final thoughts on the subject.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Warren</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
