<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1945-12-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1945-12-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="996" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d996">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">819.011/12–2945</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Panama</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hines</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 461</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Panamá</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1945-12-29">December 29,
                                1945</date>.<lb/>[Received January 4, 1946.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the
                            Embassy’s despatches No. 57, November 9, 1945,<note n="24" xml:id="d996fn24">For an extract from this despatch, see <ref target="#pg_1274">p. 1274</ref>.</note> and No. 97, November 15,
                                1945,<note n="25" xml:id="d996fn25">Not printed.</note> and to
                            enclose texts in Spanish and translation thereof of memoranda from the
                            Ministry of Foreign Affairs regarding the revision of the articles of
                            the proposed constitution relating to the jurisdiction of the air above
                            the Panama Canal and the teaching of English in schools in the Republic
                            of Panamá.</p>
                        <p>The Department will observe that Article 3 of the proposed constitution
                            relating to the jurisdiction over the air space above the Republic of
                            Panamá has been amended by the addition of a clause recognizing the
                            “jurisdictional limitations stipulated in Public Treaties prior to this
                            Constitution”. This should remove any doubt as to the jurisdiction of
                            the Government of the United States over the air above the <pb facs="1253" n="1239" xml:id="pg_1239"/> Panama Canal and/or any
                            other territory in the Republic of Panamá the acquisition of which has
                            been mutually agreed upon by the Republic of Panamá and the United
                            States under the provisions of the Treaties of 1903<note n="26" xml:id="d996fn26">
                                <ref target="frus1904#pg_543">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1904, p.
                                543</ref>.</note> and 1936.</p>
                        <p>Article 74 of the proposed constitution has been revised to permit the
                            teaching of a foreign language with the permission of the Ministry of
                            Education. The Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Minister of
                            Education have assured the Embassy that there will be no interference
                            with the teaching of English in the schools in New Cristobal.</p>
                        <p>Copies of this despatch are being sent to General Crittenberger and
                            Governor Mehaffey.</p>
                        <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Frank T. Hines</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>