<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-11-20T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-11-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="102" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d102">
                        <head>102. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_FG_1">Ford</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d102fn1"><seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_SB_1">Scowcroft</persName> relayed a report from
                                        <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rumsfeld</persName> concerning
                                    his meetings with the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>
                                    Nuclear Planning Group.</seg>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: Ford Library, National Security
                                        Adviser, Presidential Agency Files, Box 14, <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, 9/16/76–12/7/76.
                                        Confidential. <persName corresp="#p_FG_1">Ford</persName>
                                        initialed the memorandum. In a November 4 memorandum to
                                            <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rumsfeld</persName>,
                                        Assistant to the Secretary of Defense for Atomic Energy
                                        Donald Cotter reviewed the evolution of U.S. <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> theater nuclear force
                                        initiatives, with particular emphasis on his role in them.
                                        (Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_OSD_1">OSD</gloss> Files: FRC 330–79–0049,
                                            <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> 320.2, 4 Nov
                                        76)</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-11-20">November 20, 1976</date>.</dateline>
                        <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD_1">Rumsfeld</persName> has asked that
                            the following report of his meetings with the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Nuclear Planning Group be passed to you:</p>
                        <p>“As you know, the 20th Ministerial meeting of <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>’s Nuclear Planning Group was held in London this week.
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SHR_1">Robert Strausz-Hupe</persName> who had come over
                            to London from Brussels met with me on Tuesday. We had a good visit
                            about Europe and the attitudes of our allies as Robert sees them from
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> headquarters. His <pb facs="0422" n="381" xml:id="pg_381"/> ideas about the alliance and
                            the continuing buildup of Soviet military forces have merit and deserve
                            discussion at one of our meetings.</p>
                        <p>“Later I had a useful session with <persName corresp="#p_GJ_1">Al
                                Haig</persName> about the nuclear balance. I took advantage of his
                            presence as we worked up the final texts of my briefings to the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Defense Ministers. We were in full
                            agreement that we should leave the Europeans with a clear understanding
                            (1) that the alliance’s nuclear deterrent is credible, and (2) that the
                            deterrent operates and must operate across the full spectrum of all
                            allied nuclear and conventional forces. He is well respected in Europe
                            and pleased with his reappointment.</p>
                        <p>“That evening Fred Mulley, the new British Defense Minister, hosted a
                            reception for the <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> Ministers with
                            my good friend and your sincere admirer, Secretary General <persName corresp="#p_LJ_2">Joseph Luns</persName>. His very first inquiry was
                            for you; and he asked me to pass to you his thanks and his very best
                            wishes.</p>
                        <p>“Wednesday was devoted to formal sessions that continued until mid-day
                            Thursday. There was, as expected, much European concern about the
                            growing Soviet capabilities and many questions on the SS–X–20 missile;
                            but I am hopeful that this meeting put the issue in better focus. Our
                            cruise missile developments, both ALCM and SLCM, led to a number of
                            questions. Again, I think that this <gloss target="#t_NPG_1">NPG</gloss>
                            meeting stripped some of the romanticizing and provided our allies with
                            a clearer understanding of the realities.</p>
                        <p>“Between the meetings I had a bilateral meeting with Greek Defense
                            Minister Averoff, a fine man who has just recovered from three serious
                            operations, who thinks reasonably about both Cyprus and the Turks. I
                            only wish his health and domestic Greek politics allowed him to exercise
                            more influence in Athens. In addition, I had a bilateral meeting with
                            the new Canadian Defense Minister Danson, who has been in office for
                            only two weeks. He impressed me as a much stronger figure than his
                            predecessor and a man with whom the U.S. can work to improve North
                            American and alliance defenses. Danson asked to visit Washington in the
                            coming weeks, and I agreed it would be useful for him to do so.</p>
                        <p>“Finally, I visited with Fred Mulley at his office in the <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> Ministry of Defense. Her Majesty’s
                            Government has problems and, as you would expect, most of the subjects
                            he voiced had to do with money. I shall try to do what I can to be of
                            help to him and a nation that is a valued ally and to Mulley himself,
                            who is decent, well-meaning and hard-working.</p>
                        <p>“Later yesterday and this morning I made a quick stop in Scotland at the
                            U.S. Navy facility for our Poseidon Submarines in Holy Loch. It is my
                            pleasure to report that the ships and crews and morale are superb. One
                            cannot help but be proud of them.</p>
                        <pb facs="0423" n="382" xml:id="pg_382"/>
                        <p>“I was in North Germany tonight where the installations and facilities
                            are being prepared to receive the U.S. army brigade that will soon take
                            up its station on the North German Plain. I will be back in Washington
                            Saturday.</p>
                        <p>“All in all the North Atlantic Alliance is healthy and vibrant, in my
                            view. America’s security relations with our European allies are on a
                            sounder footing and more problem free than in many, many years. The
                            people I have just met know that you are genuinely interested in <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>; they know what you and your
                            Administration have done in the past two years to strengthen America’s
                            defenses and the trans-Atlantic bonds; and they are understandably
                            grateful.</p>
                        <p>“I look forward to seeing you on Monday and trust your time in California
                            was relaxing.”</p>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>