<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>210. Telegram 283446 From the Department of State to the Embassy in
                    Spain</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve15p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d210</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">210</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-12-02T06:37:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-12-02T06:37:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-12-02T06:37:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-12-02T06:37:00-05:00" n="210"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d210">
                <head>210. Telegram 283446 From the Department of State to the Embassy in Spain<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d210fn1">
                        <seg type="summary">Summary: The Department sent instructions for <persName
                                corresp="#p_SW_4">Stabler</persName>’s meeting with <persName
                                corresp="#p_JCI_1">Juan Carlos</persName>.</seg>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy Files, N750006–0388. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Cherokee_1"
                                    >Cherokee</gloss>; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1"
                                    >Nodis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BR_1"
                                    >Barbour</persName> in <gloss target="#t_EURWE_1"
                                >EUR/WE</gloss>; cleared by Hoganson and Woods in <gloss
                                    target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss>; and approved by <persName
                                    corresp="#p_HA_2">Hartman</persName>. In telegram 284990 to the
                                Secretary’s Delegation, December 3, the Department forwarded to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> a report from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SW_4">Stabler</persName> on his December 3
                                talk with <persName corresp="#p_JCI_1">Juan Carlos</persName>.
                                (Ibid., N750006–0428) <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                                    >Kissinger</persName>’s proposed trip to Madrid in December was
                                postponed until January 1976.</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1975-12-02T11:37:00+00:00">December 2, 1975, 1137Z</date>.</dateline>
                <p>Following <gloss target="#t_SECTO_1">Secto</gloss> 23011 sent action <gloss
                        target="#t_SECSTATE_1">SecState</gloss> Nov. 30; repeated to you. Quote.
                        <gloss target="#t_SECTO_1">Secto</gloss> 23011. Action: <gloss
                        target="#t_SECSTATE_1">SecState</gloss>, WashDC. From <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> Del Secretary on board 27000. Subject: Action
                    Memo—Draft Instructions on Spain (<gloss target="#t_SS_1">S/S</gloss> 7523824).
                    For: <persName corresp="#p_HA_2">Hartman</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SW_4"
                        >Stabler</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName>
                    from the Secretary.</p>
                <p>1. In the following paragraphs are the instructions which <persName
                        corresp="#p_SW_4">Stabler</persName> should use with <persName
                        corresp="#p_JCI_1">Juan Carlos</persName> on <persName corresp="#p_SW_4"
                        >Stabler</persName>’s return to Madrid December 2. They are substantively
                    the same instructions you cabled out in draft with, however, a number of
                    deletions. You should not draw any conclusions from these deletions. They cover
                    matters which in my judgement can not be set down adequately in writing and
                    which I would like personally to discuss to the King when we meet.</p>
                <p>Begin text of approved instructions for the Ambassador from the Secretary.</p>
                <p>1. You should see <persName corresp="#p_JCI_1">Juan Carlos</persName> as soon as
                    possible following your return to Madrid and tell him that I look forward to
                    seeing him in Madrid on either December 13 and 14 or December 14 and 15, if
                    these dates are convenient. The exact dates will depend on whether or not the
                    consumer-producer conference is held in December and this we should know later
                    in the week. Just as soon as something is determined I shall be back in touch
                    with you to work out the final dates and the timing of the announcement
                    agreeable to the King. You should tell <persName corresp="#p_JCI_1">Juan
                        Carlos</persName> that I hope to meet privately with him at least once
                    during my stay in Madrid (i.e. without government Ministers.)</p>
                <p>2. You should also tell the King that I have instructed you to inform the Foreign
                    Minister that we are prepared to resume discussions immediately with the GOS to
                    complete the seven complimentary agreements under the framework agreement and
                    that, assuming all the work will have been completed by then, I shall be
                    prepared to sign the overall agreement with the Foreign Minister while I am in
                    Madrid.</p>
                <pb facs="0729" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/>
                <p>3. I also wish you to convey the following thoughts to <persName
                        corresp="#p_JCI_1">Juan Carlos</persName>. Tell him that these reflect some
                    of the comments he made to the Vice President, with whom I have discussed his
                    conversation and impressions. You should tell him that I look forward to full
                    discussions with him on these matters during my visit.</p>
                <p>(A) The most important objective must be to maintain stability and internal
                    tranquility both politically and economically while moving slowly to adapt the
                    political situation in a way acceptable to the Spanish people, but also in a way
                    which will permit Spain in the near future to play a role within the Western
                    European and Atlantic framework. But the King should understand that Europe
                    cannot set the pace for Spain.</p>
                <p>Spain has to find its own way to its own set of institutions at its own pace. In
                    particular the King should not permit himself to be pressed to go faster than
                    the stability and tranquility of Spain will be able to tolerate.</p>
                <p>(B) It is essential that the King, by his actions, establish himself as quickly
                    as possible as the undisputed leader of Spain. Decisiveness, such as that
                    displayed by his trip to the Sahara, will give the King the image as well as the
                    substance of leadership. He should seek to achieve promptly as wide a popular
                    base as possible. The King may want to consider, once he has made the necessary
                    decisions on the President of the Cortes, the President of the Government, and
                    the composition of the Council of Ministers, undertaking a series of visits
                    throughout Spain to capitalize on his popular appeal and to establish his own
                    personal contacts, not only with the people but with local leaders in various
                    fields. The creation of this wider national base will give him his own
                    constituency and thus additional authority in the central decision making
                    process.</p>
                <p>(C) The first order of business (unless these decisions have already been made)
                    must be the choice of President of the Cortes and a decision on whether or not
                    to carry on with <persName corresp="#p_ANC_1">Arias</persName> for a few months
                    longer. It is vital that the person chosen for the Cortes be the “King’s man”
                    and that his designation be a clear signal of the King’s desire to pursue a
                    gradual, prudently-paced evolutionary course. It is important that in this first
                    decision the King have his way and that he not permit a decision to be forced on
                    him.</p>
                <p>(D) By the same token the Prime Minister and the key Cabinet Members must all be
                    men who will be prepared to respond positively to the King’s leadership and be
                    absolutely loyal.</p>
                <p>(E) While the King may have chosen not to preside over the Council of Ministers
                    meetings in the belief that he should not become involved in the routine conduct
                    of government, he must be certain that his wishes and views are fully known and
                    fully represented to the gov<pb facs="0730" n="689" xml:id="pg_689"/>ernment as
                    a whole. Here again the Prime Minister and the individual Ministers will play a
                    key role. The King must take a special care to see to it that he will not be
                    relegated to a “figure-head” role. In such a role he will be defenseless.</p>
                <p>(F) The King would do well to create immediately in his household a small but
                    highly competent “Private Council” which can follow in detail everything that is
                    happening, prepare studies and options for him, and act as his independent
                    channel into the government, the military and the private sector. He would do
                    well not to rely on the bureaucracy as such for the necessary analyses and
                    action recommendations, but rather on a small selected group of loyal, younger
                    men who are completely trustworthy.</p>
                <p>(G) In all of this it is useful that the King have the most favorable press
                    possible. He should appoint a competent and respected Press Secretary who can
                    have good access to both the domestic and foreign media. TV is also of
                    particular importance and the Press Secretary would have a special role in
                    serving as a direct link between the King and the Information Minister whose
                    choice is also a particularly important one.</p>
                <p>(H) Vice President <persName corresp="#p_RN_1">Rockefeller</persName> mentioned
                    to the King public opinion polls as a tool to determine what the people want and
                    the possible direction of public policy. We are prepared to help in any way we
                    can to advise on how these polls might be used and on the techniques. The King
                    will want to have a polling mechanism on which he can personally rely and we are
                    not certain that a mechanism presently exists in Spain which can be adapted for
                    this purpose.</p>
                <p>(I) The King should be careful not to move too fast with respect to the
                    evolutionary process. His first decisions on the presidency of the Cortes and on
                    the Prime Minister are crucial. He should reflect carefully on the sort of Spain
                    he would like to see emerge in the next two or three years and then plot a
                    program of gradual but sustained progress towards that goal. He must at all
                    times work to maintain and to increase his own political base and strength in
                    the country. Each action of an evolutionary nature should be accompanied by a
                    period of consolidating and reinforcing his own personal position, through
                    trips, through appointments to national and provincial positions of younger men
                    linked to him both personally and as the leader of the younger generation in
                    Spain, through media contact, through foreign visits, etc. Ultimately some
                    thought might be given to a referendum but it is our belief that this should be
                    kept in the background until the King’s position is so consolidated that its
                    successful outcome cannot be in doubt (here again public opinion polls would be
                    useful in making the necessary judgements).</p>
                <pb facs="0731" n="690" xml:id="pg_690"/>
                <p>(J) We recognize that one of the most difficult problems for the King will be the
                    accurate measurement of the relative strength of the contending political
                    forces. The fact is that the <persName corresp="#p_FGF_1">Franco</persName>
                    institutions remain firmly in place and have a defined strength. The
                    non-Communist opposition, while clearly existing, has not had its relative
                    strength tested through any electoral process. We believe that there are many
                    Spaniards who believe that evolution can be achieved through the gradual
                    adaptation of the present system and that the notion of a “democratic rupture”
                    is not only unnecessary but a dangerous way of thinking. With this we agree. The
                    King may wish to consider the creation of some special commissions to study
                    various political, regional, labor and economic problems. The appointment of
                    such commissions would in themselves have a psychological impact, although if
                    they should unduly prolong their deliberations, they could have ultimately a
                    negative effect.</p>
                <p>(K) We do not have, nor should we have, an ideal prescription for Spain. We know
                    that there are vast numbers of Spaniards who do not want the pattern of the past
                    years to remain unchanged in the future. However we are certain that the King
                    recognizes that the problem is to relate changes to stability. This can only be
                    assured if change is brought about gradually and in the full knowledge that the
                    overwhelming majority of the Spanish people want to preserve the benefits of
                    economic and social progress which they have achieved.</p>
                <p>(L) The King well knows that he has our support as he moves forward and he should
                    never hesitate to look to us for whatever advice and council we may be able to
                    give him.</p>
                <p>End approved instructions. Unquote.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_IR_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_IR_1">Ingersoll</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
