<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="89" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d89">
                        <head>89. Memorandum From the <gloss target="#t_Coun_1">Counselor</gloss>
                                (<persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName>) to Secretary of
                            State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d89fn1"><seg type="summary">Summary: <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName> discussed the
                                    evolution and sensitivity of the quadripartite Foreign Ministers
                                    consultation forum.</seg>
                                <p><seg type="source">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Records of
                                        the Office of the <gloss target="#t_Coun_1">Counselor</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Helmut
                                            C. Sonnenfeldt</persName>, 1955–1977, Entry 5339, Box 6,
                                        Quadripartite Memcons, Feb. 1976–. Secret; Eyes Only.
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sonnenfeldt</persName> did
                                        not initial the memorandum. Tab A, a memorandum of
                                        conversation for a February 20 Political Directors meeting;
                                        Tab B, a memorandum of conversation for a March 26 Political
                                        Directors meeting; and Tab C, a memorandum of conversation
                                        for a January 23 Ministerial meeting were not attached. The
                                        February 20 and March 26 memoranda of conversation are ibid;
                                        the January 23 memorandum of conversation was not
                                        found.</seg></p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <dateline>
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1976-04-22">April 22,
                                1976</date>.</dateline>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The Quadripartite Consultation Forum: Your Meetings with <persName corresp="#p_CA_1">Crosland</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Sauvagnargues</persName>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Your periodic meetings with your German, <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss> and French colleagues, and the intervening sessions of
                            the “Political Directors” which I have attended, have become one of the
                            more rewarding means of Western consultation and policy coordination.
                            Their occurrence, although it has vaguely seeped out, has largely
                            remained secret; it is potentially explosive—domestically in France and,
                            more broadly, within <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> and the international community
                            generally—since it smacks of a directorate that tends to undercut or
                            supersede other intra-Western forums. The fact that in actuality while
                            it may be a pseudo-directorate, it distinctly <hi rend="italic">reinforces</hi>, rather than undercuts, existing Western
                            institutions will be lost sight of if its existence and the topics dealt
                            with become common knowledge.</p>
                        <p>You will be meeting with two of your colleagues from this new
                            institution, and possibly <persName corresp="#p_GHD_1">Genscher</persName> also, before the next regular meeting in Oslo.
                            Schedules permitting, we are trying to have another political directors
                            meeting before Oslo, possibly here in Washington during the <persName corresp="#p_GEV_1">Giscard</persName> visit when De Laboulaye will
                            be here anyhow and the others are thinking of coming.</p>
                        <p>Topics currently under consideration include (1) Yugoslav contingency
                            planning, (2) Italy and Communism in Western Europe, (3) the Northern
                            Flank. There has also emerged, among my colleagues, an intense interest
                            in using the forum to vent problems ranging from Southern Africa,
                            Spanish Sahara, Lebanon, Cyprus to Spain, Portugal, Malta, Turkey,
                            Greece, i.e., literally no problem of common interest has been excluded.
                            The French, indeed, while becoming extremely legalistic about what
                            topics can properly be taken up in the <gloss target="#t_NAC_1">NAC</gloss>, have been <pb facs="0387" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                            eager to use the four-power forum without limitation. Further, as I have
                            reported to you, my three European colleagues have often used our
                            meetings to air sensitive internal <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>
                            problems in my presence.</p>
                        <p>You may want to talk to your colleagues individually about the future of
                            this operation. Carefully handled, it is clearly in our interest to
                            maintain it, including for its utility to fertilize and envigorate
                            other, broader forums in which all participate such as <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> itself. But it does run the risk of
                            exposure. And with changes in personnel (<persName corresp="#p_CA_1">Crosland</persName> vice <persName corresp="#p_CJ_1">Callaghan</persName>; Van Well may soon be promoted, Campbell may
                            be reassigned, and my days are numbered), continuity will become a
                            problem. Furthermore, with the discussions now ranging far afield from
                            East-West and intra-Western problems, my ability to contribute is in any
                            case circumscribed, given the disparity in responsibilities between my
                            colleagues and myself. (My colleagues are so sensitive about the forum
                            that they are reluctant to have it widened by excessive introduction of
                            experts, though we have of course brought in <persName corresp="#p_HA_1">Haig</persName> and his two Yugoslav planners, and, occasionally,
                            an African or other senior expert.)</p>
                        <p>I attach a copy of my report on the last two political directors meetings
                            and the account of the last Ministerial meeting for your reference.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>