<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-10-12T08:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-10-12T08:00:00-05:00" n="1063" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1063">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">760d.61/248: Telegram</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                        </hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-10-12T16:00:00+03:00">October 12,
                                1939—4 p.m.</date>
                            <lb/> [Received October 12—2:18 p.m.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>734. For the Secretary and Under Secretary. Your 194, October 11, 5 p.m. I
                        saw Molotov at 3 p.m., and handed him the President’s <pb facs="0981" n="969" xml:id="pg_969"/> message for immediate delivery to Kalinin. He
                        promised to bring the message to Kalinin’s attention at once and stated that
                        while he could not speak for Kalinin he would be glad to give me his own
                        opinion. He said that he anticipated the “American sentimental interest in
                        Finland.” He proceeded: “It must be borne in mind that Finland exists as an
                        independent nation pursuant to the treaty of 1920 with the Soviet Union
                        under the terms of which the area of Finland was substantially increased as
                        a result of the volunteer action of the Soviet Government.”<note n="44" xml:id="d1063fn44">A Finnish national government, appointed by a legally
                            elected Finnish Diet, declared the independence of Finland on December
                            6, 1917. This independence was recognized by the Bolshevik government of
                            Russia on January 4, 1918. The treaty of peace between Finland and the
                            Russian Socialist Federated Soviet Republic was signed at Dorpat on
                            October 14, 1920 (see footnote 24, <ref target="#pg_960">p. 960</ref>).
                            Recognition of Finnish independence, and of the Government of Finland
                                <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>, by the United States occurred on
                            May 7, 1919 (<ref target="frus1919v02#pg_215">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii</hi>, p. 215</ref>). The unqualified “full
                            recognition of Finland as of May 7, 1919” by the United States was
                            accorded in the note of January 12, 1920 (<ref target="frus1919v02#pg_226">
                                <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., p. 226</ref>, and footnote 10).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>He then pointed out to me on a wall map the territorial benefits which
                        Finland received under this treaty with particular emphasis on the surrender
                        of the Petsamo district<note n="45" xml:id="d1063fn45">It was the Finnish
                            contention that the cession of the Petsamo district with its ice-free
                            port of Pechenga was the belated fulfillment of a declaration of
                            Alexander II, made in 1864, as compensation for a strip of land ceded by
                            the Duchy of Finland on the Karelian Isthmus.</note> by the Soviet
                        Government. He continued: “It is not alamode for one country to take
                        territory from another” and asserted that he did not believe that anyone
                        could fairly criticize the recently concluded treaties with Estonia, Latvia,
                        and Lithuania<note n="46" xml:id="d1063fn46">For correspondence concerning
                            negotiations between the three Baltic States and the Soviet Union for
                            Pacts of Mutual Assistance, see <ref target="frus1933-39#pg_934">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Soviet Union,
                                1933–1939, pp. 934</ref> ff.</note> as constituting a seizure of
                        territory inasmuch as these treaties had been negotiated in each instance in
                        the mutual interests of the countries concerned by joint collaboration and
                        that the return of Wilno by the Soviet Union to Lithuania clearly evidenced
                        the Soviet Government’s regard for the right of small countries. He added
                        that the treaties with Latvia and Lithuania had been negotiated on a
                        friendly basis and that in all of them the Soviet Union had evidenced its
                        respect for the independence of the country concerned.</p>
                    <p>He concluded with the statement that in so far as concerned the negotiations
                        about to be undertaken [with] Finland he was sure that these negotiations
                        would reenforce the friendly relations between the two countries and would
                        be carried on with due regard for the interests of both countries. He
                        specifically stated that the proposed arrangement with Finland [“]will not
                        in the slightest degree affect or impair the independence of Finland” and
                        that if Finland had the same desire as the Soviet Government to arrive at an
                        understanding having regard to the respective interests of the two countries
                        he believed the matter could be arranged without any difficulty, if <pb facs="0982" n="970" xml:id="pg_970"/> desired. Kalinin is a mere
                        figurehead and that all of the recent negotiations have been carried on by
                        Stalin and Molotov in violation of Kalinin’s presence. I regard the
                        observations made by Molotov as virtually constituting the reply of the
                        Soviet Government regardless of any formal answer that Kalinin may make.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>