<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">107</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-04-06T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-04-06T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-04-06T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-04-06T16:00:00-05:00" n="107"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d107">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">741.60c/62: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-04-06T21:00:00+00:00"
                            >April 6, 1939—9 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received April 6—8:55 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>665. Leger read to me this evening a telegram which he received today from
                    Corbin, French Ambassador in London, giving the exact position of the
                    Polish-British negotiations in London.</p>
                <p>Beck promised that Poland would go to war on the side of Great Britain in case of
                    an attack by any power on Great Britain in return for the similar promise by
                    Great Britain.</p>
                <p>Lord Halifax then said to Beck that Great Britain was pledged to go to the
                    support not only of France but also of Switzerland, Belgium and the Netherlands
                    in case of a German or other attack on those powers. Thus Great Britain might be
                    drawn into war with Germany through an attack that was not in the first instance
                    directed against Great Britain but touched vital neighboring countries. Halifax
                    then asked Beck if the Polish promise to go to war on the side of Great Britain
                    would cover a war provoked by invasion of the Netherlands, Belgium or
                    Switzerland.</p>
                <p>Beck said that he could not make any such promise without most careful thought,
                    and has not yet replied. Beck will have a further talk with Halifax tonight and
                    will presumably give an answer of one sort or another.</p>
                <p>Beck also was most embarrassed when Halifax said to him that both France and
                    England had made offers of mutual assistance agreements <pb facs="0129" n="117"
                        xml:id="pg_117"/> to Rumania and that 4 days ago the Government of Rumania
                    had replied that it would be glad to enter into such agreements.</p>
                <p>Halifax requested Poland to enter into a similar agreement with Rumania.</p>
                <p>Beck replied that, inasmuch as Poland had what amounted to a defensive alliance
                    with Hungary, Poland would be most embarrassed if it were necessary to enter
                    into a defensive alliance with Rumania that included defense against Hungary.
                    Halifax continued to argue this point but Beck said he must reserve
                    judgment.</p>
                <p>The two undecided points mentioned above were those which prevented the signature
                    of a pact of mutual assistance between Great Britain and Poland and
                    supplementary agreements.</p>
                <p>Leger asserted that if Poland should refuse to make a pact of mutual assistance
                    with Rumania both France and England were prepared to withdraw their promises of
                    assistance to Poland.</p>
                <p>Corbin reported that Halifax still felt confident that he could obtain complete
                    satisfaction from Beck on both these points.</p>
                <p>Leger on the other hand said he believed that while Beck might accept the
                    obligation vis-à-vis the Netherlands, Belgium and Switzerland he would refuse to
                    accept the obligation vis-à-vis Rumania. Thus he could return to Warsaw and say
                    to Moscicki<note n="85" xml:id="d107fn85">Ignace Moscicki, President of
                        Poland.</note> and Smigly-Rydz, “I did everything I could but the demands of
                    the British were impossible” and could thus continue his old policy of working
                    on the German side.</p>
                <p>Inasmuch as Beck and Leger are mortal enemies I feel that Leger’s opinion is not
                    to be taken too seriously; but that the truth probably lies somewhere between
                    Halifax’s optimism and Leger’s pessimism.</p>
                <p>Beck has indicated that he would like to see me while his train is passing
                    through France. I shall therefore spend an hour and a half with him tomorrow
                    while traveling from Calais to Lille.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
