<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in France ( (Bullitt) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d110</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">110</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-04-09T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-04-09T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-04-09T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-04-09T18:00:00-05:00" n="110"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d110">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">741.60c/65: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in France</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bullitt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-04-09T23:00:00+00:00"
                            >April 9, 1939—11 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received April 10—9:44 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>687. The Polish Ambassador, who traveled as far as Brussels with Beck, asked to
                    see me urgently as soon as he returned to Paris.</p>
                <pb facs="0133" n="121" xml:id="pg_121"/>
                <p>He said that Beck had asked him to say to me that the shortness of the period
                    that I was on his train had made it impossible to explain his views to me in as
                    detailed a manner as he had wished.</p>
                <p>Beck had been embarrassed by my questions with regard to the obligation of Poland
                    to go to the assistance of England in case of a German attack on Holland,
                    Belgium or Switzerland, for the simple reason that his plenipotentiary powers
                    gave him the right to agree to an alliance in case of direct attack on Great
                    Britain but not in case of an indirect attack. He had been obliged therefore
                    when in England to take the personal responsibility for saying that he was
                    certain that his Government would agree to fight in case Great Britain should
                    judge an attack against the Netherlands, Belgium or Switzerland, to be an attack
                    against the vital interests of Great Britain. He had not wished to make any
                    statement to any one on this subject until he had seen Moscicki and Smigly-Rydz
                    and had received full authority to make this premise officially on behalf of the
                    Polish Government.</p>
                <p>The Polish Ambassador added that Beck was certain that the Polish Government
                    would approve his action and would promise officially and at once to go to war
                    on the side of Great Britain in case of any conflict which Great Britain judged
                    should menace its vital interests.</p>
                <p>The Polish Ambassador said that Beck also wanted him to explain further to me his
                    thoughts with regard to Rumania. When the Rumanian Minister in London had called
                    on him he had asked the Rumanian Minister flatly for an explanation of the
                    Rumanian Government’s request to the Governments of France and England to
                    arrange for Rumania a defensive alliance with Poland directed against Hungary
                    and Germany. The Rumanian Minister had replied evasively and had said that his
                    Government had given him no explanation of its failure to approach Poland
                    directly. Beck’s own opinion was that the <hi rend="italic">démarche</hi> which
                    he had made in Budapest in which he had indicated that if Hungary should attack
                    Rumania, Poland would be obliged to assist Rumania, to which the Hungarian
                    Government had replied in most reassuring terms that Hungary had no intention
                    whatsoever of attacking Rumania, had convinced the Rumanians that they were
                    today enjoying all the benefits of an alliance with Poland without any of the
                    burdens. If the Rumanians should ask Poland for a defensive alliance against
                    Hungary and Germany the Poles certainly would ask Rumania to agree to go to war
                    in case of a German attack on Poland. Beck felt therefore that the reason why
                    the Rumanians had not approached Poland directly was because they desired to
                    avoid giving any promise to go to war at once on the side of Poland in case of a
                    German attack on Poland.</p>
                <p>The Polish Ambassador was extremely depressed and apprehensive with regard to the
                    entire situation. He said that his most recent information <pb facs="0134"
                        n="122" xml:id="pg_122"/> indicated that there were German troop movements
                    which might be interpreted as preparation for an immediate German attack on
                    Poland. The position of Poland if war should not break out at once would be
                    greatly strengthened by the British-Polish alliance but if war should break out
                    at once no real assistance from England could be given. The British had no army
                    and Poland would be cut off from British supplies. The Polish Army was in
                    desperate need of airplanes, tanks and heavy artillery.</p>
                <p>Beck had instructed him to see Bonnet yesterday and he had done so. He had
                    requested the shipment immediately of military supplies from France to Poland
                    and especially airplanes. I said to him that he must know that France had so few
                    airplanes today that it would be impossible to send any to Poland. He said that
                    unfortunately this was true. He hoped however that a similar request which his
                    colleague in London had made to the British Government might result in the
                    shipment of planes to Poland.</p>
                <p>The Polish Ambassador said that Beck had instructed him to say to Bonnet also
                    that he felt it was time for the Polish-French alliance to be placed on the same
                    basis as the British-Polish alliance, that is to say each country should be the
                    sole judge of the moment when its vital interests were attacked and declarations
                    of war should be automatic. The Polish Ambassador went on to say that unless the
                    French Army could retain on the French frontier at least two-thirds of the
                    German Army the position of Poland would be hopeless. I called his attention to
                    the fact that the highest military circles here estimate that the Germans on the
                    Siegfried line could hold up the entire French Army with one-third of the German
                    Army. The Polish Ambassador said that he feared this was true; therefore the
                    position of Holland, Belgium and Switzerland would become most important.</p>
                <p>Unless the French Army should be able to attack Germany by way of Belgium it
                    would be possible for Germany to throw an overwhelming mass of troops against
                    Poland.</p>
                <p>The Polish Ambassador asked me if it might not be possible for Poland to obtain
                    financial help and aeroplanes from the United States. I replied that I believed
                    that the Johnson Act<note n="88" xml:id="d110fn88">Approved April 13, 1934; 48
                        Stat. 574.</note> would forbid any loans from the United States to Poland
                    but added that it might be possible for England to purchase planes for cash in
                    the United States and turn them over to Poland.</p>
                <p>Lukasiewicz, throughout our conversation, was laboring under the burden of the
                    thought that within a very few weeks his country might be removed from the map
                    of Europe by German invasion.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bullitt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
