<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Minister in Finland ( (Schoenfeld))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1156</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1156</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-01-03T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-01-03T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-01-03T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-01-03T18:00:00-05:00" n="1156"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1156">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">760d.61/890: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Minister in Finland</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Schoenfeld</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-01-03T18:00:00-05:00"
                            >January 3, 1940—6 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2. (1) Your 487, December 30, 7 p.m.,<note n="35" xml:id="d1156fn35">Not printed;
                        it repeated some further thoughts by the Prime Minister of Finland
                        concerning a possible move for ending hostilities with the Soviet Union
                        (760d.61/887).</note> leaves us almost as confused as we were as to
                    precisely what the Prime Minister has in mind. It <pb facs="1052" n="1040"
                        xml:id="pg_1040"/> is not clear, for instance, whether he desired the United
                    States in cooperation with other powers to endeavor to arrange for a peace
                    conference in which a number of countries would participate with the purpose of
                    bringing about a cessation of the conflict between Finland and the Soviet Union,
                    or whether it is his idea that the United States, together with other powers,
                    should merely try to persuade the Soviet Union to enter into bilateral peace
                    negotiations with Finland.</p>
                <p>(2) We are now in receipt of a telegram from Steinhardt in reply to our telegram
                    to him referred to in the last paragraph of our no. 219 of December 29, 6
                        p.m.,<note n="36" xml:id="d1156fn36">Not printed.</note> to you. For your
                    personal information only, Steinhardt says that he is in possession of no
                    evidence which would justify a belief that now is a propitious time to approach
                    the Soviet Government with a view to prevailing upon it to enter into
                    negotiations with the Finnish Government, and that he has observed nothing thus
                    far which would indicate that the Soviet Government has any desire to extricate
                    itself from the difficulties which it is encountering as a result of its war
                    with Finland.</p>
                <p>(3) You are authorized orally to inform the Prime Minister that while we do not
                    wish to leave untaken any step which might lead in the direction of the
                    cessation of hostilities between the Soviet Union and Finland, the results of
                    our own investigations cause us to doubt that an approach by this Government to
                    the Soviet Government for a peace conference would serve any useful purpose at
                    the present time. We are nevertheless willing to give consideration to any
                    suggestions or concrete proposals which the Finnish Government may at anytime
                    desire to make to us.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
