<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in the United Kingdom ( (Johnson) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-08-16T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-08-16T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-08-16T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-08-16T12:00:00-05:00" n="222"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">760C.62/836: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Johnson</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-08-16T18:00:00+01:00"
                            >August 16, 1939—6 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received August 16—2:45 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1172. My 1146, August 9, 9 p.m.<note n="29" xml:id="d222fn29">Not printed.</note>
                    Through the courtesy of the Foreign Office I was shown this afternoon a résumé
                    of the conversation between Herr Hitler and Burckhardt as well as an instruction
                    to the British Ambassador at Warsaw, both of which were telegraphed to the
                    Ambassador last night. I understood that both texts have likewise been
                    telegraphed to the British Ambassador at Washington for communication to
                        you.<note n="30" xml:id="d222fn30">Transmitted by the British Ambassador on
                        August 15; not printed.</note> From the instruction to the British
                    Ambassador at Warsaw will be seen the official British view of the present
                    situation and the nature of the pressure which they are endeavoring to bring to
                    bear on the Polish authorities.<note n="31" xml:id="d222fn31">On August 21,
                        1939, the British Embassy informed the Department of State that the British
                        Ambassador in Poland was authorized at his discretion to suggest to the
                        Polish Foreign Minister that the Polish Government might convey in some way
                        to the German Government its readiness to discuss the minority problem. The
                        British Government was not, however, suggesting that the Polish Government
                        should give anything away with regard to Danzig or otherwise compromise its
                        position. (740.00/2114)</note> I also understand that the British Ambassador
                    has been instructed to make clear to Colonel Beck the great importance which
                    this Government attaches to a full and frank exchange of views and intentions
                    before Poland takes the initiative in replying to various forms of German
                    pressure by any act which could be represented in Germany as Polish aggression.
                    The Foreign Office has been at pains through background press conferences to
                    discuss current speculations that Dr. Burckhardt had acted as an agent in
                    communicating messages to Hitler from the British Government or that he had
                    conveyed any message to the British Government from Hitler.</p>
                <p>Dr. Burckhardt, in whom Foreign Office officials express confidence, has given a
                    clear-cut account of his interview with Hitler. Officials here however do not
                    feel that it has thrown any additional light on what Hitler’s real intentions
                    are as to the issue of peace or war.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Johnson</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
