<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-05-25T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-05-25T15:00:00-05:00" n="260" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d260">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">741.61/646: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-05-25T21:00:00+01:00">May 25,
                                    1939—9 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received May 25—5:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>745. For the Secretary and the Under Secretary. My 734, May 24, 7 p.m.
                            The text of a draft agreement which the British propose shall be
                            presented by themselves jointly with France to the Soviet Government was
                            delivered to the French Government today for approval. The text<note n="92a" xml:id="d260fn92a">For official text, see <hi rend="italic">Documents on British Foreign Policy, 1919–1939</hi>, Third
                                Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, doc. No. 624, p.
                                679.</note> is substantially as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>The Governments of Great Britain, France and Russia, desiring in
                                    their capacity as members of the League of Nations to give
                                    effect to the principles of mutual support embodied in the
                                    Covenant of the League of Nations,<note n="93" xml:id="d260fn93">
                                        <ref target="frus1919Parisv13#pg_69">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Paris
                                            Peace Conference, 1919, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, p. 69</ref>.</note> have reached the
                                    following agreement: <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>If France and the United Kingdom are engaged in
                                            hostilities with any European power in consequence of
                                            (1) aggression by that power against another European
                                            state which they had in conformity with the wishes of
                                            that state undertaken to assist against such aggression,
                                            or (2) assistance given by them to another European
                                            state which had requested such assistance in order to
                                            resist violation of its neutrality, or (3) aggression by
                                            a European power against either France or Great Britain,
                                            Russia acting in accordance with the principles of
                                            article XVI, paragraphs 1 and 2, of the Covenant of the
                                            League of Nations, will give France and Great Britain
                                            all support and assistance in its power.</item>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>Sets forth the identical obligations as in 1 above on
                                            the part of France and Great Britain to the Government
                                            of Soviet Russia.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>The three contracting Governments will concert as to
                                            methods by which such mutual support and assistance
                                            could in case of need be made effective.</item>
                                        <label>4.</label>
                                        <item>In the event of there arising a threat which would
                                            call their undertakings of mutual support and assistance
                                            into operation, the three Governments will immediately
                                            enter into consultation with each other. The methods and
                                            scope of such consultations will at once be the subject
                                            of further discussions between the three
                                            Governments.</item>
                                        <label>5.</label>
                                        <item>The obligation of rendering support and assistance in
                                            the cases outlined in preceding articles is without
                                            prejudice to the rights and position of other
                                            powers.</item>
                                        <label>6.</label>
                                        <item>Each of the three Governments will communicate to the
                                            others the terms of any undertaking to which they are
                                            now committed, <pb facs="0275" n="263" xml:id="pg_263"/>
                                            referred to in paragraphs 1 (1) and 2 (1) above, and
                                            before taking on any similar obligations in the future
                                            each of the three powers will consult with the
                                            others.</item>
                                        <label>7.</label>
                                        <item>The agreement is to continue for 5 years and the three
                                            Governments will consult as to the desirability of
                                            renewal, with or without modifications, not less than 6
                                            months before its expiration.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>The Foreign Office is hopeful that by the very careful and precise
                            definition in articles I and II of the circumstance under which the
                            obligation to render aid will become effective, any existing
                            apprehensions of Poland and Rumania as to the desirability of Russian
                            aid will be allayed and that the terms of article V will serve to allay
                            the apprehensions of the Baltic countries that Russian aid might under
                            certain circumstances be thrust upon them without their wishing it.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Kennedy</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>