<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-08-30T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-08-30T13:00:00-05:00" n="390" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d390">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">760C.62/1196: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-08-30T19:00:00+01:00">August 30,
                                    1939—7 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received August 30—3:50 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1324. Personal for the Secretary. My 1321, August 30, 5 p.m. The text of
                            the British reply has been telegraphed to Ambassador Henderson at Berlin
                            with instructions not to present it until he receives the word “go”.
                            This it is expected will be sent later today. The reason for this delay
                            is consultation with the French from whom, however, no objections to the
                            British draft are anticipated. The text of the note has likewise been
                            cabled to the British Ambassador at Washington for transmission to
                                you<note n="90" xml:id="d390fn90">Copy transmitted by the British
                                Ambassador to the Secretary of State, August 31, 1939. For text of
                                note, see British Cmd. 6106, Misc. No. 9 (1939), doc. No. 89, p.
                                142.</note> and has been cabled to the British Ambassador at
                            Warsaw.</p>
                        <p>A second telegram will be sent to the Ambassador at Warsaw<note n="91" xml:id="d390fn91">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, doc. No. 90, p. 144.</note> referring
                            to the British reply to Germany which the Ambassador is instructed to
                            communicate to Colonel Beck. In doing so he is to <pb facs="0403" n="391" xml:id="pg_391"/> point out that while the first part of the
                            German Government’s reply consisted of an indefinite and misleading
                            presentation of the German case, the really important part consists of
                            Germany’s acceptance of the proposal for direct discussion, of the
                            suggestion regarding the proposed international guarantee, and Germany’s
                            assertion that she intended to respect Polish vital interests. The
                            instruction to Warsaw further states that it is unnecessary at this
                            stage to take exception to much that is included in the German reply of
                            which the British Government would be as critical as it has no doubt the
                            Polish Government is. They draw attention to the fact that the Germans
                            had included in their reply the demand that a Polish plenipotentiary
                            arrive in Berlin today and it is pointed out to Colonel Beck that he
                            would see the British Government’s attitude to this clearly stated in
                            the reply to Hitler. The German Government is now drafting its proposals
                            and when these are received (for the German Government has promised to
                            give them to the British) it will then be easier to decide how and when
                            consultation might best be effected and negotiations carried on.</p>
                        <p>Colonel Beck will see from the British reply that proposals have been
                            made for a military standstill during the discussions and the British
                            Government earnestly hope that the Polish Government will have no
                            objection. Ambassador Kennard is requested to secure urgently a
                            statement of the Polish views and in view of the Polish Government’s
                            authorization to the British Government to say that Poland would be
                            prepared to enter into direct discussions with Germany, the British
                            Government hopes that, provided the method and general arrangements for
                            the discussions can be satisfactorily agreed upon, the Polish Government
                            will be prepared without delay to indicate its own readiness. It is most
                            important to bear in mind the internal situation in Germany and world
                            opinion. In view of the fact that the German Government has professed
                            itself ready to negotiate, it should not be given any opportunity to
                            place the blame for declining direct negotiations on Poland. Ambassador
                            Kennard is told to emphasize to Colonel Beck that the British Government
                            has made quite clear to Herr Hitler its irrevocable determination to
                            implement its obligations without reserve and that there is no
                            misunderstanding on that score in Berlin. The position of the Polish
                            Government is very different from what it was last March since now it is
                            supported both by a direct British guarantee and by the British
                            undertaking to participate in any guarantee of a settlement which might
                            be reached. All the conversations will be carried on against this
                            background. Another consideration present in the minds of the British is
                            that according to information it has received from Berlin there is
                            reason to suppose that the German Government’s demands do not represent
                            Hitler’s last undertaking. On the other hand, [Poland’s] refusal to
                            negotiate <pb facs="0404" n="392" xml:id="pg_392"/> would merely serve
                            to fortify the forces in Germany which are working for war and enable
                            Hitler to place the onus of a breakdown on Poland.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Kennedy</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>