<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Norway ( (Harriman) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d560</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">560</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-12-22T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-12-22T06:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4aR8M0MGWA0lla" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-12-22T06:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-12-22T06:00:00-05:00" n="560"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d560">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/1314: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Norway</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Harriman</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Oslo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-12-22T12:00:00+01:00"
                            >December 22, 1939—noon</date>.<lb/>[Received 4:06 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>118. Legation’s despatch No. 539, December 12.<note n="10" xml:id="d560fn10">Not
                        printed.</note> Professor Wilhelm Keilhau, adviser to the Nobel Institute
                    since 1922, told me today that in an effort to ascertain present opinions in
                    leading German circles he recently sent to Berlin Tryggve Gran, a world known
                    Norwegian <pb facs="0548" n="536" xml:id="pg_536"/> pilot, in whom he has
                    complete confidence and one who is a personal, intimate friend of Goering
                    through their common interest in aviation. Gran made the first flight across the
                    North Sea in 1914 and was an officer in the British air force during the last
                    war.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Gran returned to Oslo yesterday after a conference alone with Goering
                        following which the latter after consultation with the German Foreign Office
                        arranged a meeting between himself, Gran and high officials of the Foreign
                        Office. Goering told him that as he was not Foreign Minister he could not
                        take the responsibility of answering all Gran’s questions but that what the
                        Foreign Office officials stated at the meeting were also his views.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The following is the substance of the information Gran received at this
                        meeting: the German pact with Russia was concluded in the belief that it was
                        necessary but it would never have been negotiated if Germany had known the
                        weakness of the Polish Army. To obtain the pact with Russia, Germany was
                        forced to promise inactivity in case of a Russian attack on Finland and of a
                        probable Russian attack on Sweden and Norway if the latter two countries
                        declared war on Russia to help Finland. Germany therefore considers Finland
                        as lost if the war in the West continues. This means an embarrassing
                        position for the German Government as the German people and army are in full
                        sympathy with Finland.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The defeat of Finland will take 6 months whereas Russia believes that it
                        can be accomplished in much less time. In the event of defeat of Finland,
                        Russia will not claim in Norway as far south as Narvik (the important
                        seaport terminal of Norwegian-Swedish railway connecting with Sweden’s
                        mines) but it would claim those Norwegian ports further north which might be
                        dangerous to Murmansk and also Spitzbergen and in the latter case claiming
                        that Spitzbergen has majority of Russian workmen.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Germany is willing to enter peace negotiations if the initiative is taken
                        principally by the United States or failing that by Italy and if Britain or
                        France do not beforehand make any conditions, Germany wishing to enter
                        negotiations on the same footing as other states. Germany on its part will
                        not claim an armistice or interruption of blockade as conditions for
                        negotiations. If peace could be obtained Germany is willing to break
                        completely with Russia and even bring about a situation which might allow it
                        to give military support to Finland. Stalin has made so many moves of which
                        Hitler does not approve that there would be a way to find a <hi
                            rend="italic">casus belli</hi>. In this case the whole of Poland might
                        be restored as completely independent provided Danzig and the Corridor
                        remain German and Poland can be <pb facs="0549" n="537" xml:id="pg_537"/>
                        allowed a new Corridor to the east. Czechoslovakia might also be restored
                        provided Beneš<note n="11" xml:id="d560fn11">Eduard Beneš, former President
                            of Czechoslovakia.</note> be not recalled. Such a peace would be the
                        only possibility for Great Britain to restore Poland without war against a
                        German-Russian alliance.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Keilhau states that in Gran’s belief Germany is strong enough to resist
                        for a long time so that if peace came now it would spare the world
                        incalculable suffering and would perhaps be the only means of saving Finland
                        and preventing the whole of Scandinavia from being devastated by war. He is
                        of the opinion that this information should receive earnest official
                        American consideration.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Keilhau emphasized that Gran’s mission to Berlin must be kept strictly
                        confidential as the Germans have stated that they will deny that any such
                        information had been given should it be published.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriman</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
