<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-09-12T09:40:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-09-12T09:40:00-05:00" n="780" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d780">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War 1939/55:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Minister in the Netherlands</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Gordon</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Hague</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-09-12T16:00:00+01:20">September
                                    12, 1939—4 p.m.</date>
                                <lb/> [Received September 12—1:56 p.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>171. My 160, September 8, 4 p.m., particularly section 4.<note n="26" xml:id="d780fn26">i. e., the last three paragraphs of the telegram
                                under reference.</note> At the Breda meeting referred to in my said
                            telegram Belgians informed Secretary General of Dutch Foreign Office
                            that they had just received a cable from the Belgian Ambassador in
                            Washington substantially as follows: Secretary of State told the
                            Ambassador that the American Government wish to see maritime
                            communications with Belgium kept open; the American Government felt that
                            the best procedure was to get in touch with London to examine possible
                            measures to be taken for overcoming blockade difficulties; after the
                            American and British Governments had been in communication the former
                            would get in touch with Belgium and Holland.</p>
                        <p>Secretary General has referred to this matter several times in my
                            conversations with him in the intervening days. The Dutch felt that this
                            probably had some connection with subject matter of the conversation
                            referred to in Department’s 69 of August 30, 5 p.m. and wondered whether
                            a similar communication would be sent here. Secretary General says that
                            the Belgians appear to be uncertain as to whether we intend first to
                            talk to London and then approach Holland <pb facs="0744" n="732" xml:id="pg_732"/> and Belgium but the Dutch interpret the message to
                            mean this. A very brief telegram of clarification would be
                            appreciated.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Gordon</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>