<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-10-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-10-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="815" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d815">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112 European War 1939/281:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the
                                Division of European Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-10-07">October 7, 1939</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Baron de Gruben, Counselor of the Belgian Embassy, telephoned this
                            morning to say that the Embassy had received a direct query from
                            Brussels as to whether the United States was going to take the
                            initiative in the matter of a “sea lane” to Belgium and Holland.</p>
                        <p>I replied that if by “sea lane” they meant a physical channel, I thought
                            the more experts looked into it, the more difficulties were found. If by
                            “sea lane” they meant keeping commerce open between the United States
                            and Belgium, he could reply that the United States was as interested as
                            ever in the maintenance of bona fide neutral trade between one neutral
                            and the other if for the latter’s own use. This was implicit in the
                            statement which Mr. Hickerson had handed him under instructions of the
                            Secretary of State.<note n="48" xml:id="d815fn48">Presumably the
                                statement referred to in telegram No. 1117, September 29, 8 p.m., to
                                the Ambassador in the United Kingdom, <ref target="#pg_751">p.
                                    751</ref>.</note> As to shipping questions, it was obvious that
                            the Executive could not finally determine its position pending the
                            conclusion of the debates on the neutrality bill.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierrepont Moffat</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>