<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Kennedy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d871</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">871</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-11-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXmtj6SyvT64JYD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic warfare</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-11-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-11-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="871"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d871">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">300.115(39) Oakman/8: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-11-04">November 4,
                            1939</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1374. Your 2236, November 1, 5 p.m. Statement of Ministry of Economic Warfare
                    seems to concede that the <hi rend="italic">Oakman</hi> was delayed 10 days or
                    more while British authorities were bringing themselves to accept facts
                    evidenced by ship’s papers which showed innocent character of cargo and vessels
                    and that therefore there was no “probable cause” for seizure or detention.
                    Manifestly the damages resulting from such acts of British Government should not
                    be allowed to fall on the innocent neutrals involved. Therefore please request
                    statement from Ministry as to what is contemplated by it in the way of
                    compensation to innocent parties for damages resulting in this manner.</p>
                <p>In this connection you may also call to the attention of the Ministry the fact
                    that the Gulf Mediterranean Ports Conference representing shipping companies
                    operating vessels from United States to Mediterranean ports has filed complaint
                    regarding interferences with vessels at Gibraltar, from which complaint the
                    following is an extract: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Shortly following the outbreak of War the British Contraband Control
                            Committee began taking vessels into Gibraltar for examination, and
                            latterly those belonging to American and Italian owners have suffered
                            serious detention. Our members are cooperating to the extent of issuing
                            only straight bills of lading (this practice became effective about
                            October 12th), and since that time also copies of manifests have been
                            sent by Clipper Ship to London to the Ministry of Economic Warfare with
                            the object of having them conduct any necessary investigation prior to
                            the arrival of vessels at Gibraltar.</p>
                        <p>“Striving as we are to meet British requirements we should like to see
                            inspection expedited at Gibraltar, and to this end shall appreciate it
                            if you will use your good offices with the British Government. We would
                            state that the Lines have been endeavoring to secure some expression
                            from the British authorities as to the requirements which must be met in
                            order to avoid or minimize detention of vessels but no definite
                            information has been obtained up to this time.</p>
                        <p>“We foresee that unless speedy handling can be had at Gibraltar, sailing
                            schedules from this side will be seriously interrupted with consequent
                            injury to American commerce.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0816" n="804" xml:id="pg_804"/>
                <p>The foregoing seems to indicate that the difficulties complained of are resulting
                    despite the fact that the cooperative procedure suggested by the Ministry has
                    been observed by shippers in the past.</p>
                <p>You may advise Ministry that it is the view of this Government that the situation
                    at Gibraltar is a serious one which it is believed merits the British
                    Government’s prompt and effective efforts to rectify.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
