<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the United Kingdom ( (Kennedy) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1939v01</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d953</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">953</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1939-09-08T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1939-09-08T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec65d5a63ab10e2d2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Rubber</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recF2jh59vGhjZ2KX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00000787"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Quota</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recfpP15yVGwzw4hZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1939-09-08T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1939-09-08T10:00:00-05:00" n="953"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d953">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.6176/97: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kennedy</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1939-09-08T16:00:00+01:00"
                            >September 8, 1939—4 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received September 8—11 a.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1528. The following letter from the Colonial Secretary<note n="30"
                        xml:id="d953fn30">Malcolm MacDonald.</note> speaks for itself and is the
                    result of the representations which I have made here. Both Malcolm MacDonald and
                    Sir John Campbell wish to prevent a speculative movement setting in and would
                    very much appreciate a statement from Washington which would have this effect as
                    indicated in the ultimate paragraph of his letter. I have no doubt that there
                    will be a real temptation to interpret “a reasonable price” as meaning a
                    reasonable dollar price but the preamble of the rubber restriction scheme
                    defines the price aim as “a price reasonably remunerative to efficient
                    producers” and therefore we should continue to think in terms of a sterling not
                    a dollar price thus permitting our rubber manufacturers to benefit by the
                    exchange advantage. The larger United States manufacturers should therefore do
                    all that they can immediately to adjust the New York price to a sterling basis
                    of about 10D. (which price would allow for some increase in shipping and
                    insurance costs). Their action or inaction within the next few days may well be
                    decisive particularly as we must recognize that as the war develops and Great
                    Britain’s foreign exchange resources decline the Government as well as the
                    producers will have an interest in a higher dollar price for rubber. The letter
                    reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“I have now discussed the rubber and tin<note n="31" xml:id="d953fn31"
                                >For correspondence concerning tin quotas, see <ref target="#pg_906"
                                    >pp. 906</ref> ff.</note> position with my advisers here. All
                            details are available but in this letter I propose to deal with the
                            matter only on the broadest lines.</p>
                        <p>While the rubber and tin control agreements will remain operative,
                            increases in the quota can only be obtained with the fairly general
                            consent of the signatory parties. If the Dutch and the British are in
                            agreement their views as regards rubber would be decisive; as regards
                            tin that agreement would just secure the majority required, but one
                            opposing delegation could hold up a decision and insist on a meeting.
                            Meetings are now quite impracticable at short notice anyhow; and the
                            securing of consent by written and telegraphic communications would
                            probably involve some, though we hope not material, delay.</p>
                        <p>Supplies are, we consider, adequate to meet all normal trade demands and
                            all probable war demands at present, provided speculation does not
                            dominate the situation, and future supplies are most fully assured. We
                            went into the question of the position regarding both tin and rubber in
                            the 1914–1918 war most carefully; and the broad conclusion was that the
                            war demand for both commodities was easily <pb facs="0880" n="868"
                                xml:id="pg_868"/> met without affecting prices. Towards the end of
                            the war the dominating influence on prices was shipping difficulty. At
                            no time in the case either of tin or rubber did inadequacy of production
                            make any difficulty. Conditions are not the same admittedly; but we
                            still think that war, even long continued war, should have but little
                            effect on the trend of the total demand. The real danger is speculation
                            and particularly speculation in the United States of America, or
                            unfounded fears on the part of consumers there leading them to the
                            purchase of large immediate supplies. Sir John Campbell tells me that on
                            the latest information available to him there has been excited buying of
                            tin from America, and he took up with Captain Oliver Lyttelton, the
                            Metal Controller here, the question of a further substantial increase in
                            the tin quota yesterday. He has not yet had Lyttelton’s reply, but hopes
                            that it was possible for him (Lyttelton) to discuss the proposals
                            Campbell had made with Mr. Van Der Broek, one of the Dutch
                            representatives who was over here yesterday, but did not come to
                            London.</p>
                        <p>In this connection, and the point seems to me the most important of all
                            at the moment, I enclose a summary of a telephonic conversation which
                            Mr. Pawson, the Secretary of the International Rubber Regulation
                            Committee, had with Mr. Butterworth yesterday. Campbell entirely agrees
                            with the views expressed in that summary; and he hopes very much that
                            some action will be taken at once in America in the direction suggested
                            by Mr. Pawson as regards both rubber and tin. That to my mind would be
                            the most useful and practically effective step which could be taken at
                            the moment. Meanwhile the buffer stock is selling all the tin which it
                            can be permitted, by the War Control authorities here, to sell at the
                            fixed price of £230 a ton.</p>
                        <p>I am sending a copy of this letter to Lyttelton whose office is outside
                            London.</p>
                        <p>As soon as the action which it seems advisable to take in respect of tin
                            can be decided upon, Campbell proposes to attempt to obtain the consent
                            necessary by telegraph from the delegations of the signatory countries.
                            As regards rubber a proposal was made on the 31st of August to increase
                            the quota for the last quarter of 1939 to 70%, to provide the first
                            installment of the rubber required under the Exchange Agreement. All
                            have agreed except the Dutch; despite repeated efforts we have not yet
                            been able to obtain any reply from them. Campbell also proposes to call
                            together such members of the Rubber Committee as may be available to
                            discuss with them what further action if any should be taken in the
                            light of the most recent events.</p>
                        <p>I should greatly appreciate any action that you may find it possible to
                            take to make the facts known.”</p>
                    </quote>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Telephone conversation between Mr. Butterworth and Mr. Pawson, 5:50
                            p.m., June 9, 1939.</p>
                        <p>I rang up Mr. Butterworth hearing that he had been trying to get in touch
                            with Sir John Campbell and myself.</p>
                        <p>I told him the present position in regard to the proposed issue of a
                            communiqué announcing an increase in the rubber quota for the last
                            quarter of 1939 from 60% to 70% and said we were awaiting the reply of
                            the Dutch delegation. He asked whether any action had been taken on the
                            proposal contained in a telegram from Mr. Viles that, in addition to the
                            10% increase for the purpose of implementing the agreement <pb
                                facs="0881" n="869" xml:id="pg_869"/> for exchange of cotton and
                            rubber, a further 5% increase to the general quota should be considered
                            by the Committee. I said that Mr. Viles’ telegram was being circulated
                            to all members of the Committee with a covering letter saying that the
                            proposal for holding a meeting of the Committee in the near future to
                            consider the general position was being kept in mind. Mr. Butterworth
                            stressed the fact that there was great uneasiness in America in regard
                            to rubber supplies; he said that present stocks were low and asked if he
                            could be assured that the Committee would be willing to release more
                            rubber in the near future? I said that I had talked to Sir John Campbell
                            that morning and that he had in view the possibility of the Committee
                            releasing more rubber if any speculative movement in America should
                            cause a run on rubber and an increase in demand leading to much higher
                            prices.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Butterworth asked if I did not think there would be a greatly
                            increased consumption of rubber in war time? I said that past experience
                            did not show this and, in any case, enormous supplies of rubber were
                            available to deal with any increased demand which might arise. It must
                            be remembered that the production of rubber would go on unhindered by
                            war in all producing territories and that adequate rubber supplies were
                            only a question of shipping whereas consumption would suffer definite
                            reduction from the prevention of enemy countries from access to crude
                            rubber supplies, and the diminution of civilian rubber consumption in
                            ‘war’ countries. The chief danger to rubber, at the moment, was from the
                            speculator who might rush to buy rubber, and create a false demand
                            resulting in a temporary rise in price—present indications in America
                            showed this was a real danger at the present time. If such a situation
                            should arise, I said that I knew it was the view of the Chairman that
                            the Committee would do everything in their power to meet it by raising
                            the quota but I thought that the most effective weapon would be
                            immediate propaganda in America against this ‘war’ speculative
                            psychology, which was, in our opinion, based on entirely wrong premises
                            and could only lead to great financial losses to any of those engaged in
                            it, and create difficulties that need never arise. Nothing seemed more
                            certain than that all the rubber the world required could and would be
                            supplied at reasonable prices throughout the duration of war however
                            long it might last—the only unknown factor was the shipping position but
                            it was reasonably certain that this could never create difficulties in
                            the supply of rubber to America other than perhaps purely temporary
                            difficulties at one time or another.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Butterworth asked if he could pass on the gist of my remarks to the
                            Ambassador. I said that I was speaking on my own authority but I felt
                            certain that I was expressing very generally the personal views of the
                            Chairman and I thought he could make any unofficial use of my remarks on
                            that basis that he thought fit.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kennedy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
