<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 145The United States High Commissioner for Germany (McCloy) to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d145</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">145</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-05-13T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-05-13T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recu0jAoErrAESV42" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002775"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Airlift</term>
                    <term ref="recC7rknrVEB9QNEK" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85014919"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recZOfMQQ0T1ERq22" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="border-administration" subject="border-administration" lcsh-match="no_match">Border incidents</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-05-13T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-05-13T16:00:00-05:00" n="145"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d145">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">762 0221/5–1352: Telegram</note>
                <head>No. 145<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner for Germany (<persName
                            corresp="#p_MJJ1" type="from">McCloy</persName>) to the <gloss type="to"
                            >Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d145fn1">Repeated to London, Paris, Moscow, and
                        Berlin.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret priority</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bonn</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-05-13T22:00:00+01:00"
                            >May 13, 1952—10 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2803. A series of developments over past fortnight suggests to us Kremlin is
                    embarking on a tough line toward West <gloss target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss>. Among
                    these incidents were stoppage of MP movement from Berlin,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d145fn2">On May 8 Soviet authorities had refused to allow U.S.
                        Military Police to continue their courtesy patrols along the autobahn from
                        Berlin to Helmstedt. For texts of letters protesting this refusal and the
                        attack on French aircraft on Apr. 29, referred to in the fourth paragraph of
                        this telegram, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                        Sept. 1, 1952, pp. 311 ff.</note> purge in <gloss target="#t_GDR1"
                        >GDR</gloss>, heightened <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> militancy
                    toward West, riot in Essen<note n="3" xml:id="d145fn3">On May 11 West German
                        police had quelled a riot by several thousand <gloss target="#t_FDJ1"
                            >FDJ</gloss> who had been in Essen to protest against the contractual
                        agreements and the rearmament of Germany.</note> shrill <persName
                        corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> statements yesterday.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d145fn4">At a press conference on May 12 <persName corresp="#p_UW1"
                            >Ulbricht</persName> had warned Bonn against signing the contractual
                        agreements and had threatened retaliation against Berlin if they were
                        signed. Berlin reported the substance of the press conference in telegram
                        1335, May 12. (662.001/5–1252)</note>
                </p>
                <p>We have felt that such a turn was almost inevitable once it became evident that
                    tactics of enticement had failed to produce practical political results in West.
                    Time has now come if Kremlin is to achieve its objectives of detaching <gloss
                        target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss> from West and bringing about collapse of
                        <gloss target="#t_EDF1">EDF</gloss>, to attempt to impress upon West <gloss
                        target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss>s ominous alternative to accepting package offer
                    contained in Sov notes. This does not of course exclude possibility that Kremlin
                    may put forward further offers. But for time being it appears to be
                    concentrating on driving home to West <gloss target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss>s peril
                    of rejecting its offers.</p>
                <p>This, however, is not an easy task for Moscow. <gloss target="#t_GER1"
                        >Ger</gloss> public has come over years to regard threats from <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> as cries of wolf wolf. Therefore, if this
                    tactic of menace is to have desired effect on West <gloss target="#t_GER1"
                        >Ger</gloss>s it must carry convincing tone of imminent and great danger.
                        <pb facs="0374" n="340" xml:id="pg_340"/> At same time, assuming Kremlin
                    does not seek war, scope of its threats are limited by what it must regard as
                    risk of explosive American reaction. Range between this floor and ceiling is not
                    great and must pose vexing problems for Kremlin.</p>
                <p>Berlin is of course most obvious point of exploitation. Kremlin has already
                    hinted in Air France and MP incidents what it can do on perhaps our most
                    vulnerable point, that of access, and in so doing has demonstrated to <gloss
                        target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss>s its position of control. We are not now
                    inclined to believe, however, that Kremlin will impose a full scale blockage. To
                    do so might well provoke another airlift which probably would politically
                    boomerang. It seems to us more likely that Kremlin will impose a creeping
                    blockade, possibly even restricting it to outward movements from Berlin combined
                    with an offer to absorb all Berlin production to East. Whatever Russians may do
                    on this score our guess is that they will apply their harrassing tactics
                    selectively trying to avoid cementing West <gloss target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss>
                    and Allies.</p>
                <p>As contractuals and <gloss target="#t_EDF1">EDF</gloss> progress toward
                    implementation Kremlin may <hi rend="italic">pari passu</hi> insist that we take
                    our troubles to <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GDR1"
                        >GDR</gloss> may be increasingly thrust into front position against us.
                    While such maneuver would obviously have many drawbacks for Kremlin tradition of
                    operating thru others with itself bearing minimum responsibility and retaining
                    thereby maximum flexibility.</p>
                <p>Foregoing is of course not all that Kremlin can do by way of intimidation. And
                    Moscow may well calculate, as we do, that these measures may not of themselves
                    suffice to stop contractuals and <gloss target="#t_EDF1">EDF</gloss>. What
                    remains is creation of East <gloss target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss> armed forces,
                    border incidents and rumblings of Sov milit power. First two would not
                    necessarily approach ceiling of American tolerance but third might. Because of
                    this we in Bonn do not see what Sov armed forces can do beyond ostentatious
                    display of force in East <gloss target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss>.</p>
                <p>What actual effect of Kremlin’s tough line will be on West <gloss
                        target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss>s is impossible to predict. In <gloss
                        target="#t_FedRep1">FedRep</gloss>s present circumstances, crust of West
                        <gloss target="#t_GER1">Ger</gloss> courage is understandably thin. It may
                    be hardened if we keep our own nerves steady and show determination to counter
                    Sov moves. On other hand it may break and West <gloss target="#t_GER1"
                        >Ger</gloss>s become paralyzed if Kremlin can create atmosphere that we are
                    undependable and that lining up with West will surely lead to civil war,
                    invasion, devastation by American bombing and Tartar occupation. Next few weeks
                    may be the test.<note n="5" xml:id="d145fn5">On May 14, in a telegram cleared
                        with <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_MHFD1">Matthews</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1"
                            >McCloy</persName> was informed that the Department of State believed
                        the reasons and conclusions presented in this telegram were sound and he
                        could “count on the full and steady Dept support in all efforts” which he
                        would “undoubtedly have to make [to] demonstrate Western coolness, firmness
                        and dependability.” (Telegram 3117 to Bonn, 762.00/5–1352)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">McCloy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
