<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-06-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-06-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="201" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d201">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">562.00/7–653</note>
                            <head>No. 201<lb/><hi rend="italic">The United States High Commissioner
                                    for Germany (<persName corresp="#p_CJP1" type="from">Conant</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d201fn1">The source
                                    text was attached to a reply from <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, dated July 6, which stated that it was
                                    being shown to <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>
                                    and <persName corresp="#p_RJW1">Riddleberger</persName> and
                                    that, in general, the Secretary of State agreed with everything
                                    that the High Commissioner said.</note></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret eyes
                                        only<lb/>personal</hi></seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Bonn</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-06-25">June 25, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Foster</persName></hi>: This is a personal letter to give
                                you my own appraisal of the situation here in Germany. It may be of
                                interest to you as a supplement to our regular cables. You will
                                notice the date and realize by the time this reaches you the
                                situation may have altered for events are moving fast here in
                                Germany. However, I hope that we are in a relatively quiet period
                                and therefore this report by mail may not be wholly out of date when
                                it reaches you.</p>
                            <p>The first point I should like to emphasize is the difficulty of
                                assessing German opinion in the Federal Republic because of the
                                party conflicts intensified by the coming elections. As I write, the
                                election law providing the way the elections will be carried out has
                                not yet been passed by the Bundestag. The Chancellor is definitely
                                worried about the nature of this law. His opponents accuse him of
                                wishing to insert in the law arbitrary provisions which will ensure
                                the return of the coalition. The coalition itself seems to be split
                                on <pb facs="0513" n="479" xml:id="pg_479"/> the merits of various
                                proposals involving the highly complicated problem of proportional
                                representation.</p>
                            <p>These intense party feelings, which are being generated at this time,
                                tend to obstruct the view of German political leaders about events
                                in the East Zone. Certainly they make for lack of candor in the
                                public statements. The Chancellor, for example, feels that he must
                                publicly support the opposition’s view, at least in part. Hence his
                                rather impulsive telegram of last Sunday to the President and the
                                Prime Ministers of England and France.<note n="2" xml:id="d201fn2">For text of Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>’s message to President <persName corresp="#p_EGADD1">Eisenhower</persName>, see <ref target="frus1952-54v07p2#d715">Document 715</ref>. For text
                                    of his letters to <persName corresp="#p_MR3">Mayer</persName>
                                    and <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>, see <hi rend="italic">Papers and Documents</hi>, pp. 119–120.</note>
                                As you know, he does not in the least desire a 4-Power conference
                                before the German elections. Indeed, nothing would be less helpful
                                to him in the coming campaign and more helpful to the opposition. He
                                does not favor even a discussion between the three High
                                Commissioners and the new Soviet High Commissioner. He told me only
                                yesterday that any friendly move between the French, British and
                                Americans, on the one side, and the Russians, on the other, would be
                                misconstrued by the German people as representing sympathy to the
                                oppressors rather than the victims of what has been going on in the
                                East Zone.</p>
                            <p>The opposition leaders, on the one hand, both publicly and privately,
                                are pushing for conversations between the Allied High Commission and
                                the new Soviet Commissar. Privately, a few weeks ago they were
                                pushing for a 4-Power conference and were willing to suggest
                                privately that Germany might make great concessions in the way of
                                boundary conditions and even reparations if unification could be
                                obtained at once. To what extent they believe in the reality of
                                these ideas, which seem to be fantastic, I am not prepared to
                                say.</p>
                            <p>Mayor <persName corresp="#p_RE1">Reuter</persName>’s judgment about
                                the situation in Berlin is likewise affected by his ambitions as a
                                leading personality of the opposition party. He, for example, told
                                the Commandants that he desired an “all-Berlin election”. When I
                                asked him, in private conversation, what he meant by this attractive
                                slogan, he had to admit that until there were new arrangements made
                                with the Russians the election of a Mayor and <hi rend="italic">Senat</hi> for all of Berlin would be disastrous. For, on
                                pushing my argument with him, he admitted readily that a Mayor and
                                    <hi rend="italic">Senat</hi> acting for all Berlin would, under
                                the old arrangements which are still in force in theory, have to be
                                subjected to the veto power of a Russian member of a 4-Power
                                Kommandatura. He then proposed that the Allied High Commission
                                should negotiate with the Russians to establish arrangements in
                                Berlin <pb facs="0514" n="480" xml:id="pg_480"/> similar to those
                                that exist in Vienna. But, as he had to admit, on pushing, this was
                                a far more complicated, delicate and far-reaching proposal than the
                                attractive slogan “all-Berlin elections.”</p>
                            <p>My analysis of German opinion today is that the most intelligent
                                Germans are torn between their desire for re-unification and their
                                realization that, barring miracles, the Russians are not going “to
                                be talked out of” their Occupation status. The events in the East
                                Zone have demonstrated to the whole world the failure of the Russian
                                policy insofar as making converts of the working people is
                                concerned.</p>
                            <p>What is not always realized in talking about the East Zone is the
                                fact that some 10 percent of the population has already left. It is
                                my estimate, based on talks with a number of people who should be
                                good sources of information, that essentially all the middle and
                                upper class families have left the Zone. Only the workers, the
                                peasants and older retired people are left. This presents a rather
                                special situation in Europe, therefore, and one which the Russians
                                may well have thought was readily susceptible to their form of
                                propaganda. Exactly the reverse seems to have been the case. Workers
                                seem to have rejected the Communistic leadership partly for
                                political reasons but largely, I believe, for economic reasons. The
                                situation in regard to food in the East Zone seems to have been much
                                worse even than some of us, who were pessimistic about the
                                situation, had imagined.</p>
                            <p>Whatever may have been the cause, it is important to know that the
                                workers in their demonstrations pulled down the Red flag of the
                                    <gloss target="#t_SPD1">SPD</gloss> and seemed to be almost as
                                hostile to the Socialistic Party as to the Communistic leaders.
                                Workers in Germany in this mood could well be supporters of a
                                powerful right-wing reactionary movement. I believe there is a
                                danger here which must not be underrated, though it cannot be
                                publicly discussed.</p>
                            <p>One of the questions which may be settled before this letter reaches
                                you is whether or not the Russians can establish a new puppet
                                government in the East Zone. If they cannot and continue to rely on
                                the old regime they will in essence be controlling the affairs of
                                the East Zone themselves. I assume, of course, that martial law will
                                be lifted before long and that they will restore conditions in
                                Berlin to the situation that existed two weeks ago, though even this
                                is not certain. It may be they will decide to try to bargain with us
                                about the Berlin situation, since they have been forced to
                                accomplish what they have long threatened to do, that is, to cut
                                Berlin in half. It would be my judgment, as of today, that we should
                                be very loathe to enter into any talks with the new Russian High
                                Commissioner, Semenov, except on a bilateral basis, that is, between
                                each one of the High Commissioners and Semenov himself. I should <pb facs="0515" n="481" xml:id="pg_481"/> think that any offer on
                                his part to meet with the three Allied High Commissioners should be
                                carefully explored before we agree and one of the conditions should
                                be a restoration of conditions in the entire East Zone to what they
                                were on the 1st of June. A further condition, in my mind, should be
                                a specialized agenda and above all it should be made plain that we
                                are not in any sense re-establishing the old 4-Power Control
                                Council. Of course, even the mention of such a possibility as the
                                re-establishment of the 4-Power Control Council terrifies all
                                Germans. You will have seen by our cables that there is a difference
                                of opinion in my staff as to the extent of the pressures in the
                                coalition parties for 4-Power talks at any level. <persName corresp="#p_HW1">Hallstein</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BHAH1">Blankenhorn</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LO1">Lenz</persName>, at my house today, seemed to
                                express almost the opinion of the Chancellor. But one cannot be sure
                                whether they were merely echoing what they knew to be his private
                                thoughts, as shown to me, or whether they sincerely believed in his
                                secret position.</p>
                            <p>Until the Chancellor himself, as a judge of the political situation
                                here should pass the word to us that he believed negotiations with
                                the Russians should be undertaken, I would be very sure of going
                                very slowly in the direction of a meeting of the Allied High
                                Commission and the Russian High Commissioner on any 4-Power talks
                                about the state of Germany. Even if the Allied occupying powers are
                                blamed for procrastination in going forward with the negotiations, I
                                believe we should be well advised to hold the present line until
                                after the German elections. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Sir Winston
                                    Churchill</persName>’s recent reply<note n="3" xml:id="d201fn3">For <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s reply,
                                    June 24, see <hi rend="italic">Papers and Documents</hi>, pp.
                                    120–121.</note> to the Chancellor’s telegram seems to give us a
                                clear line of defense: namely, we again offer the Russians, as we
                                did in our last note,<note n="4" xml:id="d201fn4">For the tripartite
                                    note of Sept. 23, 1952, see <ref target="#d138">Document
                                        138</ref>.</note> the opportunity for free all-German
                                elections provided they meet the terms we then specified. I do not
                                believe that they can possibly meet these terms when we start to
                                spell out the details of what they must involve.</p>
                            <p>I hope these somewhat rambling comments of a complicated and rapidly
                                moving situation may be of some value to you.</p>
                            <p>With all good wishes,</p>
                            <p>Sincerely,</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_CJP1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Jim
                                            Conant</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>