<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 370Memorandum of Conversation, by the Counselor of the Embassy in Austria
                    (Davis)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d370</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">370</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-01-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-01-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="370"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d370">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 205</note>
                <head>No. 370<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Counselor of the Embassy in
                        Austria (<persName>Davis</persName>)</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d370fn1">Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_MLT1"
                            >Merchant</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FRB1"
                        >Freund</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1954-01-27">January 27, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <item>Participants: Dr. <persName>Roessler</persName>, Member of the Unofficial
                        Austrian Delegation</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>R.H. Davis</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">Subject: Austrian Inquiry on Developments Affecting Austria at
                    the Four-Power Conference</p>
                <p>At Dr. <persName>Roessler</persName>’s request I saw him at 4:30 this
                    afternoon.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. Austrian Participation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Dr. <persName>Roessler</persName> inquired how we thought the conference was
                    going along in regard to the Austrian question. I replied that there was little
                    I could tell him beyond what he probably had read in the newspapers but I was
                    authorized to say confidentially that the three powers had agreed to take up the
                    question of Austrian participation in the discussions on the Austrian treaty
                    question at the first appropriate moment and when such action promised
                    success.</p>
                <pb facs="0883" n="849" xml:id="pg_849"/>
                <p>I inquired whether the Austrian delegation had in its files in Berlin a copy of
                    the Soviet note of January 16 to the Austrian Government, which referred to the
                    Austrian note of January 5 requesting participation.<note n="2" xml:id="d370fn2"
                        >No copy of the Soviet note has been found in Department of State files. The
                        Austrian note was transmitted in telegram 1678 from Vienna, Jan. 5 (396.1
                        BE/1–554); for text, see Department of State <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bulletin</hi>, Jan. 25, 1954, p. 111.</note> Dr.
                        <persName>Roessler</persName> replied he did not know but if they had a copy
                    with them, he would make it available tomorrow.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. Position of Austrian Item on Agenda</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I inquired in view of Dr. <persName corresp="#p_SJ2">Schoener</persName>’s
                    comments to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d370fn3">On Jan. 25 Schoerner had paid a courtesy call on
                            <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> and
                            <persName>Davis</persName> during which he expressed the hope that the
                        Austrian Treaty would be discussed before the conference became deadlocked
                        on Germany. (Memorandum of conversation, by <persName>Davis</persName>, Jan.
                        25, Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 203)</note> whether the Austrian
                    delegation was disappointed that an agenda had been adopted which placed the
                    Austrian item at the end. Dr. <persName>Roessler</persName> replied that there
                    were two points of view on this and no one could say whether it would be good or
                    bad to have the Austrian item considered first or last. I assented to this and
                    pointed out that some were of the opinion that the Austrian item had a better
                    chance of success at the end of the conference. This opinion was based on
                    reasoning that the Soviet Union would not like to see the conference completely
                    without result; that Austria was a question on which they could give without
                    paying too great a price and should the first two items on the agenda not
                    produce any results, it was possible that something could come out of the
                    discussions on the Austrian State Treaty.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">3. Yugoslav Observer</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Dr. <persName>Roessler</persName> inquired whether we had yet heard anything in
                    regard to a Yugoslav observer. I said the Department of State had been informed
                    orally by the Yugoslav Embassy in Washington that the Yugoslav Ambassador to
                    Bonn, Ivekovic, had been named as an official observer to the Berlin Conference
                    and the Embassy had been merely informed by the Department that the delegation
                    in Berlin would be informed (see <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_Tosec1">Tosec</gloss> 35<note n="4" xml:id="d370fn4">
                        <gloss target="#t_Tosec1">Tosec</gloss> 35 reported that Ivekovic had been
                        named as the official Yugoslav observer to the Conference. (Conference
                        files, lot 60 D 627, CF 211)</note>). Also this morning the Yugoslav
                    Military Liaison Office in Berlin had delivered an official note<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d370fn5">Not found in Department of State files.</note> addressed to
                    the “Conference of the Foreign Ministers” which merely stated that Yugoslavia
                    was sending its Ambassador at Bonn to Berlin as an observer at the
                    Conference.</p>
                <p>I said there was no present intention to reply to this note. I said that we did
                    not recognize officially the status of an observer at the Conference and that if
                    a Yugoslav representative made inquiry, we <pb facs="0884" n="850"
                        xml:id="pg_850"/> propose to inform him that as regards the Austrian treaty,
                    Yugoslavia might be kept informed on matters affecting its interests.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">R.H. Davis</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
