<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 385Notes by the Special Assistant to the President (Jackson) on a Dinner
                    at the Residence of the Soviet High Commissioner for Germany, Berlin, January
                    29, 1954</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d385</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">385</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-01-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recDxa7szVhIjbJXw" type="compound-subject" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Where we were</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-01-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="385"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d385">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 204</note>
                <head>No. 385<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Notes by the Special Assistant to the President (<persName
                            corresp="#p_JCD1">Jackson</persName>) on a Dinner at the Residence of
                        the Soviet High Commissioner for Germany, Berlin, January 29, 1954</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1954-01-29">January 29, 1954</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>After handshakes all around the party remained standing and drank a glass of
                    vermouth. Conversation was sparse and artificial. <persName>Gromyko</persName>,
                    who looked like death warmed over, tried to be jovial by indulging in some
                    banter with <persName>Semenov</persName> about his baldness which
                        <persName>Gromyko</persName> attributed to his long tenure as High
                    Commissioner. High Commissioner <persName corresp="#p_CJP1">Conant</persName>’s
                    ample locks could only be explained by the fact that he had held office for only
                    one year. This spirited exchange took place in the center of the large,
                    hall-like room at the far end of which the dinner table was set. In the section
                    of the room where we were standing there were two tables at opposite sides of
                    the room surrounded by exactly the right number of chairs <pb facs="0913"
                        n="879" xml:id="pg_879"/> and loaded with fruit, candy, glasses, bottles of
                    Russian cognac, plates and sugar bowls, indicating that after dinner we were to
                    break up into equal sized groups, sufficiently separated to prevent easy
                    overhearing of the other group’s conversation.</p>
                <p>Shortly, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> led a move toward the
                    dinner table, lavishly set with china, silverware, four wine glasses, a bottle
                    of vodka and a bottle of Georgian wine for every two persons and profusely
                    spread with hors d’oeuvre type cold dishes.</p>
                <p>The Russian hosts started the vodka act almost immediately. They all drew special
                    attention to the vodka bottles which have several slivers of red pepper lying on
                    the bottom. They all explained that the red pepper did not increase its
                    intoxicating quality but simply served to give it a sharper taste.</p>
                <p>A series of cold dishes, led off by caviar, were served, fish, meat, salads,
                    vegetables.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> sat between <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> and interpreter
                        <persName>Troyanovsky</persName>. Commissioner <persName corresp="#p_CJP1"
                        >Conant</persName> sat approximately opposite <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                        >Dulles</persName>.</p>
                <p>Quite early, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> arose for his
                    first toast, to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>, who looked somewhat tired
                    when we sat down, apparently enjoys the toasting ritual. His whole face changes.
                    The downward curving lines of his face seem to develop an upturn and he smiles
                    and twinkles. His humor, even in translation, has a really entertaining edge and
                    never seems heavy.</p>
                <p>After toasting the Secretary, <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName>
                    toasted Dr. <persName corresp="#p_CJP1">Conant</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BCEC1"
                        >Bohlen</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JCD1">Jackson</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_NFC1">Frank Nash</persName>. He was a trifle confused
                    on <persName corresp="#p_NFC1">Nash</persName>’s exact status and because of his
                    Defense Department connection assumed that he was a military “character”.
                        <persName corresp="#p_NFC1">Nash</persName> disabused him and then the
                    Secretary referred to <persName corresp="#p_NFC1">Nash</persName> as a bridge
                    between the Defense and State. This idea started some lively chatter winding up
                    with the suggestion that if <persName corresp="#p_NFC1">Nash</persName>
                    continued to do such a good job between Defense and State, he should be given
                    the job of handling the bridge between Washington and Moscow. <persName
                        corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> commented that in such a job the task
                    of avoiding collisions would be heavier.</p>
                <p>The Secretary during the course of the dinner referred to the fact that the
                    President had asked him to convey his regards to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1"
                        >Molotov</persName> whom he remembered meeting during the war. There seemed
                    to be a little doubt as to exactly when the meeting had taken place, but
                        <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> cleared that up, the first
                    time in Washington in 1942 and the second time in Moscow in 1945.</p>
                <p>The President and President <persName>Voroshilov</persName> were naturally
                    toasted and then Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MVM1">Molotov</persName> got all
                    wound up in a second toast to the Secretary in which he was laying it on rather
                    thick. All of a sudden he stopped and said “I suppose I should not be speaking
                    this way because I will be accused of polemics”, a reference to the <pb
                        facs="0914" n="880" xml:id="pg_880"/> constant appearance of the word
                    polemic during the Conference meetings where almost all speakers announce that
                    they will avoid it and then launch into it.</p>
                <p>All the other American guests each got their toast and the Secretary replied for
                    the whole group.</p>
                <p>Having no previous experience in such dinners I do not know if the consumption of
                    vodka was up to standard. However, there seemed to be an impressive array of
                    empty vodka bottles and an equally impressive array of erect Americans.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d385fn1">For a record of the conversation following dinner,
                        see the memorandum of conversation by <persName corresp="#p_MLT1"
                            >Merchant</persName>, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
