<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 511Position Paper Agreed by the Delegations of the United States, the
                    United Kingdom, and France</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d511</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">511</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="reclX4mzFRYzavuL4" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections">Free elections</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7qTHF1AQkAKGHv" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                    <term ref="recAPhAIrM8XS4R2T" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial integrity</term>
                    <term ref="rec8Yg8zBxh2Slo2M" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="prisoners-of-war"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106971"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prisoners of war</term>
                    <term ref="rec992a6b996ec03c1" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="german-peace-treaty">German peace treaty</term>
                    <term ref="rec8b79a8b95ce4a65" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="atlantic-charter">Atlantic Charter</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="511"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d511">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 200</note>
                <head>No. 511<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Position Paper Agreed by the Delegations of the United States,
                        the United Kingdom, and France</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d511fn1">Attached to the source text was a cover sheet which
                        indicates that it was circulated in the records of the U.S. Delegation as
                        BER D–4/4c and that it represented a slightly revised version of BER D–4/4b,
                        a copy of which has not been found in Department of State files. The cover
                        sheet indicates further that it had not been shown to the Federal Government
                        and that it had not been decided whether or when to use the declaration. The
                        text was agreed at a meeting of the Tripartite Working Group on Feb. 1 (see
                        BER MIN–8, <ref target="#d397">Document 397</ref>), but there is no
                        indication in the records of the conference that it was ever
                        introduced.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/> [BER D–4/4c]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-02-01">February 1,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Declaration of Intent Regarding German Peace Treaty</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">four-power meeting in berlin, january 1954</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>I.</label>
                    <item>On January 29, 1954 the United Kingdom Delegation tabled proposals for
                        free elections to be held throughout Germany at the earliest possible date
                        with a view to forming a National Assembly and an all-German government
                        which would proceed to negotiate with the four occupying powers a peace
                        treaty for Germany.<note n="2" xml:id="d511fn2">FPM(54)17, <hi rend="italic"
                                >supra</hi>.</note> The Delegation therefore recommends that the
                        four occupying powers should hold themselves ready to open negotiations for
                        a German peace treaty as soon as representatives of a reunited Germany have
                        been appointed in the manner envisaged in the proposal of the United Kingdom
                        Delegation.</item>
                    <pb facs="1215" n="1181" xml:id="pg_1181"/>
                    <label>II.</label>
                    <item>The Delegation considers that such a peace treaty should embody the
                        following principles: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Germany shall be recognized as a sovereign State.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Germany shall apply for membership in the United Nations. The
                                other Powers signatory to the peace treaty will undertake to support
                                this application.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Pending admission to the United Nations, Germany shall declare her
                                intention of conforming to the principles of the Charter and shall
                                undertake to conduct her foreign relations in accordance therewith.
                                Germany shall also be authorized to assure her defense as provided
                                by Article 51 of the Charter. Germany shall accept the obligations
                                set forth in Article 2 of the Charter, in particular: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>to settle her international disputes by peaceful means in
                                        such a manner that international peace and security, and
                                        justice, are not endangered;</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>to refrain in her international relations from the threat
                                        or use of force against the territorial integrity or
                                        political independence of any State or in any other manner
                                        inconsistent with the purposes of the United Nations;</item>
                                    <label>(c)</label>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>to give the United Nations every assistance in any action
                                            it takes in accordance with the Charter and to refrain
                                            from giving assistance to any State against which the
                                            United Nations may take preventive or enforcement
                                            action;</p>
                                        <p>For their part, the Signatory Powers would be guided by
                                            the principles of Article 2 of the United Nations
                                            Charter in their relations with Germany.</p>
                                    </item>
                                </list>
                            </item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The question of frontiers shall be settled by the peace treaty as
                                a result of free negotiations between the interested powers,
                                including the government of a unified Germany, in the spirit of
                                points 1 and 2 of the Atlantic Charter and Article 1 of the <gloss
                                    target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The return of all remaining German prisoners of war and civilian
                                internees should be carried out within the shortest possible time
                                and shall be completed without exception not later than 90 days
                                after the coming into force of the peace treaty.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The all-German Government, subject to the provisions of the peace
                                treaty, shall determine whether to put into force, with respect to
                                unified Germany, international agreements concluded after May 8,
                                1945, and before its assumption of office, with the consent of the
                                other parties to those agreements.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>
                                <p>The peace treaty should contain no provisions which might prevent
                                    the people of unified Germany from building and maintaining a
                                    sound economy. The treaty should ensure to Germany, subject to
                                    its international obligations, the unfettered freedom to
                                    regulate its own economy, which is the normal prerogative of
                                    every sovereign State.</p>
                                <p>The treaty should dispose finally of all claims arising out of
                                    the war and occupation. Any industrial enterprises in Germany
                                    whose ownership or control was acquired after May 8, 1945, by or
                                    on behalf of any foreign government, should be surrendered and
                                    disposed of in accordance with appropriate German legislation
                                    unless <pb facs="1216" n="1182" xml:id="pg_1182"/> such
                                    acquisition has quadripartite approval and the interest so
                                    approved is subject to German law.</p>
                            </item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>The signatory powers to the peace treaty should include all
                                States, or the successors thereof, which were at war with
                                Germany.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
