<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 519Proposal of the Soviet Delegation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v07p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d519</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">519</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recILtkyFxUcMxK9f" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-02-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-02-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="519"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d519">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, CF 197</note>
                <head>No. 519<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Proposal of the Soviet Delegation</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d519fn1">This proposal was introduced at the fifteenth
                        plenary on Feb. 12. For a record of that meeting, see <gloss
                            target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 129, <ref target="#d464">Document
                            464</ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">[Translation]</note>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                        <lb/> FPM(54)55</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-02-12">February 12,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Conclusion of the State Treaty for the Re-Establishment of
                        an Independent and Democratic Austria</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Governments of the USSR, France, the United Kingdom and the USA recognize
                    that the consolidation of peace in Europe and the need for ensuring the national
                    rights of the Austrian people require an early re-establishment of a free and
                    independent Austria, and that, the settlement of the Austrian question should be
                    in conformity with the existing Four-Power agreements.</p>
                <p>Accordingly the Governments of the Four Powers agree:</p>
                <p>1. To instruct the Deputy Ministers for Foreign Affairs to draft, within a period
                    of three months, the final text of “The State Treaty <pb facs="1228" n="1194"
                        xml:id="pg_1194"/> for the Re-establishment of an Independent and Democratic
                    Austria”, on the following lines:</p>
                <p>a) To conclude the preparation of the draft State Treaty with Austria, which was
                    in the main agreed among the Four Powers in 1949, according to which Austria
                    shall be re-established as a sovereign, independent and democratic state and
                    shall be freed from control by the Four Powers, the existing control
                    machinery—the Allied Commission for Austria and all its organs—being abolished
                    and the occupation of Austria being terminated.</p>
                <p>b) To insert in the text of the State Treaty with Austria the following
                    additional article: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>“Austria undertakes not to enter into any coalition or military alliance
                            directed against any Power which participated with its armed forces in
                            the war against Germany and in the liberation of Austria.</p>
                        <p>“Austria undertakes further not to permit the establishment on its
                            territory of foreign military bases and not to permit the use of foreign
                            military instructors and specialists in Austria”.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>The Governments of the USA, the United Kingdom, France and the USSR on their part
                    shall assume the obligation to observe the provisions of this Article;</p>
                <p>c) Note shall be taken of the communication of the Soviet Government to the
                    effect that, being desirous of meeting the wishes of the Austrian Government, it
                    agrees that Austria shall pay, in the form of deliveries of goods the sum which,
                    in accordance with Article 35 of the draft State Treaty, is due to the Soviet
                    Union on account of the former German assets.</p>
                <p>2. In order to prevent any attempt at a new <hi rend="italic">Anschluss</hi>, to
                    postpone, pending the conclusion of a peace treaty with Germany, the withdrawal
                    of the troops of the Four Powers stationed in the territory of the respective
                    zones of Austria.</p>
                <p>To withdraw from the city of Vienna all foreign troops simultaneously with the
                    abolition of the Allied Commission.</p>
                <p>The troops of the Four Powers temporarily left in Austria shall not be occupation
                    troops and shall not perform the functions of occupation, nor shall they
                    interfere in the affairs of the Austrian Administration nor in the social and
                    political life of the country.</p>
                <p>The legal status of these troops shall be determined by a special agreement which
                    shall be prepared by the Four Powers with the participation of Austria, and
                    which shall enter into force simultaneously with the coming into force of the
                    State Treaty with Austria.</p>
                <p>3. To instruct the Deputy Ministers for Foreign Affairs to consider the question
                    of Trieste in connection with the proposal of the Soviet Government that the
                    City of Trieste and the territory adjacent to it shall not be used as a military
                    base.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
