<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>181. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in the
                    Congo</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-12-26T18:59:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-12-26T18:59:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-12-26T18:59:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-12-26T18:59:00-05:00" n="181"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                <head>181. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in the Congo<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d181fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 770G.00/12–2661. Confidential; Priority. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_RE1">Eisenberg</persName>; cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_JWF1">Fredericks</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SBV1"
                            >Vance</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GCM1">McGhee</persName>, and in
                        substance by <persName corresp="#p_WW1">Wallner</persName>; and approved by
                            <persName corresp="#p_DR1">Rusk</persName> (<persName corresp="#p_GCM1"
                            >McGhee</persName> initialed for him). Repeated to London, Brussels,
                        Paris, <gloss target="#USUN1">USUN</gloss>, and Salisbury.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-12-26T18:59:00-05:00">December 26, 1961, 6:59 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1128. From Secretary for Ambassador. I am greatly pleased by adroit and effective
                    way in which you brought US influence to bear during course Kitona discussions
                    to avoid breakdown. There is no doubt in my mind that this was done without
                    undue pressure on either party.</p>
                <pb facs="0375" n="347" xml:id="pg_347"/>
                <p>It is vital to our interests that Kitona agreement be implemented. You aware of
                    program of pressures we preparing apply on <persName corresp="#p_MT1"
                        >Tshombe</persName> if needed to bring him along to its implementation. On
                    other hand it is very important that <persName corresp="#p_CA1"
                        >Adoula</persName> continue conciliatory attitude both in order that he be
                    prepared accept <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> effort implement
                    agreement if <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> reasonable but also
                    to avoid giving Katangan extremists excuses for urging non implementation.</p>
                <p>You have in past made very clear to <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>
                    what risks and difficulties US Govt has been up against in giving him and <gloss
                        target="#UN1">UN</gloss> support which made Kitona agreement possible. He
                    will therefore understand importance his avoiding statements or measures at
                    present juncture which might jeopardize the peaceful reintegration of Katanga we
                    both seek. Measure of success which Kitona represents for <persName
                        corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> should facilitate his adopting public
                    posture of firmness but forebearance toward Katangans and Belgian business
                    interests that area.</p>
                <p>I am greatly impressed by <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>’s
                    statesmanship and I trust that, given mutual confidence and esteem which you
                    have been able to build up with him, <persName corresp="#p_CA1"
                        >Adoula</persName> will continue be receptive to our advice even where
                    personal feelings and political pressures might suggest somewhat different
                    course.</p>
                <p>Suggest in your talk with <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> you draw
                    in general terms upon recent telegrams outlining nature of pressures we prepared
                    apply on <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> in attempt convince
                        <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> resort to force should not be
                    required and threats thereof could play into hands of extremists in Katanga.</p>
                <p>Suggest you also reiterate to <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>
                    assistance he could give to our efforts marshal widespread support behind our
                    Katangan policy and his if he were to move definitively against <persName
                        corresp="#p_AG1">Gizenga</persName>.</p>
                <p>Finally, it is of utmost importance that <persName corresp="#p_CA1"
                        >Adoula</persName> not be tempted to overreach himself in expectation of
                    more US and <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> support than can be furnished. He is
                    not in driver’s seat to extent he supposes and must assume a statesmanlike
                    approach to a Congo settlement.<note n="2" xml:id="d181fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName> reported in telegram 1661,
                        December 26, that he had met the previous day with <persName
                            corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>, who “seemed more flexible and
                        conciliatory than previously.” <persName corresp="#p_EAG1"
                            >Gullion</persName> commented, “We hope to be able to keep <persName
                            corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> in this conciliatory frame of mind
                        but past experience teaches us how volatile and sometimes elusive even the
                        most stable Congolese politicians can be.” He stated that within a week the
                        United Nations would move a “small number” of <gloss target="#ANC1"
                            >ANC</gloss> troops to Kamina, which was supposed to be their southern
                        limit of advance, and he had prepared <persName corresp="#p_CA1"
                            >Adoula</persName> for a U.S. refusal to move the troops in U.S.
                        aircraft. (Ibid.)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DR1">Rusk</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
