<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-09-28T05:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-09-28T05:00:00-05:00" n="298" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d298">
                        <head>298. Telegram From the Embassy in the Congo to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d298fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Central Files, 110.12–McG/9–2862. Secret; Priority. Also
                                sent to <gloss target="#USUN1">USUN</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Léopoldville</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-09-28T11:00:00+01:00">September 28, 1962, 11 a.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>761. Department also pass to White House. Eyes only Acting Secretary from
                                <persName corresp="#p_GCM1">McGhee</persName>. <gloss target="#USUN1">USUN</gloss> eyes only for Secretary and <persName corresp="#p_AES1">Stevenson</persName>. Following summary of
                            situation here as I see it after first days talks with Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName> and staff, Acting
                            Foreign Minister, <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_MK1">Khiari</persName>, Belgian, <gloss target="#UK1">UK</gloss>, German Ambassadors and Canadian Charge: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>It is generally agreed that implementation conciliation plan
                                    is stalled (see <gloss target="#Embtel1">Embtel</gloss>
                                        755).<note n="2" xml:id="d298fn2">Dated September 27.
                                        (Ibid., 770G.00/9–2762)</note> Key members of three
                                    commissions in Elisabethville returning to Léopoldville with
                                    others remaining as holding action. <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> clearly does not recognize Commissions
                                    as implementing agencies but only as discussion groups and has
                                    injected into their deliberations impossible procedural as well
                                    as substantive issues. No important irreversible step has been
                                    taken under plan. As <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName> puts it, it is only question of whether
                                        <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> admits situation, not as to
                                    whether it exists.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Although I have not yet seen <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>, three hour meeting having been scheduled
                                    for September 28th, all sources indicate that he is not prepared
                                    to give on constitutional consultation issue and that his
                                    already weak political position would be greatly endangered if
                                    he did. We do not know, however, his reaction to U <persName corresp="#p_UT1">Thant</persName>’s letter of September 24
                                    on this subject which he has requested 24 hours to consider.
                                    Agreement to consultation will be prime objective of my
                                    discussion with <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> and
                                    all possible variants as to how consultation can be arranged
                                    will be exhausted.</item>
                                <pb facs="0616" n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName> states
                                    clearly that he has not up to this point considered himself a
                                    mediator between <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>
                                    and <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> in furtherance
                                    of plan, which means that there is no real link now between
                                        <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss>-<persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName>’s position is that he will not go to
                                    Elisabethville until he sees evidence good faith on <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName>’s part which,
                                    particularly in light of day’s revelations, is not likely unless
                                    some new element is injected into situation.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>I do not see any objection to <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> proceeding with letters re payments from
                                    mining companies agreed to between <persName corresp="#p_PHS1">Spaak</persName> and Secretary General outlined <gloss target="#Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 134.<note n="3" xml:id="d298fn3">Telegram 905 to <gloss target="#USUN1">USUN</gloss> (<ref target="#d297">Document 297</ref>)
                                        was repeated as telegram 134 to Léopoldville.</note> This
                                    appears to be in line with other steps being taken by <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> pursuant to plan and
                                    should not provide excuse for <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> that he cannot proceed with plan under
                                    threat. Indeed steps should add useful pressure on <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> and in event Belgians
                                    succeed in getting <gloss target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> to
                                    deposit revenues with Central Government will put onus on
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> if any
                                    retaliatory move is made.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>I have received proposal from <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> covering two or three day visit which with some
                            modifications I propose to accept arriving October 1st. If agreeable to
                            Department, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName>
                            and <persName corresp="#p_LH1">Hoffacker</persName> will accompany me to
                            Elisabethville. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName> would participate in initial meeting.</p>
                        <p>Other discussions with <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> will
                            be requested alone.</p>
                        <p>My immediate strategy, unless Department perceives objection is as
                            follows.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Attempt persuade <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> to
                                some form of compromise on constitutional consultation issue.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Attempt persuade <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> of
                                necessity following through with plan and to receive <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName> in a frame of mind which
                                can result in fruitful negotiations on specific issues removal of
                                which would permit resumption work of Commissions and carrying out
                                plan. I will seek avoid mediatory role.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Persuade <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName>,
                                contingent on success efforts with <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName>, to go to Elisabethville immediately
                                following my return. I would in such case remain in Léopoldville to
                                await outcome after having made it clear to <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> that my report to Secretary
                                and President <pb facs="0617" n="589" xml:id="pg_589"/> would hinge
                                largely on concrete results of <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName> meeting that can be put into effect without
                                    delay.<note n="4" xml:id="d298fn4">Telegram 525 to Léopoldville,
                                    September 29, replied that <persName corresp="#p_GCM1">McGhee</persName>’s three-point strategy appeared sound but
                                    questioned the advisability of <persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName> accompanying him to Elisabethville, lest
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> use this as an
                                    excuse for lack of cooperation. (Department of State, Central
                                    Files, 110.12–McG/9–2862) Meanwhile, <persName corresp="#p_GCM1">McGhee</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName> had agreed that <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName>’s visit to
                                    Elisabethville should precede <persName corresp="#p_GCM1">McGhee</persName>’s; <persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName> remained in Léopoldville, pleading prior
                                    engagements. (Telegrams 770 and 778–780 from Léopoldville,
                                    September 29, and 781, September 30; ibid., 110.12–McG/9–2962
                                    and 110.12–McG/9–3062, respectively)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>