<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-11-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-11-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="324" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d324">
                        <head>324. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for
                            National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CK1">Kaysen</persName>)
                            to President <persName corresp="#p_JFK1">Kennedy</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d324fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JFK1">Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security Files, <persName corresp="#p_WHB1">Brubeck</persName> Series, Congo.
                                Confidential.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-11-07">November 7,
                                    1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">Mr. President: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The attached paper from the Department of State<note n="2" xml:id="d324fn2">The attachment is a copy of the “Proposed
                                        Contingency Plan for the Congo;” see <ref target="#d323fn5">footnote 5, Document 323</ref>.</note> gives their
                                    estimate of the Congo situation and proposals for a U.S. course
                                    of action.<note n="3" xml:id="d324fn3">A November 5 memorandum
                                        from <persName corresp="#p_JFK1">Kennedy</persName> to
                                            <persName corresp="#p_DR1">Rusk</persName>, signed but
                                        never sent, reads as follows: “I wish you and George
                                            <persName corresp="#p_GWB1">Ball</persName> would take a
                                        long look as to where we are in the Congo. “If the <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> effort is going to collapse we
                                        should work out some alternatives. We should at least be
                                        laying our ground work. “A handwritten note on a copy of the
                                        memorandum states that it was not sent because a meeting had
                                        already been arranged for the following day; see <ref target="#d325">Document 325</ref>. (<persName corresp="#p_JFK1">Kennedy</persName> Library, National
                                        Security Files, Country Series, Congo)</note> It has been
                                    reviewed by the Secretary; he has approved its transmission to
                                    you, but it does not necessarily represent his own final view of
                                    what should be done.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>In brief, the paper argues that the present stationary
                                    situation will soon dissolve in a way highly unfavorable to the
                                    U.S. unless we take positive action now. If we fail to take
                                    action, the results will at best be a serious loss of U.S. and
                                    Western position throughout Africa and in the <pb facs="0680" n="652" xml:id="pg_652"/>
                                    <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss>, the replacement of <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> by a radical,
                                    irresponsible and probably Soviet-influenced government in
                                    Léopoldville, and at least sporadic fighting in Katanga and
                                    other parts of the Congo. At worst, there might be a full-scale
                                    war in which the other African states will join in with the
                                    Central Congo Government, while the Central Africa Federation,
                                    South Africa and the Portuguese will join in support of the
                                    Katanga: something like White –Black war in Africa. The
                                    recommended course of action contains three elements: (a)
                                    Strengthening <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> along
                                    the lines previously discussed. (b) Strengthening the <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> in the Congo, especially increasing
                                    its military capacity by additional transport and combat
                                    aircraft and perhaps by additional troops. (c) Putting pressure
                                    on <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> by diplomatic
                                    means, but holding in reserve and making known to <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> a definite decision to
                                    impose economic sanctions after a firm deadline of one month.
                                    State estimates that this course of action would succeed,
                                    although it might conceivably involve some fighting between
                                        <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> troops and Katanga
                                    gendarmerie.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><p>As I see it, there are two major problems in the paper.
                                        First, what confidence can we have in State’s assessment of
                                        the urgency of the situation? The view expressed in the
                                        paper is very strongly held by Governor <persName corresp="#p_GMW1">Williams</persName> and the whole
                                        Bureau, as well as by Ed <persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName> in Léopoldville. If it is not
                                        correct, it is obvious that we have more time to continue
                                        the more cautious policy represented by <persName corresp="#p_GCM1">McGhee</persName>’s efforts to promote
                                        some conciliatory steps by both <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>. Second, the means of enforcing
                                        sanctions lie mainly in Belgian, and, to some extent, in
                                        British hands. So far we have no indication that the
                                        Belgians will in fact agree to commit themselves now to
                                        imposing sanctions on a specified deadline. At a minimum, we
                                        must get them to share our view of the urgency of the
                                        situation, before they are at all likely to consider this
                                        step. So far, they do not seem to share this view.</p>
                                    <p>As I indicated to you this morning, Governor <persName corresp="#p_GMW1">Williams</persName> and all his staff
                                        feel very strongly that decision to go ahead along the lines
                                        proposed is absolutely necessary to the maintenance of an
                                        effective U.S. and Western presence in Africa. I think
                                            <persName corresp="#p_GMW1">Williams</persName> would
                                        like to go a little further than the plan in the paper, by
                                        moving to expel Struelens now, and by a high-level U.S.
                                        statement indicating that we were determined to move ahead
                                        on a settlement of the Katanga issue within a specified
                                        time.</p></item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Yesterday at the Congo Advisory Committee meeting, U <persName corresp="#p_UT1">Thant</persName> expressed his view that
                                    time was running out in the Congo. He gave November 15 as a
                                    deadline for satisfactory replies to the <persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName> letters to <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName>.<note n="4" xml:id="d324fn4"><persName corresp="#p_RKAG1">Gardiner</persName> wrote to both <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> on November 1 urging
                                        them to take the steps necessary for the implementation of
                                        the U.N. Plan. (U.N. doc. S/5053/Add.13, Annex XVII; also
                                        printed in <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy:
                                            Current Documents, 1962</hi>, pp. 896–897)</note> These
                                    had urged them to get on with their respective <pb facs="0681" n="653" xml:id="pg_653"/> moves under the <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> plan. If no satisfactory replies
                                    were received, U <persName corresp="#p_UT1">Thant</persName>
                                    said he would consider the reconciliation plan scrapped and
                                    adopt an as yet unspecified alternative policy. The Indian
                                    representative of the Advisory Committee said that they had no
                                    intention of withdrawing their troops from the Congo.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <closer><signed>C.K.<note n="5" xml:id="d324fn5">Printed from a copy that
                                    bears these typed initials.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>