<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>357. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in the
                    Congo</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d357</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">357</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-12-13T21:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-12-13T21:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-12-13T21:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-12-13T21:30:00-05:00" n="357"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d357">
                <head>357. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in the Congo<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d357fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 770G.00/12–1362. Confidential; Niact. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_GMG1">Godley</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GMW1"
                            >Williams</persName>; cleared in substance by <persName
                            corresp="#p_GCM1">McGhee</persName>; approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_GMW1">Williams</persName>. Repeated to Paris for <persName
                            corresp="#p_DR1">Rusk</persName> and to Brussels, London, and
                        Elisabethville.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-12-13T21:30:00-05:00">December 13, 1962, 9:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>873. For Ambassador from <persName corresp="#p_GMW1">Williams</persName>. Re
                        <gloss target="#Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 870 to Léopoldville, repeated Paris
                        <gloss target="#Tosec1">Tosec</gloss> 20.<note n="2" xml:id="d357fn2"
                        >Telegram 499 to Elisabethville, <ref target="#d356">Document 356</ref>, was
                        repeated to Paris as <gloss target="#Tosec1">Tosec</gloss> 20.</note>
                    Believe <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>’s reaction to <gloss
                        target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> payments <pb facs="0754" n="726"
                        xml:id="pg_726"/> scheme to be crucial. Reftel points out great importance
                    Secretary and others in Department attach to scheme and fact that it is key to
                    progress on U <persName corresp="#p_UT1">Thant</persName> Plan. I personally
                    believe a satisfactory <gloss target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> payments scheme to be
                    the most important single element in conjunction with others in effectuating the
                    U <persName corresp="#p_UT1">Thant</persName> Plan.</p>
                <p>You should make <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> realize that the
                    United States has exercised every effort to get the GOB, <gloss target="#UMHK1"
                        >UMHK</gloss> and Katanga to take forward steps of recognition by <gloss
                        target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> and <persName corresp="#p_MT1"
                        >Tshombe</persName> of <gloss target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> payments to
                    Central Government. Not only does <gloss target="#USG1">USG</gloss> believe
                        <gloss target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> payments will be efficacious in
                    achievement of other parts of U <persName corresp="#p_UT1">Thant</persName>
                    Plan, but with <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>’s acceptance of the
                    proposal <gloss target="#USG1">USG</gloss> could more readily undertake other
                    efforts to achieve reintegration if necessary. Contrarywise, if <persName
                        corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> does not accept proposed plan while US
                    would proceed to secure implementation of U <persName corresp="#p_UT1"
                        >Thant</persName> Plan, it would be more difficult to take strong measures
                    which might prove necessary.</p>
                <p>Your attention called to parallel cable from Department<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d357fn3">Reference is to <gloss target="#Tosec1">Tosec</gloss> 25 to
                        Paris, December 13. (Department of State, Central Files,
                        770G.00/12–1362.</note> indicating adoption attitude toward <persName
                        corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName>’s proposal that it constitutes clear cut
                    acceptance of <gloss target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> obligations to make its
                    payments to Central Government; that <gloss target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> should
                    stop further payments to <gloss target="#GOK1">GOK</gloss> and proceed to
                    negotiate with <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> necessary modalities
                    and that as little as possible should be said about <persName corresp="#p_MT1"
                        >Tshombe</persName>’s conditions which need not be accepted as preconditions
                    to the change.</p>
                <p>Two things of utmost importance. First that <persName corresp="#p_CA1"
                        >Adoula</persName> make a response that will establish a good public
                    position both in Congo and in the rest of the world. Second, that he understand
                    the advantages of the payment plan and undertake to negotiate and accept
                    mutually satisfactory plan.</p>
                <p>Therefore hope would be possible for you to persuade <persName corresp="#p_CA1"
                        >Adoula</persName> to respond to <persName corresp="#p_MT1"
                        >Tshombe</persName> proposal by welcoming <persName corresp="#p_MT1"
                        >Tshombe</persName>’s recognition of <gloss target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss>’s
                    obligation to make future payments to Monetary Council, that he expects such
                    payments will be made and that he is prepared to work out procedures for <gloss
                        target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> and Katanga to receive their appropriate
                    sharing of foreign exchange.</p>
                <p>To give earnest to his intentions he might indicate he has appointed someone such
                    as Ndele, assisted by Badre, Frasca,<note n="4" xml:id="d357fn4">Felice Frasca,
                        President of the Congolese Monetary Council.</note> or other technicians to
                    work out details of implementation.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> should realize that any
                    arrangements would apply only for interim period and after unification
                    currencies identical exchange controls will result in equal criteria applied to
                    use of exchange available for <pb facs="0755" n="727" xml:id="pg_727"/> all
                    parts of Congo and normal trade flows which should be established will serve to
                    balance payments between different parts of country.</p>
                <p>This is a critical point in integration program and trust you will be able to
                    convince <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> of importance of proper
                    public posture and of possibility to use this offer as a major step to the
                    achievement of the U <persName corresp="#p_UT1">Thant</persName> Plan in all of
                    its other aspects.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#FYI1">FYI</gloss>: Recognize need for clarification and
                    satisfactory spelling out of important details which will have to be achieved in
                    negotiation in particular that Léopoldville not required purchase Katanga francs
                    for conversion <gloss target="#UMHK1">UMHK</gloss> Congo francs for more than
                    250 million francs stipulated in <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName>
                        letter<note n="5" xml:id="d357fn5">See <ref target="#d356fn1">footnote 1,
                            Document 356</ref>.</note> plus estimated 60 million conditional on lack
                    traditional exports to Katanga.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GWB1">Ball</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
