<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>358. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Kaysen) to President ) to President Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d358</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">358</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-12-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-12-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="358"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d358">
                <head>358. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CK1">Kaysen</persName>) to President
                        <persName corresp="#p_JFK1">Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d358fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JFK1"
                            >Kennedy</persName> Library, President’s Office Files, Congo Security,
                        1962. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-12-13">December 13, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Attached are some background papers for tomorrow morning’s Congo meeting.
                        George <persName corresp="#p_GWB1">Ball</persName> will have an official
                        Department proposal for the meeting but this will not be ready until
                        tomorrow morning. If you have time to look at any of the attached you may
                        find it useful.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>At Tab 1 is a good clear statement by Roger <persName corresp="#p_RH1"
                            >Hilsman</persName> on the alternatives.<note n="2" xml:id="d358fn2">Tab
                            1 was a memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_RH1">Hilsman</persName> to
                                <persName corresp="#p_GWB1">Ball</persName>, dated December 11, on
                            “The Congo: An Appraisal of Alternatives.” It is summarized and the
                            circumstances of its drafting are described in Roger <persName
                                corresp="#p_RH1">Hilsman</persName>, <hi rend="italic">To Move a
                                Nation: The Politics of Foreign Policy in the Administration of
                                    <persName corresp="#p_JFK1">John F. Kennedy</persName>
                            </hi>, pp. 263–266.</note> It argues that, as a preferred alternative,
                        we should choose to move with greater force in the Congo in order to achieve
                        integration. The only other alternative is withdrawal. This would have large
                        costs in terms of our general position in Africa vis-a-vis the Soviets and
                        in the prestige and future usefulness in the <gloss target="#UN1"
                        >UN</gloss>. At Tab 2 are (a) a recent cable from Moscow, and (b) another
                            <persName corresp="#p_RH1">Hilsman</persName> paper on the possibilities
                        of Soviet <pb facs="0756" n="728" xml:id="pg_728"/> military assistance or
                        direct interference in the Congo.<note n="3" xml:id="d358fn3">Tab 2 was
                            telegram 1478 from Moscow, December 12, and a memorandum from <persName
                                corresp="#p_RH1">Hilsman</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_DR1"
                                >Rusk</persName>, dated December 7, on “Possible Soviet Military
                            Assistance to the Congo.” The memoranda in Tabs 1 and 2 were part of a
                            package that <persName corresp="#p_GWB1">Ball</persName> sent to
                                <persName corresp="#p_MB1">Bundy</persName> on December 13. The
                            package included copies of a December 12 memorandum from Chester
                                <persName corresp="#p_CAB1">Bowles</persName> to the President, a
                            December 10 memorandum and a December 12 draft from <persName
                                corresp="#p_GMW1">Williams</persName>, memoranda of December 12 and
                            November 29 from <persName corresp="#p_RH1">Hilsman</persName>, and
                                <persName corresp="#p_MB1">Bundy</persName>’s December 11 letter
                                (<ref target="#d353">Document 353</ref>). <persName
                                corresp="#p_GWB1">Ball</persName>’s covering memorandum noted that
                            the attachments “all move in the direction of a hard line on the Congo.”
                                (<persName corresp="#p_JFK1">Kennedy</persName> Library, National
                            Security Files, Congo) The <persName corresp="#p_CAB1">Bowles</persName>
                            memorandum is printed in part in Chester <persName corresp="#p_CAB1"
                                >Bowles</persName>, Promises to Keep: My Years in Public Life,
                            1941–1969, pp. 497–498. Telegram 1478 from Moscow is in Department of
                            State, Central Files, 661.70G/12–1262)</note> Both come to essentially
                        negative conclusions, at least for the near future.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RH1">Hilsman</persName>’s first paper makes a good
                        argument. I think there are two comments to be made on it. First, it
                        overstates the Soviet threat. Accordingly, the immediate costs of the
                        continuance of our present policy of attempting reconciliation through
                        persuasion are likely to be less spectacular. Probably the <persName
                            corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> government will fall, to be succeeded
                        by a more radical government. Perhaps the more radical government will
                        attempt military action against Katanga. However, without our support,
                        neither the central Congo government nor the <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss>
                        can take significant military action. Accordingly, the situation may just
                        continue to deteriorate, perhaps at an accelerated pace and with increasing
                        sporadic violence. The more radical government may well denounce the <gloss
                            target="#UN1">UN</gloss> operation and ask for its withdrawal. This
                        would be a significant defeat for U.S. policy. Our position in the <gloss
                            target="#UN1">UN</gloss> and the <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss>’s
                        future usefulness in peace-keeping and our position in Africa would all be
                        damaged seriously by this course of events. However, this is different from
                        Soviet intervention in Africa or a spectacular outbreak of civil war.</item>
                </list>
                <p>My second comment is that, while <persName corresp="#p_RH1">Hilsman</persName>
                    properly emphasizes that our plan of action must be such as to give <persName
                        corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> room to back down, he does not emphasize
                    enough the importance of limiting the objectives of forcible action. What we
                    want is to achieve that degree of disarmament of <persName corresp="#p_MT1"
                        >Tshombe</persName> and explicit admission by him that Katanga must
                    integrate which will make integration stick, provided that <persName
                        corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> is willing to come to terms with the
                    realities of <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName>’s economic and
                    political power. In the past <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>, the
                        <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> people, and, I fear, our Embassy in
                    Léopoldville have all stood, perhaps unconsciously, for unconditional surrender.
                    It is obvious that <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName> might as well
                    go down in flames as surrender unconditionally, and if pressed to the end, he
                    will do so. This proposition, in turn, underlines the importance of dismissing
                    Parliament and strengthening <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>’s rule
                    in the first place, and then making it clear to him that he must use his
                    strength to deal with <persName corresp="#p_MT1">Tshombe</persName>, after we
                    have achieved the limited objectives of partially disarming him and ending
                    formal Katanga secession.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>CK</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
