<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>364. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Kaysen) to President ) to President Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v20</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d364</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">364</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec0tfPbYHg7imwab" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067175"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Intelligence community</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" subject="intervention">Intervention</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-12-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-12-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="364"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d364">
                <head>364. Memorandum From the President’s Deputy Special Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CK1">Kaysen</persName>) to President
                        <persName corresp="#p_JFK1">Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d364fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JFK1"
                            >Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security Files, Congo.
                        Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-12-17">December 17, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Congo Issues</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>You have heard all the positive arguments for going in to the Congo along
                        the lines of the Department’s proposal this morning. It is perhaps useful to
                        re-state the purpose for which we would put force in; namely, to back up the
                            <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> force in its mission to prevent Katanga
                        from blocking the application of the <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss>
                        reconciliation plan by force.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>However, this morning’s discussion did not bring out clearly the
                        alternatives to the proposed course of action. The real question is whether
                        any of them is less likely to result in an unacceptable situation in the
                        Congo which will call for U.S. intervention on a larger scale at a later
                        date.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The first alternative is to continue as we have in support of the <gloss
                            target="#UN1">UN</gloss>, including giving U <persName corresp="#p_UT1"
                            >Thant</persName> some of the assistance he asked for, but without
                        attempting to assert a strong influence on the course of events directly.
                        The likely result of this course of action is <gloss target="#UN1"
                            >UN</gloss> action in January that will lead to an outbreak of fighting.
                        Such fighting runs a high risk of involving the Europeans in the Katanga. It
                        is much more likely to be inconclusive, than conclusive. It would have
                        serious domestic political repercussions, especially with the Congress in
                        session. It would further run down <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> finances,
                        and probably lead to force withdrawals.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The second alternative is <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> withdrawal,
                        forced by our refusal to continue to support the operation. This would have
                        as its immediate result a serious defeat for the prestige of the <gloss
                            target="#UN1">UN</gloss>, and for our policy in Africa. Further, it
                        would almost certainly lead to the fall of the <persName corresp="#p_CA1"
                            >Adoula</persName> Government in Léopoldville, and the accession to
                        power of a more radical government. The new government would seek military
                        aid directly from all sources that would assist it, including the Soviet
                        Union. While the intelligence community estimates that the likelihood of a
                        quick Soviet response to such a request is low, there may well be responses
                        from the Algerians, the Ghanaians and others, and some indirect assistance
                        by the Soviets through these countries. The result would be a long drawn-out
                        but probably still inconclusive struggle in the Congo. The changed
                        government in Léopoldville would be certain to throw the Belgians fully on
                        the side of the Katanga and might well cause the defeat of <pb facs="0777"
                            n="749" xml:id="pg_749"/>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PHS1">Spaak</persName> because of his support for the
                        reconciliation policy. It is unlikely that the Léopoldville Government could
                        get enough help in these circumstances to end the Katanga secession. What we
                        could expect is a situation of intermittent fighting with an increasing
                        temptation for the Soviets to get in as time went on.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The same situation might well come about at a somewhat later date as a
                        result of an unsuccessful <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> effort to clean up
                        the Katanga problem by <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> military action next
                        month. After failing in this attempt, the <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss>
                        might find it impossible to hold on to its forces, and we might well find it
                        impossible to continue supporting the <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss>
                        operation. <persName corresp="#p_PHS1">Spaak</persName>’s continuance in
                        power would also be threatened by this course of events.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The alternatives can be summed up then as follows: We can take a risky
                        step now which, by general agreement, has the best chance of moving the
                        Congo problem from its present posture as a Congo-Katanga war to an internal
                        political problem within a nominally unified federal Congo. However, that
                        chance is probably not much better than 50–50. The other alternative is
                        immediate voluntary, or later, involuntary withdrawal of the <gloss
                            target="#UN1">UN</gloss> and the U.S. from the operation. This involves
                        immediate losses of <gloss target="#UN1">UN</gloss> and U.S. prestige and
                        may require at some future date, a year or so from now, renewed U.S.
                        intervention, because of the danger of Soviet involvement in a continuing
                        Congo-Katanga struggle. It will certainly result in a change from the
                        present moderate to a radical Léopoldville Government, and the loss of all
                        European support for the Central Government.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>C.K.<note n="2" xml:id="d364fn2">Printed from a copy that bears these
                            typed initials.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
