<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-12-21T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-12-21T11:00:00-05:00" n="379" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d379">
                        <head>379. Telegram From the Embassy in the Congo to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d379fn1">Source: Department
                                of State, Central Files, 770G.2/12–2162. Secret; Niact. Received at
                                1:25 p.m. and repeated to <gloss target="#USUN1">USUN</gloss> and
                                Brussels.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Léopoldville</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-12-21T17:00:00+01:00">December 21, 1962, 5 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1495. Saw <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> to find out what
                            he was prepared to do to prevent liberation of <persName corresp="#p_AG1">Gizenga</persName> or to cope with consequences.
                                <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>’s only positive
                            statement was that government would ignore order of Parliament (this was
                            before it was known that vote was unanimous with even GOC Ministers in
                                favor).<note n="2" xml:id="d379fn2">The Chamber of Deputies passed a
                                motion on December 21 calling for <persName corresp="#p_AG1">Gizenga</persName>’s release.</note></p>
                        <p>I asked <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> if he would not see
                            fit to take action before <persName corresp="#p_AG1">Gizenga</persName>
                            was released. He would only say that <persName corresp="#p_JK1">Kasavubu</persName> was not ready and seemed unconscious of the
                            situation. “We”, he said, “were entirely ready.” He then said musingly
                            that there would probably be armed conflict here in Léopoldville.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> said he would like to ask
                                <gloss target="#USG1">USG</gloss> for advice as to what he should do
                            if he were not able to restore working majority. I replied foreign
                            government could hardly give him advice on such questions as proroguing
                            Parliament. He said he realized that but what he intended to ask about
                            was his own resignation. I asked whether there was anyone to whom he
                            could conscientiously turn over government at this point. <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> said there was no reliable person
                            but nevertheless there was no lack of candidates. I remarked that we
                            seemed to be reverting to post-independence period with military
                            takeover best of several bad solutions. <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> answered that military takeover might take place
                            but said no <pb facs="0805" n="777" xml:id="pg_777"/> one could foresee
                            where such a development might lead. I said this was so, but it was only
                            too clear where the present course was leading.<note n="3" xml:id="d379fn3"><persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName>
                                commented in telegram 1498 from Léopoldville, December 21, “I
                                believe that unless government takes action to prorogue Parliament,
                                it will go down the drain along with Congo unification, U <persName corresp="#p_UT1">Thant</persName> plan, anti-communist front and
                                U.S. aid committed thus far.” (Department of State, Central Files,
                                770G.00/12–2162)</note></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName> then reiterated that his
                            government was “prepared to take action”. <persName corresp="#p_CA1">Adoula</persName>’s attitude was neither despairing nor determined;
                            merely detached.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_EAG1">Gullion</persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>