<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>165. Memorandum Prepared in the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d165</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">165</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="recbqzzF4Eebaylpi" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="border-administration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006007505"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Border control</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recgpNhn3NejuQEjr" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85075302"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Law enforcement</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="165"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d165">
                <head>165. Memorandum Prepared in the Department of State<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d165fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, POL 7 COSTA
                        RICA. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CVL1"
                            >Collins</persName> and O.L. Sause of <gloss target="#t_AID1"
                            >AID</gloss>. Filed as an attachment to an April 22 memorandum from
                            <persName corresp="#p_BWH2">Brubeck</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>, which stated that it was a further
                        response to the President’s March 22 written inquiry to
                            <persName>Martin</persName>. <persName>Kennedy</persName>’s March 22
                        memorandum to <persName>Martin</persName> asked <persName>Martin</persName>
                        to let him know that steps he was taking to implement “the testament of San
                        Jose.” A copy is filed with a March 25 memorandum from <persName
                            corresp="#p_BWH2">Brubeck</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_BMG2"
                            >Bundy</persName> enclosing an initial report. (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian"
                            notAfter="1963-04-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                            notBefore="1963-04-04T00:00:00-05:00">undated</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Implementation of Agreements Reached at San Jose</item>
                </list>
                <p>The initial report of March 25 indicated that a meeting of Ministers of
                    Government would take place at Managua, Nicaragua, on April 3 to draw up
                    security measures against subversion in the Isthmian countries. Deputy Attorney
                    General Katzenbach headed the United States Delegation to this meeting and
                    results were considered most successful.</p>
                <p>The most significant of the resolutions promulgated at the end of the meeting
                    April 4<note n="2" xml:id="d165fn2">The resolutions are printed in Department of
                        State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, May 6, 1963, pp. 719-721.</note> were
                    the following: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>To recommend to their governments that they adopt, within the
                            limitations of their respective constitutional provisions, measures to
                            be <pb facs="0377" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/> put into effect immediately
                            to prohibit, restrict and discourage the movement of their nationals to
                            and from Cuba. To this end, the Meeting proposes the adoption of the
                            following measures: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Provide, as a general rule, that every passport or other
                                    travel document which may be issued carry a stamp which
                                    indicates that said passport is not valid for travel to
                                    Cuba.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Declare officially that nationals who are permitted to travel
                                    to Cuba should have the permission duly inscribed in their
                                    official travel document.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>Promulgate regulations restricting the granting of visas to
                                    foreigners who have travelled to Cuba within a stipulated period
                                    of time.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>To recommend that their governments take action to impede the
                            clandestine movement of arms into the Isthmian countries, including
                            specific instructions to border control forces to intensify port,
                            airfield and border inspection of incoming and outgoing cargo in order
                            to prevent contraband shipment of arms; establish strict security and
                            accountability with respect to arms and ammunition issued to their armed
                            forces and law enforcement agencies.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>To recommend to their governments the adoption as soon as possible and
                            to go into effect immediately, of effective measures to prevent
                            activities for subversive purposes that may be instigated by <persName
                                corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName>-Communist propaganda or agents
                            in each of the Central American countries.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>To recommend to the Governments of Central America and Panama the
                            establishment, as soon as possible, of an organization in each state,
                            with the sole purpose of counteracting Communist subversion in the
                            Central America-Panama area. These organizations will be primarily
                            responsible for: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Detecting, controlling and counteracting actions and
                                    objectives of the members, organizations, sympathizers and
                                    collaborators of the Communist Party.</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Lending mutual support to each other and continually
                                    exchanging information regarding movements of persons or groups,
                                    propaganda, funds and arms for Communist subversive
                                    purposes.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>These resolutions do not represent commitments on the part of governments but
                    only recommendations to governments. In order to assist the Central American
                    Governments to put these recommendations into effect and in order to find out
                    what technical or material assistance the United States should offer, a team
                    with Immigration Service, <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>, Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff, <gloss target="#t_CINCARIB1">CINCARIB</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_USIS1"
                        >USIS</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and State representation
                    will visit each of the Central American countries starting from Panama
                    around</p>
                <pb facs="0378" n="346" xml:id="pg_346"/>
                <p>April 23 and ending in Guatemala. The report of this team<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d165fn3">The report of the Interdepartmental Team on Counter
                        Subversive Measures in Central America and Panama, which visited Central
                        America and Panama April 23-May 11, is in the <persName>Kennedy</persName>
                        Library, National Security Files, Regional Security Series, Latin
                        America.</note> will be used to persuade the Central American Governments to
                    put more recommendations into effect and also as a basic paper for the United
                    States Delegation to the next regular meeting of Ministers of Government of
                    Central America which, at Managua, was set for 90 days hence, i.e., July 5.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of the implementation of decisions on economic
                    matters.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
