<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>180. Circular Telegram From the Department of State to to Posts in the
                    American Republics</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d180</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">180</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-03-31T21:33:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-03-31T21:33:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-03-31T21:33:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-03-31T21:33:00-05:00" n="180"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                <head>180. Circular Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                    to <gloss type="to">Posts in the American Republics</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d180fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 735.00/3-3162. Secret; Priority. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_WHR1">Wellman</persName> and approved by
                            <persName>Martin</persName>. Repeated to Buenos Aires, London, <gloss
                            target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, Madrid, and <gloss target="#t_POLAD1"
                            >POLAD</gloss>
                        <gloss target="#t_CINCARIB1">CINCARIB</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-03-31T21:33:00-05:00">March 31, 1962, 9:33 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1657. Relations with new Argentine Government.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1)</label>
                    <item>Particularly in view repercussions Argentine developments throughout
                        Hemisphere and interest already expressed by certain governments in US
                        position we wish to exchange information and views <pb facs="0402" n="370"
                            xml:id="pg_370"/> with Government to which you are accredited. You are
                        requested to confer with Government at high level promptly for this
                        purpose.</item>
                    <label>2)</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Following is summary of current governmental situation in Argentina based
                            on reports from our Embassy which should be conveyed to Foreign
                            Office:</p>
                        <p>Constitutionally elected President <persName corresp="#p_FA2"
                                >Frondizi</persName> removed from office on March 29 by Argentine
                            military forces after he had persistently resisted strong military and
                            civilian pressures to resign. <persName corresp="#p_GJM1">Jose Maria
                                Guido</persName>, President of Senate, took oath office as President
                            on March 29. He reaffirmed assumption office in public ceremony March 30
                            before Supreme Court in presence Members of Congress and military
                            leaders. New government claims right legal succession under Article 75
                            Argentine Constitution as implemented by Law of Congress 1868. This
                            provides that 1) in event Republic without a head due to lack of a
                            president in certain contingencies (in this case absence from capital)
                            and Vice President (resigned) executive power shall be vested in
                            President of Senate, and 2) new President shall within thirty days call
                            for new election of President and Vice President.</p>
                        <p>Reportedly Senate President was at first reluctant to serve but took
                            Presidential office at personal sacrifice to himself with consent or
                            perhaps even request <persName corresp="#p_FA2">Frondizi</persName> and
                            at urging of leaders UCRI (<persName corresp="#p_FA2"
                                >Frondizi</persName>’s) party in order to avoid installation of
                            military government. <gloss target="#t_UCRP1">UCRP</gloss> (which was
                            principal opposition party in Congress) has reportedly announced support
                            for him. Military commanders accepted <persName corresp="#p_GJM1"
                                >Guido</persName> after initial reluctance and some leading military
                            have reportedly asked to be retired.</p>
                        <p>Cabinet not yet formed. <persName corresp="#p_GJM1">Guido</persName> is
                            civilian and although military will probably have much to say about
                            composition of Cabinet, it seems likely to be largely non-military in
                            character. Congress will probably be called into session within next few
                            days to enact electoral and other urgent legislation.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3)</label>
                    <item>You are requested to state that it will always be source of regret and
                        concern for <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> when a democratically
                        elected government which is cooperating in the <gloss target="#t_OAS1"
                            >OAS</gloss> and with the Alliance for Progress is replaced at
                        insistence of military forces. We hope however that a civilian government
                        will be established in Argentina which will command support from the
                        Congress, democratic political parties and majority populace, as Well as
                        military forces, that this Government will operate within democratic
                        constitution and that it will observe its international and inter-American
                        obligations including those under Alliance for Progress. If a government of
                        substantially this character is organized by <persName corresp="#p_GJM1"
                            >Guido</persName>, it should be in the interest of all states with the
                        interests of Argentine people at heart to assist it in strengthening
                        democratic institutions in <pb facs="0403" n="371" xml:id="pg_371"/>
                        Argentina and resuming the social and economic programs called for by our
                        mutual commitments under Alliance.</item>
                    <label>4)</label>
                    <item>You should state that <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> therefore
                        intends to watch developments in Argentina very closely over next several
                        days, and in particular will be interested in composition new Cabinet when
                        formed, congression-al support of new government, plans for new election
                        pursuant to constitution and other indications of policies it will follow.
                        In this connection <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> will be pleased to
                        receive such information and views as foreign government may have on
                        Argentine situation.</item>
                    <label>5)</label>
                    <item>Report promptly Government’s reactions together with any comments you may
                            have.<note n="2" xml:id="d180fn2">The responses are ibid.,
                            735.00.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
