<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-05-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-05-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="378" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d378">
                        <head>378. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Haiti</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d378fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, POL HAI. Top Secret; Operational Immediate. Repeated to
                                Caracas and Santo Domingo. No time of transmission appears on the
                                source text. Relayed to the White House.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Port-au-Prince</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-05-02">May 2,
                                1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>521. Through situation reports and cables on specific incidents we have
                            attempted to convey accurate picture abnormal situation prevailing <pb facs="0814" n="782" xml:id="pg_782"/> here in recent days.<note n="2" xml:id="d378fn2">After the April 26 abortive kidnapping
                                attempt on his family by Haitian dissidents, <persName corresp="#p_DF1">Duvalier</persName>’s agents began to arrest
                                oppositionists, many of whom fled to the sanctuary of foreign
                                embassies. The government cordoned off the Dominican and other Latin
                                American Embassies in Port-au-Prince to prevent potential political
                                refugees from obtaining asylum. On April 26 Haitian police forcibly
                                entered the Dominican Embassy. The Dominican Republic called for a
                                special meeting of the Council of the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss>, which in turn created an investigative committee
                                that visited both countries. As a result of the visit and in
                                anticipation of the report, Haiti removed its forces from the
                                Dominican Embassy and allowed some Haitian asylees safe conduct to
                                the Dominican Republic. Documentation on this conflict is primarily
                                ibid., POL DOM REP-HAI. See also <persName corresp="#p_MJB2">John
                                    Bartlow Martin</persName>, Overtaken by Events, pp.
                                416-447.</note> I believe it now essential for US Govt consider
                            urgently what it can do together with other interested govts to get this
                            powder keg under control and turn the crisis to advantage in terms our
                            objectives and interests in Haiti and Latin American generally.</p>
                        <p>It is difficult to exaggerate the fear, both justified and unreasoning,
                            which now dominates Port-au-Prince. It permeates all elements of the
                            population, Haitians and foreigners, officials and non-officials, rich
                            and poor. Many ordinary Haitians are drifting back to their villages in
                            the hinterland. No curfew has been declared but there is little
                            nocturnal activity because of the fear of being inadvertently shot by
                            army and militia patrols posted around city. Except for violent action
                            by <persName corresp="#p_BC5">Barbot</persName> group (which now
                            believed be ones who killed guardians Duvalier children and to whom is
                            also attributed last night’s reportedly successful raid on weapons depot
                            at Martissant area) <persName corresp="#p_DF1">Duvalier</persName>’s
                            security forces appear to have everything under control. Yet
                            apprehension persists as crowds of simple people are harangued in
                            inflammatory creole speeches by <persName corresp="#p_DF1">Duvalier</persName> and his henchmen. <persName corresp="#p_DF1">Duvalier</persName> himself in “apres moi le deluge” mood as he
                            continues to crack down on all elements suspected of opposing him.</p>
                        <p>Both because of personal indignities suffered at hands police authorities
                            and accounts of atrocities reaching them from increasing number asylees
                            in Latin American Embassies foreign diplomats are deeply troubled about
                            situation. To what extent this has as yet had impact on their
                            governments cannot be determined from here, but I would judge that our
                            own general position re Duvalier regime now more widely supported than
                            before recent events.</p>
                        <p>Arrival <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> commission welcomed here by
                            all except <gloss target="#t_GOH1">GOH</gloss> itself which wants it out
                            of town as soon as possible. Our only contact with commission has been
                            through Dean Diplomatic Corps, those Latin American Embassies whose
                            countries are on commission and American journalists. I understand that
                            there are differences in the commission about how broadly they should
                            interpret terms of reference (Emb would appreciate official info from
                            Department on this subject) and how long they should stay in Haiti. Dept
                            should, I believe, use its full influence to keep <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> in this country as long as possible.
                            Appreciate that problem of <pb facs="0815" n="783" xml:id="pg_783"/>
                            intervention in internal affairs presents difficulties, but <gloss target="#t_GODR1">GODR</gloss> charges do in themselves afford
                            bridge for <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> to delve into the real
                            factors underlying the fundamentally unsatisfactory situation here and
                            to make recommendations equal to challenge. This is also virtually
                            unanimous view my diplomatic colleagues.</p>
                        <p>Unless <persName corresp="#p_DF1">Duvalier</persName> removed soon from
                            scene (he shows no signs of voluntary departure) I find it difficult to
                            envisage any solution other than intervention. Under certain
                            circumstances (shooting of US Embassy officials or storming any local
                            embassy to kill asylees) I would recommend unilateral use of US forces.
                            Far preferable however would be collective <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> intervention. Economic sanctions as in Dominican case
                            hardly seem appropriate in country like Haiti so close subsistence level
                            already and might only have adverse propaganda impact. What is required
                            is collective “police” action which would result in effective physical
                            control local situation including if necessary pacification opposing
                            groups. Recognizing that old-fashioned marine type occupation no longer
                            feasible would it not be possible to work on emergency basis towards
                            Venezuelan and Dominican participation, perhaps only symbolic, along
                            with our own forces in <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> sanctioned
                            collective police effort here? I submit that dangers inherent in
                            continued laissez faire policy re Haiti are sufficiently grave to
                            warrant this kind of extraordinary action by our inter-American
                                system.<note n="3" xml:id="d378fn3">In telegram 323 to
                                Port-au-Prince, May 2, the Department reminded <persName corresp="#p_TRL1">Thurston</persName> that there was little
                                enthusiasm in Latin America for intervention in Haiti, and that the
                                United States had yet to convince the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> that a “police action” was needed. Nonetheless, the
                                Department assured <persName corresp="#p_TRL1">Thurston</persName>
                                that its policy was “far from one of laissez faire.” (Department of
                                State, Central Files, POL HAI)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_TRL1">Thurston</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>