<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>398. Memorandum From Secretary of State Rusk to President to President
                    Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">398</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-10-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-10-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="398"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d398">
                <head>398. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="from"
                        >Rusk</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2" type="to"
                        >Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d398fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSAM1">NSAM</gloss> Files: Lot 72 D 316, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSAM1">NSAM</gloss> 95. Secret. No drafting information
                        appears on the source text, but it was approved by <persName
                            corresp="#p_GRN2">Goodwin</persName> on October 18.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-10-09">October 9, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Recommendations on Improving Relations with Panama</item>
                </list>
                <p>Your memorandum of September 15, 1961 requests the establishment of a special
                    working group to prepare recommendations on improving relations with Panama.</p>
                <p>Such a group, under the chairmanship of Under Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGW1">George W. Ball</persName>, and including representatives
                    from Defense, the Budget Bureau and the White House staff has carefully examined
                    this problem in the last two weeks.</p>
                <p>The group has found that an analysis of our basic interests in the Canal Zone, a
                    determination of the concessions we might make to Panama, and the terms on which
                    we could reasonably expect to get a long-term settlement of our problems with
                    Panama, are matters which require far more detailed study than is possible for
                    the group to undertake in such a short period of time.</p>
                <p>To formulate a workable policy governing our relations with Panama and the Canal
                    will require an intensive study by a group of experts. To achieve this, it is
                    recommended that you designate the policy group <pb facs="0849" n="817"
                        xml:id="pg_817"/> under Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> as
                    an <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Working Group and authorize the
                    appointment of a special study group of experts, under the chairmanship of the
                    Department, to examine in detail problems confronting us in our relations with
                    Panama. The Department would propose to appoint Ambassador Muccio,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d398fn2">Ambassador to Guatemala John J. Muccio.</note> who has had
                    extensive experience in treaty renegotiation with Panama in 1955, as Coordinator
                    of this study group. The study group’s report would be submitted to Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>’s policy group within 90
                    days.</p>
                <p>Suggested terms of reference for the proposed subgroup are enclosed.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d398fn3">Entitled “Administrative Actions to Improve Relationships.”
                        None of the enclosures is printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Pending the completion of the report of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    Working Group, it is recommended that we proceed on a selective basis with
                    certain administrative actions which can improve our relations with Panama
                    without treaty change, as outlined in the second enclosure.</p>
                <p>A draft reply to the letter from President <persName corresp="#p_CJRF1"
                        >Chiari</persName>, requesting that we renegotiate the canal treaties, is
                    also enclosed.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Dean Rusk</persName>
                        </hi>
                        <note n="4" xml:id="d398fn4">Printed from a copy that indicates <persName
                                corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> signed the original.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
