<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>63. Memorandum From the Secretary General of the International Peace Corps
                    Secretariat (Goodwin) to President ) to President Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d63</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">63</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-09-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-09-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="63"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                <head>63. Memorandum From the Secretary General of the International Peace Corps
                    Secretariat (<persName corresp="#p_GRN2" type="from">Goodwin</persName>) to
                    President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2" type="to">Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d63fn1">Source: <persName>Kennedy</persName>
                        Library, President’s Office Files, Staff Memoranda, <persName
                            corresp="#p_GRN2">Goodwin</persName>. No classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-09-10">September 10, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In the last couple of weeks (while on vacation) I have given considerable thought
                    to the Alliance for Progress in my recent capacity as disinterested
                    observer.</p>
                <p>I believe this is the most important on-going program of your Administration (as
                    distinct from critical decisions such as Cuba, test ban etc.). Moreover it is a
                    new and significant initiative in U.S. policy toward an area of the world which
                    has been of historic and intimate concern to us; an area which is second in
                    importance only to Europe. Its success would be viewed as one of the great
                    achievements of U.S. policy ranking with the Marshall Plan, the Good Neighbor
                    policy etc.; policies which now have the gloss of past triumphs but which were
                    intrinsically no more path-breaking or significant than the Alianza.</p>
                <p>It is increasingly disappointing that a program which is sound in conception and
                    historically right is operating at about one-half effectiveness. (And that may
                    be a generous estimate.) I have continual self doubts about this estimate since
                    Washington is a city filled with reassurances and self-justification; but every
                    time I get involved or go to the field (I was recently in Bolivia) my dismay and
                    alarm keep crowding back. As an example: about a year ago we suggested the
                    state-to-country program using California and Chile as a pilot. Everyone
                    concurred in this idea. Several times you indicated your personal interest in
                    it. Yet one year later a person is being placed on the staff to implement the
                    project. This, I submit, is inexcusable and, as a result, we have lost not only
                    time in the Alianza but all hope of political benefit in time for Congressional
                    actions on the <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> request. Another example: The
                        <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> Director in Bolivia has been waiting six
                    months for a qualified loan officer despite the fact that he has one of the
                    largest, if not the largest, loan program in Latin America. Individual instances
                    of this sort can always be explained and justified; but they are part of a
                    pattern of lack of imagination, daring, administrative efficiency etc. which is
                    critically damaging the program.</p>
                <p>Much of the delay etc. is explained on the grounds of the necessity to be careful
                    about what Congress thinks. But all the cautions in the world have not only
                    failed to win over those hostile to the Alianza; but the consequent failures and
                    delays and inefficiencies have helped to alienate our friends. A dynamic,
                    successful program—well-publicized—is the way to win congressional support
                    rather than the building of an intricate network <pb facs="0179" n="147"
                        xml:id="pg_147"/> of safeguards which protect the individuals running the
                    program, but not the program itself. The fact that obvious failures cannot be
                    blamed on anyone is itself a bad sign. For people unwilling to take chances of
                    personal failure will never run the risk of success.</p>
                <p>Probably the most serious single problem is personnel. The Alianza has the same
                    trouble as the Washington Nats—they don’t have the ballplayers. There are, of
                    course, some very good people, but there is also a tremendous amount of
                    mediocrity in high places. No program is better than the people who run it. The
                    reasons for this are many and too detailed to go into here, but they include:
                    complete lack of a good recruiting effort, impossible personnel procedures, a
                    structure which discourages individual initiative and responsibility, a
                    careerist mentality, and inability to recognize mediocrity when it is seen.
                    There are good people available, and they can be recruited. I know this for
                    several reasons: (1) I know enough people to know there are good people
                    available; (2) <persName corresp="#p_SRSJ1">Shriver</persName>’s success at
                    recruiting people, some of them formerly among the best of <gloss
                        target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>. The Alianza is intrinsically more exciting,
                    bigger and more glamorous than the Peace Corps and there is no reason why it
                    should not attract as good or better people; (3) A year and a half ago I
                    proposed to <persName corresp="#p_MT4">Moscoso</persName> that we should try and
                    recruit the brightest young men from Wall Street law firms etc. to come to
                    Washington to work in the Alianza. We would give them a six months’ training
                    program to prepare them to become development desk officers for various
                    countries. He thought this was fine. I organized a cocktail party in New York
                    (our intention was to follow it up with similar gatherings in other cities).
                    About thirty-five young lawyers and businessmen attended. They were nearly all
                    men with outstanding scholastic records at major law or business schools; of
                    high caliber personally and rising in their firms. I talked with them about the
                    Alianza and asked those who were interested in joining the training program to
                    send a letter with a resume. Twenty-two sent letters. Their quality can be
                    judged by the fact that Bicks (the antitrust chief under Ike) told an
                    acquaintance of mine that the Alianza was getting all the bright young lawyers
                    in New York. I sent the names and letters to the Alianza. No action was taken to
                    my considerable personal discomfort. But it did prove the people are there.</p>
                <p>I can think of only one answer to all of this: to tell Shriver he must run the
                    Alianza for at least a year, get it on its feet and recruit a successor. This
                    does not mean that he is the only one who can do it. But he is the only one I
                    know; especially since to put a new man, no matter how good, into the existing
                    situation who lacks the personal muscle and experience to destroy the
                    bureaucratic obstacles will not do the job. <persName corresp="#p_SRSJ1"
                        >Shriver</persName> must also get what he thinks he needs to do the job.
                    This will mean radical organizational and personnel changes. Many people,
                    including some of your best and most trusted people, will object. It will run
                    afoul of all sorts of <pb facs="0180" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/> theoretical
                    administrative objections, and some serious practical difficulties. All I can
                    say to this is: (a) We have had two and one-half years trying to do the job the
                    other way; (b) If you expect a good man to try a difficult job you must give him
                    the tools he thinks he needs to do it, not what others think he needs; (c) For
                    whatever it’s worth it is my judgment that this is the only way to do the job,
                    and I disagree with those who think it is not; (d) It is a good idea to break up
                    a losing ball club.</p>
                <p>This approach will conflict with many ambitions, desires and the considered views
                    of thoughtful and dedicated people. It will hurt <persName corresp="#p_MT4"
                        >Moscoso</persName>, whom I admire and like deeply. But I feel so strongly
                    about the importance of this program to the country and to your Administration,
                    that I am confident everything must be tried. We will be judged on whether we
                    won or lost, and not how we played the game.</p>
                <p>There will also be some feeling that things are not going so badly. I submit that
                    much of this is because we have lived so long with existing shortcomings, lack
                    of imagination etc., that we regard them as part of the nature of things and
                    lower our sights accordingly. The Peace Corps has helped show what an overseas
                    program can be when approached with great imagination and skill. I think we
                    could do as much for the Alianza, although I recognize the great difficulties
                    involved.</p>
                <p>I also believe action of this sort should be taken quickly. Latin America will
                    probably be a foreign policy issue in the campaign; and the Alianza is likely to
                    be a principal target both in Congress and outside unless it can be raised above
                    too much reproach rather quickly. Otherwise we will be in a weaker position on
                    it, to say nothing of the very real danger of losing much of it in the Congress.
                    This year is really the “year of truth”—to paraphrase a Latin phrase.</p>
                <p>I do not want to sound as if I have all the answers, or that I am sure that this
                    approach is the right one. But I have felt this with increasing strength for a
                    long period of time, and would be remiss toward you if I did not relay my
                    thought.</p>
                <p>It would be helpful if you did not circulate this memorandum since I have to deal
                    with many of the people affected; but I leave that entirely to your judgment as
                    to the best approach.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">Dick</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Frankfurter always told me that I would only be of use as an assist-ant as
                        long as I was willing to say unpleasant things.</p>
                    <p>P.S. Of course, I have told Sarge about this memo.<note n="2" xml:id="d63fn2"
                            >The last two sentences are handwritten by <persName corresp="#p_GRN2"
                                >Goodwin</persName> on the source text. Reference is to Supreme
                            Court Justice Felix Frankfurter, for whom <persName corresp="#p_GRN2"
                                >Goodwin</persName> clerked in 1958-1959, and to <persName
                                corresp="#p_SRSJ1">Sargent Shriver</persName>, Director of the Peace
                            Corps.</note>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
