<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1948-12-30T13:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1950-03-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1950-03-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1948-12-30T13:00:00-05:00" n="11" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d11">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Editorial Note</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The holding of periodic conferences of the chiefs of missions in Eastern European
                    countries was originally suggested by President Truman to Secretary of State
                    Acheson during a meeting on May 16, 1949. The President felt that such meetings,
                    which he suggested be held in one of the Embassies in Eastern Europe, might
                    produce interesting policy suggestions and would in any case have a useful
                    effect on the Eastern European countries (Memorandum by the Secretary of State
                    of Meeting with the President, May 16, 1949; Secretary’s Memoranda, Lot 53 D
                    444). Officers of the Department of State quickly endorsed the President’s
                    suggestion, and Department planning of the first Eastern European chiefs of
                    mission conference was begun. At his meeting with President Truman on September
                    19, Secretary Acheson discussed the plans for the first such conference
                    tentatively scheduled for Paris in early October. The President was “delighted”
                    with plan, which he approved, and he expressed an interest in being informed of
                    the outcome of the conference. In late September Ambassador Bruce urged that the
                    site of the proposed conference be shifted from Paris in view of the concurrent
                    meeting of principal Ambassadors in Western Europe, October 21–22, 1949. It was
                    feared that so large a gathering of American officials in Paris would cause
                    embarrassment to the French Government and give rise to harmful Communist
                    propaganda. With the agreement of British Foreign Secretary Bevin, the
                    conference site was changed to London and the date of October 21 agreed upon.
                    The agenda for the conference was developed in the course of an exchange <pb
                        facs="0042" n="28" xml:id="pg_28"/> of telegrams between the Department of
                    State and the various Eastern European missions. Documentation on the planning
                    and arrangements for the London Conference of Eastern European Chiefs of Mission
                    is included in Department of State file 120.3 Conferences. The immediately
                    following documents in this volume are concerned with the proceedings of the
                    Conference and its principle conclusions and recommendations.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
