<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Acting Secretary of State to Certain Diplomatic Offices</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1949-06-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-06-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recbmmC3Qhr3E4JGh" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112309"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Political refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-06-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-06-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="176"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d176">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">840.00/6–2149: Circular airgram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss> to
                        Certain <gloss type="to">Diplomatic Offices</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d176fn1">This airgram was sent to 24 Embassies, Legations,
                        and Missions in Europe and the Middle East.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-06-21">June 21,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The formation of National Committee for Free Europe, Inc., with headquarters in
                    New York, was announced on June 1, 1949. This Committee is a private
                    organization concerning itself with democratic leaders and scholars who are
                    exiled from the following countries: Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Rumania,
                    Yugoslavia, and Bulgaria. The Committee will be financed by private
                    contributions.</p>
                <p>The following is quoted from a statement issued by Joseph C. Grew,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d176fn2">Former Ambassador in Japan (1982–1941) and Under Secretary
                        of State (1945).</note> Chairman of the Committee, in announcing its
                    formation:</p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“Our program begins with the tangible fact of the presence here of these
                        exiles and refugees. There is an American tradition of hospitality to
                        political refugees. The promise which we gave at Yalta remains unredeemed.
                        More than that we have a definite self-interest in helping to keep alive,
                        and in full vigor, political leaders who share our view of life—leaders who
                        have refused to knuckle under, men who have not hesitated to risk their
                        lives for their democratic faith. As item No. 1 in our immediate program we
                        propose—have in fact already begun—to find suitable occupations for these
                        democratic exiles … We are setting out to find suitable positions for them
                        in colleges and universities. We are proposing to ask others of them to
                        prepare studies on topics for which they are especially equipped … At the
                        same time we are encouraging each national group of exiles to draw together
                        politically—all democratic elements, that is, those other than Fascists or
                        Communists—in order to form in their temporary American haven National
                        Committees which can stand as symbols of democratic hope for their
                        countrymen in Eastern Europe … We look forward to the day when there will no
                        longer be an Iron Curtain … and these six nations which we helped liberate
                        from the Nazi <pb facs="0304" n="290" xml:id="pg_290"/> oppression will be
                        free from the Communist oppression and once more can organize their
                        existence in their own way. When that time comes, there will be something
                        close to social chaos and political vacuum, for the first effort of
                        totalitarian regimes is to destroy all constructive elements which might
                        build anything different from themselves. Looking forward to that historic
                        and critical time we have in mind that, if meanwhile democratic leaders have
                        been helped to keep alive and in vigor in the democratic havens to which
                        they have been driven, we can hope that, returning, they will have parts in
                        a democratic reconstruction. Our second purpose will be to put the voices of
                        these exiled political leaders on the air, addressed to their own peoples
                        back in Europe, in their own languages, in the familiar tones. We shall help
                        them also if we can to get their messages back by the printed word. … Of
                        course we are not going to compete with the Voice of America. We shall
                        endeavor to supplement the Voice of America, for the Voice is under
                        restrictions by reason of its official character. It is our American habit
                        not to leave everything to government. In the field of the contest of ideas
                        there is much which private initiative can accomplish best. The third and
                        final point in our immediate program is to set out at once to bring the
                        exiled leaders into a broad contact with American life. … Our idea is to
                        enable these proven champions of democracy to see with their own eyes how
                        freedom and democracy are working out in the United States. … I have no
                        doubt that as we go along other activities will be added to our program.
                        …”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Members of the Committee, as of June 1, 1949 were: Frank Altschul (Treasurer),
                    Hamilton Fish Armstrong, A. A. Berle, Francis Biddle, Robert Woods Bliss, Hugh
                    A. Drum, Allen W. Dulles, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Mark Ethridge, James A. Farley,
                    William Green, Joseph C. Grew (Chairman), Charles R. Hook, Arthur Bliss Lane,
                    Henry R. Luce, Arthur W. Page, DeWitt C. Poole (Executive Secretary), Charles M.
                    Spofford, Charles P. Taft, DeWitt Wallace, Mathew Woll.</p>
                <p>For your information, the Department has been continually informed of the process
                    of formation of the Committee. Although the Department has no active concern
                    with the Committee’s activities, it has given its unofficial approval to the
                    Committee’s objectives. Because of the implicitly political nature of the
                    Committee’s work, there will be coordination between it and the Department. We
                    expect that the Committee will cooperate in every way toward the accomplishment
                    of our objectives in Eastern Europe and of the general aims of our foreign
                        policy.<note n="3" xml:id="d176fn3">At his press and radio news conference
                        on June 23, Secretary of State Acheson was asked if the State Department
                        supported or endorsed the newly established National Committee for Free
                        Europe. The Secretary replied that the Department was very happy to see the
                        formation of the distinguished group. He also said that the Department felt
                        the purpose of the organization was excellent and was glad to welcome its
                        entrance into the field and give it hearty endorsement (News Division
                        Files).</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
