<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="185" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d185">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">875.00/5–1449</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Director, Office of European
                                Affairs</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hickerson</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant
                                Secretary of State for United Nations Affairs</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Rusk</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-16">May 16, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_SE1">SE</gloss>’s attached memorandum of
                                conversation<note n="1" xml:id="d185fn1">The reference here is to
                                Campbell’s memorandum of conversation of May 14, <hi rend="italic">supra</hi>.</note> with Behar Shtylla, Albanian Minister to
                            France, indicates that the Albanian Government wishes to discuss the
                            establishment of diplomatic relations with the United States and may be
                            willing to meet the condition (acceptance of prewar treaty obligations)
                            which we set and which they refused in 1945–46. We are not sure why this
                            approach is being made at this time. It may be assumed that it is made
                            with Soviet consent and probably on Soviet suggestion. Albania’s
                            difficult economic situation may be a major factor in the picture.</p>
                        <p>There would be certain obvious disadvantages to establishing relations
                            with the Hoxha Government at this juncture. It is now a 100 percent
                            Moscow-controlled police regime. Recognition by the US would be resented
                            by anti-Hoxha elements among Albanians and also by the Greeks. It might
                            be subjected to some criticism in this country as a sign of favor to a
                            particularly unsavory government. In opposing Albania’s entry into the
                            UN we have stated that we consider the Hoxha Government unable or
                            unwilling to fulfill the obligations of the Charter.</p>
                        <p>On the other hand, an agreement by Albania to accept the prewar treaties
                            would partially meet this criticism. Moreover, if recognition were
                            accorded, the US could state explicitly that such action did not involve
                            or imply approval of the policies and methods of the Albanian
                            Government. The establishment of diplomatic relations would enable us to
                            protect US citizens better than we can at present. It would also <pb facs="0317" n="303" xml:id="pg_303"/> contain advantages, from the
                            standpoint of information and possibilities of action, that we do not
                            now enjoy. In the present state of affairs in the Balkans, and
                            especially in Albania, which is a weak spot in the Soviet sphere, the
                            presence of a US Mission in Albania might be very useful.</p>
                        <p>In any further discussions on the subject the Department might indicate,
                            without setting absolute conditions at the outset, that we would require
                            some assurances not only on the question of prewar treaties, but also on
                            the freedom of any American diplomatic mission to perform its duties
                            without vexatious interference such as Mr. Jacobs had to put up with in
                            1946. Furthermore, we would have a right to expect changes in Albania’s
                            attitude toward Greece and toward <gloss target="#t_UNSCOB1">UNSCOB</gloss> indicating that the Albanian Government had the
                            intention of respecting international law and the rights of other
                            states.</p>
                        <p>The Albanian approach requires some thought and discussion here and
                            possible consultation with the British. It seems unwise and in fact
                            hardly possible to give the Albanians an early statement of a definite
                            US position.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <hi rend="italic">Recommendations:</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d185fn2">A
                                marginal handwritten notation on the source text indicates that
                                Assistant Secretary Rusk approved numbered recommendations 1, 2, and
                                3 on May 16. A further handwritten notation by John Campbell records
                                that the recommendations were telephoned to Harry Howard in New York
                                on May 16.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>It is recommended that: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>We let Shtylla know informally today that he cannot expect an
                                    immediate answer to his query, and that there is no reason for
                                    him to delay his return to Paris on that account.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>We let him know at the same time that the matter can hardly be
                                    considered apart from related questions such as Albania’s role
                                    in the war in Greece, her failure to cooperate with the UN,
                                    etc.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>We inform him also that we will consider any views which he
                                    may wish to present later.<note n="3" xml:id="d185fn3">In the
                                        source text this recommendation has been revised in
                                        handwriting presumably by or at the direction of Assistant
                                        Secretary Rusk. The recommendation originally read as
                                        follows: “(3) We inform him also that the Department would
                                        be glad to take under consideration any proposals his
                                        Government may have to offer.”</note>
                                </item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>In preparing for any further exchanges and in formulating the
                                    Department’s position on the subject, we should keep our
                                    approach flexible, bearing in mind the advantages, in principle,
                                    of having diplomatic relations with Albania so long as
                                    reasonable conditions are met and so long as the establishment
                                    of such relations contributes to the furtherance of our general
                                    policy objectives toward the USSR, the Balkans, Greece, etc.,
                                    and is consistent with our obligations to the UN.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hickerson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>