<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Minister in Bulgaria (
                        Heath
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d205</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">205</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-05-10T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-05-10T12:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-10T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-10T12:00:00-05:00" n="205" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d205">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">124.74/5–1049: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Bulgaria</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Heath</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Sofia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-10T19:00:00+02:00">May 10, 1949—7 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>387. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 143, May 6.<note n="1" xml:id="d205fn1">Telegram 353, April 28, from Sofia, not printed,
                        transmitted the text of Bulgarian Foreign Ministry note of April 27 asking
                        for a reduction in the size of the American Legation (124.74/4–2849).
                        Telegram 354, April 28, from Sofia, not printed, observed that the British
                        Legation had received a similar note, but the Soviet Embassy had not
                        (124.74/4–2849). The telegram under reference here, not printed, asked the
                        Legation’s views and recommendations upon the note (124.74/4–2849).</note> I
                    remarked to Assistant Foreign Minister [Evgenii] Kamenov that I regretted to
                    find on my return to Bulgaria<note n="2" xml:id="d205fn2">Minister Donald R.
                        Heath resumed charge of the Legation in Sofia on April 28 following a period
                        of consultation in the United States.</note> a note asking Legation to
                    reduce its staff. While tone of note was unexceptionable it was against
                    international practice and good relations for a receiving state to attempt to
                    prescribe size and composition of the sending state’s diplomatic representation.
                    I said I was without instructions in matter but that I could discuss with
                    Ganovsky and if possible with Foreign Minister Kolarov,<note n="3" xml:id="d205fn3">Vasil Petkov Kolarov, member of the Politburo of the
                        Bulgarian Communist Party, Deputy Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign
                        Affairs. It was announced on April 15 that Kolarov had been designated
                        Acting Prime Minister during the illness of Prime Minister Georgi
                        Dimitrov.</note> now Acting Premier, this and related questions. While I
                    must reject principle of this note I might state that our Government is, of
                    course, interested in economy and had no desire to maintain a larger
                    representation than its interest required. The size of our Government
                    establishment and its interests had grown and diversified and our missions in
                    all countries were accordingly larger than before the war. As regards
                    enlargement of military staff our Government had now three defense departments
                    each of which naturally desired its own representatives. Before war there were
                    only War and Navy Departments.</p>
                <p>Our Government made no restrictions on size of Bulgarian staff in Washington and
                    many countries, particularly the Soviets had extremely large establishments in
                    our capital.</p>
                <p>Kamenov said he agreed that rigid numerical reciprocity should not be insisted
                    upon, that it was not in accord with good international practice or relation.
                    However, he thought there must be some approximation between diplomatic staffs
                    exchanged by any two governments. French Foreign Office Ministry had refused to
                    allow increase of Bulgarian staff in Paris and had insisted on strict numerical
                    equality on diplomatic staffs of two countries and same proposition had been
                    advanced in House of Lords although not adopted by British Foreign Office. He
                    said he would agree not to press the request but hoped there would be
                    discussions taking into account Bulgarian housing shortage and other
                    considerations which would settle matter without difficulty. <pb facs="0345" n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/> I remarked there was always some changes and
                    reduction of staff occurring and observed that Lt. Colonel Yatsevitch<note n="4" xml:id="d205fn4">Lt. Col. Gratian Yatsevich, Assistant Military Attaché in
                        the Legation at Sofia.</note> (aggressive officer whom Bulgarian Government
                    probably fear because of his long experience in the country and language
                    qualifications) was planning to return to States at end of summer. Question of
                    Colonel Pitchford<note n="5" xml:id="d205fn5">Col. John C. Pitchford, Air
                        Attaché in the Legation at Sofia.</note> then arose and Kamenov stated that
                    Government had considered declaring him <hi rend="italic">persona non grata</hi>
                    but refrained in order not to worsen relations and because they had mistakenly
                    understood he was to be transferred last fall. I remarked it was desire of Air
                    Department that he finish his time here, to which Kamenov replied that Colonel
                    Pitchford would not be welcome in Bulgaria.</p>
                <p>I then observed that Bulgarian Government some months ago had asked US Government
                    to unblock Bulgarian funds at rate of $15,000 a month plus 50,000 to purchase
                    Bulgarian Legation in Washington. I had talked over matter in Washington and had
                    hoped to enter into definite discussion soon after my return, but that
                    unfortunate note asking for staff reduction had naturally held up consideration
                    of this matter. I also remarked that Legation was having difficulty in matter of
                    car licenses and living quarters. Also I had been shocked to find that two
                    native employees during my absence had resigned without explanation or advance
                    notice. I could only attribute these resignations to militia intimidation of our
                    staff—and action which did not correspond with Bulgaria’s professed desire to
                    enjoy good relations and their assertions that human rights were protected in
                    Bulgaria. Kamenov here attempted to argue that in case of one of these
                    employees, her mother and brother had been exiled from Sofia and she had freely
                    elected to go with them. I did not inform Kamenov that we knew that the employee
                    had been warned to leave by the militia by a certain date or face consequences
                    and that further warned not to inform Legation of departure. Nor did I mention
                    that another employee is now under similar threat. He went on to argue that
                    number of our Bulgarian clerks was excessive and I said three chancery
                    translators could not be considered an excessive number.</p>
                <p>Kamenov terminated interview by stating we could forget about the note until we
                    had entered into discussion of these and related problems. He thought with good
                    will solution of problems and questions arising from a reduction of staff would
                    be found.<note n="6" xml:id="d205fn6">Acting on instructions of the Department
                        of State, Minister Heath on May 23 informed Assistant Foreign Minister
                        Kamenov that the Legation chancery staff would be limited to a minimum of 25
                        Americans—a number no greater than that of a year earlier (telegram 431, May
                        23, from Sofia: 124.74/5–2349).</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Heath</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
