<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the Secretary of
                        State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d226</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">226</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-12-12T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="226" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d226">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Secretary’s Memoranda, Lot 53D444</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Telephone Conversation, by the Secretary of
                        State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-12">December 12,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I telephoned the President<note n="1" xml:id="d226fn1">The President was
                        vacationing at Key West, Florida.</note> today on another matter and he
                    brought up the subject of our telegram to him about Ambassador Heath in
                        Bulgaria.<note n="2" xml:id="d226fn2">At his daily meeting on the morning of
                        December 12 with his principal advisers, the Secretary of State heard a
                        presentation by Assistant Secretary of State Perkins of the question of
                        relations with Bulgaria. Perkins recommended that relations with Bulgaria be
                        broken if the situation continued its current course. Perkins proposed the
                        text of the telegram to be sent to President Truman on the Bulgarian
                        situation. The telegram outlined the background of the current situation and
                        the course of action described in telegram 426, December 12, to Sofia (<ref target="#pg_375">p. 375</ref>). The Secretary was informed that the
                        telegram constituted the first occasion that the President was apprised of
                        the Bulgarian-situation. After considerable discussion, the telegram to the
                        President was approved. The Secretary asked that the telegram be sent to the
                        President immediately, and that arrangements be made for him (the Secretary)
                        to speak to the President early that afternoon (Secretary’s Daily Meetings,
                        Lot 58D609).</note> The President said that he thought that the procedure
                        <pb facs="0387" n="373" xml:id="pg_373"/> outlined in the telegram was the
                    correct one; that he could see no other procedure to follow. I reiterated that
                    if our policy worked out (as we hoped it would) we would leave the Ambassador
                    there.</p>
                <p>The President and I agreed that, while we thought it important to react strongly
                    to any campaign in the satellite countries to humiliate us, we should not get in
                    the position of stating that the Bulgarian case is a precedent and that we will
                    recall our ambassadors from other countries under similar circumstances, but
                    that we should be able to, take what we think is the right course in each
                    country.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>D[<hi rend="smallcaps">ean</hi>] A[<hi rend="smallcaps">cheson</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
