<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-12-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-12-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="227" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d227">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">711.74/9–1249</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                                State</hi> (<persName><hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d227fn1">The substance of
                                this conversation was the subject of a statement issued to the press
                                by the Department of State on December 12; for text, see Department
                                of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, December 26, 1949.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-12-12">December 12, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">The Under Secretary, Mr. Webb</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Dr. Peter Voutov, Charge d’Affaires, ad
                                    interim of Bulgaria</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Campbell, <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Dr. Voutov called on me at 5:30 today at the Department’s request. I told
                            him that I wished to talk about the present deplorable situation in
                            relations between Bulgaria and the United States brought about by the
                            conduct of the Bulgarian Government, particularly the attempt to involve
                            the American Minister, Mr. Heath, in the present trial now in progress
                            in Sofia. In my brief remarks to him I made the following points: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Mr. Heath on December 3 made a statement to the Assistant
                                    Foreign Minister of Bulgaria protesting against the inclusion in
                                    the published official indictment of Kostov and others of
                                    manifestly and demonstrably false statements concerning alleged
                                    conversations between Heath and Kostov.<note n="2" xml:id="d227fn2">Regarding the conversation under reference
                                        here, see telegram 1011, December 3, from Sofia, <ref target="#pg_365">p. 365</ref>.</note> Mr. Heath made
                                    clear that the Bulgarian Government was in a position to
                                    establish the falsity of these allegations, since no such
                                    conversation ever took place, and requested the Ministry of
                                    Foreign Affairs to use its good offices to have his denial
                                    published in the Bulgarian press. Mr. Heath stated further, on
                                    instructions of his government, that the United States took a
                                    serious view of the Bulgarian Government’s use of unwarranted
                                    and false statements concerning US representatives in Bulgaria
                                    and that in these circumstances the United States Government
                                    could not be expected to place <pb facs="0388" n="374" xml:id="pg_374"/> faith in the Bulgarian Government’s
                                    intentions with respect to the maintenance of normal and
                                    friendly relations between the two countries.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Heath’s protest of December 3 was entirely justified, because
                                    the statements attributed to him were patent falsehoods which
                                    the Bulgarian Government could and had a duty to correct.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>The purpose of Heath’s statement was not merely to establish
                                    the truth concerning the allegations in question but also to
                                    impress upon the Bulgarian Government the seriousness with which
                                    the United States has viewed its recent actions culminating in
                                    the charges against the American Minister in Sofia and the
                                    Bulgarian Government’s apparent intention to disregard
                                    international law and comity in conducting its relations with
                                    the United States.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The Bulgarian Government has ignored Minister Heath’s request
                                    to publish his denial. Moreover, its course of action since his
                                    statement was made has served only to increase the concern with
                                    which the United States Government regards relations between the
                                    two countries. The Bulgarian press, which is under the control
                                    of the government, has continued its unwarranted attacks on the
                                    United States and on the American Minister. The official <hi rend="italic">Otechestven Front</hi> published on December 8
                                    an article signed by a responsible official of the Bulgarian
                                    Foreign Office directly accusing the United States Government
                                    and its official representatives of engaging in espionage in
                                    Bulgaria.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>The United States Government takes the most serious view of
                                    such deliberate actions which must inevitably affect relations
                                    between the two countries, already brought to a low state by the
                                    restrictions and indignities to which the American Legation in
                                    Sofia has been subjected for some time.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>I requested Dr. Voutov to communicate urgently with his Government the
                            substance of my remarks. He stated that he was not fully informed on
                            everything that had happened recently in Sofia in connection with the
                            trial and with the position of Minister Heath but that he had seen a
                            good deal about it in the newspapers. He said that when Heath first
                            arrived in Bulgaria two years ago the Bulgarian Government had hoped for
                            normal and friendly relations with the United States and was well
                            disposed toward Heath himself. In regard to the present situation of Mr.
                            Heath in Sofia, particularly in connection with the Kostov trial, Dr.
                            Voutov said that the Bulgarian Government of course had a reasonable
                            basis for its course of conduct. He suggested that it might be better to
                            wait until all the evidence was in and the trial was over before coming
                            to any final conclusions. He said that he would, as I had requested,
                            communicate immediately with his Government and that he would inform the
                            Department in the event that his Government wished to reply through the
                            Legation here. As the conversation came to an end I stressed to him once
                            more the serious view which the Department took of the situation and
                            stated that the US Government could not ignore deliberate and
                            unwarranted actions <pb facs="0389" n="375" xml:id="pg_375"/> which were
                            in complete disregard of normal practices in the conduct of
                            international relations.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>