<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-05-11T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-05-11T15:00:00-05:00" n="246" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d246">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860F.00B/5–1149: Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Czechoslovakia</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-05-11T16:00:00-04:00">May 11,
                                    1949—4 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>549. Munich Desp. 113 Apr. 14,<note n="1" xml:id="d246fn1">Not printed;
                                it reported the substance of a Munich newspaper account of alleged
                                sensational changes in the offing in the leadership of the
                                Czechoslovak Communist Party (860F.00B/4–1449).</note> report No. 54
                                <gloss target="#t_MA1">MA</gloss> Bern Apr 20 rptd <gloss target="#t_MA1">MA</gloss> Praha and summarized Bern’s 9 Apr 22<note n="2" xml:id="d246fn2">Not printed; it reported the substance of a
                                Bern newspaper story regarding the alleged confiscation in Praha of
                                several issues of the Soviet newspapers <hi rend="italic">Pravda</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Izvestia</hi> because of
                                articles which might upset Czechoslovak public opinion
                                (760F.61/4–2549).</note> allude to sensational developments Czecho
                            Communist Party which may be accentuated by current internatl
                            developments.</p>
                        <p>As we view situation differences between Czecho and USSR re econ
                            assistance are within realm possibility and dissension among Czecho
                            Communist leaders likely. Communist Congress May 25 to 29 provides
                            excellent opportunity settling accts. Hence expect exacerbation
                            intraparty strife in immed future with opposing factions jockeying for
                            support lower party functionaries and delegates chosen attend Congress.
                            Do not envisage Tito-like development but consider moderates able hold
                            their gen position especially in view likelihood widespread
                            dissatisfaction lower echelon party officials as result increasing
                            Moscow pressure and exploitation. Expect avoidance open conflict,
                                Gottwald<note n="3" xml:id="d246fn3">Klement Gottwald, President of
                                Czechoslovakia and Chairman of the Czechoslovak Communist
                                Party.</note> retain chairmanship party and few outward changes to
                            take place. Nevertheless changes composition inner Party comms which
                            might not be published are important and worth careful investigation.
                            Believe outcome struggle might be determined by position taken
                                Zapotocky,<note n="4" xml:id="d246fn4">Antonin Zápotocký,
                                Czechoslovak Prime Minister, Member of the Politburo of the
                                Czechoslovak Communist Party and Chairman of the Czechoslovak Trade
                                Union Council.</note> provided he can effectively control rank and
                            file trade unions.</p>
                        <p>Wld appreciate your appraisal this view, and evaluation Zapotocky’s
                            attitude and relative power in Party. If you concur this analysis would
                            appreciate recommandations possibility our exploitation present struggle
                            in Communist Party and imminent showdown at Congress toward weakening
                            hold Moscow Communists or preventing change <hi rend="italic">status
                                quo</hi> in favor Moscow. Believe no chance however small toward
                            this end should be overlooked. Continuing econ deterioration and
                            symptoms awareness some Czecho Communists that closer econ ties with
                            West desirable might provide entering wedge. At the same time, great
                            caution shld be exercised not to give impression that US <pb facs="0416" n="402" xml:id="pg_402"/> condones nationalist Communist regimes.
                            Similarly our belief Czecho essentially Western nation and will return
                            to community democratic countries shld be reiterated.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>