<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-01-24T17:25:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-01-24T17:25:00-05:00" n="25" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d25">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">London Embassy Files: 500 Marshall Plan:
                            Telegram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Deputy Chief of the Economic Cooperation
                                Administration Mission in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Siegbert</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in France</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-01-24T22:25:00+00:00">January
                                    24, 1949—10:25 p. m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                            <gloss target="#t_Torep1">Torep</gloss> 519. Ref Caffery tel SecState,
                            247 rptd London 57 Jan 19,<note n="1" xml:id="d25fn1">
                                <hi rend="italic">Supra.</hi>
                            </note> Paris <gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss> London 287, rptd
                                <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss> Eepto 2381.<note n="2" xml:id="d25fn2">Not printed. It reported that Alphand explained the
                                delay in French acceptance of the 1A and 1B lists was attributable
                                to consultations currently being conducted between the British and
                                the French working toward a common policy (<gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Telegram Files, Lot W–130, Paris <gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss>).</note> Show Finletter and
                                Moffat.<note n="3" xml:id="d25fn3">The reference here is to Thomas
                                K. Finletter, Chief of the European Cooperation Mission in the
                                United Kingdom and Abbot L. Moffat, Chief of the Trade Division of
                                the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">E.C.A.</gloss> Mission, who were
                                presumably in Paris.</note>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Have been pressing Brit to place under export control those 1A
                                        <pb facs="0085" n="71" xml:id="pg_71"/> items on which
                                    agreement has been reached. Brit have drawn up their own list
                                    which covers one hundred one out of one hundred sixty-one items
                                    on US 1A list. Items not on Brit list are either still under
                                    consideration by Brit Working Party or are not being recommended
                                    to Cabinet for export control. Brit list follows by air
                                    pouch.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Although Brit now agree that more than one control order may
                                    be necessary, before taking any action they wanted discuss
                                    common approach with other countries given 1A list by US.
                                    Initial consultation held Jan 17 at informal meeting in Paris
                                    outside <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> framework called
                                    by French at Brit suggestion and attended by Italy, Netherlands,
                                    Belgium, Sweden, Switzerland, France and United Kingdom. Bizone
                                    not invited because (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) Brit feel this
                                    subject one for agreement between Bizone authorities and
                                    Washington and London, and (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) French and
                                    Brit felt other countries would be more reticent if American
                                    present.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>At meeting Brit took lead in urging all countries approach 1A
                                    problem as a common security matter as well as in security
                                    interest each country. Brit gave other countries copies their
                                    draft list and explained consultation continuing on those items
                                    not yet agreed.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Brit indicated other countries in general anxious that control
                                    of 1A items not be considered by iron curtain countries as
                                    declaration economic warfare and are therefore most desirous
                                    handling matter discreetly. (Brit, however, informed us Poles
                                    well aware of list and in fact practically asked Brit for copy
                                    during trade negotiations just completed.) Without specifying
                                    reactions individual countries Brit stated there were three
                                    categories of reactions: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) countries
                                    like France which agreed with Brit that each country should
                                    agree on its own 1A list in consultation with US, recognizing
                                    such action to be in its own security interest as well as
                                    broader mutual Western European security; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) countries which wanted merely to accept US 1A list
                                    as information and guidance without further consultation <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> missions and without
                                    necessarily taking steps control all items; and (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) countries which approach subject in
                                    very circumspect fashion without agreeing to any firm line of
                                    action. Italian rep apparently not informed measure of agreement
                                    reached with his govt.<note n="4" xml:id="d25fn4">In the autumn
                                        of 1948 the Italian Government expressed its willingness to
                                        cooperate fully in the program to control exports to Eastern
                                        Europe.</note> Brit reported he was almost inaudible and
                                    talked only about recent Italo-Soviet trade agreement.<note n="5" xml:id="d25fn5">An Italian-Soviet Treaty of Commerce
                                        and Navigation together with agreements on trade, payments,
                                        and reparations was signed in Moscow on December 11, 1948.
                                        Materials on the concern of the United States with respect
                                        to these agreements are presented in <ref target="frus1948v04#pg_489">
                                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 489</ref> ff.</note>
                                    Although other countries agreed this subject not <pb facs="0086" n="72" xml:id="pg_72"/> one for exploration within <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> framework, Netherlands and
                                    Belgium had received US 1A list so recently that reactions of
                                    their Paris <gloss target="#t_reps1">reps</gloss> were somewhat
                                    tentative. Brit was asked not to take any action in making
                                    public their list (which must be done when Brit puts items under
                                    export control) until other countries had time consider list and
                                    consult further. Brit meeting with French again Jan 26
                                    preliminary to next meeting with other countries scheduled Jan
                                    29. Brit will report results those meetings to us Jan 31.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>In light reactions expressed at initial consultation Brit,
                                    while reserving complete freedom of action, told other countries
                                    they would consult us before deciding whether to place agreed
                                    items immediately under export control or accede wishes other
                                    participating countries and delay until further informal
                                    consultation with other European countries can be had. Brit
                                    reasons for further delay are: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) by
                                    taking leadership as they are now doing and consulting further
                                    with other European govts before putting their list under formal
                                    export control it may be possible to secure more uniformity in
                                    other countries’ list; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) publication of
                                    Brit list now would inevitably restrict scope of negotiations
                                    between other countries and <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>
                                    since Brit current agreed list shorter than US 1A list; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) publication Brit list in advance of
                                    further consultation and in advance of other countries applying
                                    controls may prejudice Brit future competitive status re trade
                                    negotiations with Eastern countries. Re (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) we pointed out Italians already were applying
                                    controls hence Brit would not be alone if list were laid before
                                    Parliament soon. Brit indicated clearly their feeling Italian
                                    controls would actually be only partially effective irrespective
                                    of any decrees on paper.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>Brit now awaiting <gloss target="#t_OSR1">OSR</gloss> and
                                    Washington reaction as to whether achievement of 1A security
                                    aims would be assisted by having Brit delay applying controls
                                    until other countries further along. Our tentative feeling is
                                    that delay up to four weeks might prove helpful provided Brit
                                    continue leadership with other countries, <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> consultations with other
                                    countries can advance, and other countries make effort catch up
                                    with Brit. Delay beyond four weeks would only cause footdragging
                                    by countries concerned. Concur that common consultations while
                                    helpful should not be used as excuse for procrastination and had
                                    already made this point clear to Brit. Brit most anxious that US
                                    not view such consultations as delaying tactic and appear more
                                    prepared to take leadership in encouraging other countries go
                                    along with common approach than they were several months
                                    ago.</item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item>Ref <gloss target="#t_Torep1">Torep</gloss> 331 reptd <gloss target="#t_Toeca1">Toeca</gloss> 404 Nov 12,<note n="6" xml:id="d25fn6">Not printed.</note> Brit still feel they
                                    must issue parliamentary order as statutory instrument which
                                    will undoubtedly <pb facs="0087" n="73" xml:id="pg_73"/> raise
                                    questions in Parliament. <gloss target="#t_FonOff1">FonOff</gloss> insistent that no hint of discrimination be
                                    contained in published order but <gloss target="#t_MOS1">MOS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_BOT1">BOT</gloss> feel
                                    administrative burden required by examination of export license
                                    applications irrespective of destination would be impossibly
                                    heavy and therefore wish to reduce number of examinations
                                    required. In effect this would be done by requiring licenses for
                                    all destinations but at same time or shortly after statutory
                                    instrument published by issuing supplemental order specifying
                                    that open licenses would be issued for certain named
                                    destinations such as Commonwealth, Western Hemisphere and <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> countries. Brit will further
                                    consider details of control methods and keep us informed.</item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item>Because of difficulty of precise definitions Brit may control
                                    some few items through administrative action direct with
                                    manufacturers or exporters instead of requiring licenses. In
                                    these cases Brit want it clearly understood that such
                                    administrative controls may not prove 100 percent effective
                                    although in fact we are assured this type of control almost as
                                    effective as license requirement.</item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item>Ref para 3 London <gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss> 287
                                    reptd <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>
                                    <gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss> 2381<note n="7" xml:id="d25fn7">Paragraph 3 of the message under reference
                                        (see footnote 2) reported that American <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> officials had been informed
                                        that the Italian position would be buttressed if the British
                                        Ambassador in Italy could unofficially communicate to
                                        Italian officials the British willingness to concert their
                                        efforts toward the achievement of a common policy.</note>
                                    Brit were told Italian concern and feel presence Italian rep at
                                    Paris meeting sufficient to ensure Italian Govt knowledge Brit
                                    attitude on 1A list.</item>
                                <label>10.</label>
                                <item>
                                    <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> please pass State. <gloss target="#t_OSR1">OSR</gloss> please pass appropriate country
                                    missions.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Sent Paris <gloss target="#t_Torep1">Torep</gloss> 519, rptd Washington
                                <gloss target="#t_Toeca1">Toeca</gloss> 616.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Siegbert</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>