<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Ambassador in Czechoslovakia (
                        Briggs
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d255</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">255</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-11-29T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-29T06:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-29T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-29T06:00:00-05:00" n="255" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d255">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860F.00/11–2949: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Czechoslovakia</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Briggs</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Praha</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-11-29T12:00:00+01:00">November 29, 1949—noon.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1767. Though Embassy inclined to view as academic differences between British
                    attitude and that of Embassy Moscow toward possibility Clementis defection (re
                    Moscow’s 2926, November 25) it does not share Moscow’s surprise at British
                        contention.<note n="1" xml:id="d255fn1">Telegram 4100, November 14, to
                        London, repeated to Praha as 1147, not printed, reviewed recent reports that
                        Foreign Minister Clementis, in New York as the head of the Czechoslovak
                        Delegation to the United Nations General Assembly, might be contemplating to
                        defect. The Department viewed the reports with skepticism (860F.00/11–1449).
                        Telegrams 4574, November 16 and 4757, November 29, from London, neither
                        printed, reported that officers of the British Foreign Office felt it would
                        be in the best interests of the West if Clementis returned to Czechoslovakia
                        and continued either as Foreign Minister or as a dissident Communist
                        (860F.00/11–1649 and 860F.00/11–2949). Telegram 2926, November 25, from
                        Moscow, not printed, expressed surprise at the British view and suggested
                        that every effort be made to encourage Clementis to defect
                        (860F.00/11–2549).</note> Without intention discount previous propaganda and
                    possible intelligence benefits his defection, nor with any intention give
                    impression his influence on basic policy is decisive, Embassy feels it is
                    important to understand that he constitutes definite moderating influence in our
                    day to day relations with Czechoslovak Government, in which it is most helpful
                    to be able to deal with relatively reasonable person who understands West.</p>
                <p>Sent Department 1767, repeated London 46. Department pass Moscow 30.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Briggs</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
