<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chargé in the Soviet Union (
                        Kohler
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d328</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">328</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-02-14T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recR6pcxcU9pXbBvw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="agriculture" subject="agricultural-production" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002427" lcsh-match="bad_close">Agricultural production</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="economic-development" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804" lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="328" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d328">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">800.50/2–1449</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kohler</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                        <lb/> No. 85</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-14">February 14,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>With reference to previous Embassy reports concerning the “Varga affair”, the
                    Charge d’Affaires ad interim has the honor to transmit <pb facs="0585" n="571" xml:id="pg_571"/> herewith a translation<note n="1" xml:id="d328fn1">Not
                        printed.</note> prepared in the Embassy of E. Varga’s speech made at the
                    meeting of the Enlarged Session of the Learned Council of the Institute of
                    Economics of the Academy of Sciences of the USSR held October 2–5, 1948. This
                    speech was published in the magazine <hi rend="italic">Questions of
                        Economics</hi> No. 9, 1948, as the concluding section of a report entitled
                    “On the Shortcomings and Tasks of Scientific Research Work in the Field of
                    Economics”. According to the first section, appearing in <hi rend="italic">Questions of Economics</hi> No. 8 (see Embassy’s Airgram No. A–29, January
                    11, 1949<note n="1" xml:id="d328fn2">Not printed.</note>) this report
                    constitutes an “abbreviated stenographic account” of the proceedings at the
                    meeting of the Learned Council.</p>
                <p>In addition to the speeches of Varga and other delegates, <hi rend="italic">Questions of Economics</hi> No. 9 prints the concluding remarks of K. V.
                    Ostrovityanov, Director of the Institute of Economics, in which he repeated in
                    general the themes mentioned in his opening address concerning Varga (Embassy
                    telegram no. 2850, December 6, 1948<note n="2" xml:id="d328fn3">
                        <ref target="frus1948v04#pg_940">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 940</ref>.</note>) but added some
                    pointed words of advice directed squarely at Varga himself. These reveal,
                    perhaps more clearly than many of the previous remarks regarding Varga, the
                    extent to which the latter has defied attacks from the Party and the press
                    against his unorthodox views. After saying that Varga’s speech had shown that he
                    did not wish to acknowledge his mistakes honestly, as befits a Bolshevik,
                    Ostrovityanov made the somewhat menacing statement “You should know from the
                    history of our Party to what sad results a stubborn insistence on mistakes
                    leads”. Further in this vein, the Director said “… if Comrade Varga continues
                    stubbornly to insist on his reformist mistakes, then no good can come from his
                    further works. The necessary condition for the success of his future scientific
                    work is the decisive, bold and honest review of his reformist positions and work
                    on the problems of imperialism in the spirit of Marxist-Leninist
                    methodology”.</p>
                <p>The report of Varga’s speech in <hi rend="italic">Questions of Economics</hi> No.
                    9 indicates that, while admitting his incorrect stand in some things, namely in
                    regard to the existence of state capitalism in the countries of the people’s
                    democracies and in his statement that agricultural production in the periphery
                    countries had suffered as a result of the agrarian reform, the economist refused
                    to recant his theories concerning the importance of government planning in
                    bourgeois states during a war period and the existence at certain times of a
                    conflict between the interests of the state and of separate monopolies which
                    compell the state to proceed against the latter. He questioned the possibility
                    that a war between the imperialist states is imminent, pointing out that the
                    economic and military supremacy of the United States, the war of the colonial
                    peoples against the imperialists, the fear of defeat and of the <pb facs="0586" n="572" xml:id="pg_572"/> possible involvement of the mighty Soviet Union in
                    the opposition camp, all combine to slow down the forces working for an
                    inter-Imperialistic war.<note n="3" xml:id="d328fn4">The Embassy added further
                        illustrations of the criticism of Varga’s views on some of these subjects as
                        had been developed in an article in <hi rend="italic">Planned Economy</hi>
                        (No. 6, November–December 1948), the organ of the State Planning Commission
                        of the Soviet Union (<gloss target="#t_Gosplan1">Gosplan</gloss>), in
                        despatch No. 102 from Moscow on February 18, 1949: “Varga’s overall
                        anti-Marxist tendency is seen as a constant inclination to blur the sharp
                        distinctions between capitalism and socialism and minimise the basic
                        cleavage between the two world systems, even to the point of asserting that
                        the struggle between them can be halted under certain conditions and
                        furthermore that this actually took place within the wartime anti-Nazi
                        coalition. This in turn is found to lead Varga to the acceptance of the
                        possibility for peaceful evolution from capitalism to socialism and of class
                        collaboration, both within a given country and on a world scale. Such views
                        are considered directly contrary to the Leninist thesis of the basic
                        irreconcilability of the two systems and the inevitability of revolutionary
                        upheaval.” At this point <hi rend="italic">Planned Economy</hi> exclaimed:
                        “It is amazing how much all this recalls the time worn views of the
                        Mensheviks!” (861.50/2–1849)</note>
                </p>
                <p>Turning to specific criticisms of his book, <hi rend="italic">Changes In The
                        Economy Of Capitalism As A Result Of The Second World War</hi>, Varga
                    admitted that the very “tone” of the book was at fault, saying: “… on it lies
                    the imprint of the times, since the book was written in the period of the war,
                    when special conditions dictated a certain moderate tone. Therefore, it does not
                    have that sharp critical tone which is demanded today”. He acknowledged also
                    that it would have been preferable to have made a joint development of economic
                    and political problems in his work and that the use of the word “planning” with
                    regard to the economy of capitalist countries was an “unsuccessful expression”
                    which could lead to confusion. In standing his ground on the question of the
                    possibility that a capitalist state in war-time can act against individual
                    monopolies, however, the economist claimed that this was not a perversion of
                    Marxism but a subject which “must be calmly considered within the bounds of
                    Marxism”.</p>
                <p>Other evidences of Varga’s recalcitrance are seen in his insistence that the
                    submission of the Western European countries to the dictates of the United
                    States is caused by economic reasons, and his statement that India’s position
                    underwent a significant change following the withdrawal of the British troops
                    which altered its colonial status. In expressing his disagreement with his
                    critics, Varga is reported as having said “I cannot follow the advice to
                    recognize all criticism of my work as correct. This would signify that I deceive
                    the Party, hypocritically saying ‘I agree with the criticism’ while I am not in
                    agreement with it.… I honestly acknowledge much of that for which I have been
                    criticized, but there are things which I cannot acknowledge”.</p>
                <p>As previously indicated in <hi rend="italic">Planned Economy</hi> No. 5, 1948, L.
                    Ya. Eventov was the only one of the Varga adherents who came forth at the
                    October Session with a complete recantation of his previously-held views. The
                    version of his speech as given in <hi rend="italic">Questions of Economics</hi>
                    No. 9, the first full account which has come to the Embassy’s attention, <pb facs="0587" n="573" xml:id="pg_573"/> reveals that, unlike Varga, he
                    acknowledged <hi rend="italic">in toto</hi> the correctness of all the
                    criticisms levelled at him in the press and by the Institute of Economics.
                    Admitting that his fundamental mistake lay in not recognizing that the struggle
                    between the two camps of socialism and capitalism did not cease during the war,
                    Eventov went on to blame himself for having mistakenly estimated in his works on
                    England the role of the class struggle, the traitorous machinations of the
                    Laborites—supporters of the anti-Soviet Churchill<note n="4" xml:id="d328fn5">Winston S. Churchill was British Prime Minister and Minister of Defence,
                        1940–1945.</note> line during the war—and the future economic development of
                    England. He recognized the a-political character of his writings and said that
                    “this sad lesson” shows to what result the ignoring of Bolshevik Partyism and
                    ideological principles leads. Eventov finished his speech of self-condemnation
                    by calling for close ties between research and the policy of the Party, together
                    with a deeper study and application of Marxist-Leninist methodology, as the best
                    guarantee of scientific production corresponding with contemporary demands.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Questions of Economies</hi> No. 9 also prints the Resolution
                    adopted by the Learned Council of the Institute following the October Session.
                    This resolution hits the reformist work of the Varga economists, naming, besides
                    Varga, Trachtenberg, Eventov, Bokshitski, and Lan, stating that some of these
                    authors have failed to come forward with criticisms of their mistaken line.
                    Concerning Varga himself, the resolution confines itself to saying that his
                    speech at the session reveals that he continues to stand on his grossly-mistaken
                    positions and that he is committing a series of new errors.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
