<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Chargé in the Soviet Union (
                        Kohler
                    ) to the Secretary of
                            State</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d329</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">329</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-02-16T06:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-02-16T06:00:00-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-02-16T06:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-02-16T06:00:00-05:00" n="329" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.2361/2–1649: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Kohler</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">restricted</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-02-16T14:00:00+03:00">February 16, 1949—2 p. m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>391. Third person note No. 9 dated February 15 received from Foreign Office
                    reference previous notes January 30, March 4, April 9, July 7, 1948<note n="1" xml:id="d329fn1">The first three notes are not printed, but see <ref target="frus1948v04#pg_841">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, footnote 1, p. 841</ref>. The substance of
                        the note No. 116 of July 1 is printed <ref target="frus1948v04#pg_899">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 899</ref>.</note> re violations freedom
                    commercial navigation on high seas by American planes. Note draws attention
                    Embassy to continuing violations arid stated Soviet authorities have registered
                    only during last three months following new facts. Note then goes on to list 3
                    instances in October, 10 in November, 6 in December 1948 and 3 in January 1949
                    when American planes allegedly observed at close quarters various Soviet vessels
                    navigating in Far Eastern waters.</p>
                <pb facs="0588" n="574" xml:id="pg_574"/>
                <p>Note concludes: “Stating the above and considering that reply to note of Foreign
                    Office No. 116, July 7, 1948 has not yet been received. Ministry upon
                    instructions of Soviet Government again confirms statements made by it earlier
                    re inadmissible violations freedom commercial navigation on high seas by
                    American airplanes and expects that Government US will take necessary measures
                    prevent repetition of similar incidents in future”.<note n="2" xml:id="d329fn2">In a memorandum of March 4, 1949, Mr. Robert G. Hooker, the associate chief
                        of the Division of Eastern European Affairs, wrote to Mr. Llewellyn E.
                        Thompson, the deputy director of the Office of European Affairs, in part as
                        follows: “In view of the comprehensive nature of our note of May 25, 1948
                        which clearly stated this Government’s position that our Air Force actions
                        in those waters are not violations of the freedom of commercial shipping, it
                        is suggested that the present note be filed without reply.” Mr. Thompson
                        approved the suggestion. (811.2361/3–449) The Embassy in the Soviet Union
                        was informed of this decision in A–202 on August 16, 1949, not printed.
                        (811.2361/7–149) For text Of note No. 316 of May 25, 1948, from the Embassy
                        in the Soviet Union to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, see <ref target="frus1948v04#pg_874">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p. 874</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Unless instructed otherwise, Embassy will forward full translation by pouch
                    leaving Moscow February 20.<note n="3" xml:id="d329fn3">The full text of note
                        No. 9 was sent in despatch No. 106 from Moscow on February 18, 1949; not
                        printed.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Kohler</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
