<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-07-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-07-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="363" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d363">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.4212/7–849: Airgram</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Kirk</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">[Extracts] <lb/>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-07-08">July 8,
                                1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>A–713. Eugene Varga’s name has appeared in the Soviet press for the first
                            time since his recent confessional (reEmbtel 1093, April 29). He is
                            listed as one of the members of the Presidium of the Academy of
                            Sciences, USSR, who will direct the “practical application of scientific
                            and technical achievements to the national economy”. This may possibly
                            signify that Varga has, in the words of the reference telegram, taken
                            the “first step on the road to complete restoration” as a topflight
                            economic theorist.</p>
                        <p>Of some interest is the manner in which the announcement made its
                            appearance as well as the names of the other Soviet scientists and
                            theoreticians associated with Varga in this project—notably Lysenbo<note n="1" xml:id="d363fn1">Trofim Denisovich Lysenko was an agronomist
                                and biologist, a member of the Academy of Sciences of the Soviet
                                Union, whose unorthodox theories in genetics on the influence of
                                heredity or environment in determining the characteristics of
                                organisms had recently provoked a bitter conflict, which persisted
                                for many years, among scientists in the Soviet Union and the Western
                                World.</note> and A. F. Joffe.<note n="2" xml:id="d363fn2">Abram
                                Fëdorovich Ioffe was an eminent and influential physicist of much
                                versatility, a professor and organizer, and a member of the Academy
                                of Sciences.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Soviet authorities, for reasons best known to themselves, chose the June
                            26th issue of <hi rend="italic">Sovetskaya Litva</hi> as the medium for
                            publication of <pb facs="0645" n="631" xml:id="pg_631"/> a brief undated
                            Tass item, a translation of which appears in the following
                                paragraph.<note n="3" xml:id="d363fn3">Not printed. This Tass
                                bulletin stated that “a series of organizational questions was
                                considered” at the meeting of the Presidium of the Academy of
                                Sciences. The better to solve these problems of the practical
                                application of achievements to the national economy “responsibility
                                was divided among various members of the Presidium” who were
                                qualified in particular fields. Varga was assigned responsibility
                                “for economics and law.”</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>Coincident with Varga’s reappearance in good company, his chief opponent
                            throughout the Varga “affair”, K. V. Ostrovityanov, received his first
                            public chastisement in the form of a signed article which appeared in
                                <hi rend="italic">Culture and Life</hi>, June 30.<note n="4" xml:id="d363fn4">The detailed criticism of Konstantin Vasilyevich
                                Ostrovityanov, as the Director of the Institute of Economics of the
                                Academy of Sciences, for the unsatisfactory work of the
                                State-Planning Publishing House (Gosplanizdat), which had failed “to
                                guarantee the preparation of serious technical works on the most
                                imporant problems of socialist economy”, is omitted.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">. . . . . . . . . . . . . .</p>
                        <p>This criticism of Ostrovityanov does not necessarily mean his eclipse by
                            a reascendant Varga but it is interesting to note the coincidence of the
                            publication of the criticism and the news of Varga’s new assignment.
                            Future developments will be watched carefully and reported as they
                            occur.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Kirk</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>