<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Minutes of Meeting of the Subcommittee on Naval Ships
                    This meeting was held in the Department of State,
                        beginning at 3:30 p. m.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d438</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">438</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec9429801e8b840d1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="lend-lease">Lend-Lease</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-09-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="438" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d438">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.24/9–2649</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Minutes of Meeting of the Subcommittee on Naval Ships</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d438fn1">This meeting was held in the Department of State,
                        beginning at 3:30 p. m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-09-26">September 26,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi>
                    <list>
                        <item>R. G. Hooker, Chairman <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>Capt. Wm. C. Floyd, Navy <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>.</item>
                        <item>Lt. Comdr. J. C. Davis, Navy <gloss target="#t_Dept1">Dept</gloss>.</item>
                        <item>C. C. Matlock, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>F. T. Murphy, <gloss target="#t_EP1">EP</gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>M. H. Cardozo, <gloss target="#t_LE1">L/E</gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>J. M. McSweeney, <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>G. E. Truesdell, <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>There was presented for consideration by the group a memorandum from Mr.
                    Truesdell to Mr. Hooker<note n="2" xml:id="d438fn2">Not printed.</note>
                    containing suggestions for a 4:00 p. m. meeting with Soviet Naval experts. A
                    copy of this memorandum <pb facs="0751" n="737" xml:id="pg_737"/> will be found
                    in File No. 3 of the USSR Lend-Lease Settlement files.</p>
                <p>The memorandum summarized Moscow telegram 2394 of September 3 [<hi rend="italic">23</hi>]<note n="3" xml:id="d438fn3">Not printed.</note> which states that
                    the Embassy had been informed by the head of the American Section of the Foreign
                        Office<note n="4" xml:id="d438fn4">Georgy Filippovich Saksin was at this
                        time Acting Chief of the American Division in the Ministry of Foreign
                        Affairs of the Soviet Union.</note> that Panyushkin had been authorized on
                    September 22 to sign the agreement on return of lend-lease icebreakers and
                    frigates as presented by the United States group. Although from the text of this
                    telegram it appeared that Ambassador Panyushkin would sign the agreement it was
                    considered possible that he might delegate his authority to Admiral Piterski. It
                    was agreed that should Admiral Piterski sign that Mr. Hooker and Captain Floyd
                    would sign for the United States; if the Ambassador should sign Mr. Thorp had
                    stated that he would be available this afternoon or tomorrow for the
                    purpose.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that in view of the information contained in the Moscow telegram
                    that the Soviets would probably not request any substantive modification of the
                    agreement; however, if they should insist upon inclusion in the agreement of a
                    guarantee by the United States not to retransfer the vessels to a third
                    government, it was agreed that Mr. Hooker should under no circumstances make
                    concessions but should attempt to place the Soviets in a defensive position by
                    requesting an explanation of the basis for such a provision. It was suggested
                    that in this connection Mr. Hooker might state that the President had determined
                    these vessels to be of use to the United States as set forth in our note of
                    October 7, 1948, that the Soviet Government had made no request for such a
                    guarantee with respect to the return of the tankers a year ago last March, and
                    that no other countries have insisted upon such a provision in returning
                    lend-lease articles. It was agreed that it might be pointed out that these
                    vessels were “leased” to the Soviet Government and therefore there was no
                    question as to their being United States property and that the United States
                    does not choose to limit itself as to how it handles its own property. It was
                    agreed that Mr. Hooker might also state that such a guarantee would be a
                    modification of article V of the Master Agreement which was a matter of
                    substance and would have to be referred to the appropriate United States
                    authorities. It was also agreed that Mr. Hooker might add at this point that
                    this matter had been discussed by Ambassador Panyushkin with Mr. Webb and Mr.
                    Thorp and it was not an appropriate matter for the Naval experts. Commander
                    Davis objected to the use of the statement made by Mr. Webb in his discussion
                    with the Ambassador that the United States does not in fact intend to dispose of
                    these vessels. It was agreed that this statement should not be used <pb facs="0752" n="738" xml:id="pg_738"/> by Mr. Hooker unless absolutely
                    necessary. The group agreed that at the conclusion of a signing of the agreement
                    on return of the icebreakers and frigates that Mr. Hooker or as the case may be
                    Mr. Thorp should raise with his opposite number the question of further
                    discussion by the experts of the details of return of other Naval craft citing,
                    if appropriate, the several communications between our two governments which
                    refer to this subject as follows: <list>
                        <item>Soviet note of December 9, 1948</item>
                        <item>United States note of May 25, 1949</item>
                        <item>Soviet note of June 26, 1949 and</item>
                        <item>United States note of July 26, 1949</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
