<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-09-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-09-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="440" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d440">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">861.24/9–2749</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Side Minutes of Combined
                                Meeting</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d440fn1">This meeting was held in
                                the Department of State, beginning at 9:15 a. m. These are not
                                agreed combined minutes.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-09-27">September 27, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi>
                        </p>
                        <table cols="2" rows="11">
                            <row>
                                <cell>U.S.</cell>
                                <cell>USSR</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Mr. W. L. Thorp, U.S. Chairman</cell>
                                <cell rows="2">The Soviet Ambassador, Alexander S. Panyushkin</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rows="2">Mr. R. G. Hooker, Head U.S. Working Group on Naval
                                    Craft</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rows="2">Aide to Soviet Ambassador Adm. N. A. Piterski, <gloss target="#t_Sov1">Sov</gloss>. Navy</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Capt, Wm. O. Floyd, USN</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Lt. Comdr. J. C. Davis, USN</cell>
                                <cell rows="2">Capt. 2nd C1. M. I. Vanyukin, <gloss target="#t_Sov1">Sov</gloss>. Navy</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Mr. C. C. Matlock</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Mr. M. H. Cardozo</cell>
                                <cell>Mr. B. K. Sokolov, <gloss target="#t_Sov1">Sov</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_Emb1">Emb</gloss>. (Interpreter)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Mr. F. T. Murnhv</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Mr. J. M. McSweeney</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Mr. G. E. Truesdell</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>The purpose of this meeting was to sign the “Agreement on Dates and
                            Procedures for Return of Three Icebreakers and Twenty-Seven Frigates of
                            the United States Navy Received by the Union of Soviet Socialist
                            Republics Under the Lend-Lease Act”<note n="2" xml:id="d440fn2">For
                                text, see Department of State, Treaties and Other International Acts
                                Series (TIAS) No. 2060, or 63 Stat. 2810.</note> which had been <pb facs="0754" n="740" xml:id="pg_740"/> agreed upon the previous
                            evening by the working group on Naval craft. After initial introductions
                            Mr. Thorp and the Ambassador signed two English texts and two Russian
                            texts of the agreement true copies of which are attached hereto
                                (D–119–A–3).<note n="3" xml:id="d440fn3">Not printed.</note> After
                            completion of the signing, Mr. Thorp asked the Soviet Ambassador if the
                            Soviet Naval experts were prepared to discuss the question of the other
                            Naval craft, which subject had been included in recent correspondence
                            between our two Governments. Mr. Thorp mentioned that both sides had
                            contemplated that certain of remaining Naval craft would be returned by
                            the Soviet Union and certain would be sold under surplus property
                            arrangements. The Ambassador stated that he had requested instructions
                            from Moscow concerning these and other lend-lease matters but had not as
                            yet had a reply. He agreed to inform Mr. Thorp when such instructions
                            had been received. He added that he was now occupied at the United
                            Nations General Assembly in New York and thus there might be some delay.
                            Mr. Thorp replied that he felt this was a matter which could be
                            discussed more efficiently by the experts and thus a meeting with the
                            Ambassador would not be necessary.</p>
                        <p>After the meeting Mr. Sokolov provided information by telephone to Mr.
                            Truesdell that the frigate which had been lost and would not be returned
                            was that bearing Hull number 35.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>