<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State (
                        Webb
                    )</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d448</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">448</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc></profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-11-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="448" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d448">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.33/11–1249</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Webb</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <dateline>[<placeName>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                    </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1949-11-12">November 12, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">The Under Secretary</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. Vladimir I. Bazykin, Soviet Chargé
                            d’Affaires</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">
                            <gloss target="#t_EE1">EE</gloss>—Mr. Reinhardt</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The Soviet Chargé d’Affaires came in at his own request and spoke as follows:</p>
                <pb facs="0766" n="752" xml:id="pg_752"/>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <p>“One out of the three icebreakers (the icebreaker ‘South Wind’) has already
                        come out of the Arctic ice and can be transferred to the American
                        authorities in one of the ports of Japan before December 1, 1949.</p>
                    <p>As far as the other two icebreakers—‘West Wind’ and ‘North Wind’—are
                        concerned they have not yet succeeded in breaking through the heavy ice of
                        the Arctic, which fact renders impossible the transfer of these two
                        icebreakers in the current year.</p>
                    <p>However these two icebreakers can be transferred in one of the ports of
                        Northern Japan in May–June of 1950. In case the ice situation in the Arctic
                        permits piloting these two icebreakers before the date stated above, the
                        Government of the USA will be informed regarding a corresponding advancing
                        of the dates of transfer of the icebreakers.</p>
                    <p>Taking into consideration that on September 27, of this year there was signed
                        an agreement about the transfer of the three icebreakers in the port of
                        Bremerhaven (Germany), the Soviet Government is also ready to transfer the
                        two mentioned or, if the United States Government wishes, all three
                        icebreakers in the port Bremerhaven after piloting them through the Arctic
                        from East to West during the forthcoming Arctic navigation season in
                        1950.”</p>
                </quote>
                <p>I told Mr. Bazykin that we would have to discuss his communication with the Naval
                    authorities who were principally concerned in this matter and that he would
                    subsequently hear from us.<note n="1" xml:id="d448fn1">On November 29 the Chargé
                        of the Soviet Union was informed that the United States Government was
                        prepared to accept the icebreaker <hi rend="italic">South Wind</hi>
                        immediately in the Japanese port of Yokosuka. In a conversation with Deputy
                        Under Secretary of State Dean Rusk on December 6, Chargé Bazykin gave the
                        information that the Soviet authorities would be able to return the <hi rend="italic">South Wind</hi> at the port of Yokosuka not later than
                        December 25.</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Webb</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
