<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Memorandum by Mr. Robert P.
                            Joyce, Member of the Policy Planning Staff to Mr. Carlton Savage, Executive Secretary of the Policy
                        Planning Staff
                    This memorandum is an attachment to the brief summary
                        record of the 56th Meeting of the Policy Planning Staff, April 1, 1949. That
                        record indicates only that the meeting was devoted to a discussion of papers
                        on the Eastern European satellite countries. Regarding earlier Policy
                        Planning Staff meetings on this same subject, see the Record of the 36th
                        Meeting, March 1, and annotations thereto, supra.
                        Present for this meeting were the following members of the Policy
                            Planning Staff: Director George F. Kennan; Deputy Director George H.
                            Butler, Staff members Ware Adams, James Lampton Berry, Dorothy Fosdick,
                            Robert P. Joyce, Gordon P. Merriam, and Edwin C. Wilson, and Staff
                            Executive Secretary Carlton Savage. Also present were: Ambassador at
                            Large Philip C. Jessup; Former Representative to Bulgaria Maynard
                            Barnes; John C. Campbell, Assistant Chief of the Division of Southern
                            European Affairs; Minister to Hungary Selden Chapin; James F. Clarke,
                            Chief of the Balkan Section of the Division of Research for Europe;
                            Minister to Bulgaria Donald R. Heath; Edwin McCammon Martin, Acting
                            Director of the Office of International Trade; George F. Bernhardt,
                            Chief of the Division of Eastern European Affairs; Minister to Romania
                            Rudolph Schoenfeld; former Ambassador to the Soviet Union Walter Bedell
                            Smith; Llewellyn E. Thompson, Deputy Director of the Office of European
                            Affairs.</title></titleStmt><sourceDesc><bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1949v05</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-id">d5</bibl><bibl type="frus-document-number">5</bibl><bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><settingDesc><setting><date notBefore="1949-04-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1949-04-01T23:59:59-05:00"/></setting></settingDesc>            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="propaganda" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443" lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="radio" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385" lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="antisemitism-post-world-war-ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="anti-semitism">anti-Semitism</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs" subcategory="general" subject="information-programs" lcsh-match="no_match">Information programs</term>
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="east-west-trade" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584" lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc></teiHeader><text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-04-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-04-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="5" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_PPS1">PPS</gloss> Files, Lot 64 D 563, <gloss target="#t_PPS1">PPS</gloss> Meetings</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. <persName type="from">Robert P.
                            Joyce</persName>, Member of the Policy Planning Staff to Mr. <persName type="to">Carlton Savage</persName>, Executive Secretary of the Policy
                        Planning Staff</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d5fn1">This memorandum is an attachment to the brief summary
                        record of the 56th Meeting of the Policy Planning Staff, April 1, 1949. That
                        record indicates only that the meeting was devoted to a discussion of papers
                        on the Eastern European satellite countries. Regarding earlier Policy
                        Planning Staff meetings on this same subject, see the Record of the 36th
                        Meeting, March 1, and annotations thereto, <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi>
                        <p>Present for this meeting were the following members of the Policy
                            Planning Staff: Director George F. Kennan; Deputy Director George H.
                            Butler, Staff members Ware Adams, James Lampton Berry, Dorothy Fosdick,
                            Robert P. Joyce, Gordon P. Merriam, and Edwin C. Wilson, and Staff
                            Executive Secretary Carlton Savage. Also present were: Ambassador at
                            Large Philip C. Jessup; Former Representative to Bulgaria Maynard
                            Barnes; John C. Campbell, Assistant Chief of the Division of Southern
                            European Affairs; Minister to Hungary Selden Chapin; James F. Clarke,
                            Chief of the Balkan Section of the Division of Research for Europe;
                            Minister to Bulgaria Donald R. Heath; Edwin McCammon Martin, Acting
                            Director of the Office of International Trade; George F. Bernhardt,
                            Chief of the Division of Eastern European Affairs; Minister to Romania
                            Rudolph Schoenfeld; former Ambassador to the Soviet Union Walter Bedell
                            Smith; Llewellyn E. Thompson, Deputy Director of the Office of European
                            Affairs.</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-04-01">April 1,
                            1949</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I made no really complete or adequate notes at the meeting this morning but I did
                    jot down certain ideas which were expressed, which I set forth below: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Ambassador Smith said that he considered it important for us to answer
                            Soviet allegations against the United States no matter how outrageous
                            and silly they might be. He pointed out that the Russian <pb facs="0025" n="11" xml:id="pg_11"/> and satellite peoples have great respect for
                            the printed word and could be calculated to believe a great deal of the
                            false propaganda constantly pumped into them by the printed word and by
                            the radio. Lies and distortions about the United States should therefore
                            be answered and their falsity pointed out. Mr. Thompson generally agreed
                            but advanced the thought that it might not be feasible to answer all of
                            the allegations against the West and particularly against the United
                            States which are produced by Soviet propaganda. We would find ourselves
                            in a maze and would be in a position of replying in accordance with the
                            Soviet terms of reference.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Ambassador Smith spoke of the always latent anti-Semitism in Russia
                            and said that this fact might be used in counter-propaganda. Many of the
                            top Kremlin agents in the satellite areas are Jews. The Soviet Union
                            makes use of the intellectual qualities of these Jews but when they have
                            accomplished their purposes they are usually liquidated.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The idea was expressed that it would be a good idea to get some of the
                            Jewish voices off of the Voice of America as it had been discovered that
                            many of the Voice broadcasts to the satellite countries were made with
                            heavy Jewish accents in the languages of the countries concerned.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Minister Chapin stated that Communist propaganda in the satellite
                            areas was drumming in the idea that the United States was reactionary
                            and, in Hungary in particular, would like to see a return to Horthy and
                            the feudal landlordism of previous Hungarian regimes. Mr. Chapin thought
                            that there should be clearer statements which could be carried on the
                            Voice of America that the United States did not stand for a return to
                            feudal conditions but stood for progress. Such statements give heart to
                            social-democratic thinking which in many instances has been made to
                            suspect the motives of the United States.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Minister Heath stated that what we might do in the satellite areas
                            could perhaps be divided into three fields: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                            psychological; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) economic; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) political. He particularly emphasized what might be done in
                            the political field in the way of encouraging the establishment of free
                            Bulgarian organizations outside of Bulgaria. Such organizations could
                            lay the foundation for underground organizations in Bulgaria which could
                            keep the spark of hope alive. Our propaganda should stress the fact that
                            the United States has by no means forgotten the satellite peoples but is
                            taking what steps are possible to alleviate their unhappy condition.
                            <lb/> There was some discussion of the Church in the various satellite
                            countries as a source to keep alive resistance and hope. The Orthodox
                            Churches in Bulgaria, Rumania and Yugoslavia were not as effective <pb facs="0026" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/> as the Catholic Church as the
                            Orthodox Churches have to varying degrees gone over to the Communist
                            regimes or at best were nationalist forces. The Catholic Churches in
                            Poland and Hungary were particularly potent forces in keeping alive the
                            sparks of hope and resistance to Communist domination.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Minister Schoenfeld was in general agreement with what had been said
                            but questioned the desirability of stepping up the ideological attack on
                            Communism and the Soviet Union. He thought that this was too negative
                            and that our propaganda should be more positive in setting forth what we
                            stood for. He indicated that he did not consider that anything could be
                            accomplished in Rumania in the propaganda field with respect to
                            anti-Semitism. He said that he believed that the Jews are in Rumania to
                            stay rather than as temporary Kremlin agents. Mr. Schoenfeld considered
                            that our information programs should harp on the theme that the
                            communist regimes in the satellite countries were minority regimes
                            imposed from without. The satellite peoples should have constantly
                            dinned in their ears that they were being oppressed and their
                            civilizations destroyed by a gang of foreigners.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>It was generally agreed that the most vulnerable point of attack was
                            the relation between the communist regimes in the satellite countries
                            and the Kremlin. This theme should be pounded constantly. The people
                            should be encouraged to distrust the Kremlin agents who were oppressing
                            them and the local Communist leaders themselves be encouraged to resent
                            the iron control of the Kremlin. Mr. Kennan pointed out that the bond
                            binding the Communist leaders in the satellite countries with the
                            Kremlin was a very tenuous one. Everything possible should be done to
                            increase the suspicion between the Kremlin and its agents abroad.
                            Titoism as a disintegrating force in the Kremlin monolith should be
                            stimulated and encouraged by all devices of propaganda.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>There was a considerable discussion regarding what could be done in
                            the economic field to break the hold of the Kremlin on the satellite
                            countries. Mr. Martin spoke of East-West trade and how the satellite
                            countries might be allowed to obtain certain much needed commodities.
                            They would base their economic planning on supply of such commodities
                            from the West and when the flow of the desired commodities were cut off
                            confusion in the economic field would result. Mr. Martin remarked,
                            however, that there was a great deal of pressure, particularly in
                            England, to seek outlets for consumers goods in the satellite countries.
                            He pointed out that British manufacturers were up to 50% over and above
                            the level of 1938 and in France as well the 1938 levels had been reached
                            or surpassed. Both of these western European countries naturally did not
                            desire to lose their Eastern European markets.</item>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>There was considerable discussion with regard to the Albanian
                            situation and it was generally agreed that something very definitely <pb facs="0027" n="13" xml:id="pg_13"/> might be accomplished now in the
                            way of: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) assisting in the overthrow of the
                            present pro-Kremlin regime by a pro-Tito gang, or (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) assisting in the setting up of a new regime which would be
                            anti-Communist and therefore pro-western.<note n="2" xml:id="d5fn2">For
                                additional documentation regarding the attitude of the United States
                                toward the regime in Albania, see <ref target="#pg_298">pp.
                                    298</ref> ff.</note>
                        </item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Out of the general discussion it might be said that the following
                            conclusions were reached: <list>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">a</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Our propaganda should be more active, if possible, in replying
                                    quickly and clearly to the lies about American institutions and
                                    intentions. Our information services should also have a definite
                                    positive accent of making the peoples of the satellite countries
                                    quite certain that the United States stands for basic human
                                    freedoms and dignities and is with them in their struggle
                                    against communist domination and Russian imperialism.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Our propaganda should keep before the satellite peoples the
                                    fact that they are being held in subjection and their respective
                                    cultures are being destroyed by a small minority of foreigners
                                    or native quislings who are working in the interests of the
                                    Soviet Union.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">c</hi>.</label>
                                <item>We should single out the weak points in the Kremlin control of
                                    the satellite peoples and concentrate on these troublesome areas
                                    in our propaganda approach. We should encourage a healthy
                                    nationalism within the satellite countries as an antidote to the
                                    iron controls exercised by Moscow. Titoism within the Soviet
                                    orbit should be encouraged and fostered wherever possible and by
                                    all means of propaganda.</item>
                                <label>
                                    <hi rend="italic">d</hi>.</label>
                                <item>Full use should be made of the refugee organizations
                                    representing the various free movements within the satellite
                                    countries. Assistance and, wherever possible, support should be
                                    given to elements within the captured countries which represent
                                    a weakness in the political control within the Russian
                                    orbit.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert P. Joyce</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
