<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-08-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-08-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="557" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d557">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">660H.119/7–2949</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss> to the Under Secretary of State</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Webb</hi></persName>)<note n="1" xml:id="d557fn1">Attached to the source text, which is headed
                                “Personal for Mr. Webb”, is the following paper by the Secretary of
                                State, dated August 11 and headed “Memorandum of Conversation With
                                the President”: <p>“Item No. 3. <hi rend="italic">Blooming
                                        Mill.</hi>
                                </p>
                                <p>I informed the President of the solution reached here. He
                                    expressed himself as pleased with this solution as he thought it
                                    was the right one.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-08-08">August 8, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Blooming Mill for Yugoslavia</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Please read this memorandum so that you may take the necessary action but
                            do not circulate it.</p>
                        <p>This afternoon Secretary Johnson, Secretary Sawyer, and I met alone to
                            discuss the blooming mill. After a good deal of talk Secretary Johnson
                            read us a proposed letter. The upshot of it was that he wished to state
                            his opposition to the granting of the license but would acquiesce in it
                            provided: (1) the matter was reviewed at the end of a year, when the
                            mill would be ready to be delivered; (2) the mill was redesigned so that
                            its capacity would be equal only to the present ingot producing capacity
                            of Yugoslavia; and (3) he objected to Secretary Sawyer’s interpretation
                            of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> paper<note n="2" xml:id="d557fn2">
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 18/2, February 17, not printed;
                                see editorial note, <ref target="#pg_868">p. 868</ref>.</note>
                            contained in the following words of his letter:</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“It is true that I am required in connection with 1–A items to
                                consult with the Secretary of Defense, which of course I am not only
                                willing <pb facs="0935" n="921" xml:id="pg_921"/> but glad to do.
                                However, my interpretation of the language referred to is that
                                foreign policy considerations as set forth by the Secretary of State
                                will be paramount in my determination of ‘U.S. national
                                interest.’”</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>Mr. Johnson’s contention was that Secretary Sawyer was subordinating
                            security interests to foreign policy and was announcing that he would
                            follow the advice of the Secretary of State at all times.</p>
                        <p>We had a long talk about this, in which Secretary Sawyer and I said that
                            that was not what Secretary Sawyer was saying but that the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> paper itself stated the policy, which
                            was that even important material capable of munition production was to
                            be given Yugoslavia in the event that the present breach between Tito
                            and the Kremlin continued. Secretary Sawyer was, therefore, getting from
                            me instruction only as to whether a particular action continued to be
                            regarded as proper.</p>
                        <p>Further discussion indicated the futility of attempting to redesign the
                            mill.</p>
                        <p>The upshot of the matter finally was that Secretary Sawyer announced that
                            he proposed to take the following series of actions, which was
                            acquiesced in by Secretary Johnson and me;</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>He would issue the license for the mill. In this connection he
                                would make no statement, and no publicity in the normal course of
                                events would occur until the mill had been exported, which would be
                                a year or more from now. We all thought it important that everybody
                                should refrain from talking and, therefore, knowledge about the
                                blooming mill should be held as closely as possible. (Please talk
                                with me about who is told, what telegrams are sent, and how they are
                                circulated. I do not want any leaks from the State
                                Department.)</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Before the mill is exported, we will review the matter, and, if
                                the breach between Tito and the Kremlin has continued or been
                                widened, the export will be made; if, on the other hand, the
                                situation has worsened from our point of view, the mill will not be
                                exported.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Secretary Johnson’s staff and ours will get together and rewrite
                                Paragraph 3 of the recommendations of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 18/2. After this agreement has been reached,
                                Secretary Johnson will then propose the rewrite to Secretary Sawyer
                                and me, and we will agree with it. (I can talk with you in more
                                detail about how this might be rewritten.)</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>In the event that articles are proposed for export which affect,
                                say, biological warfare, but the manner in which they affect it
                                cannot be disclosed, Secretary Johnson will raise the matter
                                personally with Secretary Sawyer and me, and the matter will be
                                worked out between us.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I think this is a highly satisfactory solution. I hope that we can carry
                            it on without having the matter get into the press, as that will only
                            create more difficulties between the Departments.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Dean Acheson</hi>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>