<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1949-10-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1949-10-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="587" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d587">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">860H.51/10–2149</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Deputy Assistant
                                Secretary of State for European Affairs</hi> (<persName><hi rend="italic">Thompson</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                            </seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1949-10-21">October 21, 1949</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Participants:</cell>
                                <cell>The Belgian Ambassador, M. Silvercruys</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Paul Hubert, Attaché</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>The Secretary of State</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Mr. Thompson, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>
                                </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>The Secretary said he had asked the Ambassador to come in in order to
                            discuss the current Yugoslav situation. He emphasized the importance of
                            the Yugoslav break with the Kremlin and said that at the present time
                            Yugoslavia was faced with a difficult situation in its balance of
                            payments. The situation was particularly difficult with respect to the
                            rest of this year and for 1950. It appeared that the long term outlook
                            beginning with 1951 looked good. We had arranged an Export-Import Bank
                            loan of 20 million dollars and when these and other steps that were
                            being taken had time to take effect, Yugoslavia would be able to
                            increase its exports and would probably not be in an unfavorable
                            situation. The British were negotiating a commercial agreement which we
                            understand involves 13 million pounds credit, and the French are looking
                            into the situation to see what they can do. The World Bank is
                            considering a substantial loan. The immediate difficulty is that
                            Yugoslavia owes Belgium some 4½ million dollars, representing short term
                            credits advanced to pay for earlier purchases and it is expected that
                            there will be a trade deficit on current account of about another 1.5
                            million dollars. On September 10, 1950, the Yugoslavs will owe Belgium
                            another 4.5 million dollars under the present payments agreement. The
                            Secretary said that in view of the importance to us all of keeping Tito
                            afloat, he hoped the Belgian Government would see what it could do to
                            assist in this matter and particularly the possibility of deferring
                            payment for a year of the 6 million dollars due Belgium this year. The
                            Secretary referred to the risk involved in any assistance to Yugoslavia
                            but said he felt that the importance of the Yugoslav defection could
                            scarcely be exaggerated and said he thought the Russians themselves gave
                            it first priority.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador said he would faithfully inform his Government of the
                            Secretary’s remarks, and said he need not assure the Secretary they
                            would receive full and sympathetic consideration. He pointed to the fact
                            that Belgium had already done a great deal, not entirely with altruistic
                            motives, in assisting not only Yugoslavia but also other European
                            countries. This had given employment in Belgium but the situation had
                            now been reached where Belgium had, in connection with <pb facs="0986" n="972" xml:id="pg_972"/> its trade arrangements, allowed credit
                            balances to be built up which amounted to some 300 million dollars. This
                            was a large amount for Belgium which was now faced with a possible
                            unemployment situation which might necessitate large scale expenditures
                            on public works. It was for this reason that he was having discussions
                            with Mr. Black of the World Bank and with <gloss target="#t_EximBank1">Ex-Im Bank</gloss> officials. He said these matters moved slowly
                            and he might wish to come to the Secretary for assistance in connection
                            therewith.</p>
                        <p>The Ambassador again said that he would promptly inform his Government of
                            our interest in this matter.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>[<hi rend="smallcaps">Llewellyn</hi> E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Thompson</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>