<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>284. Memorandum From the Director of the Antarctica Staff (Owen) to the
                    Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs () to
                    the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs
                    (Walmsley))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">284</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvKzKYvgKzjgPFZ" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-bases"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085159"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military bases</term>
                    <term ref="recpqcSvEFyuxPc7E" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134146"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Testing</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86005172"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific research</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recqoadbXLYoTaPm3" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Territorial claims</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recjGGYhJwHrOAt0d" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recN3ACLajqlUoUpy" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="recv7NC1vhHG399Za" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006378"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public relations</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="rec1ldfvh0EmC9PyC" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recgO0zWiwmY4SEHo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002995"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Airspace</term>
                    <term ref="rec3xWCKc8tJ1gyWw" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="rec1KxhYuvBVGJngc" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85134107"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Territorial waters</term>
                    <term ref="rec3U9TKkW5rS0s3i" type="topic" category="international-law" subcategory="law-of-the-sea" subject="freedom-of-navigation" lcsh-match="no_match">Freedom of the seas</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-03-13T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-03-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="284"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d284">
                <head>284. Memorandum From the Director of the Antarctica Staff (<persName
                        corresp="#p_OGH1" type="from">Owen</persName>) to the Deputy Assistant
                    Secretary of State for International Organization Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_WWNJ1" type="to">Walmsley</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d284fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 702.022/3–1359.
                        Secret. Copies were also sent to <gloss target="#t_AF1">AF</gloss>, <gloss
                            target="#t_ARA1">ARA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_H1">H</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_INR1">INR</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_L1">L</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SAE1">S/AE</gloss>,
                            <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_SS1"
                            >S/S</gloss> A.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-03-13">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 13, 1959</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Your Request for a Rundown of the Points of Agreement and Disagreement in
                        Current 12-Power Preparatory Talks on Antarctica</item>
                </list>
                <p>This summary follows the order of the articles of the draft working paper (copy
                        attached<note n="2" xml:id="d284fn2">Not attached, but a copy of this paper
                        is attached to the memorandum of the 26th informal meeting, November 11,
                        1958; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 702.022/10–1858.</note>) distributed at
                    the November 18, 1958, meeting, which covers roughly (but in different order)
                    the list of topics tentatively agreed by the working group (October 8, 1959<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d284fn3">A copy of the list of topics is attached to the
                        memorandum of the 20th informal meeting, October 8; <hi rend="italic"
                            >ibid</hi>., 702.022/10–858.</note>) for discussion at the
                    conference.</p>
                <p>At all times during the talks all representatives have made it clear that their
                    proposals and the views they express are preliminary and not necessarily
                    approved by their governments. References to countries by name in connection
                    with positions described below would be read with this in mind. The positions
                    described are based on what the representatives have indicated to date at the
                    regular meetings and in discussions on the side.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article I “Peaceful use only”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There is unanimous agreement to have a provision that Antarctica be used for
                    peaceful purposes only.</p>
                <p>The Soviet representative wishes to elaborate on this with an express prohibition
                    of “military bases,” “maneuvers,” and “weapons testing.” In principle, there is
                    no objection to this, but it does involve close scrutiny of wording in order to
                    avoid ambiguities which might be exploited against us.</p>
                <p>Also, we favor the express provision that the principle of Article I does not
                    preclude use of military equipment and personnel for peaceful purposes. This the
                    Soviets wish to delete, as do the Australians. On strict logic alone this
                    provision may seem unnecessary since the peaceful purpose of an activity is not
                    determined by the military or civilian administrative category of persons and
                    things. We have made that clear. The Soviets, whose Antarctic operation is
                    administratively civilian, presumably seek to embarrass us since at present we
                    are not <pb facs="0570" n="540" xml:id="pg_540"/> organized for carrying out our
                    program with other than Department of Defense logistic support. The Australians,
                    anxious to keep the Soviet operation civilian, would like not only to delete
                    this provision but even to write in a commitment to make all operations
                    civilian. The Argentines and Chileans, whose operations are almost entirely
                    conducted by their military are strongly against this, and practically all
                    others also agree with us, including those who have purely “civilian” operations
                    now (Norway, France).</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article II “Freedom of Scientific Research in Antarctica”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There is unanimous agreement that there should be freedom of scientific research
                    in Antarctica. The Soviets have proposed language closer to that of our May 2
                    note: “The citizens’ organizations and governments of all countries have freedom
                    of scientific research, etc.” The United Kingdom and Australia do not find this
                    objectionable. Argentina, Chile, New Zealand and others prefer the more general
                    language of the working draft. Key words in the draft are “in conformity with
                    the provisions of the present treaty” (cf. Article VIII, <hi rend="italic">
                        <ref target="#d285">infra</ref>
                    </hi>). The Soviets have not insisted on their deletion.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article III “Scientific cooperation”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>There is unanimous agreement that there shall be international cooperation for
                    scientific research in Antarctica. Our draft enumerates some specific types of
                    cooperation (e.g., exchange of information and scientists) with the saving
                    clause “to the greatest extent feasible and practical.” There have been several
                    proposals concerning the language, most of which are not of great substantive
                    importance. We ourselves wish to improve the language of the working paper. The
                    U.S.S.R. and the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K</gloss>. would like to add something
                    about cooperation with international scientific organizations, the former
                    wishing to mention <gloss target="#t_SCAR1">SCAR</gloss>, which we do not favor.
                    The Norwegian has made known his concern that inflexible obligations to
                    cooperate may be a burden to small countries.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article IV “Status quo as to claims” or “setting aside
                        political considerations”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Nine representatives have indicated agreement to the inclusion of this article as
                    is. The French, who earlier had resisted this draft somewhat stubbornly, now
                    merely have some changes in language, mainly because the draft is not easily
                    translated into French. The Argentines, acting on instructions which reflect a
                    preoccupation with sovereignty-consciousness at home with some lack of
                    appreciation of the broader international issues, have reserved their position
                    on one portion of the draft.</p>
                <pb facs="0571" n="541" xml:id="pg_541"/>
                <p>The purpose of the article is to set aside the question of territorial claims and
                    consequent political rivalry in order to facilitate scientific cooperation. The
                    Soviets agree, but maintain that the best way of setting this problem aside is
                    by not mentioning it in the treaty at all. The actual reason for Soviet
                    objection probably centers on the prohibition of the assertion of new
                    claims—alongside the express “non-renunciation” of claims already asserted. (The
                    Soviet representative has explicitly agreed to the inclusion of the topic
                    “Provisions to ensure that political considerations do not prejudice the
                    peaceful and constructive objectives of the treaty” in the agenda of the
                    conference.) Our reason for insisting on Article IV as a whole is that we know
                    it is a sine qua non for the claimant states. The remaining nonclaimants
                    (Belgium, South Africa, Japan) also support it.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article V “Jurisdiction”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The subject matter of this article is the establishment of a minimum set of rules
                    on jurisdiction over persons. Although we included this in the draft, we have
                    stated we would willingly transfer this problem to Article VII, namely, as one
                    to be considered at future meetings of the signatories’ representatives, a view
                    with which the Argentines and Chileans agree. The Australians, British and
                    Japanese have declared their interest in retaining a positive provision of this
                    sort. The problem is not of great political importance, but it is a very
                    complicated legal one and to thresh out a satisfactory formula at the conference
                    would only hold up the treaty as a whole.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article VI “Inspection”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Most representatives have agreed to this “inspection” article. The Soviets have
                    said they agree to it “in principle,” but maintain that the substance of its
                    provisions should not be discussed at these preparatory talks but only at the
                    conference itself where “experts” will attend. The Argentines have expressed
                    some misgivings toward the article based once again on their Government’s
                    emphasis on sovereignty over their sector, to the exclusion of greater
                    problems.</p>
                <p>The basic idea of our working draft Article VI is to avoid the difficulties
                    inherent in setting up an international body to conduct inspection, i.e.: (1)
                    the dilemma that the Soviets would not accept a body making decisions by less
                    than unanimous voting, which would make it useless, and (2) the strong
                    opposition to anything in the nature of a supergovernment or international
                    control which is shared by most, if not all, claimant countries. That is why our
                    Article VI in essence provides quite simply that <hi rend="italic">each</hi>
                    party can freely inspect <hi rend="italic">all</hi> installations of others and
                    that there shall be free aerial inspection everywhere at all times. This, of
                    course, required careful drafting.</p>
                <pb facs="0572" n="542" xml:id="pg_542"/>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K</gloss>. has proposed an unoriginal approach,
                    namely, to set up an “International Committee of Control” which would actually
                    manage this inspection, taking decisions by two-thirds majority vote. We believe
                    that the U.K. proposal is one the Soviets would not buy without a built-in veto.
                    Moreover, Chile and Argentina have declared they would drop out of the treaty if
                    the U.K. proposal were to prevail since it tends to set up a supergovernment.
                    New Zealand, Australia, Japan, Norway and South Africa have indicated preference
                    for our draft. Also, the U.K. proposal has very many objectionable details, in
                    its present form, aside from this major difficulty. In the face of this
                    opposition, the U.K. representative explains he is acting under instructions. It
                    may be they believe it best to hold out for a two-thirds majority managed
                    inspection system as a bargaining position for other articles, or even other
                    problems. But they have not said so to us.</p>
                <p>There is no evidence that the Soviets have not understood that the <hi
                        rend="italic">intention</hi> of our draft is that the all-important
                    inspection provision be complete in the treaty itself and not dependent on
                    “administrative measures” to be worked out subsequently under Article VII, q.v.,
                    with its obvious veto provision. They have said, so far, that the details of an
                    inspection system should be worked out at the conference rather than during the
                    preparatory talks, but they have not said this should be done after the treaty
                    is signed. Presumably they are scrutinizing Article VI for loopholes if, in
                    fact, the principle of inspection, <hi rend="italic">insofar as Antarctica is
                        concerned</hi>, is really something they consider to be contrary to the
                    interests of communism. The strategic value of Antarctica is quite possibly as
                    much of an unknown to them as it is to us. It should also be borne in mind that
                    in trying to close all loopholes to prevent Soviet evasion of inspection, we
                    should not provide them with a nuisance value in inspecting us.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article VII “Administrative Maneuvers”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>No representative has objected to a provision for periodic meetings of the
                    signatories’ representatives to <hi rend="italic">recommend</hi> “measures” for
                    adoption by the governments. This article is the remnant of earlier ideas for an
                    “Antarctic Organization,” favored by the British, from which the concept of the
                    future “adoption” of measures by a group of representatives has been
                    eliminated—thus obviating the problem of majority vote or unanimity-and-veto.
                    Earlier concepts of the treaty envisaged <hi rend="italic">adoption</hi> at
                    these future meetings of “administrative measures” to assure effective
                    implementation of the treaty, such as an inspection system (for Article I), and
                    procedures for cooperation in science, etc. The present draft has separate
                    full-fledged treaty articles on these points (Articles VI and III) so that they
                    are “built in” and do not depend on future agreement. The enumeration, not
                    exhaustive, in the present version of Article VII of the kinds of measures which
                    the <pb facs="0573" n="543" xml:id="pg_543"/> periodic meetings would discuss
                    and recommend could be enlarged or reduced. (The inclusion of any item may
                    facilitate its discussion in the future, if we so wish, but does not, of course,
                    either assure or compel the discussion of such item or the production of
                    recommendations pertinent thereto.)</p>
                <p>The Chileans wish to provide in this enumeration for the eventual creation of an
                    “International Institute of Antarctic Research” as a device whereby
                    non-signatories would become associated with the treaty and declare their
                    acceptance of the treaty principles, a problem which is the subject matter of
                    Article VIII, <hi rend="italic">
                        <ref target="#d285">infra</ref>
                    </hi>. We, New Zealand and others have pointed out the possibility of
                    duplication with <gloss target="#t_SCAR1">SCAR</gloss>, and other problems with
                    the scientific community, that this Chilean proposal invites.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K</gloss>., as a corollary to their substitute
                    proposal for Article VI (their Control Committee), wish to omit measures related
                    to the “peaceful use” provision, i.e., inspection, from the matters listed in
                    Article VIII, since their Control Committee would purportedly do all that,
                    leaving only the business of scientific cooperation and administrative matters
                    to the meetings under Article VII. New Zealand, Australia, Norway, Argentina,
                    Chile and we, have pointed out that this tends to a proliferation of groups
                    dealing with Antarctica.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article VIII “Relationship of treaty to nonparties”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>While there has not been full opportunity to date to hear an expression of the
                    Soviet position in this regard (the discussion was incomplete), all other
                    representatives agree that there should be some provision for
                    “extending”—insofar as possible—the treaty obligations to countries other than
                    the twelve, and that this might be achieved by compelling, in practice, or
                    inducing observance of these obligations by these other countries, or such of
                    them as may eventually engage in Antarctic activities. It is also agreed that
                    this should be done in a form that avoids the appearance of seeking to <hi
                        rend="italic">impose</hi> obligations on nonparties and that should, on the
                    contrary, have a “public relations” appeal as regards the rest of the
                    evergrowing family of nations, especially if pressure for a <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> take-over of Antarctica discussions is to be
                    averted.</p>
                <p>With this in mind our draft Article VIII states that administrative measures
                    which come into existence pursuant to Article VII will apply without
                    discrimination to nonparties so long as they respect the principles of the
                    treaty. This leaves the inference that there shall be discrimination against the
                    nonparties who do not respect the said principles, which include, of course,
                    “peaceful use only,” exchange of scientific information, no new claims, and so
                    forth. Actually, such administrative measures as are envisaged as more likely to
                    impose restrictions than to confer benefits.</p>
                <pb facs="0574" n="544" xml:id="pg_544"/>
                <p>The Article must be read in conjunction with Article II where freedom of
                    scientific investigation is recognized (or <hi rend="italic">conceded</hi>
                    insofar as claimant states are concerned) for the benefit of all others “in
                    conformity with the provisions of the present treaty.” This means that this
                    freedom shall not extend to those who do not observe the principles of the
                    treaty. The proposition contained in Article VIII that certain rules generated
                    pursuant to the treaty will be applied to nonparties, provided they observe the
                    treaty principles, might logically have been appended to Article II. But it
                    would seem to be inappropriate for the treaty among twelve parties to ordain
                    that a condition (observance of treaty principles) is imposed on the exercise of
                    certain activities (research in Antarctica) which the nonclaimant states, such
                    as we in particular, who recognize no claims, must admit they already have as a
                    matter of preexistent right, since all countries are now free to engage in
                    scientific and <hi rend="italic">any other</hi> activities in Antarctica, if, as
                    we maintain, no one has sovereignty there.</p>
                <p>While a considerable majority of representatives accept our draft Article VIII,
                    there is no general agreement as to what also should be set forth in the treaty
                    regarding the problem of the treaty’s relationship to countries other than the
                    twelve. However; (1) a bare majority, U.S., New Zealand, South Africa, Norway,
                    presumably Argentina and Belgium, and probably France, agree that our Article
                    VIII is sufficient; (2) Chile agrees with the Article but also wants its
                    provision for a future scientific institute in addition thereto (see Article
                    VII, <hi rend="italic">
                        <ref target="#d284">supra</ref>
                    </hi>); (3) Japan and Australia, in addition to Article VIII, want a
                    qualitatively listed accession clause; and (4) the U.S.S.R. agrees to our
                    Article VIII but wants an unlimited accession clause as well. Both the Japanese
                    and Australians at one time asserted that an accession clause would dispense
                    with this Article, but they seem to have understood that with or without
                    accession there will always be nonparties, namely, those who neither sign nor
                    accede.</p>
                <p>We, the British, and all except Australia, Japan and the Soviets, oppose an
                    accession clause because there is no justifiable reason for states not having an
                    active interest in Antarctica to participate in this arrangement and it would
                    merely open the door to certain countries without any such interest at all or
                    with only a political interest, to meddle. Claimant states, especially the
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K</gloss>., Chile, Argentina, New Zealand and
                    France are particularly sensitive on this point and rest their case on the
                    historical fact of their efforts and sacrifices in Antarctica, which, they
                    argue, gives them, together with nonclaimants who have been active there, the
                    right to make the rules. All opponents of accession point out that there is no
                    need for it because the treaty does not seek to deny anything to other states.
                    In fact it guarantees them the benefit of free scientific investigation there
                    which, so far as the claimant states are concerned, they do not necessarily now
                    have.</p>
                <pb facs="0575" n="545" xml:id="pg_545"/>
                <p>The Japanese agree that an accession clause is not desirable per se but that it
                    is the only way to avert: (1) criticism and complaints on the part of other
                    countries that they are being “left out” of something, and (2) the eventual
                    injection of the United Nations into the problem. Under the Japanese accession
                    formula, moreover, only members of the United Nations could be admitted and then
                    only by vote of the original twelve signers. The Australians, from the
                    beginning, have favored an accession clause, likewise, in part, to avoid
                    criticism that the treaty is “monopolistic,” but mainly because they believe
                    that an accession clause is the best manner whereby other states can be, as it
                    were, compelled to accept all the treaty obligations if they have an interest in
                    Antarctica. Yet, an accession clause, while creating the problem of undesirable
                    meddling, would not provide a means to “bind” those who neither sign nor
                    accede.</p>
                <p>On the other hand the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K</gloss>., as a solution to the
                    problem, has proposed a separate “Protocol” which it believes can be a
                    substitute for this article. This would, in effect, be a document open for
                    signature by countries <hi rend="italic">other than</hi> the twelve who would
                    thereby proclaim voluntarily, but unequivocally, their acceptance of the
                    principles of the treaty. The “Protocol” of the British has not met with
                    approval of anyone. Its obvious defect is that it is extremely unlikely that any
                    country would sign it, since it amounts to voluntarily assuming obligations in
                    exchange for the dubious privilege of becoming a kind of second-class party to
                    the whole arrangement. A further technical defect of the proposal is that even
                    if a member of important other countries were to adhere to this Protocol, the
                    result would be that these countries would have a treaty with each other but not
                    with the twelve parties to the main treaty, and they could modify their own
                    treaty as they pleased.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article IX “Zone of Application”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The purpose of this Article is to delimit the zone of application of the treaty.
                    Although in our draft it was left incomplete in order to prompt discussion, we
                    have indicated that we favor that this zone include all of the area south of
                    Latitude 60° S. but excluding the high seas. The issues of disagreement here are
                    whether to extend the zone of application to (1) large areas of the sea
                    surrounding Antarctica and (2) to the airspace above Antarctica.</p>
                <p>Against inclusion of the sea are: U.S., <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K</gloss>., New
                    Zealand, South Africa, Norway, presumably Belgium, and, a recent convert, Chile.
                    For inclusion of the sea south of 60° S: Argentina and Australia. (The coastline
                    is mostly nearer to 70° S.) The Soviets have not spoken on this point recently.
                    In much earlier discussion of the matter they appeared to favor inclusion of the
                    sea. (They proposed to limit the zone by the line of the “Antarctic Convergence”
                    which extends to 50° or <pb facs="0576" n="546" xml:id="pg_546"/> more.) The
                    Japanese appear not to have made up their minds on this yet. The French have
                    proposed working out a line by metes and bounds which would include a minimum
                    area of sea.</p>
                <p>The advantages of extending the “peaceful use only” provision to the surrounding
                    ocean appear to be well outweighed by the disadvantage of limiting in any way
                    our own right to do what we please in that portion of the high seas. Also, the
                    efficacy of inspection provisions as regards the sea is not only questionable
                    but poses grave problems of interferences with the freedom of the seas. There
                    may, however, be good reason to include within the zone the waters a short
                    distance from the land or fixed ice. The problem is further complicated by the
                    fact that claimant states presumably maintain that there are “territorial
                    waters” in Antarctica as anywhere else, to which they certainly wish the
                    “peaceful uses only” provision to apply; whereas we, for instance, presumably
                    consider all waters in the area to have the legal status of “high seas” since we
                    deny there is any coastal sovereign.</p>
                <p>Aside from “peaceful use only,” the applicability of the other treaty provisions
                    to sea areas is unnecessary and undesirable. These considerations may lead
                    Australia and Argentina, as they already have Chile, to come around to the
                    formula we favor.</p>
                <p>The injection of airspace into this problem (proposed by Australia and Argentina)
                    is very recent. So far, <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K</gloss>., New Zealand, Japan,
                    Chile and we have objected. Discussion of this has only just begun. It involves
                    even more acutely the problems involved in inclusion of sea areas in the zone of
                    application.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article X “Settlement of Disputes”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This is a provision for peaceful settlement of disputes arising under the Treaty
                    by (1) consultation among all the signatories, (2) the usual methods of
                    settlement, and (3) the <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss>. This has not yet
                    been discussed. It is expected that the U.S.S.R. and Argentina will not accept
                    compulsory submission to the <gloss target="#t_ICJ1">ICJ</gloss>.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article XI “Revision”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This draft article has not been distributed at the 12-power meetings. The British
                    dislike it. We have no great attachment to it.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Article XII “Ratification, Entry into Force”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This is a procedural article. Of significance is our proposal of entry into force
                    only upon ratification by all twelve. If the U.S.S.R. does not ratify there is
                    little reason for this treaty. Possibly some other treaty or treaties and
                    arrangements would then be desirable. Aside from this, the article has only
                    procedural significance. <pb facs="0577" n="547" xml:id="pg_547"/> However, the
                    various proposals for an accession clause, already discussed in connection with
                    Article VIII, would probably be debated in connection with the subject matter of
                    this Article XII.</p>
                <p>This memorandum has not been seen by the Special Adviser on Antarctica,
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DPC1">Daniels</persName>, temporarily absent,
                    who has conducted these negotiations. I believe he would agree with all
                    statements herein.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
