<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>285. Memorandum of Discussion at the 401st Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, April 2, 1959</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d285</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">285</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1959-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1959-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="rectXll6XKk0xZnDr" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002234"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exploration</term>
                    <term ref="recENG9eU9z7Tfb9L" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85128458"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-04-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-04-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="285"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d285">
                <head>285. Memorandum of Discussion at the 401st Meeting of the National Security
                    Council, Washington, April 2, 1959<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d285fn1"
                        >Source: <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> Library, Whitman
                        File. Top Secret; Eyes Only. Prepared by Gleason on April 2.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-04-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 2, 1959</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows a paragraph listing the participants at the meeting.]</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">1. U.S. Policy on Antarctica</hi> (<gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 5804/1; <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> Report on <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5804/1, dated January 21, 1959; <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2050; <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 5905; Memo for <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> from
                    Executive Secretary, same subject, dated April 1, 1959<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d285fn2">For <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5804/1 and the
                            <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> Report, see <ref target="#d269"
                            >Documents 269</ref> and <ref target="#d282">282</ref>. A copy of <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 2050 is in Department of State,
                            <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        (Miscellaneous) Files: Lot 66 D 95; regarding <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                            >NSC</gloss> 5905, March 25, 1959, see <ref target="#d286fn1">footnote
                            1</ref>, <hi rend="italic">
                            <ref target="#d286">infra</ref>
                        </hi>. A copy of the memorandum from the Executive Secretary is in
                        Department of State, <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>–<gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files: Lot 62 D 1, Antarctica Subject
                        File.</note>)</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName> briefed the Council on the
                    proposed revision of U.S. Policy on Antarctica. (A copy of Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName>’s briefing note is filed in the Minutes of
                    the Meeting and another is attached to this Memorandum.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d285fn3">Not printed.</note>)</p>
                <p>When in the course of his briefing Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName>
                    reached Paragraph 20, he pointed out the split of views between the Majority of
                    the Planning Board and the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>-Budget members.
                    He then read Paragraph 20 as follows:</p>
                <table cols="2" rows="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell>“<hi rend="italic">Majority</hi>”</cell>
                        <cell>“<hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                            </hi>–<hi rend="italic">Budget</hi>”</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>“20. If required at any time for the protection of U.S. interests,
                            claim the unclaimed area of Antarctica and reserve U.S. rights in the
                            areas claimed by other powers or make claims in such areas as deemed
                            appropriate.”</cell>
                        <cell>“20. As a means of expediting the achievement of an acceptable
                            agreement on Antarctica, announce a U.S. claim to the unclaimed area of
                            the Antarctic and reserve U.S. rights in the areas claimed by other
                            powers or make claims in such areas as deemed appropriate; but advise
                            the interested governments that the United States is prepared to defer
                            action to implement claims and would agree to leave all other claims and
                            rights unaffected if an international agreement is reached, such
                            deferment to continue for so long as the agreement remains in
                            force.”</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb facs="0578" n="548" xml:id="pg_548"/>
                <p>After briefly explaining the basis of this different point of view, Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName> called on Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> who was sitting at the Council table for
                    the Acting Secretary of State.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> commented that it is the
                    view of the State Department that our objectives in Antarctica, on which all of
                    the departments and agencies were in agreement, were actually in the course of
                    being reasonably well achieved through negotiations looking to the establishment
                    of an acceptable international agreement on Antarctica. Therefore, if we were
                    suddenly to inject into the situation at this time a U.S. claim to portions of
                    Antarctica, the result would almost certainly be a statement of claims in
                    Antarctica by the Soviet Union. Such a course of action would therefore not
                    serve the purpose which the Joint Chiefs of Staff and the Budget people, in
                    their version of Paragraph 20, think it would serve; namely to act as a catalyst
                    to produce an acceptable international agreement. Thus while the State
                    Department cannot agree with the proposal by the <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                        >JCS</gloss> and the Bureau of the Budget, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> did point out that the State Department
                    already has available the text of a U.S. claim to Antarctica. Accordingly, we
                    would be prepared to make such a claim at any moment that it is decided to be in
                    the U.S. advantage to do so.</p>
                <p>When Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> had completed his
                    statement, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName> called next on General
                        <persName corresp="#p_TGNF1">Twining</persName>. General <persName
                        corresp="#p_TGNF1">Twining</persName> replied that the Joint Chiefs of Staff
                    felt that the U.S. is bound to encounter difficulties with the Soviet Union in
                    Antarctica no matter what approach we took. This being the case the Chiefs felt
                    that failure to announce a U.S. claim at the present time would merely cost us
                    the loss of our initiative with respect to Antarctica without actually advancing
                    the prospects of achieving an acceptable international agreement on
                    Antarctica.</p>
                <p>The President inquired of General <persName corresp="#p_TGNF1">Twining</persName>
                    about the views of the Chiefs of Staff as to the defense or military value of
                    the Antarctic area. General <persName corresp="#p_TGNF1">Twining</persName>
                    answered that the Chiefs did not as of now see much military value to Antarctica
                    and believed that its chief value was in the <pb facs="0579" n="549"
                        xml:id="pg_549"/> scientific field. The President then said that as he
                    understood our policy, we are urging upon the other nations a peaceful solution
                    of possible conflicts of interest in Antarctica. If, while we are urging such a
                    solution the U.S. suddenly injects a territorial claim in Antarctica, the result
                    would certainly be to increase the confusion. Moreover, in order to support such
                    a U.S. claim, we might actually be called on to defend areas of the Antarctic,
                    perhaps to send the Marines there. General <persName corresp="#p_TGNF1"
                        >Twining</persName> replied that he thought it was mostly U.S. prestige
                    which was at stake here rather than the military value of the area to the
                    U.S.</p>
                <p>Asked for his opinion by Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName>, the
                    Director of the Budget commented that the hard facts of the current political
                    situation made him wonder where the U.S. would find itself if the Soviet Union
                    was the first of the two to make a claim in Antarctica. Accordingly, even if the
                    argument in the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>-Budget version of Paragraph
                    20, that a U.S. claim now might act as a catalyst to achieve a peaceful
                    solution, was not a valid argument, he felt that the facts of the situation, as
                    just described, motivated the Bureau of the Budget in supporting the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>-Budget text.</p>
                <p>Mr. John Patterson, Acting Director of the Office of Civil and Defense
                    Mobilization, desired to change the position taken by its representative at the
                    Planning Board and switch its support to the <gloss target="#t_JCS1"
                    >JCS</gloss>-Budget position on Paragraph 20. Mr. Patterson explained this
                    change as resulting from anxiety lest the U.S. lose initiative and prestige to
                    the Russians in Antarctica.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_AGV1">George Allen</persName> said, on the other hand,
                    that he wished strongly to support the Majority text of Paragraph 20,
                    particularly from the point of view of pubic relations. If either the U.S. or
                    the Soviet Union were now to stake out a claim in Antarctica, such an action
                    would have the automatic effect of recognition of the legitimacy of the claims
                    made by all the claimant powers. Mr. <persName>Allen</persName> felt that the
                    prestige of the U.S. over the years in Antarctica as a whole was so very much
                    greater than that of any other power that we would be unwise to claim only some
                    portion of the Sub-Continent.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> said he felt strongly
                    indeed that we ought to increase the prestige of the U.S. in the Antarctic area
                    but he felt that this objective was effectively accomplished by other paragraphs
                    in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5905 and indeed that these paragraphs
                    promised a much greater contribution to U.S. prestige than would be achieved by
                    a U.S. claim to specific areas in Antarctica at the present time.</p>
                <p>The President explained that the reason he had asked General <persName
                        corresp="#p_TGNF1">Twining</persName> about the defense or military interest
                    in Antarctica was his belief that if Antarctica does not have a military-defense
                    aspect, then primary responsibility for determining our courses of action with
                    respect to Antarctica should be lodged with the State Department. The President
                    stressed that he did not want the U.S. simply to have pieces <pb facs="0580"
                        n="550" xml:id="pg_550"/> of the Antarctic pie. If we were ever to make
                    claims in the area, we had better claim it all. We should continue to base our
                    position with respect to Antarctica on our long record of exploration and
                    expeditions. On the other hand, the President did believe that this government
                    should state something at the appropriate time, as we had in the past, that we
                    have as much right to any area of Antarctica as has any other nation.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DAW1">Allen Dulles</persName> warned that if the
                    Soviets continue on with their extensive Antarctic program, they will in due
                    course have a better claim to the interior portions of the Sub-Continent than
                    the U.S. had. In answer to a question from the President, Mr. Dulles went on to
                    point out that most of the exploration of Antarctica up to the present time had
                    been confined to the coastal areas leaving the interior of the Sub-Continent
                    open to future exploration and possible claims.</p>
                <p>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> stated that it was virtually
                    the unanimous view of the scientific community in the U.S. that this country
                    should not make any claims in Antarctica at this time. International
                    cooperation, including the cooperation of the U.S.S.R., in Antarctica had been
                    altogether remarkable and our scientists did not wish our government to take any
                    action which might impair this promising development.</p>
                <p>The President repeated his view that the U.S. ought to assert a right to go
                    anywhere it damned pleased in Antarctica and that the U.S. should at the same
                    time refuse to recognize the claims of any other nation to any part of
                    Antarctica. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> commented
                    that the only real problem areas in the Sub-Continent at the present time were
                    the areas claimed by the Latin American countries, particularly Chile and
                    Argentina. To this the President replied that the proximity of the areas of
                    Antarctica claimed by Chile and Argentina to the Straits of Magellan gave to
                    these Latin American countries a clear defense interest. He said that he would
                    be inclined to recognize their claims to this relatively small portion of
                    Antarctica.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> then repeated his conviction
                    that essentially the prestige of the U.S. with respect to Antarctica derived
                    from activities conducted by the U.S. in the area. The President in turn
                    repeated his view that we ought to, at an appropriate time, make a statement
                    which would uphold our rights to go anywhere we wished to go in Antarctica under
                    an international aegis. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>
                    told the President that this was of course our present policy but that he could
                    certainly reiterate it. The President said the essence of such a statement would
                    be that we gave up nothing of our rights in Antarctica but that we made no
                    specific claims to portions of the Sub-Continent.</p>
                <p>Apropros of the earlier discussion of the military or defense aspects of our
                    interest in Antarctica, Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName>
                    pointed out that there could arise a U.S. defense or space interest in the area
                    because it might be the scene of the launching of satellites with polar
                    orbits.</p>
                <pb facs="0581" n="551" xml:id="pg_551"/>
                <p>Mr. Patterson inquired whether it would not be useful to strengthen Paragraph
                    23–a regarding the U.S. presence in Antarctica by spelling out in greater detail
                    the specific activities which the U.S. would undertake in order to provide for a
                    continuing U.S. presence in Antarctica. The present statement seemed to Mr.
                    Patterson to be too general in character. The President turned to Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KJRJ1">Killian</persName> and asked what possible reason there
                    was to launch rockets from Antarctica. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KJRJ1"
                        >Killian</persName> replied that the purpose served would be the observation
                    of the upper air. The President then repeated his view that it was the right of
                    the U.S. and of every other nation to use the whole area of Antarctica for
                    peaceful purposes. Thereafter, the President inquired if it was the U.S. Navy
                    alone which provided logistic support to U.S. activities in Antarctica. General
                        <persName corresp="#p_TGNF1">Twining</persName> and others pointed out that
                    in addition to the Navy the Air Force provided substantial logistical support
                    for such activities. In turn the President inquired of Dr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_WAT1">Waterman</persName> information as to the scope of the
                    scientific effort of the U.S. in Antarctica in terms of the money and resources
                    being devoted to this effort. Dr. <persName corresp="#p_WAT1"
                        >Waterman</persName> supplied the figures requested by the President.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> expressed the opinion
                    that the kind of statement which the President had in mind about U.S. rights in
                    Antarctica seemed to be almost identical with the statement contained in the
                    note sent on May 2, 1958 by the U.S. to the governments of the eleven nations
                    participating in the International Geophysical Year activities in Antarctica
                    which note was set forth in Annex A to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5905.
                    The President expressed his agreement with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1"
                        >Dillon</persName>’s suggestion but argued that one would have to keep
                    repeating the U.S. view in order to convince people that we were being good
                    boys.</p>
                <p>At this point Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName> returned to his
                    briefing note and discussed in general terms the organizational arrangements
                    within the U.S. Government for Antarctic activities. He pointed out that the
                    responsibility was now divided among several agencies and also pointed out that
                    the discussion in the Planning Board and in the <gloss target="#t_OCB1"
                        >OCB</gloss> had indicated that the existing arrangements of divided
                    responsibility left much to be desired, particularly when it came to determining
                    the scope of the program and the means of funding its various aspects. This
                    situation induced the Planning Board to make a specific recommendation for the
                    re-examination of the management aspects of our Antarctic program. He read
                    Paragraph 24 which called for such a review and expressed the hope that the
                    Bureau of the Budget would undertake the review and complete it within a period
                    of sixty days.</p>
                <p>With respect to the Financial Appendix, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6"
                        >Gray</persName> pointed out that no increase in funds for the Fiscal Year
                    1960 would be required even if the new policy were adopted. On the other hand,
                    the figures for FY 1961 and FY 1962 were by no means so firm and could
                    conceivably be larger than those indicated in the Financial Appendix.</p>
                <pb facs="0582" n="552" xml:id="pg_552"/>
                <p>Lastly in his briefing Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName> reached
                    Paragraph 25 which contained the only other split view and which Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GG6">Gray</persName> read as follows:</p>
                <p>“25. Until a different organizational arrangement for the handling of Antarctic
                    activities is adopted,</p>
                <table cols="2" rows="2">
                    <row>
                        <cell>“<hi rend="italic">Majority</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>“<hi rend="italic">Defense</hi>–<hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>“the current arrangements should be continued under which the
                            Department of Defense is the Executive Agent of the U.S. Government in
                            supporting scientific and other expeditions to Antarctica.”</cell>
                        <cell>“the Department of Defense will be the Executive Agent of the U.S.
                            Government for operations in Antarctica, coordinating related activities
                            therein and providing logistic support for U.S. Antarctic programs at
                            approximately the FY 1959 level. Any logistic support in excess of this
                            level will be funded by the agency or agencies sponsoring an expanded
                            program.”</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>He then indicated that he had, as a result of discussions with officials of the
                    Defense Department and the National Science Foundation, formulated a new version
                    of Paragraph 25 which he thought acceptable to the National Science Foundation,
                    to the Department of Defense, and to the Joint Chiefs of Staff. He distributed
                    this new version of Paragraph 25 and pointed out that the views of State with
                    respect to the new version had not yet been ascertained. It was generally agreed
                    that the new proposal for Paragraph 25 was acceptable.</p>
                <p>The discussion closed with questions by the President as to how and why so many
                    Government Departments seemed to be involved in our Antarctic programs. This
                    suggested to the President that there might be unnecessary duplication.
                    Secretary Seaton of the Department of the Interior pointed out that Interior’s
                    interest lay only in the mapping activity inasmuch as Interior was the primary
                    government mapping agency. Mr. Mueller, the Acting Secretary of Commerce,
                    pointed out that his Department’s interest in Antarctica was through the agency
                    of the Weather Bureau, the Bureau of Standards, and the Geological Survey.
                    However, Commerce he said had only about thirty people in Antarctica. Even after
                    these explanations the President expressed himself as puzzled as to why so many
                    different agencies seemed to be concerned with the weather in Antarctica and
                    said he presumed this was why we needed to review the organization of our
                    programs in Antarctica.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>a. Discussed the draft statement of policy on the subject contained in <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5905; in the light of the views of the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff thereon, transmitted by the reference memorandum of April 1,
                    1959.</p>
                <pb facs="0583" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/>
                <p>b. Adopted the statement of policy in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5905,
                    subject to the following amendments:</p>
                <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Page 15</hi>: Insert the following new paragraph 20,
                    renumbering subsequent paragraphs accordingly:</p>
                <p>“20. As timely and appropriate, reiterate the U.S. position on Antarctica as
                    reflected in the Statement by the President and the Note of May 2, 1958,
                    contained in Annex A hereto.”</p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Page 15, old paragraph 20</hi> (<hi rend="italic">new
                        paragraph 21</hi>): Retain the majority proposal, and delete the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>-Budget proposal.</p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">Pages 16–17, old paragraph 25</hi> (<hi rend="italic">new
                        paragraph 26</hi>): Substitute the following:</p>
                <p>“26. Pending the adoption of definitive arrangements for the conduct,
                    coordination and funding of Antarctic activities following the completion of the
                    review called for in Paragraph 25 above, the present arrangements with respect
                    to the Department of Defense as Executive Agent will continue.”</p>
                <p>c. Requested the Bureau of the Budget to undertake the review called for in
                    Paragraph 24 of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5905, and to complete this
                    review within the next 60 days.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 5905, as amended by the action in b above,
                    subsequently approved by the President; circulated as <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 5905/1 for implementation by all appropriate Executive
                    departments and agencies of the U.S. Government, and referred to the Operations
                    Coordinating Board as the coordinating agency designated by the President.</p>
                <p>The action in c above, as approved by the President, subsequently transmitted to
                    the Director, Bureau of the Budget, for appropriate implementation.</p>
                <p>[Here follow the remaining agenda items.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">S. Everett Gleason</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
