<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-10-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-10-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="299" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d299">
                        <head>299. Memorandum From the Head of the Delegation to the Conference on
                            Antarctica (<persName corresp="#p_PH5" type="from">Phleger</persName>)
                            to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d299fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 399.829/10–2659. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_PH5">Phleger</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_FWW1">Fisher</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-10-26"><hi rend="italic">October 26,
                                1959</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Committee I met at 11 a.m. and began discussion of Article VI (zone of
                            application of the treaty). The U.S. spoke in favor of the working paper
                            draft, which includes the area south of 60° with the exception of the
                            high seas, pointing out that the Conference was called to deal with
                            Antarctica and not with the regime of the high seas.</p>
                        <p>Argentina spoke in favor of its proposal, quoted below, but said its
                            position was flexible:</p>
                        <p>“For the purposes of the present Treaty, Antarctica shall include all the
                            lands, waters, and atmospheric space within the zone south of 60° South
                            Latitude.”</p>
                        <p>Japan suggested that there may be a need to include those parts of the
                            sea adjacent to Antarctica covered by ice at any time of the year.
                            France also favored some form of definition based on the limit of
                            permanent ice. The Soviet Union favored including the entire area south
                            of 60°, claiming that the use of the high seas within this area for
                            peaceful purposes would not contradict the regime of the high seas.</p>
                        <p>The Committee also opened discussion of Article IX (relationship of
                            treaty to non-parties). New Zealand favored permitting accession on a
                            wide basis to avoid giving the impression that the treaty is
                            monopolistic, and to permit accession of countries having a genuine
                            interest in Antarctica, provided they are members of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> or its specialized agencies.</p>
                        <p>Speaking in favor of its proposal, quoted below, the Soviet Union favored
                            opening accession to all countries carrying out scientific investigation
                            in Antarctica, whether members of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                            or not:</p>
                        <p>“The present Treaty shall be open to the adherence of any state carrying
                            out scientific investigation in Antarctica.”</p>
                        <p>The Soviet Union insisted that the formula of restricting accession to
                            members of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> was designed to keep
                            out certain socialist states such as the People’s Republic of China,
                            East Germany, etc., and was being relentlessly put forward as a
                            consequence of the cold war, which the Soviet Union wanted to liquidate
                            as soon as possible in accordance with its policy of coexistence and
                            strengthening peace. It said the <pb facs="0621" n="591" xml:id="pg_591"/> objection that the Soviet proposal would permit the accession of
                            states not recognized by some signatories is without weight since
                            participation in a multilateral international agreement does not
                            constitute recognition and, therefore, entails no legal difficulties
                            under international law.</p>
                        <p>Australia strongly supported the New Zealand proposal as a fair and
                            reasonable one and stated that restriction of accession to members of
                            the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> would exclude from Antarctica the
                            conflicts of the cold war, which was one of the objectives of the
                            treaty.</p>
                        <p>Committee II met at 3 o’clock and continued discussion of Article VIII
                            (administrative measures). The discussion culminated in an agreement to
                            send the Article, together with all proposals relating to it that have
                            been submitted, to the Drafting Committee.</p>
                        <p>It was agreed to postpone discussion of the provision on jurisdiction
                            until tomorrow, pending submission of a revised <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal.</p>
                        <p>Chile, supported by Argentina, proposed that the treaty include a time
                            limit of ten years’ duration. Australia, the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, and Belgium opposed any period of duration for the
                            treaty, arguing that it would create a bad psychological effect to
                            suggest that the treaty was temporary in nature, and pointing out that
                            the contemplated Administrative Committee would be able to make
                            recommendations for changes in the treaty when considered necessary.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PH5">Phleger</persName> met Professor
                                <persName corresp="#p_GA6">Gros</persName>, Legal Adviser of the
                            French Foreign Office; Sir <persName corresp="#p_FG2">Gerald
                                Fitzmaurice</persName>, Legal Adviser of the British Foreign Office;
                            and Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TGI1">Grigory I. Tunkin</persName>,
                            Head of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> Delegation, at the
                            French Embassy at breakfast at the invitation of Professor <persName corresp="#p_GA6">Gros</persName>.</p>
                        <p>Professor <persName corresp="#p_GA6">Gros</persName> expounded at length
                            on the difficulty the French were having in accepting the draft of
                            Article IV 1(c) which is designed to protect the rights of countries
                            which do not recognize territorial claims. He admitted that it was
                            appropriate that such claims should be protected by an appropriate
                            provision. He said that his problem would be made much easier if the
                            entire paragraph 1 of Article IV were put in a protocol. He agreed that
                            the legal effect of putting the provision in the protocol would have to
                            be exactly the same as if it were retained in the treaty.</p>
                        <p>The British representative produced a reformulation of subparagraph (c)
                            which the French legal adviser thought was much more acceptable although
                            it did not change the meaning. It was agreed that the British
                            representative would draft a form of protocol to carry into effect the
                            French proposal and circulate it. This was done and the draft
                            follows:</p>
                        <pb facs="0622" n="592" xml:id="pg_592"/>
                        <quote rend="blockquote"><p>“At the moment of signing the Treaty of this day
                                ( date ) respecting (Antarctica), the undersigned plenipotentiaries
                                duly authorized to that effect by their respective Governments, have
                                agreed on the following Declaration, which shall have the same legal
                                effect as the provisions of the Treaty:</p>
                            <p>“Nothing etc. …<note n="2" xml:id="d299fn2">Ellipsis in the source
                                    text.</note></p>
                            <p>“a—without modification</p>
                            <p>“b—without modification</p>
                            <p>“c—prejudicing the position of any High Contracting Party as regards
                                its recognition or non-recognition of any other country’s right to
                                territory or claim or basis of claim to territorial sovereignty in
                                Antarctica.”</p></quote>
                        <p>Later, in response to inquiry, the French, British and Soviet delegates
                            agreed that if a protocol as suggested were to be used, the treaty
                            itself should provide that the treaty and the attached protocol which is
                            an integral part thereof shall become effective when the treaty and
                            protocol are ratified in accordance with the constitutional
                            requirements, thus making the protocol and the treaty one and
                            inseparable.</p>
                        <p rend="right">For the U.S. Representative:</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_FWW1">Wayne W.
                                        Fisher</persName><lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretary</hi></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>