<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-23T09:15:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="3" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d3">
                        <head>3. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>On December 4, 1957, Soviet Deputy Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_ZVA1">Zorin</persName> handed Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLET1">Thompson</persName> an aide-mémoire protesting
                            demonstrations outside the Soviet Mission at the United Nations. The
                            aide-mémoire referred specifically to disturbances on October 23 and
                            November 7, alleging that U.S. authorities had not taken appropriate
                            steps to prevent them, despite having previously promised to do so. It
                            stated further that a Mission employee had been assaulted during the
                            November 7 incident. The aide-mémoire asserted that the disturbances had
                            violated the Mission’s diplomatic immunity, and noted that Soviet
                            resentment about the protests might incite similar demonstrations at the
                            Embassy in Moscow. For text, see telegram 1033 from Moscow, <ref target="frus1955-57v11#pg_257"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi>, 1955–1957, volume XI, page 257</ref>.</p>
                        <p>The Department of State sent the Embassy a draft response in telegram
                            700, December 30. (Department of State, Central Files, 310.361/12–457)
                            The Embassy suggested an addition to the text (telegram 1159, December
                            31; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 310.361/12–3157), with which the
                            Department concurred. (Telegram 711, January 2, 1958; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.)</p>
                        <p>On January 3, 1958, the Embassy reported that it had delivered the
                            aide-mémoire to <persName corresp="#p_ZVA1">Zorin</persName>. (Telegram
                            1174, January 3; <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 310.361/1–358) The
                            aide-mémoire stated that the United States was unaware of any
                            interference experienced by the Soviet Mission in carrying out its
                            activities, or of any violation of the Mission’s diplomatic immunity.
                            Police records, it continued, did not support Soviet contentions that
                            appropriate measures had not been taken to prevent the incidents, or
                            that a Mission employee had been assaulted. The aide-mémoire concluded
                                <pb facs="0035" n="5" xml:id="pg_5"/> by noting that the U.S.
                            Government could not interfere with its citizens’ rights to freedom of
                            speech and peaceful assembly. A copy is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>