<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-04-08T20:49:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-04-08T20:49:00-05:00" n="358" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d358">
                        <head>358. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Germany</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d358fn1">Source: Department of State: Central
                                Files, 399.731/4–858. Confidential; Priority. Drafted and approved
                                by <persName corresp="#p_PJHJ1">Pender</persName> who signed for
                                Dulles and cleared with <persName corresp="#p_LWW1">Looney</persName>, <gloss target="#t_UNP1">UNP</gloss>, and
                                    <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>. Also sent to Brussels,
                                Lisbon, Luxembourg, Madrid, Paris, Rome, and The Hague, and repeated
                                to nine other Western European capitals.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-04-08T20:49:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">April 8,
                                        1958—8:49 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>2639. Law of Sea. US has decided vigorously support Canadian compromise
                            as only proposal with realistic chance averting result of 12-mile
                            territorial sea. Since such latter result would affect surface and air
                            navigation as well as fishing it would be economically harsher on
                            countries of action addressees than would Canadian proposal and, in
                            addition, would seriously impair defense capabilities US and free world.
                            (Canadian formula would preserve three-mile territorial sea but would
                            add 9-mile contiguous zone wherein coastal state would have full control
                            over fishing. Retention three-mile territorial sea essential for US to
                            carry out most effectively its burden defense responsibilities free
                            world.) Practically all states pressing for extension territorial sea
                            (except Soviet and Arab blocs) doing so to control adjacent resources.
                            It appears they have good chance achieving at least 12 miles that
                            purpose by one means or another.</p>
                        <p>Canadian proposal had begun make headway with that group and others when
                            UK announced its six-mile compromise. As we see it <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> compromise will not attract pivotal group
                            and can only split forces who must pull together if 12-mile territorial
                            sea is to be averted.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal likely encourage those willing
                            to settle for Canadian formula to hold out for more. Anticipate move to
                            blend Canadian and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposals so as to
                            come out with six-mile territorial sea plus six-mile fishery zone.</p>
                        <p>Conference breakup in present temper undesirable since in such event very
                            likely large number states would afterwards act unilaterally in way
                            perhaps at least as seriously jeopardizing our interests as Conference
                            adoption 12-mile territorial sea. E.g., <gloss target="#t_FONMIN1">FonMin</gloss> Iceland recently announced whatever outcome
                            Conference Iceland will extend its fishery limits.</p>
                        <p>Acceptance Canadian formula is least damaging course; offers only
                            realistic hope Conference agreement which necessary avoid wholesale
                            unilateral extensions.</p>
                        <p>US fully understands undesirable economic impact Canadian proposal
                            particularly on those who have historically fished certain areas since
                            US itself has similar problems off Canada and Latin America. US <pb facs="0713" n="683" xml:id="pg_683"/> hopeful suitable arrangements
                            can be worked out since states such as Canada, Ireland and Denmark have
                            at Geneva confidentially indicated some willingness discuss measures to
                            mitigate economic effects on fishing states. Believe something
                            constructive can be achieved this respect provided states concerned
                            avoid public emotional campaign. US must endeavor resolve problem
                            satisfactorily through some technique in order meet needs US
                            fishermen.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, Canadian proposal needs strong support in order avert result
                            with graver economic and security consequences.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName>Dulles</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>