<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>369. Telegram From the Delegation to the to the Conference on the Law of the
                    Sea to the to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1958-60v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1958-04-21T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1958-04-21T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="recGPO6TEVZ9esQhG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general">Fishing rights</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recmnRTtwUBtjR3ea" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="rece2kzYOqajIos1G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95000558"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="rec1ldfvh0EmC9PyC" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048697"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">High seas</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recR14DB6JC2udxCS" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="rec81deb9Nh3WRhWg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Commercial
                        aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="reczz1d8j78JEEJZg" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031551"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Continental shelf</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-04-21T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-04-21T05:00:00-05:00" n="369"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                <head>369. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation</gloss> to the <gloss
                        type="to">Conference on the Law of the Sea</gloss> to the <gloss type="to"
                        >Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d369fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 399.731/4–2158. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_NIACT1"
                        >Niact</gloss>. A retyped copy of this telegram was transmitted to President
                            <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> by Dulles on April 24.
                            (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 399.731/4–2458)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Geneva</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-04-21T11:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 21, 1958—11 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1209. Law of Sea. Conference clearly reveals work of well planned, well
                    organized, well disciplined blocs of <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and
                    its satellites led by Professor <persName corresp="#p_TGI1">Tunkin</persName> of
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> working with Afro-Asian bloc led by
                    Sen of India and following collapse of Sen’s leadership because of his
                    sponsorship of Canada, Mexico and Indian proposal (our 1165<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d369fn2">See <ref target="#d367fn2">footnote 2, Document
                        367</ref>.</note>) which shocked the conscience of the conference, by Loutfi
                    of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and Shukairi of Saudi Arabia and with
                    Latin American bloc led by <persName corresp="#p_GRA1">Garcia Robles</persName>
                    of Mexico. [<hi rend="italic">2 sentences (11 lines of source text) not
                        declassified</hi>] Cambodia in abstaining also indicated each member
                    Afro-Asian group in caucus had been forced publicly to state they would vote
                    with bloc and would not change vote even though they had previously indicated
                    they were favorable to US. Even Barnes of Liberia who abstained on our proposal
                    appeared badly intimidated by group tactics.</p>
                <p>Bhutto of Pakistan who stood staunchly with US indicated group was trying to
                    cause trouble for him at home.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GRA1">Garcia Robles</persName> in asking for a roll call
                    on our motion for priority (our 1207<note n="3" xml:id="d369fn3">Telegram 1207,
                        April 20, transmitted brief summaries of the three meetings of the First
                        Committee on April 19 in which all four proposals on the width of the
                        territorial sea lost. (Department of State, Central Files,
                        399.731/4–2058)</note>) said he did so in order that opinion in Latin
                    American countries might know where to place Latin American Delegates voting
                    with US in asking for priority over Indian-Mexican Resolution.</p>
                <p>Our support of Israel and situation in Gulf of Aqaba of course unites entire Arab
                    bloc against US on twelve-mile limit.</p>
                <p>This hardening of disciplined blocs who vote as unit on all questions without
                    regard to merits particular issue raises most serious questions for United
                    States policy. For even in countries where we have extended extensive aid and
                    have long record of friendship with US apparently deem themselves bound as newly
                    emancipated nations to vote solidly with their brethren against their former
                    masters and those associated with them.</p>
                <p>Speeches by French and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Delegates were for most
                    part received in sullen silence.</p>
                <p>Even though differing from US and not supporting US because of bloc voting or
                    because new nations without experience or little or no realization of the actual
                    meaning of the three-mile breadth of territorial <pb facs="0731" n="701"
                        xml:id="pg_701"/> sea or the duties involved in adopting and policing a
                    wider breadth of territorial sea, such newer nations favor the Indian-Mexican
                    three to twelve-mile proposal supported by the Soviet and Arabs as a bloc
                    because it gives such newer nations freedom to choose own breadth and regulation
                    up to twelve miles of customs immigration and fishing without restraint in
                    respect historic fishing rights and because seemed more consonant with their
                    dignity and sovereignty as new nations.</p>
                <p>Time and again the three-mile breadth was attacked and ridiculed not because it
                    was inherently wrong but because the particular state was not in existence when
                    it was adopted and they must have change labelled as progress.</p>
                <p>Even though the unilateral extension to twelve miles and the closing of bays by
                    the Soviet deprived millions of the right to free navigation and fishing it was
                    regarded nevertheless as progress because it cut down the area formerly freely
                    available to the large maritime powers who are deemed to be wholly selfish in
                    wanting to come within three miles of any coast or to fish up to that distance
                    and overfly high seas within that distance without express permission.</p>
                <p>The ingenuity, ability, capital and markets of the older powers is resented and
                    the use of large mother ships off coastal waters is frequently denounced as
                    taking the bread out of the mouths of local coastal fishermen operating out of
                    port on a small ship—on one day basis.</p>
                <p>Freedom of the high seas instead of a common heritage is regarded as a legal
                    fiction invented by the maritime powers or their lawyers in order to rob the
                    populations of the newly created nations who, since there is no more land, wish
                    to annex the high seas as their lawful right and who is to say to them nay
                    except the greedy maritime powers.</p>
                <p>It is readily apparent that a new social revolution is bursting forth and
                    burgeoning among the peoples of the newly created states who will insist on
                    re-examining all laws, customs and mores adopted by older civilizations before
                    their birth as a nation and who now proclaim whatever is new is better than the
                    old.</p>
                <p>In other words—move over pleasantly or else.</p>
                <p>In my judgment the implication of this moving social revolution of new
                    nationalities must be studied with the utmost seriousness and concern and every
                    effort made to understand it. For with bloc voting, constructive and imaginative
                    proposals, supposedly persuasive speeches and ideas and the sacrifice of
                    positions vital to US may not essentially change the voting results. Indeed the
                    very positions may be ridiculed and lampooned.</p>
                <p>Indeed in this conference quite apart from the ability of individual experts all
                    positions are alloted on a bloc basis or five major power basis which puts US
                    into the category of “has beens” since certain <pb facs="0732" n="702"
                        xml:id="pg_702"/> positions in addition are allotted to the Eastern
                    Europeans and Western Europeans, Afro-Asians and Latin Americans but none to
                    North Americans.</p>
                <p>It is, I think, clear that if the Greek proposal for three-mile territorial limit
                    had come to a vote it would not have received over eight votes and the Swedish
                    proposal for a straight six-mile territorial sea while not entirely conclusive
                    received a maximum of sixteen votes.</p>
                <p>Although our proposal with its reservation of historic fishing rights was not
                    satisfactory to new nations who wanted at least 12 miles for an unrestricted
                    territorial sea for security, fiscal, immigration, fishing and other reasons it
                    was praised by many countries who, even though not favoring it, recognized it as
                    a creative, bold and imaginative attempt to reach a solution.</p>
                <p>Even though our proposal failed to receive a majority due to the defection of the
                    Philippines, Korea and Liberia, El Salvador and Costa Rica, the failure to be
                    present of San Marino and Laos, and abstention of Sweden we were praised for
                    making it and practically every speaker praised the United States for its
                    constructive, helpful and conciliatory attitude in trying to make the conference
                    a success.</p>
                <p>This illustrates, I believe, the need for US not to be too negative or stand pat
                    in our approaches but to be thinking constantly of new and challenging ways to
                    meet what will become an increasingly difficult problem.</p>
                <p>The Soviet Union made no concessions here whatsoever. They operated almost
                    entirely behind the scenes in blocs or through their very effective associates
                        [<hi rend="italic">16 words not declassified</hi>].</p>
                <p>But they certainly can’t claim any moral leadership in the public conference and
                    so far the conference certainly has not enhanced their prestige.</p>
                <p>The Indians and Mexicans will certainly press in plenary for a two-thirds vote
                    for their 3- to 12-mile flexible territorial sea and the Canadians will press
                    hard for six miles territorial sea and six unrestricted fishing zone or twelve
                    miles unrestricted fishing zone overall. The proposal has its attractions. Our
                    historic rights has its liabilities.</p>
                <p>We have clearly stated we are for three miles and have made a forward looking,
                    imaginative proposal for six and six restricted for which leadership we have
                    been commended but now we are asked to go further.</p>
                <p>Sir Claude Corea of Ceylon asked today for our further or new position and I
                    stated we had already gone very far. I recommend we listen but continue to press
                    for our proposal and that we make no further offers of compromise and that we do
                    not accept the Canadian proposal of six and six unrestricted. The <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Delegation agrees.</p>
                <pb facs="0733" n="703" xml:id="pg_703"/>
                <p>The Canadian proposal means a tremendous loss to our fishermen and constitutes a
                    great detriment to our <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">merchant</persName> fleet and
                    commercial aircraft as well as to defense and I doubt if public opinion would
                    sustain it or further concessions. The Canadian attitude will undoubtedly hurt
                    the extension of the reciprocal trade act or lead to tariff imposition on
                    Canadian products which should be pointed out in Ottawa.</p>
                <p>So I recommend we continue to press for our reasonable position and continue to
                    appear patient and constructive but that we not yield further in order to get
                    agreement at this conference unless you believe even further concessions are in
                    order.</p>
                <p>At present, the failure of the conference cannot be laid at our door. We have
                    united our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies and aside from effect of
                    our proposal on Japan and Iceland, which is not remediable and the completely
                    selfish attitude of Canada which is unfortunate in our over-all relations we
                    have been able to accomplish a great deal of constructive work on fisheries and
                    the Continental Shelf with Latin Americans and others.</p>
                <p>We might, of course, have picked up certain Latin American votes by eliminating
                    all reference to arbitration; or we might have attracted the vote of some of the
                    newer nations if we had provided for the establishment of a base period on the
                    percentage of fish caught by pounds or dollars; but the disruption of fishing
                    fleets and gear during World War II and the multiplication of new nations not in
                    existence in 1946–1950 and the difficulty of putting a ceiling on future
                    development of larger ships, scientific development of fisheries, greater
                    investment of capital and ideas, particular geographical zones, types of fish,
                    exclusion of the products of the Continental Shelf, etc. Identifying the
                    particular nations to whom the right accrued, etc. by a too rigid base period
                    expressed in either tons, dollars or percentages might also have lost the votes
                    of other nations and is too complicated to work out in remaining time.</p>
                <p>Ecuador, for example, wanted historic rights to terminate after five years and
                    Argentina wanted them established only by a prescriptive period under civil law
                    which might have given the Japanese rights existing before World War II and
                    would be difficult to prove.</p>
                <p>The Swedes have been excluded from fishing in the Baltic by the Soviet and so
                    were the Japanese by the establishment of the MacArthur line by <gloss
                        target="#t_SCAP1">SCAP</gloss> but if we modify “regularly” by force majeure
                    we open Pandora’s box.</p>
                <p>In future conference believe to maximum extent possible we should attempt iron
                    out all differences of maritime powers in advance and not permit foreign office
                    to advise abstention or negative votes on really important issues because of
                    much less important matters pending between Department. We are only participant
                    here who is not a <pb facs="0734" n="704" xml:id="pg_704"/> member of a bloc
                    having group information on meetings. Time and time again our closest friends
                    vote against us or fail to support us. As bloc voting increases we must do
                    everything possible to avoid this.</p>
                <p>If conference postponed for only short period believe issues may harden and blocs
                    may well gain votes if time is not used to straighten out difficult issues. On
                    many of them we don’t appear to have reliable and up to date information and
                    trade association information often appears exaggerated or possible losses
                    stated at maximum.</p>
                <p>Will continue explore situation most sympathetically but am saying we have put
                    forward our very best proposition and we have no intention of bettering it and
                    ball is now in field of twelve-mile extremists.</p>
                <p>Expect continued tough in fighting on Articles 3 and 66 and strong attack our
                    position in plenary.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
