<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-04-27T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-04-27T20:00:00-05:00" n="429" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d429">
                        <head>429. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Delegation to the Conference
                                on the Law of the Sea</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d429fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 399.731/4–2860. Confidential.
                                Repeated to Tehran.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-04-28T02:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">April 28,
                                        1960—2 a.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1887. Attention: Secretary. Law of Sea. Would like to express
                            appreciation of wonderful backing received your Department and of
                            magnificent cooperation of Embassies and Ambassadors. Fully realize
                            enormous burden hurry-up calls from conference such as this place on
                            Embassies which have other important matters between countries to
                            negotiate.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely sorry wording we finally worked out and hoped would satisfy
                            Philippines could not bring them from an abstention to a “yes” vote,
                            which would of course have carried the conference as we only lost by one
                            vote.</p>
                        <pb facs="0838" n="808" xml:id="pg_808"/>
                        <p>In Committee of the Whole Argentina had presented an amendment to joint
                            U.S.-Canadian proposal that coastal state had absolute preferential
                            rights in coastal waters beyond twelve miles, which failed to carry with
                            Soviet bloc abstaining.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_TGI1">Tunkin</persName> (<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>) then went to Pablo Pardo (Argentina) and stated that
                            if Argentine amendment introduced in plenary Soviets and Arabs would
                            support. Since many states had instructions to vote for such
                            preferential rights and fishing interests were against, such an
                            amendment might have crippled our proposal. Consequently called meeting
                            several Latin American Ambassadors and worked out what subsequently
                            became Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay proposal, or L.12 in plenary, that commission
                            set up by Article 9 of Fishing Convention of 1958 would have
                            jurisdiction to pass on coastal states preferential claims beyond twelve
                            miles after hearing views fishing states involved, to which Argentina,
                            Chile and Guatemala pledged support and Ecuador and El Salvador pledged
                            abstention. Placing Cuba’s name as sponsor on this and by treating it as
                            an amendment to other report of the Committee of the Whole rather than
                            as an amendment to the U.S.-Canadian proposal. Garcia Amador (Cuba) was
                            able to stay as sponsor and to vote “yes” on L.4 (second) in plenary,
                            being U.S.-Canadian proposal as reported by Committee of the Whole as
                            amended in plenary by Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay proposal [<hi rend="italic">4
                                lines of source text not declassified</hi>]. After working out terms
                            of Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay proposal <persName corresp="#p_CJ6">Correa</persName> (Ecuador) and Ponce-Carbo, Under Secretary
                            Ecuadorian Foreign Office then insisted on further amendment that if
                            coastal state during base period of five years, in our proposal 1953–58,
                            had passed its own internal law extending its territorial sea beyond six
                            miles then fishing states involved would have to agree they acquired no
                            historical rights to outer six mile zone under such circumstance. When
                            fishing states refused such amendment, I undertook write letter that
                            U.S. would not as executive member take steps to prove any practice of
                            fishing by American vessels in outer six mile zone Ecuadorian waters in
                            base period and that consequently Paragraph 3 U.S.-Canadian proposal not
                            apply as between Ecuador and U.S.A. Immediately drafted agreement to
                            this effect and submitted to Correa and Ponce Carbo and shook hands on
                            basis Ecuador would abstain.<note n="2" xml:id="d429fn2">Text of this
                                agreement was transmitted in telegram 1868 from Geneva, April 28.
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.)</note> Two days later Ponce Carbo
                            (Ecuador) demanded I waive, release and quit claim to Ecuador all claims
                            U.S. Government and American nationals against Ecuador by virtue
                            Ecuadorian enforcement of its 200-mile territorial sea. Explained
                            Congress alone could do this and had no authority sign such an agreement
                            and would be fraudulent if I did. Then delegated Wainhouse to work this
                            matter out finally and up to 1 a.m. Tuesday, <pb facs="0839" n="809" xml:id="pg_809"/> April 26 Ecuadorians were still contending for
                            this clause. At 1:15 a.m. politely but firmly told them we could not
                            grant. At 10:30 a.m. while in Assembly Hall after plenary voting session
                            called to order by Prince <persName corresp="#p_WWKNBP1">Wan</persName>,
                            Correa (Ecuador) sent me note “must see in corridor,” where he and
                            Ambassador Trujillo and Ponce Carbo insisted I sign document with
                            above-mentioned release in it immediately or Ecuador would vote “no.” As
                            I was explaining why this could not be done received message from Prince
                            Wan he was holding up voting because I was not in my seat. Thereupon
                            left to re-enter Assembly Hall. Upon leaving, saw Correa summon
                            Melo-Lecaros (Chile) shake hands with him and say “it is a deal.”
                            Whereupon as I resumed seat in Assembly, Melo-Lecaros approached me and
                            said that although he had agreed vote “yes,” he had just received
                            instruction President Alessandri (Chile) to vote “no” and could not
                            change them.</p>
                        <p>After Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay proposal, L.12 plenary, received two-thirds
                            vote with Paragraph 5 of proposed amended U.S.-Canadian proposal L.11 in
                            plenary having been substituted for Paragraph 1 of Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay
                            proposal in order to meet insistence of Italians and Koreans they had to
                            have Paragraph 5 in order to vote “yes.” Japan then told us instructions
                            were for her to abstain on U.S.-Canadian proposal as amended by
                            Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay proposal because her fishing interests strongly
                            objected to commission created Paragraph 9 Fishing Convention 1958
                            having jurisdiction to grant preferential rights coastal state beyond
                            twelve miles. Consequently on voting on our proposal as amended Ecuador
                            and Chile voted “no” and Japan abstained increasing “no” voting by two
                            and reducing “yes” vote by one.</p>
                        <p>Burma despite strenuous Commonwealth efforts, voted “no” and Guinea,
                            despite suggestion just before voting might abstain.</p>
                        <p>India voted “no” because Sen had received cable from <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Krishna Menon</persName>, Minister of War,
                            instructing him to vote “no” unless we accepted prior authorization
                            passage of warships in entire twelve-mile zone and prohibition against
                            assembling or maneuvering of war vessels in such zone, Prime Minister
                            Nehru having ignored personal message from Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_MHS2">Macmillan</persName> and President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> received during Chou En Lai
                            visit New Delhi.</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">Paragraph (17 words of source text) not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>Melo-Lecaros (Chile) subsequently insisted Chile could not get written
                            release of 1952 agreement with Peru and that [<hi rend="italic">36 words
                                not declassified</hi>] this “no” vote was actually on explicit
                            instructions from President Alessandri.</p>
                        <pb facs="0840" n="810" xml:id="pg_810"/>
                        <p>Wish to emphasize significance at conference of being able to break Arab
                            bloc despite solemn Arab League agreements vote as unit and should
                            especially commend Tunisia and Jordan for voting “yes” and Lebanon for
                            abstaining or more accurately for absenting themselves from voting due
                            to threats.</p>
                        <p>Also consider significant Ethiopia and Ghana voted “yes”.</p>
                        <p>Impossible to describe third degree methods, threats of personal
                            violence, threats of ostracism on returning to their own country and
                            other methods [<hi rend="italic">9 words not declassified</hi>] used in
                            effort not to get them to vote “yes” and believe threats of personal
                            violence on his return Lebanon had effect on Fattal’s absenting himself
                            entirely. Think special efforts should be made to thank countries voting
                            “yes” for their steadfastness and where Presidential messages previously
                            sent Presidential appreciation should be expressed.</p>
                        <p>Ambassador Sohn, Kim and Han (Korea) very helpful and steadfast
                            throughout and would appreciate McConaughy be advised at Seoul.</p>
                        <p>In State Department and Navy announcements and in State Department
                            bulletins believe emphasis should be laid on fact international law is
                            what majority of countries say it is and that this constituted a vote of
                            54 with 28 against and 5 abstentions for six miles as compared to vote
                            of 39 in 1958 for 12 miles. In 1960 twelve miles were only able to
                            muster 31.</p>
                        <p>Guinea representative advised that when they chose independence from
                            French union within 48 hours all French officials and entire
                            governmental records withdrawn from country and credits closed.
                            Consequently there is great bitterness against France and because of
                            Algerian war and possible incursion of French vessels into Tunisian or
                            Libyan waters and explosion second French bomb there is a source of
                            great feeling against France.</p>
                        <p>Sharpeville incident in Union of South Africa shortly after conference
                            began had profound effect upon Africans forcing Union of South Africa
                            delegate to withdraw from speaking and explosion of second French bomb
                            in Sahara almost caused similar incidents against France, and boycotting
                            of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> ship <hi rend="italic">Cleopatra</hi> in New York harbor caused tensions of that
                            delegation to arise.</p>
                        <p>Since we started without agreement with Canada and with their proposal
                            providing for no phase-out and we were able to table joint proposal with
                            ten-year phase-out and did not have to grant either authorization or
                            notification to warships either in inner six or outer six mile zone and
                            we in statement made clear we only voted for Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay
                            proposal giving Commission under Article 9 fishing convention authority
                            pass on coastal state’s preferential claims beyond twelve miles as means
                            to obtaining agreement on breadth territorial sea and fishing zone and
                            that we did not stand for such <pb facs="0841" n="811" xml:id="pg_811"/>
                            proposal standing alone and also explained we would adhere three mile
                            limit despite failure of conference by one vote on the whole believe we
                            emerge from conference relatively unscathed and with our datas
                            considerably advanced.</p>
                        <p>In forthcoming months or years <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>,
                            Saudi Arabia and Mexico will of course do everything possible promote 12
                            mile territorial sea and emergence of new members of United Nations will
                            make solution this problem more difficult as months go by.</p>
                        <p>Witman did yeoman work with Ethiopia, Ghana and Tunisia and was untiring
                            in his efforts to convince Guinea and Libya, and believe would be
                            helpful to have him write memorandum on how we can work with African
                            States and what should be done to improve our working relations.</p>
                        <p>Since uncommitted nations may regard this as a military and diplomatic
                            defeat by the Soviet Union of the US, every effort should be taken to
                            point out nations such as Japan, Philippines and India who did not
                            support us the fundamental importance of a narrow territorial sea
                            although naval exposition with charts on this question at Delhi
                            undoubtedly contributed to <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Krishna
                                Menon</persName>’s instructions as Minister of War though <persName corresp="#p_MVKK1">Menon</persName> insisted that their demand on
                            authorization passage warships was at insistence Asian-African
                            nations.</p>
                        <p>Baig (Pakistan) informs me all of Sen’s (India) efforts on this score
                            here were received coldly.</p>
                        <p>Ago (Italy), Quiroga (Spain) and Bailey (Australia) have suggested 54
                            nations would themselves sign convention or multilateral treaty in form
                            present text US-Canadian proposal as amended by Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay
                            proposal, deposit it in United Nations and ask all others to join.
                            Bailey (Australia) also wants to promote this idea at meeting of
                            Commonwealth Prime Ministers in London next week and asked me to have
                            Secretary of State give matter his careful attention.</p>
                        <p>Throughout conference in effort to avoid embarrassing noncommitted
                            nations, in all my speeches, talks and discussions, I have carefully
                            refrained from talking defense matters, referring to Russian submarines
                            or to have provided enemy submarines by wider territorial sea in time of
                            war and many uncommitted nations have complimented us on this
                            attitude.</p>
                        <p>On other hand <persName corresp="#p_SA12">Shukairy</persName> (Saudi
                            Arabia) and <persName corresp="#p_GRA1">Garcia Robles</persName>
                            (Mexico) in close and daily conferences <persName corresp="#p_TGI1">Tunkin</persName> (<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>) and
                            Shukairy as representative Saudi Arabia, where we have air force base,
                            continued repeated bitter attacks on USA and peaceful aims of <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> gloated over our defeat and
                            filibustered against further action. This may have repercussions in
                            capitals of uncommitted countries and Embassy Jidda may wish consider
                            mentioning Saudi Arabian Prime Minister that [<hi rend="italic">14 words
                                not declassified</hi>] sale of their oil wealth is dependent on
                            continued <pb facs="0842" n="812" xml:id="pg_812"/> good economies in
                            USA and Western Europe and narrow territorial sea essential to
                            transportation. [<hi rend="italic">1 sentence (27 words) not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>These parliamentary tactics of delay, confusion and distortion are
                            exceedingly confusing and disturbing to small uncommitted nations. They
                            are I believe a part of much larger Soviet tactics to permit no
                            constructive agreement on any subject to lull the world into a false
                            sense security by a constant Pollyannaish manner of sweetness and light,
                            to attack the capitalistic countries as war mongers and profiteers and
                            to lead the world up the garden path of a do-nothing summit and hence
                            build up a sense of discouragement at the inability of the free world’s
                            leaders to come to grips with problems both domestic and foreign so
                            people will complain about the burden of taxation and armaments.</p>
                        <p>Bailey (Australia) is convinced impossible to work out legal agreements
                            at <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> conference and strongly urges
                            signing convention among Commonwealth countries, Scandinavian countries,
                            USA, Latin America, Western European and such Asian and African
                            countries as wish to join. <persName corresp="#p_DGA2">Drew</persName>
                            (Canada) agrees. [<hi rend="italic">2 sentences (4 lines of source text)
                                not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>Would like to compliment entire staff for loyal, devoted unflagging work
                            day and night and for a wonderful spirit of cooperation. Consulate and
                            Moore and Owsley most helpful and considerate. All liaison officers did
                            splendid job. Please thank Admiral <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Burke</persName> for work of Admiral <persName corresp="#p_CVAOS1">Colclough</persName> and Captains Hearn and Hardy and Commander
                            Hoag and for service of Consulate Marines. Please thank Seaton and
                            Interior for splendid cooperation and work of Suomela, <persName corresp="#p_TWM1">Terry</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_TFE1">Taylor</persName> and Fishery advisers. They with <persName corresp="#p_HWC4">Herrington</persName> attended all meetings, were
                            freely and constantly consulted and gave unstintingly of their time.
                            They were fully consulted in working out Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay proposal
                            and though they did not approve, they thoroughly understood my reasons
                            and strategy. In conference of 88 countries with things moving and
                            breaking fast and where instantaneous decisions must be made, it is not
                            always possible to keep everyone advised throughout every hour of the
                            day and of necessity much of work has to be done in cooperation Western
                            Europe, Afro-Asians, and Latin American groups who will only talk to
                            head of delegation. They all assure me of their complete satisfaction
                            with consultation and with spirit of cooperation. <persName corresp="#p_HWC4">Herrington</persName>, as usual, turned in an
                            indefatigable, fine performance and naturally must fight hard and long
                            for fishing rights. <persName corresp="#p_RAL1">Richards</persName> made
                            splendid vice chairman. Wainhouse, <persName corresp="#p_YRT1">Yingling</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WEE1">Wright</persName>
                            and <persName corresp="#p_KEL1">Kerley</persName> were most helpful.
                            This is a technical difficult and exceptionally complicated subject
                            requiring the constant conjuring up of new solutions, careful drafting
                            and constant examination of implications of other proposals both
                            legally, economically and politically on <pb facs="0843" n="813" xml:id="pg_813"/> all countries together with constant study of
                            conference rules and possible parliamentary maneuvering, which may be of
                            more immediate importance than substance. Recommend careful course in
                            this for all liaison officers as well as careful exposé voting
                            technique, such as obtaining adoption of proposals by wide abstentions
                            as in the case of Iceland’s first proposal in committee. Much impressed
                            by liaison work of Clough, <persName corresp="#p_HIT1">King</persName>,
                            Owsley, Roberts and Witman. Doctor Pearcy and Miss Lucas very
                            helpful.</p>
                        <p>Regret necessity of voting against Iceland’s proposal on special fishing
                            rights and amendment taking away historical rights from our proposal and
                            were it not for necessity obtaining Dr. Garcia Amador’s “yes” vote on
                            committee proposal and his joint sponsorship of Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay
                            proposal as amendment to committee report would have moved to consider
                            committee report last, in which event in case adoption Brazil, Cuba,
                            Uruguay proposal there would have been no necessity voting on Icelandic
                            special rights proposal.</p>
                        <p>Peru withdrew its proposal L.5 and I urged Dr. Garcia Amador to withdraw
                            L.6, to which he agreed but after failure committee report as amended by
                            Brazil-Cuba-Uruguay amendment he insisted on having L.6 voted on and we
                            led in having it defeated for which <persName corresp="#p_TGI1">Tunkin</persName> (<gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>) taunted
                            him.</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">Paragraph (5 lines of source text) not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p>Constantly pressed <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> for Icelandic
                            solution and if this had occurred before conference would have had
                            Icelandic vote and would have avoided conference sympathy for small
                            nation’s problems. Icelandic Delegation hurt but they voted throughout
                            with <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> despite <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> commitments. Andersen, Icelandic
                            Ambassador, believed <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proposal good but
                            officials would not accept and run risk home displeasure.</p>
                        <p>Support of fishery interests for new proposals in all countries is slow,
                            sullen, grudging and generally too late for effective conference action
                            and this hampered <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, Japan, France,
                            Belgium and Norway as well as ourselves.</p>
                        <p>Correa (Ecuador) conferred his country’s highest medal on <persName corresp="#p_GRA1">Garcia Robles</persName> (Mexico) while here.
                            Latter skilled, tricky and smart parliamentarian with thorough knowledge
                            of all conference’s rules, loopholes and devices.</p>
                        <p>Wiener of <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> very helpful
                            throughout.</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">Paragraph (6 lines of source text) not
                                declassified</hi>]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>