<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-03-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-03-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="69" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                        <head>69. Letter From Acting Secretary of State <persName type="from">Herter</persName> to Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LJSB1" type="to">Lloyd</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d69fn1">Source: Department of State, Presidential Correspondence: Lot 66 D
                                204. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_NMH2">Newlin</persName> on March 3.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-03-11"><hi rend="italic">March 11,
                                1959</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: Thank you for your letter
                            of February 23 in which you commented on the five-step course of action
                            on Hungary suggested in Secretary Dulles’ February 2 letter to you.<note n="2" xml:id="d69fn2"><persName corresp="#p_LJSB1">Lloyd</persName>’s letter is <ref target="#d66">Document 66</ref>.
                                Dulles’ letter is <ref target="#d61">Document 61</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>I am glad to see that we agree on the necessity for not permitting the
                            Hungarian issue to die through inaction. However, we have a somewhat
                            different view of <persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir Leslie</persName>’s
                            mandate and the extent to which the Soviets and the Hungarians are
                            interpreting our failure to take stronger action at the last General
                            Assembly as an indication of weakness. Concerning the latter, it appears
                            to me that <persName corresp="#p_ZVA1">Zorin</persName>’s statement
                            hailing the reduced majority for the resolution on Hungary as a
                                “victory”,<note n="3" xml:id="d69fn3"><persName corresp="#p_ZVA1">Zorin</persName>’s statement has not been identified.</note>
                            the offensive Hungarian note of January 27 which the American Legation
                            in Budapest was instructed to return,<note n="4" xml:id="d69fn4">Telegram 215 from Budapest, January 29, transmitted the text of a
                                January 27 note from the Hungarian Government which termed relations
                                between the United States and Hungary “abnormal and absurd” and
                                accused the United States of pursuing a “consistently hostile
                                policy” toward Hungary. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                611.64/1–2959) Telegram 175 to Budapest, January 30, instructed the
                                Legation to return the note to the Hungarian Foreign Office and to
                                state that its tone belied the Hungarian Government’s assertion that
                                it wished to establish normal relations with the United States. (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 611.64/2–2959) Telegram 217 from
                                Budapest, January 31, informed the Department of State that the note
                                had been returned. (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>.,
                                611.64/1–3159)</note> and the recent threatening complaints to the
                            United Kingdom, French, and Italian Missions in Budapest regarding the
                            policies of their respective Governments on Hungary,<note n="5" xml:id="d69fn5">Despatch 466 from Budapest, February 20, transmitted
                                a copy of the Hungarian note to the British Legation. (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 310.364/2–2059) Despatch 484 from
                                Budapest, February 27, reported that the Legation had seen the
                                Hungarian notes to the French and Italian Legations and compared
                                their texts to the note the British Legation had received. (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 310.364/2–2759)</note> are all
                            indicative of aggressive attitudes which should not be encouraged by
                            seeking to restrict the scope of <persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir Leslie
                                Munro</persName>’s activities.</p>
                        <p>We consider <persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir Leslie</persName>’s mandate
                            sufficiently broad to enable him to do as much or as little as he sees
                            fit. He is certainly more than a rapporteur, since this title was
                            deliberately rejected in favor of that of “Agent” at the time the
                            resolution on Hungary was drafted in New York. When other co-sponsors
                            objected to the connotations surrounding the word “Agent”, the language
                            finally decided upon was “Decides <pb facs="0148" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/> to appoint <persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir Leslie
                                Munro</persName> to represent the United Nations for the purpose of
                            reporting to Member states or to the General Assembly on significant
                            developments relating to the implementation of the resolutions of the
                            General Assembly on Hungary.” Although the resolution does not require
                            him to approach the Soviet and Hungarian authorities or call upon the
                            Communist regimes concerned to cooperate with him, he is not limited to
                            the narrow functions of a rapporteur. The reference to implementation of
                            the Assembly’s resolutions makes this abundantly clear.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir Leslie</persName> himself suggested that
                            he might begin his activities with informal behind-the-scences
                            approaches to the Soviets and the Hungarians. I believe that, although
                            the prospects of success are dim indeed, <persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir
                                Leslie</persName> should not be discouraged from his proposed
                            private initiatives. Communist charges of provocation, if made, would
                            probably only serve further to advertise Soviet and Hungarian
                            intransigence, and would be unlikely to affect adversely our own
                            objectives with respect to Hungary. Moreover, I am convinced that
                                <persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir Leslie Munro</persName>, in any
                            case, should be encouraged to make eventual public approaches to the
                            Soviets and the Hungarians before he prepares his report. I hope upon
                            further consideration this course will commend itself to you.</p>
                        <p>We have told <persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir Leslie Munro</persName> that
                            we hope he will keep us informed during his public and private efforts,
                            as well as during the preparation of his report. Such close coordination
                            should be mutually valuable.</p>
                        <p>In the event <persName corresp="#p_MSL3">Sir Leslie</persName>’s efforts
                            fail, I continue to believe that we must then consider what further
                            action should be sought on Hungary in the United Nations. In the light
                            of your letter of February 23 and after further consideration here in
                            the Department of State, I agree that we should postpone consideration
                            of moves to expel Hungary through action in the Security Council or to
                            press for rejection of Hungarian credentials at the next General
                            Assembly. The situation mentioned in your letter, i.e., the possibility
                            that the Hungarian regime might commit flagrant future outrages, had
                            also occurred to me and is a strong argument for keeping in reserve
                            drastic action in the Security Council and the General Assembly on
                            Hungary. Meanwhile, I suggest we continue to maintain close consultation
                            on the subject of Hungary and carefully watch developments in that
                            country.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong">Christian A. Herter<note n="6" xml:id="d69fn6">Printed from a copy that bears this stamped
                                        signature.</note></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>