<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-07-14T20:02:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-07-14T20:02:00-05:00" n="81" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d81">
                        <head>81. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Mission at the United Nations</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d81fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 320/7–1459. Confidential. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_HVF1">Hartley</persName> on July 7; cleared by
                                Green, <persName corresp="#p_NWT1">Nunley</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_MGN1">Monsma</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BRE3">Bacon</persName>; and approved by <persName corresp="#p_WWNJ1">Walmsley</persName> who signed for <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-07-14T21:02:00-04:00"><hi rend="italic">July 14,
                                        1959—9:02 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>27. Re: 15th <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> Presidency. <gloss target="#t_DEPT1">Dept</gloss> shares your concern re apparent
                            stimulus being given <persName corresp="#p_NJ4">Nosek</persName>
                            candidacy for presidency 15th <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>. Also
                            agrees we must seek avoid “irresistible trend” in favor <persName corresp="#p_NJ4">Nosek</persName> (<gloss target="#t_URTEL1">urtel</gloss> 1179<note n="2" xml:id="d81fn2"><ref target="#d78">Document 78</ref>.</note>). At same time, US should not be in
                            position stimulating <persName corresp="#p_BFH1">Boland</persName>
                            candidacy until clear he preferred choice West Europeans and clear
                            satisfactory assurance re <gloss target="#t_CHI1">Chi</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_REP1">Rep</gloss> can be obtained. US should also
                            avoid formal commitment this matter so far in advance in order not
                            establish awkward precedent and retain for US as much latitude as
                            possible in circumstances. Mission should therefore seek early
                            opportunity discuss <persName corresp="#p_NJ4">Nosek</persName>
                            candidacy with <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and French delegations
                            in first instance as follows:</p>
                        <p>1) We recognize with <gloss target="#t_LA1">LA</gloss> President this
                            year it European turn to have <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>
                            presidency next year.</p>
                        <p>2) We assume they and other friendly European members agree with us on
                            undesirability at this time of Soviet-bloc president, whose election we
                            would anticipate having actively to oppose.</p>
                        <p>3) Open fight against Soviet-bloc candidacy if it has gained substantial
                            support likely affect unfavorably atmosphere whole <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> mission.</p>
                        <p>4) We hope therefore Western Europe can reach early agreement on
                            acceptable non-Communist candidate so as present united front and thus
                            discourage build-up Soviet-bloc candidacy.</p>
                        <pb facs="0173" n="143" xml:id="pg_143"/>
                        <p>5) Following our usual practice, we would give full weight West European
                            choice and would expect be able support it when taking our own position
                            on 15 <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> president. <persName corresp="#p_BFH1">Boland</persName> acceptable if West European
                            choice provided problem presented by Irish position on <gloss target="#t_CHI1">Chi</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_REP1">Rep</gloss> issue can be resolved, and we intend
                            ourselves indicate this Boland privately unless there serious
                            objections.</p>
                        <p>Mission should indicate <persName corresp="#p_BFH1">Boland</persName>
                            that our only difficulty respect his possible candidacy next year, which
                            we agree is European turn, is Irish failure support moratorium formula.
                            We hope he can persuade his Government modify its stand this question,
                            which so far as we can foresee would assure our support provided he West
                            European choice.<note n="3" xml:id="d81fn3">At this point in the source
                                text the following sentence was deleted before transmission: “We
                                would hope even be able support him if he West European choice on
                                basis his personal assurances that he would not be influenced by
                                Irish position on moratorium formula in his actions as presiding
                                officer.”</note></p>
                        <p>Mission should immediately make clear <gloss target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss>
                            and <persName corresp="#p_CAW1">Cordier</persName>, Soviet-bloc
                            candidate not acceptable US for President 15th <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> in present circumstances and also make points covered in
                            (3) and (4) above. Mission should point out:</p>
                        <p>1) election Soviet-bloc candidate to office such prominence as <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> presidency would give <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and its satellites aura
                            respectability and international prestige unwarranted by their present
                            conduct and might have seriously adverse effect on US opinion toward
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>;</p>
                        <p>2) quite aside any difficulties Soviet-bloc president could create at
                            regular <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss> session, opportunity presented
                            him for trouble-making by any Emergency Special Session could have most
                            serious consequences.<note n="4" xml:id="d81fn4"><persName corresp="#p_BJW2">Barco</persName> reported in telegram 194 from
                                    <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, August 14, that he had
                                not spoken with <persName corresp="#p_BFH1">Boland</persName>, who
                                was away from New York, but that <persName corresp="#p_BH10">Beeley</persName> had indicated the British would probably
                                support Boland and had already begun working quietly to develop his
                                candidacy. Roux of the French Mission noted U.S. opposition to a
                                General Assembly president from Eastern Europe and stated that Paris
                                had not reacted to Boland’s possible candidacy. <persName corresp="#p_HD3">Hammarskjöld</persName> stated he must remain
                                detached from the election of General Assembly officers, but
                                indicated that he felt personally that the United States should not
                                try to block an Eastern European presidency. <persName corresp="#p_BJW2">Barco</persName> observed that <persName corresp="#p_CAW1">Cordier</persName> would probably speak in
                                favor of an Eastern European president and, by virtue of his
                                position in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">U.N</gloss>. Secretariat,
                                would appear to be speaking for the Secretary-General. (Department
                                of State, Central Files, 320/8–1459)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName></hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>