<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>112. Memorandum From William J. Jorden of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d112</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">112</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-05-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-05-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-05-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="112"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d112">
                <head>112. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_JWJ_1">William J. Jorden</persName>
                    of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d112fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: In this memorandum, <persName
                                    corresp="#p_JWJ_1">Jorden</persName> informed <persName
                                    corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> of an assassination
                                threat against <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> and
                                examined the potential political crisis looming on the
                                horizon.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 776,
                                Country Files, Latin America, Chile, Vol. VII. Secret; Sensitive.
                                Sent for information.</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-05-18"
                        >May 18, 1972</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Threatened Assassination of <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                            >Allende</persName>; Political Crisis Looms in Chile</item>
                </list>
                <p>You should be aware of the following:</p>
                <p>We have a report that outbreaks of violence may occur in Chile beginning tomorrow
                    (May 19) culminating in an attempt to assassinate President <persName
                        corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> on Sunday (May 21). The
                    information—which comes from two sources, [<hi rend="italic">2 lines not
                        declassified</hi>]—is too detailed to be ignored. It may, of course, be
                    exaggerated. However, rumors of impending violence—and even civil war—have begun
                    to spread through Santiago.</p>
                <p>The plot is attributed to leaders of the Movement of the Revolutionary Left
                        (<gloss target="#t_MIR_1">MIR</gloss>), a group dedicated to revolutionary
                    violence. They are reportedly disillusioned with <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName> because of his failure to move Chile faster and farther
                    toward leftist totalitarian rule. They are opposed by the Communist Party of
                    Chile which supports <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> in his
                    policy of gradualism in building a socialist state. It is the Communists who
                    reportedly have disclosed the <gloss target="#t_MIR_1">MIR</gloss> plot to
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>.</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_MIR_1">MIR</gloss> plan appears to be: to foment serious
                    civil disturbances in southern Chile. This would draw significant elements of
                    the Army to the south and away from Santiago. Then, on Sunday May 21, when
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is scheduled to open the new
                    session of the Congress, the <gloss target="#t_MIR_1">MIR</gloss> would strike
                    in Santiago—with terror and murder and massive violence.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> has taken the threat with enough
                    seriousness to triple his own bodyguard. He is also reported to have put Chilean
                    Army units in the south on special alert. We also have a report that he has
                    called a special emergency session of leaders of Popular Unity (<gloss
                        target="#t_UP_1">UP</gloss>), the government coalition, to consider how to
                    deal with the problem.</p>
                <p>The Communists are said to have threatened to withdraw from the ruling coalition
                    unless <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> takes forceful action to
                    oppose the <gloss target="#t_MIR_1">MIR</gloss> promptly. The Communists are
                    reportedly demanding an immediate confrontation with MIR. They are also
                    insisting that <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> remove <pb
                        facs="0619" n="579" xml:id="pg_579"/> some 700 <gloss target="#t_MIR_1"
                        >MIR</gloss> members or sympathizers from government jobs. Our intelligence
                    sources indicate that <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is not the
                    only intended victim of attack. Apparently there may also be attempts made on
                    the lives of some Communist Party leaders and even some foreign diplomats
                    (especially Communists). The purpose of these actions is said to be to “prove”
                    that rightists are responsible for the violence. Once violence erupts, the
                        <gloss target="#t_MIR_1">MIR</gloss> would use the resulting confusion as a
                    pretext for revolution and violent take-over of authority.</p>
                <p>There is <hi rend="italic">no</hi> indication in any of the intelligence reports
                    of anything more than coincidence between the alleged plotting of violence in
                    Chile and President <persName corresp="#p_NRM_1">Nixon</persName>’s departure
                    for Moscow.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
