<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>47. Telegram From the Embassy in Chile to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve16</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d47</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">47</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-01-06T15:59:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-01-06T15:59:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recfIX2Uumy8inHEq" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85144526"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wages</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85074300"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Land reform</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077482"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Literacy</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recVY6Dxn96NsplUd" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97008889"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Law of the sea</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85032278"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88004886"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Journalist</term>
                    <term ref="recFzikmNCJDCCGBL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade union</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recy94pCDcRAr4voG" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003012251"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Freedom of expression</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-01-06T15:59:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-01-06T15:59:00-05:00" n="47"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d47">
                <head>47. Telegram From the Embassy in Chile to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d47fn1">
                        <p>
                            <seg type="summary">Summary: In this fourth of four related telegrams
                                titled “The Evident Becomes Obvious,” <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1"
                                    >Korry</persName> described <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                                    >Allende</persName>’s use of populist reforms to build support
                                amongst the majority of the Chilean people and the ways in which
                                    <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> was trying to
                                control the media and consolidate power in Chile. The Ambassador
                                concluded by highlighting the <gloss target="#t_UP_1">UP</gloss>
                                coalition’s desire to remain unified.</seg>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            <seg type="source">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                                    >RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1970–73, POL 2–2 Chile. Secret;
                                    <gloss target="#t_Limdis_1">Limdis</gloss>. Repeated to
                                Asunción, Bogotá, Bonn, Brasilia, Buenos Aires, Canberra, Caracas,
                                Guatemala, Kingston, La Paz, Lima, London, Madrid, Managua,
                                Melbourne, Mexico City, Montevideo, Ottawa, Panama, Paris, Port au
                                Prince, Port of Spain, Quito, Rio de Janeiro, Rome, San José, San
                                Salvador, Santo Domingo, Tegucigalpa, and <gloss
                                    target="#t_USCINCSO_1">USCINCSO</gloss>. Reference telegrams 43,
                                46, and 52, Parts I–III, are <ref target="#d44">Documents
                                    44</ref>–<ref target="#d46">46</ref>.</seg>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Santiago</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1971-01-06T20:59:00+00:00">January 6, 1971, 2059Z</date>.</dateline>
                <p>59. Subj: The Evident Becomes Obvious (Part IV of IV). Ref: Santiago’s 43, 46 and
                    52.</p>
                <p>1. By any objective measure, the actions of the <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName> govt please the majority of the Chilean people. Moreover
                    the majority of <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s actions will
                    benefit the mass. And “mass” is the key word for the Marxists.</p>
                <p>2. Although the Communist <persName corresp="#p_CLL_1">Corvalan</persName> can
                    state with chilling accuracy that this govt does not intend to be “reformist”
                    and does not intend merely to increase employment, effect redistribution and
                    augment production, <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is building
                    his irresistible momentum by such reforms. What political party can be opposed
                    to higher wages, price rollbacks, greater social security benefits and a massive
                    redistribution of income? What politician can argue against “land reform” that
                    will initially expropriate only the 3500 to 4000 farms that remain above the
                    maximum limit of 200 basic irrigated acres? For the mass of peasants with tiny
                    holdings, the word “cooperative” is not and should not be a discouraging
                    perspective despite the simultaneous use of “state farm”. <pb facs="0289"
                        n="249" xml:id="pg_249"/> In the interim <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName> has cancelled the land tax for all those with incomes of
                    less than some $3000. What is objectionable about reducing the cost of credit by
                    25 percent and promising to make it available to the small industrialist, to the
                    small farmer and to the cooperatives? What is more logical in a country of only
                    9,300,000 than to trim from eleven to three the number of auto companies? What
                    is more sensible than to create mass money supply so that domestic industries
                    will get a volume sufficient to lower real costs and so that the society as a
                    whole can concentrate on increasing output and boost its non-traditional
                    exports? Who would oppose a half liter of milk to every child daily, free school
                    books, free medicines, greater access to university and even “peoples courts”?
                    This last idea is justified as unclogging a court system overloaded with minor
                    cases that could easily be decided on a neighborhood level by representatives of
                    the people.</p>
                <p>3. The evident truth is that <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is
                    doing a great many things that most people would agree are good for Chile and he
                    is doing nothing that he did not say he would do prior to the election. He has
                    so far reneged on only one of his electoral planks—to leave the <gloss
                        target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>—and who would fault him for reversing that
                    pledge? He said he would wage class war against a small minority that had
                    inordinate power and wealth; they are his only domestic victims so far. He said
                    he would reduce Chile’s tremendous dependence on the US. He is fulfilling that
                    goal. Because the conservatives in this country are, and have been so deservedly
                    discredited and because the anti-Marxists threw away their numerical majority in
                    blind parochialism, the majority of the middle class in this unique land with
                    its 90 percent literacy and 75 percent urbanization is not at all perturbed by
                    what has occurred in the first two months of the <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName> govt. I might add that the majority of US press, itching
                    with a hairshirt of guilt, sticks to a birdseye view and flutters with joy.</p>
                <p>4. DeGaulle when he visited Chile several years ago described it as “the pilot
                    country for Latin America”. Regis Debray, a young revolutionary whose ideas
                    contributed to the May 1968 French upheaval that led to the downfall of
                    DeGaulle, said last night in his first press conference that the Chilean
                    revolution was a “colossal” event and that it would have repercussions in Europe
                    as well as Latin America. Debray is much intrigued by the novelty of the Marxist
                    methodology here and is delaying his departure to Cuba to learn more before he
                    begins applying his experience in other parts. For what it is worth, I think
                    both Frenchmen, like De Toqueville about the US, have an extraordinary
                    perspicacity.</p>
                <p>5. Two months of observing <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> has
                    reinforced my original appreciation. He is a dedicated socialist; he is a shrewd
                    politician; he is not a Communist; he is determined to serve six years, to
                    effect his pro<pb facs="0290" n="250" xml:id="pg_250"/>gram of establishing a
                    “Republic of the Workers”, to do it within a legal framework. He wants Chile to
                    be independent in the sense of not being dependent on a foreign country, be it
                    the Soviet Union or China. But he is unalterably and implaccably opposed to all
                    that US society represents today, starting with the profit motive and our
                    historic record in L.A. Except where the US will agree with the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, he will oppose us in every international
                    forum and in some cases such as the Law of the Sea, he will stand against both
                    the superpowers. So far, there is nothing exceptionable in the foregoing insofar
                    as other areas of the world are concerned. But he will cooperate in every manner
                    possible to have the Chilean experience emulated in every Latin country and
                    indeed, his success here has already had manifold effects. For the US therefore,
                    it means a complete overhaul of its assumptions about Latin America,
                    particularly South America. That political genius of Chilean Communism,
                        <persName corresp="#p_TV_1">Velodia Teitelboim</persName>, said in an
                    interview in Montevideo last month, that Popular Unity proved that President
                    Frei had exaggerated the importance of the US in Latin America and that Foreign
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_VSG_1">Valdes</persName> had understood and
                    enacted a contrary foreign policy that had great significance. In that sense,
                    DeGaulle’s terminology might well be prophetic.</p>
                <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> has set in motion the greatest
                    change Chile has known since independence. Leaving aside foreign implications,
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> would be a rare leader
                    indeed if he could control the forces he has loosed. He is enacting a populist
                    program that will reinforce the already sharp appetites of a population that
                    was, under Frei, emerging rapidly from backwardness, marginality and isolation.
                    He is establishing a bureaucratic centralism that will directly or indirectly
                    convert every nonpolitical organization in Chile into a full or quasi arm of the
                    state. This combination has inevitably led elsewhere to greater controls, more
                    centralism and finally to repression.</p>
                <p>7. <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> and his associates are raising
                    hell publicly with the Supreme Court’s reversal of a lower court’s decision to
                    lift the congressional immunity of rightist Senator Raul Morales on charges
                    growing out of the <persName corresp="#p_SCR_1">Schneider</persName>
                    assassination. At the same time he is deliberately encouraging prosecution of
                    such dubious cases as of the Edwards Bank and is seeking to establish a kangaroo
                    court for the copper nationalization. In sum he is arranging events in order to
                    justify an overhaul of Chile’s traditional independent judiciary. He is doing it
                    legally but it is the threat of the mass pressure that will produce the result
                    he and the Communists want.</p>
                <p>8. <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is also raising hell publicly
                    with the two leading anti-Communist newsmen in radio and privately his
                    lieutenants are beginning to put pressure on some of the few remaining
                    non-conformist voices in the press. TV is already his. With decreasing
                    advertising and <pb facs="0291" n="251" xml:id="pg_251"/> consequent decreasing
                    numbers of news pages, with increasing dependence on the state for revenue, for
                    price increases, for credit, for labor peace and for other govt favors, can
                    anyone seriously propound the notion that the conditions for a free press
                    genuinely exist? (<hi rend="italic">El Mercurio</hi> has many problems not the
                    least of which is that <persName corresp="#p_EEA_1">Agustin Edwards</persName>’s
                    sister Sonia, the only Edwards on the board of directors and an Allendista, is
                    now hopelessly in love with the extreme left wing Socialist Senator <persName
                        corresp="#p_AOC_1">Altamirano</persName>.) Perhaps most illuminating is the
                    case of Dario Saint Marie, known as Volpone here the sole owner of <hi
                        rend="italic">Clarin,</hi> the most populist of all Chilean papers, second
                    only to <hi rend="italic">Mercurio</hi> in circulation and a staunch supporter
                    of <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>. Volpone is a millionaire
                    many times over as a result of his start in life as a successful blackmailer,
                    drug-runner and today, as a crypto-racketeer. <hi rend="italic">Clarin</hi> has
                    been licensed to print money with the Frei govt buying peace from <hi
                        rend="italic">Clarin</hi> by stuffing it with govt advertising and an aid
                    special letter of credit to buy new modern equipment. Now Volpone has discovered
                    that the paper has been effectively captured by the Communists through their
                    control of the shop journalist union. Although a close personal friend of
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>, his complaints have so far
                    been unavailing and he may well try to sell the paper and quit Chile to enjoy
                    his fat foreign bank accounts. But he is so vulnerable that the Communists are
                    standing firm and the outcome of this test of amoral wills is going to have
                    wider implications.</p>
                <p>9. Wildcat strikes unless prompted by the govt have almost disappered since
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> came to power. There has
                    been one at the Chuquicamata oxide plant for one week but as I have noted in the
                    past that mine has the most bloody-minded workers in the country and they will
                    not be easy to cow. The govt has already won the support there of all the unions
                    at the mine against the strikers (whose walkout is totally unpublicized in the
                    free press) and it would not be rash to predict that the govt will have its way.
                    Since the Communists control the national trade union <gloss target="#t_CUT_1"
                        >CUT</gloss>, and since <gloss target="#t_CUT_1">CUT</gloss> has been
                    designated the sole voice of labor in its dealings with gov, the demise of
                    pluralistic trade unionism is not far off.</p>
                <p>10. Political parties and indeed democracy depend in the last analysis on freedom
                    of expression and the effective capacity to have that expression reach the
                    electorate. The <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss> can appear on TV debates
                    and state its views; it can publish its one newspaper with a claimed circulation
                    of 25,000 (as opposed to <hi rend="italic">Mercurio</hi>’s estimate of 15,000)
                    and it can broadcast on the one of the 29 stations in Santiago that it owns. The
                    other opposition parties have no Santiago newspaper per se although the <hi
                        rend="italic">Mercurio</hi> trio must be credited to their cause and only
                    two remaining radio stations, neither of which will be in hands unfriendly to
                    the govt for long since a combination of tight money and of govt blackmail
                    against the current owners are forcing the proprietors to consider only
                    “friendly” bids.</p>
                <pb facs="0292" n="252" xml:id="pg_252"/>
                <p>11. Political parties depend also on mass organization and structure. The
                    Communist Party had its way this week, gaining <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName>’s concurrence against initial Socialist opposition, to
                    convoke the Santiago provincial apparat that the U.P. organized for <persName
                        corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s campaign so that the governing unity
                    will be reinforced for the municipal elections. Hardly a worker or a small or
                    large businessman will not be forced to buy the equivalent of “protection” by
                    contributing to the U.P. campaign for the nationwide municipal elections in
                    early March. Many will do so gladly in gratitude for the many benefits that
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> has conferred. But many with
                    meager means and with doubts will cough up because of the peer pressure and out
                    of fear; hence they will neither be able to work for or contribute to opposition
                    parties. Once again a birds-eye view misses the subsurface.</p>
                <p>12. I have cited a few of the instances by which Chilean democracy and traditions
                    are being altered in substance if not in appearance. The point is that a
                    momentum is being developed that will give the Unidad Popular a huge vote in the
                    municipal elections, that between them the Communists and Socialists may get 40
                    percent of the total vote, that these two Marxist parties will not fall into the
                    trap of competing openly with each other but will concentrate its efforts on
                    grinding down the opposition and that this Marxist combination is establishing a
                    tight bureaucratic centralism that will develop its own accelerating
                    anti-pluralistic thrust. A great many romantic Chileans believe they can split
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> from the Communists. The
                    Communists need <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> indispensably as
                    the umbrella under which they legitimize their push for power; nothing can
                    unstick them. Senator <persName corresp="#p_AOC_1">Altamirano</persName>, who
                    was considered to be an anti-Communist because of his Maoist views, told <hi
                        rend="italic">Punto Final:</hi> “Socialist-Communist unity is and will be
                    the base for all our action which in turn ought to be founded on a solid
                    identity of both strategic and tactical goals.” Debray makes the same point of
                    the need for Marxist unity with the Revolutionary Left (<gloss target="#t_MIR_1"
                        >MIR</gloss>) acting as the defender of the revolution to prevent the govt
                    or the U.P. from being entrapped by becoming bourgeois or by being softened by
                    the bourgeoisie. Significantly Debray says that <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName> understands this entrapment threat and will combat it.
                    There are others, particularly in the <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss>, who
                    argued that the U.P. could not run its economy without their cooperation; they
                    are dead wrong. Not only does the U.P. have just as many trained technicians of
                    more or less equal calibre, but they have an ideological outlook that is
                    cohesive and they have the labor discipline and the mass structure to enforce
                    their will. <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss>ers will be given the option of
                    being loyal or of being outcasts.</p>
                <p>13. For all these reasons, the opposition is now hastily confronting the
                    realities and the most intelligent of their leaders are talking the kinds of
                    deals that might make some sense. Here are some short-term possibilities:</p>
                <pb facs="0293" n="253" xml:id="pg_253"/>
                <p>A. The Nacional Party has designated Deputy Silvia Alessandri to be its candidate
                    for the senatorial seat vacated in Magallanes by <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName>. She has not yet formally accepted. The <gloss
                        target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss> has not yet named a candidate. There is a
                    chance that a deal will be arranged whereby Alessandri withdraws her name at the
                    last moment before the election and gives freedom of action to her supporters.
                    The anti-Marxists have a majority in Magallanes and a victory for the <gloss
                        target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss> there would do much to balance the
                    simultaneous weak showing they expect in the municipal elections.</p>
                <p>B. An overturning of the U.P.’s control of the Mesa Directiva in the Chamber of
                    Deputies and its replacement by a coalition of oppositionists.</p>
                <p>C. A coordinated resignation of various private enterprise association heads
                    rather than the inchoate and ineffectual individual dealings.</p>
                <p>D. Successful efforts to alter various legislation in the Congress submitted by
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>.</p>
                <p>E. Greater effectiveness in publicizing in the Western world the sharply
                    increasing preoccupations so that the [garble] here will provide a better base
                    for opposition.</p>
                <p>14. None of these measures will alter the inevitable thrust of events but they
                    might provide enough footing to enable the opposition to assure enough pluralism
                    for later confrontations when the consequences of state control of the economy
                    begin to be felt. It will be the politicians and the mass of the people, not the
                    army, that might save Chilean pluralism. The armed forces are considered totally
                    safe now by the Communists and Socialists. They are not a political force in
                    Chile; they are always for order and the fatherland. (End Part IV)</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_KEM_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
