<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-06-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-06-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="12" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d12">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">841.248/452</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Prime Minister of Australia</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Menzies</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to President <persName type="to">Roosevelt</persName>
                                </hi><note n="18" xml:id="d12fn18">File copy on letterhead of the
                                    Australian Legation, not signed.</note>
                            </head>
                            <p>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. President</hi>: I recently had the honour
                                to communicate with you on the subject of possible United States
                                assistance to the Allied arms. Since then the position has become
                                rapidly grave and as it might well become worse, I do not exaggerate
                                when I say that as a British and democratic country we are forced to
                                contemplate the possibility of a beaten France and a Great Britain
                                in danger of being overwhelmed <pb facs="0024" n="12" xml:id="pg_12"/> not by superior courage or by a good cause but by a villainous
                                combination of international lawlessness and a long-prepared
                                mechanism of superiority.</p>
                            <p>In certain events we in Australia may have to fight for our own lives
                                and I want to tell you that with all the defects of our equipment we
                                will fight for them to the end.</p>
                            <p>At this moment the eyes of the whole liberty-loving world are turned
                                to you and your great people.</p>
                            <p>I believe even now, if the United States, by a magnificent and
                                immortal gesture, could make available to the Allies the whole of
                                their financial and material resources, Germany could be defeated.
                                The effect on the spirit of France would be transfiguring while the
                                whole of the English-speaking peoples of the world would by one
                                stroke be welded into a brotherhood of world salvation.</p>
                            <p>On behalf of the people of Australia and the future of this land I
                                appeal to you for the fullest possible measure of co-operation and
                                help.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-06-14">14 <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi>, 1940</date>.</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>