<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in the Soviet Union ( (Steinhardt) ) to the Secretary of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d214</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">214</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-11-05T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-11-05T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recHEnRX74raOryAY" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044893"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Espionage</term>
                    <term ref="receqDO15mlMSmrzP" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87000436"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Visas</term>
                    <term ref="recVMjpePTbXrmHOO" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037040"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Deportation</term>
                    <term ref="rec9yKWGNvCFmqmdD" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-11-05T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-11-05T05:00:00-05:00" n="214"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d214">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">861.20211/67: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Soviet Union</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Steinhardt</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Moscow</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-11-05T13:00:00+03:00"
                            >November 5, 1940—1 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/> [Received 6:12 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1487. The Department may wish to take cognizance of the following statements
                    recently made at the Embassy by one of the more intelligent visa applicants who
                    has been experiencing difficulties in obtaining a Soviet exit visa.</p>
                <p>The applicant stated that he was in considerable disfavor with the local
                    authorities in the town of his residence in Soviet occupied Poland because he
                    had refused to accept repeated offers from them to issue to him the desired exit
                    visa and to facilitate his departure from the Soviet Union in every possible way
                    and even to pay him substantial and regular compensation in the United States
                    provided he would sign an agreement to undertake espionage work in the United
                    States. He said the Soviet authorities had told him they were not granting
                    permission to anyone to leave the Soviet Union unless the individual <pb
                        facs="0247" n="235" xml:id="pg_235"/> gave an undertaking to the foregoing
                    effect and that he was foolish to refuse if he really wished or hoped to leave
                    the Soviet Union. The authorities further stated that they already had many new
                    agents working for them in the United States and that he should seize the
                    opportunity extended to him as it was only a question of a short time before the
                    Soviets would take over the Government of the United States.</p>
                <p>The foregoing which reflects a common practice long known to the Department and
                    recently applied in the Baltic States indicates that many visa applicants and
                    doubtless many among the individuals who acquire American passports to return to
                    the United States are being solicited to sign such agreements as a condition
                    precedent to the issuance of exit visas. Nearly all of these individuals have
                    relatives remaining in Soviet territory and are therefore subject to pressure in
                    the United States if they fail to carry out their agreement. Furthermore the
                    undertaking required of them might be availed of to bring about their
                    deportation from the United States or to prevent them from ultimately acquiring
                    American citizenship thus constituting a continuing form of blackmail during
                    their stay in the United States.</p>
                <p>I accordingly feel fortified in my previously expressed view that the best
                    interests of the United States are not served by permitting aliens residing in
                    territory under Soviet dominion to emigrate to the United States at the present
                    time in any large numbers.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Steinhardt</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
