<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="246" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d246">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">701.6111/984</note>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by Mr. Edward Page, Jr., of the Division of
                                European Affairs</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-26">April 26, 1940</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">The Hostile Attitude of the Soviet Ambassador to
                                the State Department</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Last evening I dined at the Lithuanian Legation. Among those present were
                            the Soviet Ambassador, the Latvian, Lithuanian, and Bulgarian Ministers,
                            the Counselor and First Secretary of the Soviet Embassy, and Mr. Todd,
                                Tass<note n="8" xml:id="d246fn8">Telegraph agency of the Soviet
                                Union, official communications organization of the Soviet
                                Government.</note> representative in Washington.</p>
                        <p>During after-dinner coffee, Mr. Oumansky adopted a smug, complacent and
                            domineering attitude over his colleagues (Ministers whose countries
                            exist under the shadow of the Soviet Union),<note n="9" xml:id="d246fn9">For correspondence concerning the activities of the Soviet Union in
                                the Baltic States, see <ref target="frus1933-39#pg_934">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Soviet Union,
                                    1933–1939, pp. 934</ref> ff., and <ref target="frus1940v01#pg_357">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1940, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp. 357</ref> ff.</note> The
                            Ambassador also went out of his way to be hostile toward the State
                            Department. He started the after-dinner conversation by suggesting that
                            we all enter into a short discussion, and then adjoined with words
                            somewhat as follows: “But perhaps this would not be fair, for I am sure
                            we would all be grouped together against Mr. Page”. He then went on to
                            explain in a sarcastic tone that the American Government had instructed
                            American flagships to refuse to carry mails to the Soviet Union and to
                            the Baltic States, and added that this was not surprising. I asked the
                            Ambassador where he had received this information, and was told that he
                            had read it in the press. I stated that I felt sure that the press
                            report was false, since I had been informed only that morning that
                            mails, with the exception of parcel post, to the Soviet Union and the
                            Baltic were being despatched via Italy and Germany. I observed that the
                            parcel post question was under consideration, and that I doubted whether
                            the temporary absence of this service would create much hardship, since
                            I did not believe that, with the exception of small shipments through
                            Intourist, the volume of parcel post amounted to much.<note n="*" xml:id="d246fn11">Mr. Lammiel, Director of the Foreign Mails Section
                                of the Post Office, confirmed this morning what I had told Mr.
                                Oumansky, that is, that mails were going to the Soviet Union and the
                                Baltic via Italy and Germany, and that there had been no refusals to
                                carry mails to these countries on the part of American ships. Mr.
                                Lammiel also informed me that the Post Office was endeavoring at
                                this time to make arrangements with the Rumanian postal authorities
                                for despatching parcel post to the Soviet Union via Rumania.
                                [Footnote in the original.]</note> The Ambassador stated that he was
                            glad to receive this news, and changed the subject.</p>
                        <pb facs="0306" n="294" xml:id="pg_294"/>
                        <p>Mr. Oumansky then pointed out to all those present that because of the
                            unfriendly attitude of the State Department, Intourist, as well as
                            Bookniga and Amkino, had been forced to close down. I interposed that
                            there was no reason why such firms should not carry on their legitimate
                            business provided they registered with the State Department as agents of
                            foreign principals. Mr. Oumansky remarked that it was unlikely that
                            Intourist, Bookniga, et cetera, would open up again, in view of the
                            attitude of the State Department. He commented at length on how Soviet
                            citizens had been insulted and humiliated in this country by being
                            photographed, handcuffed to police authorities, and by being commented
                            upon in the American press in an insulting manner.</p>
                        <p>The Latvian, Lithuanian and Bulgarian Ministers maintained a discreet
                            silence during this tirade. I was of the opinion that they considered
                            the Ambassador to be acting in extremely bad taste in criticizing in
                            fairly strong terms the Government to which he was accredited. I did not
                            wish to enter into a heated discussion with Mr. Oumansky, and merely
                            observed that the firms in question had not complied with our
                            regulations regarding registration, and had been prosecuted according to
                            law.</p>
                        <p>Later, in commenting on the difficulties which the Soviet Embassy was
                            encountering in receiving radio broadcasts from Moscow, Mr. Oumansky, in
                            a joking, yet extremely sarcastic manner, observed that it would not
                            surprise him to learn that the State Department had deliberately
                            arranged interference in order to hinder the Embassy’s radio reception.
                            This remark was typical of the critical and hostile manner in which Mr.
                            Oumansky conducted himself throughout the entire joint conversation.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Oumansky later drew me aside and after commenting at length on the
                            discriminatory attitude of the State Department in regard to the
                            much-discussed question of the notification by the Embassy of the
                            presence of Soviet officials in this country, stated that he had
                            reluctantly approved of the procedure of notification agreed upon by
                            Messrs. Gromyko, Chuvakhin, Henderson and Page early last week. He then
                            brought up the usual complaints regarding the Maritime Commission, moral
                            embargo, et cetera, and inferred that the State Department was
                            principally to blame for the present strained situation in
                            American-Soviet relations. I advanced some of the usual rejoinders, and
                            stated that I saw no purpose in going into the matter again. Mr.
                            Oumansky concluded by asking me to tell Mr. Henderson that he was still
                            expecting a reply in regard to his representations over the refusal of
                            the Maritime Commission to charter vessels to Amtorg. His favorite word
                            throughout the evening appeared to be “discrimination”.</p>
                        <pb facs="0307" n="295" xml:id="pg_295"/>
                        <p>I was strongly impressed during the entire evening by the outspoken
                            animosity and hostility toward the American Government, and especially
                            towards the State Department, on the part of Mr. Oumansky, and the First
                            Secretary, Chuvakhin. Mr. Gromyko, Counselor of the Soviet Embassy, on
                            the other hand, appeared to be quite friendly, and conducted himself
                            much more befitting a diplomat in a country to which he is
                                accredited.<note n="10" xml:id="d246fn10">Andrey Andreyevich Gromyko
                                had been in the United States only since the previous November; see
                                the memorandum of November 17, 1939, by the Acting Secretary of
                                State, <ref target="frus1933-39#pg_794">
                                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, The Soviet Union,
                                    1933–1939, p. 794</ref>.</note>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>E[<hi rend="smallcaps">dward</hi>] P[<hi rend="smallcaps">age</hi>]</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>