<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">258</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec6eGRLPExgj2z1M" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="rec6wtE9zoj1Zw652" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recItilmdY8wKocmo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005329"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Conservation</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Conferences</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="258"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.61/738</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-06-12">June 12,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Ambassador of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics called, at his request.
                    I was familiar with his numerous conferences with other officials in the
                    Department and of the topics discussed, as well as the rather vituperative tone
                    and demeanor of the Ambassador. I therefore proceeded to do most of the
                    talking.</p>
                <pb facs="0328" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/>
                <p>First I reviewed and discussed at some length the extremely dislocated and
                    lawless state of the world as a result of the policies of those who are carrying
                    out plans of conquest by force and applying force in carrying out almost all of
                    their governmental activities. I again reviewed the course of our relations with
                    Soviet Russia, especially since 1933, and referred to our wishes to comply with
                    the urgent desire of Russia for recognition on account of dangerous relations
                    between her and Japan in particular. I pointed out how I and some of my
                    associates had incurred bitter criticism during all the past seven years because
                    of our earnest efforts to cooperate with Russia. We had hoped that this
                    cooperation would be not only for our mutual benefit but that it would be a
                    stabilizing factor in the international situation, and that it would result in
                    discouraging heavy armaments and in preventing possible war in the future. I
                    pointed out how we had been hopelessly disappointed in many important respects
                    in these efforts. I then passed in review the world situation relative to peace
                    and the developments of danger to peace during the past seven years,
                    notwithstanding the constant preachments and strenuous efforts of this
                    Government to work with every other country at all disposed to go in the
                    direction of peace. This especially included Russia. I then said that it was
                    with unspeakable disappointment and regret that all of the efforts of this
                    country in pursuing the foregoing objectives had come to naught; that the world
                    was being rapidly subjected to a reign of force and destruction of most of the
                    worthwhile things; that in these circumstances this Government had proceeded on
                    a new policy of arming and arming and arming in order to defend itself against
                    anybody wherever defense might legitimately be called for; that to this end this
                    Government has no hesitation in taking necessary materials and otherwise
                    conserving all of the commodities needed for this day-and-night program of
                    military armament; that if anything unlawful is done this Government is
                    responsible; that I am not intimating anything on that question; that I need not
                    do so for the purpose of what I am saying; that my Government has no notion of
                    making further sacrifices or engaging in further delays that would in the
                    slightest retard or handicap its program of armament; that here it stands, and
                    the Government of the Ambassador ought to be able to understand and realize that
                    this is exactly our position.</p>
                <p>I then said that it was a matter of great disappointment that we could not have
                    the cooperation of Russia to a much fuller and broader extent than we have had
                    during the past seven years, especially in view of the far-reaching extent to
                    which we have gone to encourage and induce such broader cooperation for peace
                    and mutual welfare. The Ambassador then began to speak of the trade
                    discriminations <pb facs="0329" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/> which he says this
                    Government is practicing. I said that I was surprised, in the existing
                    far-reaching exigencies, to see his Government engaging in such small topics of
                    controversy. I said that his Government is discriminating in favor of other
                    countries in its trade methods and that we are saying nothing; that this
                    includes immense war supplies to Germany.<note n="27" xml:id="d258fn27">For
                        correspondence on wartime cooperation between the Soviet Union and Germany,
                        see <ref target="frus1940v01#pg_539">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp.
                            539</ref> ff.</note> The Ambassador said this was normal trade. I
                    replied in any event that it comprised immense supplies urgently needed for war,
                    which fact made it vastly different from normal trade. I added that Russia had a
                    perfect right to pursue this trade so far as this Government is concerned, but
                    that we followed a very different policy toward Italy with our trade during the
                    Italian-Ethiopian war,<note n="28" xml:id="d258fn28">For correspondence
                        concerning United States neutrality in the Ethiopian-Italian conflict, see
                            <ref target="frus1936v03#pg_188">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1936, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 188</ref> ff.</note> holding it down
                    to the pre-war level by a moral embargo. I rested my contention, however,
                    paramountly and primarily on our present policy of conserving supplies and
                    materials for increasing our armaments, and that these references to Soviet
                    policies were only casual.</p>
                <p>I said then that in our extreme desire to see Russia pursue a course that would
                    give her a great influence for peace, the President generously offered his good
                    offices to Russia before she invaded Finland.<note n="29" xml:id="d258fn29">See
                        telegraphic instruction No. 252, November 29, 1939, 3:13 p.m., to the Chargé
                        in the Soviet Union, <ref target="frus1939v01#pg_1003">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 1939, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                            1003</ref>.</note> The Ambassador rather sarcastically said, yes, but
                    his Government did not very well respond or react to the President’s speech on a
                    certain occasion at that time. I replied that when a giant country has a little
                    microscopic helpless country by the throat and is choking it to death, I must
                    agree that the Government of the large country is not in a position to respond
                    or to react; that naturally the deepest possible silence is about the only
                    recourse in such circumstances. The Ambassador looked uncomfortable but said not
                    a word in reply.</p>
                <p>I then said that I was not sure that Mr. Litvinov and Mr. Molotov are really
                    friendly toward this country in view of the disposition to haggle and engage in
                    vituperative language about a number of matters so infinitely small in the light
                    of the present terrific problems that are being grappled with; (and having in
                    mind the bitter and patronizing talk of Molotov to Thurston at Moscow a few days
                    ago, and the loud and vituperative talk of the Ambassador himself here in
                    Washington on all possible occasions) I proceeded to say that Mr. Molotov seems
                    to have gotten on a “high horse” and that I have been hearing of the
                    vituperative talks about Washington by his representative. I then said that this
                    is, in part, my compensation for having undergone biting criticism for seven
                    years in my efforts to <pb facs="0330" n="318" xml:id="pg_318"/> keep up
                    anything like desirable relations with Soviet Russia and the reward for my hope
                    of their improvement.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador then handed me the accompanying note from Molotov,<note n="30"
                        xml:id="d258fn30">See note by the Soviet Ambassador, June 12, <hi
                            rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note> which is self-explanatory. I said that
                    I had already anticipated the contents of this paper, because I had heard
                    nothing harped on except these comparatively small items, and that I must again
                    call his attention to our policy of conserving materials for emergency armament
                    purposes and that nothing would stand in the way of it. There were some brief
                    references to these questions in virtually the same language that they have been
                    discussed between the Ambassador and my associates in the Department and, to
                    some extent, between him and myself some weeks ago. I said that other
                    governments are not raving like his about similar conditions existing between us
                    and those other governments, and that soon even his Government will be obliged
                    to see more clearly that in view of our determination to conserve strategic and
                    other needed materials for armament purposes the operation of the policy is
                    general. The Ambassador repeatedly returned to the matters of difference set out
                    in the written statement handed to me from Molotov. I said it was useless to
                    protract this sort of discussion since I had made clear the broad policy of
                    conservation on which our action primarily rested.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador again denied that his Government was aiding Germany any more than
                    normal relations would aid her. I again replied that the Soviet Union had the
                    privilege of taking any of the various courses to which I had referred that she
                    might see fit; that I was not raising any question for discussion on its merits
                    but merely to point out that in effect Russia discriminates as between different
                    countries.</p>
                <p>When the Ambassador again returned to some of his complaints I replied that my
                    Government could list a whole ream of earnest complaints against Russia, but
                    that I would not undertake to do so in this connection except to the extent I
                    had gone. He invited me to list any that I might have in mind. I thereupon read
                    off to him the first page of the statement in the files recently dictated by
                    Ambassador Steinhardt,<note n="31" xml:id="d258fn31">Not found in Department
                        files.</note> and added that I could read several additional pages but would
                    not do so.</p>
                <p>Finally, I referred again to the long and earnest efforts I and others had made
                    to get along amicably with Russia and on a broad basis of cooperation for all
                    purposes, as heretofore stated, and added that this Government would be glad
                    whenever Russia should see fit to return to a set of policies that would make
                    possible the fuller development of the relations of peace and mutually
                    profitable cooperation in every practicable way. I pointed out that while the
                    amount of Russian <pb facs="0331" n="319" xml:id="pg_319"/> trade with this
                    country is relatively small, and that it would be a mistake to exaggerate any
                    special importance that we might attach to it, we would be glad to see it
                    retained and developed, provided it is possible for such development to take
                    place under mutually acceptable relations between the two countries.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
