<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Chargé in Egypt ( (Hare) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d384</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">384</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recA365XAlFrgaB1r" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft Convention</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-17T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="384"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d384">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">711.8321/17</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Egypt</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hare</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 2066</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-17">April 17,
                            1940</date>.<lb/>[Received May 16.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to refer to the Department’s
                    instruction no. 416 of September 13, 1939<note n="44" xml:id="d384fn44">
                        <ref target="frus1939v04#pg_477">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., p. 477</ref>.</note> enclosing a draft
                    Consular Convention to <pb facs="0523" n="511" xml:id="pg_511"/> be presented to
                    the Egyptian authorities, and to the Legation’s despatch no. 1903 of November 6,
                        1939<note n="45" xml:id="d384fn45">Not printed.</note> reporting that the
                    draft had been submitted to the Foreign Office and duly acknowledged.</p>
                <p>In this connection the Legation has recently been giving consideration to that
                    part of Article 11 of the Montreux Convention<note n="46" xml:id="d384fn46"
                        >Signed at Montreux May 8, 1937; Department of State Treaty Series No. 939,
                        or 53 Stat. 1645.</note> which provided that consuls should continue to
                    enjoy the immunities possessed at the time of the signature of the Convention
                    pending the conclusion of Consular Conventions “and in any case during a period
                    of three years as from the date of the signature of the present Convention”. The
                    Convention having been signed on May 8, 1937, the three year period prescribed
                    in Article 11 therefore terminates on May 7, 1940. The question thus arose
                    whether in the absence of the signature of a Consular Convention within the
                    specified three year period consular officers in Egypt would continue to enjoy
                    the immunities to which they were previously entitled. Since the American
                    Government had some months ago submitted a draft Consular Convention for the
                    consideration of the Egyptian Government and since responsibility for delay in
                    such negotiations therefore lay with the Egyptian Government for having failed
                    to pursue the matter further, it seemed to the Legation that a strong case could
                    be made for arguing that American consular officers would be entitled to the
                    continuance of their immunities regardless of such action as the Egyptian
                    Government might contemplate taking in other cases. However, it was thought
                    advisable to look into the matter with a view to avoiding possibly unforeseen
                    complications.</p>
                <p>The matter was first discussed informally with Mr. E. F. W. Besly, Legal
                    Counselor of the British Embassy, who said that the British Government had in
                    fact prepared a draft Consular Convention for submission to the Egyptian
                    Government but that it had been decided not to submit it until after the war. He
                    said that it was his opinion that under the terms of Article 11 of the
                    Convention the specification of a three year period was not intended to indicate
                    the period within which a Consular Convention should be concluded but rather the
                    period during which consuls would be entitled to previous immunities regardless
                    of whether or not a Consular Convention was concluded. However, when it was
                    observed to Mr. Besly that such an interpretation would, if correct, make it
                    possible, by merely adopting obstructionist tactics, indefinitely to delay the
                    conclusion of a Consular Convention and thus ensure by such tactics the
                    maintenance of consular immunities, he admitted that he might perhaps have been
                    somewhat precipitate in reaching the decision that the conclusion of <pb
                        facs="0524" n="512" xml:id="pg_512"/> Consular Conventions could be
                    postponed beyond the three year period without running the danger of loss by
                    consuls of their immunities. In this connection he thereupon consulted a
                    published work on the Montreux Convention by Messrs. Aghion and Feldman and
                    found that it was categorically stated in the commentary on Article 11 that in
                    the absence of the signature of a Consular Convention within the three year
                    period specified in the Article consuls would cease to enjoy their customary
                    immunities. Mr. Besly said he was glad this matter had been brought to his
                    attention because he thought the Embassy might wish to reconsider the matter and
                    possibly to submit its draft Convention in the early future.</p>
                <p>This question was also raised informally on April 6 with Mohamed Said Bey, Acting
                    Director of the Administrative Section of the Foreign Office, who appeared to be
                    thoroughly conversant with the subject and said that although the Foreign Office
                    was aware that the three year period specified in Article 11 of the Montreux
                    Convention was approaching its termination no immediate action in respect of the
                    abolition of the immunities of consuls was anticipated. The matter was, however,
                    under study by the appropriate authorities and it was his understanding that the
                    final decision reached would probably be to propose that the privileges of
                    consuls should be placed on a reciprocal basis. In any event, he reiterated, he
                    could give assurance that no precipitate action was in prospect.</p>
                <p>Under the circumstances the Legation is of the opinion that there is adequate
                    assurance that the immunities of American consular officers in Egypt are
                    adequately safeguarded for the time being. It is also reassuring to learn that
                    the Egyptian Government contemplates adopting the principle of reciprocity as a
                    basis for according such immunities in the future in view of the liberal
                    treatment specified in Article IV of the draft Consular Convention referred to
                    above which the American Government is prepared to accord Egyptian consular
                    officers.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Raymond</hi> A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hare</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
