<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of European Affairs
                    ( (Moffat))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d394</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">394</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="394"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d394">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/2611</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Chief of the Division of
                        European Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Moffat</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-24">April 24,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The Greek Minister<note n="2" xml:id="d394fn2">Cimon P. Diamantopoulos.</note>
                    called this morning.</p>
                <p>After talking over various phases of the war, he said that from the Greek point
                    of view the matter of greatest interest was Italian intentions. He recognized
                    that the tension in Italy had somewhat subsided and he believed that Mussolini
                    would, in no event, make a move until the Scandinavian campaign had been decided
                    one way or the other.</p>
                <p>If Italy moved, however, he thought it would not be against Yugoslavia. He said
                    that the Serbs were magnificent fighters, and even the Croats had no sympathy
                    for the Italians. If Italy moved, he believed it would be on Salonika, probably
                    a march which would avoid violating <pb facs="0537" n="525" xml:id="pg_525"/>
                    Yugoslav neutrality. Of course, the Greek Army would resist, and probably the
                    Turkish Army would come to her assistance. If so, he foresaw that the Turks
                    would move through western Thrace and not try to cross Bulgarian territory. If
                    the Italians were fighting alone, the Minister thought that the Bulgarians would
                    remain neutral. If Germany should also enter the Balkans, he felt that Bulgaria
                    would adopt toward the Germans very much the same attitude as had the Danes. He
                    had lived many years in Sofia and professed to know the Bulgars well. They would
                    not want to fight, partly because their experiences in the last war had been
                    unfortunate, and partly because they were very much afraid of the Turks. They
                    were not in favor of a German victory, neither were they in favor of an allied
                    victory. They were playing all their cards on the chance of a negotiated peace.
                    The peace conference, they felt, would give them more than a military
                    campaign.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>P[<hi rend="smallcaps">ierrepont</hi>] M[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >offat</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
