<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-10-22T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-10-22T10:00:00-05:00" n="425" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d425">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/6207:
                                    Telegram</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Greece</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">MacVeagh</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                            State</gloss>
                                    </hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-10-22T17:00:00+02:00">October 22, 1940—5 p.m.</date>
                                        <lb/> [Received 11:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>260. The Under Secretary for Foreign Affairs told me this morning
                                    that the Greek Government is completely at a loss to understand
                                    recent British agency and radio reports of Axis demands on this
                                    country in view of the fact that no such demands have been made.
                                    Furthermore he said that while the concentrations of Italian
                                    troops in Albania must still be considered as a potential
                                    menace, official <pb facs="0556" n="544" xml:id="pg_544"/>
                                    relations between Greece and the Axis powers are easier at the
                                    moment than for some time past. He personally suggested as a
                                    possibility that the British maneuver may be part of a campaign
                                    to alarm Russia over Axis intentions in the Balkans linking it
                                    up with recent false rumors from British sources in Rumania.
                                    Regarding the Albanian concentrations he said that they may have
                                    been effected in anticipation of the collapse of Great Britain
                                    this summer, when the moment would have been opportune for a
                                    Balkan snatch, and quoted a remark of the Italian Minister here
                                    to the effect that if Italy really wished to invade Greece she
                                    would have done so in August and not waited until now.</p>
                                <p>The British and Yugoslav Military Attachés both are informed that
                                    the condition of the Italian troops on the Albanian border, many
                                    of whom are under canvas, is rapidly becoming untenable, and
                                    believe that they must soon either advance or retire. In this
                                    connection the Under Secretary believes that retirement is the
                                    more likely not only because of the immediate difficulties in
                                    the way of advance, but because the latter would “certainly
                                    involve widespread consequences”. He still thinks any war in the
                                    Balkans unlikely at least before next spring and in view of the
                                    difficulties to be surmounted by the Axis in attacking vital
                                    British centers in Asia or Africa without command of the sea,
                                    considers the final German decision may have to be to stake all
                                    on putting England out by direct attack.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">MacVeagh</hi>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>