<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of State (
                    (Welles))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1940v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d5</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">5</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1940-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1940-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                    <term ref="receEP5YJv8hHaXra" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="air-safety" subject="civil-aviation" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001360" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aviation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-05-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-05-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="5"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d5">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">811.22742/310</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Under Secretary of
                        State</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Welles</hi>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-05-27">May 27,
                            1940</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The British Ambassador called to see me this morning with the Canadian Chargé
                    d’Affaires, Mr. Mahoney. The Ambassador stated that the British and Canadian
                    Governments desired to ascertain whether the United States Government would
                    permit or possibly facilitate the training of British and Canadian pilots in
                    governmental schools and airfields. The Ambassador stated that such pilots would
                    come to the United States in a civilian capacity and as individuals.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador stated that he understood that I had been informed of this matter
                    beforehand.</p>
                <p>I said to the Ambassador that, as Mr. Mahoney knew, the views of this Government
                    had been communicated some days before to the Canadian Prime Minister with
                    reference to the enlistment of American citizens in Canada for service in the
                    British and Canadian air forces, but that I had had no prior knowledge of the
                    request the Ambassador had just made of me except a cryptic message<note n="10"
                        xml:id="d5fn10">Not printed.</note> from Ambassador Kennedy<note n="11"
                        xml:id="d5fn11">American Ambassador in the United Kingdom.</note> saying
                    that Lord Lothian would discuss with me an aviation question and that the
                    Ambassador felt it would be better to handle the matter in Washington rather
                    than in London.</p>
                <p>I stated to Lord Lothian and to Mr. Mahoney that it seemed to me there were two
                    questions involved, first, whether the proposed step would violate any of our
                    neutrality requirements, and, second, whether the facilities now existing in the
                    United States would be sufficient to make possible the training of non-American
                    pilots other than the few which we took from the other American Republics. I
                    said this latter problem seemed to me difficult to overcome in view of the
                    present rearmament program and in view of the fact that Lord Lothian had
                    indicated that something like one hundred thousand aspirants had <pb facs="0019"
                        n="7" xml:id="pg_7"/> registered for training as pilots in Canada and in
                    Great Britain. In order to answer these two questions, I said I would have to
                    consult certain of the appropriate authorities of this Government and I said
                    that I would inform the Ambassador of our decision as soon as might be
                    possible.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>S[<hi rend="smallcaps">umner</hi>] W[<hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >elles</hi>]</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
