<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1940-04-17T00:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1940-04-17T00:35:00-05:00" n="549" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d549">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">661.9131/183: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Iran</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Engert</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to
                                    the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Tehran</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1940-04-17T09:00:00+03:25">April
                                        17, 1940—9 a.m.</date>
                                    <lb/> [Received 5:40 p.m.]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>77. Legation’s 63, April 5, 9 p.m.<note n="16" xml:id="d549fn16">Not
                                    printed.</note> It seemed best to await completion of English
                                and French translations before commenting.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Immediate result of the signing of the treaty was a distinct
                                        <hi rend="italic">détente</hi> in Irano-Soviet relations.
                                    Feeling of optimism has taken the place of fear of grave
                                    developments which were freely predicted only a few months ago.
                                    Although the exact nature of the difficulties which have for
                                    nearly 2 years been found insurmountable has never been
                                    divulged, enough has leaked out to show that Moscow originally
                                    wanted an agreement of much wider scope than a simple treaty of
                                    commerce. Ever since the Soviets established military domination
                                    over the Baltic States, the Iranian Government has been
                                    expecting similar treatment. Moscow had already hinted that
                                    political relations with Iran could be “improved” by means of a
                                    so-called nonaggression or mutual assistance pact or even a
                                    military alliance. The present treaty has therefore been hailed
                                    as a pleasant surprise and as a welcome sign of a definite
                                    easing of the tension. Please see also my despatch No. 1694,
                                    September 28<note n="16" xml:id="d549fn21">Not printed.</note>
                                    and telegrams 120, October 17 and 152, December 1.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Informed diplomatic circles express the view that had Finland
                                    yielded like the Baltic States, Iran’s turn would probably have
                                    come next but the Finnish war—as stated in the Legation’s
                                    telegram No. 40, March 7, 9 p.m.—had a direct influence on the
                                    negotiations. Iran adopted a somewhat firmer tone and avoided
                                    being drawn into political discussions. It seems also certain
                                    that Great Britain and Turkey lent their moral support and
                                    expressed great interest in the maintenance of the <hi rend="italic">status quo</hi> in Iran. On the other hand,
                                    they are said to have advised the Iranian Government to make
                                    every possible concession consistent with her independence and
                                    neutrality in the hope that the Soviets might postpone pressing
                                    any political claims. The mere fact that the treaty was signed
                                    in Tehran instead of Moscow is considered by Iranians as a great
                                    diplomatic victory.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Although the Foreign Minister denies that there are any secret
                                    clauses, it is generally believed that certain promises have
                                    been made by the Iranian Government such as, for example, the
                                    release of Communist prisoners reported in the Legation’s 60,
                                    April 2<note n="16" xml:id="d549fn22">Not printed.</note> and
                                    facilities in case Russia should find it necessary to invoke
                                    articles V and VI <pb facs="0642" n="630" xml:id="pg_630"/> of
                                    the treaty of 1921<note n="19" xml:id="d549fn19">Treaty of
                                        Friendship, February 26, 1921, League of Nations Treaty
                                        Series, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">ix</hi>, p. 383.</note>
                                    (see my despatch 820, February 2, 1922<note n="20" xml:id="d549fn20">Not printed.</note>) it has been tacitly
                                    assumed by Iran that article VI had become a dead letter but it
                                    is clear from two specific references to the 1921 treaty that
                                    the Soviet Union wished to stress the fact that it considered
                                    the old treaty in full force.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>The clauses in the new treaty which worry Iranians most are
                                    those giving the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics the right
                                    to maintain trade representatives with diplomatic immunity and
                                    to establish filling stations. Distrust inspired by recent
                                    tendencies in official Soviet policy is so great that it is
                                    firmly believed these rights will be abused and exploited for
                                    propaganda purposes. So long as Russia’s plans and ambitions
                                    remain obscure and subject to sudden change Iran feels she will
                                    have to keep the closest watch on her every move.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>Comments regarding technical questions will be made by mail.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Engert</hi>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>