<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-11-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1960-11-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="235" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d235">
                            <head>235. Memorandum From the Under Secretary of State for Political
                                Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MLT1" type="from">Merchant</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of State for
                                European Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KFD1" type="to">Kohler</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d235fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 762.00/11–260.
                                    Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> and initialed by both <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName>. Copies were also sent
                                    to <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> and
                                        <persName>Smith</persName>.</note></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1960-11-02">November 2,
                                        1960</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p>As you know, I have had like yourself Berlin on my mind, particularly
                                with reference to (a) whether we should take any nearby initiative
                                in seeking to open private negotiations with the Soviets, and (b)
                                the type of agreement which we should seek if negotiations are
                                resumed in the next few months, either by our own or Soviet
                                initiative.</p>
                            <p>I recently reread your memorandum of July 6, 1960<note n="1" xml:id="d235fn1">In this memorandum, <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> offered four possible assumptions
                                    regarding the evolution of the Berlin problem: 1) Soviet
                                    transmission of a proposal along the lines of its May 9 paper
                                    (see <ref target="#d154">Document 154</ref>); 2) Soviet call for
                                    a new summit meeting; 3) no Soviet move on Berlin until the new
                                    administration took office; and 4) the signing of a Soviet-East
                                    German peace treaty. <persName corresp="#p_KFD1">Kohler</persName> speculated further that “Solution <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>” (see <ref target="#d72fn8">footnote 8, Document 72</ref>) seemed to offer the best
                                    possibilities for an interim solution.</note> on the Development
                                of U.S. Position in Berlin, which deals at some length with Solution
                                    <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>. I am not aware as to the status
                                of the proposed surfacing again of Solution <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss> in the Four Power Working Group of Germany.</p>
                            <p>If talks are not under way with our allies in that forum, I think we
                                should plan to initiate them.</p>
                            <pb facs="0651" n="617" xml:id="pg_617"/>
                            <p>I have come, myself, to the following conclusions: <list>
                                    <label>(a)</label>
                                    <item>In any foreseeable future negotiation with the Soviets the
                                        objective of an interim agreement a la Geneva is neither
                                        realistic nor achievable.</item>
                                    <label>(b)</label>
                                    <item>I think we must accept as an inevitability the signing by
                                        the Soviets and their satellites of a separate peace treaty
                                        with the <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> before twelve
                                        months are up. Parenthetically, I do not regard this as
                                        catastrophic or even calamitous unless by our own
                                        intervening position and statements we make it such.</item>
                                    <label>(c)</label>
                                    <item>Solution <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>, or an
                                        arrangement closely resembling it, if negotiable, would
                                        enable us to live with the signature of a separate peace
                                        treaty by the Soviets, and if abided by on the part of the
                                        Soviets would enable West Berlin to live economically and in
                                        freedom.</item>
                                    <label>(d)</label>
                                    <item>It would be desirable for us to take the initiative in at
                                        least seeking to reopen negotiations on Berlin with the
                                        Soviets, most preferably quietly through diplomatic
                                        channels. This probably is not practicable prior to the new
                                        Administration coming into office. There is in the meantime,
                                        however, much work which could be done if the foregoing
                                        conclusions were accepted within our own Government and with
                                        our three allies principally concerned.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>After you in <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> have given some
                                thought to this matter, I suggest we plan an early meeting, with
                                Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> and
                                    <persName>Smith</persName> invited, with a view to formulating
                                recommendations for the Secretary’s consideration.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>