<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1958-02-14T12:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-02-14T12:00:00-05:00" n="266" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d266">
                        <head>266. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Mission at Berlin</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Germany</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d266fn0">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                762B.00/2—1458. Confidential. Repeated to Washington, Moscow, Paris,
                                London, Warsaw, Prague, and Budapest and pouched to <gloss target="#t_POLAD1">POLAD</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_USAREUR1">USAREUR</gloss> and DCSI <gloss target="#t_USAFE1">USAFE</gloss>. The source text is the
                                Department of State copy.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Berlin</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1958-02-14T18:00:00+01:00">February
                                    14, 1958, 6 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>899. Ref: <gloss target="#t_ourtel1">ourtel</gloss>s Bonn 878, 873, rptd
                            Dept 937 and 931.<note n="1" xml:id="d266fn1">Telegram 878, February 9,
                                summarized in detail <persName>Erich Honecker</persName>’s report to
                                the plenum of the <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss> on the
                                expulsion of <persName>Karl Schirdewan</persName>, <persName>Ernst
                                    Wollweber</persName>, and <persName>Fred Oelssner</persName>
                                from the Central Committee. Telegram 873, February 7, transmitted
                                extracts from the communiqué of the 35th plenum, February 7. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 762B.00/2–958 and 762B.00/2–758,
                                respectively)</note> Thirty-fifth plenum <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss><gloss target="#t_CC1">CC</gloss> actions must be viewed
                            in perspective of general stirrings throughout Eastern European
                            satellites following 20th Party Congress <gloss target="#t_CPSU1">CPSU</gloss> winter 1956. Charges against Schirdewan–Wollweber:
                            specifically refer to their opportunistic interpretation results 20th
                            Party Congress and stressed their advocacy of democratization and
                            relaxation. Removal Schirdewan and Wollweber for reasons given <gloss target="#t_ourtel1">ourtel</gloss> 878 reveals, however, existence
                            in top <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss> leadership since Oct 1956 of
                            strong oppositional group animated by ideas emerging in wake 20th Party
                            Congress <gloss target="#t_CPSU1">CPSU</gloss>. While in Poland
                            oppositional elements led by <persName corresp="#p_GW1">Gomulka</persName> were able establish new regime committed to
                            policies of liberalization, while in Hungary party oppositional elements
                            were unable control course of events resulting bloody repression popular
                            uprising by <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss> Armed Forces, while in
                            Czechoslovakia development oppositional forces nipped in bud early
                            summer 1956 by prompt action of <persName>Nowotny</persName> and
                                <persName>Siroky</persName>,<note n="2" xml:id="d266fn2"><persName>Antonio Novotny</persName>, President of
                                Czechoslovakia, and Viliam Siroky, Czech Premier.</note> fourth
                            variant has taken place East Germany. Oppositional group was formed
                            below surface presumably seeking an occasion bring downfall <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName>’s successful suppression Schirdewan–Wollweber
                            group appears mean relative terminal point of <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss> Party unrest in form stimulated by 20th Party Congress
                                <gloss target="#t_CPSU1">CPSU</gloss> and Polish-Hungarian events
                            Oct 1956.</p>
                        <p>Schirdewan and Wollweber held key positions, Schirdewan as party cadre
                            chief and head of party intelligence service, and Wollweber until Nov 1,
                            as Minister for State Security. Selbmann and Ziller were both top level
                            party leaders in the economic sphere. Since charges speak frequently of
                            “others” involved it may be assumed that strong forces within party
                            hierarchy were involved in opposition. If this group was unable to upset
                                <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName>, then it is unlikely
                            that any oppositional forces can soon develop within <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss> able to bring about his downfall,
                            particularly now that Party Secretariat has been packed by vigorous
                            young <pb facs="0746" n="712" xml:id="pg_712"/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> henchmen. Also we
                            anticipate concentrated effort remove from important positions “others”
                            of Schirdewan–Wollweber group, both in process reorganization economy
                                (<gloss target="#t_ourtel1">ourtel</gloss> 887 to Bonn rptd Dept
                                946)<note n="3" xml:id="d266fn3">Dated February 12, telegram 887
                                from Berlin to Bonn reported that the Volkskammer had on February 10
                                begun consideration of a law to reorganize the state economic
                                apparatus. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>., 762B.00/2–1258)</note> and
                            in new party elections preliminary to 5th Party Congress July, in order
                            fill party and government positions so far as possible with reliable
                                <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> men.</p>
                        <p>According to intelligence reports, downfall Schirdewan–Wollweber has had
                            demoralizing effect on middle and lower party functionaries. However, we
                            do not believe these unsettling effects will be of great moment in the
                            near future, but expect party discipline will be maintained under
                            tightened <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> control.
                            Opposition to <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> personally
                            and to his Stalinist policies nevertheless will presumably persist deep
                            underground within party.</p>
                        <p>Judging by 35th plenum documents, <gloss target="#t_SED1">SED</gloss>
                            leadership under <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> intends
                            intensify communization East Germany thus accelerating course which
                            became discernible last fall. For example, increased pressure on labor,
                            both economic and political, was forecast by Warnke (<gloss target="#t_ourtel1">ourtel</gloss> to Bonn 882 rpted Dept 942).<note n="4" xml:id="d266fn4">Dated February 10, telegram 882 from Berlin
                                to Bonn transmitted excerpts from a speech to the 35th plenum by
                                Herbert Warnke. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.,
                                862B.062/2–1058)</note> Propagation atheism is to be increased.
                            Press is to engage more actively in ideological indoctrination. New
                            measure has been prepared by Politburo to increase party role in East
                            German Army. Honecker reported Politburo desires to transform
                            universities, technical academies and other schools to real
                            Socialist-training institutions and stated “we must more strenuously
                            link and control all forms of art and cultural expression.” Further
                            communization may be partially achieved unless, as purged group
                            apparently feels, policies themselves create retardism difficulties or
                            provoke mass popular reaction. Stalinism has not so far been able to win
                            support of East German population and is unlikely to do so in future
                            even with greater controls and isolation from West which regime intends.
                            Solution of domestic economic problems also unlikely through hard
                            course. Present trend is thus likely increase tensions among all groups
                            East German population.</p>
                        <p>Following are implications <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName>
                            victory: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Prospect of negotiations regarding reunification or related
                                    issues affecting Germany becomes bleaker than ever. One charge
                                    against Schirdewan–Wollweber refers to their not wanting
                                    understand dangers resulting from illusionary desire bring about
                                    German unity at any price. This charge that they were willing
                                    compromise essential Communist features of <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> in interest reunification may
                                    indicate at least that these <pb facs="0747" n="713" xml:id="pg_713"/> top party leaders were skeptical about
                                    intrinsic feasibility endeavor establish separate state in East
                                    Germany.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>In line with current emphasis <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> sovereignty and efforts establish <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> as a real German state,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> might seek
                                    from Sovs opportunities major encroachments on Western position
                                    in Berlin. Soviets, however, are specifically able to control
                                        <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> regime in
                                    these matters. <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss> decisions on
                                    specific encroachments or general effort against Allied position
                                    in Berlin, e.g., by turnover authority <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss>, are difficult to foresee, since they would be
                                    presumably related over-all Soviet policy considerations.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Schirdewan–Wollweber were charged with overestimating
                                    difficulties connected with further socialization <gloss target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and dangers of Hungarian-type
                                    [revolt?] connected therewith. If <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName>, without restraint, presses forward
                                    with harsh measures of continued economic exploitation, with
                                    raising work norms, etc., with repressive measures against
                                    church, and with a doctrinaire Communist line objectionable to
                                    masses of population, then there may come a point when an
                                    exacerbated East German population despite its memories of June
                                    17, 1953, might attempt rise against regime. Doubtless the Sovs
                                    would seek to forestall such a development. But <gloss target="#t_SOV1">Sov</gloss> record in dealing with
                                    Hungarian party in a similar situation does not give one
                                    confidence that Sovs would correctly appraise situation. For
                                    these reasons hard <persName corresp="#p_UW1">Ulbricht</persName> course carries with it prospective
                                    danger major dimensions.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_GB1"><hi rend="strong">Gufler</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>