<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1959-07-15T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1959-07-15T09:00:00-05:00" n="317" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d317">
                        <head>317. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Austria</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d317fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 763.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/7–1559. Secret.
                                Also sent to <gloss target="#t_USCINCEUR1">USCINCEUR</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Vienna</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1959-07-15T15:00:00+01:00">July 15,
                                    1959, 3 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>155. Department pass Defense (for <gloss target="#t_OASDISA1">OASD/ISA</gloss>).</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Negotiations for formation of new Austrian Govt indicate
                                possibility of cuts in present and future defense budgets. According
                                to press, Socialist Party at one point proposed $8 million cut in
                                this year’s budget <pb facs="0842" n="808" xml:id="pg_808"/> and
                                informed sources from Austrian General Staff predict Socialists will
                                demand cut in next year’s budget up to 50 per cent. Country team
                                considers heavy US investment in creation effective military posture
                                in Austria justifies expression of US views on any action which will
                                seriously adversely affect creation such posture.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><p>Country team recommends adoption following US position on these
                                    possible developments:</p>
                                <p>Any significant reduction in Austrian defense budget will
                                    preclude attainment of jointly agreed upon build-up of Austrian
                                    Army and therefore will be tantamount to abrogation by Austrian
                                    Govt of informal agreement reached by the two govts in 1955–56
                                    which led to establishment of military assistance program for
                                    Austria. Should this occur, additional military equipment cannot
                                    be effectively utilized by Austrian Army and further equipment
                                    deliveries will be re-examined with view to prompt and orderly
                                    termination.</p></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>I recommend that I be given discretionary authority to communicate
                                this US position to leading members both political parties in event
                                major reductions in Austrian defense budget appear likely to
                                    materialize.<note n="1" xml:id="d317fn1">The requested
                                    authorization was granted in telegram 205 to Vienna, July 17.
                                        (<hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.) Over the next few weeks,
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MHF1">Matthews</persName> expressed
                                    his concern about the proposed reduction to various Austrian
                                    officials, generally eliciting the reply that the reductions
                                    were not really intended and that talk thereof was only the
                                    result of political bargaining in the attempt to form a new
                                    government. Documentation on this subject is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 763.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>.</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_MHF1"><hi rend="strong">Matthews</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>