<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1960-12-17T17:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1958-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="329" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d329">
                        <head>329. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>Before traveling to New York on October 5 as head of the Austrian
                            Delegation to the United Nations, Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_KB1">Kreisky</persName> met with Under Secretary
                                <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> on October 4. Briefing
                            memoranda for the meeting are in Department of State, Austria Desk
                            Files: Lot 68 D 123. Memoranda of conversation are <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation: Lot 64 D 199.
                            The conversations covered the following topics: the South Tyrol problem,
                            relations between the <gloss target="#t_EEC1">EEC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_EFTA1">EFTA</gloss>, joint Austrian-Yugoslav aid
                            programs, Jewish claims under Article 26 of the Austrian State Treaty,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KNS1">Khrushchev</persName>’s conduct at the
                            United Nations, and the progress of the Austrian Assets Treaty in the
                            U.S. Congress.</p>
                        <p>Prior to the meeting with <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KB1">Kreisky</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Livingston Merchant</persName>, with whom he
                            discussed the South Tyrol problem. After meeting with <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KB1">Kreisky</persName> and the rest of the Austrian Delegation met at a
                            roundtable discussion with a U.S. Delegation led by Deputy Assistant
                            Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_WIB1">Ivan White</persName>. No
                            memorandum of the conversation with <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> has been found. A memorandum of the roundtable
                            meeting, at which Article 26 claims, the Austrian Assets Treaty, dollar
                            bonds, and the South Tyrol were discussed, is <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., Austria Desk Files: Lot 68 D 123.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>