<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-02-14T22:06:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-02-14T22:06:00-05:00" n="171" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d171">
                        <head>171. Telegram From the Department of State to Secretary of State
                                <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> in Mexico and the
                            Embassies in Afghanistan and the Soviet Union<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d171fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> Material,
                                Cables File, State Department Out, Box 115, 2/14–28/79. Sensitive;
                                Niact Immediate; <gloss target="#t_NODIS_1">Nodis</gloss>. Sent for
                                information Immediate to the White House. Printed from a copy that
                                indicates the original was received in the White House Situation
                                Room. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SHW_1">Shinn</persName>;
                                cleared by Stanislaus R.P. Valerga (S/S–O); approved by <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>. (National Archives,
                                RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, P840176–0105) <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> was in Mexico with <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> on a state visit, February
                                14–16.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-02-15T03:06:00+00:00">February 15, 1979, 0306Z</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <p>Tosec 10016/38921. Subject: (S) Death of Ambassador Dubs: Acting
                            Secretary’s Meeting With <persName corresp="#p_DOA_1">Dobrynin</persName>. Ref: Kabul 1098.<note n="2" xml:id="d171fn2">Telegram 1098 from Kabul, February 14, outlines the kidnapping and
                                assassination of Adolph Dubs, American Ambassador to Afghanistan,
                                who was killed on February 14 en route from his residence to the
                                chancery. (National Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D790072–0735)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>1. (S-entire text)</p>
                        <pb facs="0548" n="513" xml:id="pg_513"/>
                        <p>2. Acting Secretary<note n="3" xml:id="d171fn3">
                                <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1">Christopher</persName>.</note> called
                            in <persName corresp="#p_DOA_1">Dobrynin</persName> evening of February
                            14 and, noting that he had been in touch with the Secretary, made the
                            following points:</p>
                        <p>A. I want to express to you in the strongest possible terms our shock
                            over the role played by Soviet advisers to the Kabul police in the
                            events which led to the assassination of our Ambassador to
                            Afghanistan.</p>
                        <p>B. We have reports from highly reliable eyewitnesses that Soviet advisers
                            were intimately involved in the carrying out of the ill-advised assault
                            which resulted in Ambassador Dubs’ death. For example, a <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Embassy officer on the scene saw a
                            Soviet adviser helping arm an Afghan policeman with full knowledge that
                            the assault was to follow momentarily, and despite repeated pleas from
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Embassy representatives that no
                            such assault be launched. We also have a highly reliable report that a
                            Soviet adviser was present in the room in the Afghan Interior Ministry
                            in which the assault was planned.</p>
                        <p>C. I am not accusing the Soviet advisers of responsibility for Ambassador
                            Dubs’ death. I am charging them with failure to heed repeated requests
                            by our personnel that the assault not be undertaken.</p>
                        <p>D. The refusal of consultation by the Soviet advisers on the spot is
                            impossible to justify, given the fact that the life of the American
                            Ambassador was in jeopardy.</p>
                        <p>E. I ask you to furnish us with a full report of the actions taken by the
                            Soviet advisers involved in this tragedy. We have already protested to
                            the Afghan authorities.<note n="4" xml:id="d171fn4">See telegram 1217
                                from Kabul, February 19, in which Bruce Amstutz, <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Chargé to Afghanistan, reported on
                                his meeting with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_AMH_1">Hafizullah Amin</persName>; and telegram 1274 from Kabul,
                                February 20, in which Amstutz reported on Afghani efforts to
                                minimize the role of Soviet advisers in Dubs’s death. (National
                                Archives, RG 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D790077–1181 and
                                D790079–0098)</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>F. I wish to stress to you that this incident may well cause serious
                            damage to our relations. We are already receiving press queries about
                            the role that the Soviet advisers to the Afghan police may have played
                            in the incident. I strongly advise you to recommend that your
                            authorities respond immediately and fully to the presentation I have
                            made.</p>
                        <p>3. On a personal basis the Acting Secretary noted that he had had a
                            number of calls during the day from Capitol Hill and that the depth of
                            concern there was significant. He added that when the fact of Soviet
                            participation came out publicly it could have a devastating effect.</p>
                        <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_DOA_1">Dobrynin</persName> asked for
                            clarification on several points, for which the Acting Secretary read
                            passages directly from reftel. He assured <persName corresp="#p_DOA_1">Dobrynin</persName> that the eyewitnesses involved were US Embassy
                            officials. <pb facs="0549" n="514" xml:id="pg_514"/> When <persName corresp="#p_DOA_1">Dobrynin</persName> asked for names of the Soviet
                            security advisers the Acting Secretary mentioned Sergey Bakhturin.</p>
                        <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_DOA_1">Dobrynin</persName> said he had no
                            details on the matter, only what he had heard on the radio. He promised
                            to report the demarche immediately to Moscow. He expressed his deep
                            condolences not only as a fellow ambassador but as someone who had known
                            Ambassador Dubs personally, especially when he was office director for
                            Soviet Affairs and Charge in Moscow. He said he was sure the Ministry
                            echoed these sentiments. The Acting Secretary replied that this made the
                            matter all the more perplexing to us.</p>
                        <p>6. For Moscow: You should not make any further representations to the
                            Soviets on this matter for now. We will be advising you further.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_CWM_1"><hi rend="strong">Christopher</hi></persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>