<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>244. Telegram From the Embassy in Afghanistan to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v06</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">244</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-12-26T00:52:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-12-26T00:52:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-12-26T00:52:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-12-26T00:52:00-05:00" n="244"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d244">
                <head>244. Telegram From the Embassy in Afghanistan to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d244fn1">Source: Carter Library, National
                        Security Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>
                        Material, Cables File, Afghanistan, Box 1, 12/23–26/79. Confidential;
                        Sensitive; Immediate. Sent for information to Ankara, Athens, Beijing,
                        Islamabad, London, Moscow, New Delhi, <gloss target="#t_USNATO_1"
                            >USNATO</gloss>, Paris, <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC_1">CINCPAC</gloss>,
                        and <gloss target="#t_CINCEUR_1">CINCEUR</gloss>. Printed from a copy that
                        indicates the original was received in the White House Situation
                        Room.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Kabul</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-12-26T05:52:00+00:00">December 26, 1979, 0552Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>8592. <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC_1">CINCPAC</gloss> &amp; <gloss
                        target="#t_CINCEUR_1">CINCEUR</gloss> also for POLAD. Subj: (<gloss
                        target="#t_LOU_1">LOU</gloss>) Massive Soviet Air Operations into Kabul
                    Continue.</p>
                <p>1. (C-entire text)</p>
                <pb facs="0743" n="708" xml:id="pg_708"/>
                <p>2. Summary: Massive Soviet air operations into Kabul began Christmas morning and
                    have not stopped yet. AN–22s, heavy jets, and AS–12s have been observed in large
                    numbers, and the total flights may now exceed one hundred fifty to two hundred.
                    (Most of these aircraft have had Soviet Air Force markings.) No information is
                    available as yet regarding what was on those planes, but we have not yet seen
                    any Soviet troops on the streets of Kabul, nor have we observed any significant
                    increase in the Afghan military’s alert status in the capital. End of
                    summary.</p>
                <p>3. The first of three phases of intensive operations began at about 0400
                    Christmas morning and continued until just before 0700. These flights were
                    probably all AN–22s, since they were the only aircraft seen after dawn broke at
                    about 0600. Numbers of aircraft involved is very difficult to pin down, but at
                    one point an Embassy officer (a former Air Force intelligence officer) could see
                    five AN–22s stacked over the city, despite his limited field of view caused by
                    nearby buildings and trees. Given this density of traffic, we would estimate
                    that a minimum of twenty AN–22s arrived and/or departed Kabul during this first
                    phase, although the number could have been much higher. Some of these aircraft
                    departed the city beginning at about 1100, while at least four were observed
                    still on the ground at 1500.</p>
                <p>4. These operations were just the preliminary, however, as more action appeared
                    to get underway at about 1800 Christmas evening. Heavy jet aircraft were heard
                    arriving in fairly quick succession, but by that hour darkness had fallen and,
                    combined with a low ceiling, it was impossible to determine the exact type of
                    plane. These were definitely heavy jets, however, possibly IL–76 or something
                    somewhat smaller. Again, the numbers of aircraft involved is impossible for us
                    to determine with any certainty but we estimate that about twenty jet transports
                    may have been operating during this second phase.</p>
                <p>5. Finally, at about 2200 Christmas evening, operations switched to turbo-prop
                    aircraft (most probably AN–12s, but possibly AN–22s as well). These seemingly
                    unending flights continued throughout the night and have not stopped as yet. One
                    officer counted more than one hundred and thirty flights between 2200 and about
                    0600 this morning. Since daybreak, we have seen AN–12s and AN–22s in the skies
                    over Kabul.</p>
                <p>6. We have no firm information as yet regarding what was on these aircraft,
                    although some credible reports contend that heavy equipment and ammunition was
                    on yesterday morning’s AN–22 contingent. We have not seen anything resembling
                    mass movements of any Soviet troops who may have been on these planes, but there
                    are routes leaving the airport which the regime could use which would not be
                    visible to innocent observers. It strikes us that this massive sky train could
                    easily <pb facs="0744" n="709" xml:id="pg_709"/> have brought in thousands of
                    personnel, and we will report immediately if any Soviet troops are seen in or
                    around the capital.</p>
                <p>7. After the above was written, a State officer arriving from New Delhi this
                    morning saw about 200 Soviet Army troops around some of the planes at Kabul
                    Airport. He also saw a group of <gloss target="#t_APC_1">APCs</gloss> deployed
                    at the east end of the runway. This leads us to believe that the Soviet troops
                    are probably being deployed directly from the aircraft to waiting
                    transportation, thereby bypassing the main highway into Kabul.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Amstutz</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
