<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sir Frederick Bruce to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d290</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">290</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-06-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-06-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-06-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-06-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="290"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d290">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Sir Frederick Bruce</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-06-20">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 20, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                    your note of the 19th instant, relative to Earl Russell’s despatch of the 2d
                    June, copy of which I left at the State Department, and 1 have forwarded a copy
                    of that note to her Majesty’s government.</p>
                <p>It is not within my province to discuss the general observations therein
                    contained on the despatch in question; but, as the construction I put on its
                    terms differs on one important point from that contained in the note you have
                    done me the honor to address to me, I venture to submit at once the views I
                    entertain of its intention for your consideration.</p>
                <p>In that note it is stated that “her Majesty’s government avow that they will
                    continue still to require that any United States cruisers which shall hereafter
                    be lying within a British port, harbor, or waters, shall be detained twenty-four
                    hours so as to afford an opportunity for an insurgent vessel then actually being
                    within the said port, harbor, or waters to gain the advantage of the same time
                    for her departure from the same port, harbor, or waters.”</p>
                <p>On a mature consideration of the terms of Earl Russell’s despatch, its intention
                    appears to me to be different from the statement contained in the above extract.
                    I understand it to lay down, that the benefit of the twenty-four-hours rule is
                    withdrawn from the so-called confederate vessels-of-war, and that the only
                    exception to this decision will occur under the following circumstances:</p>
                <p>If a vessel of this description is lying in a British port when these fresh
                    instructions are received by her Majesty’s authorities, the said vessel having
                    already entered that port on the faith of previous proclamations, and if a
                    cruiser of the United States is lying in the same port, the said vessel is <hi
                        rend="italic">then and for the last time</hi> to enjoy the benefit of the
                    twenty-four-hours rule.</p>
                <p>According to my view, therefore, the case can only arise once on the receipt by
                    her Majesty’s authorities of the instructions alluded to in Earl Russell’s
                    despatch; nor do I understand, that, except in the particular and improbable
                    contingency above mentioned, there will be any deviation hereafter from the
                    rules of intercourse as practiced towards the vessels-of-war of a friendly
                    state.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with the highest consideration, sir, your most obedient,
                    humble servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>FREDERICK W. A. BRUCE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c</hi>.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
