<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-05-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-05-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="515" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d515">
                        <head><persName type="from">Mr. Pike</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Hunter</persName></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 166.]</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation,</hi>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Hague,</hi></placeName>
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-17"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 17, 1865.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your despatches of the 21st, 22d, 24th, and 28th of April,
                            Nos. 228, 229, 230, and one not numbered; also your two despatches of
                            May 2, Nos. 230 and 231, (also No. 232,) the latter containing the
                            gratifying intelligence of the continued improvement in the condition of
                            the Secretary of State and the Assistant Secretary.</p>
                        <p>The rapid progress of military events during the month of April has taken
                            everybody by surprise for their remarkable completeness. Europe views
                            our final triumphant successes with the liveliest interest. They have
                            alike disappointed the hopes and falsified the confident predictions of
                            the ruling classes here, with few exceptions. The question now uppermost
                            with all is, “What will become of the intrusive emperor of Mexico?”</p>
                        <p>On the reception of the news of the surrender of Johnston with the
                            remaining forces of the rebellion I addressed a note to the minister of
                            foreign affairs, of which I enclose a copy.</p>
                        <p>I have the honor to be, with great respect, your most obedient
                            servant,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>JAMES S. PIKE.</signed></closer>
                        <postscript>
                            <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William Hunter,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary of State, Washington.</hi></p>
                        </postscript>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head><persName type="from">Mr. Pike</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr. Cremers</persName></head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation,</hi>
                                        <hi rend="italic">The Hague,</hi></placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-15"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 15, 1865.</date></dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to call your attention to the
                                fact that the insurrection which has for some time past existed in
                                the southern States of the Union has been finally quelled, and that
                                the so-called confederate government has ceased to exercise or
                                possess any controlling authority in any part of the United States.
                                Its seat of government has been seized, its armies have been
                                destroyed or captured, its military and civil officers are prisoners
                                or fugitives.</p>
                            <p>It is under these circumstances that I beg to suggest to your
                                excellency the revocation of the orders heretofore given to the
                                Netherland colonial authorities to grant certain privileges to
                                vessels sailing under the so-called confederate flag, and the
                                usefulness of instructing those authorities to regard all vessels
                                making use of this flag in future as pirates.</p>
                            <p>You will allow me to observe that this suggestion nas a -direct
                                practical bearing upon the interests of the United States at this
                                moment, inasmuch as an iron-clad steamer called the Stonewall lately
                                left Europe on a tour of depredation upon American commerce, and is
                                supposed to be now in the West India seas, under the confederate
                                flag.</p>
                            <p>I beg, at the same time, to call your excellency’s attention to the
                                proclamation of the late President Lincoln, issued on the 11th of
                                April last, in which he gave notice that the United States
                                considered the time had arrived when they were entitled to claim the
                                same friendly rights and hospitalities for their naval vessels in
                                foreign ports which they themselves are willing to concede to those
                                of all maritime nations, but which have been refused in many cases
                                during the progress of the slaveholders rebellion.</p>
                            <p>I avail myself of the occasion to renew to your excellency the
                                assurances of my high consideration.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>J. S. PIKE.</signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>His Excellency E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Cremers</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Minister of Foreign Affairs</hi>.</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>