<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. van Limburg to to Mr. Hunter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d542</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">542</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-05-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-05-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-05-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="542"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d542">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. van Limburg</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Hunter</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">New York,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-05-16">
                            <hi rend="italic">May</hi> 16, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In the Netherlands, as everywhere else, the news
                    of the assassination of President Lincoln and of the attempt on the life of the
                    Secretary of State has caused a universal shock and deep indignation.</p>
                <p>On the part of the royal government, the minister of foreign affairs would have
                    wished to request Mr. Pike to be so good as to transmit to Washington the
                    assurances of the sorrowful impression caused throughout the Netherlands by this
                    double crime; but the temporary absence of the minister resident of the United
                    States not putting that in his power, it is in virtue of the King’s order, and
                    in accordance with, a resolution adopted by a council of ministers, that I am
                    charged to present without delay to the American government the assurance of
                    lively sympathy in the loss and profound indignation at the crime in which all
                    the Netherlands partake with the King.</p>
                <pb facs="0477" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/>
                <p>I am charged to express, sir, at the same time, the wishes of his Majesty and of
                    the royal government that Divine Providence may preserve the life of Mr. Seward,
                    so precious to the people of the United States.</p>
                <p>In acquitting myself of this duty, sir, I have the honor to repeat to you the
                    assurances of my high consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>ROEST VAN LIMBURG.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William Hunter,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary of State, Washington,D. C.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
