<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Burlingame to to Mr. Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d554</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">554</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-03-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-03-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="554"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d554">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 100.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-03-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">March</hi> 7, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to send correspondence (marked
                    from Ato L) relating to foreign residence at Tangchau.</p>
                <p>From this you will learn—</p>
                <p>1st. How difficult it is to secure, in the first instance, our treaty rights
                    against the prejudices of a powerful class in China,</p>
                <p>2d. The importance of having capable agents, like Dr. McCartee, to arrange
                    successfully disputes which might otherwise lead to serious complications.</p>
                <p>You will observe in the correspondence that the point is made that Tangchau is,
                    by the spirit of the treaty, to be included as a place of residence with Yentai,
                    its dependent port, as in the conceded instances of Canton and Whampoa, Niogpo,
                    and Chenhai, Peintsin and Taku.</p>
                <p>As to the remark in my letter (L) that I will suggest Dr. McCartee’s name, for
                    another position, I have to say that I hope soon to show in person, or by
                    letter, how the government may secure the valuable services of Dr. McCartee,
                    himself consenting, without any additional legislation, in the position of
                    assistant interpreter at Peking.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, &amp;c.,&amp;c.,&amp;c.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Schedule.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <table cols="2">
                        <row>
                            <cell>A.</cell>
                            <cell>From A. Burlingame to D. B. McCartee, asking for documents and
                                forwarding despatch, &amp;c.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Aug. 22, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>B.</cell>
                            <cell>From Prince Kung to A. Burlingame, complaining of Mr. Mills at
                                Tangchaufee, in the matter of renting a house.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Aug. 14, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>C.</cell>
                            <cell>From A. Burlingame to Prince Kung. Will send to United States
                                consul and ascertain the facts.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Aug. 20, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>D.</cell>
                            <cell>From D. B. McCartee to A. Burlingame. Reports on Mr. Mills’s case,
                                and enclosures</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Sept. 9, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>E.</cell>
                            <cell>From C. R. Mills to D. B. McCartee. Statement of the circumstances
                                and opposition experienced in renting the premises at
                                Tangchau.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Sept. 2, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>F.</cell>
                            <cell>From A. Burlingame to D. B. McCartee. Indicates his reasons for
                                up-holding the right to lease property there and encloses despatch
                                to.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Oct. 8, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>G.</cell>
                            <cell>From A. Burlingame to Prince Kung, showing that the opposition to
                                Mr. Mills came from the gentry and not from the owner.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Oct. 3, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>H.</cell>
                            <cell>From D. B. McCartee to A. Burlingame. Reports progress made in
                                arbitrating Mr. Mills’s case.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Oct. 25, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>I.</cell>
                            <cell>From A. Burlingame to D. B. McCartee. Approves of his action and
                                quotes similar cases of opposition to renting houses by
                                foreigners.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Nov. 16, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>J.</cell>
                            <cell>From D. B. McCartee to A. Burlingame. Reports an amicable
                                settlement of Mr. Mills’s case by arbitration, with approval of
                                Chinese local authorities at Tangchau</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Nov. 21, 1864.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>K.</cell>
                            <cell>From D. B. McCartee to A. Burlingame. Resignation of consular
                                functions.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Dec. 31, 1864. </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>L.</cell>
                            <cell>From A. Burlingame to D. B. McCartee. Acceptance of
                                resignation.</cell>
                            <cell rendition="#bottom #nowrap">Feb. 20, 1865.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0500" n="426" xml:id="pg_426"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>[Enclosure A.]</opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            McCartee</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-08-22">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 22, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have only recently learned from Mr. Seward
                        that you have been appointed United States consul for the port of Tangchau
                        and Chifu, and have accordingly informed the Chinese government of the same,
                        in order that they may send the necessary instructions to the local
                        authorities for your recognition. I beg to express my great satisfaction at
                        your appointment, and your previous acquaintance with the duties of the
                        consular office in China will render them easy</p>
                    <p>In this connexion I now enclose copies of a communication, lately received
                        from the Foreign Office, concerning an accusation made by the district
                        magistrate of Punglai of an injustice done by the Rev. Mr. Mills in renting
                        and repairing a house at Tangchau, and of my reply to the same, asking for
                        further time to enable me to ascertain the facts of the case. As this may
                        prove to be a test case, I wish to have such documents as will enable me to
                        prove to the government that he did not violate the treaty in his
                        proceedings.</p>
                    <p>I request, too, that you will express my thanks to Mr. Morrison, her
                        Britannic Majesty’s consul, for his kind exertions in behalf of Mr.
                        Mills.</p>
                    <p>I remain, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ANSON BUKLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>D. <hi rend="smallcaps">Bethune McCartee,</hi> Esq., M. D., <hi
                                rend="italic">United States Consul, Chifre,</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>[Enclosure B.]</opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Prince Kung</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Burlingame.</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date
                                calendar="chinese-era chinese-lunisolar                         gregorian"
                                when="1864-08-14">AUGUST 14, 1864, <hi rend="italic">(Tunchu,</hi>
                                    3<hi rend="italic">d year,</hi> 7<hi rend="italic">th moon,</hi>
                                    13<hi rend="italic">th day.)</hi>
                            </date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Prince Kung, chief secretary of state for foreign affairs, herewith sends a
                        communication.</p>
                    <p>On the 12th instant I received a despatch from the governor of Shantung,
                        enclosing a report from the district magistrate of Punglai at Tangchau,
                        concerning the case of a widow named Hwang, neé Chang, as follows:</p>
                    <p>“Near the east gate stands a house and lot which a foreigner wished to rent
                        or buy, but she had declined, and her husband’s brother, Hwang Tsung-King,
                        who had gone into Chihli province expecting to get an office, had left
                        orders with her not to sell or rent the premises. The foreigner came again
                        in May to talk about it, and was still more urgent for her to sell or lease
                        it, but she declined to do either. What was her surprise, therefore, to see
                        masons and carpenters coming to the spot on the 22d of July for the purpose
                        of pulling down the building. He would not listen to her remonstrances, but
                        declared that if she would neither sell nor lease it, he was still
                        determined to pull it down and repair it as he pleased.</p>
                    <p>“The district magistrate was investigating the matter, when the intendant of
                        Tangchau and Taican circuit sent him notice that Mr. Morrison, the British
                        consul, had informed him that Mr. Mills, an American missionary who lived at
                        Tangchau as a teacher of religion, had stated to him that having recently
                        arrived there with others, for the purpose of teaching, they could get no
                        residences, and had arranged to rent the oil shop of Hwang Tsung-King,
                        outside of the eastern gate, which the owner was willing to lease; but Yuen
                        Tingehm and others of the gentry had united in an envious spirit to spread
                        false reports about the missionaries, and had forbidden the owner of the
                        house to let it.</p>
                    <p>“Thereupon the said district magistrate made very careful inquiry among the
                        gentry, who assured him that they had never spread false reports, nor
                        interfered in this matter. It also appeared that one Hwang Chan-hen, a
                        nephew of the widow, and another man, a constable at the east gate,
                        corroborated the statement concerning the foreigner coming to her house and
                        demolishing the buildings on this lot. I have, therefore, to request inquiry
                        may be made and the case judged.”</p>
                    <p>On receiving the above I examined the 12th article of the American treaty,
                        which reads thus: “Citizens of the United States, residing or sojourning, at
                        any of the ports open to foreign commerce, shall be permitted to rent houses
                        or places of business, or hire sites on which they can themselves build
                        houses or hospitals, churches, and cemeteries. The proprietors shall not
                        demand an exorbitant price, and the citizens of the United States shall not
                        unreasonably insist on particular spots, but each party shall conduct with
                        justice and moderation.” Now, in the present case, the missionary, Mr.
                        Mills, wished to rent the widow Hwang’s house, but she was unwilling to
                        mortgage or sell it and the lot, as <hi rend="italic">the</hi> evidence all
                        proves, as it also does that the neighbors did not interfere. He, however,
                        obstinately bent on renting and repairing the premises, turns round and
                        alleges in his defence that she was willing to lease them, but that the
                        gentry interfered to prevent it, as was stated in his untrue report to Mr.
                        Morrison.</p>
                    <pb facs="0501" n="427" xml:id="pg_427"/>
                    <p>Such conduct clearly violates the provision in the treaty, that no one shall
                        he forced to rent or have his premises encroached on; and further, Mr. Mills
                        has oppressed a desolate widow, which is contrary to the excellent precepts
                        of his religion. Again, the city of Tangchau is not an open port for trade,
                        and if this missionary acts in such a violent manner, despising and
                        ill-treating the people, that it is not improbable that they will resist,
                        and serious trouble may grow out of it.</p>
                    <p>I therefore send this information to your excellency that you may presently
                        require Mr. Mills immediately to reimburse the widow Hwang for the buildings
                        he has demolished, and not allow him again to try to repair any more
                        premises without their owner’s permission, for this is very important. I
                        shall also send instructions to the governor of Shantung to direct the
                        district magistrate at Tangchau <hi rend="italic">to</hi> prevent this
                        attempt to rent, and when he has learned the amount of damage incurred by
                        taking down the buildings, to demand it of Mr. Mills and pay it to the
                        widow.</p>
                    <p>His Excellency <hi rend="smallcaps">Anson Burlingame</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >United States Minister.</hi>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>[Enclosure C]</opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to"
                            >Prince Kung.</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-08-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 20, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to acknowledge your
                        communication of the 14th instant, in which you inform me that the governor
                        of Shantung has reported to you the case of Mr. Mills, an American
                        missionary, who wished to rent premises of the widow Hwang, living outside
                        of the east gate of Tangchau, and had sent masons and other workmen to the
                        place, on the 22d of July last, to pull down and repair the buildings
                        without her consent and against local usages. And further, that a despatch
                        had been received from Mr. Morrison, the British consul, who had stated in
                        it that the owner was willing to lease the premises, but that one Yuen
                        Tingchin, and others among the gentry, had interfered to prevent her doing
                        so.</p>
                    <p>It is to be inferred that as these two statements differ in many respects,
                        there are still some other circumstances not fully explained; and as I have
                        hitherto heard nothing of the case, I will immediately instruct Mr.
                        McCartee, the American consul, to inquire into the matter, and report to me
                        in order to come to a settlement of the matter.</p>
                    <p>In the despatch, under reply, it is stated that such an act as oppressing a
                        desolate widow is contrary to the precepts of religion, and this is quite
                        true; but I have heard that Mr. Mills has been engaged in missionary labors
                        in a quiet way, and that he is a kind and honorable man. The allegations
                        made in the despatch should therefore be thoroughly examined and sifted to
                        learn their truth, and a summary decision not be made on the report of one
                        party; an opinion in which your highness will no doubt concur.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your highness’s obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Imperial Highness <hi rend="smallcaps">Prince Kung</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">&amp;c.,&amp;c.,&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>[Enclosure D.]</opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. McCartee</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            Bmlingame.</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chifu,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-09-09">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 9, 1864.,</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> In pursuance of the instructions contained in
                        your excellency’s despatch of August 22, I have now the honor to report,
                        that I have carefully examined the statements of the Rev. C. R. Mills, and
                        of several Chinese who are still or who have been in his employ during the
                        time of the contention about the premises in dispure, and I would
                        respectfully submit as my opinion, that while there is no evidence that he
                        had any intention to violate the treaty in his proceedings, he unfortunately
                        can produce nothing in the form of a deed of sale or landlord’s agreement,
                        nor any document from the owner of <hi rend="italic">the</hi> premises,
                        Hwang Tsung-King, authorizing their sale or rental. Mr. Mills seems to have
                        felt satisfied of the willingness of the owner, from the assurances of the
                        house-agents, Hwang Chuh-Kian and Chu Sin-Ugan as also of a man named Lin,
                        who professed <hi rend="italic">to</hi> have been sent to him by the latter,
                        but particularly of the broker Ching, a native of Nganhwai province, who
                        professed to act under the authority of a power of attorney, asserted to
                        have been executed by the owner, Hwang Tsun-King, to his wife’s nephew, Wang
                        Tsin-ping, authorizing the latter to sell or otherwise dispose of the
                        property. It does not appear that Mr. Mills ever saw this document, Or that
                        he ever personally met, or had any communication in writing with, either of
                        these two persons, but seems to have taken possession of the premises at the
                        instigation of the aforesaid Ching. This man assured him that the owner was
                        perfectly willing, but feared to incur the enmity <pb facs="0502" n="428"
                            xml:id="pg_428"/> of the gentry of Tangchau, who, it is reported, have
                        formed a league to intimidate and hinder all persons from renting or selling
                        houses to foreigners. Ching advised Mr. Mills to enter and occupy the house
                        at once, promising to obtain a regular bill of sale or lease three days
                        after so doing.</p>
                    <p>Neither rent nor parchase money have yet been paid, and the only document Mr.
                        Mills holds from any of the parties interested is a receipt from Hwang Yuh,
                        and signed by his father with his mark, but not attested by the signature of
                        witnesses. By the advice of Ching Mr. Mills also wrote to the district
                        magistrate of Punglai, inquiring if a deed of sale executed to a foreigner
                        would be considered valid, to which no written reply was received, but a
                        verbal message was sent to him “impeaching the validity of the purchase.”
                        One native witness whom I examined stated that in this message the
                        magistrate also warned Mr. Mills that he would not be responsible for
                        compensation if he (Mr. Mills) allowed himself to be swindled by dishonest
                        men.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Mills then went to Chifu and consulted the. British consul, M. C.
                        Morrison, esq., expressing to him his satisfaction that the owner of the
                        property was willing to transfer it to him. Mr. Morrison, upon the
                        supposition that Mr. Mills had sufficient evidence of this willingness,
                        concurred, as the latter states, “in the propriety of so doing, only
                        recommending that it should not be done if likely to produce a popular
                        rising.</p>
                    <p>“He returned to Tangchau, and, at the request of Hwang Yuh, the tenant,
                        having notified the family of the owner, proceeded to take possession of the
                        premises, and to make alterations and repairs. He was opposed by Hwang
                        Tanming, a nephew of Hwang Tsun-King, who drove away his workmen, whereupon
                        his colleague, Mr. Mateer, and himsef commenced to make the repairs and
                        alterations with their own hands. At this time, thel widow Hwang and the
                        nephew or nephews of Hwang Tsun-King, petitioned the district magistrate
                        against Mr. Mills, accusing him of taking violent possession, &amp;c, who
                        replied by issuing a proclamation, in which he quoted that part of article
                        XII of the United States treaty which prohibits proprietors from demanding
                        exorbitant prices, and citizens of the United States from taking forcible
                        possession of houses, &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Mills proceeded with his repairs, leaving a servant in charge of the
                        premises during his absence or Mr. Mateer’s. An attempt was made by some
                        unknown person to blow up the house with gunpowder, whereupon one of the
                        Chinese witnesses testifies that Messrs. Mills and Mateer armed themselves
                        with a revolver and took turns in watching the premises day and night. Hwang
                        Tan-ning hearing of this, and being apprehensive that a serious disturbance
                        might arise, went there, and calling Mr. Mills aside, told him to go on with
                        the alterations, assuring him that sooner or later the premises would be
                        conveyed to him in a legal manner.</p>
                    <p>This account is derived from the statement of Mr. Mills, and of Chinese who
                        now are, or were at the time, in his employ. Tangchau is distant from Chifu
                        about 165 li, or 50 English miles by the ordinary road, which renders it
                        impossible for me to get from it the evidence of the witnesses for the
                        plaintiff, or to communicate with and receive replies from the authorities
                        relating to this affair, without such delay as will preclude the possibility
                        of forwarding the results to Peking by the steamer for Tientsin, which is
                        expected to arrive this evening.</p>
                    <p>It appears to me that this case is likely to prove, as your excellency
                        remarks, a “test case;” and if Mr. Mills, whether innocently or otherwise,
                        has violated the treaty and shall be compelled to evacuate the premises, and
                        pay damages to the injured parties, the result will be most disastrous to
                        foreign influence in Tangchau, and calculated to embolden the gentry of that
                        city in their endeavors to prevent the missionaries and others from renting
                        or obtaining building sites, not only in that place but in every other where
                        their influence extends.</p>
                    <p>You are doubtless aware that for more than twenty-one years I have held the
                        appointment of missionary physician and translator, under the same society
                        of which Mr. Mills is a clerical missionary. It might be supposed,
                        therefore, that I should wish him to be successful in this suit, and if it
                        should appear that his course is one which ought justly to be sustained, I
                        shall be most happy to contribute all the energies I possess to the
                        furtherance of this cause. But the question of justice or injustice, as in
                        duty bound, I respectfully submit to your excellency’s decision, and beg to
                        subscribe myself,</p>
                    <p>Very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>D. B. McCAKTEE,</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Excellency Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">Anson Burlingame,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">United States Minister, Peking.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>P. S.—I enclose a copy of a communication from the district magistrate of
                            Punglai, addressed to the missionaries at Tangchau, calling their
                            attention to an order coming, in the first place, from the foreign
                            office, requiring him to summon Mr. Mills, and order him to obey the
                            treaty by evacuating the premises if he had been guilty of taking
                            forcible possession.</p>
                    </postscript>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>2d P. S.—September 14. I had hoped to be able to send the formal
                            statements of Messrs, Mills, Mateer, and Crawford, and of the Chinese in
                            Mr. Mills’s employ, but they have not reached me. I, however, send a
                            copy of Mr. Consul Morrison’s despatch to the intendent of circuit,
                            which has been kindly placed at my disposal. In a private note he
                            remarks: “The impression which (without a <hi rend="italic"
                                >personal</hi> knowledge of the circumstances) Mr. Mills’s narrative
                            gives me is, that his view of the case is probably the correct one. I
                            think if he remain quietly <pb facs="0503" n="429" xml:id="pg_429"/> in
                            possession for a little while, that the opposition will die away, which
                            appears to have emanated from the gentry and scholars, more than from
                            the owners of the property.”</p>
                        <p>The names of the gentry mentioned in Mr. Morrison’s despatch are Yuen
                            Ting-chin, Mu Yerch-King, “and others, men of distinction in this place,
                            who, on behalf of themselves and the principal property owners, have
                            resolved at a public meeting that no more real estate shall be conveyed
                            to foreigners.” This remark is an extract from Mr. Mills’s
                            representation to the British consul, but I have no documentary evidence
                            in proof of it, I am able only to send Mr. Mills’s informal statement of
                            the case at this time.</p>
                    </postscript>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>D. B. McC.</signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>[Enclosure E.]</opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Statement of Rev. C. R. Mills.</persName>
                    </head>
                    <p>Early in the spring, when the renting of the property was first proposed, I
                        called on the owner at his house in reference to the matter. A public
                        meeting of the gentry had just been held in reference to my renting another
                        house in the city; and, as the district magistrate in formed me, they had
                        proposed offering violence to foreigners; while others have told me that
                        they declared to him that, though the owner of the house in question desired
                        to rent it to foreigners, they would not permit it. As I had avowed that my
                        object was the negotiation about the house, it was from this cause, I
                        believe, that I had difficulty in obtaining an inter view. At last I
                        received a message from the owner that the matter should be intrusted to a
                        neighbor, Mr. Lin, who would communicate with me, and two days after this
                        man told me the property was rented. He also remarked that he had heard the
                        owner say he had no personal objections to renting to foreigners, as they
                        would probably pay a good price; the only real difficulty was the opposition
                        of the gentry, but that the tenant might sublet to me if he chose. </p>
                    <p>About the same time Hwang Yuh, the tenant, came to my chapel voluntarily,
                        and, in the presence of Wang Hwa-yuen, affirmed that he had no objection to
                        my coming, provided the owner was willing; but, as he did not put this in
                        writing, I did not act upon it, and gave up for the time all expectations as
                        to the house. In the mean time the owner left the city.</p>
                    <p>Some time after two real estate agents, named Hwang and Chu, called to say to
                        me that they came to open negotiations for the house, and, as I believed,
                        with authority to do so; for one of them, then or soon after, said that the
                        owner had been written to upon the subject, and his answer was expected.
                        They were informed that I preferred to rent rather than buy, and were told
                        that I knew the property in question had been bought for 600 strings of
                        cash. This remark accounted for their not returning, I fully believe, as
                        they had promised to do. Another period elapsed, when a third agent, named
                        Ching, came to me, proposing to sell the property; and, as it seemed
                        impossible to rent, I reluctantly opened negotiations with him for buying
                        it. After some bargaining the price was agreed upon at 800 strings of cash
                        in the presence of two men, Lin and Chang. He claimed an extra allowance as
                        broker because I was a foreigner, and I subsequently agreed to pay him eight
                        strings of cash, with which he was satisfied, and the bargain was closed in
                        the presence of Chang and Lin. No intimation was given that the transaction
                        was not on behalf of the owner, and the agent Ching particularly stated that
                        he had been heard from. I certainly believed it to be a <hi rend="italic"
                            >bona fide</hi> bargain, and so did all the Chinese witnesses.</p>
                    <p>I offered to pay the money at once on his giving up the title, but he
                        objected, which I attributed to a suspicion he might have that I wished to
                        get the document and then refuse to faithfully pay the money, and not to any
                        invalidity in the purchase. It might also be an honest mistake as to the
                        feasibility of getting a title for a foreigner, for he asked me to write to
                        the district magistrate and inquire whether a title could be given to a
                        foreigner. I regarded this as gratuitous, but did so to remove the agent’s
                        scruples, and he promised to apprise this officer of the sale of the
                        property. The district magistrate made no written reply to my letter, but
                        sent a verbal message to me impeaching the validity of the purchase.</p>
                    <p>I then investigated the matter with the agent, who then told me that the
                        owner, owing to the opprobrium attaching to the sale of land to a foreigner,
                        chose to use the name of a certain relative in this transaction named Wang
                        Tsin-ping. such transfers being frequently made in China, and strongly urged
                        me to move at once in to the house, assuring me that the title should
                        afterwards be given. He added that this relative had a claim on the
                        property, his grandfather having lent money and taken this land as payment
                        for his debt.</p>
                    <p>Before following this advice I went to Chifu to consult with Mr. Morrison,
                        the British consul, (there being no United States consul near.) and told him
                        my purpose to take possession of the premises, according to the suggestion
                        of the agent. He concurred in the propriety of the step, only recommending
                        that it should not be done if likely to produce a popular rising.</p>
                    <p>I returned and proposed to take possession of the house, informed the tenant
                        so, and asked him to let the owner’s family know; but, at his request, I
                        told them. Hwang Tang-ming, <pb facs="0504" n="430" xml:id="pg_430"/> a
                        nephew of the owner, objected, but I have no evidence that he acted by
                        authority, and he had declined to negotiate early in the spring, when I
                        wished to rent it. Some angry words passed at this interview, at which I
                        probably showed too much feeling. The next day, June 22d, I went to the
                        house, and in this man’s presence Mr. Mateer removed a window from it,
                        whereupon he left as in a passion. The next day he came and ordered some of
                        the workmen to leave; but in the afternoon, in company with another member
                        of the family, he returned and offered to settle the matter for me. I agreed
                        to do so if he would put his offer in writing, but he declined doing that,
                        and, as a third course, proposed to leave the whole matter to the decision
                        of the district magistrate. I consented, and we repaired to the office for
                        that end, but the magistrate refused to see us. I then proposed to accept
                        the same terms from the prefect; but he declined going to that officer
                        unless I would lead the way to his office, which I objected to, not being a
                        Chinese subject. We therefore did not visit the prefect.</p>
                    <p>The next day, June 24th, two land agents, named Hwang (a distant relative of
                        the owner) and Chu, came to my house early, and requested me to postpone my
                        repairs on the house. They said they came with authority, and were sent by
                        the nephew. I accordingly stopped work; but, toward evening, they came again
                        to say that the title could not be made out then, but directed me to go
                        forward with the repairs. I believed this to be authoritative.</p>
                    <p>A day or two after the nephew, Hwang Tang-ming, met me there, and we
                        conversed together without any ill feeling, when he intimated that some
                        difficulty existed which he wished to explain privately to my assistant.
                        They then held a private conversation, when Hwang said that the only fear
                        was that the district magistrate, taking advantage of a misunderstanding
                        existing with the owner, Hwang Tsun-King, since last winter, would make a
                        pretext of the sale to injure them. They both urged me to call on him in
                        their behalf to request him to settle the case. I did so, but he failed to
                        execute the promise he made to settle it. Shortly after my teacher called on
                        the family, when this nephew and others of the household promised him that
                        they would draw up a paper authorizing me to proceed with the repairs, but
                        it was never sent.</p>
                    <p>My relations with the renter, Hwang Yuh, have uniformly been friendly. He had
                        sublet the house to one or more persons, one of whom received a compensation
                        from me for moving out. Hwang Yuh has consistently expressed the utmost
                        willingness that I should occupy the property, and has given me a receipt
                        signed by his father-in-law for the 20,000 cash which i paid him for damages
                        done to the garden during the alterations made on the premises.</p>
                    <p>I have made this statement at Chifu, and there is consequently a want of
                        precision in the dates; but I have given all the facts, so far as I know,
                        necessary to a clear understanding of the case, and am not conscious of
                        having withheld any facts because they might not promote a decision in my
                        favor.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>CHAS. R. MILLS.</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chifu</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1884-09-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 2, 1884</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>P. S.—I have just received from a man at Tangchau, in whom I have entire
                            confidence, what purports to be a message from the district magistrate,
                            recommending me to hand the eight hundred strings of cash to the consul,
                            with the request that he would in turn hand it to the intendent of
                            circuit, who was to be requested to transmit it to the district
                            magistrate, who would then offer to pay it to the owner and give me a
                            title to the property.</p>
                        <p>I started for Chifu the next day in order to pay the money to Mr.
                            Morrison, in compliance with these suggestions, and had actually called
                            on him for that purpose, when I learned that D. B. McCartee had been
                            invested with authority to examine the case, which would probably render
                            such a course inexpedient at present. I may add that my informant stated
                            that the district magistrate wished it might not transpire that this
                            action was proposed by him.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>C. R. M.</signed>
                        </closer>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>[Enclosure F.]</opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">Mr. Burlingame</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                            McCartee.</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-10-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 8, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I beg to acknowledge your despatch No. 2 of
                        the 9th ultimo, with its enclosures, referring to and explaining the renting
                        of the premises outside of the east gate of Tangchau by the Rev. C.J.R.
                        Mills These papers together with your own clear statement, have put me in
                        possession of those facts and inferences which have enabled me to present
                        the case to the foreign office in as favorable a manner as they permitted. I
                        have not yet received an answer to my proposition to Prince Kung to refer
                        the settlement of the case back to you and the local authorities at
                        Tangchau, but as. he may notify the latter of this proposal before he
                        replies, I send you a copy of my despatch to him that you may see how I have
                        stated the case. In it I maintain the right of foreigners to live at
                        Tangchau city by treaty, and base this right on the city and its dependent
                        port being both included in the intention of the treaty. Tientsin and Taku
                        Canton and Whampoa, Ningpo and Chinhai, a.e all similar cases in this
                        respect, <pb facs="0505" n="431" xml:id="pg_431"/> except that at Tangchau
                        no consuls have opened their offices. When the treaty was made in 1858, its
                        capabilities as a port where ships could anchor and trade be carried on were
                        not well known, and it has since proved to be less commodious than was
                        expected.</p>
                    <p>As soon as I receive an answer from the Chinese officials I will furnish you
                        with a copy and such directions as may be necessary.</p>
                    <p>I am, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="italic">,.</hi> ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>D. B. <hi rend="smallcaps">McCartee,</hi> Esq., M. D., <hi rend="italic"
                                >United States Consul, Chifu.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure G]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-10-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 3, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to inform you that on the
                        19th of August I sent orders to D. B McCartee, the United States consul at
                        Tangchau, and he has, in return, furnished me with the following report
                        respecting the case of Rev. C. R. Mills renting a house and lot:</p>
                    <p>“It appears that when Mr. Mills desired to rent the old garden and premises
                        belonging to the widow Hwang, situated outside the east gate of Tangchau, he
                        employed one man named Ching. with three others as brokers, whose occupation
                        was to arrange the leasing of houses, and they inquired of the owner Hwang
                        Tsun-King, and informed Mr. Mills of the conditions on which the place could
                        be rented, and that the owner, Hwan Tsun-King, was quite willing to come to
                        an arrangement. These brokers said that he was willing enough, but as the
                        gentry might make difficulty when they heard of it, perhaps the best way
                        would be to make the repairs first, and that the contract for the terms of
                        the lease could be drawn up after they (the foreigners) had moved in.</p>
                    <p>“It was in this way that the brokers induced the two missionaries to begin
                        making repairs; and they knowing that both the owners of the property and
                        the brokers were men of respectable character, while they were much crowded
                        in their present residence, and the/hot weather was approaching, and had
                        even come, accordingly came with workmen to repair the buildings. The work
                        had gone on for a few days, when Hwang Tan-ming, a nephew of the owner, came
                        to the place and compelled the workmen to leave, and also entered his
                        complaint before the district magistrate of Punglai. The missionaries then
                        continued the, repairs themselves, as it was difficult to stop them midway;
                        and the nephew likewise expressed himself as quite willing to allow Mr.
                        Mills to proceed with the repairs, and that afterwards a regular contract
                        could be made with the owner. When these repairs had been completed a man
                        named Hwang Yuh, who had lived on the premises as a gardener, complained
                        that the workmen had injured and trampled down his garden while doing the
                        job; which, when Mr. Mills learned, he compensated him for, by paying him
                        the sum of 20,000 cash ($27,) and took his receipt for the money, dated
                        August 29, now in Mr. Mills’s possession.</p>
                    <p>“It is evident from these statements that the landlord and Mr. Mills had a
                        good understanding with each other, and it was owing measurably to the
                        arrangements and advice of the brokers that no regular lease was made out.
                        Mr. Mills had no desire to oust any person by violence, nor had he the least
                        intention to insult or oppress the widow, Hwang, in anything that he
                        did.”</p>
                    <p>In presenting this report, I may observe that the port of Tangchau is
                        mentioned in the foreign treaties among the ports where foreigners can
                        reside for trade, although, owing to the discommodities of the anchorage at
                        the city of Tangchau, the merchants carry on their trade at Yentai, and
                        their vessels anchor there. Moreover, foreigners have resided at Tangchau
                        itself several years, and leased houses there, so that it cannot be regarded
                        as a violation of treaty stipulations to do so. The consul has forwarded to
                        me several documents connected with this affair; and as the whole matter
                        seems to be much mixed up, and there are discrepancies in the statements, I
                        think the best way will be for me to refer it back to the consul to manage:
                        and I request that the Foreign Office will likewise instruct the local
                        magistrates to meet him, and let them consult upon, and amicably settle, the
                        whole question between them in a spirit of mutual consideration.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be. Sir. your highness’s obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>His Imperial Highness <hi rend="smallcaps">Prince King</hi>. <hi
                                rend="italic">&amp;c.,&amp;c.,&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure H.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Chifu</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-10-25">
                                <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 25, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to inform your excellency
                        that, on the 29th of September, I received a communication from the Rev.
                        Messrs. Mills and Mateer, American citizens, residing at Tangchau, informing
                        me that they “understood that prosecution had been instituted before Chinese
                        officers against Chang Kan-chin, on account of his having attempted to rent
                        houses” for them in Tangchau, and soliciting for him “protection,that he may
                        not be delivered up to Chinese officers”</p>
                    <pb facs="0506" n="432" xml:id="pg_432"/>
                    <p>In replying to this communication, I informed these gentlemen that, although
                        by treaty the United States government had secured to its own citizens
                        exemption from the jurisdiction of the Chinese officers, “the Chinese
                        government had never surrendered its jurisdiction over its own subjects, and
                        that, should it appear that any of them are accused of infraction of their
                        own laws, the officers of the United States of America have no power to
                        interfere to prevent their arrest or punishment;” but that “if it can be
                        shown that they suffer injury on the part either of the government or of
                        individal Chinese for their lawful employment under American citizens,” that
                        “this will be an infraction of article XXV of the treaty of Tientsin, and
                        will constitute a proper subject on which to demand redress. Such redress
                        may, however, come too late to remedy the evils complained of. I also
                        reminded Messrs. Mills and Mateer “that the consular representative of the
                        United States of America is stationed at Chifu, fifty miles from Tangchau;
                        that he has no man-of-war or other force at his disposal; and that his
                        ability to render aid, or to enforce the provisions of the treaty must
                        depend in a great measure upon the prudent conduct and cordial support and
                        co-operation of his fellow-citizens.” I also forwarded to them a document in
                        Chinese, to be given to Chang Kan-chin, (enclosure No. 1,) in which, after
                        reciting the provisions of article XXV of the American treaty of Tientsin, I
                        request from the local officers their aid and protection for him while
                        peaceably pursuing his employment according to the treaty. At the same time
                        I advised Messrs. Mills and Mateer that Chang “is a Chinese subject, and
                        that we have no right to prevent his arrest for an alleged crime against the
                        laws of China;” that “even should we suspect that the alleged crime was but
                        a pretext for persecution on account of his lawful connexion with the
                        citizens of the United States of America, it might be very difficult to
                        obtain such proofs before the trial as would justify the foreign authorities
                        in interfering;” and that if, in their opinion, “the man is in danger of
                        arrest, the safest plan would be to send him at once to this consulate, and
                        let the Chinese officers make their requisition for him uponUS,” &amp;c.</p>
                    <p>I have also the honor to acknowledge the receipt (on the 18th) of your
                        excellency’s despatch of the 8th ultimo, enclosing a copy in Chinese of your
                        despatch to Prince Kung, proposing to him to refer the settlement of Mr.
                        Mills’s case back to myself and the local authorities at Tangchan. On the
                        20th instant I received an official visit from Pwan, intendant of circuit,
                        &amp;c., who carne to propose that he should send for the district
                        magistrate of Pung-lai, together with the men, Wang Tsin-ping and Ching,
                        referred to in my previous despatch to you, and that I should send for Mr.
                        Mills, when the dispute could be examined and decided by the public officers
                        of the two nations, acting in conjunction, agreeably to article XXVIII of
                        the treaty. I informed him that I had just received your excellency’s
                        despatch, in which you stated that you had proposed to Prince Kung to refer
                        the settlement of the case to the local authorities and myself, and that I
                        thought it would be better to await the answer from the Foreign Office. He
                        replied that the prefect of Tangchau was then absent from the city, but
                        would probably return in about ten days, and that I might fix upon any time
                        after that for the joint trial. I told him that by the time specified I
                        thought I should be able to make some arrangement of the kind proposed.</p>
                    <p>About an hour after he left me I received a letter from Mr. Mills, at
                        Tangchau, dated October 17, enclosing a document from the district
                        magistrate of Punglai, addressed to the American missionary, (or
                        missionaries,) and sent to Mr. Mateer’s house on the 15th. In it he says
                        that he has received instructions from the intendant to eject Mr. Mills
                        summarily from the house, and restore it to Mrs. Hwang-Chang, and, after
                        accusing him of breach of treaty and gross irregularity, requests him to fix
                        a day upon which he will leave the house, and enjoins him not to delay. Upon
                        the receipt of this letter, I addressed the intendant, reciting the
                        stipulations of articles XI and XXVIII of the treaty, reminding him of the
                        proposition he had made to me with reference to a joint trial; acquainting
                        him with the fact of the magistrate’s order to Mr. Mills, which I quoted in
                        full; and telling him that it appeared to me to be irreconcilable with his
                        own proposition the day before, as well as contrary to the treaty. In his
                        reply the intendant states that his proposition to have the district
                        magistrate bring Wang Tsin-pin, &amp;c, and that I should cite Mr. Mills to
                        Chifu for a joint trial, was according to article XII,-which prohibits
                        citizens of the United States from “compelling [persons] to rent, and from
                        taking forcible possession,” &amp;c, (Chinese text;) that his order to the
                        magistrate was given because Mr. Mills had taken forcible possession of a
                        house without having had any agreement to rent it, and has already occupied
                        it four months and more; and that he had been ordered by the Foreign Office
                        to command the magistrate of Punglai to transmit orders to Mr. Mills to
                        respect the treaty, which did not allow compulsory renting of people’s
                        houses, and that if Mr. Mills had forcibly taken possession of one he must
                        leave it, in obedience with the treaty; and that, therefore, his (the
                        intendant’s) orders to the magistrate were not contrary to the treaty, nor
                        incompatible with his proposal to me. (See enclo-surd No. 2.)</p>
                    <p>Yesterday I again addressed the intendant on the same subject. (Enclosure No.
                        3.) Whether his proposition to me was an afterthought, and in consequence of
                        a wish to have a new trial—if, indeed, any trial could be said to have taken
                        place—and thus avoid the charge of having failed to conform to the
                        stipulations of article XXVIII; or whether it was intended to take advantage
                        of Mr. Mills’s absence to recover possession of the house, I am unable at
                        present to say. I am fully convinced, however, that there is a powerful
                        party in Tangchau <pb facs="0507" n="433" xml:id="pg_433"/> which is
                        determined to oust, not only Mr. Mills, but all other foreigners from the
                        city; and this of itself would be enough to prevent the landlord from
                        executing a lease of the premises to Mr. Mills. Under present circumstances,
                        it would be quite impracticable to induce witnesses to give testimony which
                        might draw down upon them the vengeance of the league of the gentry; and
                        that not only the magistrates, as Mr. Crawford deposed, (see my last
                        despatch, enclosure A,) but the intendant also is intimidated by them, and
                        feels it to be his safest course to side with the opposition. The previous
                        magistrate of Punglai district lost his office in consequence of a
                        disturbance among the literary candidates, in which he was beaten by them;
                        and the intendant himself, when we first spoke of this affair, related to me
                        the ill treatment he had experienced at the hands of the people of
                        Wai-hai-wei, where he went last year to establish new custom-house
                        regulations. He was surrounded by several thousand men, who compelled him by
                        threats of violence to write a proclamation upon a stone tablet, assuring
                        him that no alteration should be made in the duties.</p>
                    <p>Since writing the above, I have received (October 26) a second despatch from
                        the intendant, (enclosure 4,) from which you will learn that the Chinese
                        officers have prejudged the case, and that a joint trial would be of no
                        avail. If I had legal proof that Mr. Mills had rented the house in question,
                        or if he had even obtained a document from any person pretending to be
                        authorized to act for the owner, I might have some hope of making it appear,
                        at least, that he had not acted wilfully, but had been deceived.
                        Unfortunately, I am in possession of no such proofs; and from the tone of
                        the intendants despatches it is evident that the Chinese officers do not
                        consider the question as an open subject at all; while, from what he says in
                        reference to article XII of the treaty, it appears as if his object in
                        proposing that I should send for Mr. Mills to come to Chifu was solely to
                        have him punished by the consul according to the laws of the United States
                        of America.</p>
                    <p>As I am obliged to prepare this despatch and its enclosures for the steamer
                        hourly expected, and am entirely without assistance, so that I must do the
                        whole of the translating from and into Chinese, and the copying, (save only
                        of the Chinese documents,) I beg your excellency to excuse any appearance of
                        haste in the present communication, and believe me that I have the honor to
                        be, very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>D. B. McCARTEE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. A. B<hi rend="smallcaps">urlingame</hi>, <hi rend="italic">United
                                States Minister at Peking,</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure I.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Peking,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-11-16">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 16, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have received your despatch of the 25th
                        ultimo, with its enclosures, and have carefully read them, and beg to
                        express to you my thanks for the careful and judicious manner in which you
                        have acted in this difficult case, and for your lucid statement of its
                        present condition.</p>
                    <p>So far as I can see, the wisest course to follow now is to wait for the
                        Chinese officials to move. If they insist on Mr. Mills vacating the
                        premises, the right of residing at Tangchau at all must then be settled, and
                        that involves their power to enforce a treaty stipulation, for they may not
                        quote one part of an article so as to nullify another part of the same
                        article; if Americans have the right to live in that city, the first part of
                        article XII must needs be effectual to enable them to obtain houses
                        somewhere in it.</p>
                    <p>A similar dispute about obtaining dwellings occurred at Canton in 1846, in
                        which, however, the United States authorities had a better case on their
                        side; for a lease had been obtained from the owner, who had readily
                        consented to a profitable disposal of his house and lot on the strength of
                        the treaty; yet he was imprisoned and harshly treated, and forcibly
                        prevented renting the house. Another man died in prison, about the same
                        time, for the same offence against the seclusive pride of the gentry of
                        Canton. Subsequently the opposition died away, and our countrymen succeeded
                        in obtaining good residences, and I hope a similar change will be seen at
                        Tangchau and Yentai.</p>
                    <p>If the Chinese still insist on Mr. Mills leaving these premises, they should
                        offer him others, and allow the owner of these to arrange with him, on
                        equitable terms, for the repairs laid out on the place. From what you
                        remark, it now seems unlikely that any good would come from an attempt to
                        settle the matter by the local authorities and yourself, and it will be
                        advisable to wait further developments both there and in the capital.</p>
                    <p>The principle which you have expressed in your reply to Mr. Mills respecting
                        the interference of the United States authorities in behalf of Chinese
                        subjects is the correct one; the Chinese government has never surrendered
                        its jurisdiction over its own subjects, and all we can do in behalf of those
                        who may be unjustly accused or punished is to represent the facts in their
                        case as opportunity presents. We can make no demands, nor require any com
                        pensation or satisfaction for their wrongs.</p>
                    <p>I am your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ANSON BURLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>D. B. McC <hi rend="smallcaps">irtee,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">United
                                States Vice Consul. Chifu</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0508" n="434" xml:id="pg_434"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure J.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chifu,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-11-21">
                                <hi rend="italic">November</hi> 21, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> I have the honor to inform your excellency
                        that the suit of the widow Hwang-Chang against Rev. C. E. Mills, on an
                        action of trespass and ejectment, has been amicably settled both parties
                        having agreed at my suggestion to refer the case to arbitration. At the
                        instance of the district magistrate of Punglai, the representatives of Hwang
                        family nominated as their referee a Chinese named Li, (who I was afterwards
                        informed was the assistant magistrate of the district,) and Mr. mills
                        nominated H. G. Howlett, esq., (who was connected with the British
                        consulate.) An indenture was drawn up in duplicate, and signed by Mr. Mills
                        and by the representatives of the Hwang family, by which Mr. Mills
                        covenanted to vacate the house on condition that the magistrate should rent
                        for him a temple, which he specified, and the Hwang family to pay Mr. Mills
                        400 taels for the improvements put upon the house, and he to pay a specified
                        rent to the family until he left the premises.</p>
                    <p>I enclose a copy of the bond given to the district magistrate and myself by
                        the representatives of the widow Hwang, and also a corresponding bond
                        executed by the Rev. C.R. Mills. Their originals are filed in the office of
                        the magistrate and in this consulate. I also enclose a copy of the indenture
                        made between Mrs. Hwang and Mr. Mills in duplicate, signed by both parties,
                        and witnessed by their referees, each party retaining a copy; also a copy of
                        a note from the magistrate asking for an abatement of the award, and of my
                        reply declining to do so. His worship returned to Tangchau on the 19th
                        instant, and I expect in a few days to receive a despatch from him
                        acknowledging the adjustment of the case; when I get it I shall again
                        address your excellency, and forward copies of the correspondence.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>D. B. McCARTEE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Burlingame</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >&amp;c.,&amp;c.,&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Enclosure K.]</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consulate,</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chifu,</hi>
                            </placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1864-12-31">
                                <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 31, 1864.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> More than a month has now elapsed since I had
                        the honor to address your excellency, announcing the amicable settlement of
                        the suit brought by the widow Hwang-Chang against the Rev. C. R. Mills, and,
                        as yet, I have heard nothing further from his worship, the district
                        magistrate of Punglai. From private letters from Tangchau, I am led to
                        believe that the complainants represented by the widow have come to the
                        conclusion that it is more to their advantage to allow Mr. Mills to continue
                        to occupy the house in dispute at the rent specified in the bond, than to
                        pay him the sum awarded as remuneration for the improvements he put upon the
                        house. I think it may be safely concluded that the affair is now finally
                        settled.</p>
                    <p>As it was solely with reference to the adjustment of this case that I
                        consented to act as vice-consul, I beg, now, respectfully to announce to
                        your excellency that I have written this day to the consul general,
                        requesting that officer to transmit the Department of State my resignation
                        of the office. This is the fourth time that I have had the honor conferred
                        upon me without solicitation, and it is gratifying to my feelings to learn,
                        through the secretary of legation, that the manner in which I have
                        discharged the duties of the office,<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> during the
                        brief term for which I have held it, has met your approval:</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to enclose a communication from Mr. Mills, relative to
                        outrages committed upon the graves in the American cemetery at Tangchau,
                        sent at my request, as I thought I might wish to make some use of it in the
                        discussion with the district magistrate. Finding, however, that he was much
                        more likely to be conciliated than my previous correspondence with the
                        intendant had led me to expect, I did not think it advisable to complicate
                        the discussion by bringing forward the desecration of the tombs at that
                        time. I now send Mr. Mills’s statement, as Dr. Williams suggests that it may
                        be of use to preserve among the archives of the legation for future
                        reference.</p>
                    <p>His worship, the magistrate of Punglai, was very anxious that I should write
                        to your excellency in reference to his conduct in this affair, in such terms
                        as would induce you to make favorable mention of his name to the foreign
                        office. I am very happy to testify that I found him,much more reasonable,
                        and apparently anxious to settle the affair amicably, and in accordance with
                        the spirit of the treaty, than the intendant, who evidently desired to press
                        the case to a decision adverse to Mr. Mills, and to drive him from
                        Tangchau.</p>
                    <p>In taking official leave at this time, I beg to assure your excellency that,
                        although the requirements with reference to consular officers are now such
                        that it is impossible for me to retain the office under my present
                        circumstances, yet, should any exigency arise in which my long residence in
                        this country, and my acquaintance with the written and spoken language of
                        China, may render my services desirable to promote the interests of the
                        United States in China, I shall always be ready and willing to render such
                        services to the extent of my ability.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to remain, sir, very respectfully,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>D.B. MccARTEE.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>Hon. A. <hi rend="smallcaps">Burlingame</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                >&amp;c.,&amp;c.,&amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0509" n="435" xml:id="pg_435"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>[Enclosure L]</opener>
                    <head>
                        <persName type="from">J Mr. Burling ame</persName> to <persName type="to"
                            >Mr. McCartee</persName>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Peking</hi>,</placeName>
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-02-20">
                                <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 20, 1865.</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your despatch of December 31, 1864, has been
                        received. It informs me of the successful settlement of one of the most
                        difficult cases ever presented for diplomatic action. Your conduct
                        throughout the negotiations is deserving of special commendation. The
                        department will learn, as I do, of your resignation with regret, and will
                        appreciate your patriotic efforts in the past, as well as your proffer of
                        similar services in the future.</p>
                    <p>I shall have the honor to suggest your name to the government in connexion
                        with a place better suited than the one which you have had for the exercise
                        of your rare qualities as a Christian, patriot, and scholar.</p>
                    <p>I have the honor to be, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>ANSON BUKLINGAME.</signed>
                    </closer>
                    <postscript>
                        <p>D. B. <hi rend="smallcaps">McCartee,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic"
                                >Chifu,</hi>
                        </p>
                    </postscript>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
