<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Perry to  to Mr.
                                Seward</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d586</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">586</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-01-31T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-01-31T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                    <term ref="recPsPNFSAm6ZOPcW" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85081306" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maritime</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-01-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-01-31T00:00:00-05:00" n="586" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d586">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Extract.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Perry</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                                Seward</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 161.]</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-01-31">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 31, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir:</hi> The debates in the Spanish senate, which
                            have run over a period of about twenty days, have been unusually
                            interesting.</p>
                <p>On the question of the reply to the Queen’s speech, senators of the
                            opposition have taken occasion to review the whole policy of the
                            government.</p>
                <p>Attacked on the questions of the abandonment of Santo Domingo, and the
                            plan for the relief of the treasury by the adherents of O’Donnell, with
                            that leader at the head, and on the queston of the enciclical letter of
                            the Pope and general-policy of ministers toward Rome and Italy by the
                            new Catholic orators, I have rarely witnessed a debate in which there
                            has been more vigor and persistence shown in the attack, or a cooler and
                            more solid ability displayed in the defence. The orators of the
                            government have had the best of the argument on every point, but the
                            struggle has been severe.</p>
                <p>The name of the United States has been used as a bug-bear by the orators
                            of the opposition, who claimed that the occupation of Santo Domingo by
                            the Spaniards was the only way of averting the annexation of Dominica to
                            the United States, and the consequent rum of Spanish interests in the
                            West Indies. The Duke of La Torre, the same captain general of Cuba who
                            made the arrangement with the Dominican general, Santara, was the
                            loudest in this argument.</p>
                <p>The Marquis of Valdeterrazo, minister of Spain to London in 1860, made
                            the declaration of which I enclose a translation.</p>
                <p>The Marquis of the Habana, (General Concha,) who has been twice captain
                            general of Cuba, and is now out with O’Donnell, defended the policy of
                            abandonment, and said that the United States had long ago refused the
                            annexation of Dominica, (referring to the Cazneau treaty,) and that
                            Spain had taken them up only after they had been refused by other
                            powers.</p>
                <p>The Duke of La Torre (General Servaro) spoke strongly in favor of a
                            declaration by Spain that the slave trade is piracy, and wanted steps to
                            be immediately taken for the abolition of slavery in Cuba.</p>
                <pb facs="0546" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/>
                <p>The Marquis of Havana desired the extinction of slavery, but preferred
                            measures like those which Brazil had taken to suppress the slave trade,
                            and which had been sucessful in two years.</p>
                <p>He said that if there were anything to be apprehended from the side of
                            the United States, or from any quarter, as a military man he must say
                            that he thought the policy of Spain ought to be to consecrate her power
                            as much as possible; and the possession of Santo Domingo added no
                            strength to Spain but was a decided source of weakness. The resources of
                            Cuba were uselessly employed in Santo Domingo, and they might be needed
                            in that island itself. * *</p>
                <p>The debate was closed last evening, and the reply to the Queen’s speech
                            being put to the vote, passed the senate by a vote of 102 for and 58
                            against the policy of the government.</p>
                <p>This is not a direct vote upon the bill for the abandonment of San
                            Domingo; this bill not being before the senate but before the lower
                            house, to come up afterwards to the senate; but the question is thus
                            already debated and settled indirectly, so far as the senate is
                            concerned, the house having done little eels except to adjourn over from
                            day to day to give the members an opportunity to be present at the
                            senate debates, and allow ministers also to be all present in the upper
                            house.</p>
                <p>This great trial of parliamentary strength over, all the interest now
                            centres in the lower house, and the senate adjourns over to allow
                            ministers to be all present in the other house, as well as the senators
                            themselves.</p>
                <p>But the question of San Domingo is already prejudged, and the bill for
                            the abandonment is already virtually carried by the government.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * * * *</p>
                <p>With sentiments of the highest respect, I remain, sir, your obedient
                            servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HORATIO J. PERRY.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>Hon. <hi rend="smallcaps">William H. Seward,</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of State, Washington.</hi>
                    </p>
                </postscript>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <head>[Translation.]</head>
                    <p>A mistake has been made in saying that the United States have made a
                                treaty of annexation with Santo Domingo. This is not the fact.</p>
                    <p>When I was in London I was authorized by the government of her
                                Majesty to occupy myself in this question, all the necessary
                                facilities being conceded to me to engage not only the English
                                government but also the French, to associate with the Spanish
                                government to carry out a demonstration to be made in the bay of
                                Samana. Being authorized in this way, I conferred with the English
                                government on the serious damage which would be caused by the
                                occupation of the bay of Samana by the Anglo American
                                government.</p>
                    <p>The English government understood it in this light, but did not wish
                                to bind itself unless the French government associated itself also.
                                I addressed myself to the latter, making a full explanation of the
                                evils, the inconveniences, and the damage which the commerce of the
                                three nations would receive if the United States should found an
                                establishment or raise a fortification in that harbor. The French
                                government understood the gravity of the question, associated itself
                                with the English and Spanish governments, and the result was that
                                the three made a demonstration towards the bay of Samana, at the
                                same time giving instructions to their representatives at Washington
                                to manifest the displeasure which the three governments would feel
                                if the treaty of which we had advice, but whose tenor was not known,
                                should be carried into effect.</p>
                    <p>The English government some time after, having given the necessary
                                orders for the uniting of the maritime forces of the three powers
                                with the above-named object, obtained the first copy of this treaty,
                                which it remitted to the government of her Majesty.</p>
                    <p>In this treaty the annexation was not established; that which was
                                alone established was the right to raise a fortification and to
                                found a national establishment in the bay of Samana by means of a
                                compensation and other services to the republic of Santo Domingo.
                                For this reason the Duke de la Torre said very opportunely that the
                                occupation of Samana is highly important, and that the Spanish
                                government should not abandon a post of so much value, not only for
                                the governments of England and France, but much more for the
                                interests of Spain. In this I agree with the Duke de La Torre, and I
                                say to the ministers that the abandonment of Santo Domingo is a
                                danger; and I also say to the ministers that they ought <pb facs="0547" n="473" xml:id="pg_473"/> to consider well to what
                                an extent the security of our provinces beyond sea is compromised by
                                the abandonment of Santo Domingo. The government is still in time to
                                avoid the evils and consequences which this measure may produce; and
                                let it not be said that this is but an echo, for in order to defend
                                Porto Rico and the island of Cuba, more expense will have to be
                                borne than is necessary to preserve Santo Domingo.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
