<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Seward to to Mr. Burnley</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1865p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1865-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1865-01-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recF3ysi5EbmSbV2R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85071077"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Jurisdiction</term>
                    <term ref="recsNQ59E979BphyM" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009675"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1865-01-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1865-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="93"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d93">
                <head>
                    <persName type="from">Mr. Seward</persName> to <persName type="to">Mr.
                        Burnley</persName>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State,</hi>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington,</hi>
                        </placeName>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1865-01-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">January</hi> 25, 1865.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my note to Lord Lyons of the 20th of
                    December, 1863, requesting through his lordship that, in virtue of the
                    provisions of the treaty stipulations on the subject, her Majesty’s government
                    would issue the necessary warrant for the delivery of John C. Braine, H. A.
                    Parr, John Parker Locke, David Collins, George Robinson, John Wade, and others,
                    charged with the commission of piracy and murder in the American steamer
                    Chesapeake, I have now the honor to state that information has been received at
                    this department from the consul of the United States at St. John’s to the effect
                    that, upon the discharge of the parties arraigned under the charge of piracy
                    committed on board of the before-named Chesapeake, new warrants were issued by
                    Justice Parker for the apprehension of all the offenders known to have been
                    concerned in the transaction; that these warrants were not, and, perhaps, could
                    not have been, served at the time, by reason of the escape of the criminals to
                    parts unknown.</p>
                <p>It having recently come to the consul’s knowledge that four or five of these
                    fugitives had returned within the jurisdiction of New Brunswick, he has notified
                    the high sheriff, in whose hands these warrants now are, of the fact.</p>
                <p>It is hoped that every facility may be afforded by the provisional authorities
                    for their apprehension and commitment; and I now have the honor to request,
                    through you, sir, that upon the apprehension and commitment of the said
                    fugitives, or any of them, within the province of New Brunswick or elsewhere,
                    within the jurisdiction of her Britannic Majesty, her Majesty’s proper
                    authorities will be pleased to issue the necessary warrant for the delivery of
                    the said fugitives to any person duly authorized by the government of the United
                    States to receive them, in order that they may be brought back to the United
                    States for trial.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, with high consideration, sir, your obedient servant,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>WILLIAM H. SEWARD.</signed>
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    <p>J. <hi rend="smallcaps">Hume Burnley,</hi> Esq., <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,
                            &amp;c., &amp;c</hi>.</p>
                </postscript>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
