<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-03-16T12:15:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-03-16T10:30:00-05:00" n="118" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d118">
                    <head>118. Summary of Conclusions of a Presidential Review Committee
                            Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d118fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> Library, National Security
                            Council, Institutional Files, Box 68, <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss>–058, 3/16/78, Monetary Situation. Secret; Sensitive.
                            The meeting took place in the White House Situation Room. <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> sent the Summary of
                            Conclusions to <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> under
                            cover of a March 18 memorandum in which he noted “that <persName corresp="#p_SCL_1">Schultze</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SJR_1">Schlesinger</persName> agree with <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1">Blumenthal</persName> on the recommendations.”
                            (Ibid.)</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" from="1978-03-16T10:30:00-05:00" to="1978-03-16T12:15:00-05:00">March 16, 1978, 10:30 a.m.–12:15 p.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Dollar Crisis</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">State</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Cyrus Vance</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_CRN_1">Richard Cooper</persName> Under Secretary
                            for Economic Affairs</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Defense</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BH_3">Harold Brown</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Treasury</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1">Michael Blumenthal</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SAM_1">Anthony Solomon</persName> Under Secretary
                            for Monetary Affairs</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Energy</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SJR_1">James Schlesinger</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Council of Economic Advisors</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_SCL_1">Charles Schultze</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Federal Reserve Board</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MGW_1">William Miller</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">White House</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Zbigniew Brzezinski</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ADL_1">David Aaron</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry Owen</persName>
                        </item>
                        <item>David Rubinstein</item>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">
                                <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                            </hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DT_1">Timothy Deal</persName>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">SUMMARY OF CONCLUSIONS</p>
                    <p>The group agreed that we have a potentially serious problem on our hands. In
                        recent months, the dollar’s depreciation against major currencies has
                        accelerated and markets have become increasingly disorderly. The trend is
                        continuing despite public efforts to turn the tide. We have used up $3
                        billion through intervention in exchange markets. Additional intervention by
                        other countries has totaled $20 billion. Private capital is beginning to
                        flow out of the US, and in the 4th quarter of 1977 net capital outflows
                        amounted to $10 billion. New purchases of US securities by Saudi Arabia and
                        other <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> states have declined
                        markedly.</p>
                    <p>The main factors behind these developments are: (1) our large trade and
                        current account deficits, and (2) a lack of confidence abroad in the US
                        economy, relating to concerns about both energy and inflation. The US trade
                        deficit will probably deteriorate further this year to $30–32 billion
                        despite earlier more optimistic forecasts. The US <pb facs="0386" n="351" xml:id="pg_351"/> business and banking community and foreign investors
                        are not confident that the US is able or willing to deal with the dollar
                        crisis. In their view, we are not acting forcefully to correct fundamental
                        problems.</p>
                    <p>The group saw the following possible consequences if the US could not halt
                        the dollar’s decline:</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> would increase oil prices.</hi>
                        <gloss target="#t_OPEC_1">OPEC</gloss> might either raise them directly or
                        begin to denominate them in non-US currencies. Either action would have an
                        adverse impact on the US and world economy.</p>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Domestic inflationary pressures would intensify.</hi> A
                        depreciating dollar raises domestic prices. (Depreciation to date in 1978 is
                        projected to raise prices by 0.5% by the end of the year.) The dollar’s
                        decline is partly responsible for the stock market’s malaise. These
                        developments could further erode business confidence and dampen private
                        investment flows. Eventually, depreciation-induced inflation might have a
                        snowballing effect leading to still further adverse consequences.</p>
                    <p>3. <hi rend="italic">US leadership abroad in economic policy and foreign
                            affairs would suffer.</hi> The trade negotiations would probably fail;
                        the North/South dialogue would deteriorate. The international economic
                        system would enter into a decline with a serious impact on Allied solidarity
                        and the probability of adverse social and political consequences in key
                        Allied countries.</p>
                    <p>The group agreed that the Administration must act now to deal with the dollar
                        problem. We cannot afford to wait until self-correcting forces (e.g., a
                        depreciating dollar leading to increased exports) take hold. Immediate
                        action would forestall more drastic measures later. The group agreed on the
                        following steps to deal with the dollar crisis:</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Energy.</hi> The President should next week call in
                        appropriate Congressional leaders and energy conferees and inform them in
                        general terms that because of the deteriorating international economic
                        situation, if they are not able to agree on an energy tax program by late
                        April, he will be compelled to restrict oil imports by other means. The
                        public announcement of such a meeting should be carefully phrased to avoid
                        the appearance that the President has given Congress an ultimatum, and
                        should be linked to the other measures described below. If the Congress does
                        not act in a month or so, we should be prepared to impose a fee on imported
                        oil. The group agreed that there are strong national security grounds for
                        this action. Consequently, if we present our case effectively and give
                        Congress advance warning of our intentions, the risk of Congressional action
                        to withdraw the President’s power in this area should be manageable.<note n="2" xml:id="d118fn2">
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> wrote “?” in the margin
                            adjacent to this paragraph.</note>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0387" n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Anti-inflation program.</hi> The President should
                        announce an anti-inflation program. The group agreed that this program
                        should emphasize the anti-inflation controls in our original economic
                        strategy and would not entail any basic change in our overall economic
                        objectives. We would continue on a growth path designed gradually to reduce
                            unemployment.<note n="3" xml:id="d118fn3">
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> wrote “ok” in the margin
                            adjacent to this and the next two paragraphs.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Export promotion efforts.</hi> The Administration would
                        announce a series of measures to stimulate exports.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Next Steps:</hi> The President will be given separate
                        action memoranda recommending anti-inflation steps, export promotion
                        measures, and the meeting with Members of Congress. The <gloss target="#t_PRC_1">PRC</gloss> recommended that the President announce
                        all three actions simultaneously.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>