<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-05-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-05-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="132" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d132">
                    <head>132. Decision Memorandum From Secretary of the Treasury <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1">Blumenthal</persName> and Acting Secretary of
                        Commerce <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Harman</persName> to President
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d132fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName>
                            Library, White House Central Files, Subject File, Box TA–6, TA 3
                            1/1/78–5/31/78. No classification marking. Sent to <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> under cover of a May 30
                            memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1">Blumenthal</persName>, who
                            wrote: “We decided at <gloss target="#t_EPG_1">EPG</gloss> last Thursday
                            [May 25] to have the attached decision memorandum on <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> forwarded immediately, as the Ways
                            and Means Committee is presently marking up the tax bill. It is in
                            keeping with the Export Task Force package to be presented to you on
                            June 15 and has the endorsement of the Task Force’s membership.” (Ibid.)
                            Minutes of the May 25 <gloss target="#t_EPG_1">EPG</gloss> meeting were
                            not found.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1978-05-30">May 30, 1978</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Export Tax Incentive</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>We have been fighting for repeal of the Domestic International Sales
                        Corporation (<gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss>) on the grounds that it
                        is not cost-effective. <pb facs="0438" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/> The
                        existing <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> rewards companies for export
                        profits, not for export sales. The rewards go primarily to big
                        multinationals that export anyway. At best, the additional exports created
                        in 1978 by <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> are only about $3 billion,
                        while the revenue cost is about $1.1 billion.</p>
                    <p>These arguments are still valid. Yet there appears to be virtually no chance
                        that Congress will terminate the <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss>
                        program this year. Twenty-eight of the 37 members of the Ways and Means
                        Committee have indicated their opposition to any cutback in <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> benefits. It appears, however, that some
                        of those members are willing to talk compromise. <hi rend="italic">The
                            Export Policy Task Force has developed an export tax incentive proposal
                            that contains the elements of a compromise which reconciles the needs of
                            trade policy with the needs of tax policy, and holds the possibility of
                            turning this issue into a victory for the Administration.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Operational Constraints</p>
                    <p>The policy considerations stem primarily from our growing balance of payments
                        problems:</p>
                    <p>—The U.S. badly needs to recoup export market shares. Adjusted for inflation,
                        U.S. exports have not grown since 1974; the volume of U.S. manufactured
                        goods has actually declined. The rest of the industrial world, by contrast,
                        has seen a 12 percent growth in export volume since 1974;</p>
                    <p>—Incentives will have to be provided to medium and small-sized firms if we
                        are to augment the export accomplishments of large multinationals;</p>
                    <p>—In the eyes of the business community, a credible and effective export
                        policy must include an appropriate incentive for exports;</p>
                    <p>—The Congress views a tax incentive as the simplest, fastest and most nearly
                        self-executing method of export stimulation. Rightly or wrongly, it is in no
                        mood to jettison <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> in the absence of an
                        alternative.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Proposed Alternative</p>
                    <p>The Export Policy Task Force’s basic proposal would: (1) <hi rend="italic">reduce</hi> the benefits of the present <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> program; (2) <hi rend="italic">restructure</hi> the
                        benefits to emphasize export sales rather than export profits; and (3) <hi rend="italic">use part</hi> of the revenue saving to create, within the
                            <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> framework, a direct export
                        incentive targeted on small and medium-sized companies. The specifics of
                        this proposal are summarized at Tab A.<note n="2" xml:id="d132fn2">Tab A,
                            attached but not printed, is an undated memorandum entitled “Specifics
                            of Export Policy Task Force Proposal.”</note>
                        <hi rend="italic">The revenue cost totals $750 million, a $350 million
                            reduction from the present <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss>
                            program.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>This proposal is designed to make the <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss>
                        significantly more cost-effective while keeping the number of legislative
                        changes to a minimum. The Congress has no appetite for a complicated
                        revision of <pb facs="0439" n="404" xml:id="pg_404"/>
                        <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss>. Moreover, the more complex the
                        Administration proposal, the less certain we can be of the final
                        outcome.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                        <gloss target="#t_MTN_1">MTN</gloss> Considerations</p>
                    <p>
                        <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> itself, and any new variant, is
                        contrary to the thrust of our international negotiations to limit export
                        subsidies. Further, the adoption of a new incentive for small and
                        medium-sized firms will be seen as inconsistent with our vigorous
                        enforcement of the U.S. countervailing duty statute against the export
                        subsidies used by the <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>, Canada, Brazil,
                        Colombia, and other nations. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SRS_1">Strauss</persName>, however, believes that while the recommendation
                        might be awkward to our international posture, it would not be fatal to the
                        negotiations. <hi rend="italic">A smaller <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> is clearly more acceptable to our trading partners
                            than a larger <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss>.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Recommendation:</hi> That you authorize Treasury, in
                        consultation with Commerce and others, to negotiate a revised <gloss target="#t_DISC_1">DISC</gloss> with the Congress along the lines
                            suggested.<note n="3" xml:id="d132fn3">
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> did not indicate his
                            preference with respect to this recommendation; however, see <ref target="#d135">Document 135</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed><list>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1"><hi rend="strong">W. Michael
                                            Blumenthal</hi></persName><note n="4" xml:id="d132fn4">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1">Blumenthal</persName> signed
                                        “Mike” above this typed signature.</note>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_HS_1"><hi rend="strong">Sidney
                                        Harman</hi></persName><note n="5" xml:id="d132fn5">
                                        <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Harman</persName> signed
                                        “Sidney” above this typed signature.</note>
                                </item>
                            </list></signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>