<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>163. Memorandum From the Special Representative for Trade Negotiations
                    (Strauss) to President ) to President Carter</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">163</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-09-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources">Oil crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051682"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade liberalization</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="rec2r0t2UkWjO2ZV1" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004011274"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Subsidies</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="rec7VZnpkBjTjtzfd" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033350"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Textiles</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recm0kKdhKGPVOMsn" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85022963"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Chemicals</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic relations</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="petroleum-and-natural-gas" lcsh-match="no_match">Natural gas</term>
                    <term ref="recYoVAQrTzsBsOmP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="new-international-economic-order" subject="new-international-economic-order" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067395" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">International economic relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-09-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-09-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="163"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d163">
                <head>163. Memorandum From the Special Representative for Trade Negotiations
                        (<persName corresp="#p_SRS_1">Strauss</persName>) to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d163fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1"
                            >Carter</persName> Library, Records of the Office of the Staff
                        Secretary, Presidential File, Box 103, 9/25/78 [1]. Secret. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> wrote at the top of the page:
                        “Bob—The harder &amp; better we bargain now, (obviously) the better in
                        Congress next year. J.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-09-22">September 22, 1978</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>A Political Assessment Of The Tokyo Round</item>
                </list>
                <p>This memorandum will enlarge upon the brief reference to the Tokyo Round and its
                    negative aspects in last week’s summary.<note n="2" xml:id="d163fn2">The summary
                        was not found.</note> For sometime now, I have wanted to give you a personal
                    report on the negotiations. I have been reluctant to add to your concerns, which
                    I know are many, but I sense that the time has arrived to give you my judgment
                    of where we are and where we are heading.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Background.</p>
                <p>Twenty months ago, as you know, the Tokyo Round was in danger of foundering. The
                    political will of key participants—an indispensable ingredient for such an
                    ambitious undertaking—had been sapped by the oil crisis and the ensuing global
                    recession. Repeated efforts by the previous Administration to revitalize the
                    negotiations had failed. Many <pb facs="0542" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/>
                    governments, faced with growing protectionist pressures, wished the negotiations
                    would go away.</p>
                <p>At the Downing Street Summit, under your leadership, we began the task of moving
                    the negotiations from a state of inertia to one of action. In the past sixteen
                    months, I can report, we have continued to make slow but steady progress. The
                    status of each phase of the negotiations was described in detail in the
                    “Framework of Understanding”<note n="3" xml:id="d163fn3">See <ref target="#d144"
                            >Document 144</ref>.</note> which was reported to the recent Bonn
                    Summit.</p>
                <p>Our work has been painstaking, because of the recalcitrance of many of our
                    trading partners. Concessions have been difficult for everyone concerned. Trade
                    liberalization is never easy, but never so difficult than in the face of
                    domestic economic problems and the resulting mounting protectionist pressures.
                    Many serious issues remain, including several which could jeopardize the entire
                    negotiations. I am far from certain, but nevertheless, I am hopeful that with
                    luck it will be possible to conclude the international negotiations by December
                    15—or 60 days thereafter—and then turn our full attention to the task of
                    domestic implementation.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Domestic Implementation.</p>
                <p>Our present plan is to submit the domestic implementing legislation to Congress
                    by mid-March of next year, for consideration and decision under the
                    up-or-down-vote-no-amendments procedures set forth in the Trade Act. If such a
                    schedule is adhered to, the legislation will likely be voted on by the House and
                    Senate next summer.</p>
                <p>The package of implementing legislation which we would send to the Hill next
                    spring would, under the most favorable circumstances, be as complex and
                    controversial piece of legislation as any to be considered by the next Congress.
                    Because of the nature of the negotiations, it is not yet possible to describe
                    with precision what the final package will contain. There still exists the risk
                    that in some critical areas, most notably agriculture and subsidies, we will
                    fall unacceptably short of what we must have to sell the deal at home. The
                    reason would be simply that our trading partners, despite their sincere efforts,
                    have been unable to deliver the necessary concessions to satisfy our
                    agricultural constituents even though it will exceed what has been done before
                    or what they expected this time.</p>
                <p>If there is to be a deal, there is no question that it will contain both pluses
                    and minuses. It will address subjects which are both politically sensitive and
                    disparate, ranging from tariffs to government procurement policies, from customs
                    valuation to the difficult problem of subsidies and countervailing duties.</p>
                <pb facs="0543" n="508" xml:id="pg_508"/>
                <p>Throughout these negotiations I have consulted closely with the Congress, and
                    sought to respond to the needs of individual Members. Wherever possible, we have
                    attempted to include in the package features to add political buoyance to offset
                    those negative aspects we could not avoid. At the present time, because we do
                    not yet know fully what concessions our trading partners will be able to
                    deliver, it is not possible to say whether the package is a net plus or net
                    minus in terms of domestic political acceptability. It is probably one of those
                    issues that will hurt in the short run and be praised in later years.</p>
                <p>As our consultations with Congress have progressed, I have noted a steady
                    chilling in the atmosphere on Capitol Hill, exemplified most recently in the
                    soundings we have taken regarding obtaining an extension of the waiver on
                    countervailing duties. Congressional concerns over import penetration in
                    sensitive sectors, such as steel and textiles, combined with large trade
                    deficits, have created an atmosphere which is the worst imaginable in which to
                    seek approval of the results of the Tokyo Round. I cannot overemphasize this
                    negative attitude that prevails, even among some of the most ardent supporters
                    of a liberal trade policy.</p>
                <p>It is my present view that the final package will be adopted, but only after a
                    bruising and costly fight. It will pit the relatively small and disorganized,
                    although highly respected, constituency which supports liberal trade against a
                    formidable coalition of labor and management from numerous industries, most
                    notably textiles, steel, dairies, and chemicals. It will require an effort on
                    the part of the Administration not a great deal less than was mounted in the
                    case of the Panama Canal Treaties<note n="4" xml:id="d163fn4">Reference is to
                        the <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> administration’s effort
                        to secure ratification of the Panama Canal Treaties concerning Panamanian
                        control and operation of the Panama Canal. The United States and Panama
                        signed the two treaties in September 1977, but the Senate did not vote to
                        ratify them until March and April 1978.</note> and the natural gas
                        compromise,<note n="5" xml:id="d163fn5">Reference is to the agreement on the
                        pricing of natural gas reached in April 1978 by members of Congress with
                        help from <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> administration
                        officials. (Steven Rattner, “Conferees on Energy Agree on Gas Pricing,
                        Ending Long Impasse,” <hi rend="italic">The New York Times,</hi> April 22,
                        1978, p. 1) On September 19, the Senate rejected an attempt by opponents of
                        the bill to send it back to a House–Senate conference committee for changes.
                        (Richard L. Lyons, “Senators Reject Attempt To Scuttle Gas Compromise,” <hi
                            rend="italic">The Washington Post,</hi> September 20, 1978, p.
                        A1)</note> and the chance of success is little, if any better. Needless to
                    say a failure would be a major setback for the Administration and for the
                    credibility of the United States in its international economic relations. It
                    could also trigger a world-wide protectionist retrenchment that would endanger
                    the western world’s economic prosperity as well as political stability.
                    Obviously, we must go forward. While the agreements themselves certainly will
                    not dra<pb facs="0544" n="509" xml:id="pg_509"/>matically change the patterns of
                    world trade they will help move in the right direction.</p>
                <p>I assure you we are going forward aggressively and will continue to press for the
                    best result possible but you should be aware of the probable domestic political
                    costs that Congressional consideration will entail.</p>
                <p>All of this, of course, must be evaluated by you in the broader context of
                    Administration policy, and from a longer, historical perspective. In the coming
                    weeks and months as we proceed we must evaluate, and re-evaluate, the results of
                    the Tokyo Round and reach our decision as to how best to proceed. It was to
                    alert you to the problems I foresee and to encourage such an evaluation by the
                    appropriate advisors that I have written this memorandum. Accordingly, I am
                    sharing copies of this memorandum with <persName corresp="#p_BWM_1"
                        >Blumenthal</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>,
                        <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CRN_1"
                        >Cooper</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_ESE_1"
                    >Eizenstat</persName>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
