<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-12-01T09:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-12-01T09:00:00-05:00" n="228" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d228">
                    <head>228. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d228fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> Library,
                            National Security Affairs, Staff Material, Special Projects, <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry Owen</persName>, Box 23, Memcons:
                            12/79–5/80. Confidential. Drafted by Beaudry and cleared by <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName>. The meeting took place in
                                <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName>’s office.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1979-12-01T09:00:00-05:00">December 4, 1979, 9 a.m.</date>
                        </dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss>–Summit Relations</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <item>
                            <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> Secretary General Emile van
                            Lennep</item>
                        <item>Stephen Marris, Economic Adviser to Secretary General van
                            Lennep</item>
                        <item>Tom Alexander, Special Assistant to Secretary General van
                            Lennep</item>
                        <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SH_1">Herbert Salzman</persName>,
                            U.S. Representative to the <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry Owen</persName>, Special
                            Representative to the President for Economic Summits</item>
                        <item>Robert M. Beaudry, Director, <gloss target="#t_EURRPE_1">EUR/RPE</gloss>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> said he was
                        particularly sensitive to the concerns expressed by the smaller
                        industrialized countries that they were excluded from the Summit process and
                        that he wished to talk to Secretary General van Lennep to see if they cannot
                        minimize the problem. <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> said he
                        would arrange in the preparation for the Summit and at the Summit itself to
                        take account of the interests and sensitivities of the smaller countries. He
                        suggested that van Lennep could help by organizing an <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> meeting immediately after the June 21–22
                            Summit<note n="2" xml:id="d228fn2">The Venice <gloss target="#t_G7_1">G–7</gloss> Summit took place June 22–23, 1980.</note> at which he
                        would be prepared to brief the other members and discuss the outcome of the
                        Summit with them.</p>
                    <p>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VLE_1">Van Lennep</persName> expressed his
                        appreciation for <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName>’s attitude
                        noting that the U.S. has always had an open approach to summitry unlike some
                        of the other Summit countries. He suggested that <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> might wish to broaden the scope of
                        his proposed scope and concentrate on the <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> as an institution rather than aiming to satisfy specific
                        small countries. <persName corresp="#p_VLE_1">Van Lennep</persName> believes
                        it would be helpful if the Summit communique could refer to the <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> since he was anxious that the solidarity
                        and cohesion of the <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> not be damaged by
                        the impression that the organization had two classes of members. <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> indicated that he would let
                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SH_1">Salzman</persName> know in advance of
                        the substance of issues being prepared for the Summit. In this connection he
                        noted that the <gloss target="#t_IEA_1">IEA</gloss> would make a major
                        contribution to the Summit. The <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> is,
                        thereby, directly involved in Summit preparations. <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> noted that the <gloss target="#t_IETG_1">IETG</gloss> would submit its report at the end of
                        March. <persName corresp="#p_VLE_1">Van Lennep</persName> said <pb facs="0698" n="663" xml:id="pg_663"/> that the <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> Ministerial has not yet been set but consideration was
                        being given to the first days of June.<note n="3" xml:id="d228fn3">The
                                <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> met at the Ministerial level
                            June 3–4, 1980.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Turning to the other traditional Summit topics, <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> suggested that trade matters would probably not take up
                        too much time. Monetary reform would probably be limited to some discussion
                        of the substitution account and North/South issues (food and energy) would
                        receive minimum attention. The traditional section on macro-economic policy
                        presents a problem. <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Owen</persName> said that
                        once we attempt to go beyond generalities it becomes extremely difficult to
                        know which way to go. He asked van Lennep and Marris if they had any ideas.
                        Marris said he is not certain that any of the various <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss> activities would be sufficiently ripe to
                        be worthy of inclusion at this level. It was suggested that van Lennep might
                        issue a progress report on Marris’ efforts which could inform governments
                        and thus contribute to the preparations of the Summit. <persName corresp="#p_VLE_1">Van Lennep</persName> said it was essential that such
                        effort be kept within the <gloss target="#t_OECD_1">OECD</gloss>.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>