<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>233. Memorandum From Secretary of the Treasury Miller</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-02-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="rec6BvhdMDi4TnEMh" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067405"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">International monetary system</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recBIWbnPJBWQERtR" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003709"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Appropriation</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="rechrPce7erABw7F0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067245"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Interest rate</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="233"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d233">
                <head>233. Memorandum From Secretary of the Treasury <persName corresp="#p_MGW_1"
                        >Miller</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d233fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1"
                            >Carter</persName> Library, National Security Affairs, Staff Material,
                        Special Projects, Hazel Denton, Box 60, International Monetary Fund:
                        2–11/80. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-02-28">February 28, 1980</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list>
                    <head>MEMORANDUM FOR</head>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_MWF_1">Walter Mondale</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_VC_1">Cyrus Vance</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_SCL_1">Charles Schultze</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_ESE_1">Stuart Eizenstat</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_CRN_1">Richard Cooper</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_OHD_1">Henry Owen</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_VP_1">Paul Volcker</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_WH_1">Henry Wallich</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>The Honorable <persName corresp="#p_GL_1">Lyle Gramley</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0714" n="679" xml:id="pg_679"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Our Meeting on the Proposed <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>
                        “Substitution Account,” March 4, 1980<note n="2" xml:id="d233fn2">No record
                            of the meeting was found.</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I have requested this meeting because the Substitution Account proposal involves
                    some potentially important obligations as well as benefits for the U.S., and
                    negotiations on the Account are nearing a decision point.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d233fn3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_SAM_1">Solomon</persName> briefed <persName
                            corresp="#p_MGW_1">Miller</persName> on the status of the deputy-level
                        negotiations concerning the substitution account in a January 16 memorandum.
                        (National Archives, RG 56, Office of the Under Secretary of the Treasury for
                        Monetary Affairs, Subject Files of <persName corresp="#p_SAM_1">Anthony
                            Solomon</persName>, 1977–1980, Box 2, <gloss target="#t_G5_1"
                            >G–5</gloss>)</note> It will be discussed by finance ministers at a
                    meeting of the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>’s Interim Committee in late
                    April and, at the request of the French, will also be taken up at the Venice
                    Summit.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Outline of the Proposal</p>
                <p>In brief, the Account would accept dollar deposits by foreign central banks and
                    issue, in exchange, claims denominated in Special Drawing Rights (SDRs), which
                    are valued on the basis of a “basket” of 16 currencies. The Account would invest
                    its dollar holdings in interest-earning U.S.G. securities and would pay interest
                    to the holders of the <gloss target="#t_SDR_1">SDR</gloss>-denominated claims.
                    The claims issued by the Account would be of indefinite maturity, as is the
                        <gloss target="#t_SDR_1">SDR</gloss> reserve instrument created by the
                        <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>. Initially, the Account might start at
                    $10–20 billion and could rise to $50 billion over 5 years or so.</p>
                <p>This scheme presents a number of potential advantages for the United States and
                    other countries:</p>
                <p>—The international monetary system is moving in an uncontrolled way from
                    extremely heavy reliance on the dollar toward greater reliance on other major
                    currencies such as the Deutschemark, the Swiss franc and Japanese yen. The
                    process of diversification, if left to itself, can lead to heavy pressures on
                    the dollar at inopportune times and potentially large costs to the U.S. in terms
                    of dollar support. It can also cause serious economic and financial problems for
                    the countries whose currencies are “targets” of diversification, such as
                    Germany.</p>
                <p>—While the existence of the Account would not necessarily halt this process, it
                    could provide an attractive and non-disruptive off-market alternative to
                    diversification through the market, and a “safety valve” that could be made
                    available to potential diversifiers in times of market strain.</p>
                <p>—From a longer-term perspective, the Account would be supportive of the generally
                    agreed objective of moving away from national currencies and toward the <gloss
                        target="#t_SDR_1">SDR</gloss> as the principal reserve asset of the
                    international monetary system. If the Account succeeds and the <gloss
                        target="#t_SDR_1">SDR</gloss> as<pb facs="0715" n="680" xml:id="pg_680"
                    />sumes an increasingly important role, the international monetary system as a
                    whole should become more stable through minimization of shifts among various
                    reserve assets.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Main Issues in the Negotiations</p>
                <p>The central issues relate to maintaining financial balance in the Account. The
                    Account can experience losses of two kinds: the interest it receives from the
                    U.S. Government on its dollar investments may not be enough to cover the
                    interest it pays on its <gloss target="#t_SDR_1">SDR</gloss>-denominated
                    liabilities; and it can show a negative “net worth” if the dollar exchange rate
                    declines relative to the <gloss target="#t_SDR_1">SDR</gloss>. The question is
                    how these losses are to be financed. Although other countries entered the
                    negotiations with the position that the U.S. should bear these costs, it is now
                    generally accepted that the Account is of potential benefit to depositors and
                    the system as a whole as well as to the United States, and that any costs should
                    therefore be shared equitably.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Gold.</hi> One approach to financing losses—which is essential
                    if this key issue is to be resolved, and which appears to have the support of
                    the major countries—is use of part of the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>’s
                    gold holdings. Assuming general agreement to use of some <gloss
                        target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> gold, the main question here is whether the
                    gold should be available to finance <hi rend="italic">all</hi> losses by the
                    Account, or whether the U.S. should be obligated to make special above-market
                    interest payments to cover part of any interest gap, with the balance of any
                    losses to be financed with <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> gold.</p>
                <p>Some countries are interested in minimizing the need for sales of <gloss
                        target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> gold, and see special U.S. “extra” interest
                    payments as a way of achieving this objective. Others are less concerned about
                    the modest gold sales that would be needed to cover interest shortfalls than
                    they are about assuring—symbolically, for domestic political reasons—that the
                    U.S. carries a “burden” in connection with the Account’s operations. We have
                    argued that the U.S. cannot agree to such supplementary payments over and above
                    market interest rates; that it is politically impossible for us; that it is
                    unnecessary given the availability of <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> gold;
                    and that it is unrealistic and inappropriate for others to insist on such
                    payments for the sake of imposing a symbolic burden.</p>
                <p>There is some concern over presentational aspects of using gold for the
                    substitution account—that it could be interpreted as a step toward
                    “remonetization,” contrary to U.S. policy and interests. It is difficult to see
                    how the gap in negotiating positions can be bridged without some use of <gloss
                        target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> gold, but it is at the same time important to
                    minimize such presentational or image problems. We have therefore insisted, and
                    the other major countries have agreed, that there must be some provision for
                    actual <hi rend="italic">sales</hi> of gold to meet an interest gap; and that
                    remaining gold held by the Account would <hi rend="italic">not be valued at the
                        market,</hi> but would be re<pb facs="0716" n="681" xml:id="pg_681"/>corded
                    in ounces as a memorandum item on the Account’s books or valued only at the
                    price necessary to cover any net worth shortfall.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Guarantees.</hi> Even if the gold issue can be resolved
                    satisfactorily, gold does not provide the whole answer: it is conceivable that
                    the amounts of <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> gold available to the
                    Account may become insufficient to maintain the Account’s financial position,
                    and participants will insist on a contingency provision to cover this
                    possibility. We have indicated that, although we are <hi rend="italic">not</hi>
                    prepared to make supplementary interest payments to the Account, we <hi
                        rend="italic">are</hi> prepared to consider sharing (proportion not yet
                    discussed) in financing any negative balance in the Account at the time of a
                    decision to terminate its operations—<hi rend="italic">provided</hi> that such a
                    decision requires the joint consent of the U.S. and other participants, i.e.,
                    that we have a veto. Under such an arrangement, there would be at least two
                    options in the event <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> gold became
                    insufficient to balance the Account’s financial position: the Account could
                    terminate at that point and redeem its obligations in full without any calls on
                    guarantees; or it could continue operations (creating new <gloss
                        target="#t_SDR_1">SDR</gloss> claims on itself to cover any current interest
                    shortfall) and balance its accounts through claims on the ultimate
                    guarantees.</p>
                <p>Some countries, while indicating there is a need for an ultimate guarantee at
                    liquidation of the Account, have gone further to argue that guarantees should be
                    callable periodically—before liquidation of the Account—to provide for
                    “maintenance of value” on a current basis. This would mean that
                    someone—presumably the U.S. and depositors in some agreed proportion—would have
                    to pay money into the Account each year a shortfall occurred. The U.S. has
                    argued that current maintenance of value is unnecessary, given the
                    permanent/indefinite maturity of the Account’s obligations and operations, and
                    that the ultimate guarantees should suffice to maintain the integrity of the
                    Account. We have also said that there is no realistic prospect that the U.S.
                    would be able to obtain legislative authority to make maintenance-of-value
                    payments on a current basis. It is also doubtful whether other countries would
                    in fact be prepared to make such periodic payments to the Account.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Legislative Implications</p>
                <p>Although we cannot determine precise legislative requirements at this point, some
                    form of legislation would probably be necessary under any variant of the Account
                    that could be negotiated.</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">Authorization</hi> would be required for the U.S. to
                    participate in a joint guarantee to be activated upon termination of the
                    Account. It is also possible, but not certain, that the Congress would require
                    some form of <hi rend="italic">appropriations</hi> action, even though a call on
                    the U.S. commitment would be subject to U.S. veto. (If appropriations were
                    required, <pb facs="0717" n="682" xml:id="pg_682"/> we would probably have to
                    seek a permanent/indefinite appropriation, since the amount of our obligation
                    would be indefinite.)</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">Authorization and appropriations</hi> would almost certainly
                    be needed in advance if the U.S. were to assume obligations to make guarantee
                    payments on a current basis.</p>
                <p>—<hi rend="italic">Authorization</hi> might be required to raise the ceiling on
                    long-term Treasury debt, depending on the exact arrangements negotiated on the
                    Account’s investment of its dollar holdings.</p>
                <p>—U.S. payment of special above-market interest rates on the Account’s
                    investments, to cover part of any interest shortfalls, technically would not
                    require legislation, but could trigger Congressional criticism and efforts to
                    curtail the Secretary of the Treasury’s authority to determine interest payable
                    on the public debt. In any event we do not contemplate any such supplementary
                    payments, and have made that position very clear.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation</p>
                <p>I recommend that the U.S. take the following position at the forthcoming
                    meetings:</p>
                <p>First, that we are prepared to support establishment of a substitution account if
                    key questions can be resolved satisfactorily.</p>
                <p>Second, that we are not prepared to make supplemental, above-market, interest
                    payments to the Account.</p>
                <p>Third, that we will support use of a portion of the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1"
                        >IMF</gloss>’s gold to meet financial imbalances in the Account, whether
                    such imbalances arise from interest rate differentials or from exchange rate
                    changes, subject to safeguards to minimize any interpretation that gold is being
                    “remonetized.”</p>
                <p>Fourth, that we will participate in a shared guarantee of the Account’s financial
                    position, to be activated upon a decision to terminate the Account, with that
                    decision subject to veto by either the U.S. or a majority of the depositors.</p>
                <p>Fifth, that we are not prepared to agree to calls on this guarantee in advance of
                    a decision to terminate the Account.</p>
                <p>If an arrangement along these lines can be negotiated, and there is at least a
                    reasonable chance, the Account would entail minimal costs or potential exposure
                    to costs for the U.S. The interest rate paid to the Account would be a market
                    rate, comparable to what the Treasury would have to pay on borrowings from any
                    other source. The ultimate guarantee would be shared, would be payable upon
                    liquidation, would be subject to U.S. veto, and in all likelihood would never be
                    called.</p>
                <p>The inter-agency International Monetary Group chaired by <persName
                        corresp="#p_SAM_1">Tony Solomon</persName> has been closely involved in
                    developing U.S. positions <pb facs="0718" n="683" xml:id="pg_683"/> throughout
                    the negotiations, and is unanimously agreed on the course recommended above. In
                    addition, Tony has consulted periodically with Senate Banking Committee members
                        <persName corresp="#p_PW_1">Proxmire</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_SAE_1">Stevenson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_HHJ3_1"
                        >Heinz</persName>, Senator <persName corresp="#p_JJK_1">Javits</persName>,
                    and Chairman <persName corresp="#p_RHS_1">Reuss</persName> and others on the
                    House Banking Committee. They are very supportive of both the broad principle
                    and the specific U.S. negotiating objectives.<note n="4" xml:id="d233fn4">On
                        April 24, Finance Ministers in Hamburg for a meeting of the <gloss
                            target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> Interim Committee announced that work on a
                        substitution account would be suspended. (Paul Lewis, “Dollar Plan For
                        I.M.F. Is Shelved,” <hi rend="italic">The New York Times,</hi> April 25,
                        1980, p. D1) In the official <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> history,
                        Boughton offers three explanations for the abandonment of the substitution
                        account. The first two, <persName corresp="#p_SAM_1">Solomon</persName>’s
                        March 1980 resignation (Boughton notes that <persName corresp="#p_SAM_1"
                            >Solomon</persName> was the initiative’s strongest advocate in the
                        administration) and <persName corresp="#p_VP_1">Volcker</persName>’s
                        anti-inflationary monetary policy (which “eased fears of a continuing glut
                        of dollars”), decreased the urgency with which the project was pursued. The
                        third reason (which was “more fundamental,” according to Boughton) “was the
                        dissatisfaction with the stalemate over how to cover exchange risk. Without
                        a consensus on the use of the Fund’s gold as part of an overall
                        burden-sharing plan, the proposal had no hope for success.” (Boughton, <hi
                            rend="italic">Silent Revolution,</hi> p. 943)</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
