<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-08-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-08-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="170" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d170">
                    <head>No. 170.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bassett</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Port au Prince,
                                    Hayti</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-08-11"><hi rend="italic">August</hi> 11, 1877</date>.
                            (Received Sept. 3.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 523.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to that portion of my No. 522, of
                        the 28th ultimo, which made mention of a note just then received from the
                        Dominican plenipotentiaries, I have the honor to send you herewith inclosed
                        a careful translation of the note, and to invite your convenient attention
                        thereto.</p>
                    <p>It will be seen that the note professes to give an outline both of the
                        unsatisfactory relations which have arisen between the two republics of this
                        island and of the efforts which have been made by the Dominican Government
                        to improve those relations, and that its recitals and general tenor are such
                        as to lead to the conclusion that the responsibility for the actual
                        condition of things between the two republics rests with Hayti. As a whole,
                        it might be taken as even a bold affirmation of the <pb facs="0362" n="314" xml:id="pg_314"/> correctness of the statements and apprehensions
                        somewhat reservedly expressed in my dispatches of recent dates, numbered
                        498, 507, and 508, and I must give it as my impression that, with few
                        exceptions, the assertions in the note are fairly reliable.</p>
                    <p>* * * * * **</p>
                    <p>But I do not think, as it is affirmed in the plenipotentiaries’ note, that
                        this government has “consented,” although it may have, and probably has,
                        tacitly permitted and so connived “that armed incursions against, the public
                        order and tranquillity of the Dominican Republic should have their center
                        and headquarters of depredatory operations on the frontiers of Hayti.” For
                        since the ignominious failure of Soulouque to subdue the Dominicans by force
                        of arms in 1855–’56, the policy of this government in regard to that of
                        Santo Domingo has, according to the best of my knowledge and belief, been to
                        keep up before the world an Appearance of friendly relations between the two
                        republics, while at the same time it has, except under Salnave, steadily,
                        but covertly, sought to foment discord among the Dominicans, and most
                        cunningly and secretly to intermeddle in and control their political
                        affairs. Therefore, whatever provocation the plenipotentiaries may have had
                        for the assertion, I am sure this government does not wish or intend other
                        nations to understand or be able to prove that “the Haytian authorities act
                        toward the Dominicans as if they had not the least international obligation,
                        according either to the law of nature or the law of nations.”</p>
                    <p>It has all along been my impression that President Baëz perfectly comprehends
                        the policy of this government toward his own. And I regard his endeavor,
                        through the sending of plenipotentiaries hither to settle in an amicable way
                        the difficulties which have arisen between the two governments, not only as
                        discreet and wise, but also as one which ought to disarm this government of
                        all pretext for further clandestine or other interference in the internal
                        political affairs of the Dominican Republic.</p>
                    <p>It appears to me, also, that the Dominican plenipotentiaries, in their
                        argument favoring the recognition of the treaty between the two countries,
                        had right, justice, and honor on their side.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>EBENEZER D. BASSETT.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Dominican
                                    plenipotentiaries</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">foreign
                                    representatives at Port-au-Prince</gloss>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Dominican Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Port-au-Prince</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-07-27"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 27,
                                1877</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">To the diplomatic or consular
                                representatives of the United States of America, of France, of
                                England, and of Spain, at Port-au-Prince:</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Messieurs les Représentants</hi>: In our quality of
                            diplomatic envoys of the Government of the Dominican Republic near the
                            Government of the Republic of Hayti, it is of our greatest interest—an
                            interest altogether moral and patriotic—to bring to your knowledge both
                            the actual state of the official relations between the two governments
                            above mentioned and the results which, in regard to these relations, our
                            labors in the view of formalizing and fixing them according to the
                            principles of the law of nations universally admitted, have
                            obtained.</p>
                        <p>The Dominican nation, by a spontaneous and unanimous effort, in December,
                            1876, overthrew the usurped and derisive dictatorship of Mr. Ignacio M.
                            Gonzales, who imposed himself by surprise and force upon the legitimate
                            government of Mr. Ulises Espaillat. General Baez was in consequence
                            invested with supreme power, and the fall of Gonzales responded so
                            perfectly to the general wish that President Baez in order to establish
                            his government had no occasion to employ any dictatorial act or to <pb facs="0363" n="315" xml:id="pg_315"/> combat any resistance. He had
                            the happiness to insure peace to his fellow-citizens, and to establish
                            his administration on the basis of eminently liberal principles and
                            strictest equity.</p>
                        <p>But the government of Mr. Baez found in its path, from its first day, the
                            ill will of the Haytian Government, which, in contempt of the treaty
                            existing between the two nations sought to entice over to Haytian
                            territory all the discontented who, without constraint of any kind,
                            chose to withdraw from Dominican authority; and then it consented that
                            armed incursions against the public order and tranquillity of the
                            Dominican Republic should have their center of organization and
                            headquarters of depredatory operations on the frontiers of Hayti.
                            Prohibitions on the commerce of Dominican produce were established by
                            the Haytian custom-house regulations to the prejudice and in flagrant
                            violation of the above-named treaty; and, finally, the Haytian
                            authorities act toward the legitimate government of the Dominicans as if
                            they had not the least international obligation, according either to the
                            law of nature or the law of nations.</p>
                        <p>The reclamations of the Dominican authorities as to the disorders on the
                            frontiers are altogether, useless; and, in consequence, a handful of
                            insurgents hold in check the troops of the Dominican Government, which,
                            in fact, finds itself under the weight of enormous expenses in order to
                            face insignificant bands that freely cross and recross the Haytian
                            frontier. It was in vain that, soon after his elevation to power,
                            President Baez was pleased to resort to conciliatory measures and to
                            appeal to reason and justice to bring the Haytian Government to a
                            respect of the public faith of nations. To this end he caused a
                            commission to come to Port au Prince in January last, to reclaim arms
                            belonging to the Dominican Government, and to demand the suppression of
                            the insurgents, who had just then opened hostile operations on the river
                            Massacre, near Dajabon. At the same time, the Dominican commissioner
                            came charged to make the otter of the pacific sentiments of his
                            government to the Haytian Government, and to seek the strengthening of
                            good relations by means of the complete execution of the clauses of the
                            treaty.</p>
                        <p>The commissioner obtained nothing; a marked coldness, evasive answers,
                            and insolent demeanor (<hi rend="italic">manifestations
                                outrageantes</hi>) in return for the loyalty of the Dominican
                            Government, finished by convincing our commissioner, Mr. Cabral, that
                            there were, on the part of the Haytian Government, a foregone conclusion
                                (<hi rend="italic">parti pris</hi>) and insurmountable prejudices.
                            It was under these painful impressions that he returned to Santo Domingo
                            and rendered an account of his mission.</p>
                        <p>The government of President Baez was not disheartened notwithstanding
                            this unhappy trial. Holding it at heart to give a more convincing
                            testimony of his moderation and his desire for concord with the
                            neighboring country, he decided that a new commission should be
                            furnished, with conciliatory instructions, in order to come to a
                            reasonable agreement by means of new engagements efficacious enough to
                            assure the Haytian Government itself as to the point of its injurious
                            suspicions growing out of imputed projects of Dominican annexation. Upon
                            us, the undersigned, fell the honor of being selected for this mission
                            of peace. We have done our best to fulfill our mission; but we have
                            stranded upon the same prejudices and the same foregone conclusion (<hi rend="italic">parti pris</hi>) as those upon which our predecessor
                            stranded. Furthermore, we have found Mr. Gonzalez established at Port au
                            Prince working actively to produce new uprisings in favor of his own
                            restoration to power, and the first effect of his labors was the
                            insurrectionary attempt which broke out and was crushed at Puerto Plata
                            the 1st of July instant.</p>
                        <p>We were under the obligation of causing the Haytian minister of foreign
                            affairs to feel how pressing was the necessity of putting an end to this
                            disorder and to these criminal intrigues against the public tranquillity
                            of the Dominicans, and of faithfully executing the stipulations of the
                            treaty in vigor; but the minister evaded our reclamations, in objecting
                            to us that “the national assembly of Hayti having declared null and void
                            the acts of General Domingue’s government, the Dominico-Haytian treaty
                            remains struck with the same nullity”; and the same Mr. Ethéart
                            submitted to us on the 14th of July a verbal communication containing
                            the conditional bases for new conventions to be entered into; he put in
                            advance, as one of the dispositions already decided upon by his
                            government, the proposition here below copied textually:</p>
                        <p>“The Dominico-Haytian treaty, signed November 9, 1874, between the
                            government of General Domingue and that of General Gonzales, remains
                            null and void, as the secretary of foreign affairs of the republic of
                            Hayti had already caused it to be understood, as well in his collective
                            note addressed to the (diplomatic) agents accredited in this country as
                            in the exposition of the situation (President’s message) to the national
                            assembly. It must be considered that the denunciation (<hi rend="italic">dénonciation</hi>) of this treaty is obligatory in some sense upon
                            this high functionary, the corps legislatif, whose decisions he must
                            respect, defend, and execute, having consecrated similar dispositions in
                            the law of October 6, 1876.”</p>
                        <p>We demanded on the other hand, as was just and natural, that the treaty
                            should be modified by the common accord of the two contracting parties,
                            for we could not admit that the public powers of Hayti, of their own
                            exclusive authority, should put <pb facs="0364" n="316" xml:id="pg_316"/> aside, by a local law, the international conventions which were
                            excluded from the local jurisdiction of either of the contracting
                            parties. We desired very much to begin at once the reform of the treaty,
                            doing justice, as much as possible, to the pretensions ‘of the Haytian
                            Government; but we sustain the validity of the treaty, as the necessary
                            starting point, so that the new conventions might carry in them the
                            guarantee of the reciprocally guarded faith indispensable to their own
                            validity and their future solidity. Here, then, is the variation made by
                            us in the sense and to the letter of the proposition of the Haytian
                            minister, by form of counter-proposition:</p>
                        <p>“To proceed to the immediate execution of the treaty in the part which,
                            by its non-fulfillment,, affects the public peace, the security and the
                            legal order existing in the Dominican Republic, and to adopt the same
                            treaty as the starting point for the stipulation of new bases, by the
                            means of which remain, from that time, in suspense, the clauses judged
                            prejudicial to the interests of either of the contracting parties, and
                            in course of execution all the other clauses until the definitive
                            formation of new conventions.”</p>
                        <p>“This formula,” we added in our dispatch of July 17th, addressed to the
                            secretary of foreign affairs, “would offer the advantage of causing to
                            cease without delay all the causes of distrust, coldness, and
                            malevolence by which are strained to-day the relations of the two
                            countries; the principle of the inalienability of the territory would
                            remain <hi rend="italic">ipso facto</hi>, agreed to conformably to what
                            the government established in the third proposition of the verbal
                            communication which is in substance the tenor of the third article of
                            the treaty of 1874, and so also the delimitation of the frontiers would
                            become obligatory in the same form consecrated by article 4 of the same
                            treaty.”</p>
                        <p>The secretary of state, in a conference held with us the 21st, expressed
                            to us the absolute impossibility of admitting the validity of the
                            treaty, and promised us a written answer by the 25th. This date passed
                            without result; we then notified the minister, according to his verbal
                            declaration of the 21st, that our conscience, our instructions, and the
                            dignity of the Dominican Republic not permitting us to consent to the
                            counter-judicial sense of not absolutely recognizing the obligations of
                            the treaty; having the conviction that all delay not justified in our
                            negotiations is equivalent to a moral complicity in the revolts and
                            machinations which flourish in Hayti against our country, we were
                            obliged to declare the negotiations finished and to return to Santo
                            Domingo by the occasion fixed upon to-day the 27th, and we have closed
                            our communication to the Haytian minister with these final
                            paragraphs:</p>
                        <p>“Let it be known, Mr. Minister, before the Haytian people, before all the
                            enlightened nations, before God, and before the civilized world, that
                            while in Hayti are put aside “the subsidiary obligations, and the
                            commercial franchises stipulated between the two republics; while in
                            Hayti a solemn conviction which fraternally united the two sovereign
                            peoples of the Island, has been disowned and denied; while in Hayti have
                            been carefully nourished and guarded the elements of the bloody
                            intestine struggles of the Dominicans in giving illimited asylum and
                            assuring the impunity of the conspirators; in indefinitely retaining
                            arms which belong to the Dominican Republic—the Dominican Government has
                            made two infructuous attempts to re-establish peace, and to cement frank
                            and loyal relations between the two states.”</p>
                        <p>The minister answered us under date of yesterday, confirming to us his
                            verbal declaration relative to the nullity of the treaty.</p>
                        <p>This is the condition in which the relations of the Dominican Republic
                            remain with Hayti: The Haytian Government, retrenching itself in a
                            non-political sense, denies all at once the obligations which the public
                            faith engaged in a solemn treaty impose upon it, and the simple duties
                            of good neighborhood according to the law of nations. The treaty
                            disowned, signifies the reserve of a liberty of illimited action in
                            maintaining the revolt on the Dominican frontier, and the conspiration
                            against our republic at the capital of Hayti. We pray you to please take
                            note of this situation, and to render an account thereof to your
                            respective governments, so that they may in advance be provided with the
                            information necessary to appreciate with justice future
                            eventualities.</p>
                        <p>We have the honor, Messieurs les Représentants, to offer to you the
                            assurances of our very distinguished consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed><list>
                                    <item>FELIPE D. F. <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> CASTRO.</item>
                                    <item>MANUEL <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi> J. GALVAN.</item>
                                </list></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>