<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-06-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-06-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="178" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d178">
                    <head>No. 178.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Marsh</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Rome</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-06-01"><hi rend="italic">June</hi> 1, 1877</date>. (Received June
                            18.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 678.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Although much improved in health since Mr.
                        Wurt’s dispatch No. 676, I do not yet think it prudent to undertake any work
                        requiring continued attention. I may, however, notice certain proceedings in
                        the Italian Parliament of some interest. The Italian ministry has gained, in
                        spite of strenuous opposition, a victory of some importance in the
                        imposition of increased duties on sugar, and in the rejection of a motion
                        for the reduction of the charges on salt, which is a government monopoly, by
                        55 centimes per kilogram. It is apparent, however, from the tone of the
                        debate and from other evidence, that the success of the ministry is due less
                        to its own strength than to the general repugnance of political men to
                        inflict upon it, in the present posture of public affairs, a defeat
                        involving its retirement and the formation of a new ministry, which, it is
                        thought, could not now be organized from the ranks of the majority. The
                        position of the ministry on these financial questions is thought not to be
                        in harmony with its promises of financial reform and relief; but it
                        proposes, by way of compensation, a considerable reduction in the taxes on
                        personal property, including the income tax. By the law at present in force,
                        incomes as low as 400 francs pay an annual tax of 39 francs 60 centimes.
                        This it is proposed to reduce to 19 francs 30 centimes. The tax on higher
                        incomes will be reduced at the rates of 37½, 33.21 and 12 per cent, for sums
                        of 500, 600, 700 and 800 francs, respectively. The ministerial bill
                        proposing these reductions will undoubtedly pass, and the measure will
                        strengthen the ministry with the country.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>GEORGE P. MARSH.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>