<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 190.Mr. Bingham to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1877</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d190</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">190</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1877-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1877-02-09T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994" lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-02-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-02-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="190" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d190">
                <head>No. 190.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bingham</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokei,
                                Japan</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-02-09">
                            <hi rend="italic">February</hi> 9, 1877</date>. (Received March
                            9.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 502.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the 1st instant, upon the invitation of His
                        Majesty the Emperor, I proceeded with my colleagues to Kiôto to be present
                        at the opening of the recently constructed railway between that ancient
                        capital of Japan and Kobe, a distance of about fifty-five miles. On the 5th
                        instant His Majesty, attended by the officials of his court, visited the
                        railway and passed over it, stopping at the stations in Kobe, Osaca, and
                        Kiôto, and in the presence of the governors of each city, of the officials
                        of the imperial court, of the foreign representatives accredited to Japan,
                        and of immense numbers of the people of Japan, declared the railway open for
                        travel hereafter and for the transportation of merchandise. On this occasion
                        the foreign representatives, through Sir Harry S. Parkes, presented a
                        congratulatory address to the Emperor, a copy of which, with the Emperor’s
                        reply, I shall forward as soon as I shall have received the same.</p>
                <p>It was very apparent that the people of Japan retain much of the old-time
                        reverence for His Majesty the Tenno, as their rightful sovereign.</p>
                <p>I have only to add that I was absent on this duty but eight days, during
                        which time I was within telegraphic communication with the legation, which
                        was open from day to day, Mr. Stevens remaining in Tokei.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>JNO. A. BINGHAM.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
