<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 205.Mr. Turner to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1877</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d205</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">205</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1877-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1877-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recF25QgGbJ7Hjysy" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001185"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Newspaper</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recBRpk2PnA6tnVFg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="205"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d205">
                <head>No. 205.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Turner</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Monrovia, Liberia</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-06-07">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 7, 1877</date>. (Received July
                        23.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 261.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: From the slowness and uncertainty with which
                    election-returns and, indeed, reports of every nature involving the use of
                    figures, are made, there are few things in Liberia requiring greater exercise of
                    patience. There being no horses or other beasts of burden in Liberia (and if
                    such animals were here the country possesses no roads except the mere “trail” or
                    “bridle-paths” worn by the foot-travel of native Africans), it is necessary to
                    convey the internal mails, through which election-returns must reach the
                    capital, by men who travel on foot. The above fact is offered in explanation of
                    my seeming delay in reporting to the Department the regular biennial election
                    for President and Vice-President and members of the Legislature of Liberia. The
                    Presidential election was held throughout the republic on the first Tuesday in
                    May, the day fixed for that purpose by the constitution of Liberia. The
                    gentlemen who had the distinction of being candidates for the Presidency are the
                    same two gentlemen who were the nominees for that post of high trust at the
                    Presidential election held in May, A. D. 1875, viz, his excellency James S.
                    Payne, President of Liberia, and the honorable Anthony W. Gardner,
                    ex-vice-president, the only person now living of those who had the honor of
                    signing the declaration of independence of Liberia. My dispatch of date the 30th
                    May, 1875, and numbered 168, treats in part of the distinguished candidates for
                    the Presidency of the republic; and as I should not engage the attention of the
                    Department unnecessarily, I will not write now of their individual
                    qualities.</p>
                <p>At this writing the returns have reached Monrovia from every district of the
                    country; and the election of Mr. Gardner to the Presidency is, agreeably with
                    what I have been able to learn, conceded by President Payne and by the political
                    supporters of that gentleman. The principal significance which this result of
                    the Presidential election will probably <pb facs="0418" n="370" xml:id="pg_370"
                    /> have is doubtless couched in the circumstance that Mr. Gardner was regarded
                    in the campaign as the champion of those prejudices and laws in Liberia which in
                    many instances tend to exclude foreign residents from the enjoyment of
                    privileges which would seem essential to their comfort and contentment in the
                    country, and in others to confine the business transactions of such persons
                    absolutely to the designated “ports of entry” situated immediately upon the
                    sea-coast. No doubt the Department is informed, through my former dispatches,
                    that the administration of President Payne has shown inclination to construe
                    such laws as bear upon the interests of foreigners resident in Liberia as
                    liberally as the text thereof and public opinion would allow. By that course the
                    present administration has fallen into outspoken and pronounced disfavor with a
                    large majority of the citizens of Liberia. The Legislature of 1875–’76 submitted
                    to be voted upon by the people at the election of which I write certain
                    propositions to amend the constitution, with the view to abrogate in favor of
                    foreigners certain exclusive and restrictive provisions of that instrument. This
                    proposal to amend the constitution of Liberia was so unpopular as to meet with
                    the almost unanimous opposition of the voters, and there were polled in all the
                    republic in favor of the adoption of the amendments to the constitution only
                    twenty-nine votes. The defeat of President Payne is said to be the most
                    overwhelming of any gentleman who was heretofore a candidate for the Presidency.
                    It is thought that the friends of Mr. Gardner will, on a two-thirds vote,
                    compose a majority of the next Legislature. I have been at some pains to collect
                    the figures from which to prepare the accompanying table, marked Inclosure No.
                    1, showing the vote for President and Vice-President in the elections held May,
                    1875, and May, 1877. It would seem from the circumstances and results of this
                    election that this spirit of unfriendliness toward the interests of foreigners
                    is in some sense fixed. Owing to the general absence of schools and a
                    well-conducted press (there is not one newspaper published in Liberia), the
                    political affairs of this country are perhaps too completely at the mercy of a
                    few men, whose designs, whether for the weal or for the woe of their country,
                    are not easily interrupted. It is for the best interests of Liberia to be
                    sincerely hoped that the few patriots who advocate the extension of equitable
                    privileges and rights to foreigners who may resort to Liberia for the investment
                    of their capital may succeed in that advocacy. I am of opinion that the
                    legislation of Lycurgus interdicting the importation of gold and the other
                    precious metals into Sparta could not have operated more effectually upon the
                    Spartans than tends this spirit of Unfriendliness to excite the timidity of
                    foreign capitalists engaged in agricultural or commercial pursuits in
                    Liberia.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. MILTON TURNER.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
