<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-03-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="25" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d25">
                    <head>No. 25.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Delaplaine</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-03-01"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1, 1877</date>.
                            (Received March 19.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 41.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to my Nos. 39 and 40, I beg to
                        advise my receipt this morning of a note from his excellency Count Andrássy,
                        wherein I am informed that His Imperial and Royal Majesty has graciously
                        been pleased to consent that his ambassador in London should undertake the
                        duty of selecting a gentleman to act as third commissioner under the
                        twenty-third article of the treaty of Washington of 8th May, 1871, and that
                        Count Beust has been accordingly instructed by his excellency the
                        imperial-royal minister for foreign affairs.</p>
                    <p>His Imperial and Royal Majesty’s ambassador has been further instructed,
                        after having made the selection, to communicate forthwith the same to the
                        foreign office in London, and to the representative of the United States at
                        that court.</p>
                    <p>I herewith append a copy of my note to Count Andrássy, and his excellency’s
                        reply, together with translation.</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>J. F. DELAPLAINE.</signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 41.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Delaplaine</persName> to
                                Count <persName type="to">Andrássy</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-02-26"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 26,
                                    1877</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>M. <hi rend="smallcaps">le Ministre</hi>: Articles XVIII, XIX, and XXI of
                            the treaty of Washington, of the 8th of May, 1871, of which I have the
                            honor herewith to inclose a copy, provide for certain privileges in
                            respect to fisheries and remission of customs duties, to be granted by
                            the United States and Great Britain respectively, and in the
                            twenty-second and twenty-third articles of the treaty it is further
                            provided: <list>
                                <item>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXII</hi>. Inasmuch as it is
                                    asserted by the government of her Britannic Majesty that the
                                    privileges accorded to the citizens of the United States under
                                    Article XVIII of this treaty are of greater value than those
                                    accorded by Articles XIX and XXI of this treaty to the subjects
                                    of Her Britannic Majesty, and this assertion is not admitted by
                                    the Government of the United States, it is further agreed that
                                    commissioners shall be appointed to determine, having regard to
                                    the privileges accorded by the United States to the subjects of
                                    Her Britannic Majesty, as stated in Articles XIX and XXI of this
                                    treaty, the amount of any compensation which, in their opinion,
                                    ought to be paid by the Government of the United States to the
                                    Government of Her Britannic Majesty in return for the privileges
                                    accorded to the citizens of the United States under Article
                                    XVIII of this treaty; and that any sum of money which the said
                                    commissioners may so award shall be paid by the United States
                                    Government, in a gross sum, within twelve months after such
                                    award shall have been given.</item>
                                <pb facs="0074" n="26" xml:id="pg_26"/>
                                <item>“<hi rend="smallcaps">Article XXIII</hi>. The commissioners
                                    referred to in the preceding article shall be appointed in the
                                    following manner, that is to say: one commissioner shall be
                                    named by the President of the United States, one by Her
                                    Britannic Majesty, and a third by the President of the United
                                    States and Her Britannic Majesty conjointly; and in case the
                                    third commissioner shall not have been so named within a period
                                    of three months from the date when this article shall take
                                    effect, then the third commissioner shall be named by the
                                    representative at London of His Majesty the Emperor of Austria
                                    and King of Hungary. In case of the death, absence, or
                                    incapacity of any commissioner, or in the event of any
                                    commissioner omitting or ceasing to act, the vacancy shall be
                                    filled in the manner hereinbefore provided for making the
                                    original appointment, the period of three months, in case of
                                    such substitution, being calculated from the date of the
                                    happening of the vacancy.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>“The commissioners so named shall meet in the city of Halifax, in the
                            province of Nova Scotia, at the earliest convenient period after they
                            have been respectively named, and shall, before proceeding to any
                            business, make and subscribe a solemn declaration that they will
                            impartially and carefully examine and decide the matters referred to
                            them to the best of their judgment, and according to justice and equity;
                            and such declaration shall be entered on the record of their
                            proceedings.</p>
                        <p>“Each of the high contracting parties shall also name one person to
                            attend the commission as its agent, to represent it generally in all
                            matters connected with the commission.”</p>
                        <p>The period of three months specified in the article above quoted having
                            elapsed, it has become necessary to take steps for the appointment of
                            the third commissioner in accordance with its provisions, and with this
                            view I have received the instructions of my government to request you to
                            invite His Imperial and Royal Majesty to be graciously pleased to
                            instruct his ambassador at London to undertake the duty of selecting
                            some gentleman properly qualified to act in the capacity of third
                            commissioner.</p>
                        <p>In consideration of the fact that the proceedings at the Halifax
                            commission will be conducted in the English language, and that any
                            evidence, documents, or oral testimony will be also in English, it
                            appears to my government to be a necessary qualification that the third
                            commissioner should possess an accurate knowledge of that language.</p>
                        <p>The commissioner appointed by the President of the United States is the
                            Hon. Ensign H. Kellogg, and the commissioner appointed by Her Britannic
                            Majesty is Sir Alexander T. Galt, K. C. B., &amp;c.</p>
                        <p>The arrangements for the constitution of the commission being otherwise
                            complete, I have the honor to suggest that it would be desirable that
                            the third commissioner should be named by the representative at London
                            of His Imperial and Royal Majesty as soon as may be convenient.</p>
                        <p>I have, further, the honor to inform you that my British colleague has
                            received instructions to act conjointly with me in making this request,
                            and he will address you a note in similar terms to that which I have now
                            the honor to present.</p>
                        <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                        <closer><signed>J. F. DELAPLAINE.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No.
                            41.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Count <persName type="from">Andrássy</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Delaplaine</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-02-28"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 28,
                                    1877</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The undersigned, minister of the imperial house and for foreign affairs,
                            has had the honor to receive the esteemed note of the 26th instant, in
                            which the chargé d’affaires of the United States of America, Mr.
                            Delaplaine, was pleased, under the instructions of his government, to
                            express the request that the imperial and royal ambassador in London of
                            His Majesty the Emperor and King should be authorized, in the sense of
                            Article XXIII of the treaty concluded at Washington on the 8th of May,
                            1871, between Great Britain and the United States of America, to
                            indicate the third commissioner for the negotiation of the differences
                            pending between these two states in the fisheries question.</p>
                        <p>In response to this note, the undersigned begs respectfully to inform the
                            chargé d’affaires that he has represented the matter to His Majesty, and
                            after having obtained His Majesty’s authorization, he has invited the
                            imperial and royal ambassador in London to undertake the nomination of
                            the third commissioner, in accordance with the enactment of the said
                            article.</p>
                        <p>At the same time Count Beust has been requested to communicate forthwith
                            the selection made by him to the foreign office in London, and to the
                            representative of the Government of the United States at that place.</p>
                        <p>The undersigned avails himself of this occasion to renew to the chargé
                            d’affaires the assurance of his distinguished consideration.</p>
                        <closer><signed>ANDRÁSSY.</signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>