<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-04-09T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="26" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                    <head>No. 26.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Beale</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-04-09"><hi rend="italic">April</hi> 9, 1877</date>.
                            (Received April 23.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 51.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As there has been a considerable discussion as
                        to the relative strength and efficiency of the Turkish and Russian armies, I
                        send you an opinion from an American of intelligence on that subject. My
                        informant has had an active experience in the field during our civil war,
                        and is, therefore, entitled to credit, and the more so in this instance as
                        he was an eye-witness to the late operations in Servia. In a letter lately
                        received from him, he says, in reply to an inquiry of mine: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>The Turks have not got 200,000 men on the Danube line. They have
                                probably that number of regulars and irregulars on the Balkan line
                                and Danube, and scattered in the intervening country, but the
                                regulars are badly officered. They are splendid privates, and have
                                good rifles and ammunition, but the quartermaster and medical, as
                                well as commissary departments, are wretchedly organized. The
                                irregulars are good enough scouts, but are not worth much as
                                fighters.</p>
                            <p>I believe the Turks have about 150,000 regulars like those above
                                mentioned, brave, patient fellows. This force of regulars is
                                scattered over the empire. Then they have two or three hundred
                                thousand irregulars, varying in utility from half-drilled reserves
                                to the entirely worthless Bashi-Bazouks.</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>E. F. BEALE.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>