<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 288.Mr. Adee to Mr. Fish.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1877</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d288</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">288</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1876-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1876-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067417"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International law</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1876-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1876-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="288"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d288">
                <head>No. 288.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adee</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Fish</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1876-12-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">December</hi> 4, 1876</date>. (Received December
                        26.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 449.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: General Concha has at last carried his point and
                    succeeded in making a set speech in the senate on the conduct of the war in
                    Cuba, in support of his recent motion reported in my No. 445. His speech was in
                    the main, a defense of his own late unfortunate command in Cuba, when the <hi
                        rend="italic">trocha</hi> was passed and Las Villas invaded with such
                    disastrous results by the insurgent forces.</p>
                <p>Mr. Calderon y Collantes replied, dwelling with much force and some bitterness on
                    the incidents of that campaign, which seems to be a sore point with the Marquis
                    de la Habana. The minister of war made a few remarks in answer to allusions, and
                    the debate was adjourned over until to-day.</p>
                <p>I send you copy of the Gaceta’s appendix with the report of the proceedings, and
                    also append translation of the remarks of the general and the minister
                    concerning the relations between Spain and the United States.</p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>A. AUGUSTUS ADEE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0539" n="491" xml:id="pg_491"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Extracts from the speeches of General Concha and Mr.
                            Calderon y Collantes, in the Senate, December</hi> 2, 1876.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#center">[From the Gaceta de
                                <placeName>Madrid</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1876-12-03">December 3, 1876</date>.]</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Marquis de la Habana</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >General Concha</hi>): * * * Mention has been made of the perils and
                        complications which the continuance of the war may cause with the United
                        States. This is a very important and serious point, and the more so because
                        of the deplorable declarations of the minister of state on the occasion of a
                        parliamentary incident which occurred when I had the honor to request of the
                        minister of war certain documents which I considered indispensable.</p>
                    <p>With what reason or right can this war of bandits, without a political banner
                        of any kind, be the cause of complications with the United States? What, has
                        not the republic of the United States in its history a war analogous to that
                        of Cuba, which lasted fourteen years? If complications arise with the United
                        States, the minister of state finds his path traced out for their solution;
                        if there be a fact of doubtful right, let him treat it with the desire of
                        reaching an honorable settlement; but if, unfortunately, the rights, the
                        dignity, or the integrity of Spain be attacked, let him answer, not
                        haughtily, but with energy, in accordance with the sentiments of the junta
                        of generals.<note n="*" xml:id="d288fn1">This junta was created in December,
                            1873.</note> But this can not occur, for there are no statesmen in the
                        American nation who can to-day wish to annex Cuba at the risk of a war with
                        Spain. For my part, I am convinced that this dread which assails the
                        minister of state is really a grave danger, for instead of a frank and
                        friendly policy with the United States it will lead to a suspicious and
                        distrustful policy, the policy of fear, which is the worst of all.</p>
                    <p>The same thing took place when the question of belligerence was treated in
                        Congress; there were some who deemed Cuba lost, and others who boastfully,
                        and without any necessity for it, went to work to enumerate the sea and land
                        forces of Spain. I was then captain-general of Cuba, and I never gave to
                        that question more importance than it possessed, because I knew that there
                        would not be taken by the American Government a step so contrary to all
                        international law.</p>
                    <p>Let the minister of state read the communications which exist; in his
                        department, and he will see that I never expressed myself alarmed because of
                        the discussion of that question in Congress, and that there is not a single
                        reclamation against me for having failed in my duty toward foreign subjects,
                        without this in any way interfering with my taking the necessary steps
                        against those who openly infringed the laws of the land. Behold, Messrs.
                        Senators, what is my understanding of our position with respect to Cuba, and
                        what good reason I have to be surprised at the words of the minister of
                        state, which of themselves alone would carry disheartenment to the
                        inhabitants of Cuba, were not a protest uttered in this place, and did not
                        all of you join with me in saying, “It is not possible; there is no peril
                        for Spain.”</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister of State</hi> (<hi rend="smallcaps"
                            >Calderon y Collantes</hi>): * * * And after all, what plans has General
                        Concha revealed which were not known before? If he has spoken for the
                        purpose of throwing light on the question, then I confess that for me he has
                        thrown no light on it at all. He says the war is difficult and cannot be
                        decided in two or three battles. I, gentlemen, a poor civilian, and ignorant
                        of war matters, have learned nothing thereby, for more than a year ago, in a
                        memorandum addressed to the foreign powers, I said the same thing as General
                        Concha, and that is, that just because the war was irregular, one of genuine
                        vandalism, it offered greater difficulties in ending it; and I cited the
                        wars in the United States, the Russian wars on the frontier of Asia, and
                        what occurred in Cataluna when 4,000 or 5,000 men kept up a war for eleven
                        months in spite of our army being commanded by one of the first generals of
                        Europe, by the illustrious Marquis del Duero,<note n="†" xml:id="d288fn2">D.
                            Manuel Gutierrez de la Concha.</note> and was it ended by force of arms?
                        No; you well know that it was not, and I say no more.</p>
                    <p>That memorandum opened men’s eyes and put a stop to astonishment at the war’s
                        lasting so long, and it became understood that it did not indicate vigor on
                        the part of the insurgents or lack of means on ours.</p>
                    <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                    <p>General Concha has also spoken of our relations with the United States and of
                        words which I had spoken in this place. I accept all the responsibility, and
                        I am about to repeat them, because I think it convenient to do so. I said
                        that the insurrection in Cuba was a peril for Spain, but not in the sense in
                        which General Concha thinks. Without the United States thinking they have
                        any right to interfere in the Cuban war, which is a mere insurrection, may
                        not controversies arise leading to war in another <pb facs="0540" n="492"
                            xml:id="pg_492"/> way? Was there any need of belligerent recognition at
                        the time of the tremendous controversy of the Virginius? Does General Concha
                        know what was done in that question, which might have caused grave disasters
                        for our country? For one of the glories I have pleasure in recognizing, one
                        of the titles to the gratitude of the nation which belongs to Mr. Castelar,
                        is his avoidance on that occasion of a war which was believed to be
                        imminent. Who can assure General Concha that to-morrow, by reason of the war
                        in Cuba, there may not occur some similar event and from which we may not
                        come out as luckily as we did from the case I have just mentioned? For the
                        present moment I see no probable conflict with any nation; but a year and a
                        half ago we were environed by them. I know what it has cost to avert them,
                        and I can give assurance that never have the relations of Spain With the
                        United States been more intimate and friendly than to-day.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
