<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-05-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-05-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="294" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d294">
                    <head>No. 291.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adee</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Madrid</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-05-08"><hi rend="italic">May</hi> 8, 1877</date>.
                            (Received May 23.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 531.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The official Gazette of yesterday published an
                        important decree, whereby, in the language of its first article, “the
                        government and administration of the province of Vizcaya shall be adjusted
                        to the laws and ordinances which are in force for the government of the
                        others of the nation.” The necessity of some such measure as this has been
                        for some time painfully evident.</p>
                    <p>The law of July 21 of last year, which, prior to its passage, formed the text
                        of Mr. Cushing’s dispatch No. 998, on the foral question, while abolishing
                        the fueros of the Basque Provinces in so far as they conflicted openly with
                        the interests of the rest of the peninsula or the national unity, authorized
                        the government to maintain, in its discretion, such of the ancient
                        provincial uses and customs, and, in particular, so much of the peculiar
                        municipal and administrative autonomy, as might be practicable, in order to
                        render easier for the loyal Basques the transition from one system to the
                        other. For this purpose the fourth article of that law authorized the
                        government to confer with the representatives of the three provinces of
                        Alava, Guipúzcoa, and Vizcaya, as to the extent of the needful concessions.
                        This was accordingly done. The provincial corporations and deputations met
                        in conference with the delegates of the nation. Victorious Spain so far
                        waived the fruits of success as to treat on terms of almost international
                        equality with the three provinces. With regard to Alava and Guipúzcoa, a
                        conciliatory spirit prevailed and mutual concessions were made.</p>
                    <p>But in Vizcaya the resistance to reform was most tenacious. All classes
                        opposed reconstruction. No public opportunity was lost of manifesting
                        discontent. At the inauguration of the new Plaza de Toros at San Sebastian
                        last year, the demonstration against national unity was so marked and
                        imposing as to occasion not only comment, but distrust, approaching to
                        alarm. Rich and poor, old and young, men and women alike wore the oak-leaf,
                        the symbol of the tree of Guernica—the charter-oak of Biscay—the type of
                        their foral privileges. It was, of course, <pb facs="0557" n="509" xml:id="pg_509"/> impossible for the provincial delegates not to reflect
                        this uncompromising tendency of the people they represented. And it was
                        perhaps natural enough that this feeling should be so universal. The loyal
                        element felt that they were entitled to retain the fueros as a reward for
                        loyalty. The disloyal resented deprivation of their time-honored
                        exemptions.</p>
                    <p>The disagreement between the foral delegations and the representatives of the
                        government has long been a matter of public notoriety, and of concern. It
                        seemed impossible to overcome the narrow provincialism of the Basques. They
                        remained indifferent to the national acts performed by Spain in their
                        behalf; at home and in the colonies they held that they were under no
                        obligations to the commonwealth; that they were entitled to the privileges
                        of Spanish nationality while exempt from its burdens. They even claimed that
                        the power of sanctioning the national laws remained with the provinces; that
                        an act of the Cortes and the King could not pass the Ebro without their
                        consent.</p>
                    <p>This state of discordance could not long continue without disparagement of
                        the prestige of the nation. The last hope of compromise having been
                        abandoned, the present decree comes to put an end to the conflict. Vizcaya
                        must hereafter share the burdens as well as the benefits of Spanish
                        nationality. Her church establishment, her highways, her post-offices, and
                        her schools become now a charge upon her, in proportion with the rest of the
                        nation, instead of being a gift at the expense of the other provinces of
                        Spain. The measure is not a sweeping one, however, and special relief from
                        onerous taxation is to be given to those towns and communities which
                        suffered in defense of the national interests during the recent Carlist
                        war.</p>
                    <p>It is hardly necessary to add that the present decree gives general
                        satisfaction to the rest of Spain, which has long chafed under the burden of
                        paying for the privileges of the Basques, in return for their
                        ingratitude.</p>
                    <p>I transmit copy of this decree, as also of the law of July 21, 1876, on which
                        it is founded.</p>
                    <p>It does not seem worth while to append translation, many of the enactments
                        being of slight or local interest.</p>
                    <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                    <closer><signed>A. AUGUSTUS ADEE.</signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>