<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 32.Mr. Delaplaine to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1877</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">32</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1877-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1877-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recy8AC9V6WtsJ3M5" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec101e79d141fc02f" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="new-states">New states</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-06-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-06-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="32"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d32">
                <head>No. 32.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Delaplaine</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-06-28">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 28, 1877</date>. (Received July
                        16.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 77.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In the sitting of the Hungarian Diet on the 26th,
                    the debate on the Oriental policy of the government was continued.</p>
                <p>Count Albert Appony declared, amid the plaudits of the chamber, that he and his
                    colleagues of the conservative party were in favor of a conservative policy in
                    the Oriental question, and for the maintenance of Turkey, and that the best
                    means for assuring protection to the interests of the country consisted in
                    manifesting respect for treaties. Upon this <pb facs="0085" n="37"
                        xml:id="pg_37"/> point, said the orator, the feelings of the nation are so
                    unanimous that it would seem as if the government could scarcely lend itself to
                    any policy opposed to the national sentiment.</p>
                <p>Mr. Benjamin Kallay, a former consul-general of Austria-Hungary at Belgrade,
                    endeavored to demonstrate that Panslavism, so far as it aimed at a union of all
                    the Sclave populations of Europe, did not actually have existence. The Sclave
                    population who were not Russians did not in the least admit that Russia had for
                    its mission the regeneration of Europe. The struggle by Russia for the
                    possession of Constantinople had lasted during many past generations, and
                    although it may still meet interruptions, he believed that the result would yet
                    be accomplished. He deprecated, however, the formation of new states at the
                    frontiers, which might become a danger to the monarchy; yet he hoped that the
                    struggle now engaged in might prove a final one. He insisted that reforms were
                    indispensable in Turkey, but all attempts had been wrecked; while he regarded
                    the nation as doomed to decay under the theocratical form of Islamism, which
                    absorbed all lawful rights.</p>
                <p>The orator, in terminating, expressed his approval of the policy hitherto
                    followed by the government, and his conviction that no fear need be entertained,
                    whatever turn events might assume.</p>
                <p>The minister-president, Tisza, rose to speak, while silence and profound
                    attention prevailed in the chamber. He declared that it was an erroneous
                    assertion frequently advanced that the policy followed was in opposition to
                    public opinion, which he explained, however, by the fact that the antagonists of
                    that policy, by their constant association with each other, readily and <hi
                        rend="italic">bonâ fide</hi> held to and believed as the public opinion of
                    the country that which was simply the sentiment of their political friends.</p>
                <p>Further, if the government had listened to and followed the suggestions of
                    certain members, at least six hundred thousand children of the country would
                    have been withdrawn from their occupations and their families, and some hundreds
                    of millions in fresh imports and charges would have laid upon the shoulders of
                    the nation. And what would have been the object of such a course? To protect our
                    interests? They have been already protected, without such sacrifices. He
                    believed when the public opinion shall be enlightened and become aware of this,
                    its verdict will be that the government has acted wisely.</p>
                <p>It has been incessantly repeated that while the nation possesses a powerful and
                    valiant army, it is unnecessary to follow a timid and reserved policy. To that
                    he would reply that if the army is well equipped the merit of that does not
                    belong to those who have constantly opposed the appropriations for that purpose.
                    Besides, a powerful army does not present a reason for engaging in premature
                    action, but, on the contrary, it affords us the ability to await tranquilly the
                    march of events. That he would still add one observation to those who uttered
                    praises of the army, and that was, that in this respect they were quite correct,
                    but, on the other hand, that various expressions of distrust and suspicion
                    against certain officers of the army were inappropriate, and should at least
                    have been refrained from. He would not pretend that members of the army had not,
                    like others, their sympathies and their antipathies; but what he would sustain
                    was, that in the army reigned the sentiment of duty, and that it would
                    accomplish this duty with enthusiasm and under all circumstances.</p>
                <p>The Hungarian minister-president then referred to his preceding declarations. The
                    policy of the monarchy has reserved for itself a full and entire freedom of
                    action, and no power accuses it of entertaining <pb facs="0086" n="38"
                        xml:id="pg_38"/> subversive tendencies. In relation to the presumed
                    occupation and to the mobilization, nothing had been decided at the last
                    ministerial council, where in fact the question had not been brought forward. He
                    did not pretend that the counsellors of the crown did not occasionally, although
                    not in that conference, discuss generally similar eventualities, inasmuch as the
                    contrary would indicate on their part indifference or remissness.</p>
                <p>However, he was able to assure the chamber that within circles having the
                    prerogative of decision no person would venture to prescribe to the ministry for
                    foreign affairs any change in the present relations of possession and force at
                    the frontiers. He continued to remark that, after what had just been said, he
                    believed that it was incumbent upon him to repeat once more, that neither as
                    regarded mobilization nor with reference to the eventuality that, according as
                    matters might develop themselves, the army might be called to cross the
                    frontiers at some point, could he give any binding promise for the future,
                    because such promise was indeed impracticable, inasmuch as by such promise the
                    monarchy would be deprived, in certain eventualities, of availing itself of the
                    most efficient means of defending its interests. That he would further repeat
                    the assurance that the government was bound by no engagement on any side, and he
                    added, that for more than a year past it had often been reproached because the
                    only idea guiding its foreign policy was the protection of the interests of the
                    Austro-Hungarian monarchy to the exclusion of all sympathies and all
                    antipathies. He declared that the blood and treasure of the Austro-Hungarian
                    people should be spared as far as practicable, and that no burdens should be
                    laid upon them which could be avoided. Still he indulged the well-founded hope
                    that when eventualities might demand, the collective populations of the monarchy
                    would with enthusiasm and devotion respond to the call of their sovereign.</p>
                <p>Under that conviction, he believed that they should calmly regard even the most
                    threatening appearances, and he besought the members of the house to reflect
                    that the constantly recurring mention of danger which did not exist indicated no
                    manly courage. Besides, it was calculated to agitate the nerves of the people,
                    which result might cause depression when the moment of action should arrive, and
                    they would disbelieve the existence of danger when danger was staring them in
                    the face.</p>
                <p>The delivery of the speech was followed by loud plaudits of the chamber. Both the
                    Austrian and Hungarian journals report that it has exercised a most assuring and
                    encouraging influence. Even a telegraphic dispatch from the Emperor has been
                    addressed to the minister-president in evidence of his satisfaction, in the
                    following words: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Tisza</hi>: I cannot omit, and my love for
                            my country urges me, to congratulate and to thank you for your patriotic
                            speech.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>A telegram from Count Andrássy followed in these words: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>I congratulate you on your speech, which was so admirable that I am
                            disposed to feel envious of you.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. F. DELAPLAINE.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
