<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No 335.Mr. Maynard to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1877</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d335</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">335</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1877-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1877-10-01T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-10-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-10-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="335" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d335">
                <head>No 335.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Maynard</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-10-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">October</hi> 1, 1877</date>.
                                (Received October 23.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 185.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: During the month just closed the
                            Turco-Russian war, judging from the position of the respective armies,
                            has made but little progress Terrible fighting is reported, but nothing
                            decisive.</p>
                <p>From Asia we have heard little of military movements. The operations seem
                            to have been confined to the frontier, and on the Russian rather than
                            the Turkish side of it. As far as can be judged at present, the Russian
                            campaign in that quarter has been a total failure.</p>
                <p>In Europe there has been ceaseless activity on both sides. The Turks have
                            made tremendous efforts to gain the Shipka Pass, of which I made mention
                            in my dispatch No. 181, dated August 31, 1877; but their enemy still
                            holds it. The bulletins report frightful losses on both sides; on that
                            of the Turks nearly half of the veterans who had fought in Monte negro.
                            The Russians have taken and still bold Loftcha (Lovatz), no doubt an
                            important advantage; and have attempted to retake Plevna, still more
                            important could they have suec eded. The defense has been brilliant and
                            to this time successful, shedding great luster on the Turkish arms and
                            on Osman Pasha, the general in command. On the Russian right, Mehemet
                            Ali Pasha and the Egyptian contingent claim advantages more or less
                            considerable.</p>
                <p>The Russians are reported to have been driven from the Lom, a stream
                            which enters the Danube at Rustchuk, and to have retired behind the
                            Yantra, a parallel stream falling into the Danube a few miles farther
                            up, and as a military line for them much stronger than the Lom, no
                            doubt, so long as the Turks hold Rustchuk, Rasgrad, and Shumla. The fall
                            rains have set in, and the season is too far advanced to admit of new
                            enterprises. Should the campaign close now, it will leave a powerful
                            Russian army resting on the Danube and stretching southward to an
                            important pass of the Balkan Mountains, certainly not an inconsiderable
                            achievement.</p>
                <p>Judging by another standard, however, the campaign has been decidedly
                            favorable to the Turks. On the one hand, the high Russian military
                            prestige has been lost, and on the other the Turks have gained in this
                            respect, and much more even than their enemy has lost. The effect of
                            this campaign upon the two armies will be to bring them into the field
                            next year under very different conditions, the Russians having a far
                            higher respect for their enemy and the Turks much less for theirs. In
                            fine, Turkey becomes from this time until the end of the war a
                            first-class military power, a fact equally understood by her armies in
                            the field and by her statesmen in the cabinet.</p>
                <p>When Russia undertook to execute the judgment of Europe as declared in
                            the conference, the other powers believed—some, indeed, feared—she would
                            easily and effectually accomplish her self-imposed task. Now that she
                            has encountered unexpected difficulties, and has met with a resistance
                            which no one of them anticipated, it will be seen whether they leave her
                            to end the struggle as best she may, or rally to her support, or in the
                            interests of civilization and humanity interfere at a juncture when
                            peace would be tantamount to her defeat.</p>
                <p>The Turks continue to be supplied with war-material from abroad. Within
                            the last few days a large English steamer has arrived from America
                            loaded with ordnance stores. Several similar cargoes have been <pb facs="0658" n="610" xml:id="pg_610"/> received since the war began,
                            and not a single one has been interrupted. Considering the length of the
                            voyage, and that it is continuous from Long Island Sound to the Golden
                            Horn, we have a significant instance of the inefficiency of the Russian
                            cruisers. In this connection I may observe the superiority of the
                            ammunition used by the Turkish soldiers over that of the Russians has
                            been remarked upon as one of the causes to which their success may be
                            attributed.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>This dispatch may properly close with a reference to Montenegro. After
                            the withdrawal of Suleiman Pasha the mountaineers seem to have had
                            everything their own way. They besieged and took the much-disputed fort
                            of Niksitch; which, for the present at least, they are likely to retain.
                            The garrison which surrendered, expecting the worst, were greatly
                            surprised, it is said, at being allowed to keep their side-arms and to
                            go their way.</p>
                <p>I am, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>HORACE MAYNARD.</signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
