<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 36.Mr. Delaplaine to Mr. Evarts.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1877</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d36</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">36</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1877-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1877-08-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034249"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="recI2HMQ5lPeFbQHZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85056208"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Grain</term>
                    <term ref="recFe9iZmLH8fc4Ed" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85103898"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Harvest</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recUWDS7mLF0Wq3PO" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85146366"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="recGxSKiAmmOVqBc0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90005695"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Drought</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1877-08-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1877-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="36"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d36">
                <head>No. 36.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Delaplaine</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Evarts</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Vienna</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1877-08-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">August</hi> 21, 1877</date>. (Received September
                        5.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 93.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have seen an official report of the condition
                    of the crops about the middle of August, and I herewith append a translation of
                    the same.</p>
                <p>Yesterday the international fair, for the exhibition and sale of cereals, was
                    opened in the Rotunda, being the vast edifice in the Prater where <pb
                        facs="0091" n="43" xml:id="pg_43"/> the universal exposition of 1873 was
                    held. At the opening, the Chevalier de Chlumeeky, imperial-royal minister of
                    commerce, was accidentally prevented from appearing, but was to-day present.</p>
                <p>The assembly of producers and grain-merchants was very numerous, those from other
                    countries among the latter being estimated at over ten thousand. It is reported
                    that the amount of transactions exceeded all anticipation. With reference to
                    this, an article in the Wiener Presse has the following observations: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>In every case the present year’s crop as well as the cereal fair, as a
                            reliable valuer of the same, may indicate a turning-point in the
                            economical relations of the monarchy. The rich blessing of the harvest
                            will introduce its enlivening operation even into the minutest channels
                            of the economical organization, and the invigoration of the increasing
                            number of the population of original producers, as well as the
                            augmentation of traffic, cannot remain without an animating reaction
                            upon other branches of production, In fact, all industrial branches
                            already prepare for a lively season. How refreshing this is for the
                            community, each member feels too deeply, and it seems superfluous to say
                            it. For more than four years we languished under the ban of an
                            unexampled crisis, and the weak hopes of improvement, wherever they
                            seemed to bud, were always quickly strangled. In truth, it would be a
                            beautiful proof of the proverbial good luck of Austria if in the midst
                            of the war perplexities in a neighboring nation the accident of a rich
                            harvest and of a fortunate position of the European market should
                            accomplish that which a sorrowful reduction of expenses and laborious
                            toil had not been able to accomplish. The lessons of the past years
                            should certainly not remain without profit for the future. A
                            conscientious self-estimate and earnest labor must further conduct the
                            well-begun work of reconstruction, and form henceforward the inflexible
                            basis of our economical existence. When the leader of our foreign
                            politics shall then succeed in keeping Austria-Hungary, as hitherto,
                            aloof from all military action, we may with confidence look forward to a
                            more fortunate condition of our economical relations.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I have, &amp;c.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>J. F. DELAPLAINE.</signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Official report of the condition of the crops up to the
                            middle of August.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The crop of winter-wheat is already completed in all the grain districts, and
                        although a large quantity of wheat has been beaten down in consequence of
                        the repeated and in part heavy rains in July, this, as it chiefly took place
                        shortly before the harvesting, did not do much material damage, and only in
                        Galicia the quality of the grain suffered from the fact that the beaten-down
                        wheat was frequently attacked with rust. Especially in Hungary is found a
                        very superior quality, and there it has only exceptionally suffered through
                        the rain. Moreover, this year’s wheat is remarkable for its purity from the
                        seed of weeds, and blight is very unusual.</p>
                    <p>The quantitative results of the harvest are reported as follows;</p>
                    <p>Very good in Hungary and Croatia, in Lower Austria, Carinthia, and Salzburg,
                        and Gorizia. Good to very good in Bohemia, Moravia, as also in Styria; good
                        in Silesia, Bukovina, in Upper Austria, Istria, and Dalmatia; middling good
                        in Galicia, Tyrol, and Vorarlberg, Carinthia, and Transylvania.</p>
                    <p>The rye crop in the northern provinces has resulted well. With regard to its
                        specific weight, the rye in the western half of the empire is, according to
                        report, superior even to wheat. In Hungary, however, the quality of the rye
                        is on the average not so satisfactory as that of the wheat.</p>
                    <p>The quantitative results of the crop are represented as follows:</p>
                    <p>A very good crop in Bohemia, Lower Austria, Salzburg, Styria, Carinthia; good
                        in Hungary and Croatia, Moravia, Silesia, and Bukovina, in Upper Austria,
                        Tyrol and Vorarlberg, the coast country, and Dalmatia; middling good in
                        Galicia and Carinthia.</p>
                    <p>The barley has everywhere remained short in the straw; however, the ears are
                        mostly so well developed, that in general a tolerably good crop is to be
                        hoped. From unfavorable weather during the harvest, a considerable portion
                        of the barley lost its fine color, but actual damage, through full growth,
                        had occurred in rare instances.</p>
                    <p>The various degrees of the harvest may, according to the reports, be
                        estimated on the average thus:</p>
                    <p>Good to very good in Carinthia and Gorizia; good in Styria and Istria;
                        middling good in Hungary, Lower Austria, Vorarlberg, Tyrol, Carmthia,
                        Dalmatia; middling <pb facs="0092" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/> in Bohemia,
                        Moravia, Silas Upper Austria, Bukovina; weak middling (almost bad) in
                        Galicia.</p>
                    <p>The harvest of oats is now, with scarcely an exception, completed, and
                        presents a good return.</p>
                    <p>Maize has made great progress during the present period. Having generally
                        been favored by the weather it has attained a stately height and has
                        everywhere produced ears. Its condition justifies, in the west provinces of
                        the empire, the hope of a good crop, and in Hungary it has also materially
                        improved.</p>
                    <p>Potatoes and beets, in the western half of the empire, are for the most part
                        in excellent condition. In the eastern they suffer partially through
                        drought; still, most gratifying intelligence has been received from that
                        quarter. Potato-rot is observed, not only in Silesia and West Galicia, but
                        also in some localities of Moravia, Lower Austria, and Gorizia.</p>
                    <p>Hops have just been plucked in Bohemia, but not yet in Galicia. By Postelberg
                        good and abundant and perfect umbels are found, while in Wittingau the
                        harvest is estimated at only one-half, Good crops are promised in Galicia,
                        Upper and Lower Austria.</p>
                    <p>Wine has lately made satisfactory progress. In consequence of repeated rains
                        various evils have occurred. Especially the grape fungus (oidium) has
                        affected the vines, and has not only extended into Southern Tyrol, Istria,
                        and Dalmatia, but also into Vorarlberg, Gorizia, and Croatia. Moreover, the
                        “Brenner,” which has prevailed for some past months in Southern Tyrol has
                        planted itself in Gorizia. Further, in Dalmatia the “tortrix,” and in
                        Istria; the “black rot,” has appeared; finally, the decay of single grapes
                        occasionally shows itself.</p>
                    <p>In the last-named provinces the anticipated hopes of an abundant vintage may
                        be somewhat diminished. In Lower Austria and Styria, however, the prospects
                        of a good middling vintage are maintained, and in Hungary the grapes, where
                        not overabundant, show a very good development.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
