<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-05-21T10:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-05-21T10:00:00-05:00" n="267" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d267">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">823.24/690: Airgram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Peru</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Norweb</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-05-21T11:00:00-04:00">May 21, 1943—11
                                    a.m.</date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>A–666. Reference is made to the Embassy’s telegram no. 614 of April
                                29, 8 p.m.<note n="58" xml:id="d267fn58">Not printed.</note> The
                                Board of Economic Warfare advises that <pb facs="0288" n="276" xml:id="pg_276"/> heretofore it has requested all applicants for
                                    SP<note n="59" xml:id="d267fn59">Special Project.</note>
                                licenses for war projects to submit a copy of the program license
                                application with bills of materials to the Embassy for its
                                information. Hereafter, such copy will be presented to the Board of
                                Economic Warfare for transmission to the Embassy. The Board of
                                Economic Warfare, in the case of mining company programs, petroleum
                                company programs and other war projects, will proceed to issue SP
                                licenses without awaiting the results of any screening operation in
                                the field. This measure is necessary to insure a steady flow of
                                supplies for the war effort. However, if the Embassy wishes to
                                forward its comments with regard to the programs, these comments
                                will be taken into consideration in licensing subsequent
                                supplies.</p>
                            <p>SP licenses for non-war projects will be screened in the field in
                                accordance with the Department’s circular instruction of April 15,
                                    1943.<note n="60" xml:id="d267fn60">Not printed.</note></p>
                            <p>The Department has no intention for the present of replacing the late
                                Colonel Barbour.<note n="61" xml:id="d267fn61">Col. Percy E.
                                    Barbour, mining technician and Senior Economic Analyst; his
                                    death had occurred May 4, 1943.</note></p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>