<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of State to the Ambassador in the United Kingdom (
                    (Winant))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">312</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-12-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXmtj6SyvT64JYD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic warfare</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="312"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d312">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112A European War 1939/36251:
                    Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to the
                        Ambassador in the United Kingdom</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Winant</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-11">December 11,
                            1943</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>7842. Reference Embassy’s 8338, November 29.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The desirability of adding the phrase “in any theater of war” depends upon
                        the nature of the plans for withdrawing economic controls. It seems to the
                        Department, however, that the insertion of this phrase would tend to weaken
                        the statement as a whole bearing in mind the purpose for which it would be
                        issued. The phrase implies that adjustments in economic warfare controls
                        would be made in Europe as soon as hostilities had ended there regardless of
                        the continuation of hostilities in the Far East. Without expressing an
                        opinion upon the desirability or likelihood of such a development, the
                        Department believes that the indication of such a possibility to Proclaimed
                        List firms in Europe would weaken the deterrent effect of the program in
                        connection with which the statement is being issued.</item>
                    <pb facs="0357" n="345" xml:id="pg_345"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The sentence “such adjustments will be carried out with due regard to
                        specific circumstances” was inserted with an eye toward Argentina and is
                        designed to remove any basis for a belief in Argentina that the relaxation
                        of controls would necessarily take place equally with respect to all
                        countries regardless of the “specific circumstances”.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The word “continued” was inserted because of the applicability of the
                        present program to firms which have been exporting to the Axis in the past
                        but whom we are now requesting to discontinue their previous rate of
                        exports.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>The reference to “aid to the economy of the enemy” seems to us appropriate
                        bearing in mind the purpose of the statement to impress those firms who are
                        now exporting substantially to Axis countries. The statement does not
                        purport to be a statement of general listing policy.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Department does not feel at all strongly about any of the points raised in
                    your 8338 and the foregoing comments are being sent to you now only that you may
                    have them in mind in discussing the statement with the British authorities. The
                    Department will await your further report after the other interested departments
                    of the British Government have indicated their views.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
