<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="339" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d339">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">835.00/1501: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Argentina</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Armour</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Buenos
                                        Aires</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-06-09T02:00:00-03:00">June 9, 1943—2
                                a.m.</date><lb/>[Received 4:50 a.m.]</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>1260. In reply to your question this morning regarding public reaction to
                            present Government it is a fact that general sentiment in this country
                            is opposed to military government of dictatorship. The difficulties
                            which Uriburu<note n="15" xml:id="d339fn15">José Evaristo Uriburu,
                                President of Argentina from September 8, 1930, to February 20,
                                1932.</note> met with increasingly until he called elections late in
                            1931 are evidence of this feeling. In present instance the public will
                            react favorably only if convinced that the military phase is temporary
                            and that the Government intends to return the country to a
                            constitutional regime.</p>
                        <p>The Radical group which was in contact with Ramírez before the revolution
                            (telegram 1144 of June 1, 3 p.m.) and which represents a good majority
                            since it comprises several factions is not yet clear as to Ramírez’s
                            future plans. According to one of the leading Radicals in contact with
                            him past assurances they have received make them hopeful that he will
                            before long call the country to general elections. The alternative is a
                            military dictatorship of at least several years <pb facs="0386" n="374" xml:id="pg_374"/> duration. The Radicals expect before the end of
                            the week to ascertain Ramírez’s position. At the same time they admit
                            they must prove to him their responsibility and solidarity as a party
                            holding out to him the attractive prospect of making him their candidate
                            which in free elections would almost certainly result in his being
                            President with the backing of a large part of the country. If
                            negotiations result favorably to them they will probably issue another
                            manifesto supporting the Ramírez government. If such a declaration from
                            the Radical Party should precede our recognition this would undoubtedly
                            be preferable but this may require some days. On the other hand certain
                            of my colleagues notably of the neighboring countries are insistent that
                            recognition should be as soon as possible. Their argument is that the
                            Supreme Court has given its official recognition; that we have received
                            informal but they consider satisfactory assurances from Ramírez and
                            Storni that he intends in due time to break relations; and delay in
                            recognition will work in favor of our enemies who are already attempting
                            to create difficulties by spreading rumors to effect that Brazil and
                            Paraguay are mobilizing on their frontiers and showing an unfriendly
                            attitude to the Provisional Government. These rumors have been
                            officially denied by the Brazilian and Paraguayan Ambassadors. The
                            Government’s notification of its constitution has been received. The
                            American Chiefs of mission will hold a full meeting tomorrow at 10
                            a.m.</p>
                        <p>I shall then know the sentiments of my colleagues. I should like the
                            opinion to prevail that we should not be precipitate and I very much
                            hope that they can be persuaded individually to withhold recognition at
                            least until the end of the week or Friday morning at the earliest. In
                            1930 the first recognition came 7 days after the revolution and although
                            conditions are never the same, twice, a delay, of at the most 3 or 4
                            days should not be considered an unfriendly attitude by the Provisional
                            Government. However, should the sentiment be as I think it may be in
                            favor of immediate recognition with the threat of individual initiative
                            by several of the neighboring countries then in the interests of
                            American solidarity I think we should be best advised to agree. A number
                            of the small countries will undoubtedly follow our lead (two at least
                            have already received instructions to do so). And if we appear
                            instrumental in having them withhold recognition while others grant it
                            we should get off to a bad start, with the Government. However, after
                            conversation this morning with the above-mentioned Radical I have the
                            impression that his group feels that the withholding of recognition by
                            all American nations for a short time may incline Ramírez to be fully
                            cooperative with them. This <pb facs="0387" n="375" xml:id="pg_375"/>
                            frankly would have the beneficial result of making the President’s
                            position more solid among Liberal elements among whom are many friends
                            of the United States and of leading to an early return of the country to
                            a constitutional regime.</p>
                        <p>With regard to foreign policy our informant of this morning feels Ramírez
                            is bent on the fullest collaboration with the United States a position
                            he has reflected to the Radicals since the beginning. This, however, he
                            does not feel will be immediate in view of division in the army on the
                            subject.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Armour</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>