<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="503" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d503">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">811.20 Defense (M) Bolivia/750</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Ambassador in
                                Bolivia</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Boal</hi>)<note n="52" xml:id="d503fn52">Copy transmitted to the Department by the
                                Ambassador in his despatch No. 1149, January 16; received January
                                23.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">La
                                        Paz</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-13">January 13, 1943</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>Mr. Crespo, Minister of Economy, asked me to call on him yesterday
                            afternoon. He said he had rather a difficult matter on his hands. He
                            recalled that some time ago an export permit to ship 25 tons of tin
                            concentrates to Argentina had been cancelled at the request of the
                            Embassy as being in conflict with existing contracts. He said that
                            unfortunately this permit had originally been issued as a result of a
                            conversation between President Peñaranda and Dr. Ibanez Benavente, made
                            while they were on a trip together; that the President quite innocently
                            without realizing the limitations imposed by the tin contracts, had told
                            Dr. Benavente (who had purchased the tin concentrates and desired to
                            ship them to Argentina as a speculative operation) that he might do so.
                            Dr. Benavente, he said, since the cancellation of the permit, had been
                            representing to the President that having made an agreement on the basis
                            of his oral assurance with the Argentine buyers, he was placed in a most
                            difficult position through his inability to comply. Mr. Crespo indicated
                            he had been asked to bring this matter up with me again.</p>
                        <p>I told him I had no authority to commit the Metals Reserve<note n="53" xml:id="d503fn53">Metals Reserve Company, an instrumentality of the
                                U.S. Government administered under the direction of the Secretary of
                                Commerce.</note> on the subject; and at the time it first came up
                            they had not been willing to make an exception and as far as I knew this
                            was still their position.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Crespo remarked that in his opinion such exceptions were dangerous,
                            as one exception would lead to another and might result very adversely
                            to the operation of the contract.</p>
                        <p>I told Mr. Crespo that in my opinion it was not desirable to have tin
                            going out in such a manner that its destination and use could not be
                            controlled with respect to hemisphere defense interests; that if the
                            present instance were to be repeated inadvertently by other officials of
                            the Bolivian Government or senators or congressmen, the same
                            embarrassment would arise again, and it might be claimed if an exception
                            had been made in one instance there was no reason to refuse to make one
                            under similar circumstances. However, I explained to Mr. Crespo that I
                            was not in a position to express an official view but this represented
                            my personal opinion. Mr. Crespo said he entirely <pb facs="0565" n="553" xml:id="pg_553"/> agreed on this point and he had already made up
                            his mind in the same sense.</p>
                        <p>I said that I did not feel I could take up the matter at all unless I had
                            specific data now on the circumstances under which the tin had been
                            purchased by Dr. Benavente, the price he paid, the price he expected to
                            sell at; any contracts or agreements involved and the names of the
                            intended consignees. He said that if it became necessary he would supply
                            such data to me, but he thought the matter might rest where it now is as
                            I evidently was not in a position to hold out any hope to him regarding
                            the making of an exception.</p>
                        <p>Mr. Crespo remarked that there was an exception allowing for an annual
                            shipment of 25 tons of unrefined tin to Chile. He wondered whether this
                            exception for one year to Chile might not be transferred to cover the
                            shipment to Argentina, cancelling the one year provision with Chile. I
                            remarked we had recently been notified by the Ministry of Economy that
                                Hochschild<note n="54" xml:id="d503fn54">Mauricio Hoehschild was the
                                owner of large tin mining properties in Bolivia.</note> desired to
                            make the current 25–ton shipment to Chile. Mr. Crespo expressed
                            surprise, stating he understood the inquiry regarding the shipment to
                            Chile had been made on the basis of one half ton, not on 25 tons. He
                            said he would look into this immediately as he was unaware that anything
                            had been done on the whole 25 ton exception for Chile.</p>
                        <closer><signed>P. <hi rend="smallcaps">de L. Boal</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>