<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-12-12T23:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-12-12T23:00:00-05:00" n="653" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d653">
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">561.333D3/1614: Telegram</note>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of State</gloss> to
                                the Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi></persName>)</head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-12-13T00:00:00-04:00">December 13,
                                    1943—midnight.</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>4553. With reference to Penteado’s statement referred to in Embassy’s
                            telegram 5660, December 10, information received by Department indicates
                            that Penteado is principally responsible for the publicity which has
                            been given to the price matter.</p>
                        <p>Department and Foreign Economic Administration now have under
                            consideration for transmittal to the Embassy a proposed note to the
                            Foreign Minister strongly urging in the interest of both countries the
                            termination of the coffee purchase agreement suggested in Department’s
                            telegram 4156, November 9.<note n="99" xml:id="d653fn99"><hi rend="italic">Post</hi>, <ref target="#pg_740">p.
                                740</ref>.</note> It is hoped therefore that developments regarding
                            the present price problem will not be such as to prejudice termination
                            of the agreement.</p>
                        <p>The Embassy is requested unless it perceives objection to bring to the
                            attention of the appropriate Brazilian authorities the following
                            observations: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>When considered in the light of the high rate of consumption,
                                    coffee stocks in this country are relatively small.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Should shipping become available for Brazilian coffee which
                                    private exporters are unable to utilize, the Commodity Credit
                                    Corporation is prepared to make use of the space to ship coffee
                                    to the United States.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Should a shortage of coffee develop in the United States, the
                                    Corporation is prepared to make available for consumption coffee
                                    which it has stored here.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>Should ships calling at Brazilian ports be unable to load
                                    coffee, present shipping schedules for coffee may not be
                                    maintained, since the shipping can be very usefully employed
                                    elsewhere.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <pb facs="0716" n="704" xml:id="pg_704"/>
                        <p>As was indicated in Department’s telegram 4417 of November 30,<note n="1" xml:id="d653fn1">Not printed; it reported that coffee stocks of
                                private exporters were insufficient to fill the shipping assigned
                                (561.333D3/1604a).</note> Department would prefer to have private
                            exporters use tonnage available for Brazilian coffee. It is,
                            nevertheless, necessary to assure continued movement of Brazilian coffee
                            to avoid reimposition of limitations on consumption in this country.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hull</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>