<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Ambassador in Brazil ( (Caffery) ) to the President of the
                    Brazilian Defense Commission ( (Portella))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d703</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">703</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1942-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1942-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXmtj6SyvT64JYD" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic warfare</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recQFlapfZuYOQASo" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042795"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Nationalization</term>
                    <term ref="recfstIIL5scNKk3A" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077402"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Liquidation</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recIlGN6hoHCxVp04" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Technical assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1942-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1942-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="703"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d703">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.00112A European War 1939/27590</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Ambassador in Brazil</hi> (<persName
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Caffery</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the President of the Brazilian Defense
                        Commission</hi> (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Portella</hi>
                    </persName>)<note n="74" xml:id="d703fn74">Copy transmitted to the Department by
                        the Ambassador in his despatch No. 10425, March 15; received March 26. Gen.
                        Arthur Silvio Portella was also Director of the War Materials Division of
                        the Brazilian War Department.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Rio de Janeiro</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1942-12-21">December 21,
                            1942</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Basis for Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Embassy of the United States of America believes that both in the economic
                    warfare and naval and military fields there should exist coordinated cooperation
                    between the allied Governments of Brazil and the United States of America, in
                    order to unite the efforts of their respective Governments in a joint program
                    against the common enemy. In accordance with this policy it is suggested that a
                    meeting be called to discuss the following points:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">I—Correlation of Controls</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Since July, 1941, the United States of America has maintained as an integral part
                    of its controls the Proclaimed List of Certain Blocked Nationals<note n="75"
                        xml:id="d703fn75">For discussions on the Proclaimed List in 1942, see <ref
                            target="frus1942v05#pg_757">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 757</ref> ff.</note> for the purpose of
                    publicizing the names of persons and firms to which the commercial and financial
                    facilities of the United States are to be refused. The Government of the United
                    States of America believes that the maintenance of this list is essential to the
                    war effort. It is further believed by the United States Government that the list
                    referred to has had a considerable effect in weakening <pb facs="0755" n="743"
                        xml:id="pg_743"/> the influence of enemy interests or interests acting on
                    behalf of the enemy.</p>
                <p>The Embassy was pleased to note the adoption by Brazil of Decree-Law No. 4807 and
                    the creation of the Economic Defense Commission, and believes that by this means
                    there may be effected an efficient elimination of enemy interests from the
                    Brazilian economic life. It is considered advisable that a clear and concrete
                    agreement be adopted between Brazil and the United States of America, concerning
                    the status of the Proclaimed List with respect to firms taken over by the
                    Brazilian Government.</p>
                <p>Generally speaking, the United States of America is prepared to delete from the
                    Proclaimed List all firms of real value to Brazil’s economy, in the event that
                    (1) all undesirable elements have been removed from the property and management;
                    (2) all undesirable employees have been removed; (3) all contracts and
                    connections with enemy interests are terminated. As to firms that are not of
                    outstanding value to the economy of Brazil, such as commercial and financial
                    establishments, it is hoped that those may be liquidated and that, consequently,
                    no problems will arise in connection with their deletion from the Proclaimed
                    List. The Embassy admits that it is necessary, as a measure preliminary to
                    nationalization of important enterprises, that the Commission assign
                    administrators to investigate and study the affairs of particular firms in a
                    position to be transferred to desirable private hands. The Embassy is prepared
                    to consider a plan which will extend facilities to these firms on a temporary
                    basis during the period prior to their nationalization and subsequent removal
                    from the Proclaimed List. In such cases, however, it is assumed that the
                    Economic Defense Commission is prepared to offer guarantees to the United States
                    of America that the administration will be an indivisible part of the program of
                    nationalization, which will be effected within the minimum possible time. As to
                    purely commercial enterprises which are not essential to the economy of Brazil
                    (many of which were centers of enemy activities), it is assumed that there will
                    be no necessity of granting them special facilities and that from the outset the
                    administrators will actually act as liquidators. This distinction is of
                    importance in the consideration of the subject by the Government of the United
                    States of America, it being understood that many of these enterprises are of
                    pronounced enemy character and have already been adversely affected, and that
                    the firms are virtually in a state of liquidation. The negotiation of an
                    agreement of this nature prior to action by the Commission in special cases will
                    afford the two Governments an opportunity to proceed jointly in a spirit of
                    understanding.</p>
                <pb facs="0756" n="744" xml:id="pg_744"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">II—Financial and Technical Assistance</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The United States of America believes that the nationalization of enemy
                    industrial enterprises in Brazil is of great importance to our common war
                    effort. Many of these enterprises are equipped to produce materials of vital
                    importance, and their nationalization will have the effect both of destroying
                    the enemy interests and of increasing Brazilian war potential.</p>
                <p>In order to avoid the transfer of these properties to undesirable hands the
                    Government of the United States of America is prepared, if so desired, to offer
                    financial assistance in the form of advances of credit to reliable Brazilian
                    parties, in order to facilitate the purchase of these properties after their
                    expropriation. It is further suggested that this matter be discussed with the
                    Director of Exchange of the Bank of Brazil,<note n="76" xml:id="d703fn76"
                        >Francisco Alves dos Santos Filho.</note> who is familiar with the opinion
                    of the President of the Export-Import Bank<note n="77" xml:id="d703fn77">Warren
                        Lee Pierson.</note> on this subject. The Export-Import Bank, generally
                    speaking, transacts business in Brazil exclusively through the intermediary of
                    the Bank of Brazil.</p>
                <p>To the extent desired, although within the limits imposed by our present war
                    effort, the United States of America is prepared to extend technical assistance
                    to nationalized firms, or, if the Economic Defense Commission so desires, to try
                    to interest American firms in participation in specific cases where technical
                    assistance is necessary.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">III—Consultation and Exchange of Information</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It is suggested that there be created a permanent and extra-official system of
                    contact and consultation between the two Governments, through the media of the
                    Economic Defense Commission and the Embassy of the United States of America, in
                    order to reach an understanding with respect to specific cases and exchange of
                    information. In this respect reference is made to Resolution No. VIII adopted by
                    the Inter-American Conference on Systems of Economic and Financial Control,<note
                        n="78" xml:id="d703fn78">For text of Resolution, see Pan American Union,
                        Congress and Conference Series No. 39: <hi rend="italic">Final Act of the
                            Inter-American Conference on Systems of Economic and Financial
                            Control</hi> (Washington, 1942); for comment on the Conference, held in
                        Washington June 30–July 10, 1942, see <ref target="frus1942v05#pg_58">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1942, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, pp. 58</ref> ff.</note> which establishes a
                    mutual consultation and exchange of information. The Government of the United
                    States of America has in its possession information concerning the enemy
                    interests in Brazil which may be of great value to the Economic Defense
                    Commission. On the other hand, Brazil will have available through the
                    expropriaation of enemy firms information in regard to enemy activities in
                    Brazil and other countries which may be of vital importance to the war effort
                    and the administration of the economic warfare program <pb facs="0757" n="745"
                        xml:id="pg_745"/> in other countries. The Government of the United States of
                    America is prepared to make available to the Brazilian Government any
                    information which may be of interest to that Government in that respect, and it
                    is assumed that the Brazilian authorities are prepared to reciprocate on the
                    same basis.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
