<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Chile ( (Bowers) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1943v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d757</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">757</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1943-01-22T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1943-01-22T18:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1943-01-22T18:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1943-01-22T18:00:00-05:00" n="757"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d757">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">740.0011 European War 1939/27401: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Chile</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bowers</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santiago</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1943-01-22T19:00:00-04:00"
                            >January 22, 1943—7 p.m.</date>
                        <lb/>[Received 10:48 p.m.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>149. For Under Secretary. Saw Fernández this morning and told him reason for
                    delay in President’s reply<note n="19" xml:id="d757fn19">President Roosevelt was
                        attending the war conference at Casablanca.</note> under pledge of absolute
                    secrecy to be known solely to him and President Ríos. The latter left for Vina
                    del Mar this morning because of son’s illness leaving instructions that anything
                    from Roosevelt be sent him at once. Thus explanation given was all the more
                    necessary.</p>
                <p>He said that the necessary steps are being taken to implement the agreements
                    after the rupture. Chile is asking Switzerland to take over Chilean interests on
                        [<hi rend="italic">in</hi>] Axis countries and if refused, Sweden will be
                    asked. Yesterday Spanish Ambassador told him he had not received instructions
                    from his Government but German Ambassador had said that naturally he assumed
                    Spain would take over.</p>
                <p>He said Fresco, the Argentine Fascist, now here has been under closest
                    observation of Secret Service and that he attended a dinner of 20 including von
                    Marees, the crazy leader of the Nazi party, and that not only were the speeches
                    taken down but a photograph was taken. Fresco was given 24 hours to leave the
                    country. He protested his inability to get reservation before Monday and
                    Government promised to secure the reservation. It did appeal to us and we got
                    the reservation for today. But Argentine Ambassador made an appeal on ground
                    Fresco a very prominent Argentinian who had come here with a letter from
                        Castillo<note n="20" xml:id="d757fn20">Ramon Castillo, President of
                        Argentina.</note> and begged he be permitted to stay until Monday and not
                    openly expelled. Out of deference to Ambassador this agreed to with notice to
                    Fresco should he see anyone [he?] would be taken up.</p>
                <p>This section sent to Buenos Aires.</p>
                <pb facs="0817" n="805" xml:id="pg_805"/>
                <p>German press appeared yesterday and misrepresented President’s speech and I
                    discussed this [apparent omission] with Fernández who was surprised and promised
                    to take it up with Morales at once.</p>
                <p>Important—he said that since we are now all together it would be greatly
                    appreciated and helpful were the Government permitted to have a representative
                    on the secret committee passing on the Black List<note n="21" xml:id="d757fn21"
                        >For correspondence on Proclaimed or Black List matters and efforts to
                        control financial transactions involving the Axis, see <ref target="#pg_308"
                            >pp. 308</ref> ff.</note> so if at any time Chilean economy is
                    threatened in any proposed case it can be discussed. Since the vote in the
                    contested case would be 2 to 1, the British and American on one side, and
                    especially since instructions received sometime ago said that in the event of
                    rupture this would be considered, would like instructions as soon as
                    possible.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Bowers</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
