<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-07-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-07-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="110" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d110">
                        <head>110. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d110fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss> (<persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>) Files, Job 80–B01285A, <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss> Memoranda for the Record,
                                6/5–7/20/63. Secret; Eyes Only. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> on July 12.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-07-11">July 11,
                                    1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Discussion with Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, 11 July, 5:00 p.m.</item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The content of my letter of July 10th<note n="2" xml:id="d110fn2">In his letter of July 10 to <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, attached but not printed, <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName> described discussions
                                    with the Director of the Bureau of the Budget concerning the
                                    extent to which <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>
                                    as Director of Central Intelligence (as contrasted with Director
                                    of the Central Intelligence Agency) was involved in the
                                    planning, preparation, and review of budgets, programs, and
                                    personnel requirements of the intelligence community. The letter
                                    set forth a brief agenda of issues for discussion at the July 11
                                    meeting with <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>.</note> on the subject of the budget was
                                discussed in considerable detail. It was agreed that I, as <gloss target="#t_DCI1">DCI</gloss>, should have access to the Defense
                                intelligence budgets. SecDef plans to prepare for all intelligence
                                budgets by function, setting forth cost and manpower requirements
                                similar to that of the CCP study. This will be true for <gloss target="#t_NRO1">NRO</gloss>, which is now nearing completion,
                                for General Carroll’s <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>, and the
                                classical Service intelligence operations, and for certain other
                                particular activities. All of these are in preparation at the
                                present time, and will be completed by <hi rend="italic">F</hi>all.
                                The guidelines for the preparation of budgets have been established
                                and there will be ample opportunity for review.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>I confirmed that such a procedure would meet my needs, but that it
                                was essential that I assure myself and the President that existing
                                resources in all Agencies are being used to the maximum, that there
                                is minimum duplication, that there are no visible gaps, and that the
                                intelligence community is operating efficiently and effectively.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> agreed. I
                                particularly raised the question of utilization of <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> resources and special skills.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> agreed that
                                these should not be duplicated by <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>, but that <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>
                                should make maximum utilization of such skills.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>I raised the question of LeMay’s desire to take over all aerial
                                reconnaissance. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                                indicated that this would not be advisable; he would not approve it;
                                he had so told LeMay that as far as he was concerned this issue was
                                dead. He said he thought <gloss target="#t_NRO1">NRO</gloss> was
                                operating more effectively now, and he hoped there would be a
                                continual close-working arrangement between Fubini, <persName corresp="#p_MMB1">McMillan</persName> and the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> staff.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>I raised the question of the control of detection and analysis of
                                Soviet missile and space activity, referring particularly to Dr.
                                    <persName>Wheelon</persName>’s plan for Mistic. <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> asked that Dr.
                                    <persName>Wheelon</persName> review this organizational plan
                                with Fubini, as <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>
                                felt the idea had great merit, although he was not familiar with the
                                details.</item>
                            <pb facs="0258" n="218" xml:id="pg_218"/>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> had not been
                                brought into the discussion of membership of GMAIC. He had no
                                comment, except to say that he felt there were far too many people
                                involved in all decision-making processes. He did not see why <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> necessarily had to be brought
                                into the intelligence processes merely to make their facilities
                                available, that the disciplines in NASA existed elsewhere, and in
                                general he had some reservations about the plan merely because he
                                thought that too many people were involved in all Government
                                policy-making processes. He pointed out that the number of people
                                who had injected themselves into the test ban discussions really had
                                no right to a voice with respect to policy. I would expect <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> would support Carroll’s
                                objection to <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss>’s membership on
                                GMAIC.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Reference the supplying of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                                with information on Soviet capabilities as outlined in the 11 July
                                memorandum of Elder’s and the June 14th memorandum of <gloss target="#t_USIB1">USIB</gloss>,<note n="3" xml:id="d110fn3">The
                                    July 11 memorandum is attached but not printed; the June 14
                                    memorandum was not found.</note><persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> could not recall how this question arose,
                                and asked that we discuss it further later, with General Carroll,
                                and if the issue still was unresolved, further discussion could take
                                place.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>[<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (12 lines of source text) not
                                    declassified</hi>]</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>