<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-01-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-01-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="144" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d144">
                        <head>144. Memorandum From President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2" type="from">Kennedy</persName> to the Director of the U.S. Information Agency
                                (<persName corresp="#p_MER1" type="to">Murrow</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d144fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, National
                                Security Files, Departments and Agencies Series, <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>, Box 290. Confidential. <persName corresp="#p_MER1">Murrow</persName> submitted this restatement
                                of the <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>’s mission to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> on September 26; see <ref target="#d140">Document 140</ref>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-01-25">January 25,
                                    1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>The mission of the United States Information Agency is to help achieve
                            United States foreign policy objectives by (a) influencing public
                            attitudes in other nations, and (b) advising the President, his
                            representatives abroad, and the various departments and agencies on the
                            implications of foreign opinion for present and contemplated United
                            States policies, programs and official statements.</p>
                        <p>The influencing of attitudes is to be carried out by overt use of the
                            various techniques of communication—personal contact, radio
                            broadcasting, libraries, book publication and distribution, press,
                            motion pictures, television, exhibits, English-language instruction, and
                            others. In so doing, the Agency shall be guided by the following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Individual country programs should specifically and directly
                                    support country and regional objectives determined by the
                                    President and set forth in official policy pronouncements, both
                                    classified and unclassified.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Agency activities should (a) encourage constructive public
                                    support abroad for the goal of a “peaceful world community of
                                    free and independent states, free to choose their own future and
                                    their own system so long as it does not threaten the freedom of
                                    others;” (b) identify the United States as a strong, democratic,
                                    dynamic nation qualified for its leadership of world efforts
                                    toward this goal, and (c) unmask and counter hostile attempts to
                                    distort or frustrate the objectives and policies of the United
                                    States. These activities should emphasize the ways in which
                                    United States policies harmonize with those of other peoples and
                                    governments, and those aspects of American life and culture
                                    which facilitate sympathetic understanding of United States
                                    policies.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The advisory function is to be carried out at various levels in
                            Washington, and within the Country Team at United States diplomatic
                            missions abroad. While the Director of the United States Information
                            Agency shall take the initiative in offering counsel when he deems it
                            advisable, the various departments and agencies should seek such counsel
                            when considering policies and programs which may substantially affect or
                            be affected by foreign opinion. Consultation with the United States
                            Information Agency is essential when programs affecting communications
                            media in other countries are contemplated.</p>
                        <pb facs="0308" n="268" xml:id="pg_268"/>
                        <p>United States Information Agency staffs abroad, acting under the
                            supervision of the Chiefs of Mission, are responsible for the conduct of
                            overt public information, public relations and cultural activities—i.e.
                            those activities intended to inform or influence foreign public
                            opinion-for agencies of the United States Government except for Commands
                            of the Department of Defense.<note n="2" xml:id="d144fn2">In an October
                                25 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SBK1">Bromley
                                    Smith</persName>, the Chief of the Bureau of the Budget’s
                                International Division, Robert Amory, Jr., commented negatively on
                                this paragraph of the draft statement submitted to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> on September 26: “we do not believe
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> has legal authority to
                                carry out all public information activities of other agencies
                                abroad, e.g., Peace Corps, <gloss target="#t_HEW1">HEW</gloss>,
                                Commerce, <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>, etc.” The paragraph,
                                however, was not changed.</note></p>
                        <p>Where considered advisable, and except for direct international
                            broadcasts by the Voice of America, the United States Information Agency
                            is authorized to communicate with other peoples without attribution to
                            the United States Government on matters for which attribution could be
                            assured by the Government if necessary. The United States Information
                            Agency shall, when appropriate, coordinate such activities with the
                            Central Intelligence Agency.<note n="3" xml:id="d144fn3">President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> signed an
                                unclassified version of this memorandum on February 25 for public
                                dissemination that omitted the last paragraph on <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> coordination. (Department of State,
                                    <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> Historical Collection,
                                Agency History/63) In a May 25 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SBK1">Bromley Smith</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_STC3">Tom Sorensen</persName> requested that the
                                January 25 statement be declassified except the last paragraph,
                                which should remain confidential in order that the <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss> have a single statement with more
                                force. <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName> replied
                                affirmatively in a June 17 memorandum to
                                    <persName>Sorensen</persName>. (Both in the Kennedy Library,
                                National Security Files, Departments and Agencies Series, <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>, Box 290)</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KJF2"><hi rend="strong">John
                                        Kennedy</hi></persName><note n="4" xml:id="d144fn4">Printed
                                    from a copy that indicates President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> signed the
                            original.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>