<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>237. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Mission to the
                    United Nations</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d237</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">237</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-02-14T16:07:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-02-14T16:07:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQ0ODajfiIQB8Cy" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="debt" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130" lcsh-match="exact">Debts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-02-14T16:07:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-02-14T16:07:00-05:00" n="237"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d237">
                <head>237. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Mission to the United Nations</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d237fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1960–63,
                            <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 10. Confidential; Priority; Limit
                        Distribution. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WW6">Woodruff
                            Wallner</persName> and Wilbur H. Ziehl and cleared and approved by
                            <persName corresp="#p_HFK1">Frank Hefner</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-02-14T16:07:00-05:00">February 14, 1963, 4:07 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2147. For <persName corresp="#p_PFTP1">Plimpton</persName>. Revised draft
                    instructions.</p>
                <p>Consultation with number of Congressional leaders, several friendly governments
                    and further consideration within Executive Branch, lead to following conclusions
                    and instructions which should govern <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> on
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> financing issue under consideration in
                    Committee of Twenty-One:</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Congo and Middle East operations continue to
                    serve national interest of U.S. and our financial support must be continued even
                    in face of opposition by communist bloc members, certain non-communist powers,
                    and financial incapacity or limited sense of responsibility of <pb facs="0563"
                        n="523" xml:id="pg_523"/> certain less developed governments. Support for
                    this assistance will be on increase as favorable developments continue in Congo
                    and size and cost of <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Congo forces are
                    reduced.</p>
                <p>However, measure of support for our financial assistance for Middle East and
                    Congo operations, particularly in Congressional arena, will also be influenced
                    by extent to which our negotiations successfully <list>
                        <label>(a)</label>
                        <item>enable substantial reductions from level of 47–1/2% (assessed and
                            voluntary contributions) to a maximum contribution of less than 40% for
                            U.S.,</item>
                        <label>(b)</label>
                        <item>eliminate system whereby our voluntary contributions have, in effect,
                            provided reductions to smaller countries—including communist
                            countries,</item>
                        <label>(c)</label>
                        <item>provide for increased contributions over regular budget scale for
                            other major powers, including <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                            >USSR</gloss>,</item>
                        <label>(d)</label>
                        <item>establish ad hoc “peace and security scale or scales,” to apply not
                            beyond 1964 and only for existing operations, and</item>
                        <label>(e)</label>
                        <item>provide for a control mechanism which affords greater voice to the
                            U.S. in <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> financing of large scale
                            peace-keeping operations.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> is urged support general criteria which
                    recognize: that whenever special circumstances make such financing possible,
                    peace-keeping operations shall be financed primarily by the nations most
                    directly concerned (for example, the present split in costs for West New Guinea
                    between the Netherlands and Indonesia); that minor peace-keeping operation
                    shall, as at present, be financed through the regular budget at the regular
                    scale (as is now done for armistice supervision teams in Kashmir, Korea, and the
                    Middle East); and the collective financial responsibility of all <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> members for approved operations.</p>
                <p>Ideally, U.S. contribution based on regular <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    scale, should be used as basis for supporting <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>
                    peace-keeping operations. Dept. fully aware of conditions that will not enable
                    achievement this objective. <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> should,
                    however, stress our strong views this position in view all other U.S.
                    contributions to international organization, magnitude our foreign assistance
                    and support regional defense arrangements.</p>
                <p>Mission should seek to secure acceptance of principle that a minimum amount for
                    Congo and Middle East operations should be financed at regular budget scale
                    rates. Dept. believes this minimum should be set at $10 million for each
                    operation.</p>
                <p>Basic point of departure for amounts above $10 million per operation should be
                    effective rates which experience has shown to be maximum which could be
                    assessed, by nation, in 1962 for Congo and Middle East. (For example, 1962
                    Afghanistan regular budget rate was 0.05%. Effective assessment peace-keeping
                    rate was 0.01%.)</p>
                <p>Remaining unassessed percentage (after above computations) to be distributed over
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership based on criteria which assures
                    that <pb facs="0564" n="524" xml:id="pg_524"/> costs are shared as widely as
                    possible among major contributors and holds the U.S. percentage of total costs
                    as close to 32.02% as possible. In no event should U.S. cost reach 40% of total
                    cost.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> should urge 21-Committee to ask <gloss
                        target="#t_SYG1">SYG</gloss> for forecast soonest of budget requirements,
                    separately for Congo and Middle East, for periods July thru December, 1963;
                    January–June 1964; and July–December, 1964. Magnitude believed partial key to
                    construction of special scale.</p>
                <p>Every effort shall be made to provide a control mechanism which affords greater
                    voice to the U.S. in the financing of large-scale peace-keeping operations. (A
                    small Committee, preferably of 15 nations or less, seems preferable.)</p>
                <p>P.L. 87–731 (bond authorization legislation),<note n="2" xml:id="d237fn2">An Act
                        to promote the foreign policy of the United States by authorizing a loan to
                        the United Nations and the appropriation of funds therefor, signed into law
                        on October 2, 1962. (76 Stat. 695)</note> especially sections 1, 4, and 5
                    contain guidance and prohibitions and are to be considered a part of these
                    instructions. They should be strictly construed. Similarly the law restricting
                    budget commitments to 33–1/3% must be carefully observed by <gloss
                        target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> in its negotiations and public
                    statements.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> shall urge the inclusion of a strong
                    section in 21-Committee’s report on the need for immediate, effective emphasis
                    on collection of back debts and 1963 assessments. Consider also whether a formal
                    recommendation from the Committee for a “Finance Minister” is advisable.</p>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> authorized use own discretion in
                    discussing these instructions in advance with friendly nations and reporting
                    reactions prior unveiling position in 21-Committee.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                            <hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
