<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-03-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-03-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="24" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d24">
                        <head>24. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant for National
                            Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG2" type="from">Bundy</persName>) to the President’s Special Counsel (<persName corresp="#p_STC3" type="to">Sorensen</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d24fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, National
                                Security Files, <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> Chron
                                File, March 1963. No classification marking.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-03-08">March 8,
                                    1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Decisions in the White House</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>It is a great advantage for you not to know how much academic nonsense is
                            written about “the decision-making process,” and it is probably not
                            sensible for me to try to add to what you know so well about the real
                            life here. Nevertheless the subject is interesting even outside the
                            world of academic jargon, and the following points occur to me: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The modes of Presidential decision are enormously varied:
                                    there is the legislative method, the press conference reply, the
                                    individual appointed, the candidate encouraged, the interview
                                    granted and refused, the news that is made or prevented, the
                                    effort at persuasion included or omitted, the speech delivered,
                                    and perhaps as important as any group of these together, the
                                    ceaseless process by which, if an administration is lively,
                                    recommendations and proposals are ground forward for
                                    consideration. What I think many people forget is that the
                                    entire Presidential existence is in this sense a process of
                                    decision.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Most big decisions have lots of history. In the most notable
                                    single case, the missile crisis, it appears as if the decision
                                    were made between Tuesday and Sunday. But the fact is that very
                                    important antecedent decisions were made at the end of August
                                    and in early September, and incorporated in Presidential
                                    statements of major significance. Earlier still, in the speeches
                                    which followed the Bay of Pigs and in a consistent set of
                                    comments <pb facs="0086" n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/> on Cuba for
                                    more than a year thereafter, the President had laid down a line
                                    of policy which was plainly inconsistent with a strategic
                                    missile base in Cuba. Equally clearly he had laid down a line of
                                    conduct developed out of his conviction that invasion of Cuba by
                                    the U.S. Armed Forces, in the absence of a major change in the
                                    situation, would not be in the national interest. Carefully
                                    construed, the decisions of October 1962 are an outgrowth of a
                                    line of policy developed by the President in many different
                                    modes over a long period of time. (And one may say, by contrast,
                                    of the Bay of Pigs, that it grew out of an early history which
                                    was not of the President’s making and had to be grafted on to a
                                    point of view which was incompletely shaped in his own mind by
                                    the time decision became necessary-and in addition he was
                                    hampered by all the difficulties and unfamiliarities and
                                    failings of men who did not know him or their own roles as
                                    perhaps they have been learning to do since.) I think the steel
                                        case<note n="2" xml:id="d24fn2">Reference is to President
                                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName>’s
                                        successful effort in April 1962 to persuade the steel
                                        industry to rescind steel price increases.</note> has quite
                                    a similar trail of preparation which was really governing in
                                    what was required of the President when the moment came, but you
                                    know much more about that than I.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>At least in my experience there is always a lot of discussion
                                    of the relative roles of the WH Staff and of Cabinet officers
                                    and their Departments and Agencies. You know as much about this
                                    as I do; my own belief is that our best course as staff officers
                                    is to make it clear that we are operating within the framework
                                    of the President’s own immediate responsibilities and are not
                                    trying to replace or blockade those who have major operational,
                                    statutory, and advisory responsibilities of their own.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>The President’s use of all arms for information and comment is
                                    as striking as his very good record in using only responsible
                                    officers for final advice and decision. This is familiar to
                                    you—but not to everyone else.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>The President’s larger policies: an open door to Moscow, an
                                    open door to all underdog Americans, an open door to
                                    intelligence and hope, honor to bravery, equal sense of past and
                                    future, gallantry to beauty, and pride in politics—these are
                                    colors of a permanent palette—reflected in the small as well as
                                    the large decisions, drawn from in a hundred ways.</item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item>The President relies heavily on others for all sorts of
                                    follow-up, and intercommunication, and preparation and
                                    recommendation. He also delegates, massively but selectively.
                                    But he is still probably the most personal President of modern
                                    times—doing more himself. You know the millions of
                                    examples.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_BMG2"><hi rend="strong">McG.
                                    B.</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d24fn3">Printed from a
                                    copy that bears these typed initials.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>