<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-07-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="259" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d259">
                        <head>259. Message from Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DHSAF1" type="from">Lord Home</persName> to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d259fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Presidential
                                Correspondence: Lot 66 D 204, <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                                Officials and <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, Box 181.
                                Top Secret. A July 29 covering memo from Denis A. Greenhill of the
                                British Embassy to Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> indicated that the attached message was for his
                                and the President’s eyes only.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>London</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-07-29">July 29,
                                1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>I have sent you my official reply to your proposal for a “moderate”
                            Resolution on Portugal and Angola but it only hints at what I want to
                            say for your and the President’s ear.<note n="2" xml:id="d259fn2"><ref target="#d260">Document 260</ref>.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Time and again you face us with situations in which you ask us to
                                vote for Resolutions which will undermine any chance we have to keep
                                the pace of independence for our remaining colonial territories
                                under reasonable control. Time and again you beg us on bended knee
                                to prevent British Guiana from achieving independence within the
                                foreseeable future, but everywhere else you make it almost
                                impossible for us to maintain control. I do not seem to be able to
                                persuade your people that you cannot have it both ways.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>If we have to vote for a Resolution which insists on the
                                employment of a highly placed United Nations personage who will go
                                to colonial territories with instructions which clearly contemplate
                                that he will confer with the members of the opposition parties, our
                                policy of bringing independence by orderly processes would be
                                completely undermined.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>If you set store, as you obviously do, by our maintaining control
                                of the situation in British Guiana, we cannot obviously allow a
                                United Nations personage to consult with Dr.
                                    <persName>Jagan</persName>.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>If we are to bring Southern Rhodesia to the point of adjusting
                                their franchise and accepting a programme whereby the African
                                majority will control the government machine within a reasonable
                                time, the <pb facs="0615" n="575" xml:id="pg_575"/> very last thing
                                we would do would be to introduce the United Nations. It would
                                immediately close the ranks against any such plan and make Rab’s
                                aims unobtainable.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>I do beg you to help us in this matter and not to corner us and
                                face us with a dilemma whether to veto, because we cannot wish upon
                                Portugal what we could not accept for ourselves, thereby getting the
                                Africans steamed up about us again in Southern Rhodesia and the High
                                Commission territories; or whether rather ingloriously to abstain
                                and then see action taken under a Resolution for which we have voted
                                solely because we did not like being parted from our friends and
                                find ourselves the next victims and unable to stand up for ourselves
                                because we have set a precedent.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>I have sent certain suggestions in my “open” message and I do hope
                                they can be adopted. The Prime Minister and I feel very strongly
                                about this and I hope you can instruct your Delegation in New York
                                to take account of our difficulties.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Without your help we will be bound to chuck in our hand in our
                                remaining Colonies and you cannot, I know, want that. I look forward
                                to talking about this soon. Meanwhile, forgive this straight
                                talking.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer><signed><persName><hi rend="strong">H.</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d259fn3">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                                    initial.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>