<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>299. Memorandum From the Chief of the Economic and Social Affairs Section of
                    the Mission to the United Nations (Finger) to the Representative to the United
                    Nations () to the Representative to the United Nations (Stevenson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d299</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">299</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="reczScuN4NlwDUBHo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85136216"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Totalitarian</term>
                    <term ref="recFzikmNCJDCCGBL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Trade unions</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-07-16T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-07-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="299"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d299">
                <head>299. Memorandum From the Chief of the Economic and Social Affairs Section of
                    the Mission to the United Nations (<persName corresp="#p_FSM1" type="from"
                        >Finger</persName>) to the Representative to the United Nations (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SAEII1" type="to">Stevenson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d299fn1">Source: Kennedy Library, <persName corresp="#p_CH4"
                            >Cleveland</persName> Papers, Human Rights, Box 19. Confidential. Copies
                        were sent to <persName corresp="#p_YCW1">Charles W. Yost</persName> (<gloss
                            target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>), <persName corresp="#p_BJB2">Jonathan B.
                            Bingham</persName> (<gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>), and
                        Nathaniel McKitterick (<gloss target="#t_IOOES1">IO/OES</gloss>). An
                        attached handwritten note by <persName corresp="#p_SAEII1"
                            >Stevenson</persName> reads: “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CH4"
                            >Cleveland</persName>—Could we discuss this? <gloss target="#t_AES1"
                            >AES</gloss>.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-07-16">July 16, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>18th <gloss target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>—Human Rights</item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. <persName>McKitterick</persName> (OES) has told me that <persName
                        corresp="#p_CH4">Harlan Cleveland</persName> is eager to have a “klieg
                    light” approach by the United States to human rights at the 18th <gloss
                        target="#t_GA1">GA</gloss>.</p>
                <p>In giving some very preliminary thought to this question, the following occur to
                    me: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Open Societies. You are familiar with this proposal elaborated a few
                            years ago but never presented as a package. I think it might be time to
                            take another look at this idea in the light of new developments.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Emphasis on the right of independent organizations. This is clearly a
                            fundamental difference between a totalitarian and a free society. The
                            very existence of organizations like <gloss target="#t_CORE1"
                                >CORE</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_NAACP1">NAACP</gloss>, not
                            to mention the Communist Party of the USA and the John Birch Society,
                            testify to the deep-rooted nature of this right in the United States.
                            Its denial to African students in Bulgaria precipitated the serious
                            incidents which developed there. This is a concept which should appeal
                            to the Africans and Asians; it is not an issue bearing a cold war label.
                            Indeed, the right of independent organizations, whether of trade unions
                            or of political groups, has often been a key element in the attainment
                            of independence around the world.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Declaration on Freedom of Information. The United States launched this
                            proposal at <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> four years ago. A
                            declaration has been approved by <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1"
                                >ECOSOC</gloss>, but the Third Committee of the General Assembly has
                            not yet acted upon it. According to a decision of the Third Committee
                            last fall, freedom of information is to get priority treatment at the
                            forthcoming session.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>It seems to me that emphasis on the foregoing aspects of human rights would put
                    the spotlight on areas in which the United States is relatively strong and the
                    Soviets relatively weak. Obviously we would make no attempt to evade the
                    question of racial equality—on the contrary, I assume we would continue to meet
                    it by full and frank exposition—but <pb facs="0699" n="659" xml:id="pg_659"/> I
                    think there is a certain tactical advantage in emphasizing general principles in
                    areas where we are strong.</p>
                <p>Thank you very much for your letter of July 10.<note n="2" xml:id="d299fn2">Not
                        found.</note> I am glad that my draft made a modest contribution to your
                    speech at <gloss target="#t_ECOSOC1">ECOSOC</gloss> which, by all accounts, was
                    most successful.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
