<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>375. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for European
                    Affairs (Tyler) to Secretary of State ) to Secretary of State Rusk</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d375</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">375</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recmwauIRZeRVl1dG" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="rec5leqjXNtlx0kjy" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85096156"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Outer space</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Science and technology</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="recptHDgZD7RVRQ5A" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recQTM14yBsvNgBmv" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="outer-space">Space program</term>
                    <term ref="recORcNZq5ClDOVNg" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85046356"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Exhibit</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear energy</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                    <term ref="recc5wAbpL3cvsf8h" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="375"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d375">
                <head>375. Memorandum From the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for European
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_TWR2" type="from">Tyler</persName>) to Secretary
                    of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d375fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                        Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, <gloss
                            target="#t_SCI1">SCI</gloss> Central Files: Lot 65 D 473. Official Use
                        Only. Drafted by D.R. Morris and R.F. Packard (<gloss target="#t_SSA1"
                            >S/SA</gloss>).</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-09-07">September 7, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Cooperation with Europe in the Development and Production of Space Launch
                        Vehicles</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">The Problem:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The recent establishment of the ten-nation European Space Research Organization
                        (<gloss target="#t_ESRO1">ESRO</gloss>) and the seven-nation European
                    Launcher Development Organization (<gloss target="#t_ELDO1">ELDO</gloss>)<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d375fn2">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <gloss target="#t_ESRO1">ESRO</gloss>
                        </hi> now includes the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, France, West
                        Germany, Italy, The Netherlands, Belgium, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland and
                        Austria. It is expected that Norway and Denmark will join within a year or
                        two. <hi rend="italic">ELDO</hi> includes the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                            >UK</gloss>, France, West Germany, Italy, The Netherlands, Belgium and
                        Australia. [Footnote in the source text.]</note> reflects European
                    aspirations in the field of outer space and raises questions of long-range
                    United States policy toward a potentially vigorous and sustained European effort
                    in space science and technology. Current US policy foresees, and <gloss
                        target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> has already offered, cooperation with <gloss
                        target="#t_ESRO1">ESRO</gloss> in <pb facs="0882" n="842" xml:id="pg_842"/>
                    space research as well as in launching its satellite experiments. There are many
                    indications, however, that the Europeans will not be content, for economic and
                    political reasons as well as for considerations of prestige, to continue to be
                    dependent upon US launch vehicles. We have been told specifically that <gloss
                        target="#t_ESRO1">ESRO</gloss> planning looks to the launching of
                    European-developed space satellites by European-built launch vehicles as soon as
                    technically possible. <gloss target="#t_ELDO1">ELDO</gloss>, with its mandate to
                    develop a European space launch vehicle, is the most obvious expression of this
                    determination. We believe, therefore, that the United States must look beyond
                    cooperation with <gloss target="#t_ESRO1">ESRO</gloss> to the more complicated
                    question of our cooperation with <gloss target="#t_ELDO1">ELDO</gloss> in the
                    development of European launch vehicle technology.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The formation of <gloss target="#t_ESRO1">ESRO</gloss> and particularly of <gloss
                        target="#t_ELDO1">ELDO</gloss> (despite US offers to supply launch vehicles
                    for the scientific payloads of individual European countries) reflects the force
                    of European determination to mount an active space program and to develop an
                    indigenous capability not dependent upon US technology and US launch vehicles.
                    In addition to considerations of prestige and pride, there is widespread view
                    among European industrial and government leaders that space technology is a
                    frontier of modern industry and of applied science which cannot be left
                    unexploited, if the dynamics of European industry and science are to be
                    maintained in the future. Visits to the United States by representatives of
                    European industry and reports from representatives of American industry abroad
                    point to an impressive level of enthusiasm, activity, and technical progress. It
                    is clear that the Europeans intend to forge ahead in this new technology.</p>
                <p>The military implications of a growing European space capability are inescapable,
                    given the fact that the technology of launch vehicles for placing satellites in
                    orbit can be applied in varying degrees to the development of missiles. The
                    extent to which this application will actually occur will depend in part on the
                    general direction in which European space technology develops. It is during the
                    present stage of initial formulation of the European effort that the United
                    States has the best opportunity to influence the direction of that effort, not
                    only toward projects less directly related to military applications, but also
                    toward an integrated, multinational program which would reinforce our broad
                    policy objectives in Europe in other fields. If we exhibit now a willingness to
                    cooperate, it may also be possible to steer the European Community toward a
                    capability in space technology which would complement our own (i.e., one which
                    would avoid duplication of our efforts and would encourage the most effective
                    use of limited Western scientific and industrial resources).</p>
                <pb facs="0883" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/>
                <p>If, however, we stand aloof from the development of European space technology,
                    the Europeans will clearly go it alone. Their capability for doing so is
                    unquestioned. There is considerable evidence that they already possess a large
                    body of knowledge gained from our technical literature, from visits to and from
                    American industry and space laboratories, from exchange of information between
                    American and European industrial representatives, from US military contracts,
                    from the Blue Streak technology, and from their own growing efforts. (A summary
                    of European programs in this field is attached at Tab B.)<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d375fn3">Not printed.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Given such an informational base and the enthusiasm displayed in industrial,
                    scientific and engineering circles, there is no doubt that the Europeans will
                    develop an independent space technology. At the same time, despite the fact that
                    the Europeans realize that they must to some extent enter this new field of
                    technology from the ground up, they hope that they may build upon experience
                    already extant in the United States so as to avoid useless duplication and to
                    make it possible for them to advance the over-all Western capability at an early
                    stage. Cooperation to this end in the foundation of an independent European
                    Community capability in space technology would be consistent with our broader
                    goals in Europe. It would parallel the similar developments which we are
                    encouraging in the field of nuclear energy.</p>
                <p>The United States has welcomed the formation of <gloss target="#t_ESRO1"
                        >ESRO</gloss> and has indicated its willingness to cooperate with the
                    Organization in the space sciences as well as to provide launch assistance for
                    the Organization’s experiments. We have not been enthusiastic about the separate
                    establishment of <gloss target="#t_ELDO1">ELDO</gloss> since its initial program
                    calls for the development of a space launch vehicle which will largely duplicate
                    existing US vehicles. We have agreed, however, to assist <gloss
                        target="#t_ELDO1">ELDO</gloss> indirectly in one respect, i.e., we have
                    agreed that the British may pass on to the other members of the Organization
                    certain data (other than information on guidance and re-entry) which we had
                    previously provided to the British and which they have used in the development
                    of the Blue Streak missile (Blue Streak was developed initially by the British
                    as a prototype intermediate-range ballistic missile, but is now to be converted
                    into the first stage of the proposed three-stage <gloss target="#t_ELDO1"
                        >ELDO</gloss> space launch vehicle.)</p>
                <p>US policy limits cooperation in space launch technology to that which would not
                    significantly enhance any national ballistic missile delivery capability. As a
                    practical matter, however, no specific guidelines have been agreed as to what
                    areas of cooperation would be permissible; nor has the question whether some
                    cooperation of this sort would be desirable been considered carefully in the
                    broader context of <pb facs="0884" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/> over-all policy
                    toward the European Community. Such guidance is being sought by <gloss
                        target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> and by representatives of the American
                    aero-space industry. In the absence of specific guidelines reflecting an
                    over-all policy, we have had to deal with requests for cooperation or
                    assist-ance in this field on an ad hoc basis, applying as the over-riding
                    criterion for decision in each case the lowest common denominator (i.e., the
                    question whether such a release or license approval would appear to assist in
                    any way the development of a national missile delivery capability) without
                    regard to other desiderata or policy considerations. Reliance on this procedure
                    is not only inadequate for <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss> and our own
                    industry, but precludes any advantageous initiative on our part and forces us to
                    stand aside from these European developments. It creates the impression that we
                    are unable to cooperate or that our cooperation is grudging at best.</p>
                <p>There is attached at Tab A for your consideration a suggested draft United States
                    Position on Cooperation with Europe in the Development and Production of Space
                    Launch Vehicles.<note n="4" xml:id="d375fn4">Not printed. An excerpt from the
                        October 3 Staff Record from the Executive Secretariat indicates that the
                        Department approved the draft position paper on October 1. The Assistant
                        Secretary for European Affairs was designated to represent the Department in
                        discussions with <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss>, the Defense
                        Department, and the President’s Science Adviser. (National Archives and
                        Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, <gloss
                            target="#t_SCI1">SCI</gloss> Central Files: Lot 65 D 473)</note> It
                    reaffirms our own national interest in such cooperation, sets forth criteria for
                    judging the general acceptability of any proposed area of cooperation, and
                    charges the Department in conjunction with <gloss target="#t_NASA1">NASA</gloss>
                    and the Department of Defense to identify specific projects involving space
                    launch technology which would contribute to Atlantic Community aims and would
                    not at the same time contribute significantly to the development of national
                    military missile capabilities.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
