<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-02-09T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-02-09T17:00:00-05:00" n="500" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d500">
                        <head>500. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Canada</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d500fn1">Source: National Archives and Records
                                Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files
                                1960–63, 399.731/2–962. Confidential; Limit
                            Distribution.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Ottawa</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-02-09T17:00:00-05:00">February
                                    9, 1962, 5 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>757. For Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> from
                            Ambassador. Greatly appreciate your attention to question US reply to
                            long-standing Canadian request on Law of Sea.</p>
                        <p>Following are my comments seriatim on questions raised your 744.<note n="2" xml:id="d500fn2"><ref target="#d499">Document
                                499</ref>.</note></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>(A)</label>
                            <item>Outright refusal on our part participate proposed canvass
                                interested nations would, I assume, greatly lessen interest <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and others. If it thus became
                                apparent to Canadians no point in pursuing multilateral
                                possibilities, then I believe Canadians might well feel obliged take
                                unilateral action.</item>
                            <label>(B)</label>
                            <item>Issue is active in Canada today though without burning intensity
                                which surrounds number other domestic political issues. Government
                                has thus far avoided action by publicly implying international
                                negotiations in progress. Liberal opposition has publicly said it
                                stands for cooperation with other interested nations but would if
                                necessary take unilateral action. <gloss target="#t_CCF1">CCF</gloss> (Socialist) member Parliament has presented bill
                                which would provide unilateral extension fishing rights to twelve
                                miles. This bill however unlikely come to vote so long as government
                                can indicate alternative solution being pursued. We are in heavy
                                pre-election atmosphere and government is growing increasingly
                                restive on this question. By coincidence <gloss target="#t_EXTAFF1">ExtAff</gloss> at personal request Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GHC1">Green</persName> made oral approach to us
                                again today urging early US reply.</item>
                            <label>(C)</label>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_CCF1">CCF</gloss> bill referred to above speaks
                                of “12-mile fishing zone” and presumably is not concerned with other
                                territorial rights. In its approach today <gloss target="#t_EXTAFF1">ExtAff</gloss> emphasized to us GOC speaking of Six plus Six
                                formula with 10-year phase-out of historic fishing rights.</item>
                            <label>(D)</label>
                            <item>I believe that by affirmative response to request participate in
                                canvass or even response which falls short of this but indicates
                                willingness sit down and talk (my telegram 234, September 1,
                                    1961).<note n="3" xml:id="d500fn3">In telegram 234, Ambassador
                                        <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> urged the
                                    Department to indicate readiness to discuss the Law of the Sea
                                    Convention with Canada even if it were not possible to hold a
                                    meeting before the Canadian Parliament reconvened on September
                                    7. (National Archives and Records Administration, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1960–63,
                                    399.731/9–161)</note> We would have good chance forestalling
                                unilateral Canadian action during <pb facs="1161" n="1121" xml:id="pg_1121"/> present session Parliament and probably until
                                after elections. For sake our bilateral relations with Canada I
                                would of course hope we could participate in canvass. I cannot judge
                                other factors involved but in this connection Canadians made clear
                                to us again today their understanding our participation would imply
                                no substantive commitment whatsoever.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In any event, as indicated my A–291<note n="4" xml:id="d500fn4">Not
                                printed.</note> there is some reason believe Canadians are becoming
                            concerned over state US-Canada relations and particularly over manner in
                            which they have dealt with us in certain current bilateral issues. If we
                            can now be moderately forthcoming on this question (and, as I believe,
                            at same time further our interests on Law of Sea question) I think we
                            would further encourage their remorse and would contribute to their
                            sense of need to husband more carefully their store of goodwill in US.
                            This would be most welcome development.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_MLT1"><hi rend="strong">Merchant</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>