<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-10-07T11:36:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-10-07T11:36:00-05:00" n="258" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d258">
                        <head>258. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy</gloss> in France to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d258fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#t_Pol1">POL</gloss> GREECE.
                                Confidential; <gloss target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-10-07T16:36:00+00:00">October 7, 1969,
                                1636Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>15340. Delto 2176. For <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1">Sisco</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_RSW1">Rockwell</persName>
                            <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> from Lodge. Ref: State 166250.<note n="2" xml:id="d258fn2">Not found. In telegram 169560 to Paris,
                                October 6, the Department of State commented: “Obviously too soon to
                                judge effect on internal developments in Greece of Karamanlis
                                initiative and succeeding moves. As long as Karamanlis working at
                                his objectives, he is keeping up desirable pressure on the Greek
                                regime.” (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_Pol1">POL</gloss> GREECE–<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>)</note> Subj: Lunch with
                            Caramanlis.</p>
                        <pb facs="0709" n="665" xml:id="pg_665"/>
                        <p>I attended a lunch of ten persons in honor of my wife and me at
                            Caramanlisʼ apartment. Before sitting down, Caramanlis drew me aside and
                            said the following: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>The situation in Greece could still be saved but there was not
                                    more than between 3 and 6 months left. At the end of that time
                                    the situation would become impossible to change in a peaceful
                                    way. It would only be possible to change by violence.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>He had made his statement out of a “sense of duty” because he
                                    considers himself to be “permanently retired from politics.” He
                                    had had an excellent reaction to his remarks.<note n="3" xml:id="d258fn3">See <ref target="#d256fn7">footnote 7,
                                            Document 256</ref>. In telegram 4516 from Athens,
                                        October 10, the Embassy expressed the view that the
                                        Karamanlis initiative was “aimed primarily at influencing
                                        forthcoming <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> policy
                                        decision.” (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 593, Country
                                        Files—Middle East, Greece, Vol. I Jan 69–Oct 70)</note>
                                    Reports reaching him indicated that 80 percent of the people in
                                    Greece applauded what he had done. He would be willing to serve
                                    if elected, but he believed strongly that not only must the
                                    colonels go but that all the old parties and politicians must go
                                    too. There had to be a new constitution and a new political
                                    structure.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Greece today, he said, had the type of military dictatorship
                                    which occurs frequently in Latin America. And yet, he said,
                                    Greece is very different from Latin America. The colonels were
                                    ignorant of politics and frivolous and impulsive in political
                                    actions of which they obviously did not foresee the
                                    consequences.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>I tried to draw him out on the question of whether the
                                    colonels would allow him to come back and conduct a political
                                    campaign. There was, I said, not much use in being popular if
                                    you could not run. After several attempts, I failed to get him
                                    to answer this in an even remotely intelligible way. Perhaps
                                    Caramanlis believes that if there was a great sentiment for him
                                    abroad, the colonels would be inclined not to prevent him from
                                    coming back to run.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_LJD1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Lodge</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>