<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-06-14T11:55:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-06-14T11:55:00-05:00" n="336" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d336">
                        <head>336. Telegram From the Embassy in Greece to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d336fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 594,
                                Country Files—Middle East, Greece, Vol. III Jan 72–Oct 73. Secret;
                                    <gloss target="#t_Exdis1">Exdis</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Athens</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-06-14T16:55:00+00:00">June 14, 1972,
                                1655Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>3335 Subj: Further Comments on the Position of Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_PLCG1">Papadopoulos</persName>.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Recent developments tend to confirm our earlier reports<note n="2" xml:id="d336fn2">
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TH1">Tasca</persName> discussed the
                                    stability of the Greek regime in telegram 2842 from Athens, May
                                    19. (Ibid.)</note> that while PriMin <persName corresp="#p_PLCG1">Papadopoulos</persName> has ostensibly
                                strengthened his position by taking over regency, he has in fact
                                isolated himself further from his colleagues and stimulated further
                                potential opposition within the establishment. He continued to be
                                concerned about the loyalty of his combat unit commanders and has
                                now taken steps to institute his own independent surveillance over
                                the activities of these units (see [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                                    line not declassified</hi>]). He has irritated both <persName corresp="#p_MN1">Makarezos</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_PS1">Pattakos</persName>, stripping them of their
                                ministries in his effort to consolidate his personal power. In
                                addition, it is becoming clear that while General Angelis is still
                                loyal, he has an independent position. The PriMin tried to induce
                                Angelis to take his man as deputy, but Angelis was able to insist on
                                naming his own deputy. Further, the precipitous appointment of
                                Colonel Roufogalos over some general officers as head of the
                                intelligence service (<gloss target="#t_KYP1">KYP</gloss>) seems to
                                have been designed to pre-empt that position before the selection
                                board assigned another officer there. This has not strengthened the
                                PriMinʼs position in a critical area within the regime.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In my view, <persName corresp="#p_RCM1">Roufogalis</persName> is
                                unsuited for this sensitive position. He is emotional and impulsive
                                whereas the Prime Minister needs even reporting and straight
                                analysis. Moreover, <persName corresp="#p_RCM1">Roufogalis</persName> is not particularly liked by his
                                colleagues in the establishment.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Another indication, always reliable during my tour of duty here,
                                that the PriMin feels insecure is the marked stepup in press and TV
                                coverage of his meetings with top <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> military. This appears to be message to his
                                colleagues that <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> military is
                                supporting him. One recent example was awkward way in which he
                                requested permission to have General Burchinal and himself
                                photographed with myself at beginning of recent special briefing by
                                Burchinal. Another recent example was insistence that General Ryder,
                                newly arrived <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> Chief, place
                                wreath on tomb of unknown soldier with TV coverage, although this
                                had not been included in original <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> program.</item>
                            <pb facs="0886" n="842" xml:id="pg_842"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Moreover, his health has apparently been bothering him, which led
                                him to have a basic examination not long ago. This tended to
                                coincide roughly with period of Burchinal briefing. He is deeply
                                concerned about his personal safety and security precautions have
                                obviously been increased in recent months, which contribute to his
                                growing isolation.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>His position is likely to be improved by recent military
                                promotions. However, larger than usual number of retirements
                                combined with stirrings among both officers in grade for lengthy
                                periods and some indications of growing restlessness among younger
                                officers, also probably increase his feeling of insecurity. It may
                                be that it is this feeling of insecurity that leads him to some
                                extent to take measures which in fact, by increasing his isolation,
                                only serve to make situation worse.<note n="3" xml:id="d336fn3">The
                                    Embassy provided an analysis of discontented elements within the
                                    Greek armed forces in telegram 5586 from Athens, September 29.
                                    (Ibid.)</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>All of this must be measured against the background of a regime
                                that has had its successes, notably in the economic field, but that
                                as yet has failed to give a clear indication of the nature of the
                                regimeʼs basic objectives and measurable achievements against these
                                objectives. The failure to implement the 1968 Constitution has been
                                a key factor in this context. There is thus an atmosphere of
                                attentisme in the country with a growing uneasiness that the regime
                                lacks political direction and momentum.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_TH1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Tasca</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>