<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>391. Telegram From the Embassy in Greece to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v29</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d391</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">391</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1972-02-09T12:10:00-05:00" notAfter="1972-02-09T12:10:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recSIsJwyicghR7T3" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Subversion</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-02-09T12:10:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-02-09T12:10:00-05:00" n="391"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d391">
                <head>391. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Greece</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d391fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 592, Country Files—Middle East,
                        Greece, Vol. III Jan 72–Oct 73. Secret; Priority; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1"
                            >Exdis</gloss>. Repeated to Nicosia and Ankara. Another copy is ibid.,
                        RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_Pol1">POL</gloss>
                        27–CYP.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Athens</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1972-02-09T17:10:00+00:00">February 9, 1972,
                        1710Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>722. Subj: Cyprus: Next Moves by Greek Government.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>: Greek Government has so far shown restraint,
                        but Czech arms import, growth of Communist Party on Cyprus, and threat of
                        Soviet involvement may be beginning tip scales in favor of some Greek
                        initiative to protect its national interests in Cyprus. In such event Greece
                        may make further attempt, either alone or in concert with Turkey, to induce
                            <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> to abandon his
                        intransigent position on compromise solution. We should be prepared to put
                        forward suggestions of our own in this context that will keep situation in
                        path of negotiation. <hi rend="italic">End summary</hi>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Until now we have sought to avoid speculating on possible Greek moves once
                        it concluded that situation in Cyprus was threatening important Greek
                        interests. While Greek Governmentʼs relations with <persName
                            corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> were precarious they were
                        manageable, and a complementary feeling of good will between Greece and
                        Turkey was slowly growing. Greek interests seemed temporarily best served by
                        a continuation of intercommunal talks, even if prospects for reaching a
                        solution through them were not great. Under those circumstances, attempting
                        to determine what might cause change in Greek position and what action
                        Greece might take as a result was highly speculative exercise indeed. Now,
                        however, in wake of import of Czech arms by <persName corresp="#p_MIII1"
                            >Makarios</persName> we consider time has come to offer some thoughts on
                        how Greeks may assess their interests in Cyprus and what steps they could
                        take. We caution, however, that our comments are based more on logic of
                        situation than on evidence.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Cyprus at present time mainly important to Greece for negative reasons.
                        While <persName corresp="#p_PLCG1">Papadopoulos</persName> could become
                        national hero through successful union of island with mother country, risks
                        are too great. Cyprus remains extremely important to Greece, however,
                        because of (A) possibility of military conflict with Turkey over Cyprus; (B)
                        effect of national crisis over Cyprus on tenure of present Greek regime; and
                        (C) threat of Cyprus to Greece should it become center of Communist
                        subversion and potential Soviet base.</item>
                    <pb facs="0999" n="955" xml:id="pg_955"/>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Any of these problems could be serious for Greece, the regime, and
                            <persName corresp="#p_PLCG1">Papadopoulos</persName> personally. Until
                        now, however, the Greek Government has shown considerable restraint in
                        dealing with Cyprus. Dangers of taking initiative, whether in concert with
                        Turkey or alone, have outweighed dangers of allowing Cyprus problem to
                        remain unsolved. It is now beginning to appear, however, that scales may
                        have come even or perhaps even tipped the other way. Thus, from point of
                        view of its own national interests, Greece may decide that some action is
                        better than allowing situation to continue to drift to point of possible no
                        return.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Since past experience has demonstrated that Greece cannot reach an
                        agreement with <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> that is
                        satisfactory to <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss> nor can it coerce him
                        into doing what it wants, the question will arise whether stronger pressures
                        on <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> could succeed.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Greek Government may soon reach conclusion that importation of Czech arms,
                        (which they may fear for distribution to leftist and Communist elements
                        supporting Archbishop), growing strength of <gloss target="#t_AKEL1"
                            >AKEL</gloss>, and possibility if not probability that situation will
                        develop in such a way that <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>
                        will call for Soviet help are creating situation which Greece can only
                        neutralize by inducing Archbishop to give in on compromise solution. In such
                        event, following courses are open to <gloss target="#t_GOG1">GOG</gloss>: <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>Arrange <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>ʼ removal
                                from power, possibly to some other ecclesiastical position, and hope
                                that ensuing confusion on Greek Cypriot side could be brought under
                                control before it degenerated into chaos;</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>Reach an agreement with Turkey on the terms for an interim
                                settlement and present Archbishop with form of ultimatum, while
                                taking steps to prevent violent reaction by forces under his
                                control;</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Reach an understanding with General <persName corresp="#p_GLGG1"
                                    >Grivas</persName> that Greek Government would not look
                                unfavorably on a mounting campaign of intimidation against Cypriot
                                Government, which would eventually so weaken <persName
                                    corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>ʼ position that he would
                                be forced either to resign or acquiesce in Greek proposals for
                                intercommunal solution giving Turk Cypriot greater autonomy than he
                                is now prepared to concede; and</item>
                            <label>D.</label>
                            <item>Mount political action campaign to discredit <persName
                                    corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName> with his own community
                                and to build up prestige of alternative leadership, presumably
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CG1">Clerides</persName>, with expectation
                                that—under a somewhat longer timetable—Archbishop could be forced
                                out of office.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>There are obviously variations and combinations of possibilities
                        enumerated above. All are dangerous, and we strongly doubt that Greek
                        Government would resort to any of them unless it concluded its interests
                        seriously threatened by <persName corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>ʼ
                        policies and actions. We have no evidence that <gloss target="#t_GOG1"
                            >GOG</gloss> has embarked on new campaign of pressure on <persName
                            corresp="#p_MIII1">Makarios</persName>, but possibility that it will
                        feel obliged to do so is <pb facs="1000" n="956" xml:id="pg_956"/> becoming
                        real. Question then arises what should <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                        do once evidence is in that Greeks are preparing to move.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>If a situation such as we have described should develop, then we can
                        assume that Greek Government has reached a very difficult and serious
                        decision based on its own interests. Under these circumstances <gloss
                            target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> counsel of moderation, support for
                        intercommunal talks, and expressions of concern that <gloss
                            target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies may be drawn into conflict will no
                        longer suffice.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>We believe we should begin now to consider how we can work in conjunction
                        with our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> allies, Greece and Turkey,
                        with British, and with <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> to bring maximum
                        influence to bear on Cyprus situation. We favor strong effort involve <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> in custody of Czech arms and concerted effort
                        to induce Greece and <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> take more serious
                        view of threat to peace on Cyprus from <persName corresp="#p_GLGG1"
                            >Grivas</persName>.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>In addition, time has clearly come, as Nicosia has already suggested, for
                            <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> to do some serious contingency
                            planning.<note n="2" xml:id="d391fn2">See <ref target="#d390">Document
                                390</ref>.</note> We would welcome Department comments, as well as
                        those of Ankara and Nicosia.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TH1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Tasca</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
