<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>421. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v29</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d421</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">421</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-04-09T17:35:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-04-09T18:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="south-and-central-asia">South Asia</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Taxes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-04-09T18:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-04-09T17:35:00-05:00" n="421"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d421">
                <head>421. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d421fn1"
                        >Source: Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_OASDISA1"
                            >OASD/ISA</gloss> Subject Files: <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 330
                        72 A 6309, Turkey 333–, 1969. Confidential. Drafted on April 11 by Krebs and
                        approved by <persName corresp="#p_NGW1">Nutter</persName>. The meeting took
                        place in Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName>ʼs
                        office.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1969-04-09T17:35:00-05:00" to="1969-04-09T18:45:00-05:00"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date">April 9, 1969, 5:35–6:45 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Call of Turkish Minister of Defense <persName corresp="#p_TA1">Ahmet
                            Topaloglu</persName> on Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1"
                            >Laird</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Turkey Side</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Minister of Defense—<persName corresp="#p_TA1">Ahmet
                                    Topaloglu</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary General for International Security
                                Affairs—Sukru Elekdag (Ministry of Foreign Affairs)</item>
                            <item>Assistant Director General, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                                Department—Muammer Akcer (Ministry of Foreign Affairs)</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States Side</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Secretary of Defense—<persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Melvin
                                    Laird</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary of Defense (<gloss target="#t_ISA1"
                                    >ISA</gloss>)—G. <persName corresp="#p_NGW1">Warren
                                    Nutter</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>Director, Near East and South Asia Region (<gloss target="#t_ISA1"
                                    >ISA</gloss>)—Brigadier General</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName>John</persName> W. Baer</item>
                            <item>Country Director for Turkey, NESA Region (<gloss target="#t_ISA1"
                                    >ISA</gloss>)—Captain <persName>Edward</persName> C.
                                Krebs</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="1085" n="1041" xml:id="pg_1041"/>
                <p>The conversation opened with an exchange of pleasantries during which the <gloss
                        target="#t_MOD1">MOD</gloss> and the Secretary noted their common background
                    as politicians. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> remarked
                    that as early as 1954 he had visited Adana and had had the opportunity to travel
                    through the political district from which Minister <persName corresp="#p_TA1"
                        >Topaloglu</persName> was elected that year. The Minister said that he hoped
                    the Secretary would have another opportunity to visit Turkey.</p>
                <p>Minister <persName corresp="#p_TA1">Topaloglu</persName> then changed the subject
                    to military assistance. Noting that the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>, over
                    a period of 20 years, had given Turkey military aid in the amount of 2.5 billion
                    dollars, he wished on behalf of his countrymen to thank the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> for this assistance. He also wished, however, to
                    explain the current situation in view of Turkeyʼs importance on the southeastern
                    flank of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> replied that he had great respect for the
                    Turkish armed forces. He had watched them train and knew they were good. He had
                    also inspected some of their port and military facilities and knew how important
                    they were.</p>
                <p>The Minister said he appreciated the Secretaryʼs awareness, and believed that
                    what was needed at present was an examination of the extent the Turkish armed
                    forces had been improved by <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> aid and what more
                    needed to be done to improve them in the face of the current threat—a threat
                    that was not Turkeyʼs alone but of all of the allies. He went on to say that the
                    aid which had been given through 1966 had averaged $144 million a year and had
                    been given to the armed forces in general. Since 1966, however, <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> military assistance had been based on a five year
                    program and fixed force goals for the Turkish armed forces. To achieve this
                    program, a decision taken in the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> Senate set
                    the aid level at $134 million a year. This was determined to be the minimum
                    level to achieve the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Bravo force goals
                    established at that time.</p>
                <p>The Minister then said that since these decisions had been taken some important
                    changes have taken place: 1) the situation in the Middle East has become worse;
                    2) the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> naval forces in the Mediterranean
                    have become a threat; and 3) the hope of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    that we could reach a détente with Russia has been dashed with the invasion of
                    Czechoslovakia. Subsequently, when <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> met
                    last fall, it was decided that member countries should do more to meet the new
                    situation. In the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting of last January
                    it was agreed that <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> members who could not
                    meet their goals and who were receiving assistance should get more aid. In spite
                    of this, <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> military assistance to Turkey dropped
                    to about $95–97 million, while costs of equipment rose very sharply.</p>
                <p>Minister <persName corresp="#p_TA1">Topaloglu</persName> next pointed out that,
                    while Turkey understood the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> situation with
                    respect to Vietnam, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> balance of payments
                    problem, and <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> efforts to protect her allies
                    over the past 20 years, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> had taken on
                    herself the leadership to protect the West and western <pb facs="1086" n="1042"
                        xml:id="pg_1042"/> ideals. She must, therefore, understand the position and
                    difficulties of her allies. He went on to say that when he attended his first
                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting in 1966 he was surprised to
                    hear that most Ministers of Defense spoke more like Finance Ministers than
                    Defense Ministers. Their talk was always of curtailing expenditures. Now, while
                    Turkey does not expect the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> to impose more
                    taxes to defend <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and Europe, there remains
                    the common problem of protecting the peace. Turkey intends to cooperate with the
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> towards this aim.</p>
                <p>The Minister next focused on the situation on the southeastern flank of <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. He pointed out that Turkey has fought more
                    wars with Russia and knows Russia better than other <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> countries. He likened Turkey to a “rock” which prevents
                    Russian encroachment into the Middle East and Africa. Whether Turkey receives
                    aid or not, it intends to preserve itself as a “rock,” as it has done for
                    centuries. Since the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> has taken steps to
                    prevent the expansion of communism into <gloss target="#t_SE1">SE</gloss> Asia,
                    it is aware that the next area for communist expansion is the Middle East and
                    Africa. Turkey is sure the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> is going to prevent
                    this, but if Turkey does not receive external assistance now it will be too late
                    later on for Turkey to assist in this task. The <gloss target="#t_MOD1"
                        >MOD</gloss> then said he had some constructive suggestions to make in this
                    respect: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>During the visit of the late Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MNJT1"
                                >McNaughton</persName>, the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and
                            Turkey had agreed that a proper level of military assistance should be
                            about $134 million a year.<note n="2" xml:id="d421fn2">Force goals for
                                the Turkish armed forces were agreed upon between the United States
                                and Turkey. According to an undated memorandum for the Deputy Chief
                                of Naval Operations: “The goals were originally proposed by
                                Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNJT1"
                                    >McNaughton</persName> to the Greek and Turkish MODs in February
                                1966. This policy was not announced to <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                                    >NATO</gloss> but was treated as a bilateral matter between the
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>… and Turkey.” (Ibid., <gloss
                                    target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 330 75–0125, Turkey 000.1–333,
                                1971) Documentation on the <persName corresp="#p_MNJT1"
                                    >McNaughton</persName> goals is ibid., <gloss target="#t_FRC1"
                                    >FRC</gloss> 330 75–0009, Turkey—<persName corresp="#p_MNJT1"
                                    >McNaughton</persName>)</note> We do not want more but only that
                            which we had agreed upon. This level should be resumed.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Bring down the price of military equipment. This would not involve the
                            Senate but lies within the power of the Administration.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Minister <persName corresp="#p_TA1">Topaloglu</persName> next presented a
                    memorandum which he explained set forth the condition of the Turkish armed
                    forces following curtailment of military assistance and some suggestions for
                    improving this condition. He highlighted these suggestions by stressing the need
                    for Fletcher class destroyers and Guppy II–A submarines, accelerated supply of
                    F–100 A/C to replace obsolescent F–84s, and faster delivery of heavy vehicles
                    and equipment for the ground forces. Referring to the policy of flexible
                    response, the <gloss target="#t_MOD1">MOD</gloss> spoke of the Bulgarian and
                    Russian capability to attack without warning as underscoring the need to improve
                    and make ready the Turkish armed forces.</p>
                <pb facs="1087" n="1043" xml:id="pg_1043"/>
                <p>In concluding his remarks, the Defense Minister said that while he is convinced
                    the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> will never leave Turkey alone and
                    defenseless, he felt it was his duty to inform Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> of the weaknesses of the Turkish armed
                    forces. He then noted that the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> had the means
                    to implement the program agreed upon over two years ago, and if implemented it
                    would eliminate many hardships.</p>
                <p>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> thanked the Minister for
                    his frank remarks on the Turkish armed forces. He said that the new
                    administration was reviewing the worldwide military situation and that this
                    review encompassed not only our own forces but our military assistance programs
                    as well. He added that our commitment in Vietnam certainly gave us problems.
                    Nevertheless, President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, by his
                    trip to Europe, has shown that he is interested in improving and strengthening
                    the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> alliance. Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> went on to say that we realize how
                    important it is to maintain our force levels in Europe, and President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> has made it plain that these will depend
                    on security requirements rather than financial hardships.</p>
                <p>Making reference to the memorandum the <gloss target="#t_MOD1">MOD</gloss> had
                    submitted, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> said he was
                    interested in the remarks the Minister had made concerning the Navy and Air
                    Force and that we would look into them. He continued by saying we have not
                    finalized our military assistance programs and we recognize your needs as
                    important not only to Turkey but to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> as a
                    whole. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_LMR1">Laird</persName> completed his
                    remarks by saying that Congressmen often asked whether <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >US</gloss> aid did not permit the recipient to do less. In the case of
                    Turkey he knew this was not the case.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
