<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-03-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="441" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d441">
                        <head>441. Intelligence Information Cable<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d441fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 633, Country
                                Files—Middle East, Turkey, Vol. II 1 Jan 1970–31 Dec 1971. Secret;
                                Priority; No Foreign Dissem. Prepared in the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> and sent to members of the Intelligence
                                Community.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">TDCS 314/02595–71</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-03-10">March 10, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">COUNTRY</p>
                        <p>Turkey</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">DOI</p>
                        <p>10 March 1971</p>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Meeting of Command Council of the Armed Forces</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft">ACQ</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft">SOURCE</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">7 lines not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>An unprecedented meeting of the Command Council of the Armed
                                Forces, chaired by Turkish General Staff (<gloss target="#t_TGS1">TGS</gloss>) Chief General Memduh Tagmac, took place at <gloss target="#t_TGS1">TGS</gloss> headquarters in Ankara on 10 March
                                from approximately 1000 to 1800 hours. The meeting was attended by
                                the Commanders of the Ground Forces, the Air Force and the Navy, by
                                the Commanders of the First, Second and Third Armies, all Corps
                                Commanders, all Air Force Area Commanders and a number of other
                                general officers.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>This meeting was convened at the insistence of a large number of
                                senior officers to discuss and reach a firm decision on measures to
                                    <pb facs="1128" n="1084" xml:id="pg_1084"/> be taken by the
                                armed forces in the face of continuing deterioration of the
                                political situation following the kidnapping of four American airmen
                                on 4 March<note n="2" xml:id="d441fn2">See <ref target="#d440">Document 440</ref>.</note> and subsequent student-police
                                clashes at Middle East Technical University and elsewhere.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Lieutenant General Hayati Savasci, Chief of Staff of the Ground
                                Forces [<hi rend="italic">1 line not declassified</hi>] stated that
                                the meeting would reach one of two decisions. Either the proposal by
                                a number of younger generals for a military takeover of the
                                government apparatus would be approved, or the solution favored by
                                General <persName corresp="#p_TM1">Tagmac</persName> and others for
                                dictation by the army to President Cevdet Sunay and Prime Minister
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Suleyman Demirel</persName> of
                                specific and immediate control measures to be implemented with a
                                facade of civilian rule would have to be adopted. <persName corresp="#p_SLGH1">Savasci</persName> added that there were no
                                other remaining alternatives.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SLGH1">Savasci</persName> further said that
                                there no longer was any question of whether the army would intervene
                                in the political situation. The army was intervening and it was
                                merely the form that remained to be decided. He said it was
                                important that a clear consensus be reached during the 10 March
                                meeting. He explained that if divisions remained, a dangerous
                                situation could result in which the disappointed parties might
                                decide to try to force their own decisions on the others. Whichever
                                result is reached, <persName corresp="#p_SLGH1">Savasci</persName>
                                said, it will be rapidly communicated down the line to all
                                commands.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>([<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Air Force commanders, in particular,
                                are quite heated up in favor of immediate military intervention and
                                are expected to oppose strongly the <persName corresp="#p_TM1">Tagmac</persName> solution.)</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>([<hi rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> See [<hi rend="italic">less than 1
                                    line not declassified</hi>] (TDCS DB–315/01243–71) for another
                                account of this meeting.<note n="3" xml:id="d441fn3">Not
                                    found.</note> As of 2400 hours 10 March, Ankara was quiet and
                                there were no visible signs of a military alert.)<note n="4" xml:id="d441fn4">After receiving the military ultimatum, Prime
                                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_DS1">Demirel</persName> and his
                                    Cabinet resigned on March 12.</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>[<hi rend="italic">2½ lines not declassified</hi>]</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>