<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-07T03:15:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-12-07T03:15:00-05:00" n="76" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                        <head>76. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Bulgaria</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d76fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_Pol1">POL</gloss>
                                    BUL–<gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Sofia</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-12-07T08:15:00+00:00">December 7, 1972,
                                0815Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>1336. Subj: Policy: U.S.-Bulgarian Relations. Ref: Sofia 1322 December
                                4.<note n="2" xml:id="d76fn2">Telegram 1322 outlined likely
                                Bulgarian scenarios for improving U.S.-Bulgarian relations.
                                (Ibid.)</note>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>. In first informal encounter with
                                FonMin <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mladenov</persName> since his
                                meeting with Secretary<note n="3" xml:id="d76fn3">See <ref target="#d75">Document 75</ref>.</note> he was effusively
                                friendly and pushed for progress toward commercial agreement.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Was cornered at Finnish reception Dec 6 by FonMin <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mladenov</persName> whom I had till then
                                successfully evaded since my return (he was in Moscow and Ankara
                                part of the time). He was effusively cordial, referred with great
                                pleasure to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> meeting with Secretary
                                and said that in view of Secretaryʼs receptivity to his suggestions
                                of various kinds of agreements we should not lose momentum but get
                                along with preparation for visit by Ivan Popov. For example, now
                                that we had U.S.-Soviet model we should be able to start drafting an
                                economic and commercial agreement.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>I replied that I was all for preparatory activity and had received
                                a general verbal brief while at home to be receptive to any
                                Bulgarian initiatives. As of the moment I had not received any
                                detailed instructions. I had plenty of authority however to continue
                                negotiating consular convention on which we were waiting their reply
                                to our last proposal 18 months ago. On commercial matters there were
                                so many technicalities involved that I suspected in the final
                                analysis this might be better discussed in Washington perhaps by
                                Deputy FonTrade Min Lukanov during January visit. <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mladenov</persName> acknowledged such trip was
                                a possibility. We were interrupted before I could pin him down
                                further on consular agreement.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Just prior to above had somewhat similar conversation with First
                                Deputy FonMin Grigorov. Latter inquiring as to Codel <persName corresp="#p_SSW1">Symington</persName> reactions and expressing
                                regret we had not accepted <gloss target="#t_GOB1">GOB</gloss> offer
                                for National Assembly to be official host which he had personally
                                pushed for at policy level. I expressed appreciation for treatment
                                of Codel and other indications of better working relations which I
                                said we were noting carefully. Said (without firm commitment) Codel
                                IPU in February <pb facs="0246" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/> might be
                                more appropriate for at least partial hosting by National
                                Assembly.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> Atmosphere was clearly changed here
                                at least temporarily but it appears that tactic is to push for early
                                reward in form of commercial progress while giving as little as
                                possible on other fronts. Would appreciate early receipt
                                Departmentʼs scenario instructions after which I will seek
                                appointment with <persName corresp="#p_MP1">Mladenov</persName> and
                                try to sort out priorities.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_THGJ1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Torbert</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>