<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>106. Telegram From the Embassy in Saudi Arabia to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve09p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-03-25T01:20:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-03-25T01:20:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXODnXWMHfVPqSC" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances">Military cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="reclIDTRPrn9Z53H4" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94004349"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">DCM</term>
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recUatc2rZ79DXSzf" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85100361"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Petroleum</term>
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2019102796"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Boycott</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-03-25T01:20:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-03-25T01:20:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <head>106. Telegram From the Embassy in Saudi Arabia to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d106fn1">
                        <p>Summary: The Embassy reported on additional conversations with Prince
                                <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName> regarding the
                            implementation of the joint commissions and raised the possibility of a
                            Saudi visit, perhaps by <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName>,
                            to Washington.</p>
                        <p>Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss
                                target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 631, Country Files, Middle
                            East, Saudi Arabia, Volume V, January 1–April 1974. Secret; Immediate;
                                <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>. Telegram 1471 from Jidda,
                            March 25, is in the National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                                >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D740063–0462. Telegram
                            45027 to Jidda and telegram 1192 from Jidda are <ref target="#d104"
                                >Documents 104</ref> and <ref target="#d105">105</ref>,
                            respectively.</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Jidda</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1974-03-25T06:20:00+00:00">March 25, 1974, 0620<gloss
                                target="#t_Z_1">Z</gloss>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1472. Subject: US-Saudi Cooperation: Prince <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1"
                        >Fahd</persName> Hopes to Visit US in May. Ref: (A) State 45027; (B) Jidda
                    1192; (C) Jidda 1471.</p>
                <p>Summary: During meeting with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJ_1"
                        >Akins</persName> on March 21, Minister of Interior Prince <persName
                        corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName> said that both King <persName
                        corresp="#p_FIAAS_2">Faisal</persName> and he were strongly in favor of
                    proposed new US-Saudi economic/technological/military cooperation (ref A).
                        <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName>’s official duties would not
                    permit him to leave Saudi Arabia during April, but in May he hoped to head a
                    team (to include <gloss target="#t_MinPet_1">MinPet</gloss>
                    <persName corresp="#p_YAZ_1">Yamani</persName>, Head of Central Planning Hisham
                    Nazer, and <gloss target="#t_MinState_1">MinState</gloss> for Finance Aba
                    al-Khail) to Washington to establish form and content of three joint
                    commissions. Because of his concern that such an important project might be
                    marred by premature or controversial leak, <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1"
                        >Fahd</persName> considering whether project could be unveiled soon via
                    simultaneous announcements in Washington and Riyadh. Prince does not plan to
                    brief <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss>’s Arab friends until time of
                    announcement or very shortly before. He would like to know if we are going to
                    give advance briefings to our European allies and others. He would welcome a
                    visit by US experts to consider projects under joint commissions after (but not
                    before) his own visit to US. End summary.</p>
                <pb facs="0412" n="377" xml:id="pg_377"/>
                <p>1. During meeting with Minister of Interior Prince <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1"
                        >Fahd</persName> on March 21, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJ_1"
                        >Akins</persName> (who accompanied by <gloss target="#t_DCM_1">DCM</gloss>)
                    said that upon receiving Secretary <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>’s instructions to propose to Saudis formation of joint
                    US-Saudi economic commissions, he had hoped to bring this information to
                    attention of Prince, before discussing it with others in <gloss
                        target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss>. Because Prince had been unavailable,
                    Ambassador had at Prince’s direction, passed info to Prince Sultan and Royal
                    Advisor Rashad Pharaon. Ambassador assumed they had fully informed Prince about
                    our proposals (ref B).</p>
                <p>2. Prince said he had received a written report on joint commissions and
                    extensive oral briefings on them as well. He was happy to express his own
                    gratification at US proposals, and could assure Ambassador King <persName
                        corresp="#p_FIAAS_2">Faisal</persName> felt the same. Prince noted political
                    relations between US and Saudi Arabia were excellent and would doubtlessly
                    remain so. He was pleased, however, <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> moving
                    to further consolidate these good relations by strengthening economic and
                    military ties between the two governments. Links we suggested could be of great
                    importance to Saudi Arabia’s own development. They would also ensure a more
                    even-handed US attitude toward the Middle East. Americans would see how a just
                    policy toward Arab world was in their own material self-interest.</p>
                <p>3. Prince <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName> wanted to move forward on
                    US-Saudi economic commissions as rapidly as possible. It was his and King’s
                    belief that he should travel to United States as head of high-ranking delegation
                    to define scope and content of various projects. Among advisors in Prince’s
                    retinue would be Minister of Petroleum <persName corresp="#p_YAZ_1"
                        >Yamani</persName>, Minister for Planning Hisham Nazer, and Minister of
                    State for Finance Mohammed Aba al-Khail.</p>
                <p>4. Prince had hoped dates for US visit could be quickly established and that he
                    could leave for US “very soon.” For a number of reasons, however, it now did not
                    appear that he could plan on departing for US before May. Prince said that Arab
                    radicals most displeased with Saudi Arabian position on oil boycott, and
                    therefore security situation re oil facilities might deserve special scrutiny in
                    coming weeks. Prince added there other matters “both great and small” on which
                    King <persName corresp="#p_FIAAS_2">Faisal</persName> also wished to have his
                    advice during April.</p>
                <p>5. <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName> said that because of great
                    importance and sensitivity <gloss target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss> attached to US
                    proposals, knowledge of these proposals has been confined to small circle of the
                    highest decision-makers. Prince believed information secure in Saudi hands but
                    added “you can never tell.” He earnestly hoped that such an important and
                    promising initiative would not get off to a bad start by some premature
                    disclosure. Accordingly, for Ambassador’s private information, Prince said he
                    had suggested to King <persName corresp="#p_FIAAS_2">Faisal</persName> that he
                    and Ambassador work out simultaneous <pb facs="0413" n="378" xml:id="pg_378"/>
                    announcement of joint commissions in US and Riyadh. His visit to US in May would
                    then give added momentum to project.</p>
                <p>6. In response to Ambassador’s suggestion that it might be useful for team of US
                    experts to travel to Saudi Arabia to work with Saudi officials for selecting and
                    defining projects, <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName> said he
                    preferred that next visit be by him to US. This would start project off with
                    maximum momentum and visibility; therefore, he would welcome assistance of US
                    experts during a follow-up visit to Saudi Arabia. <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1"
                        >Fahd</persName> said he would in next few days give Ambassador his (and
                    King’s) final views on an early joint announcement.</p>
                <p>7. In response to Ambassador’s question whether Saudis would brief their Arab
                    friends in advance of joint announcement about US-Saudi economic commissions,
                    Prince believed—again because of his concern for a tendentious leak—this would
                    not be done. Instead, Saudi Arabia’s Arab friends would receive a briefing
                    simultaneously with announcement, or perhaps a very short time before. <persName
                        corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName> asked if US planned to brief Japan or
                    its European allies about proposals. The Ambassador said he did not know what we
                    wished to do, but if we did wish to brief our allies we would inform the Saudis
                    in advance. He asked that the Saudis inform us if they decided to inform any
                    other Arabs.</p>
                <p>8. Comment: Throughout the meeting with Ambassador, <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1"
                        >Fahd</persName> showed the same decisive manner that he had in his
                    immediately preceding remarks about Saudi Arabia’s political future (ref C). If
                    in fact <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName> moves in some manner
                    during month of April to further assert his primacy (after the King) in <gloss
                        target="#t_SAG_1">SAG</gloss>’s policies, the significance and potential of
                    his visit to US in May could be even greater than envisaged.</p>
                <p>9. Action requested: Department’s views on a <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1"
                        >Fahd</persName> visit to US in (early) May, and on a joint announcement to
                    take place soon on US-Saudi project.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_AJ_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_AJ_1">Akins</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
