<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>108. Memorandum from Director of Central Intelligence Colby to the
                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( to the President’s
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve09p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d108</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">108</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1974-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1974-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122"
                        lcsh-match="exact">National security interests</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="rec0tfPbYHg7imwab" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067175"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Intelligence community</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="108"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d108">
                <head>108. Memorandum from Director of Central Intelligence <persName
                        corresp="#p_CW_3">Colby</persName> to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d108fn1">
                        <p>Summary: <persName corresp="#p_CW_3">Colby</persName> provided comments
                            on <gloss target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss> 198 and the potential problems
                            of a substantially widened <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Saudi
                            relationship.</p>
                        <p>Source: Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_OASD_1"
                                >OASD</gloss> Files: FRC 330–78–0011, Saudi Arabia 1974. Secret;
                                [<hi rend="italic">handling restriction not declassified</hi>].
                                <persName corresp="#p_HS_1">Hoskinson</persName> forwarded the
                            memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Schlesinger</persName> under
                            an April 25 covering memorandum, on which <persName corresp="#p_WJ_2"
                                >Wickham</persName> wrote: “Suggest show to Mr. <persName
                                corresp="#p_CW_2">Clements</persName>.” A note on the memorandum
                            reads: “Sec Def has seen.” <gloss target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss> 198 is
                                <ref target="#d18">Document 18</ref>.</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1974-04-24">April 24, 1974</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Study Report on US-Saudi Joint Cooperation</item>
                </list>
                <p>1. As a member of the ad hoc Special Committee established by <gloss
                        target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss> 198 to supervise the drafting of an “initial
                    study” concerning joint US-Saudi cooperation, I have reviewed the report on this
                    subject produced by the Interdepartmental Group chaired by Under Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_SJ_2">Sisco</persName>. My comments follow.</p>
                <p>2. The study report submitted by the Interdepartmental Working Group appears to
                    be an essentially sound approach to intensifying our overall relationship with
                    Saudi Arabia. Its objectives, however, will not be easy to achieve and there
                    will be many difficult problems ahead.</p>
                <p>3. The following would appear to be the major substantive problem areas:</p>
                <p>a. <hi rend="italic">The concept of simultaneously intensifying bilateral
                        relationships with Saudi Arabia, Iran and Egypt and encouraging them, at the
                        same time, to solidify their own triangular relationships is certainly
                        sound.</hi> A working coalition between these key regional states and the US
                    could stabilize the Middle East political and economic situation and is also
                    consistent with Israel’s interests. An ever-present danger is that, because each
                    of the regional states harbors suspicions and jealousies of the other two, <pb
                        facs="0419" n="384" xml:id="pg_384"/> an aggressive individual US bilateral
                    approach could jeopardize attainment of the final multilateral goal of regional
                    stability. Thus, it is important, for instance, that our actions not be
                    interpreted as an attempt to split off Saudi Arabia from the other Arab states.
                    Likewise, our initiatives with Iran must be construed in a way that will create
                    confidence in the Arab countries that we are seeking regional stability <hi
                        rend="italic">and not building up Iran to dominate the Arabs.</hi> And
                    finally, of course, the Cairo relationship must not weaken the still fragile
                    Cairo-Riyadh axis around which the mainstream of major Arab policies is
                    beginning to develop.</p>
                <p>b. There are already some indications that Saudi expectations about the fruits of
                    the new cooperative relationship may create some problems. In the security area,
                    for instance, the Saudis appear to be focussed primarily on military supply
                    rather than a broader dialogue aimed at first developing a shared conceptual
                    outlook to identify on a rational basis the points where our national security
                    interests coincide, and followed by efforts to develop specific integrated
                    policies. Likewise, in the economic field the Saudis may be interested in some
                    large investments causing problems to the US. These, of course, are natural
                    start-up problems in an exercise like this, but we will need to be attentive to
                    them.</p>
                <p>c. A related problem is that the <hi rend="italic">Saudi bureaucracy</hi> and
                    top-level decision-making apparatus is already suffering acute <hi rend="italic"
                        >indigestion from the flood of ideas, proposals and plans that they are
                        being forced to evaluate.</hi> At best we can expect that our new
                    initiatives will strain to their limits the very thin crust of competent Saudi
                    technocrats and civil servants and in some areas they are likely to be
                    overwhelmed. Added to this is the fact that the Saudis are not attuned to doing
                    business in a systematic and bureaucratically formalized way and may, therefore,
                    have considerable trouble adjusting to the joint commission-working group
                    approach. Thus the success of the exercise <hi rend="italic">will depend in part
                        on the patience and sympathy</hi> with which it is implemented.</p>
                <p>d. Our initiatives will have substantial impact on the Saudi Arabian internal
                    political scene. The Saudis have interpreted even our opening gestures as being
                    an offer by the most powerful and technologically advanced society in the world
                    to be an equal partner in tackling some of their most difficult political and
                    economic problems. The idea makes them a bit dizzy. Moreover, because of the
                    importance they attach to this development, it is setting in motion significant
                    forces within the Saudi power structure. <hi rend="italic">Prince <persName
                            corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName>’s hand, for example, has been
                        strengthened</hi> and a struggle is on within the inner circle for inclusion
                    in <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName>’s Washington trip team. Those
                    chosen will be regarded as having won the first important round in a contest
                    among the present Faysal team to see who will be tabbed to carry over and play
                    big roles <pb facs="0420" n="385" xml:id="pg_385"/> under the next generation of
                    leadership. This points up the importance of noting the impact which our plans
                    will have on the Saudi domestic political scene.</p>
                <p>e. In the economic field a key element will be how our efforts are tuned to Saudi
                    preferences for ways of doing business. The middleman/commission agent is a well
                    developed institution in the Middle East who cannot be eliminated from business
                    transactions simply on the grounds that they may be making some money in ways
                    that strict Western definition might regard as “corrupt.” The primary criteria
                    for these and related activities is their effectiveness in promoting US business
                    interests and their acceptability to the Saudis. Otherwise the paternalistic
                    role of defining for the Saudis, without their agreement, what is “right” and
                    “wrong” would cause difficulty. These “middlemen” may act as promoters of US
                    business or, if opposed, have a certain capacity to sabotage our efforts in both
                    the trade and investment fields.</p>
                <p>f. The relatively mild European reaction to our opening moves toward greater
                    cooperation with Saudi Arabia may be misleading. A combination of preoccupation
                    with other developments—Pompidou’s death, and <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss>
                    problems, for instance—and adroit US diplomacy no doubt took some of the sting
                    out of the initial European reaction. Once, however, the full extent of our
                    plans becomes known, there could be a higher European price to pay in terms of
                    future European attitudes when the issue of bilateralism versus multilateralism
                    comes up again. The closest possible continuing consultation with the Europeans
                    can help offset this kind of reaction but not entirely dispel it.</p>
                <p>4. On the procedural side, the following comments are offered:</p>
                <p>a. [<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (14 lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <p>b. The intelligence community can also make analytical contributions to other
                    joint commissions. It may in fact be worth considering the participation of the
                    National Intelligence Officer for Economic Affairs in the annual deliberations
                    of the Economic Commission. At the working group level, the economic expertise
                    of <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>’s Office of Economic Research should be
                    of considerable value. Several steps have already been taken to tune our
                    collection and analytical efforts to the requirements generated by this new
                    approach to Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <p>c. The structural pattern of setting up joint working groups to operate in the
                    period between annual sessions of the joint commissions may not be feasible in
                    all cases. Qualified Saudi personnel who can do business this way will not be
                    available in many cases; we will have to be prepared to share most of the burden
                    in between annual sessions. Setting up one high level US official to coordinate
                    and oversee our contributions is wise and necessary to avoid bureaucratic
                    confusion.</p>
                <p>d. [<hi rend="italic">1 paragraph (7 lines) not declassified</hi>]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_CW_3">
                        <persName corresp="#p_CW_3">W.E. Colby</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
