<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-01-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="216" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d216">
                        <head>216. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_OR_1">Robert B.
                                Oakley</persName> and Clinton E. Granger of the National Security
                            Council Staff to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d216fn1"><p>Summary: The <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staff
                                    examined for <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>
                                    the results of Sultan <persName corresp="#p_QA_1">Qaboos</persName>’ visit to the United States and
                                    recommended an updated study of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-Omani relations.</p>
                                <p>Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files, Box 13,
                                        <gloss target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss> 217. Secret;
                                    Sensitive. Tab A, attached but not published, is a January 24
                                    draft memorandum, entitled “Security Policy Toward Oman.” There
                                    is no indication that <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> approved an option, but <gloss target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss> 217, February 6, 1975, (see
                                        <ref target="#d217">Document 217</ref>) directed a study of
                                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> security policy toward
                                    Oman. NSDMs 92 and 186 are in <ref target="frus1969-76v24#d91"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations,</hi> 1969–1976,
                                        vol. XXIV, Middle East Region and Arabian Peninsula,
                                        1969–1972; Jordan, September 1970, Documents 91</ref> and
                                        <ref target="frus1969-76v24#d120">120</ref>.</p></note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1975-01-29">January 29, 1975</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Evolution of our Policy toward Oman</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The visit of Sultan <persName corresp="#p_QA_1">Qaboos</persName> has
                            left behind some important questions about our future security policy
                            toward Oman and the Gulf. A memorandum examining aspects of our Omani
                            relationship is at Tab B. Briefly, these questions include:</p>
                        <quote>
                            <p>—The purposes for which US military ships and aircraft need to use
                                facilities in Oman, and the existence or absence of alternative
                                facilities. (The Sultan in principle has agreed to a limited US use
                                of the airfield on Masira Island. The British have asked us what use
                                we might <pb facs="0722" n="687" xml:id="pg_687"/> make of the
                                island, noting the minimal facilities there and the need to supply
                                even water by ship).</p>
                            <p>—Our interest in directly equipping, training or advising the
                                Sultan’s forces. (During the visit of the Sultan we agreed to a
                                study team for his forces which are, at present, almost entirely
                                non-Omani in nationality. They are equipped, trained and advised by
                                those states directly engaged in helping the Sultan defeat the
                                rebellion.)</p>
                            <p>—The role of other states in Omani security and their attitudes
                                toward more direct US involvement. (The Iranians, the British, the
                                Jordanians and the Saudis are now deeply involved in supporting
                                Oman, assuming the primary military role with our approval and
                                encouragement in the context of our policy of maximum regional
                                self-reliance. The <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, with the
                                help of Iraq and South Yemen, is supporting the Omani
                                opposition.)</p>
                            <p>—The strategic and political importance of Oman for the Gulf and
                                South Arabia. (The Sultan, who is reasonably well in control after
                                two years of power when oil prices were rising, blocks certain
                                radical and Soviet interests. Oman is, however, more of a dependent
                                state than one which exercises influence of its own in the region.
                                Oman also produces a small amount of oil for export.)</p>
                            <p>—The negative aspects of a deepened US commitment to Oman and the
                                implications of a growing US military presence in South Arabia and
                                the Indian Ocean.</p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>The bases for US security policy and force deployment in the Gulf and
                            Oman are <gloss target="#t_NSDM_1">NSDM</gloss> 92 of July 30, 1970 and
                                <gloss target="#t_NSDM_1">NSDM</gloss> 186 of April 24, 1972
                            (Government Arms Sales to Oman), which directs that the primary
                            responsibility for the security of the region should fall upon the
                            states of the region, and that a continuing British role should be
                            encouraged. <hi rend="italic">An up-date is needed.</hi></p>
                        <p>We believe that before we send the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss>
                            study team for a survey of either the Masira facilities or the Sultan’s
                            forces there should be a careful review of our present policy. To date,
                            this has been remarkably successful in drawing others into cooperative
                            security efforts in the Gulf as well as Dhofar. There are, however,
                            signs of strain.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="italic">We may decide that we will want to proceed no further
                                in deepening our presence in Oman—or, alternately, that we have
                                fewer qualms now about replacing the British there. We may even want
                                to seek a major role ourself in preserving Gulf security and
                                positioning ourselves for other contingencies. However, we do not
                                now want to move in either direction without considering how small
                                steps relate to our overall strategic interests, without a review of
                                other options for protecting these interests, and without
                                considering what action we can take to minimize any unfavorable
                                repercussions of a change in our present policy. The study is needed
                                in the first instance to define the terms of reference of the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> teams which go to Oman.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">We should ask the <gloss target="#t_USC_1">USC</gloss>
                                to carefully review existing studies and the subsequent NSDMs,</hi>
                            as they apply to Oman, taking into account the questions raised above.
                            Because of widening publicity—both here and <pb facs="0723" n="688" xml:id="pg_688"/> in the Arab world—about a military role for the US
                            in the Gulf area, this study should be conducted on a very close hold
                            basis.</p>
                        <p>At Tab A is a memorandum to the Chairman of the Under Secretaries
                            Committee requesting that the study mentioned above be submitted for the
                            review of the President in no more than three weeks. The memo directs
                            that in the Department of Defense arrange the despatch of its teams to
                            Oman so that they will follow the completion of the study.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">RECOMMENDATION:</hi> That you approve the memo at Tab
                            A.</p>
                        <p>Approve __________</p>
                        <p>Disapprove __________</p>
                        <p>Other (I want the study done, but the <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> teams can proceed to Oman without waiting for the
                            conclusion of the study.) __________</p>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline">
                                <hi rend="strong">Tab B</hi>
                            </note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="strong">Paper Prepared in the Department of State</hi>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian">undated</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="italic">US/OMANI RELATIONS: RESULTS OF THE QABOOS
                                    VISIT</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>It appears that as a result of the visit of Sultan <persName corresp="#p_QA_1">Qaboos</persName> to Washington, and of the US
                                Navy’s interest in obtaining aircraft support facilities on Masira
                                Island, the strategic positions of both the US and the <gloss target="#t_UK_2">UK</gloss> in Oman are being altered, and the
                                US may be undertaking—at least implicitly—a more direct military
                                commitment in South Arabia in general.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">What Qaboos Got</p>
                            <p>During his visit last week, Sultan <persName corresp="#p_QA_1">Qaboos</persName> received US commitments for an immediate
                                delivery of <gloss target="#t_TOW_1">TOW</gloss> anti-tank missiles
                                (which he originally requested in July of last year), infrared
                                night-vision equipment (which had been agreed to prior to his
                                arrival), Claymore mines, and the possibility of pilot training in
                                both fixed-wing aircraft and helicopters. The latter question was
                                discussed between Qaboos and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SJ_1">Schlesinger</persName>, but was not pinned down in detail. In
                                addition, <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> agreed to send a team
                                of three officers to Oman to study the improvement of the Omani
                                Navy, and possibly of Omani ground forces as well.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">What Qaboos Thinks He Gave</p>
                            <p>In return, Qaboos consented to the use of Masira Island’s landing
                                facilities (presently run by the <gloss target="#t_RAF_1">RAF</gloss>) by US reconnaissance aircraft in <pb facs="0724" n="689" xml:id="pg_689"/> need of refueling or emergency
                                assistance. As far as can be determined Qaboos did not ask, and was
                                not informed during any of his meetings in Washington, about the
                                types of US military aircraft which might avail themselves of Masira
                                or the purpose and frequency of use, although the impression was
                                given that this would be only occasional. He only asked that the
                                    <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> make the necessary
                                arrangements with the <gloss target="#t_RAF_1">RAF</gloss>.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">What <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss>
                                thinks Qaboos Gave</p>
                            <p>Certainly, the US Navy is interested in Masira as a convenient
                                emergency stop and a sometime refueling facility for aircraft in
                                transit to other Indian Ocean facilities. It is also apparently
                                interested in Masira as a possible regular-use airport for Lockeed
                                P–3 Orion reconnaissance aircraft now stationed at Bandar Abbas,
                                some 450 miles further north, and as a transit/refueling stop for CV
                                support aircraft, such as the Grumman C–1, operating in the area.
                                This question has taken on greater currency with the arrival of the
                                Enterprise in the Indian Ocean, but the Navy’s interest is
                                undoubtedly of longer duration than the Enterprise’s cruise.</p>
                            <p>A related factor is the interest of the US Air Force in using Masira
                                as a landing point for F–111’s. In 1971 or early 1972, shortly after
                                Qaboos took power, the British were sounded out about the
                                possibility of a small group of F–111’s flying from Europe to Masira
                                to demonstrate the US Air force’s ability to deploy into the Indian
                                Ocean if necessary. The British deferred to Qaboos, who declined
                                permission but did not shut the door completely. It is likely that
                                this request will now be renewed by the <gloss target="#t_USAF_1">USAF</gloss>.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Implications for the <gloss target="#t_UK_2">UK</gloss></p>
                            <p>Heretofore, our interests in Oman have been well served by our
                                strategy of backing the continued military presence of the <gloss target="#t_UK_2">UK</gloss> and encouraging Iran and Saudi
                                Arabia (and to a degree Jordan and Egypt) to combat radical elements
                                in the Gulf and support Oman’s military in its struggle with the
                                South Yemen-backed rebellion.</p>
                            <p>The British have assumed the primary responsibility of advising
                                Qaboos on both foreign policy and military affairs and have exerted
                                strong influence over the direction of the Dhofar war. Although they
                                have had a payback in prestige and money from military sales to
                                Oman, late last year it took our strong urging to convince them not
                                to abandon Masira as a British base.</p>
                            <p>The weakened position of the <gloss target="#t_UK_2">UK</gloss> at
                                home and abroad is undoubtedly not lost on Qaboos, who must
                                certainly realize that before too long the British could well
                                withdraw permanently their military presence from South Arabia.
                                Reservations in his own mind about the desirability of maintaining
                                the intimacy of his relationship with the British <pb facs="0725" n="690" xml:id="pg_690"/> may already exist; there have
                                certainly been costly errors of judgment committed by his military
                                advisor, Major General Creasey, in the conduct of Qaboos’s forces
                                against the Dhofari rebels; and Yahya Omar, the Libyan loyalist
                                advisor to Qaboos, who accompanied the Sultan to Washington and is
                                involved in all military matters, makes no secret of his intense
                                personal dislike of the British.</p>
                            <p>If the Sultan is considering the possibility of eventually replacing
                                the <gloss target="#t_UK_2">UK</gloss>, his visit to Washington came
                                at an opportune time. His perception of the willingness of the US to
                                work with Oman must certainly have been reinforced by his
                                conversations here, by the eagerness of <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> for access to Masira, by our immediate supply of
                                hitherto unavailable TOWs and by our decision to send a military
                                evaluation team to Oman in the next few weeks.</p>
                            <p>The British may also see the US as a possible replacement in Oman,
                                given Labor policy of progressively phasing out military presence
                                East of Suez. Turning the base and the burden for helping Oman
                                control its rebellion over to the US could have a certain
                                attraction, although there are also elements of jealousy and
                                national pride which push the <gloss target="#t_UK_2">UK</gloss> to
                                stay. In regard to our use of the Masira airfield the British have
                                asked several specific questions about the extent to which it will
                                be used, as well as about our military supply relationship. They
                                state that they are unable to logistically support more than
                                occassional aircraft. They imply that anything greater would require
                                US assistance and, very possibly, personnel.</p>
                            <p rend="sectiontitleital">Policy Implications for the US</p>
                            <p>The reasons behind keen <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> interest
                                in access to military facilities on Masira are understandable, given
                                our strategic interest in the Indian Ocean and the Middle East.
                                Masira has an excellent location for surveillance and possible
                                interdiction of hostile shipping, not only in the Indian Ocean but
                                also the Persian Gulf and Straits of Hormuz (critical for oil
                                shipments) and the Red Sea and Bab al-Mandeb (of importance
                                vis-à-vis Israel and of even greater importance, particularly
                                vis-à-vis the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, should the
                                Suez Canal reopen). It provides an excellent link between Diego
                                Garcia and facilities available to the US in Iran, Turkey and
                                Greece. It is in a good position to support US Navy operations in
                                the Gulf, Red Sea or South Arabia. It provides a good site for area
                                familiarization and training and it would be a valuable staging area
                                in event of a conflict involving US forces.</p>
                            <p>On the other side of the coin, however, US interest in Masira will in
                                all probability generate pressures for an even closer US-Omani
                                relationship, and requests from the Omanis for US assistance in
                                weaponry and military advice which may require positive responses if
                                the use of Masira, once gained, is not to be lost. In sum, the
                                Island could <pb facs="0726" n="691" xml:id="pg_691"/> become a
                                static Omani <hi rend="italic">quid</hi> for escalating US <hi rend="italic">quos</hi>. More important, any reduction of
                                British presence in Oman will place greater onus on the US to be the
                                Sultan’s strategic ally.</p>
                            <p>At the moment, US involvement is still slight. The TOWs require only
                                two US trainers on a non-government basis, and the <hi rend="italic">occasional</hi> use of Masira by aircraft may not require US
                                support personnel. Greater involvement, particularly that which may
                                follow the visit of a <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> team,
                                could well result in a semi-permanent US military presence in
                                Oman.</p>
                            <p>The primary question that needs to be answered is whether the
                                military reasons moving the US toward a deeper relationship with
                                Oman are counterbalanced by an interest in staying out. Unless
                                clearer guidelines are developed on the basis of such a policy
                                examination, we risk slipping gradually and naturally into a
                                relationship which will be seen by Oman, Saudi Arabia, Iran, Iraq
                                South Yemen, the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_UK_2">UK</gloss> and others as being deeper than now
                                foreseen.</p>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>