<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-06-16T07:54:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-06-16T07:54:00-05:00" n="67" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                        <head>67. Telegram From the Embassy in Bahrain to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d67fn1"><p>Summary:
                                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TJ_1">Twinam</persName> and
                                    Bahraini Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_KIS_1">Shaikh
                                        Khalifa al-Khalifa</persName> discussed the Bahraini request
                                    for military assistance in exchange for an extension for <gloss target="#t_MIDEASTFOR_1">MIDEASTFOR</gloss>.</p>
                                <p>Source: Ford Library, National Security Adviser, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Staff for Middle East and
                                    South Asian Affairs, Convenience Files, Box 1, Bahrain (2).
                                    Confidential; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>. Telegram 741 from Manama, June 14, is in the
                                    National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                                    Central Foreign Policy File, D760229–0013. In telegram 761 from
                                    Manama, June 16, <persName corresp="#p_TJ_1">Twinam</persName>
                                    argued that an extension on <gloss target="#t_MIDEASTFOR_1">MIDEASTFOR</gloss> should be the <hi rend="italic">sine qua
                                        non</hi> for any negotiation on military supply. (National
                                    Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 84, Manama Embassy
                                    Files: Lot 79F118, DEF 15, <gloss target="#t_COMIDEASTFOR_1">COMIDEASTFOR</gloss>) According to telegram 129738 to
                                    Manama, May 26, the Department approved sending a survey team.
                                    (Ibid., Lot 79F80, DEF 12–5 Bahrain) In telegram 904 from
                                    Manama, July 10, <persName corresp="#p_TJ_1">Twinam</persName>
                                    reported that the United States would have to make an additional
                                    “extensive military assistance commitment” in order to secure an
                                    extension longer than one year. (Ibid., Lot 79F118, <gloss target="#t_POL_1">POL</gloss> 15, Bahrain
                                Government)</p></note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Manama</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1976-06-16T12:54:00+00:00">June 16, 1976, 1254<gloss target="#t_Z_1">Z</gloss></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>762. Subject: Middle East Force and Security Assistance for Bahrain. Ref:
                            Manama 741.</p>
                        <p>Summary: June 15 Prime Minister made to me “official government request”
                            that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> consider supplying military
                            assistance to Bahrain on concessionary terms to enable Al Khalifa regime
                            to justify “extending the agreement” under which Middle East Force
                            enjoys facilities. Prime Minister and Crown Prince/Defense Minister
                            clearly want concessionary arrangement “like Jordan and Turkey, not like
                            Saudi Arabia and Kuwait”. In promising to forward request to <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>, I stressed I was without instructions
                            and hence unable to predict substance or timing of <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> response. I explained at some length,
                            however, on “personal basis” why this request seems to call for a new
                            departure in <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Gulf policy requiring
                            the most careful top-level consideration in the executive and possibly
                            legislative authorization. Therefore on basis its own recent experience
                            with proposed technical assistance program <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> should not necessarily anticipate a quick <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> response. Meanwhile June 1977 deadline
                                <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> has placed on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Navy’s departure <pb facs="0302" n="267" xml:id="pg_267"/> is drawing nigh and Middle East Force will
                            soon need to start taking some practical steps to meet it. Should not
                                <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> as first step, and without
                            additional commitment by either government, unilaterally extend the
                            deadline? Prime Minister ducked this suggestion, asked for official
                            response to his request, and reiterated he would be willing to come to
                            Washington to discuss this question personally with top <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> officials, if he could be assured a
                            definitive response there. Our own policy problems aside, this request,
                            serious though it may be, seems flawed even from Bahraini perspective.
                            End summary.</p>
                        <p>1. June 15 I spent an hour with Prime Minister Shaikh Khalifa bin Sulman
                            discussing his desire, first raised June 13 with Commander Middle East
                            Force Admiral Bigley and reported in Navy channels, to develop a
                            military assistance relationship with the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> to enable ruling Al Khalifa family to justify
                            retaining Middle East Force in Bahrain. Subsequently I spent an hour
                            with his nephew Crown Prince/Defense Minister Shaikh Hamad bin Isa
                            re-emphasizing points I had made to Prime Minister and trying to pin
                            down more definitively what price these two senior members of government
                            are asking this time. With apologies, I am persuaded this must be
                            reported in some detail.</p>
                        <p>2. Prime Minister uncharacteristically raced through pleasantries to get
                            right down to business, first ploughing the old ground of long-standing
                            Bahraini friendship for <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and his
                            unhappiness with the two decisions Cabinet has made to ask the Navy out.
                            In October 1973 Cabinet in his absence had been swayed by Arab-Israel
                            emotions. Last summer government had been under pressure re the Navy
                            from Gulf neighbors and National Assembly at home. Now he is “in
                            stronger position”: gone is the National Assembly, the people no longer
                            want to “get mixed up in politics”, and he is hence free to serve the
                            best interests of his people. He has “personal assurances” from Iran,
                            Saudi Arabia and Kuwait that they would not object if Bahrain let the
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Navy keep using “facilities
                            which have no aspects of being a base”. He understands the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Navy would like to stay in Bahrain and
                            he has been thinking of ways to make it possible. (Shaikh Hamad later
                            was eloquent in lamenting the great cost and human hardship of removing
                            the Navy’s wives and children from this garden of Eden to some “desolate
                            island” (Diego Garcia?) thousands of miles from nowhere.)</p>
                        <p>3. Prime Minister continued he had understood “<gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> is seeking” some sort of Saudi/Iranian approval for
                            continued Middle East Force presence and wanted me to know that both the
                            Shah and Prince <persName corresp="#p_FIAS_1">Fahd</persName> had
                            assured him Bahrain is “free to make its own decision” re Middle East
                            Force. I corrected him, noting in first place <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> would not be surprised to learn of such private
                            assurances from Tehran and Riyadh since Middle East Force is in the Gulf
                            because we believed in 1970 that it would continue to serve mutual
                            interests of us and all Gulf states <pb facs="0303" n="268" xml:id="pg_268"/> in contributing to region’s security. We were not
                            seeking Saudi/Iranian approval; rather <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> had told us Middle East Force is a domestic political
                            liability which it could no longer bear in absence of public, not
                            private, Saudi/Iranian statements of support for Bahrain’s retaining it.
                            (Shaikh Hamad later described Middle East Force as a political liability
                            which is bearable only with significant evidence of benefits, like
                            military assistance, which accrue to Bahrain by virtue of the US Navy’s
                            presence;)</p>
                        <p>4. This provoked somewhat heated response from the Prime Minister that
                            he, “not the Shah and King <persName corresp="#p_KIAS_1">Khalid</persName>”, determines Bahrain’s policy and if he decides
                            the Navy should stay he does not need Saudi and Iranian approval.
                            Bahrain has best of relations with “all Gulf states, even Qatar though
                            they are sometimes unreasonable”, but Bahrain is “independent”. Yes,
                            Saudis, Kuwaitis and <gloss target="#t_UAE_1">UAE</gloss> are being
                            helpful to Bahrain’s economic development and public welfare schemes but
                            Bahrain cannot let its neighbors make its policy and cannot become
                            dependent on them for arms. (Comment: This is most impassioned display I
                            have witnessed of the deep aversion of the proud and “aristocratic” Al
                            Khalifa to increased subservience to richer and more powerful neighbors,
                            and their consequent unrealistic longing for the return of the “special
                            relationship” with Anglo/America. See Manama 181, “Bahrain awash in the
                            Gulf” and previous reporting. We could exploit this tendency for limited
                            bilateral gains but to do so would work against our broader objective of
                            fostering regional cooperation in security matters.)</p>
                        <p>5. Prime Minister continued that “he and Shaikh Hamad” are trying to
                            build a proper defense force, “small but effective”, not equipped with
                            “obsolete weapons or second-hand equipment from Jordan or Saudi Arabia”.
                            Bahrain needs “modest things” like guns and jeeps and a few helicopters
                            and something “more than a coast guard but less than a navy”. (Shaikh
                            Hamad later said while he did not really want to have jet fighter
                            squadrons he would, of course, have to acquire them if only to prevent a
                            “vacuum in the Gulf defense belt” which would invite Iraq or Kuwait pose
                            embarrassing requests to station their aircraft in Bahrain.) Prime
                            Minister wants “to build a defensive wall around this island” so that
                            Bahraini people will feel their government can protect them, so that
                            “our neighbors will not laugh at us”, and to sustain “the morale of our
                            officers”. (Comment: That means largely Shaikh Hamad and his cousins.)
                            Prime Minister continued that he is determined to arm Bahrain adequately
                            from whatever source but obviously preferred American arms and training.
                            Bahrain, however, cannot pay the “inflated prices” private American
                            companies and the British and French ask and that the Saudis and
                            Kuwaitis can pay. As he looks around he sees <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> “helping all Bahrain’s neighbors” modernize their
                            defense forces, “seconding” military advisors and “giv<pb facs="0304" n="269" xml:id="pg_269"/>ing” weapons and training. The US Navy
                            wants to stay in Bahrain, yet Bahrain has nothing of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> military help to show its people and
                            its neighbors. Could not the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> “give”
                            Bahrain some tangible evidence of military assistance to justify the
                            continued US Navy use of Bahraini facilities?</p>
                        <p>6. I asked Prime Minister if this were a “personal inquiry” or should I
                            report it as a “formal government request”? Bristling somewhat, he
                            assured me this was “an official government request”. (Comment: This is
                            important point in considering our response. Prime Minister obviously
                            considers himself “the government” and yet sometimes prefers that we
                            believe the Cabinet is “the government”. While I was with Prime
                            Minister, his first cousin the Foreign Minister was receiving Admiral
                            Bigley for a farewell courtesy call, and he hewed to the “party line”
                            that, sad as it may be, Bahrain cannot keep the Navy in the absence of
                            public support from neighboring states for doing so. Recently
                            Development Minister Shirawi told me he had raised in Cabinet
                            possibility of extending Navy’s departure and had found scant sympathy
                            (Manama 711); Cabinet Affairs Minister Urrayed recently told me
                            America’s “best friends” in Cabinet would not touch OPIC’s agreement
                            until Navy left (Manama 620). These straws suggest to me Prime Minister
                            and Shaikh Hamad are off on a private feeler (probably with Amir’s
                            blessing) in asking for military assistance to justify keeping the Navy:
                            that the Cabinet, which has twice voted the Navy out of Bahrain, has not
                            yet been cut in. We have seen several indications over last two years
                            that Prime Minister has special problems when it comes to Bahrain’s
                            defense force. Personally he seems quite prone to arm the Al Khalifa to
                            the teeth, but he serves an Amir and presides over a Cabinet both openly
                            disdainful of military pretensions in this mini-state. And he must try
                            to keep his nephew the Crown Prince, who is also his subordinate the
                            Defense Minister, somehow active and amused without bleeding the public
                            purse. Hence we have long suspected they have a “deal” going in which
                            the Prime Minister will not press the Cabinet to divert public funds to
                            buy Shaikh Hamad weapons but will try to help him persuade other
                            countries to pay Bahrain’s defense tab. If this interpretation is
                            correct, then the Prime Minister is looking to us to make an offer of
                            military assistance he cannot refuse and can use both to persuade the
                            Cabinet to let the Navy stay and to keep the Crown Prince content.</p>
                        <p>7. After repeating standard remarks about US regard for Bahrain and its
                            welfare and our appreciation for Bahrain’s hospitality to US Navy, I
                            told Prime Minister (and later Shaikh Hamad) that I was of course not
                            instructed to reply to this request and could but refer it to Washington
                            with the recommendation that it receive urgent and high-level
                            consideration. But before I did so, both he and I must clearly
                            understand what he is asking:</p>
                        <pb facs="0305" n="270" xml:id="pg_270"/>
                        <p>(A) Did he understand <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> “gives”
                            nothing in military assistance to Bahrain’s neighbors: they pay for it.
                            Our present relationship with Bahrain is similar type: <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> is eligible for “Foreign Military
                            Sales”, we have provided a coastal survey and training for Bahrain’s
                            officers in the US, and are offering to send a helicopter force survey
                            team. What sort of relationship does Bahrain seek that we are not
                            already able to provide? A concessional one like Jordan and Turkey,
                            countries in very different situations, enjoy? Prime Minister
                            specifically acknowledged (and Shaikh Hamad later confirmed) that he is
                            indeed seeking a concessional arrangement such as “Jordan and Turkey”
                            have “not like Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, and Iran”. Prime Minister said
                            Bahrain wants to pay for US help, but at “special low prices”. (Shaikh
                            Hamad later said Bahrain was fully prepared to pay reasonable prices but
                            “not double the price like the Saudis do” for US military assistance and
                            furthermore would not deal directly with commercial companies and would
                            need “<gloss target="#t_FMS_1">FMS</gloss> credits” or “loans” from the
                                <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> to permit it to pay over time
                            for what it gets.)</p>
                        <p>(B) Did Prime Minister understand that even should <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> be able to provide a military
                            assistance program for Bahrain the types and quantities of assistance
                            provided would still be subject on a case-by-case basis to the
                            limitations imposed by our policies toward providing arms in various
                            parts of the world. He (and Shaikh Hamad later) professed to understand
                            this, contending that Bahrain’s needs are reasonable by any definition.
                            (Comment: I am still not sure they accept this reality.)</p>
                        <p>8. Then, stressing that I was now speaking “personally”, without
                            instructions and “as a friend”, I reminded Prime Minister that when
                            Foreign Minister Shaikh Mohammad had pressed Chargé Gatch back in 1971
                            for some sort of tangible evidence that Bahrain would benefit from
                            continued US Navy presence I had fielded that request in Washington.
                            Hence, counting the 1974–75 negotiations, this was the “third time
                            around” for me in the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss>’s ever more
                            expensive efforts to demonstrate to neighbors and citizens that the
                            Navy’s presence is beneficial. I reminded Prime Minister that prior to
                            Bahrain’s independence in 1971 <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> had
                            formulated a carefully reviewed and publically enunciated policy toward
                            the Gulf. One element was the decision to keep Middle East Force
                            operating out of Bahrain. We had felt this served the interests of all
                            Gulf states including Bahrain and hence have had subsequent difficulty
                            in accepting the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss>’s contention that
                            the US Navy presence is a liability for which the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> must compensate in other ways. To the
                            extent our Navy imposed any inconveniences on its Bahraini hosts, we had
                            tried to adhere to the sound approach of paying for this in rent
                            because, subject to budgetary vicissitudes, the <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> could be assured the Navy was good for its commitments
                            in <pb facs="0306" n="271" xml:id="pg_271"/> this regard. In 1974 <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> had suggested that our providing
                            civilian US technical advisors would broaden the US-Bahrain relationship
                            to make the continued US Navy presence more acceptable. This had given
                                <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> little philosophical problems
                            since making civilian expert advice available to Bahrain and other Gulf
                            states had all along been a notably popular element of overall US Gulf
                            policy. How to provide a modest contribution of US public funds to this
                            end had been a problem, but the proposed technical assistance was not
                            directly linked to the US Navy presence and was justifiable on broader
                            political/economic and commercial grounds. Still it had required
                            legislative authorization, and thus eighteen months after the US
                            executive had agreed to try to help with technical assistance the
                            commitment is still not absolutely in hand, nor are the advisors in
                            Bahrain. Now Prime Minister was suggesting a very different sort of
                            condition for keeping Middle East Force in Bahrain, a concessionary
                            military aid program which would be a new departure in US policy toward
                            the Gulf. Personally I thought this request would require the most
                            intensive top-level consideration in US executive and that responding
                            favorably to it would probably require seeking legislative authorization
                            for a commitment far more controversial than providing civilian advisors
                            to assist public administration.</p>
                        <p>9. Thus I thought Prime Minister faced an awkward timing problem. It
                            seemed to me <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> might need a lot of
                            time to sort out his request, and much longer yet to deliver thorough
                            legislation on any tentative commitment it might feel able to make. Yet
                                <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss>, quite by its own choosing and
                            despite our pleadings to contrary, had imposed a June 1977 deadline for
                            US Navy’s departure, and some time soon the Navy must start taking
                            practically irreversible steps to meet it. Therefore, in my “strictly
                            personal” view, the first step should be for <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> to extend the deadline so that, without any commitment
                            by either party, <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_GOB_1">GOB</gloss> could in propitious circumstances
                            consider under what if any conditions the Middle East Force presence
                            might continue to serve mutual interests.</p>
                        <p>10. Prime Minister ducked this by reverting to suggestion made earlier in
                            the conversation that he would be willing to make working visit to
                            Washington at appropriate time (he would prefer early fall) to discuss
                            his proposal at high level in <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>. He
                            would come with “something in black and white in hand” (I took this to
                            mean an offer to “extend the agreement”) but would have to be assured in
                            advance that he would be “received as a friend”, and that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> officials would talk with him “frankly
                            and honestly” and be prepared to give him a “definitive answer”.
                            (Comment: I take that to mean a positive commitment to provide military
                            assistance on concessional terms.)</p>
                        <p>11. I assured Prime Minister that, whenever he came to Washington, it
                            would be as a “friend” and that <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                            officials would always talk <pb facs="0307" n="272" xml:id="pg_272"/>
                            with him in candor. But insofar as a “definitive answer” is concerned, I
                            would have to inquire. He again urged that I seek an official response
                            to his request.</p>
                        <p>12. Comment: This request by Bahrain’s Prime Minister (and his nephew the
                            Crown Prince/Defense Minister) is far from frivolous. He would regard it
                            as sincere, reasonable and in a long-standing tradition of
                            Bahraini-American friendship. It must be handled with care.
                            Nevertheless, quite apart from fact this Bahraini attempt to raise the
                            price for keeping Middle East Force poses for US difficult question of
                            national purpose and policy the request is flawed even from the Bahraini
                            perspective.</p>
                        <p>(A) The Prime Minister is not conceding that the US Navy presence serves
                            Bahrain’s interest; it is rather to remain the perpetual liability in
                            the US-Bahraini relationship. Hence, we are expected to be ever in
                            Bahrain’s debt for its being here, and to pay, in ever more
                            controversial currency and seemingly open endedly.</p>
                        <p>(B) Apparently the Cabinet, which we have been led to believe has sole
                            power to let the Navy stay or make it go, is not offering us a deal.
                            Rather the Prime Minister is dropping us a hint that if we offer a
                            military assistance deal to the Cabinet he might be able to persuade it
                            to let the Navy stay.</p>
                        <p>(C) These “people of Bahrain”, whom the Prime Minister criticizes for
                            having wanted to “get mixed up in politics”, are being trotted out again
                            so that we might believe they can be taught to dislike the idea of our
                            Navy’s presence less as they learn to love Shaikh Hamad’s army more. We
                            have substantial reason to believe Bahrain’s defense force has scant
                            support in the Cabinet, to say nothing of among the populace at large.
                            Hence a significant <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> role in
                            developing the defense force, particularly if it involved presence of US
                            military advisors here, threatens to be controversial among Bahraini
                            public, and among some of Bahrain’s neighbors. How then could such a US
                            contribution turn critics of the US Navy presence around?</p>
                        <p>13. Department at its discretion may wish to repeat this message to
                            appropriate regional posts and military addresses.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_TJ_1">
                                <persName corresp="#p_TJ_1">Twinam</persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>