<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>101. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    Pakistan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d101</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">101</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-01-27T14:57:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-01-27T14:57:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recEtq3Tgt96SEVf9" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001519"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-01-27T14:57:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-01-27T14:57:00-05:00" n="101"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d101">
                <head>101. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in Pakistan</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d101fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 689.90D/1-2762. Secret; Niact. Drafted by Gatch, cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_SB1">Bromley Smith</persName> and with <gloss
                            target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>, and approved by <persName corresp="#p_TP1"
                            >Talbot</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-01-27T14:57:00-05:00">January 27, 1962, 2:57 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1505. Dept wishes take every feasible step exploit first break in impasse to
                    achieve permanent solution. Believe your impending departure<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d101fn1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> left Pakistan on February 7.
                        He was replaced as Ambassador by <persName corresp="#p_MCWP1">Walter P.
                            McConaughy</persName>, who was appointed on March 1 and presented his
                        credentials on March 20.</note> provides favorable opportunity to explore
                    this problem and lines of resolution with <persName corresp="#p_AKM1"
                        >Ayub</persName>. If your agenda for January 29 meeting crowded, you should
                    seek at least one more session devoted solely to transit dispute. You will be
                    able judge by <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>’s reaction whether you
                    should press for some agreement in principle from <gloss target="#t_GOP1"
                        >GOP</gloss> on possible solution or confine your efforts preparing ground
                    for your successor. In light vigorous US effort get <gloss target="#t_GOI1"
                        >GOI</gloss> to negotiating table on Kashmir and in wake successful
                    consortium, seems at least possible <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>
                    may be in receptive mood on Afghan matter. In mentioning Kashmir and consortium,
                    you might say you would like to leave Pakistan with at least a constructive
                    start towards solution transit dispute. This is particularly true because of
                    President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s deep interest in
                    issue. It would be gratifying to be able to make favorable report upon your
                    return to Washington.</p>
                <p>At your discretion, present US views to <persName corresp="#p_AKM1"
                        >Ayub</persName> in following general framework: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>US considers temporary reopening significant break in dispute and
                            notes with satisfaction cooperative attitude adopted by <gloss
                                target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss>. In interest of both countries, we
                            think strenuous efforts should be made keep border open permanently on
                            mutually acceptable basis. <gloss target="#t_RGA1">RGA</gloss> has made
                            forward step and we are confident <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss>
                            can also make step in return without doing damage either to its
                            interests or public position.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>We are increasingly concerned over way Soviets are exploiting
                            situation. In addition to Soviet gains previously cited, we now have
                            reliable reports of significant increase in Soviet activity with Afghan
                            armed forces. All this helps no one but the Soviets. US belief has been
                            strongly reinforced that best way to counter Soviet influence in
                            Afghanistan is with vigorous US presence exemplified by US assistance
                            programs.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Before going into specifics regarding possible solutions, at this
                            point you should request <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>
                            give his present views on situation.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>If <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> still appears adamant
                            on possible new moves toward Afghanistan, you should urge him at least
                            make early appropriate public <pb facs="0236" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/>
                            statement expressing his pleasure that border is open for aid goods and
                            reaffirming <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> position on Afghan right
                            of transit.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>If <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> appears receptive to
                            discussing ways keeping border open, you should outline proposal in
                            following paragraph and say you are prepared discuss details later at
                            working level.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>One major obstacle in resolving present impasse is <gloss
                                target="#t_RGA1">RGA</gloss> insistence on having Afghan officials
                            performing freight forwarding duties in Pakistan and <gloss
                                target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> refusal allow <gloss target="#t_RGA1"
                                >RGA</gloss> reopen trade agencies and consulates on previous basis
                            because of improper activities reportedly carried out by previous
                            officials. US suggests some arrangement by which <gloss target="#t_GOP1"
                                >GOP</gloss> would permit small offices officially designated as
                            Freight Forwarding Offices be opened in Peshawar and Quetta manned by
                            Afghan officials with consular status but not designated as consuls. In
                            granting exequaturs, <gloss target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> would exercise
                            sovereign right of determining whether any particular official
                            acceptable. It would be understood from outset that if offices
                            functioned mutually satisfactorily for reasonable length of time—e.g.,
                            six months—they would be expanded to perform full consular services and
                            redesignated consulates with freight forwarding sections. Trade agencies
                            as previously constituted, would never be reopened, and all functions
                            would be integrated in one office. Again providing everything went
                            smoothly, after reasonable period offices in Chaman and Parachinar might
                            be reopened. US believes foregoing plan would protect <gloss
                                target="#t_GOP1">GOP</gloss> security interests and allow <gloss
                                target="#t_RGA1">RGA</gloss> retain enough of its public position to
                            accept safeguarding restrictions implicit in exequatur process. At some
                            point in proceedings resumption diplomatic relations would be
                                presumed.<note n="2" xml:id="d101fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> saw <persName
                                    corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> on January 30 and discussed
                                the transit dispute along the lines of the instructions in this
                                telegram. He found <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>
                                adamant against the idea of establishing freight forwarding stations
                                in Peshawar and Quetta, but willing to consider issuing a statement
                                expressing pleasure that the border had been reopened. (Telegram
                                1300 from Karachi, January 31; Department of State, Central Files,
                                689.90D/1-3161)</note>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
