<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-05-20T02:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-05-20T02:30:00-05:00" n="22" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d22">
                    <head>22. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d22fn0">Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, International Meetings
                            and Travel File, Vice President Johnson’s Trip to the Far East, May 61.
                            Top Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>.
                            The meeting was held at the President’s House in Karachi.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Karachi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1961-05-20T12:30:00+05:00">May 20, 1961, 12:30
                            p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <p>United States:</p>
                    <p>Vice President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName></p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Stephen Smith</persName></p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName>Busby</persName></p>
                    <p>Ambassador Horace Smith</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName></p>
                    <p>Pakistan:</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName></p>
                    <p>General Burki, Minister of Health, Welfare and Social Affairs</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_QM1">Manzur Qadir</persName>, Minister of External
                        Affairs</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Mohammed Shoaib</persName>, Minister of
                        Finance</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BZA1">Zulfikar Ali Bhutto</persName>, Minister of
                        Information</p>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DSK1">Dehlavi</persName>, Foreign Secretary</p>
                    <p>Vice President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> began by
                        stating that Pakistan was held in very high regard by the United States,
                        which greatly valued its friendship. He mentioned in the context of his
                        public life his interest in international affairs, and the various trips
                        abroad which he had made on official missions since he assumed office as the
                        Vice President. He described President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> as a young and extremely vigorous man, hopeful and
                        very confident. The Vice President fully shared President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s philosophy. President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> had wanted him to visit nations of
                        Asia, particularly allies, to talk about problems of common interest and to
                        share views of how the strength of the free world might be increased. The
                        United States was anxious to do everything it could to contribute to the
                        strength of Asian nations, particularly in the fostering of economic
                        progress upon which strength could be based. It felt that impoverished
                        nations must be helped; in helping them we were in fact helping ourselves
                        since those more fortunate must share the burden of improving the lot of the
                        poorer if even the rich were to be secure. Continuing, the Vice President
                        said United States had a particular fondness for Pakistan and President
                        Ayub. Pakistan had convictions which it was willing to express. It was
                        willing to support <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>, including the
                        contribution of forces in connection with the Laos problem, and we
                        appreciated that commitment. The Vice President observed that he did not
                        know where recent events in Laos left us. He wanted to exchange views with
                        President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> on this subject.</p>
                    <pb facs="0072" n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/>
                    <p>The Vice President said that President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> was eagerly looking forward to President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>’s visit, during which many matters
                        could be discussed; however, there was substantial business which would have
                        to take place before the visit. (In this context he handed President
                            <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> a letter from President
                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>.)<note n="1" xml:id="d22fn1"><persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName>’s letter,
                            dated May 8, underlined the importance of <persName>Johnson</persName>’s
                            fact-finding mission and the significance <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> attached to <persName>Johnson</persName>’s
                            discussions with <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>. He pointed
                            to the need to build military strength to resist Communist aggression in
                            the area and noted that such strength rested upon economic development.
                            He applauded Pakistan’s efforts to promote economic development and
                            noted that his administration was engaged in reorganizing its aid
                            programs in order to better support such efforts. (Department of State,
                            Central Files, 611.90D/5-861)</note></p>
                    <p>The Vice President said that in his visits to several countries of Asia he
                        had found them all aware of the current danger and anxious to do their best
                        to meet it. All the leaders believed they had inadequate means for
                        accomplishing what they considered necessary. We were anxious to do
                        everything that we reasonably could to help them. We recognized the need for
                        additional defensive strength, but even more the need for economic
                        strength.</p>
                    <p>Referring to Laos, the Vice President said we were prepared for the worst but
                        hoped for the best. He would like to have President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>’s view as to what would be the best
                        course to follow. There were various alternatives. The United States could,
                        for example, “go back to San Francisco,” but we did not want to do that. On
                        the other hand, our people did not want to get killed in unnecessary and
                        fruitless fighting. He said we had relied on our allies to help train
                        Laotians. This had not worked out well, and the other side seemed far more
                        willing to fight than ours. In Viet-Nam 150,000 friendly forces were
                        confronting 10,000 enemy. Yet they needed even more men and equipment to
                        cope with the problem. In Thailand there were similar difficulties. The
                        problem of the defense of free forces in South Asia would of course be far
                        greater if the Chinese should come in. Yet Diem had said that if we gave him
                        help he would stand up, and Sarit said he needed not nine but 15
                        divisions.</p>
                    <p>The Vice President said he would like to be able to inform President
                            <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> of what we could expect
                        from our allies if the United States was ready to do thus and so for the
                        area. The United States did not want anything for itself beyond the
                        preservation of the independence of the states of the region. The question
                        was what would be necessary to prevent the communists from gobbling up the
                        weaker nations. It was possible that we could equip them and help them fight
                        properly. If they were not helped, they would be lost. It would be one or
                        the other.</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> responded that he
                        agreed with the Vice President’s summary of the problem. He said he would
                        like to outline at length his views on the world situation, but in view of
                        the shortage of time he <pb facs="0073" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/> thought it
                        best for the Vice President simply to read his assessment which had been
                        prepared in summary form for the purposes of the meeting. He handed to the
                        Vice President his notes, which are attached.<note n="2" xml:id="d22fn2">Not
                            attached.</note></p>
                    <p>The Vice President agreed generally with President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>’s views, but commented upon his
                        remarks about American policy by saying that we sometimes might be
                        “kindhearted but not wise.” We did, however, know who stood up, and the
                        difference between strong friends and neutrals. Regarding possible influence
                        by the United States or India to bring about a solution of the Kashmir
                        problem, he thought President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>
                        attributed to us a capacity which the Vice President was not sure we had. We
                        had tried some of these things, but had had little influence with
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> on the question.</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> responded that he knew
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> would not listen if he did not feel compelled
                        to. That did not mean that he should not listen, nor that the United States
                        did not have the power to influence him. India’s flexibility today was gone.
                        With the pressure from the Chinese Communists, India relied even more
                        heavily upon the United States. In fact, it had no alternative.</p>
                    <p>Continuing, the President said the United States was Pakistan’s friend and
                        anything going wrong with the United States hurt Pakistan. In Cuba, for
                        example, a situation had been created which greatly damaged not only the
                        United States, but also its allies, including Pakistan. He mentioned the
                        conversation which he had had with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName> on the Cuban situation and the message which he had
                        sent through the Ambassador to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">Kennedy</persName> on the subject.<note n="3" xml:id="d22fn3">Transmitted in telegram 1831 from Karachi, April 19. (Department of
                            State, Central Files, 737.00/4-1961)</note> Pakistan did not want to the
                        United States to fail. It wanted it to win against the Soviets. Its battle
                        was Pakistan’s battle. If the United States did not use its power, it hurt
                        Pakistan. The power of the United States was much greater than at times the
                        Americans seemed to think. Its power to influence <persName>Nehru</persName>
                        was very great indeed. Unless there were peace with India which would permit
                        cooperation in the defense of South Asia, there would be a very great threat
                        within a few years and that threat derived from the fact that the communists
                        wanted to control the entire subcontinent. The Soviets were pressing
                        Pakistan and would like to take over the country, but their interest was not
                        in Pakistan itself but in the entire region. Thus, the threat to India was
                        very great, both from the Soviets and from the Chinese Communists, and the
                        Indians must come to realize that. The United States was spending a terrific
                        amount of money in India. It was doing it because it sought Indian security.
                        It could not, however, say that India really was secure. The Indians must do
                        far more to achieve real security and this <pb facs="0074" n="48" xml:id="pg_48"/> involved the creation of a situation in which good
                        relations between Pakistan and India could be maintained. American
                        diffidence about <persName>Nehru</persName> bothered the Pakistani. The
                        United States should help India; but by the same token it should demand that
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> help create security in the area around
                        India. Thus India should make peace and cooperation with Pakistan
                        possible.</p>
                    <p>The President was disturbed by the fact that the Communists gave support to
                        any friend regardless of the merits of the case, but they assured themselves
                        that the countries helped would not operate against their global policies or
                        their world position. Failure of the United States to support its friends
                        created a one-sided proposition that Americans seemed not to realize.
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> only wanted American economic assistance, and
                        the assurance of help if he should get into difficulties with the Chinese.
                        He would never help the United States. His policies were in fact extremely
                        harmful to the United States; yet America had not used its leverage to bring
                        about a change in those policies, despite <persName>Nehru</persName>’s very
                        heavy reliance upon it.</p>
                    <p>The Vice President responded again that President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> attributed to us the capacity for greater influence
                        with <persName>Nehru</persName> than we in fact possessed. He did not in
                        fact think that <persName>Nehru</persName> would listen to us on the Kashmir
                        question.</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> remarked that he would
                        listen if the United States should say that it would not otherwise give him
                        all the help he asked. The Vice President remarked that President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> was suggesting the “quid pro quo”
                        approach, to which President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>
                        responded that he thought it would be a very good idea when dealing with
                        that type of person. He said again that the United States had very great
                        power and that it should use it. It should not be bluffed by Khrushchev; it
                        should do in a straightforward manner what was necessary for the American
                        and free world position.</p>
                    <p>Responding to the Vice President’s question about what should be done about
                        Viet-Nam and other Asian trouble spots, President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> said that if the present leadership in
                        those countries could not run their affairs, they should get someone able to
                        do so. It must be seen to that they were operated properly. If the leaders
                        could not get that bulk of the people to resist communism, the United States
                        should see to it that key people were in the right places to do so. He
                        thought the situation in Laos was extremely bad. Militarily, it was a
                        nightmare. The Thais were beginning to get the jitters. He thought American
                        military people in Thailand, Laos and Viet-Nam should be in a position to
                        assume command responsibilities.</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> thought the Tibetan
                        situation would have a considerable influence in India. Through Tibet, the
                        Chinese Communists were already penetrating India, not physically but in
                        influence, particularly in <pb facs="0075" n="49" xml:id="pg_49"/> the
                        Calcutta area. Fortunately the large communist party in India was presently
                        split over the Chinese situation. If this were not so the problem would be
                        even greater than it was today. Responding to the Vice President’s question,
                        President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> said that China’s
                        current economic problems were not substantially lessening Chinese
                        activities in other countries. They were in fact even more aggressive in
                        Africa than the Soviets. The Chinese were not likely, due to their own
                        internal difficulties, to concentrate on a single part of the world, such as
                        Laos, to the exclusion of others.</p>
                    <p>Responding to the Vice President’s question about <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>, President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName>
                        said no one seemed to want to fight “except us.” The Vice President remarked
                        that we appreciated Pakistan’s willingness to contribute forces to which
                        President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> responded, jokingly,
                        that he thought however that the United States should come along with them.
                        The Vice President observed that it still had not yet been decided what
                        would be necessary in Laos. Considering what other countries were prepared
                        to do and contribute, he doubted that much of a fight could be put up there.
                        President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> thought that any sort
                        of a fight by the Royal Laotians would mean that the army must be directly
                        commanded by United States officers; otherwise they simply would not
                        fight.</p>
                    <p>The President remarked that Thailand was relatively easier to defend, to
                        which the Vice President responded that he thought we would have to make a
                        stand much before Thailand was attacked.</p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> described the size and
                        disposition of the Pakistani forces, in reply to the Vice President’s
                        question. He said that Pakistan had an excellent army but that it needed
                        more equipment and more mobility. These needs had been described to the
                        American authorities and he hoped that it would be possible for them to be
                        met in light of the tremendous advantages to the United States and the free
                        world of Pakistan having a strong military force capable of real help in
                        meeting the threat in this part of the world.</p>
                    <p>The Vice President thought it would be an excellent idea if President
                            <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> could visit the leaders of
                        other Asian nations and talk with them about some of these problems. The
                        President remarked that he recently had visited several countries. He was,
                        however, very busy at the moment and did not see how it would be possible
                        for him to undertake other visits.</p>
                    <p>Turning to another subject, President Ayub and the Vice President discussed
                        economic problems and development of Pakistan. The President and Finance
                        Minister <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Shoaib</persName> described the
                        magnitude of the five year program and its general content. Replying to the
                        Vice President’s question, they said the annual deficit in foreign exchange
                        financing would be in the neighborhood of 500 million dollars, which it
                        hoped <pb facs="0076" n="50" xml:id="pg_50"/> could be financed through
                        contributions by the nations soon to meet in the consortium group under the
                        auspices of the International Bank.</p>
                    <p>The President expressed an interest in the Peace Corps and said he hoped that
                        projects could be worked out so that specialists could be sent, particularly
                        in the fields of health, education and agriculture.</p>
                    <p>The problem of water logging and salinity was discussed at some length.
                        President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> handed to the Vice
                        President copies of the Pakistan Program for Water Logging and Salinity
                        Control in the Irrigated Areas of West Pakistan. The Vice President
                        expressed a keen interest in the problem, and said he thought every
                        consideration should be given as to what assistance the United States could
                        render. The President said that Finance Minister <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Shoaib</persName> was leaving almost immediately for Washington and was
                        taking copies of the report with him. He earnestly hoped the United States
                        could provide substantial assistance in this matter. The program covered a
                        10 year period and would involve the annual expenditure of 110 million
                        dollars.</p>
                    <p>Before proceeding to lunch (during which the talks were continued),<note n="4" xml:id="d22fn4">Conversation over lunch dealt largely with
                            programs for education and land reform and prospects for economic
                            development in Pakistan. (Memorandum of conversation, May 20; Johnson
                            Library, Vice Presidential Security File, VP <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>’s Trip, Far East, May 1961)</note></p>
                    <p>President <persName corresp="#p_AKM1">Ayub</persName> described on the map in
                        his office the military problems confronting Pakistan and the necessary
                        disposition of Pakistani forces related to the dispute with India over
                        Kashmir. Settlement of the Kashmir problem would permit these forces to
                        concentrate entirely upon defense against possible communist aggression.
                        Another Pakistani interest in Kashmir was described by the President as
                        being the need for controlling the headwaters of rivers flowing into
                        Pakistan upon which Pakistan depended for its very existence. These were
                        practical and immediate reasons why Pakistan must find a solution to these
                        problems. There were other reasons, of course, relating to the desires of
                        the people concerned in Kashmir and of a historical nature.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>