<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>319. Telegram From the Department of State to the to the Embassy in
                    India</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d319</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">319</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-08-15T20:17:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-08-15T20:17:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recQJgxXbB2a4RsHo" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00009290"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consortium</term>
                    <term ref="recqk8lOkxJSwBcby" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military aid</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="rec9iefufr6RQ3AiC" type="compound-subject"
                        category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general">Quiet diplomacy</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-08-15T20:17:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-08-15T20:17:00-05:00" n="319"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d319">
                <head>319. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Embassy in India</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d319fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, <gloss target="#t_pol1">POL</gloss> 32-1 INDIA-<gloss
                            target="#t_Pak1">PAK</gloss>. Secret; Priority; Verbatim Text. Drafted
                        by Schneider and <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> and cleared
                        and approved by <persName corresp="#p_GJP1">Grant</persName>. Repeated to
                        Karachi and London.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-08-15T21:17:00-04:00">August 15, 1963, 9:17 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>393. Eyes Only Ambassadors. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 394.<note
                        n="1" xml:id="d319fn1">Telegram 394 to New Delhi, August 15, instructed
                            <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName> to deliver Kennedy’s
                        letter to <persName>Nehru</persName> in person if possible. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BCB1">Bowles</persName> was instructed to discuss the letter
                        with <persName>Nehru</persName> at the earliest opportunity and elaborate
                        upon and emphasize the themes laid out in it. (Ibid.)</note> There follows
                    text of message from the President to Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_NJ1"
                        >Nehru</persName> which you are requested to deliver urgently.</p>
                <p>“Dear Mr. Prime Minister:</p>
                <p>I must confess that your letter<note n="2" xml:id="d319fn2">
                        <ref target="#d317">Document 317</ref>.</note> and statement in the Lok
                        Sabha<note n="3" xml:id="d319fn3">In telegram 644 from New Delhi, August 12,
                        the Embassy transmitted the text of an advance copy of the speech
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> intended to make on the following day to the
                        Lok Sabha, the lower house of the Indian Parliament. In the speech,
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> reviewed the history of the Ministerial talks
                        with Pakistan on the Kashmir issue. He attributed the failure of the talks
                        to Pakistan’s determination to achieve a settlement entirely upon its own
                        terms, or to continue the existing deadlock over the issue.
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> then turned to the mediation proposal that
                        followed upon the failure of the Ministerial talks. As with the talks,
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> stated that India approached the mediation
                        proposal with the hope that it would lead to a fair and equitable settlement
                        to the dispute, but he concluded that the terms of reference proposed by
                        Pakistan for the mediation exercise made success impossible. (Department of
                        State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_pol1">POL</gloss> 32-1 INDIA-<gloss
                            target="#t_Pak1">PAK</gloss>)</note> took us by surprise. Though I can
                    understand your irritation with Pakistani behavior, I still regret that you feel
                    compelled to make such a negative statement on mediation at this time. It will
                    certainly complicate our own efforts to help India.</p>
                <pb facs="0666" n="640" xml:id="pg_640"/>
                <p>You know that we are determined to assist India to the fullest in building a free
                    society, a task now rendered more difficult by an obvious external threat. To
                    this end, we have sought to provide India with far more assistance than any
                    other single aid recipient. I might add that I personally intervened with the
                    Germans, Japanese, Italians, and British to get this year’s consortium
                    contributions up to the level finally achieved. But the setback to mediation
                    will inevitably have an adverse impact on our efforts to obtain Congressional
                    and popular support for economic and military aid to India and Pakistan. I must
                    tell you quite frankly that it is hard to counter the mounting resistance in the
                    Congress against aid programs which seem destined to aggravate disputes between
                    two nations, both of which we regard as friends. This is not anti-Indian
                    sentiment; it is a ‘plague on both your houses’ attitude.</p>
                <p>The only way we see to counter this resistance, recognizing that Kashmir and
                    other issues are not susceptible of easy and quick solutions, is to demonstrate
                    that sincere and determined efforts are nevertheless underway to solve them.
                    Here is where we had counted heavily on the mediation effort you proposed.</p>
                <p>We entirely share your appreciation of Chinese aims vis-a-vis India. We too are
                    also concerned at Pakistan’s developing relationship with Communist China, and
                    intend to do what we can to arrest this trend. But we regard it as even more in
                    India’s interest than in ours to forestall a Pakistan-China accommodation.
                    However emotionally the Pakistani are behaving, and whatever the temptation to
                    reply, surely a further heating up of the atmosphere between your two countries
                    aggravates rather than diminishes this risk. We do not see a mediatory effort as
                    weakening you against China, but as a move to lessen pressure on your flank, and
                    hopefully to lead toward a reconciliation which will greatly strengthen India’s
                    position.</p>
                <p>In the last analysis, it must be primarily the task of Indian statesmanship, in
                    seeking to strengthen India against Chinese Communist pressure, to forestall
                    aggravation of this threat via closer Pakistani-Chinese ties. We want to help,
                    but to do so effectively we must know more clearly what you propose to do. As I
                    see it, you do not rule out mediation but suggest the necessary preparatory work
                    be done by quiet diplomacy. An atmosphere must be created, but how is this to be
                    done? We wonder what steps you plan to reestablish communications. Once we know
                    what course you contemplate, we will do what we can to help bring Pakistan to
                    the mediation table, which we still believe is the course best calculated to
                    serve your larger interests and to permit us most effectively to help.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_KJF1">John F. Kennedy</persName>”</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
