<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>70. Telegram From the Embassy in India to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d70</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">70</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-12-12T02:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-12-12T02:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-12-12T02:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-12-12T02:30:00-05:00" n="70"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d70">
                <head>70. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in India</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d70fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 753D.00/12-1261. Secret; Niact. Repeated to Paris for Secretary
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and <gloss target="#t_USRO1"
                            >USRO</gloss>, London, Lisbon, and <gloss target="#t_USUN1"
                        >USUN</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New Delhi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-12-12T13:00:00+05:30">December 12, 1961, 1 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>1690. Department pass Defense-Army, Navy, Air. Embassy telegram 1681<note n="1"
                        xml:id="d70fn1">In telegram 1681 from New Delhi, December 12, <persName
                            corresp="#p_GJK1">Galbraith</persName> reported that information
                        available to the Embassy indicated an increased likelihood of Indian action
                        against Goa. He still felt, however, that there was some possibility that
                            <persName>Nehru</persName> was undecided or capable of changing his
                        mind. (Ibid., 753D.00/12-1261)</note> and Department’s telegram 1980.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d70fn2">Telegram 1980 to New Delhi, December 9, reported that
                        the Department had received information that a journalist in India had filed
                        a story alleging that an Indian attack upon Goa was imminent, and that India
                        had been assured that if the attack took place the United States would not
                        support Portugal. The Department emphasized that no such assurance had been
                        given and reiterated its opposition to the use of force in the Goan dispute.
                        The Embassy was instructed to make the same points clear to the reporter who
                        filed the story. (Ibid., 753D.00/12-961)</note> In view of the overnight
                    developments, I decided to make one more effort this morning to persuade India
                    against armed action on Goa. I accordingly delivered letter quoted next
                    following telegram to <persName>Nehru</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DMJ1"
                        >M.J. Desai</persName> this morning.<note n="3" xml:id="d70fn3">In his
                        letter, Galbraith pointed out that India’s leading role as a champion for
                        the peaceful settlement of international disputes would be seriously
                        compromised by armed action against Goa, and a dangerous precedent set for
                        similar action in disputes festering elsewhere. He cited The New York Times
                        editorial that noted that colonialism was dying in Africa and Asia and U.N.
                        resolutions calling for an end to colonialism, as evidence that India was
                        not without resources in seeking a peaceful settlement to the dispute over
                        Goa. (Telegram 1691 from New Delhi, December 12; ibid.,
                        753D.00/12-1261)</note> To be at all persuasive you will understand it was
                    essential to suggest sympathy for anti-colonial aspect and some alternative.
                    Hence The New York Times extract which avoids official commitment and the
                    reference to <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> and world support. Portugal will
                    not like but presumably will appreciate armed action less.</p>
                <p>He still felt, however, that there was some possibility that
                        <persName>Nehru</persName> was undecided or capable of changing his mind.
                    (Ibid., 753D.00/12-1261)</p>
                <p>I had a long and urgent talk with <persName>Desai</persName> afterwards
                    impressing on him the stake which India had in the avoidance of armed solution.
                    He <pb facs="0182" n="156" xml:id="pg_156"/> noted the shooting on border and
                    adjoining waters. I also said they surely realized the world would not believe
                    that Portugal was attacking India and that what India was calling a naval
                    concentration consisted of a couple of antique gunboats. I have a feeling that
                        <persName>Desai</persName> admitted the force of my argument but he made it
                    clear that the matter was passing rapidly beyond his hands. At the end of the
                    discussion he said specifically that unless the Portuguese made some major
                    concession within the next couple of days, he believed action would go forward.
                    My estimate of the likelihood of such action is now getting rather high. Some
                    vague indication of U.S. acquiescence to action was picked up by <persName
                        corresp="#p_NBK1">B.K. Nehru</persName> in Washington. I told
                        <persName>Desai</persName> this had no standing.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="strong">
                            <persName corresp="#p_GJK1">Galbraith</persName>
                        </hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
