<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>103. Letter From the Deputy Secretary of Defense (Robertson) to the ) to the
                    Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v23p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d103</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">103</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-09-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-09-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-09-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-09-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="103"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d103">
                <head>103. Letter From the Deputy Secretary of Defense (<persName corresp="#p_RRBJ1"
                        type="from">Robertson</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                        State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d103fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 794C.0221/9–2156. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1956-09-21">September 21, 1956</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: Your letter of August 7,
                        1956,<note n="2" xml:id="d103fn2">
                        <ref target="#d86">Document 86</ref>.</note> and the series of messages from
                    Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName> mentioned in your
                    letter, have been studied with particular care and with a very sincere desire to
                    develop a harmonious solution for the complex Ryukyuan land problem.</p>
                <p>As regards the first of the numbered points in your letter, I am very happy to
                    note that, in the meantime, our two Departments working together very closely
                    have found a satisfactory formula which has already been transmitted by cable to
                    the Commander in Chief, Far East, for his guidance.<note n="3" xml:id="d103fn3"
                        >See <ref target="#d88fn4">footnote 4, Document 88</ref>.</note> This
                    formula provides, on the one hand, for the acquisition of long-term interests by
                    lump sum payments, but declares it advisable on the other hand to acquire such
                    interests first to land under permanent facilities and to areas required for
                    manifestly essential training or housekeeping purposes, while other land needed
                    would be acquired at a later date. As has been specifically stated in the
                    aforementioned message to <gloss target="#t_CINCFE1">CINCFE</gloss>, this policy
                    was expressly designed to permit gaining experience by executing the program
                    first in connection with those areas whose acquisition should cause minimum
                    difficulties.</p>
                <p>I likewise believe that we are together in our views regarding additional land
                    requirements. I agree wholeheartedly with the Price Report recommendation that
                    acquisition of additional land by our forces in the Ryukyu Islands should be
                    kept to an absolute minimum. In line with this recommendation, <persName
                        corresp="#p_LGLL1">General Lemnitzer</persName> as early as July 17, 1956,
                    directed an immediate over-all review of all military land requirements in the
                    Islands. A recent Defense message to <persName corresp="#p_LGLL1">General
                        Lemnitzer</persName>,<note n="4" xml:id="d103fn4">Not further
                        identified.</note> a copy of which was transmitted to the Department of <pb
                        facs="0261" n="233" xml:id="pg_233"/> State, strongly re-emphasizes the
                    fact, moreover, that any actions or recommendations by him minimizing land
                    requirements are in consonance with Defense thinking.</p>
                <p>Concerning the last of the three points set forth in your letter, I fully share
                    your belief in the need to study most thoroughly the Ryukyuan aspects that might
                    be involved in the projected change of our command structure in the Far
                    East-Pacific area. I wish to assure you that this complex problem is being given
                    careful attention and at this time it would be impossible to reach even a
                    tentative conclusion on this subject before detailed studies of this problem in
                    its various ramifications have been completed. You will be interested to know
                    that in the forthcoming months there will be many conferences to discuss matters
                    relative to the disestablishment of the existing command in the Far East and the
                    assumption by <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> of responsibility for
                    the new command. The Department of State will be informed of the conclusions
                    reached at these conferences.</p>
                <p>Your suggestion that consideration be given to establishing direct communications
                    on matters of civil administration between the administrative authorities in the
                    Ryukyus and the Department of Defense in Washington is being studied. However,
                    it is doubtful that a solution will be reached until the command channels have
                    been determined at the aforementioned conferences.</p>
                <p>I regret that I cannot agree with the suggestion that policy guidance on civil
                    matters in the Ryukyus should be a joint responsibility, since this would be
                    inconsistent with the President’s Directive which assigns the responsibility to
                    the Department of Defense. In addition, I feel that such an arrangement would
                    encumber the actual administration of the Ryukyus to an inordinate extent. I
                    appreciate the concern expressed by the Department of State because of the
                    untimely release of the Price Committee Report which stimulated reversionist
                    activities in Japan; however, I do not feel that this incident in any way casts
                    a reflection on the administration of the Ryukyus during the past ten years,
                    which I consider has been quite good when viewed in the light of the very real
                    obstacles which confronted the local authorities during that period.</p>
                <p>I am greatly encouraged by the progress made recently by our two Departments in
                    finding solutions for some of these most difficult questions pertaining to the
                    Ryukyuan land issue. I am confident, therefore, that the same rate of progress
                    will also be maintained in the future.<note n="5" xml:id="d103fn5">In a
                        memorandum to Acting Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MRD1"
                        >Murphy</persName>, October 6, <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Walter
                            Robertson</persName> pointed out that deferral of a reply to this letter
                        was advisable because “an interim reply might be misleading either in giving
                        the impression that State is more satisfied than it actually is with the
                        existing situation or in giving the impression that it is seriously
                        dissatisfied and is merely awaiting a chance to renew the argument.”
                            <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Murphy</persName> approved this suggestion.
                        (Department of State, Central Files, 749C.0221/9–2156)</note>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0262" n="234" xml:id="pg_234"/>
                <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RRBJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Reuben B. Robertson Jr.</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
