<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>222. Telegram From the Embassy in Japan to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v23p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">222</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-09-09T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-09-09T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-09-09T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-09-09T10:00:00-05:00" n="222"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d222">
                <head>222. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Japan</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d222fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 794.5/9–1057. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_Niact1">Niact</gloss>.
                        Repeated to <gloss target="#t_CINCPAC1">CINCPAC</gloss> for POLAD.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Tokyo</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1957-09-10T00:00:00+09:00">September 10,
                            1957—Midnight</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>747. Reference: Deptel 586.<note n="2" xml:id="d222fn2">
                        <ref target="#d221">
                            <hi rend="italic">Supra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>We put Department’s revised para C language to FonOff and explained
                        difficulties found with Japanese proposal in para 4 Embtel 723.<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d222fn3">
                            <ref target="#d220">Document 220</ref>.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Later today <persName corresp="#p_OK1">Ohno</persName> said that, after
                        consultation with <persName corresp="#p_FA1">Fujiyama</persName>, they would
                        be agreeable to our language but urged one slight change which, they
                        thought, expressed more precisely meaning we intended to convey. This change
                        is to substitute “whenever” for “insofar as” in final clause. Their
                        reasoning was that our wording was susceptible of <pb facs="0498" n="470"
                            xml:id="pg_470"/> meaning, and particularly so when translated into
                        Japanese, that provisions of Article 51 are <hi rend="italic">always</hi>
                        applicable to some extent to all “measures”. Their wording, they believed,
                        made it clear, without changing meaning that provisions of Article 51 of
                        Charter applied only to <hi rend="italic">some</hi> of measures contemplated
                        by Article I of Treaty, e.g. Article 51 would not apply to measures short of
                        hostilities or to disposition of our forces in Japan.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>We said we thought that broad use of our term conveyed same thought as
                        Japanese change, but that we would refer proposed change to Department. We
                        would appreciate urgent confirmation, if it is acceptable, if possible to
                        reach us in time to convey to Foreign Ministry prior to noon meeting
                        Thursday Tokyo time of Administrative Vice Ministers’ weekly conference, at
                        which entire text must be approved if it is to receive Cabinet approval
                        Friday in time for signature Saturday. (<persName corresp="#p_FA1"
                            >Fujiyama</persName> departs Saturday<note n="4" xml:id="d222fn4"
                            >September 14.</note> for New York.)</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Tentative time for signature of exchange of notes is 9:00 am Saturday
                        morning Tokyo time, with simultaneous release in Tokyo and Washington at
                        that hour. We recognize this is not very convenient hour for Washington
                        release but hope it can be managed. (Release earlier in day in Washington to
                        be held until that hour will make trouble for us here because stories will
                        be sent back to Tokyo before signature has actually taken place.) Would
                        appreciate confirmation that proposed timing is acceptable and we will in
                        turn confirm to Department when final arrangements made.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>FonOff concurs with text of our draft reply as given Deptel 561<note n="5"
                            xml:id="d222fn5">Dated September 5, not printed. (Department of State,
                            Central Files, 794.5/9–257)</note> and will make explanatory comment
                        substantially similar to text in para 2 Deptel 561.<note n="6"
                            xml:id="d222fn6">
                            <p>Telegram 600 to Tokyo, September 10, sent in reference to telegram
                                747, reads as follows:</p>
                            <p>“1. Accept substitution ‘whenever’ for ‘insofar as’ in final clause
                                para C as suggested Japanese accordance para 2 reftel. FYI
                                complexities of Japanese language beyond us. End FYI.</p>
                            <p>“2. Also agree proposed timing simultaneous release accordance para 4
                                reftel.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 794.5/9–1057)</p>
                            <p>For text of the Understanding on the Interpretation of the Security
                                Treaty and the Administrative Agreement with respect to the Charter
                                of the United Nations, effected by an exchange of notes signed at
                                Tokyo September 14, 1957, see <gloss target="#t_TIAS1">TIAS</gloss>
                                3910; 8 <gloss target="#t_UST1">UST</gloss> (pt. 2) 1571. For text
                                of the Department’s press release issued September 13 (Washington
                                time), see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                                September 30, 1957, p. 534.</p>
                        </note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Passed <gloss target="#t_COMUSJ1">COMUS Japan</gloss> by other means.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Allison</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
