<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-04-05T13:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-04-05T13:00:00-05:00" n="115" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                        <head>115. Memorandum From the Presidentʼs Special Assistant (<persName type="from">Rostow</persName>) to President <persName type="to">Johnson</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d115fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> Library,
                                National Security File, Memos to the President—<persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt W. Rostow</persName>, vol. 1. Top Secret;
                                Eyes Only. Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_MBD1">Moyers</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-04-05T13:00:00-05:00">April 5, 1966, 1 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>I drafted the attached comment on Sunday,<note n="2" xml:id="d115fn2">April 3. Rostow gave his April 3 draft memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_Taylor1">Taylor</persName>, who commented on it in a
                                memorandum of April 4 to Rostow. (Ibid., Country File, Vietnam, Box
                                260, Gen. <persName corresp="#p_Taylor1">Taylor</persName>)</note>
                            in the midst of the worst of the Vietnam political crisis.</p>
                        <p>As a little light—only a little—breaks through,<note n="3" xml:id="d115fn3"><persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName>ʼs
                                notes for the Presidentʼs meeting with his advisers at 1 p.m. on
                                April 5 include the following brief discussion of Vietnam:
                                “Information from Vietnam seems unclear. <persName corresp="#p_Taylor1">Taylor</persName> thinks situation in
                                Danang is better, but what will Buddhists do? Rostow feels this
                                morning is much better than we anticipated last night.” The meeting
                                mainly dealt with foreign policy issues other than Vietnam. (Ibid.,
                                Meeting Notes File)</note> I would summarize its conclusions as
                            follows: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>If the Vietnamese work their way out of this—and a civil
                                    constitution-drafting group is born—we will have passed a great
                                    turning point; although there will be plenty of trouble before
                                    they actually find their political feet.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>The Communists are serious and understand the importance of
                                    politics: they will take it as a major defeat.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Then will be the time to pour it on</hi> and
                                    see if we canʼt force, in the months ahead, a resolution of the
                                    conflict. <hi rend="italic">The strain on our political and
                                        economic life and the strain on the South Vietnamese is all
                                        but intolerable</hi>. Specifically, as the memo suggests, we
                                    should <hi rend="italic">on the military side:</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <item>—continue maximum effort to impose attrition on <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_PAVN1">PAVN</gloss> forces in South
                                            Vietnam;</item>
                                        <item>—work more effectively from the air on the supply
                                            routes from the North;</item>
                                        <item>—increase the costs to Hanoi of continuing the war by
                                            going for oil or other precision target systems that
                                            hurt without killing an excessive number of
                                            civilians.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">On the diplomatic side</hi> we should: <list>
                                        <item>—keep close to the Russians, but not hope for too much
                                            until Hanoi and the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                                            are persuaded by the situation itself that the jig is
                                            up;</item>
                                        <item>—keep lines open to Hanoi;</item>
                                        <item>—begin to get word to the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> that their destiny is: to sit on the
                                            Hanoi delegation at the international conference; and to
                                            talk to Saigon about how to end the war and get back
                                            into the national life of South Vietnam.</item>
                                        <item>—request Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> to conduct a high level review of
                                            negotiating papers developed at the working
                                            level.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <pb facs="0366" n="330" xml:id="pg_330"/>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">On the side of the Honolulu program</hi> the
                                    memo argues that the most critical dimension is political. <list>
                                        <item>—We should, of course, continue our present program of
                                            concentrated effort in four areas of rural
                                            reconstruction—full blast;</item>
                                        <item>—but we should concentrate more effort, once they hire
                                            a hall and begin to talk, on political development; how
                                            to keep the Directorate together; the political party
                                            clause in the constitution; how to balance majority and
                                            minority interests; the formation of a national
                                            wide-ranging party, etc.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WLGLW1"><hi rend="strong">Walt</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>Attachment</head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-04-05">April 5,
                                        1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <p rend="center">Memorandum From the Presidentʼs Special Assistant
                                    (<persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>) to President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName></p>
                            <p>You ask for comments on the attached.<note n="4" xml:id="d115fn4">Attached but not printed are: 1) <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName>ʼs memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName>, March 28, outlining four
                                    “non-military” questions, which <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName> had asked the President and which the
                                    President wanted <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> to
                                    comment on; and 2) <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName>ʼs March 29 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName> in reply, which the
                                    President asked Rostow to comment on.</note> They follow:</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">1. The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> and Negotiations.</hi><note n="5" xml:id="d115fn5"><persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName>ʼs
                                    first question was: “Are we pursuing the one key to settlement
                                    in Vietnam—the Soviet Union?”</note></p>
                            <p>I believe Russian leverage on Hanoi depends mainly on our persuading
                                Hanoi that negotiation is the best course. Aside from what we do
                                militarily and politically in Vietnam, the Russians have little
                                leverage.</p>
                            <p>They can keep a presence by assisting with arms—notably arms to
                                defend Hanoi from the air.</p>
                            <p>Hanoi wants them as a presence: to balance Peking; to supply arms;
                                and as an insurance policy, should negotiations be undertaken.</p>
                            <p>But only we—not Moscow—can push them over the hump into
                                negotiations.</p>
                            <p>That means, in my view, that <hi rend="italic">we must push harder on
                                    the second and third elements in the military equation</hi>.</p>
                            <pb facs="0367" n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">The first element</hi>, which is going quite well,
                                is to impose heavy attrition on the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_PAVN1">PAVN</gloss> main force
                                units.</p>
                            <p>The second element <hi rend="italic">is harassment of their supply
                                    lines from the North</hi>. Here I would be prepared to take the
                                risks of B–52 bombing of Mu Gia pass and other elements of that
                                supply route in North Vietnam and Laos. I would press to the maximum
                                production and use of special interdiction weapons.</p>
                            <p>The third military element is <hi rend="italic">making the war more
                                    expensive in the North to Hanoi</hi>. There I prefer oil to
                                bombing the Northeast supply lines. The latter justifies more and
                                more Chinese engineering and logistical forces. Oil hits the
                                over-all military logistical capacity in the North, as well as
                                industrial and civil operations. Iʼm certainly not the last word on
                                this; but I do believe we should lean harder on Hanoi, on a
                                precision bombing basis.</p>
                            <p>It is not, Mr. President, that Iʼm bloody-minded or a hawk. But the
                                strain of trying to do the job principally by attrition of main
                                force units places almost intolerable burdens on the political life
                                of our country and on the war-weary South Vietnamese. <hi rend="italic">Weʼve got to try to shorten this war without doing
                                    unwise or desperate things</hi>.</p>
                            <p>I believe the Russians would fully understand and accept this course;
                                although they are keeping their oar in Hanoi as a contingency
                                whether we succeed (for negotiations) or whether we fail (to balance
                                the Chinese).</p>
                            <p>In short, I would suggest that, <hi rend="italic">if we survive the
                                    present political crisis, we do more about the supply line from
                                    the North and we increase Hanoiʼs costs for continuing the
                                    conflict</hi>.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Meanwhile, we should remain close to the
                                    Russians;</hi> because none of us is so smart—certainly not
                                me—to be absolutely sure they wonʼt help end this earlier rather
                                than later.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">2. Peace Talks.</hi><note n="6" xml:id="d115fn6"><persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName>ʼs
                                    second question was: “Have we really sorted out the sticky
                                    problems and issues of peace talks—so that we are absolutely
                                    clear on our objectives and trading points?”</note></p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">The negotiating papers are pretty good</hi>.<note n="7" xml:id="d115fn7">Presumably a reference to negotiating
                                    papers drafted during late 1965 and 1966 by the Vietnam Planning
                                    Group, chaired by <persName corresp="#p_ULS1">Unger</persName>,
                                    and in particular to the groupʼs paper on “A Settlement in
                                    Vietnam,” to which <persName corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName>
                                    referred in his memorandum of March 29. A copy of the paper,
                                    together with <persName corresp="#p_ULS1">Unger</persName>ʼs
                                    discussion of it in a memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>, March 15, is in Department of State,
                                        <gloss target="#t_EAVN1">EA/VN</gloss> Files: Lot 75 D 167,
                                    Vietnam Coordinating Committee and Working Group,
                                    1964–66.</note>
                                <hi rend="italic">They move toward</hi> what I have called <hi rend="italic">a “two-track” negotiating plan: an international
                                    negotiation</hi>, involving the Geneva Accord powers, with the
                                    <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> on the Hanoi delegation,
                                dealing with the restoration and strengthening of the 1954 and 1962
                                agreements; <hi rend="italic">an internal negotiation</hi>, between
                                Saigon and <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> to end the war <pb facs="0368" n="332" xml:id="pg_332"/> and create the conditions
                                for absorbing the South Vietnamese now caught up in the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> insurrection into the life of the
                                Country.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">There is some fuzziness about this high in the
                                    government</hi>. Some of our public talk suggests we might
                                settle internal South Vietnam affairs at an international
                                conference; some suggests no one would ever talk to the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>—ever. <hi rend="italic">The surfacing
                                    of a two-track policy is a delicate matter. But in the meanwhile
                                    what we say should be consistent with it</hi>. Incidentally, the
                                Vietnamese portion of the Honolulu Communique was consistent with a
                                two-track negotiation.</p>
                            <p>The reason for the fuzziness is that the preliminary papers have been
                                developed at the working level; and you may wish <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> to render you a
                                    personal judgment on existing plans, negotiating concepts, and
                                    ways of talking about the problem</hi>.</p>
                            <p>It follows from this line of thought that <hi rend="italic">it may be
                                    wise to find some way of suggesting to the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> that we think they ought to be
                                    talking with the government in Saigon</hi>.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">3. Political Tutelage and
                                    Organization.</hi><note n="8" xml:id="d115fn8"><persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName>ʼs third question was:
                                    “Why shouldnʼt we organize in Vietnam a highly skilled group of
                                    political professionals to work with the current government in
                                    teaching them how to become democratic leaders—and build a
                                    durable democratic party?”</note></p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Organization comes first</hi>. If there is one
                                thing I regret about Honolulu it is that we didnʼt nail <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> down harder on a date for
                                implementing the political side of his January 15th speech.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">The unrest in Vietnam doesnʼt come from hungry
                                    people</hi>. The folks carrying banners and organizing all this
                                eat regularly. And thatʼs the way it is in most political
                                disruptions in developing countries—and even in our race
                                troubles.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">What they want is either personal power (<persName corresp="#p_TQ1">Tri Quang</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_Thi1">Thi</persName>) or participation in
                                    politics</hi>, which is the application of power. And the
                                Communists are, of course, in there trying to make the most of
                                it.</p>
                            <p>The most urgent non-military business is to cut the radicals out of
                                the herd by getting the literate, urban leaders—and others—into a
                                hall and around tables talking about the political future. Some
                                force may well be necessary in this crisis; but essentially weʼre
                                trying—and the Directorate is trying—to get the moderates off the
                                streets and into a position where they have to think and talk
                                responsibly about the future of their country.</p>
                            <p>Once they are there, we have a number of ways we can help them think
                                along the right lines; Washington and Saigon are in pretty good
                                shape, if and when we get over that historic hurdle which is what
                                todayʼs crisis is about.</p>
                            <pb facs="0369" n="333" xml:id="pg_333"/>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">There may be ways of beefing up Saigonʼs
                                    administrative capacity</hi> through a relatively few first-rate
                                advisers working for the Vietnamese and acceptable to them; <hi rend="italic">but we need a government with a bit of a future
                                    first</hi>.</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">4. The Four Key Areas.</hi><note n="9" xml:id="d115fn9"><persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Valenti</persName>ʼs fourth question was: “Are we keeping
                                    close tabs on the Lodge plan for pacifying four key areas in
                                        <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>?”</note></p>
                            <p>Bob Komer will report.</p>
                            <p>I donʼt need to tell you that I support increased economic and social
                                development in South Vietnam as elsewhere.</p>
                            <p>And Iʼm sure that something like the <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> Plan—and the four key areas—is the right way
                                to proceed; by concentration of effort.</p>
                            <p>But <hi rend="italic">I donʼt think this war is going to end by
                                    pacification of most of the country</hi>.</p>
                            <p>It will end—if we win it—when some combination of the following four
                                things leads Hanoi to knock it off: <list>
                                    <item>—<hi rend="italic">sufficient</hi> attrition on the main
                                        force units to break up structures, produce a marked
                                        deterioration of morale, and an enlarged flow of
                                        defectors—to our side and back home to their <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>-controlled areas;</item>
                                    <item>—<hi rend="italic">sufficient</hi> obstruction to the
                                        supply lines to make replacements expensive and, if
                                        possible, less than attrition of men, equipment, and
                                        ammunition;</item>
                                    <item>—<hi rend="italic">sufficient</hi> cost to military, civil
                                        and economic life in the North to help tip the
                                        attrition-supply equation further in our direction;</item>
                                    <item>—<hi rend="italic">sufficient</hi> order, unity, and
                                        stability in the South to rule out a Communist political
                                        takeover in the midst of chaos.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>If this view is right, the war will not end when we have pacified
                                every district, village, and province. When it ends there will still
                                be a hell of a mess in South Vietnam—as there was in Greece, Malaya,
                                and the Philippines.</p>
                            <p>There will probably still be some last-ditch <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> to mop up; but, if other guerrilla wars carry any
                                lesson, it is that when the organizational structure cracks, it
                                cracks pretty well down the line. And the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> is the most tightly organized guerrilla structure
                                weʼve seen except that of the Chinese Communists. For example, they
                                are now feeding local guerrillas up to the main force units, in
                                order to keep them up to strength. <hi rend="italic">The main force
                                    and local guerrilla units are interlocked; if the main forces
                                    go, it will have a profound effect on the local forces</hi>.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">In short, we should carry forward rural
                                    reconstruction on orderly concentrated lines; but we should not
                                    measure the probable length of the war by the rate of successful
                                    pacification</hi>.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">The real job of rural reconstruction will be
                                    post-war</hi>.</p>
                            <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_WLGLW1"><hi rend="strong">Walt</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>