<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-05-20T16:58:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-05-20T16:58:00-05:00" n="143" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d143">
                        <head>143. Telegram From the Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff (<persName corresp="#p_WGEG1" type="from">Wheeler</persName>) to the Commander,
                            Military Assistance Command, Vietnam (<persName corresp="#p_WGWC1" type="to">Westmoreland</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d143fn1">Source: Center of Military History, Westmoreland
                                Papers, <gloss target="#t_COMUSMACV1">COMUSMACV</gloss> Message
                                Files. Secret. Repeated to Admiral <persName corresp="#p_SAUSG1">Sharp</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-05-20T21:58:00+00:00">May
                                    20, 1966, 2158Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_CJCS1">CJCS</gloss> 2837–66. 1. I believe that both of
                            you should have my reading of the effect here in the United States of
                            the continuing political turmoil and backing and filling of the several
                            contending parties in <gloss target="#t_RVN1">RVN</gloss>. We have had
                            adverse reactions here in the past arising from the numerous political
                            imbroglios in that country; however, in my judgment, the effect of the
                            present situation on the public and in the press and in the Congress
                            (both of the latter in this instance reflecting early and muted public
                            opinion) is far more adverse than heretofore. There are a number of
                            reasons for this but the principal reasons, I think, are the facts that
                            we have committed a quarter of a million men to combat in South Vietnam;
                            the prestige of the United States is at stake; and U.S. casualties are
                            mounting. I note that, for the third successive week, our casualties
                            have exceeded those of Vietnamese forces. Rightly or wrongly, this
                            latter fact is taken by the American people as proof positive of
                            assertions continuously made by those in opposition to our Vietnamese
                            policy that United States forces <pb facs="0431" n="395" xml:id="pg_395"/> are fighting the war against <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> forces while the South Vietnamese,
                            whose freedom and country are at stake, squabble pettily among
                            themselves to achieve political advantage.</p>
                        <p>2. To illustrate my point, I made an Armed Forces Day address yesterday
                            in Houston, Texas, to an overflow luncheon audience of the Houston
                            Rotary Club and the Military Affairs Committee of the Chamber of
                            Commerce of Houston. As you would expect, the audience and the local
                            press rather unanimously support an American policy of strength and
                            opposition to Communist initiatives. Nevertheless, I was impressed
                            during my conversations with civic leaders and during the following
                            press conference by the dissatisfaction and uneasiness of all as to our
                            future in Vietnam. For example, I was questioned sharply as to whether,
                            in view of the Vietnam situation, we were reducing or would cease our
                            deployments to <gloss target="#t_RVN1">RVN</gloss>. To widen the field a
                            bit, Senator <persName corresp="#p_JJK1">Javits</persName> yesterday
                            expressed the view that we should stand down our military efforts in
                            both North and South Vietnam. In brief, he advocated that we should stop
                            our air campaign against North Vietnam and should, in agreement with the
                                <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>, instruct our ground combat
                            forces to desist offensive operations and fight only to defend
                            themselves against attack. The demerits of Senator <persName corresp="#p_JJK1">Javits</persName>ʼ proposal from the military
                            point of view are so obvious that I will not discuss it further. You
                            should be aware, however, that, as farfetched as this proposal to
                            abandon the initiative to the enemy may seem to us in the military, it
                            will have a distinct appeal to all flocks of doves and, even more
                            importantly, to the relatives of our men in South Vietnam whose lives
                            are at risk. The rationale of this latter group (for whom I have much
                            sympathy) will be why should my son or brother or husband be killed
                            fighting against the <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> while the South Vietnamese whose
                            country and freedom are at stake engage themselves in political
                            bickering to the detriment of the effort against the enemy.</p>
                        <p>3. As I read the cables from Embassy Saigon and from Headquarters <gloss target="#t_MACV1">MACV</gloss> reporting upon the actions, the
                            statements and the proposals of the two sides, I get two distinct
                            impressions: (a) all parties to the controversy appear to be convinced
                            that the United States is so firmly hooked in Vietnam that nothing they
                            do, or any circumstance arising therefrom, will cause us to disengage
                            from our commitments; and (b) both parties to the confrontation are
                            acting in bad faith, are cemented in fixed positions which they will not
                            undertake to modify by compromise and that the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>, at least, is proceeding without having a clear-cut
                            objective in mind.</p>
                        <p>4. A further item in this devilʼs stew is Colonel Loan who, if the cables
                            are reasonably correct, is a continuing troublemaker. I note that at
                            last he has departed the Da Nang area for Saigon; based on the past, I
                            wonder how long he will remain absent from the scene. Moreover, I recall
                            that in response to an earlier query from me, you stated that the
                            Directorate continued to be a cohesive body. Do you judge that
                            cohesiveness <pb facs="0432" n="396" xml:id="pg_396"/> continues? I note
                            that General <persName corresp="#p_Thi1">Thi</persName> at first agreed
                            to, and has now backed out of, a meeting with General <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> at Chu Lai for reasons which at best
                            seem specious. I note also the public statements of General Dinh calling
                            for the ouster of <persName corresp="#p_Thieu1">Thieu</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName>. Does this reflect personal
                            outrage or political conviction?</p>
                        <p>5. I really do not expect that either of you have answers to the
                            questions I have posed or any reassurance of the early resolution of
                            this mess. My purpose in addressing you is to convey my own deep
                            distress and concern that the lives, the resources, and the political
                            capital we have expended in our effort to preserve South Vietnam as a
                            part of the free world approach the point of having been in vain. Very
                            frankly, I am greatly worried, the more so because in all logic one
                            cannot expect the American people to suffer indefinitely the
                            continuation of this truly sickening situation.</p>
                        <p>6. As you know, I am usually pretty much of an optimist; but always, I
                            hope, on the realistic side. This time, however, I think I can feel the
                            first gusts of the whirlwind generated by the wind sown by the
                            Vietnamese. Westy, I know that you will exert to the full your influence
                            to set things once more on a proper course. If any of the above views
                            will be of use to you, you have my full permission to use them as and
                            how you think best. Even so, even if we get some semblance of solidarity
                            and common purpose among the contending factions, we must all recognize
                            that we have lost irretrievably and for all time some of the support
                            which until now we have received from the American people. In other
                            words, regardless of what happens of a favorable nature, many people
                            will never again believe that the effort and the sacrifices are
                            worthwhile. Warm regards.<note n="2" xml:id="d143fn2">In telegram MAC
                                4070, May 22, <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>
                                responded that he believed the situation in Vietnam had been “blown
                                out of perspective” by the press. While it was “serious,” it was
                                “not desperate,” and the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> seemed
                                “to be making positive headway in restoring government authority in
                                the I Corps area.” In a telegram transmitted to Wheeler at 0929Z on
                                May 23, <persName corresp="#p_SAUSG1">Sharp</persName> concurred
                                with <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>ʼs
                                assessment. (Ibid.)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>