<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-01-11T14:05:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-01-11T13:05:00-05:00" n="15" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                        <head>15. Notes of Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d15fn1">Source:
                                Johnson Library, Meeting Notes File. No classification marking.
                                Valenti took the notes. In a memorandum written at 1 p.m. on January
                                11, McGeorge Bundy told President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> that the “main point” of the meeting with
                                Bell was “simply to emphasize the importance of the non-military
                                effort by having <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName> report
                                on the record to you.” (Ibid., National Security File, Memos to the
                                    President—<persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>,
                                vol. 18)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" from="1966-01-11T13:05:00-05:00" to="1966-01-11T14:05:00-05:00">January 11, 1966, 1:05–2:05
                                    p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PRESENT</head>
                            <item>The President, <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>,
                                Bill Bundy, Mac Bundy, <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">David
                                    Bell</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Alexis
                                    Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MBD1">Bill
                                    Moyers</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VJ1">Jack
                                    Valenti</persName><note n="2" xml:id="d15fn2">The Presidentʼs
                                    Daily Diary indicates that <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName> was also present. (Johnson
                                Library)</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_BDE1">David Bell</persName>ʼs return<note n="3" xml:id="d15fn3"><persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName> visited Vietnam January 1–5. For his
                                    written report to the President, see <ref target="#d28">Document
                                        28</ref>.</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>: Four essentials: 1.
                            Pacification for rural construction. 2. Resources allocation and
                            inflation. 3. Emphasis on non military aspects. 4. Miscellaneous.</p>
                        <p>Number one problem is rural pacification. Today <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> army can no longer clear any area; must have our
                            troops. But even so canʼt hold it. Difficult <pb facs="0077" n="41" xml:id="pg_41"/> problem. Must restore some kind of government
                            system that serves the people. A new spirit is needed—local security is
                            needed. Is not being done now. Some areas are thoroughly pacified but
                            have always been historically.</p>
                        <p>We are not yet following up and increasing hold so people can see
                            positive future for themselves. Nothing new—but did find neither the
                                <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> nor Americans are adequately on
                            top of this problem. General Khanh has done a good job to learn this
                            task. His deputy Col. Chon is one of the best—now recruiting and
                            training Vietnamese teams.</p>
                        <p>Ben de Pugh on our side understands the problem. Col. Sam Wilson also
                            good. Plans to concentrate in 4 limited priority areas. If they
                            accomplish even this, they will have affected 1/20 or 1/10 of rural
                            population but it will be first time this has happened. Key question—can
                            we get even this little done. Will take 80 man teams to go into each
                            hamlet and village and stay for months at a time. Begin to build a
                            political system and root out <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>. Takes
                            heavy volume of <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> manpower to do this.
                            Strong back-up needed also—(<gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_USIA1">USIA</gloss>,
                            etc.).</p>
                        <p>Disturbed because in general setup of U.S. mission, no one is really in
                            charge of this sort of operation. Tentative conclusion is (agreed to by
                                <persName corresp="#p_WGWC1">Westmoreland</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MCA1">Mann</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>) to place responsibility on Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PWJ1">Porter</persName>, give him small staff, integrate
                            the overall program. Can bring in wholly new man but this has
                            drawbacks.</p>
                        <p>This is number one objective save for the actual fighting to be
                            undertaken in coming year.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Resource Allocation</hi></p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> economy has changed—now in boom
                            situation. Resources over-strained, prices going up. Plans are not made
                            as to how to distribute manpower. Canʼt do anything about land reform
                            because no men available. Need someone in U.S. mission akin to <persName corresp="#p_BJF1">James Byrnes</persName>ʼ job in WW II. Would
                            identify resources and spotlight issues. Requires office and man not now
                            in <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss>. Checked with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> but neither of us are sure about
                            this.</p>
                        <p>Did a lot of work on inflation. Laid out a complete set of measurements
                            to control inflation. Principal one is to limit <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> budget expenses. Increase taxes (agreed not yet done).
                            Limit to maximum possible extent the spending by American troops.
                            (Budget deficits, troop spending, military construction program are
                            three big sources of inflation.)</p>
                        <p>Difficult to really prevent American troop spending.</p>
                        <p>Think we have the impact of spending and construction as low as
                            possible.</p>
                        <p>U.S. and <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> are agreed on approximate
                            volume of imports required. About double the imports over last year.
                            From $200M to $400M <pb facs="0078" n="42" xml:id="pg_42"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss>. Demand for increased imports are
                            already on us. Already have to transfer funds to get us through
                            January.</p>
                        <p>Finally, over and above this will be necessary to take monetary action,
                            even to devalue currency. Not now because of volatile situation.
                            Meantime, series of actions suggested—putting some money through black
                            market in Hong Kong. <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> wanted to sell
                            gold but told them it was out of the question. Inflation problem is not
                            fully met today.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Ports</hi></p>
                        <p>Badly jammed. Coastal ports are being worked on and in few months will be
                            able to handle traffic. Saigon is another problem. 500,000 tons by next
                            October. We have man out there from New York Port Authority who is good
                            man.</p>
                        <p>Through the coming year need to take series of steps which will improve
                            the port. Canʼt be done now because of administrative set up.</p>
                        <p>Recommend <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> establish a
                            single-headed Port Authority—put tough guy in charge. Put high ranking
                            military man along side him. <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName>
                            accepted recommendation in principle—has not carried it out.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Non military aspects</hi></p>
                        <p>Satisfied that <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_Zorthian1">Zorthian</persName>, Mann et al. doing all
                            they can in field. American reporters file a good deal of this non
                            military work but little of it gets printed. <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> says it would be helpful to have series of
                            visits—if they are well prepared and substantive. But there is plenty
                            for such groups to do. Careful preparation can be done.</p>
                        <p>Recommend such groups go out: Agriculture-Education-Health—in that order.
                            First visit by Freeman be held in February. Other visits later.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous</hi></p>
                        <p>Checked on refugee camps. Rather pleased at what I found. Refugees being
                            fed, not hungry, reasonably clothed. Housing varies. Some very good,
                            some very bad. Too crowded, dangerous from health view. Refugees
                            relatively static. Coming in, but others re-settled. Around 700,000 now.
                            Can handle that number okay.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Economic Warfare</hi></p>
                        <p>Diversion of American materials to <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>—Committee working on this. Difficult to manage. <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> can send purchasing agent to Saigon and
                            buy what they need. It is difficult to get to <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>. Easier to block it via transportation rather than
                            marketplace. Long, detailed process to find out about the flow—and to
                            stop it.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> expanding—1,000 Americans and 200–300
                            contract people. Bulk of additional people going in the field. All this,
                            of course, has nothing to do with military.</p>
                        <pb facs="0079" n="43" xml:id="pg_43"/>
                        <p>President: Mac, analyze written report and let us find out what we need
                            to do.</p>
                        <p>Bundy: Most important is pacification.<note n="4" xml:id="d15fn4">In a
                                memorandum to the President written at 5:30 p.m. on January 11,
                                Bundy stated: “My basic conviction is that the things Dave Bell was
                                talking about this morning are very much more important than bombing
                                the North. This is why I think the State of the Union should keep
                                attention focused on the effort in the South.” (Johnson Library,
                                National Security File, Memos to the President—<persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge Bundy</persName>, vol. 18)</note> Not
                            clear we can handle resource allocation in as straightforward way as
                            David suggests. Two kinds of civilian leadership problem—pacification
                            and resource allocation.</p>
                        <p>President: Gather pacification has gone backwards.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>: Possibly—though not much.
                            Asked provincial men how much of their area is reachable—varied—much by
                            day—less by night. Reporters I talked to didnʼt seem to know much.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> people (Roy, <persName corresp="#p_WLS1">Wehrle</persName>) are worried. Worried about
                            thinness and weakness in <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> government.
                            Only 2 or 3 strong men in government. General <persName corresp="#p_NVT1">Thieu</persName> and two others.</p>
                        <p>When you talk as I did for long hours with these men, you find they are
                            not broad gauged. <persName corresp="#p_WLS1">Wehrle</persName> is
                            troubled by this. But people in the country side are not worried—high
                            morale and working like dogs. Superb morale. Far better understanding
                            displayed today by <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> leaders in the
                            “village campaign.” <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> men in charge do
                            see the problem, making plans but they are still plans.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>: Donʼt think thereʼs
                            single area pacified.</p>
                        <p>President: What about Lansdale?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>: Has good effect on <gloss target="#t_VN1">VN</gloss> side—divisive effect in American
                            community. His personality is the reason—Deutsch is real problem. Key
                            question is whether he is worth the cost. Lansdale however is rated
                            valuable above his cost.</p>
                        <p>President: What is relationship between the American leaders?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>: Excellent.</p>
                        <p>President: Anyone make any contribution to the pause?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>: Didnʼt go into that.
                            Thailand problem is troublesome—corrupt man in charge. Everyone in
                            Thailand is aware of it. Pleased with <gloss target="#t_AID1">AID</gloss> program in N.E. Thailand. Still a long way from a
                            popular based program and government. Still handing down largesse from
                            on high.</p>
                        <p>Laos not hopeless—real base to build on in terms of development. No
                            Taiwan, but clearly not a sink-hole, hopeless. They can improve in a
                            good many ways.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: Just spent three hours
                            before House Foreign Affairs Committee. And itʼs not the same committee
                            I knew before.</p>
                        <pb facs="0080" n="44" xml:id="pg_44"/>
                        <p>President: I think it is going to get worse. Viet Nam is number one thing
                            on their mind. But when you get to specifics they wind up doing the same
                            thing. Donʼt think the polls are far wrong—55–45. Senate will be worse
                            than House. Must ride out the waves created by 100 experts who visited
                            there.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: One question: Why doesnʼt
                            Adm. allow it to debate? Told them they could debate anytime.</p>
                        <p>President: Are they critical of pause?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: No, on the whole they rather
                            like it. This has been Gung Ho committee but now they are softer—looking
                            for a way out.</p>
                        <p>President: What would your conclusion be?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: They have no solutions—just
                            deeply troubled.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_BDE1">Bell</persName>: Followed <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>—and his visits were excellent.
                            Complimentary of what he is doing. Committee not critical of peace
                            effort—worried about where we go.</p>
                        <p>President: Articles in last few days have spurred them on (Lippmann,
                            etc.).</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>