<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-07-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-07-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="179" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d179">
                        <head>179. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d179fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–14 VIET/<gloss target="#t_Elmtree1">ELMTREE</gloss>. Top Secret; Sensitive.
                                Drafted by U. <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Alexis Johnson</persName>.
                                In a July 20 letter to <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName>, Johnson indicated that messages concerning the
                                contact described in the memorandum printed here would be slugged
                                “Elm Tree.” (Ibid.)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1966-07-17">July 17,
                                1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>I met with General <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> from
                            1:00 p.m. to 4:15 p.m. July 17 in a suite at the Waldorf Astoria. As was
                            previously the case in our meetings, we conversed in a mixture of French
                            and English, with General <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName>
                            talking primarily in French and with my interrupting to clarify points I
                            did not fully understand.</p>
                        <p>After exchanging pleasantries, I referred to his previous conversation
                            with Col. Jasper Wilson,<note n="2" xml:id="d179fn2">No record of this
                                conversation has been found; prior contacts in July between
                                    <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> and the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> regarding this subject are
                                summarized in two memoranda, dated July 7 and 20, from [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] of <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> to <persName corresp="#p_BWP1">William Bundy</persName>, who are identified in the memoranda
                                by pseudonyms. (Central Intelligence Agency, DDO/<gloss target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss> Files, Job 78–000032R, Chipwood
                                    Memos-<gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>)</note> which I said had
                            been brought to the attention of the President, Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>. The President had asked that
                            I meet with General <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> to
                            follow up on that conversation and no one else was privy to our
                            conversation or to his previous conversation with Col. Wilson. General
                                <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> expressed much
                            satisfaction and at my request went over the ground he had covered with
                            Col. Wilson but in more detail.</p>
                        <p>He traced the Viet Cong movement in the South back to the “Movement
                            Republicain de Cochine” (MRC) which he said was one of several political
                            movements that originated in the South in the 1946 period, others being
                            the “Movement Populaire de Cochine”, which was a French puppet that
                            disappeared, the Dai Viet and the Viet Minh. The MRC was heavily
                            composed of Cochinchinese, essentially non-Communist intellectuals such
                            as Tho. It was subsequently suppressed by the French and its leaders
                            imprisoned. They were released in 1954 and initially worked with Diem.
                            However, to these Southerners the Tonkinese Diem was essentially a
                            “foreigner” and they broke with Diem around 1957 to form what became the
                            Viet Cong and the National Liberation Front.</p>
                        <p>While southern-born cadre trained in the North were infiltrated and some
                            supplies, the movement was thus essentially Southern as opposed to
                            Annamite or Tonkinese. However, various units were under varying degrees
                            of Communist or Tonkinese control, depending on the type and number of
                            cadre. However, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said (it
                            was not clear how much he <pb facs="0534" n="498" xml:id="pg_498"/> was
                            expressing his own opinion and how much that of “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>”)<note n="3" xml:id="d179fn3">“Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” was <persName corresp="#p_LVTMO1">Le Van Truong</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_LVTMO1">Le Van Truong</persName> identified himself
                                at a meeting with <persName corresp="#p_SP2">Paul Sturm</persName>
                                on July 27. The substance of the meeting was reported in <ref target="#d195">Document 195</ref>, and the information on
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LVTMO1">Le Van Truong</persName>ʼs
                                identify was reported in telegram 1523 from Paris, July 30. After
                                serving in Vietnam as secretary general of the Movement Populaire
                                Cochinchinois, established in 1946, <persName corresp="#p_LVTMO1">Le
                                    Van Truong</persName> had lived mostly in France from 1947 to
                                1954 and then in Saigon from 1954 to 1963, when he left Vietnam. His
                                overt political activity had principally taken the form of
                                journalism. (Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–14 VIET) In an August 11
                                memorandum for Sturm, U. <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Alexis
                                    Johnson</persName> noted that biographical information from
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> files, although very skimpy,
                                generally “checks out with” <persName corresp="#p_LVTMO1">Le Van
                                    Truong</persName>ʼs story. (Ibid.) However, as <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> saw the problem, it was a
                                “problem of the South for the South”.</note> that there were no
                            organized North Vietnamese forces introduced into South Viet-Nam until
                            after the introduction of the Americans. Nevertheless, he agreed with my
                            observation that, from what we now knew, the North began to move
                            elements of the 325th Division toward the South before the introduction
                            of the first American combat units into Danang in April 1965. We did not
                            return to or further resolve this point.</p>
                        <p>He then recounted the history of his relationship with “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” along the same lines as to Col.
                            Wilson. He said that “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>”
                            alleged that he was one of the three leaders of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> along with <persName corresp="#p_NHT1">Nguyen Huu Tho</persName> and “Mr. In”. He said that on our list of
                                <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> officers “Mr. In” was listed as
                            Ho Thu, a Deputy Secretary-General (but of course that was not his real
                            name) and, contrary to Col. Wilsonʼs understanding, he was not now
                            living in Saigon but rather in Viet Cong-controlled area in South
                            Viet-Nam.</p>
                        <p>In reply to my question as to how “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” was able to maintain from Europe the communication
                            necessary to be a leader of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said he was not
                            familiar with the details but he knew that he exchanged communications
                            in 48 hours, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> thought
                            possibly through the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> office in
                            Prague and thence through Cambodia.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” said that some three weeks ago the
                                <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss> had attempted to establish
                            contact with “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>ʼs” “liaison
                            officer” in Brussels but he had turned them down as he did not want to
                            deal with the <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said that, as a result of
                            his talks with “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>”,
                                <persName corresp="#p_Tho1">Tho</persName>, “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” and “Mr. In” now agreed on a
                            program under which they would ask for the presence of American forces
                            on the assumption that North Viet-Nam would not agree to accept any
                            arrangement for an independent South Viet-Nam and would seek to continue
                            its efforts to take it over. However, they would not want the presence
                            of other foreign forces such as the Koreans, the Australians and the
                            Philippines, as they desired to deal solely with the United States. They
                            would also ask for continued American economic assistance.</p>
                        <pb facs="0535" n="499" xml:id="pg_499"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said that he had not
                            discussed how the Viet Cong forces would come over or how arrangements
                            could be made, but he thought it important that we not talk in terms of
                            “ralliement” but rather in terms of “conciliation.”</p>
                        <p>In reply to my observation that at some stage discussions of arrangements
                            such as this would have inevitably to involve the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> and how did <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> foresee the possibility of
                            working this out, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said
                            that it would be entirely impossible with <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> and the other Tonkinese now in the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>. It would have to be a purely “Southern
                            solution” by Southerners for Southerners. America should reach agreement
                            with the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and then see that the kind
                            of a government was installed in Saigon necessary to carry it out. In
                            reply to my observation that, as <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> knew, we did not have that kind of control over
                            the political picture in Saigon, he observed that we had been very
                            successful in bringing about a satisfactory solution in the Dominican
                            Republic.</p>
                        <p>In reply to my question on how we could test the bona fides of “Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” he suggested that we
                            might ask him to arrange the release of a few selected prisoners within
                            an agreed period of time or ask for a stand-down in Viet Cong operations
                            in a specified area for a specified period of time. In this connection,
                            he said that “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” had
                            pointed out to him that the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> had at
                            one time prolonged a stand-down in operations for three days longer than
                            Hanoi had announced they were going to be stood down in order to
                            demonstrate, particularly to Rumania, the independence of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> from Hanoi. <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said that he was not clear
                            whether this was at Tet or at Christmas, but he thought it might be
                            interesting for us to look up the record and see whether in fact such an
                            event had taken place.<note n="4" xml:id="d179fn4">In a July 20
                                memorandum, U. <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">Alexis Johnson</persName>
                                stated that no substantiation had been found for this claim. (Ibid.,
                                    <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–14 VIET/<gloss target="#t_Elmtree1">ELMTREE</gloss>)</note></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> also said that Y Binh Aleo
                            (a Vice Chairman of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>), whose real
                            name he says is Y Bit, is the leader of the Montagnard element in the
                                <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and could probably bring along
                            the Montagnards in any arrangement that was reached with the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>. He said that, while, as I knew, the
                            Montagnards did not like Vietnamese in general, they liked Tonkinese
                            least of all and would prefer a southern government. <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said that as a political ploy
                            he had in mind the pattern of Malaya, in which the British had, after
                            careful arrangements, brought about the defection of the southern part
                            of the country and the Malays from the rebels and left the Chinese
                            element isolated in the North.</p>
                        <p>In reply to his question, I told <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> that he could be assured that the President was,
                            in principle, interested in vigorously pursuing the matter. I said that,
                            while the complications and difficulties were obvious, I knew that the
                            President was deeply interested in anything that could <pb facs="0536" n="500" xml:id="pg_500"/> bring about an end to hostilities in at
                            least part of the country or would in any way shorten the hostilities. I
                            told him that an individual<note n="5" xml:id="d179fn5">The reference is
                                to <persName corresp="#p_SP2">Paul Sturm</persName>, who was “Y” in
                                the <gloss target="#t_XYZ1">XYZ</gloss> negotiations (see <ref target="#d4">Document 4</ref>) and is referred to as <persName corresp="#p_George1">George</persName> in documents concerning
                                his meetings with <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> and
                                Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName> during July
                                1966.</note> who enjoyed the Presidentʼs confidence and who could
                            speak with authority was prepared immediately to go to Paris to make
                            contact with “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>”. I said
                            that the individual was a retired diplomat not now active in the
                            government who spoke good French and who could visit Paris
                            inconspicuously. I said that he was prepared to go at any time and urged
                                <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> immediately to go to
                            Paris and arrange the contact between this individual and “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>”. I pointed out the importance of
                            proceeding urgently with anything that could shorten hostilities by even
                            a week or an hour. <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName>
                            entirely agreed but said that the French had been very “sticky” about
                            his visa and had given him a visa valid only for one exit and reentry.
                            The French in Paris watched him very closely and, if he returned
                            unexpectedly and applied for another visa to return to his daughter
                            here, he was sure it would at the minimum attract much French attention
                            and they might even refuse him a visa. He felt that attracting French
                            attention in this situation was very dangerous and unwise. However, at
                            my urging he promised to think it over and see whether he could not work
                            out something that appeared practical and get in touch with me.</p>
                        <p>We also discussed how contact could be made in Paris between himself and
                            the individual we had in mind. After dismissing several possibilities
                            that did not seem practicable, we agreed that, subject to my
                            consultations in Washington, I would see him again in New York before he
                            left and arrange for him to meet the individual we had in mind so that
                            they could directly work out their arrangements for meeting in Paris
                            without the interposition of anyone else. Unless <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> can leave earlier, he will in
                            any event leave New York on July 28 with his daughter. He said that, as
                            “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” travels a great deal,
                            it will probably take him a minimum of 3 and a maximum of 7 days to make
                            contact with him after he returns to Paris.</p>
                        <p rend="center">NOTES</p>
                        <p>During the course of our conversation, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> throughout and in many ways laid heavy stress on
                            the fundamental differences and hostility between the Tonkinese, the
                            Annamites and the Cochinchinese. He gave me illustrations. He said that
                            while he was fighting in the North with the French he thought nothing of
                            bombarding a village because he looked on the people of the North as
                            being essentially “foreigners”. However, he had quite a different
                            attitude when he was fighting in the <pb facs="0537" n="501" xml:id="pg_501"/> South. He said the Tonkinese officers in the South
                            Vietnamese forces have a similar attitude towards southerners; that is,
                            they really look upon them as “foreigners” and have little care or
                            concern as to what they do to the local population. He said that the
                            Tonkinese are essentially warlike and their life revolves around making
                            war. This applied to the Tonkinese officers in the South Vietnamese
                            forces such as <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> and it would be
                            a very serious problem for which he did not have the answer working out
                            any arrangements such as we had discussed. As another example, he
                            pointed out that, when General <persName corresp="#p_Cao1">Cao</persName> was recently sent to the First Corps to put down the
                            trouble in Hue and Danang, as a Catholic whose family had suffered at
                            the hands of the Annamite Buddhists he had every reason to be very
                            “rough”. However, he did not do so because he himself was an
                            Annamite.</p>
                        <p>In discussing the dispositions of the regular North Vietnamese forces as
                            opposed to the Viet Cong forces, <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> said that, while he did not have exact and recent
                            information, it was his general impression that the North Vietnamese
                            forces were generally to be found roughly North of the line crossing the
                            southern part of the Pleiku and the northern part of Darlac down to the
                            South of Nhatrang. As far as military command was concerned, he had the
                            impression that these forces, which were generally in the V Military
                            Region, were commanded directly from Hanoi whereas the command line to
                            the forces in the South ran through the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and COSVN. He did not think that there was much
                            distinction between the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and the
                            COSVN.</p>
                        <p>He stoutly protested that he was not seeking anything for himself in this
                            but, if “we ever thought he could be of service” he would be willing to
                            consider whatever we might propose. He accepted my replies to his
                            queries to the effect that, after he had made contact between our
                            representative and “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>”, the
                            discussion should be entirely bilateral without his participation.</p>
                        <p>In reply to my query, he said that Le Van Hoach had been in touch with
                            Huynh Tan Phat, Vice Chairman of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>, during the period that I was in Saigon. He said that Phat
                            was not a Communist but that Hoach was entirely out of the question as
                            any channel or contact because he was known to everyone as such a big
                            gossip.</p>
                        <p>I pressed him hard on the identify of “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” and at one time he seemed almost to the point of
                            giving it to me, but said that he had “solemnly sworn” to “Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>” that he would not disclose his
                            identity until the meeting had been arranged. He said that we would of
                            course then learn who he was but he doubted very much that we had much
                            information with regard to him.</p>
                        <p>He expressed great fear of the French and what they might try to do to
                            prevent any such arrangement as well as what they might try to do to him
                            personally. He said the French were determined to make an arrangement
                                <pb facs="0538" n="502" xml:id="pg_502"/> that would be acceptable
                            to the Chinese and wanted to see all of Viet-Nam under the control of
                            the North.</p>
                        <p>I did not attempt to discuss with him where all of this would leave Annam
                            or how it could be fitted into the picture. The strong implication is of
                            course that the southerners do not care too much if they can make a deal
                            that will take care of themselves.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName> agreed that he would say
                            absolutely nothing to anyone concerning our meeting and I said it would
                            be discussed only with Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> at present.<note n="6" xml:id="d179fn6">In his
                                July 20 memorandum (see <ref target="#d179fn4">footnote 4</ref>
                                above), a copy of which was sent to the President, <persName corresp="#p_JUA1">U. Alexis Johnson</persName> outlined a
                                scenario for his next meeting with <persName corresp="#p_Khanh1">Khanh</persName>, scheduled for July 23, and for Sturmʼs first
                                two meetings (as yet unscheduled) with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName>. He concluded that if the
                                contact with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_Out1">Out</persName> turned
                                out to have some substance, a minimum objective was to obtain the
                                release of some American prisoners and the defection of some members
                                of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>, but that “a broad
                                political arrangement with the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss>,
                                which requires a radical shift in the personnel and orientation of
                                the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>,” presented “probably
                                insurmountable difficulties.”</note></p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_JUA1"><hi rend="strong">UAJ</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>