<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>278. Memorandum From the Chairman, Board of National Estimates (Kent) to
                    Director of Central Intelligence ) to Director of Central Intelligence
                    Helms</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d278</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">278</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-10-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-10-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recRlWb1NJm1Zsqf2" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recp5DsIbsvFElug7" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="rec7j7PIUiDj7gCN0" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recxRLdoJs9wm7rck" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99002408"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Press coverage</term>
                    <term ref="recPIvUgkPDriMVJj" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036673"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Demonstrations</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-10-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-10-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="278"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d278">
                <head>278. Memorandum From the Chairman, Board of National Estimates (<persName
                        type="from">Kent</persName>) to Director of Central Intelligence <persName
                        corresp="#p_HRM1" type="to">Helms</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d278fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                        Center, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 330, <gloss target="#t_OASD1"
                            >OASD</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ISA1">ISA</gloss> Files: <gloss
                            target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 70 A 6648, 350.09 Vietnam. Secret. In his
                        October 20 covering memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_HRM1"
                            >Helms</persName>, <persName>Kent</persName> stated that “on the whole,
                        we think the chances are better than even that the crisis will be
                        compromised in some fashion which will limit the damage and leave <persName
                            corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> about where he is.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-10-20">October 20, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Implications of the Current Cabinet Crisis in South Vietnam</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Situation</hi>. The current cabinet crisis derives from an
                        unfortunate meshing of two of the major divisive factors which have long
                        complicated political life in South Vietnam—regional rivalries and the issue
                        of civilian versus military control.<note n="2" xml:id="d278fn2">A third
                            major divisive influence is religion which is not yet openly involved in
                            the crisis; but should the crisis drag on, religious animosities and
                            political jockeying among the various religious groups could readily
                            come into play. [Footnote in the source text.]</note> It does not
                        represent a new development, but merely the first significant manifestation
                        of these fundamental maladies since the September elections. It will not be
                        the last.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The seven cabinet ministers (out of 29) who have proffered their
                        resignations are all of Southern (Cochinchinese) origin and are
                            civilians.<note n="3" xml:id="d278fn3">The exact status of these
                            ministers is unclear. <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> has said
                            that they have agreed to remain at their posts until after the Manila
                            Conference (24–26 October). Nonetheless, the resignation statements have
                            appeared in the press after the ministers supposedly agreed to stay on,
                            and the statements at least appear unequivocal. [Footnote in the source
                            text.]</note> They share the general Southern antipathy toward the
                        Northern “carpet-baggers” who dominate the <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName> government and the military establishment. They also
                        suspect that the military leadership will not fulfill its pledge for a
                        transition to a civilian government. The visits of various <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> leaders (in particular those of Police
                        Director, General <persName corresp="#p_NNL1">Nguyen Ngoc Loan</persName>)
                        to military-dominated South Korea adds fuel to Southern suspicions. With
                        this backdrop of traditional mistrust, the heavy-handed action by Loan, a
                        Northerner, in arresting an acting cabinet minister provided a
                        rallying-point for the Southern ministers. They began to pressure <persName
                            corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> and to charge that <persName
                            corresp="#p_Loan1">Loan</persName> was attempting to create a “police
                        state.” Moreover, the imminence of the Manila Conference gave them an
                        advantageous moment to bring pressure on <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName>. The ministers assumed that <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName> would be eager to avoid any political crisis before the
                        Conference, in particular one involving the issue of civilian-military
                        relations which the US considers crucial to the “other war” in
                        Vietnam.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>It is also likely that General <persName corresp="#p_DVQ1">Dang Van
                            Quang</persName> (IV Corps Commander) and perhaps General <persName
                            corresp="#p_NHC1">Nguyen Huu Co</persName> (Deputy Prime Minister and
                            <pb facs="0802" n="766" xml:id="pg_766"/> Minister of War) are involved
                        behind the scenes in the challenge to <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName>ʼs regime. Both men are Southerners. More important, they
                        have strong personal reasons to oppose <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName>: both men are prime candidates to be removed from their
                        posts for corruption.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In any event, <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName>, a Northerner
                        (Tonkinese) and a military man, is almost certainly the ultimate target of
                        the Southerners although the ministers have scrupulously avoided attacking
                        Ky personally. Instead they have aimed their attack at those close to
                            <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName>, particularly Loan, head of the
                        two principal security organizations; but also at General <persName>Le
                            Nguyen Khang</persName>, III Corps and Marine Commander; <persName
                            corresp="#p_BD1">Bui Diem</persName>, Secretary of State for Foreign
                        Affairs; and <persName>Dinh Trinh Chinh</persName>, Secretary of State to
                        the Prime Minister. These men are all Northerners. Because they command the
                        security forces in the Saigon area, <persName corresp="#p_Loan1"
                            >Loan</persName> and <persName>Khang</persName> provide much of the
                        physical protection for the <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> regime.
                        Should <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> be obliged to remove these
                        men, his power base and prestige would be seriously weakened.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The crisis has already done some damage to <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName>ʼs image. Regardless of the immediate outcome of the
                        crisis, <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> will go to Manila with his
                        domestic house in a state of some public disarray. There has already been
                        adverse foreign publicity on this score, and the heavy press coverage of the
                        proceedings in Manila will engender more. In South Vietnam, the crisis has
                        helped dim the glow left by the successful September election. It also has
                        publicly raised the issue of civilian-military conflict. This will have
                        reverberations in the Constituent Assembly where there is a sizeable and
                        vocal bloc of Southern delegates, the most notable and most vocal being
                            <persName>Tran Van Van</persName>, who may be working covertly with the
                        dissidents.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Implications</hi>. The crisis can almost certainly not be
                        resolved before the Manila Conference, and the best that can be looked for
                        is its deferral until after the Manila Conference. Such a deferral would put
                        the best face on an embarrassing problem at Manila and might allow things to
                        simmer down in Saigon. On previous occasions, <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName> has been adroit at fashioning compromises which have at
                        least temporarily tended to placate the contending elements. If no
                        compromise can be reached this time, or if <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName> is compelled to meet the problem head on, he has two
                        alternatives: 1) to accept the cabinet resignations, or 2) to sack or
                        substantially curb <persName corresp="#p_Loan1">Loan</persName>.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>If <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> does accept the resignations,
                        it would be a blow to civilian-military relations and would further
                        exacerbate regional rivalries. There would be a chorus of unfavorable
                        publicity in the foreign press. To lessen the impact of such a move,
                            <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> would probably try to replace
                        the ministers with other Southerners. He could probably do so, and this
                        would help. Nevertheless, there would be a new round of anti-<gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> statements, charges of “military
                        dictatorship”, and the like. Some of the firebrand Southerners in the
                        Assembly might resign in protest. In these <pb facs="0803" n="767"
                            xml:id="pg_767"/> circumstances, there might be some street
                        demonstrations and the militant Buddhists might strike up a temporary
                        alliance with some Catholic Southern elements.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>A move by <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> to drop <persName
                            corresp="#p_Loan1">Loan</persName> could cause more immediate and
                        serious problems. <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> realizes this and
                        has said that he will not fire <persName corresp="#p_Loan1">Loan</persName>,
                        though like all decisions in South Vietnam, this is probably not
                        irreversible. As director of the two major security organizations, <persName
                            corresp="#p_Loan1">Loan</persName> is a power in his own right.
                        Moreover, he is the foremost figure in the loose grouping of young,
                        hard-line officers collectively called the “Baby Turks.” <persName
                            corresp="#p_Loan1">Loan</persName>ʼs removal would raise the spectre of
                        renewed military factionalism which has not seriously plagued the <gloss
                            target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> since the removal of General <persName
                            corresp="#p_Thi1">Thi</persName> last spring. Moreover, <persName
                            corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> has confidence in Loan, who played a
                        major role in upholding the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> in its
                        recent victory over the militant Buddhists. In considering a move against
                            <persName corresp="#p_Loan1">Loan</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_Ky1"
                            >Ky</persName> would be aware that this would only temporarily appease
                        the opposition elements and only whet the Southernersʼ appetite for more
                        concessions. <persName corresp="#p_Loan1">Loan</persName>ʼs removal under
                        pressure would weaken <persName corresp="#p_Ky1">Ky</persName> in the eyes
                        of all concerned.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>On the whole, the best thing that could happen would be that the crisis
                        not come to a final head before Manila and that after Manila it can be
                        settled by a compromise or at least by a not overly disruptive showdown. The
                        worst that could happen would be a shattering of the unity among the
                        military. At present and for a long time to come, military support, and
                        probably predominance as well, is essential for any regime in South
                        Vietnam.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>For the Board of National Estimates:<lb/>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Sherman Kent</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
