<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-10-31T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-10-28T23:00:00-05:00" n="287" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d287">
                        <head>287. Report Prepared by the Joint Staff, Joint Chiefs of Staff<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d287fn1"><p>Source: Department of
                                    Defense, Records of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, 9155.3 (29 Oct
                                    66). Top Secret. Prepared by J–3, Directorate for Operations.
                                    Forwarded to <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName> by
                                        <persName corresp="#p_GLGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName> under
                                    cover of an October 31 memorandum, noting that the report was
                                    prepared in response to <persName corresp="#p_WGEG1">Wheeler</persName>ʼs request. A copy of the report is also
                                    at the Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File,
                                    Vietnam, box 193, Evaluation of the Effects of the Air
                                    Campaign.</p>
                                <p>In a November 7 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_GLGAJ1">Goodpaster</persName>, signed by General <persName>Robert
                                        Taylor</persName> for the Director of the Defense
                                    Intelligence Agency, <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss>
                                    commented on the report, noting that its judgments and
                                    statements “could be challenged by someone unwilling to depart
                                    from the relatively confined area of solid intelligence
                                    evidence,” but that, on the whole, <gloss target="#t_DIA1">DIA</gloss> was “inclined to accept the J–3 report as a
                                    reasonable analysis of the situation.” (Department of Defense,
                                    Records of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, 9155.3/3200 (<gloss target="#t_CY1">CY</gloss> 1966))</p></note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1966-10-31T23:59:59-05:00" notBefore="1966-10-29T00:00:00-04:00" when="1966-10">October
                                    1966</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">AN EVALUATION OF THE EFFECTS OF THE AIR CAMPAIGN AGAINST
                            NORTH VIETNAM AND LAOS</p>
                        <p>[Here follows a 2-page Summary.]</p>
                        <p rend="center">Discussion</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The war in Southeast Asia is a single conflict against an enemy
                                whose operations are integrated militarily, geographically and
                                politically, and therefore cannot properly be compartmentalized in
                                strategy or in evaluation of results. Combat operations of all
                                types, and in all areas, contribute to the eventual achievement of
                                US objectives in Southeast Asia. Thus, the results of the air
                                campaign against North Vietnam and the <pb facs="0826" n="790" xml:id="pg_790"/> infiltration routes through Laos, are directly
                                and decisively related to the success or failure of US/<gloss target="#t_FW1">FW</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                                operations in South Vietnam. Conversely, increasingly effective
                                combat operations in South Vietnam have a major influence upon North
                                Vietnamʼs capability and determination to support the insurgency.
                                (See Appendix A).<note n="2" xml:id="d287fn2">Appendices A–G are
                                    attached but not printed.</note></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>In early 1965, when the fortunes of the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> were at their lowest ebb, two important actions
                                were taken by the United States which have changed the course of the
                                war in Southeast Asia: the deployment of US combat troops; and the
                                initiation of the air campaign against North Vietnam. These two
                                actions were integral elements of a single strategy designed to
                                blunt the increasingly successful communist advance in South
                                Vietnam, and to seize the initiative from the Viet Cong/North
                                Vietnamese Army forces; eventually to cause the communists to cease
                                their aggression in South Vietnam; and finally, to assist that
                                country in its development as a viable, independent, non-communist
                                nation. It was understood at the time these critical actions were
                                taken, that US objectives would not be achieved in a short time,
                                even under optimum military conditions, and that the force build-up,
                                as well as the accumulation of the over-all impact of this military
                                effort upon the enemy, would take time. It became obvious also, as
                                indications of rapidly increasing support and participation by
                                    <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> were obtained, that the
                                successful implementation of US objectives in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>sia could not be achieved without
                                continued direct pressures against <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, unless the United States was prepared to provide a
                                major increase in the number of US ground troops already deployed or
                                programmed for deployment. (See Appendix B).</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>There is increasing evidence that US/<gloss target="#t_FW1">FW</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> combat units
                                have now successfully seized the initiative in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>. Recent past and current combat
                                results support this loss of initiative. This has been the combined
                                results of operations in <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>, and the Laos panhandle.
                                Increasingly effective combat operations in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> have aggressively searched out and attacked <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>
                                main units, destroyed their bases, constantly disrupted planned
                                schedules, and maintained continuously increasing military pressures
                                against them. (See Appendix C). At the same time, the air campaign
                                in <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> and the Laos panhandle has
                                destroyed significant amounts of materials and munitions, killed
                                numbers of troops moving south to the combat area, and disrupted
                                    <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>ʼs transportation and lines
                                of communication supporting this logistic flow. It has required the
                                enemy to divert substantial quantities of his manpower and skills
                                that are in short supply, and quantities of labor and materials have
                                been diverted because of the necessity to maintain and expand his
                                lines of communication. The lack of success thus far in enemy
                                attempts to <pb facs="0827" n="791" xml:id="pg_791"/> mount large
                                scale offensives has been due in large part to the disruption of his
                                main arteries of communication. (See Appendices D and E).</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The substantial activities in US ground, air, and naval forces in
                                    <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>sia is beginning to evidence
                                signs of positive results. Despite major military handicaps,
                                indications of some of the cumulative effects of US/<gloss target="#t_FW1">FW</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                                combat operations are now emerging. The <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> force build-up
                                has essentially leveled off, despite major attempts to infiltrate
                                and recruit larger numbers of military personnel; <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>
                                organized large scale military initiatives have dropped to a low
                                level; shortages of critical military supplies and morale problems
                                among <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss> units in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> are
                                beginning to surface; <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss> control of
                                population and area in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> is
                                decreasing; <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> support of combat
                                operations in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss> in terms of men
                                and resources has been degraded; <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>
                                has been denied a total sanctuary from which to export insurgency;
                                the life and economy of <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> has been
                                disrupted; morale in <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> has
                                suffered; national aspirations are being frustrated; large portions
                                of <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>ʼs population have been
                                displaced; <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>ʼs demands upon
                                communist nations for war-supporting equipment and materials has
                                increased substantially, and at the same time, its ability to
                                provide reimbursement has decreased; doubts are now emerging among
                                    <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> leaders as to their ability
                                to succeed in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>; major drains on
                                manpower resources have occurred; and a massive, well-coordinated
                                worldwide communist diplomatic and propaganda effort to pressure the
                                United States to cease bombings, whose scope and intensity testify
                                to the growing impact of the US combat operations, is in full
                                operation. (See Appendix F).</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>To decrease the current level of coordinated military pressures
                                against the enemy at the very time evidence of progress is beginning
                                to appear, would at a minimum, prolong the war significantly,
                                require substantial increases in US ground troops, and result in
                                greatly increased loss of US lives. It would also provide the
                                communists with new hope and new opportunities, postponing or
                                completely removing the necessity for any major strategy changes on
                                their part. It would forfeit the hard fought gains which have
                                already been achieved at significant cost in US lives and equipment,
                                and in the long run, could result in failure by the United States to
                                achieve its objectives in all of <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>sia. (See Appendix G).</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>It has been recent practice to attempt to evaluate the progress of
                                operations in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>sia by analyzing
                                known statistical results. The problems which are associated with
                                this approach are numerous and serious. It tends to separate the war
                                into separate compartments, ignoring the interrelationship of all
                                operations in support of a single strategy. Statistics on combat
                                results are unreliable at best, and in general, focus on small
                                segments of the over-all operations while overlooking the major
                                trends on which little or no data are available. In <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>sia good intelligence information on
                                the results of combat operations, particularly relative to their <pb facs="0828" n="792" xml:id="pg_792"/> overall impact upon the
                                enemy is minimal; and yet, this is the only kind of information
                                which really measures the true pulse of the enemy. Recognizable
                                indications of this kind of effect may not appear for months, or
                                perhaps years, after a military campaign has been initiated. The
                                history of past wars has repeatedly borne this out. Thus, the
                                current statistical analyses by which progress is judged have not
                                touched upon such matters as the depth of erosion of communist
                                stockpiles in <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss>, or the extent and nature of major
                                deficiencies in <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>ʼs war-supporting
                                capability. They do not indicate the extent of disruption and
                                upheaval within <gloss target="#t_NVN1">NVN</gloss>, nor the real
                                state of the morale of the North Vietnamese people. These analyses
                                have therefore not indicated the true value of the investment in
                                aircraft, munitions, and US lives that has been made to date.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>