<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>289. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d289</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">289</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1965-01-06T17:07:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-12-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recLLLyQwXdDuVMT6" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006000774"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Liberation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-12-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1965-01-06T17:07:00-05:00" n="289" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d289">
                <head>289. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>In telegram 10098 from Saigon, November 4, 1966, Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> advised the Department of State that the
                    scheme to secure the defection of National Liberation Front Chairman <persName
                        corresp="#p_NHT1">Nguyen Huu Tho</persName> by working through his purported
                    uncle, <persName corresp="#p_NHA1">Nguyen Huu An</persName>, was “largely based
                    on wishful thinking.” In forwarding the telegram to the Presidentʼs Special
                    Assistant, <persName corresp="#p_RWW1">Walt Rostow</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_MCA2">Arthur McCafferty</persName> of the White House Situation
                    Room noted in his covering memorandum that “in short, the <gloss
                        target="#t_Uncle1">uncle</gloss> is one of the best ‘fiction’ writers of our
                    time.” (Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Vietnam, box 143,
                        <gloss target="#t_Thrush1">Thrush</gloss>)</p>
                <pb facs="0833" n="797" xml:id="pg_797"/>
                <p>Two months earlier, <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> had notified the
                    Department that a promising operation had been launched to secure <persName
                        corresp="#p_NHT1">Nguyen Huu Tho</persName>ʼs defection and that other
                    high-level defections from the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> might follow;
                    see <ref target="#d204">Document 204</ref>. Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and Rostow followed the case closely, and
                    President <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName> was kept abreast of
                    developments; see <ref target="#d206">Documents 206</ref>, <ref target="#d214"
                        >214</ref>, <ref target="#d225">225</ref>, and <ref target="#d243">243</ref>
                    and the footnotes thereto. Additional information on White House and Department
                    of State interest in the operation is in the Johnson Library, National Security
                    File, Country File, Vietnam, box 143, <gloss target="#t_Thrush1">Thrush</gloss>,
                    and in Department of State, central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss>
                    30 VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_Thrush1"
                        >THRUSH</gloss>. Director of Central Intelligence <persName
                        corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName> was informed regularly about the
                    operation by his Special Assistant for Vietnamese Affairs, <persName
                        corresp="#p_CG1">George Carver</persName>, who wrote him at least 14
                    memoranda about <gloss target="#t_Thrush1">Thrush</gloss> from late September
                    through late October 1966. In an October 11 memorandum to <persName
                        corresp="#p_HRM1">Helms</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_CG1"
                        >Carver</persName> noted that Secretary of Defense <persName
                        corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, who arrived in Saigon on October 10,
                    had been briefed on <gloss target="#t_Thrush1">Thrush</gloss> and “seemed
                    pleased at the way things are being handled.” <persName corresp="#p_CG1"
                        >Carver</persName>’s memoranda are in the Central Intelligence Agency, GAC
                    Chron, Job 80–R01720R.</p>
                <p>In telegram 8635, October 17, <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName>
                    informed the Department of State of “unresolved discrepancies, inconsistencies
                    and apparent falsifications,” especially involving <persName corresp="#p_NHA1"
                        >Nguyen Huu An</persName>, which affected the substance of the defection
                    effort and called into question the honesty of the participants. A
                    “confrontation meeting” on November 3 between a <gloss target="#t_CIA1"
                        >CIA</gloss> representative and An, reported by <persName corresp="#p_LHC1"
                        >Lodge</persName> in telegram 7657, confirmed that An had “lied about all of
                    his activities during July and August.” An was still regarded as a potential
                    asset, <persName corresp="#p_LHC1">Lodge</persName> indicated, but given the
                    operation’s “metamorphosis into a longer term intelligence/defection effort,”
                    full control would be turned over to <gloss target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>
                    personnel. (Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1"
                        >POL</gloss> VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_Thrush1"
                        >THRUSH</gloss>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
