<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>347. Draft Paper Prepared by the Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian
                    and Pacific Affairs (Bundy)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d347</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">347</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiation</term>
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="budgets" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602" lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-12-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-12-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="347"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d347">
                <head>347. Draft Paper Prepared by the Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian
                    and Pacific Affairs (Bundy)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d347fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, Central Files, <gloss target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27
                        VIET <gloss target="#t_S1">S</gloss>. Top Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-12-21">December 21, 1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">1967 AND BEYOND IN VIETNAM</p>
                <p>The Rostow and Komer papers<note n="2" xml:id="d347fn2">Attachments to <ref
                            target="#d318">Documents 318</ref> and <ref target="#d319"
                        >319</ref>.</note> provide a basis for a very large area of agreement on the
                    action programs we should attempt to follow during 1967. These could be
                    summarized in a single action program, subject to the vital caveat of
                    maintaining flexibility at all times. Nonetheless, the general outlines of what
                    we want to do seem fairly clear.</p>
                <p>However, these two papers do not fully consider three inter-related factors that
                    must enter into our present thinking: <list>
                        <label>A.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">The prospect of the 1968 US elections and their impact
                                on our ability to maintain a prolonged struggle.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <label>B.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">The question of negotiation, including specifically
                                the possibility of attempting a direct “package deal” negotiation
                                with Hanoi—and above all the question any such deal would
                                necessarily raise of just what risks we might be prepared to assume
                                in connection with a <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>/<gloss
                                    target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> role in South Vietnam.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <label>C.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">The vital importance of developing a responsible and
                                effective <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>, and whether this
                                argues in some ways against certain types of US involvement and
                                action that might, in the short-term sense, appear to make
                                sense.</hi>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>These three factors are the subject of this memorandum. However, it must start
                    with a median prognosis of what we can hope to achieve by the end of 1967 and
                    mid-1968, when the impact of the US election will start to become really
                    acute.</p>
                <p>In brief, such a median prognosis, in our judgment, is not comforting. 1967 will
                    be slow going at best on the pacification front, as the <persName
                        corresp="#p_KRW1">Komer</persName> paper admits; however effectively we
                    organize the US side, <gloss target="#t_ARVN1">ARVN</gloss> will take time to do
                    a passable job of security for pacification, and the mainspring of <gloss
                        target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> government performance—already showing signs of
                    slowing down because of a pervading “caretaker” spirit—is most unlikely to have
                    shown really sharp improvement by the end of 1967 at least. The very existence
                    of a timetable for a new type of government is bound to create continuing
                    uncertainty, at least until late in the year, in the tenure and position of key
                    government and province officials on whom any real progress in pacification
                    ultimately depends. In short, even if the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>
                    and we both do the best we possibly can, the odds are on the whole against a
                    major strengthening of the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> position or a
                    true crack in <gloss target="#t_NVA1">NVA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_VC1"
                        >VC</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> morale during 1967. The
                    possibility of such a <pb facs="0999" n="963" xml:id="pg_963"/> morale break is
                    present, but its chances cannot be rated better than about one in three for
                    1967.</p>
                <p>We believe that it is against such a prognosis that we must weigh the three
                    factors stated above.</p>
                <p rend="center">A.</p>
                <p>We are not the proper experts to appraise just what the 1968 election campaign
                    would be like if the situation reaches that date without clearly evident signs
                    of major progress. On the merits, it seems unlikely that an opposing
                    candidate—be he Romney<note n="3" xml:id="d347fn3">George W. Romney, Governor of
                        Michigan and a Republican.</note> or anyone else—will be able to present the
                    American people with a clear and convincing alternative to the policy we will
                    have been pursuing. On the whole, we will probably see a Republican strategy of
                    trying to have it both ways—claiming that more might have been done (although
                    with emphasis on bombing the North alone probably rather muted), while at the
                    same time arguing that possibilities for peace have somehow been neglected and
                    that a Republican administration, as would be alleged of Korea, can find the
                    right handle of threatening greater force and thus bringing about peace.</p>
                <p>The point really may be much less what the Republican Party appears to offer than
                    the basic fact of a prolonged and diffuse national debate. Whether or not such a
                    debate brings the Republicans to power—however important in itself—may be
                    secondary to the effect of the debate alone in weakening and dividing Americans.
                    However the election comes out, a sharp deepening of the kind of malaise so
                    clearly evident in the 1966 Congressional election would leave any repeat any
                    newly elected administration in a much weaker position to carry the conflict
                    forward.</p>
                <p>Worst of all, this is almost certainly the way Hanoi would calculate it. In a
                    revealing remark only the other day, the North Vietnamese representative in
                    Paris said in effect that Hanoi had only to hang on through the 1968 elections,
                    and that only a Republican, or Conservative, administration could liquidate
                    “wars or empires.”<note n="4" xml:id="d347fn4">This remark by <persName
                            corresp="#p_MVBR1">Mai Van Bo</persName> has not been further
                        identified.</note> Apart from this being the way Hanoi would interpret a
                    possible Republican victory, they would almost certainly interpret a Democratic
                    victory, after a sharply divisive campaign, as indicating that we would weaken
                    in due course.</p>
                <p>In short, under the median prognosis given above, mid-1968 and beyond looks all
                    too likely to be a period when the US position will be substantially
                    weakened.</p>
                <pb facs="1000" n="964" xml:id="pg_964"/>
                <p rend="center">B.</p>
                <p>These thoughts alone must lead us to the question of seeking in the meantime, and
                    indeed as soon as possible, to find a negotiated answer. Yet we must reckon, at
                    the same time, that a negotiated “settlement” that involved major early risks of
                    Communist takeover—whether or not this had come about before the 1968
                    elections—would in itself virtually doom the Administration to defeat and might
                    well set off a wave of isolationist revulsion against all of our now-promising
                    efforts in the rest of East Asia. Thus, we are not talking at all about
                    “negotiation at any price” even from a domestic political standpoint.</p>
                <p>Yet, the need for seeking a negotiated solution is still acute, and we must
                    reckon that the bargaining factors may now be very close indeed to a situation
                    where both sides would see advantage in negotiation. A recent detached paper by
                    the Office of National Estimates<note n="5" xml:id="d347fn5">See <ref
                            target="#d328">Document 328</ref>.</note> points up the pressures and
                    difficulties not only in Hanoi but between Hanoi and Moscow and Peking. It
                    concludes flatly that for the first time in the last two years the present may
                    be a time in which the other side would be prepared to talk seriously about a
                    peaceful settlement falling well short of its maximum objectives.</p>
                <p>More specifically, whether the recent negotiating nibbles by third parties were
                    authorized by Hanoi or not, they most certainly indicate how very seriously the
                    Soviets and Eastern Europeans are working toward this end. They are very tough
                    indeed—and some of them are slippery—but in the last analysis they at least want
                    Vietnam to end and would accept, we can be reasonably sure, a return to the
                    Geneva status quo, albeit with some measures for protecting the lives and the
                    political role of present members of the <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and
                        <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>In short, the time is ripe. Moreover, the recent negotiating nibbles and the
                    views of such responsible third persons as Sainteny all point in the direction
                    of discussions being initiated on the basis of the outlines of a total
                    settlement, i.e., what we have called the “package deal.” The recent Cooper
                        paper<note n="6" xml:id="d347fn6">Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_CC1"
                            >Cooper</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KNB1">Katzenbach</persName>,
                        December 1, entitled “A Package Deal for Hanoi,” which was discussed at the
                        December 1 meeting of <persName corresp="#p_HWA1">Harriman</persName>ʼs
                        Negotiations Committee. (Department of State, Central Files, <gloss
                            target="#t_POL1">POL</gloss> 27–14 VIET)</note> comes very close indeed
                    to the kind of package we might try to work out, although it is very much open
                    to question whether we should table the whole thing as flatly as that paper
                    indicates, at the outset.</p>
                <p>From the standpoint of our over-all pattern of action, there is one clear
                    implication that must not be overlooked. If we are to pursue a serious
                    negotiating track on a “package deal” basis, we simply must accept that we will
                    not hit politically sensitive targets, and specifically the Hanoi <pb
                        facs="1001" n="965" xml:id="pg_965"/> and Haiphong areas, while we are
                    pursuing such a track. Whether or not the nibbles of November and December 1966
                    were actually author-ized, their present status has undoubtedly been
                    communicated to Hanoi with the conclusion that the US cannot be serious as long
                    as it even appears to escalate the bombing in this politically sensitive sense.
                    Moreover, there is rather more murky evidence from August of 1965 that Hanoi is
                    sensitive to apparent escalation. We have brought them to the point where they
                    may understand and accept continuation of the bombing at its present levels and
                    target patterns, but they simply will not enter into serious discussions if we
                    appear to be escalating, particularly during key periods of contact.</p>
                <p>The second major implication of seriously pursuing a negotiating track is that we
                    must face as nearly exactly as possible the risks that we are prepared to run of
                    an ultimate Communist takeover. Right from the beginning, and specifically in
                    the planning papers of 1964, our analysis in the Department—then regarded as
                    heretical by our military—was that there was a certain irreducible minimum
                    possibility of Communist takeover that could not be avoided in the best of
                    circumstances. The Manila commitment for withdrawal—and the practical reality
                    behind that commitment that we simply cannot effectively occupy South Vietnam
                    for any long period—simply underscore that at some point we have to accept, say,
                    a 20% chance that the South Vietnam we leave behind will so mismanage its
                    affairs that it will eventually fall prey to the highly disciplined <gloss
                        target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_VC1">VC</gloss>
                    organization, even if the latter is then receiving only the most covert
                    assistance from the North.</p>
                <p>The issue is whether we should be prepared to accept a settlement that increases
                    the irreducible 20% to perhaps 30%, or more. As of now, a guaranteed
                    institutional <gloss target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> role in the government appears
                    to raise the risk to something on the order of 60 to 70%, and we would now
                    reject it as unacceptable. But, short of this point, the question of safeguards
                    at successive stages, and possibly the question of accepting <gloss
                        target="#t_NLF1">NLF</gloss> individuals into the political structure at a
                    senior level, raise these marginal issues of acceptability that might turn out
                    to be the very crux of getting an agreement.</p>
                <p>This paper does not assess exactly what concessions we might make that involve
                    these greater degrees of risk. But it does flag the vital importance of our
                    looking hard at this issue, as indeed we are doing in the analysis of the Cooper
                    proposal.</p>
                <p rend="center">C.</p>
                <p>Finally, there is the question of building up the <gloss target="#t_GVN1"
                        >GVN</gloss>. All of us, in mid-1965, foresaw a danger that a massive
                    American presence would simply smother the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss>,
                    and inhibit the very development of responsibility and effectiveness that is the
                    object of the whole exercise. To some <pb facs="1002" n="966" xml:id="pg_966"/>
                    degree, this has plainly already been the case, and continued massive infusions
                    on the US side, or especially the US taking over where it does not absolutely
                    have to (as it may on the economic front), will simply deepen the problem. The
                    marginal issues in the assessment of our action programs for 1967 must be
                    weighed heavily from the standpoint of this intangible factor, and not merely on
                    the basis of such clear and concrete inhibiting elements as the piaster budget
                    ceiling (although we think our conclusions from the latter have been wise).</p>
                <p>The point—and a most difficult one—is that, unless an added US element really
                    changes the prognosis very markedly, we should be leery of such added elements
                    wherever possible. This might be true in any event and on any timetable of the
                        <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> being on its own. But it is particularly
                    acute if we visualize a serious effort to work out some negotiated arrangement
                    that puts the <gloss target="#t_GVN1">GVN</gloss> in this position by
                    mid-1968.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
