<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>354. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d354</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">354</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-12-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-12-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnJ2K6wD5ESYqK6" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015470"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Bombing</term>
                    <term ref="recAwQiQEe2SLmG4S" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015464"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Missile</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-12-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-12-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="354"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d354">
                <head>354. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d354fn1"
                        >Source: Johnson Library, National Security File, Country File, Vietnam, box
                        147, <gloss target="#t_Marigold1">Marigold</gloss> II. Top Secret; <gloss
                            target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>; <gloss target="#t_Marigold1"
                            >Marigold</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_TLE1"
                            >Thompson</persName> and approved in S/AL. Printed in part in Herring,
                            <hi rend="italic">Secret Diplomacy of the Vietnam War</hi>, pp.
                        321–322.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1966-12-30">December 30,
                            1966</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBEJCT</head>
                    <item>Reply to Presidentʼs Letter to <persName corresp="#p_KAN1"
                            >Kosygin</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Anatoliy F. Dobrynin</persName>,
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_TLE1">Llewellyn E. Thompson</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>I asked the Ambassador if he had brought back any reply to the Presidentʼs letter
                    to <persName corresp="#p_KAN1">Kosygin</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d354fn2">
                        <ref target="#d330">Document 330</ref>.</note> He replied that if he could
                    speak completely off the record he could tell me that a reply had nearly been
                    completed and that it was one we would have liked but then the bombing of Hanoi
                    had occurred and this draft had been torn up and another one of quite a
                    different <pb facs="1018" n="982" xml:id="pg_982"/> character started. He said
                    he had seen the report from their Embassy in Hanoi and that there was no doubt
                    in the Soviet minds as a result of this report that our bombs had fallen on
                    Hanoi itself. He said his own recommendation had been that in view of this
                    change of circumstance, it was better for the Soviet Government not to reply
                    immediately but he said that a reply would be made in due course.</p>
                <p>I said I could tell him categorically that it was not our intention to bomb the
                    civilian areas of Hanoi and we were sure that some <gloss target="#t_SAM1"
                        >SAM</gloss>s had fallen on the city. I said that one of the targets was so
                    situated that our planes came over the city after dropping their bombs and it
                    was always possible that one of the bombs had been hung up and subject to a
                    delayed release. The Ambassador remarked that even if a <gloss target="#t_SAM1"
                        >SAM</gloss> missile had landed in the city it would not have left the kind
                    of crater that had been caused there.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador referred to our conversation with the Poles and asked if anything
                    new had developed. I inquired whether he was aware of our action in stating we
                    had stopped bombing within a certain radius of Hanoi. He said he was. I said
                    that our Ambassador in Warsaw had an appointment with the Foreign Minister but I
                    did not know yet what had transpired.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador remarked that the initial stages of this affair had given the
                    Soviet Government considerable hope and he said rather cryptically that they had
                    other reasons for some optimism but that our action in bombing Hanoi had spoiled
                    everything. I pointed out that our targets were selected several weeks in
                    advance and that it had been pure coincidence that the attacks on the targets
                    near Hanoi had occurred at this time.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador said that his Government was frankly baffled by our actions in
                    Viet-Nam and did not know how to judge our policy. He said there were many, and
                    he was one of them, that wondered whether some of our military were deliberately
                    trying to frustrate a policy of moving toward negotiations or whether our policy
                    really was one of military victory.</p>
                <p>I said that I could assure him that we were genuinely interested in negotiations
                    and that although there were some who felt that we should take a stronger
                    action, this was not a question of military officers disobeying orders.</p>
                <p>Toward the end of our conversation, which covered other subjects, the Ambassador
                    asked if I thought there was real hope of getting the Viet-Namese affair settled
                    during the coming year. I said that I was personally hopeful, although the
                    difficulties were obvious. He remarked that perhaps during my stay in Moscow I
                    would be able to have contact with a certain Ambassador, obviously meaning the
                    North Viet-Namese.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
