<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>72. Telephone Conversation Between President Johnson and the Deputy Under
                    Secretary of State for Political Affairs ( and the Deputy Under Secretary of
                    State for Political Affairs (Johnson))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1964-68v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">72</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1966-02-11T09:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1966-02-11T09:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAsWFxRUa5DhtTM" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133456"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Television</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1966-02-11T09:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1966-02-11T09:00:00-05:00" n="72"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d72">
                <head>72. Telephone Conversation Between President <persName type="from"
                        >Johnson</persName> and the Deputy Under Secretary of State for Political
                    Affairs (<persName type="to">Johnson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d72fn1">Source: <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Johnson</persName>
                        Library, Recordings and Transcripts, Recording of Telephone Conversation
                        between Johnson and <persName corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName>, Tape
                        F66.05, Side A, PNO 1. No classification marking. This transcript was
                        prepared by the Office of the Historian specifically for this volume.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1966-02-11T09:00:00-05:00">February 11, 1966, 9 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of a telegram from <persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                        Bundy</persName> concerning the U.S. Mission in Vietnam.]</p>
                <p>LBJ: I would wish that you would put the best lawyer—this <persName
                        corresp="#p_MLC1">Meeker</persName>ʼs been spending his time over here
                    worrying about whatʼs gonna to happen to the Visa Division. I wish that heʼd get
                    busy on something substantive like analyzing the testimony as a lawyer and
                    making the basic points that <persName corresp="#p_GLGJM1">Gavin</persName> made
                    and that <persName corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan</persName> made.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d72fn2">See <ref target="#d64">Document 64</ref>.</note> And they
                    both seem to be unaware that we have a treaty<note n="3" xml:id="d72fn3"
                        >Reference is to the Southeast Asia Collective Defense Treaty, September 8,
                        1954; for text, see 6 UST 81–86. The treaty established the Southeast Asia
                        Treaty Organization.</note> at all or that we have a resolution<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d72fn4">Reference is to the Tonkin Gulf Resolution, Joint Resolution
                        1145, “To Promote the Maintenance of International Peace and Security in
                        Southeast Asia,” passed by the Senate and the House on August 7, 1964, and
                        signed by the President on August 10, 1964. For text, see <hi rend="italic"
                            >American Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1964</hi>, pp.
                        991–992.</note> at all or that we have a commitment at all. And they both
                    would just rather not be troubled with Asia. And theyʼd just like to be content
                    in Honolulu if somebody would leave them alone.</p>
                <p>UAJ: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>LBJ: And I would like for <persName corresp="#p_MLC1">Meeker</persName> or some
                    real expert to prepare for me forthwith today or tomorrow at the minimum,
                    first—I asked for it yesterday—the shifting positions on the loyal
                    opposition.</p>
                <p>UAJ: Yes, Bill Bundyʼs doing that.</p>
                <p>LBJ: Then second, I want somebody to analyze the opposition testimony and just
                    take their whole thing and say, “Now hereʼs what a lawyer would brief it as and
                    a rejoinder—hereʼs what they have said.” And take the toughest things theyʼve
                    said and say, “Now here is the answer to ʼem as we see it.” And I would sure see
                    that somebody follows these television things very, very carefully. I doubt that
                    anybody with any political sensitivity in the State Departmentʼs doing that. Do
                    you know?</p>
                <p>UAJ: I donʼt know if anybodyʼs looking at the television, weʼre getting the
                    transcripts.</p>
                <p>LBJ: Well now, itʼs very important to watch that and watch the hearing, watch the
                    reaction to it and what the folks are doing and things like <pb facs="0257"
                        n="221" xml:id="pg_221"/> that. [Senator Frank] Church takes the position
                    that we are [in a] very dangerous position and that weʼve got to surrender.
                    Thatʼs his position this morning on the “Today” show, Frank Church.</p>
                <p>UAJ: Oh, he was on this morning?</p>
                <p>LBJ: Yeah and rather effective. Theyʼre doing a real job each day now. I donʼt
                    think that, when you analyze, if they [were] ever answered—I think itʼd just go
                    over like a puff of wind can blow ʼem over. Everything that he said can be just
                    answered in one sentence [which] is that we have a <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss> treaty and Senator would you ignore it?</p>
                <p>UAJ: Yes, yes, yes.</p>
                <p>LBJ: And if so, how and what do you do about it? And what effect does it have on
                    the world? And he acts like he never heard of it. I think that also somebody
                    ought to brief that <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Treaty for me. So
                    letʼs get about three things for the President and get some staff officers busy
                    doing that instead of interviewing the press. First thing Iʼd have ʼem do is
                    give me the shifting positions. The second thing Iʼd do is have ʼem take the
                    position of <persName corresp="#p_GLGJM1">Gavin</persName> and the position of
                    this guy [<persName corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan</persName> ?] and answer ʼem. And
                    the third thing Iʼd like for ʼem to do is brief the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss> Treaty hearings, particularly for any comments of members,
                    who are now members of that, with quotes.<note n="5" xml:id="d72fn5">The
                        Department of Stateʼs 18-page memorandum, February 11, responding to this
                        request was forwarded to the President by <persName corresp="#p_SBK1"
                            >Bromley Smith</persName> on February 12. (Johnson Library, National
                        Security File, Memos to the President—<persName corresp="#p_BMG1">McGeorge
                            Bundy</persName>, vol. 20)</note> And particularly people like <persName
                        corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SJJ1"
                        >Sparkman</persName> and folks who apparently were members of the committee
                    at the time it was adopted. And along with that Iʼd like to have a good brief of
                    the resolution and what they said about the resolution. I would gather that
                    weʼre getting—if weʼre not, we ought to get—a brief that <persName
                        corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> or somebody can put in the record on our
                    legal position. And I think our legal position ought to be that the Commander in
                    Chief has a right to respond when his forces are attacked and that the Commander
                    in Chief powers—weʼve taken that position all along. But then we got the treaty
                    commitment, then we got the resolution specifically. And we ought to have that
                    legal position ready to put in the record. But in developing that, I want to see
                    what <persName corresp="#p_FJW1">Fulbright</persName> said when <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> was up. I want to see if he ever asked a
                    question or answered one. I want to see what questions he asked and what he
                    answered and what he said on the floor of the Senate when the resolution was
                    up.</p>
                <p>UAJ: We started work on that yesterday.</p>
                <p>LBJ: And I think that you ought to have the most astute politician youʼve got in
                    the Department watching this thing very, very carefully. Theyʼre out to destroy
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> and destroy the Department and
                    destroy our position. And theyʼre taking the position that what theyʼre doing is
                    going to change the foreign policy of this country. Now I donʼt know how <pb
                        facs="0258" n="222" xml:id="pg_222"/> theyʼre gonna change this treaty or
                    change this resolution. But <persName corresp="#p_GA1">Gore</persName> says that
                    we are going over the Presidentʼs head to the people, that the President has
                    gone over the Senateʼs head to declare war without our declaration.</p>
                <p>UAJ: I saw him on that yesterday.</p>
                <p>LBJ: Weʼre going over the Presidentʼs head, too.</p>
                <p>UAJ: Yes, yes.</p>
                <p>LBJ: Now, thatʼs what theyʼre doing and I think that weʼve got to take a little
                    time and develop this position. First, I think weʼve got to develop it pretty
                    clearly in <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName>ʼs statement.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d72fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD1">Rusk</persName> testified before the Senate
                        Foreign Relations Committee on February 18; see <ref target="#d64">Document
                            64</ref>.</note> And before he goes heʼs gonna have to background people
                    on what heʼs going to say. Heʼs gonna have to summarize what <persName
                        corresp="#p_KGF1">Kennan</persName> said and what <persName
                        corresp="#p_GLGJM1">Gavin</persName> said. “Now this is the substance of
                    what these two men have said and here are the transcripts, if you want ʼem, of
                    what theyʼve said. Now hereʼs the answer to ʼem” and let ʼem have their stuff
                    before they go up there. And when he goes in he ought to give ʼem copies of his
                    statement so they can really write because, by and large, these writers up there
                    are unfriendly to our position.</p>
                <p>UAJ: Yes they are.</p>
                <p>LBJ: The infiltration in the networks and in the press on this is rather serious,
                    I think, and I think itʼs more serious than any of us realize.</p>
                <p>UAJ: Yes, yes. Wonder about motives on some of this.</p>
                <p>LBJ: Yes, I think thereʼs no question but what [<hi rend="italic">1 minute 58
                        seconds deleted by the <persName corresp="#p_JLB1">Lyndon B.
                            Johnson</persName> Library under the donorʼs instrument of gift</hi>]. I
                    think that they think—the opposition to our system—that theyʼre gonna win this
                    thing right here in Washington.</p>
                <p>UAJ: Yes, yes. I feel that very deeply, Mr. President, as I told you yesterday.
                    Thatʼs what theyʼre betting on.</p>
                <p>LBJ: Well now, do you think weʼve got our first team out working on it?</p>
                <p>UAJ: I do sir. Dean got some of these assignments made yesterday. He was already
                    working on this.</p>
                <p>LBJ: Thatʼs sure what I want done.</p>
                <p>UAJ: I think that heʼs gonna be well prepared to handle them, insofar as they can
                    be handled.</p>
                <p>[Here follows further discussion of Vietnam.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
