<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>96. Notes of a Meeting</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1950-55Intel</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d96</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">96</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-12-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                    <term ref="rece0CacX1xkHTAHw" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="covert-actions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139574"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Covert operations</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-12-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-12-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="96"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d96">
                <head>96. Notes of a Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d96fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, RG 59, S/P Files: Lot 64 D 563, Political and
                        Psychological Warfare. Top Secret. Drafted by <persName>Phillip H.
                            Watts</persName>, Executive Secretary of the Policy Planning
                        Staff.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-12-05"
                        >December 5, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Psychological Strategy Board</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PRESENT</head>
                    <item>S/P—</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Ferguson</persName> (part)</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SC1">Savage</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Koch</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MGGC1">Marshall</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Miss <persName>Fosdick</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Tufts</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Stelle</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Villard</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Watts</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss>—<persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral
                            Stevens</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss>—Mr. <persName>Philbin</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>C—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> (part)</item>
                    <item>P—Mr. <persName>Phillips</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>P—Mr. <persName>Schwinn</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_R1">R</gloss>—Mr. <persName>Trezise</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>S—Mr. <persName>Compton</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> opened the meeting by
                    saying he was chairman of a small group in <gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss>
                    charged with “formulating a national strategic concept for psychological action”
                    as called for in the directive establishing the <gloss target="#t_PSB1"
                        >PSB</gloss> and as envisioned in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 59/1
                    and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 10/2 which include both covert and overt
                    propaganda activities.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> said he thought the covert and
                    overt activities should be kept separate.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> said that people were
                    worried today because they felt that our foreign policy was “gone at
                    piecemeal—on a hand to mouth basis” with no over-all strategic concept. A
                    strategic concept, he said was a “point of view—a tentative plan of action,
                    always under review but not rigid” and he thought that such a concept or plan
                    should be put down on paper, difficult as it might be to do.</p>
                <p>A discussion ensued about the difficulties of getting “everything down” in <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> papers and the danger of parts being lifted out
                    of context to fit particular situations.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> said that, at present,
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> papers are the only approved guides to
                    national policy and cited the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> paper on the
                        <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> in which the policy of reducing
                    the threat of Soviet power and <pb facs="0255" n="226" xml:id="pg_226"/>
                    influence is set forth. How far, he asked, do you have to reduce the power and
                    influence to have meaning. The fomenting of revolution within the <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> is to be treated separately because the
                    U.S. is not prepared for such an undertaking and would have no assurance of
                    success, but in order to form an over-all concept it has to be considered.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> referred to the <gloss
                        target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss> paper dated 15 November, entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">National Psychological Strategy</hi>,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d96fn2">A copy is in National Archives, RG 59, Central Files
                        1950–54, 100.4–<gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss>/5–1551.</note> which had
                    been sent to the Department informally the previous week. He said it was only a
                    working draft intended to evince reactions from State and <gloss
                        target="#t_CIA1">CIA</gloss>. What he’d like, would be to have <persName
                        corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NPH1"
                        >Nitze</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JRP1">Joyce</persName> and
                        <persName corresp="#p_WFG1">Wisner</persName> get together and see if they
                    couldn’t come up with a “central strategic concept.”</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> suggested that perhaps it would
                    be better to start at the narrowest part of the problem, i.e. how to reduce the
                    threat of Soviet power and influence.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> said that the <gloss
                        target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss> draft was an attempt to outline the steps
                    necessary to create a central strategic concept and that <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 10/5<note n="3" xml:id="d96fn3">
                        <ref target="#d90">Document 90</ref>.</note> was a “holding operation” which
                    he defined as “placing the maximum strain on the Soviet structure of power.”</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> pointed out that “maximum
                    strain” were meaningless words—that we should get down to the concrete.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> returned to the <gloss
                        target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss> draft and said that what State had been asked
                    for was (a) its point of view about creating revolutions in the satellites, (b)
                    what political actions would be undertaken for the holding operation set forth
                    in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 10/5, and (c) what could be accomplished
                    by other actions including propaganda controlled by State.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> again urged that we take a
                    concrete problem such as the retraction and reduction of Soviet power and
                    influence. This is <hi rend="italic">one</hi> policy objective of the U.S.
                    Government but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> the sum total of U.S. policy—there are
                    a whole hierarchy of objectives. It would be fine if Soviet power would retract
                    but as you get down to accomplishing this you get into many complex problems.
                    Stimulating a revolution in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> is not
                    now a current practical objective.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> said a statement to
                    this effect should be put out and approved by the <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss> needs this kind of a
                    statement as part of a central concept.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> said there is no single policy
                    but a multiplicity of policies like the multiplicity of dots which make the
                    whole image on a radarscope. He said he wasn’t clear how a central concept would
                    be helpful—we should look at specific areas—Albania, for example. There <pb
                        facs="0256" n="227" xml:id="pg_227"/> are many serious complications which
                    flow from creating a revolution in any satellite country.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> said he felt that we should
                    develop our capabilities in the covert field as far as possible. We should move
                    up in successive first approximations on an area by area, technique by technique
                    basis.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> agreed with the area
                    by area approach and said that <gloss target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss> must then
                    come in with what it is capable of doing. He said he realized that a central
                    concept wouldn’t solve all our problems but that we ought to try to put one down
                    on paper.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> suggested that it might be
                    possible to take specific areas such as East Germany, Poland, Czechoslovakia,
                    etc., and assuming that we had certain covert action capabilities, take a look
                    at what the political implications of such actions would be. At the same time we
                    might select certain areas and assuming the existence of favorable political
                    factors have <gloss target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss> determine what their covert
                    capabilities were. Then the two determinations might be married.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> said he worried about
                    theoretical situations. Where there existed a clear problem with concrete
                    possibilities of accomplishing something, this approach might be OK, but taking
                    a series of hypothetical situations and trying to see through all the branching
                    implications and reactions would be a negative exercise.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> said that some of the
                    fringe areas around the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> are vulnerable
                    and we should look carefully to see what can be done. He said <gloss
                        target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss> was capable of carrying out several
                    simultaneous operations if it seemed desirable to do so.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BCE1">Bohlen</persName> said that <persName
                        corresp="#p_WFG1">Wisner</persName> needs to know the general direction in
                    which we want to proceed so that he can <persName corresp="#p_LJSJ1"
                        >lay</persName> out his plans and have his agents prepared. Therefore, we
                    should take a look at individual areas.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> said it still gets
                    back to a central strategic concept. Put down on paper that we don’t want to
                    create a revolution in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> as well as
                    some of the “lesser things” we do want to do. It will just be an approximation
                    to be used as guidelines for <gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss> and <gloss
                        target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> again emphasized the difficulty
                    of setting forth general principles until you get down to specific problems.
                    There is always the danger that people will think that by having broad
                    principles lots of specific problems will be solved.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> said he still thought
                    that we’d make the biggest advance if State would undertake to respond to the
                    request in the <gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss> paper.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> said he thought that joint work
                    with <gloss target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss>
                    was called for so that everyone would be clear on the dimensions of the <pb
                        facs="0257" n="228" xml:id="pg_228"/> problem and just what was to be
                    accomplished. He suggested that we address ourselves to the specific question of
                    the retraction and reduction of Soviet power and influence. He said he could
                    envisage a paper broken down somewhat as follows: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>Reduction and retraction of Soviet power to acceptable proportions
                            over a 10-year period.</item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Any thought of revolution in the <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                                >U.S.S.R.</gloss> must come at the end of the 10-year period.</item>
                        <label>c.</label>
                        <item>Reduction of Soviet power in the Satellites in the near term.</item>
                        <label>d.</label>
                        <item>The development of techniques to accomplish a, b, and c.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>This is a first approximation and should be kept under continuing review.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> said he would like to
                    have a “good” State Department man sit with his committee to coordinate the
                    responses to the <gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss> paper.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> replied that taking responses
                    and putting them together wouldn’t work—what was needed was joint work by State,
                        <gloss target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_PSB1"
                    >PSB</gloss>.</p>
                <p>There followed an inconclusive discussion of the term “psychological strategy”,
                    during which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> pointed out the
                    dangers involved in trying to marry propaganda and covert operations. They
                    should be kept separate and made concrete and definable.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SVARLC1">Admiral Stevens</persName> returned to the <gloss
                        target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss> paper and asked if State could put anything on
                    paper which would be helpful—could it, for instance, redraft the three requests
                    made of it?</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName> said he considered the framework
                    of the paper wrong. It appeared that the retraction and reduction of Soviet
                    power and influence was the “be all” and “end all” of our policy. If this phase
                    of our policy could be taken as a specific problem and so addressed, he thought
                    we could come up with something useful. He ended the meeting by saying that we
                    would get together with someone from <gloss target="#t_OPC1">OPC</gloss> and
                        <gloss target="#t_PSB1">PSB</gloss> and try to map out a course of
                    action.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
