<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-04-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-04-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="213" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d213">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">814.00/300</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Guatemala</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Thurston</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-04-07"><hi rend="italic">April 7,
                                        1919</hi></date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received April
                                        21.</hi>]</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 754</seg>
                                <lb/>
                                <seg rendition="#left">Strictly confidential</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                                receipt of the Department’s instruction number 294 [<hi rend="italic">unnumbered</hi>], dated February 14, 1919,<note n="1" xml:id="d213fn1">Not printed.</note> stating that inasmuch
                                as it appears that the health of President Manuel Estrada Cabrera is
                                not good, the Department believes that a thorough study should
                                be-made of the conditions which are likely to exist in Guatemala
                                upon his death. …</p>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                            <p>Thus there exist in Guatemala two utterly conflicting elements: that
                                of the present and contemplated future dictatorship—and that of an
                                awakening people who demand emancipation from the intolerable burden
                                of such a dictatorship.</p>
                            <p>It is but reasonable to foresee, then, that this latter element will
                                attempt to achieve its aims at the first definite sign of the end of
                                Estrada Cabrera’s régime—and it is equally reasonable to assume that
                                those whose fortunes depend upon the continuance of such a regime
                                will violently oppose the change of system. I have already heard, in
                                fact, that a group of the President’s staff generals have formed a
                                pact to support with their troops the man among them chosen by the
                                President as his successor.</p>
                            <p>The inevitable result of such a situation will be civil war. The
                                reality of the awakening I have just referred to is demonstrated by
                                the accompanying Open Letters to President Cabrera, the first of
                                which is signed by Señor Manuel Cobos Batres and the second by
                                Bishop José Piñol y Batres.<note n="2" xml:id="d213fn2">Letters not
                                    printed.</note> Señor M. C. Batres, while not a prominent
                                citizen, seems to have placed his signature to this letter more to
                                encourage the people than to show any personal leadership—for <pb facs="0349" n="264" xml:id="pg_264"/> by doing so he risks his
                                life. Bishop Piñol is generally stated to be one of the highest type
                                of Guatemalans in the country, and the most influential member of
                                the Catholic Church. He has prepared a call to all Catholics in
                                Guatemala to rally to the support of Mr. Cobos Batres proposals, and
                                voice their approval by every pacific means within their power, a
                                translation of which will be sent by the next pouch.<note n="3" xml:id="d213fn3">Not printed.</note></p>
                            <p>While neither of these letters have, as yet, been submitted to
                                President Cabrera, nor made public, I have every reason to believe
                                they will be before the present Legislative Assembly adjourns, which
                                will be about April 15th.</p>
                            <p>If so, and if President Cabrera attempts to suppress the activities
                                of this embryo political party, a dangerous situation is very likely
                                to arise; if they are not presented, the matter will be postponed
                                but a short time.</p>
                            <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Walter C.
                                Thurston</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>