<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Minister in Cuba ( (Gonzales) ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">25</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recwCJKUNlNbGDoDy" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh93002779"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Judiciary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-07-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="25"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d25">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">837.00/1563</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Minister in Cuba</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gonzales</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-07-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 1, 1919</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received July 19.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: For the Department’s information, in accordance
                    with circular instruction dated February 19, 1918,<note n="18" xml:id="d25fn18"
                        >Not printed.</note> I have the honor to transmit, herewith, Quarterly
                    Report No. 2, giving a general outline of conditions here for the second quarter
                    of the current year. This report was prepared by Secretary Williamson.</p>
                <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">William E. Gonzales</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0112" n="27" xml:id="pg_27"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Extract]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Report of the American Legation in Cuba</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Habana</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-07-01">
                                <hi rend="italic">July 1, 1919</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">1. POLITICAL INFORMATION</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Domestic</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>(1) On May 10th the National Convention of the Liberal Party met in Habana
                        for the purpose of nominating candidates for the elections of November 1920.
                        Upon General José Miguel Gomez fell the choice for President while Doctor
                        Zayas was named for the Vice-Presidency. The vote was 83 to 8, the
                        preponderance in favor of General Gomez being enlarged by the fact that all
                        but three Zayas members absented themselves from the meeting. Although the
                        Convention was called at the behest of Doctor Zayas in April, he later
                        attempted to prevent its gathering at this time, and in fact issued
                        instructions to his supporters not to attend. He was apparently cognizant of
                        the fact that under present conditions he could not hope to secure the
                        nomination for the Presidency, and was unwilling to fill the place of
                        secondary importance. This hypothesis was borne out the next day when Doctor
                        Zayas refused to accept the candidacy for Vice President. The split between
                        the two rivals is now so broad that it will be difficult to procure any sort
                        of amalgamation between Miguelistas and Zayistas, and the possibility of the
                        two leaders appearing on the same ticket is even more remote.</p>
                    <p>The Liberal Party held its Convention in spite of the agreement, which it
                        could hardly have been unaware existed, between General Crowder and the
                        Joint Congressional Committee which would invalidate tickets nominated
                        before the calendar year of the elections. Although the Conservatives were
                        to hold their party convention in May, Doctor Rafael Montalvo, whom it was
                        expected they would nominate, requested his supporters to discontinue their
                        political agitation for the time. Through his advocacy of the step the
                        gathering was postponed until, it is to be assumed, 1920. Both parties to
                        all appearances are now reconciled to waiting, notwithstanding such sporadic
                        movements as the launching by the friends of General Emilio Nunez a short
                        while ago of a quiet campaign in his behalf.</p>
                    <p>The resignation of Doctor Patterson, the Sub-secretary of State, was a
                        disappointment to the Diplomatic Corps, as he was always deemed capable and
                        showed a marked disposition to cooperate with <pb facs="0113" n="28"
                            xml:id="pg_28"/> the foreign representatives on any subject which
                        contained a common meeting point. His resignation is thought to be caused by
                        disagreement over certain appointments.</p>
                    <p>In the light of Cuba’s larger political history the work of General Crowder
                        and his staff cannot fail to be regarded as epoch making. With the task
                        nearing its completion a brief indication of the lines it has followed would
                        not be inappropriate as a matter of record. The original undertaking for
                        which the General came to Cuba, the Electoral Law, is still before the Joint
                        Congressional Commission. Constructive and helpful criticism by that body is
                        aiding the army staff in the final polishing of the law which has as its
                        primary motive the providing of an active electoral register and the
                        establishment of a system of honest elections. The Law should very shortly
                        be ready for presentation to Congress as it has the hearty approval of the
                        Committee.</p>
                    <p>The Ortiz Census Bill, in the amended form which General Crowder has drafted,
                        provides for a Cuban Director and Sub-Director to be selected by the
                        President from a list submitted by a National Board. The method of procedure
                        of appointment as nearly as possible precludes “politics”. To insure the
                        efficient administration of its functions, the census machinery is to be
                        guided by an American Advisor and six technical experts from the United
                        States. This Bill has passed the House and in its original form the Senate,
                        so that when the thirty days suspension of the Constitutional Guarantees has
                        elapsed on the 11th of July it will go before the President with no obstacle
                        to prevent its becoming law immediately. In this connection it is
                        interesting to note that on the assumption of the bill’s inclusion in the
                        statutes and with the entire approval of President Menocal, Major Harold E.
                        Stephenson has quietly opened offices and in the capacity of advisor has so
                        far perfected the plans and arrangements that the actual work of taking the
                        census may be initiated the moment the law receives its final signature.</p>
                    <p>General Crowder regards two amendments to the Judiciary Code as of almost
                        equal importance to the larger work of his office. These alterations in the
                        code as it now stands would first of all put Municipal Judges into the
                        category of judges of career, an obviously important step, the more so now
                        that under the new Electoral Law they are to be the tribunal before which
                        election disputes are to be brought. Secondly the appointment of the
                        municipal judiciary is to be safeguarded against political influence.</p>
                    <p rend="center">. . . . . . .</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
