<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Morris) ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d414</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">414</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-04-05T10:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-04-05T10:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="reciVXr89C8BltUky" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="neutrality"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85091195"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Neutrality</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-04-05T10:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-04-05T10:00:00-05:00" n="414"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d414">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">395.116/99: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Morris</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-04-06T00:00:00+09:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 6, 1919, midnight</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received April 7, 10.25
                        a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>I received last night the following telegram from Consul General at Seoul: April
                    5, 12 noon, Eli Miller Mowry, American of Presbyterian mission [at] Pyengyang,
                    arrested for permitting Koreans to use his premises for printing
                        propaganda.<note n="62" xml:id="d414fn62">Papers on this case not printed.
                        The charge was changed to that of harboring Korean students wanted by the
                        police and the case was finally settled by the payment of a fine.</note>
                    Officially government [<hi rend="italic">Embassy?</hi>] has reported incident to
                    Japanese Minister for Foreign Affairs. I fear that this action of the Korean
                    authorities will be followed by others of a similar character. All the evidence
                    I can gather fully supports the statement that the American missionaries have
                    not directly inspired or supported the present movement of passive resistance to
                    Japanese authority and were wholly ignorant of the population [<hi rend="italic"
                        >sic</hi>] to inaugurate it. We must recognize however, that it has
                    [practically the] unanimous support of the native Christians who because of
                    better education, closer organization and enthusiastic conviction have taken a
                    prominent part in the leadership. It says [<hi rend="italic">appears?</hi>] that
                    among the leading centers of unrest are the cities in which the mission stations
                    are located. <pb facs="0546" n="461" xml:id="pg_461"/> Herein lies one of the
                    chief causes for charging the foreign missionaries with responsibility and also
                    the embarrassment of the missionaries. They have the closest possible relations
                    with their native converts and in many cases deep sympathy and affection for
                    them. Furthermore, out of some 3800 American missionaries it is safe to say that
                    [ninety] per cent of them while recognizing the material benefits of Japanese
                    rules [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] are at heart antagonistic to the Japanese
                    methods of military government in Korea.</p>
                <p>It is a sound instinct therefore which leads the Japanese authorities to see, in
                    the influence of Christian missions and the organization which it is building
                    up, a serious menace to their system. The Japanese officials recently in a
                    series of informal conferences at Seoul asked for leading missionaries to use
                    their influence in support of the Government. This was a clever request. If
                    acceded to they hoped it might aid in suppressing the movement and at the same
                    time permanently weaken the mission work. If refused, as I am reliably informed
                    it was, it tended to prove the Japanese charges and laid the ground for
                    interference with the missionaries on any pretext whatever.</p>
                <p>A committee of the Presbyterian mission body with which Bishop Welsh of the
                    Methodist mission associated himself visited me yesterday and asked my advice.
                    In reply to their questions I confidentially expressed the following personal
                    views: <list>
                        <label>1st,</label>
                        <item>I agreed with the committee that it would be inexpedient for them to
                            seek occasion to present the grieviences of the Koreans to Government
                            officials in Tokyo as had been suggested. This would only serve to
                            identify them with the national movement.</item>
                        <label>2nd,</label>
                        <item>I thought it would be most unwise for them to explain local conditions
                            for the benefit of editors of foreign newspapers in Japan. In this
                            connection I deprecated the use of the organization of American
                            missionaries by the foreign papers in China for the purpose of
                            arraigning the conduct of Japanese authorities.</item>
                        <label>3rd,</label>
                        <item>I counselled absolute neutrality urging the committee to return as
                            quietly as possible to Korea and to confine their activities to
                            religious and medical work.</item>
                        <label>4th,</label>
                        <item>I expressed the personal opinion that they were not called upon to
                            sacrifice their convictions or their influence by openly supporting what
                            they deemed to be the arbitrary and often cruel repressive measures of
                            the Japanese officials but I warned them that they must be careful not
                            to do any thing which might be interpreted as support or encouragement
                            to the popular movement.</item>
                        <label/>
                        <item>Finally, I expressed my appreciation of the practical difficulties of
                            their position but explained that if by word or deed they identified
                            themselves with the Korean national movement they would render it
                            extremely difficult for our Government to protect their interests as
                            American citizens resident in a foreign and friendly country.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Morris</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
