<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-04-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-04-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="52" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d52">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">839.00/2134</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Secretary General of the Commission to
                                    Negotiate Peace</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Grew</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-04-25"><hi rend="italic">April 25,
                                        1919</hi></date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received May
                                        13.</hi>]</dateline></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to enclose herewith
                                for the information of the Department, a copy of a translation of a
                                letter written to Mr. Stabler by Dr. Henriquez y Carvajal,
                                unrecognized Provisional President of Santo Domingo, together with a
                                copy of a translation of a memorandum submitted by Dr. Henriquez y
                                Carvajal, in regard to conditions in Santo Domingo.</p>
                            <p>Dr. Henriquez y Carvajal has been in Paris for the last two weeks and
                                has called twice on Mr. Stabler, who acting under instructions from
                                the Secretary of State, received him informally, telling him that no
                                questions in regard to Santo Domingo could be taken up in Paris, and
                                if he desired to bring any matters to the attention of the
                                Government of the United States it would be best for him to do this
                                through the Department of State. However, Mr. Stabler discussed in
                                an informal way the present situation in Santo Domingo and asked Dr.
                                Henriquez y Carvajal to give him for transmission to the Department
                                a memorandum regarding his views of the future of Santo Domingo. The
                                second memorandum referred to in his letter will be transmitted to
                                the Department as soon as received.<note n="5" xml:id="d52fn5">Not
                                    printed.</note></p>
                            <p>Dr. Henriquez y Carvajal has approached many of the Latin American
                                diplomats and delegates to the Peace Conference in connection with
                                his claim to be restored to power in Santo Domingo. From what the
                                Commission has been able to gather, nothing more than a simple
                                hearing has been accorded to him and many of the Latin American
                                delegates have come immediately to Mr. Stabler to make inquiries as
                                to Dr. Henriquez y Carvajal.</p>
                            <p>It would appear that Dr. Henriquez y Carvajal is not rabidly
                                anti-American and that he recognizes the necessity of the step which
                                the <pb facs="0192" n="107" xml:id="pg_107"/> United States has
                                taken in Santo Domingo but desires that some of the functions of the
                                Government be turned over to the Dominicans. It is not believed that
                                any difficulties will arise for the United States from his visit to
                                Paris. The Department will be kept closely informed of all of his
                                activities.</p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">J. C. Grew</hi></signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure—Translation]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Doctor <persName type="from">Henriquez y
                                            Carvajal</persName> to the Chief of the Division of
                                        Latin American Affairs of the Department of State</hi>
                                        (<persName type="to"><hi rend="italic">Stabler</hi></persName>)</head>
                                <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-04-19"><hi rend="italic">April 19,
                                            1919</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                                <p>I have the honor to send you the memorandum on the republic of
                                    San Domingo, which I promised you at our last interview.</p>
                                <p>I will now prepare the other memorandum, relative to the points
                                    which you suggested for my consideration, and I will send it to
                                    you in the course of next week.</p>
                                <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Henriquez y
                                        Carvajal</hi></signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">[Subenclosure—Memorandum—Translation]</note>
                                <note n="6" xml:id="d52fn6">File translation revised.</note>
                                <p>At the very moment when the press of the civilized world
                                    published the admonition which went out by radio to all the
                                    nations from the Peace Conference recently assembled in Paris, a
                                    spontaneous popular sentiment in favor of the Dominican people,
                                    a sentiment of sympathy which received the adherence of elements
                                    foreign to the native population, culminated in Cuba in the
                                    foundation of pro-Santo Domingo committees. The number of these
                                    committees has spread from place to place and it is possible to
                                    foresee that they will soon extend over all Latin America.</p>
                                <p>The plan of these committees, not yet definitely shaped, is to
                                    lend all the moral aid possible to the Dominican people to bring
                                    about an improvement in the present conditions, from the
                                    political point of view, as well as in intellectual, commercial
                                    and industrial development. The first step in this plan to be
                                    taken at once is to obtain for the Dominican Republic its
                                    reinstatement in the exercise of its own national free
                                    government. The invitation issued by the Peace Congress to all
                                    the nations of the earth has made it easy for each one of them
                                    to present all the claims that they had to make concerning their
                                    legitimate rights and aspirations. No one of them is in a better
                                    position than the Dominican Republic to claim the restitution of
                                    her sovereignty as a state and nation, which she has lost
                                    neither by war nor by any international agreement, voluntary or
                                        <pb facs="0193" n="108" xml:id="pg_108"/> otherwise; and she
                                    would be able, under normal conditions of international life, to
                                    solicit the place that she desires to have assigned to her in
                                    the League of Nations. Nations which appeared dead, supplanted
                                    for centuries by powerful neighboring states, have been recalled
                                    to life by the Peace Commission; why should the Dominican
                                    Republic, situated in a new continent, free and continually
                                    progressing, near the mightiest dominion of liberty and
                                    industry, bound to this very dominion by geographical,
                                    commercial and political ties which nothing can break, a link,
                                    however small, in the chain of free states which constitute the
                                    society of nations called Pan-America, why should she have to
                                    remain, as at present she is, with her sovereignty sequestered
                                    and crippled?</p>
                                <p>But before being submitted to the Peace Conference, the Dominican
                                    question, in our opinion, should be laid before the Government
                                    at Washington. By its nature, its origin and its antecedents it
                                    is a question essentially American; and it can pass beyond the
                                    limits of America only when the latter has lost all sense of
                                    justice and cordiality. And this would be a mistake; because the
                                    United States has shown on more than one occasion its good will
                                    towards the Dominican Republic and its people and has lent its
                                    valuable moral support in the ominous hours of anxiety and
                                    trouble. Even today, the intervention which has taken place in
                                    this country on the part of the Government of the United States
                                    and which keeps the said country submitted to military
                                    government and military law, seems to have no other object than
                                    to “give assistance to the end that it may return to such a
                                    condition of domestic peace as will allow it to fulfil the terms
                                    of the financial convention of 1907 and its obligations as a
                                    member of the Society of Nations “. And this proposal rests on
                                    this solemn declaration:</p>
                                <p>“This military occupation is undertaken with no intention or
                                    ulterior object of destroying the sovereignty of the Republic of
                                    Santo Domingo”. (Proclamation of Captain H. S. Knapp on November
                                    29, 1916<note n="7" xml:id="d52fn7"><ref target="frus1916#pg_246"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                                Relations</hi>, 1916, p. 246</ref>.</note>).</p>
                                <p>Such declarations justify laying all claims made in favor of the
                                    Dominican Republic before the American Government, confident
                                    that the latter will not refuse to hear the voice of those who
                                    speak sincerely and calmly for their country. And if this voice
                                    demands a hearing today in Paris, it is because all rights and
                                    claims are being submitted in this atmosphere of justice,
                                    liberty and regeneration in which the principal breath blows
                                    from the powerful North American democracy.</p>
                                <p>A rapid sketch of the facts will bring us up to the conclusions
                                    and suggestions which we wish to make.</p>
                                <pb facs="0194" n="109" xml:id="pg_109"/>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Convention of</hi> 1907</p>
                                <p>The convention signed in 1907 between the Dominican Republic and
                                    the United States is essentially financial. Its only object is
                                    to guarantee the payment of the interest and amortization of the
                                    foreign debt, to the extent of 20,000,000 pesos gold, contracted
                                    by said Republic. In guarantee of this payment the Republic put
                                    in the hands of the American Government all the customs, to be
                                    administered from that time by collectors and assistants
                                    appointed by the President of the United States. From the funds
                                    gathered by the collectors the latter put aside <hi rend="italic">ipso facto</hi> and month by month 5% destined
                                    to pay all expenses and salaries of the personnel of the customs
                                    service, and 100,000 pesos to be applied to the fund of the
                                    interest and amortization of the debt, plus half the excess
                                    above 3,000,000 pesos when the customs receipts pass this
                                    figure. This sum shall serve to increase the amortization
                                    fund.</p>
                                <p>After the aforesaid sums are reserved, the remainder of the
                                    customs receipts, in addition to the other taxes, shall serve
                                    the Dominican Government to meet the estimate of its public
                                    expenses.</p>
                                <p>The interest on the public debt has always been paid with
                                    absolute regularity. From 1907 until 1912 the public expenses
                                    were met without difficulty. From 1912 on political disturbances
                                    arose which gave rise to extraordinary expenses which at length
                                    engendered a domestic debt for deficits on estimates in various
                                    successive years.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">clause iii</hi></p>
                                <p>The third clause of the convention imposes two obligations on the
                                    Republic: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Until the total amount of the bonds of the loan shall
                                            have been paid, its public debt shall not be increased
                                            without previous agreement between the Dominican
                                            Government and the Government of the United
                                            States.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>The same agreement is necessary to modify the import
                                            duties.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>The second of these obligations has never given occasion for
                                    dispute, since the Dominican Government has at no moment
                                    contemplated modifying its import duties.</p>
                                <p>The first obligation, on the contrary, has given occasion to a
                                    difference of opinion between the two Governments. The Dominican
                                    Government has always understood that the obligation imposed on
                                    it was that of contracting no new public debt of the same kind
                                    as that guaranteed by the convention, without previous agreement
                                    with the American Government; that a debt arising from a deficit
                                    in estimates, by reason of necessary and unusual expenses of
                                    war, as well as those due to unforeseen public calamities or to
                                    a diminution of income <pb facs="0195" n="110" xml:id="pg_110"/>
                                    occasioned by bad crops or by fluctuations in merchandise, a
                                    debt irregular in its origin, involuntary and impossible to
                                    foresee and upon which it is impossible to count, is surely not
                                    the debt provided for in the third clause.</p>
                                <p>The American Government, on the other hand, asserts that in
                                    contracting this new debt, originated by expenses of war and by
                                    deficits in estimates, the Dominican Government has violated the
                                    convention. And this criterion, according to the proclamation of
                                    Captain H. S. Knapp, is the legal foundation for the armed
                                    intervention in the Dominican Republic.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">political ineffectiveness of
                                        the convention</hi></p>
                                <p>When the convention of 1907 was signed it was the current opinion
                                    in Santo Domingo that by it the era of revolutions had ended.
                                    Perhaps the same opinion was held by many people in the United
                                    States. In reality, the convention was only a financial
                                    instrument whose essential object has been fulfilled. The
                                    revolutions were more frequent and bloody than ever between 1912
                                    and 1916. The convention has not been able to forestall nor
                                    avoid nor remedy political disturbances, since that is neither
                                    its primary nor secondary object.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Debts of the Republic</hi></p>
                                <p>The public foreign debt of 20,000,000 dollars has been
                                    considerably reduced by the payment of amortization, which was
                                    to commence in 1917. Apart from the 200,000 dollars annual
                                    reserves for this purpose for ten years, which makes a total of
                                    2,000,000 dollars, this sum has been increased; by the sums
                                    resulting from the 50% of the excess over the income of
                                    3,000,000 dollars from customs duties during this same period of
                                    ten years, on one hand; on the other, by the accumulated
                                    interest which has not been paid on the bonds deposited to the
                                    account of the Republic. The amortization of the debt,
                                    therefore, will be made more and more rapidly. In the present
                                    year the estimate of the Republic sets aside for this purpose;
                                    200,000 dollars, the annual fixed quota; 440,000 representing
                                    50% of the excess over 3,000,000 of the customs duties; plus the
                                    sums accruing from the interest corresponding to bonds already
                                    paid. We may count on an annual amortization of more than
                                    700,000 dollars, which will shortly reach and go beyond
                                    1,000,000. It is no exaggeration to state that within fifteen
                                    years at the latest the debt will be paid off.</p>
                                <p>The domestic debt originating during these four years of
                                    disturbances and now in process of liquidation, is estimated at
                                    some 7,000,000. The estimate for the present year sets aside
                                    700,000 dollars <pb facs="0196" n="111" xml:id="pg_111"/> for
                                    its amortization. Its payment also will be rapid, although this
                                    rapidity will be retarded by the attribution of an annual 5%
                                    interest. This debt could have been and should have been paid
                                    without interest.</p>
                                <p>In any case, it is certain that the total amount of both debts
                                    will be paid rapidly, in view of the size of the sums destined
                                    to their amortization, which within a few years will exceed
                                    2,000,000 pesos a year, so that in this way and without creating
                                    new financial obligations, the Republic will see itself in the
                                    rare position of a state without debts. This is all the more
                                    probable, since the public income is increasing from year to
                                    year, and it will increase much more as soon as new and
                                    legitimate taxes are levied, which the country can pay without
                                    loss.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Origin of the Political
                                        Disturbances</hi></p>
                                <p>It is certain that the political outbreaks on the part of the
                                    populace arise from many various, distinct and complex causes;
                                    but the principal and perennial cause in the Dominican Republic
                                    is its present political organization. The history of the
                                    Dominican nation is a history of war. First of the American
                                    colonies, with a monastic capital city, possessing a university
                                    from which doctors and scholars went out to distant points of
                                    the continent and the neighboring islands, it little by little
                                    lost its population and its prestige by the constant emigration
                                    to other privileged regions in the process of colonization. Its
                                    insufficient population led to invasions by filibusters, who,
                                    installed in the entire western part of the island, became
                                    strong enough first to resist the violent attacks made upon them
                                    by the Spanish authorities, and later to attack the Spanish
                                    colonists themselves. These struggles lasted for more than a
                                    century; they ended when Spain ceded the island to France. But
                                    new contests soon arose. Aided by the English, the Spanish
                                    colonists fought with the French, who for a time occupied the
                                    whole island, and succeeded in reestablishing the power of
                                    Spain. The latter gave little assistance to its colony, hence
                                    the Dominicans decided to unite with Gran Colombia, This first
                                    declaration of independence came to nothing and the Dominican
                                    nation then came under the domination of the Government of
                                    Haiti, at that time strong and well-organized, a powerful
                                    neighbor in the same island constituted with all the elements of
                                    political, military and agricultural organization bequeathed to
                                    it by the French Colony.</p>
                                <p>This Haitian domination lasted twenty-two years. The germ of
                                    liberty and independence of 1821, small in appearance, day by
                                    day grew stronger in the souls of the Dominicans. The latter
                                    decided <pb facs="0197" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/> on February
                                    27, 1844, to shake off the yoke of foreign domination and
                                    definitely proclaimed the constitution of its free and
                                    independent republic. This act was followed by a bloody war
                                    which lasted seventeen years and which exacted of the Dominicans
                                    unheard-of efforts, in view of the smallness of their population
                                    and the scarcity of their resources and elements of war.</p>
                                <p>President Santana, the valiant champion of those heroic
                                    struggles, fearing that the Dominican nation, weakened by the
                                    continued strife, could not in the long run resist the power of
                                    the enemy, sought the support of Spain, who annexed the
                                    territory of the Republic without consulting the will of the
                                    people. The latter wished no foreign domination and rushed to
                                    arms again to wrest the land from the new tyrant. A bloody and
                                    unequal struggle in which the Dominican people might have been
                                    annihilated ensued, but fortunately it lasted only two years.
                                    Once more the unfortunate Dominican people emerged as a
                                    republic, free and independent, but weakened by so many long and
                                    enormous sacrifices.</p>
                                <p>What was the result of so many costly and painful efforts? A
                                    political organization based on a military organization. All the
                                    authorities assumed a military character and adopted military
                                    proceedings. The most insignificant rural police authority was
                                    military. The head of a village, the mayor of a city, the
                                    governor of a province, the minister, the President, all were
                                    ordinarily soldiers or assumed in their functions the character
                                    of soldiers. In a country which lacked and which still lacks
                                    sufficient resources to support properly such a military
                                    organization, the degeneration of militarism was a foregone
                                    conclusion. Its elements entered into all political contests and
                                    militarism engendered <hi rend="italic">caudillos</hi>. The <hi rend="italic">caudillos</hi> in turn degenerated and, their
                                    authority diminished and influence weakened by vain
                                    pretentiousness, were at last unable to engender any stable
                                    state of authority, except when by rare qualities of personal
                                    character a strong <hi rend="italic">caudillo</hi>, rising from
                                    the midst of public disturbances, succeeded in assuming a real
                                    authority over the rest or over a majority of them, subjecting
                                    them to obedience. And nevertheless, even so, unless he was
                                    favored by special and transitory conditions of the national
                                    life, he was in reality in a precarious position; because he had
                                    to compromise with each of the agents of the Government holding
                                    office in the provinces, cities and villages, and in the
                                    intemperance of the exercise of his duties each agent of the
                                    Government grew in ambition and prepared for the exercise of a
                                    higher authority, if not the highest in the hierarchy.</p>
                                <p>Under such lamentable conditions political parties were formed
                                    around a <hi rend="italic">caudillo</hi>, taking their names
                                    from him. The sole object of such parties was to predominate;
                                    their strongest bond, the necessity <pb facs="0198" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/> for self defense, and the result was the
                                    constitution of governments ordinarily tyrannical, which were
                                    ignorant of the efficacy of the laws and the advantages of a
                                    good administration, and were hence incapable of improving them.
                                    Sometimes the good sense and advanced opinions of certain
                                    elements representing the reaction against the deplorable
                                    tendencies of the parties, succeeded in imprinting on the latter
                                    a wise direction and in placing in the President’s chair certain
                                    eminent and honored citizens, whose presence in power was a hope
                                    for gubernatorial regeneration. But such situations were
                                    precarious and transitory.</p>
                                <p>Nevertheless, the country has progressed. Many of its sons have
                                    attained the highest culture. Public instruction is widespread
                                    and opinion hostile to demagogy and its system of government has
                                    become general; and today it is the wish of many Dominicans to
                                    transform the political condition of the Republic by completely
                                    annulling the tradition and the influence of the <hi rend="italic">caudillos</hi>, burying forever the old
                                    degenerate militarism, the constant disturber of the peace of
                                    the Republic and the cause of its bankruptcy.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">The Remedy</hi></p>
                                <p>The remedy does not lie in the convention, as we have already
                                    said. The American Government has sought it in an interpretation
                                        <hi rend="italic">a fortiori</hi> of the third clause of the
                                    convention and has exacted: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>That, with a view to preventing the increase of the
                                            debt, the direction of public affairs be entrusted to a
                                            financial adviser, who should receive powers above those
                                            of the legislative body. A scrupulous organization of
                                            the business, so that the taxes should be collected
                                            regularly, honestly and fairly and that the public
                                            expenses, adjusted to a well thought-out estimate,
                                            should be paid in conformity with the law that had
                                            previously fixed them;</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>And in order that the public force shall not be placed
                                            in the hands of disloyal leaders who, far from employing
                                            this force to preserve order and peace and to guard the
                                            constitution and laws of the state, use it to overthrow
                                            the President and to create disturbances, let the sole
                                            public force which ought to exist in the country, the
                                            republican guard, be vested in a high North American
                                            official, who shall be assisted by a number of officials
                                            also North American, in the organization, command and
                                            discipline of such a body.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>Doubtless this reform remedies the evil but does not cure it
                                    definitely. It would leave alive all the old institutional
                                    mechanism, of Franco-Spanish colonial tradition, in which
                                    authority is everything and the people nothing. We should still
                                    have governors, chiefs of communes and chiefs of sections
                                    abusing their authority and crushing the spirit of the
                                    people.</p>
                                <p>The Republic needs in its institutions a total reform aimed to
                                    free the soul of the people from all the oppressive,
                                    constrictive and restrictive <pb facs="0199" n="114" xml:id="pg_114"/> bonds in which it has lived and enable it
                                    to expand in the atmosphere of liberty in which its will may act
                                    and aspire to better conditions of life than those which it
                                    enjoys at present. A succinct program of this reform was
                                    published about three years ago in the press of New York and
                                    Santo Domingo. This program includes: (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)
                                    the formation of political parties, with written program and
                                    elective duties to constitute the directives of its assemblies
                                    from the city wards to the national assembly; (<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) a free municipal organization and government of the
                                    villages and cities by a municipal authority elected by the
                                    people; (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>) civil governors and
                                    provincial councils elected by the people of their respective
                                    provinces; (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>) chambers in which shall be
                                    represented at the same time majority and minority; (<hi rend="italic">e</hi>) president and vice-president elected
                                    by presidential electors; (<hi rend="italic">f</hi>) public
                                    force, the national guard, by voluntary enlistment, with police
                                    functions, directed under the orders of the president; (<hi rend="italic">g</hi>) national reserve army, as in
                                    Switzerland; (<hi rend="italic">h</hi>) administrative service
                                    with the rule of civil service and pecuniary bond obligatory for
                                    all those who hold financial office; (<hi rend="italic">i</hi>)
                                    the development of a great plan of national culture, from
                                    elementary instruction, free and obligatory, with a minimum of
                                    attainment, to special and professional schools and university
                                    instruction; (<hi rend="italic">j</hi>) protective laws for
                                    immigration and labor, with a compulsory minimum time schedule
                                    and an optional maximum schedule.</p>
                                <p>The general disarmament of the people, the dissolution of the
                                    standing army, the withdrawal of all military command from the
                                    governors and subaltern authorities; all this would make it
                                    immediately possible to undertake the reorganization of the
                                    Republic in conformity with the plans above furnished.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Difference of
                                    Judgment</hi></p>
                                <p>In the discussions which the undersigned, while President of
                                    Santo Domingo, held with Rear Admiral Pond and Minister Russell,
                                    this plan was explained various times, and comparing it with the
                                    one submitted by the aforesaid representatives of the American
                                    Government to the Dominican Government, the undersigned
                                    signified that he had decided to resolve: <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>Concerning financial affairs, that the collection of
                                            all the taxes of the Republic, for a certain time and
                                            for so long as may be necessary to perfect and complete
                                            the entire service of the aforesaid affairs, should
                                            remain in the care of the General Treasury, which should
                                            effect the payments ordered by the auditor’s office,
                                            whenever (and only at such times) the orders of payment
                                            shall be based on the articles of the law of public
                                            expenditures or in accordance with other laws which
                                            determine special expenditures, and should designate the
                                            origin of the funds to meet such distributions. It was
                                            also decided to ask for the assistance of a financial
                                            adviser, an expert <pb facs="0200" n="115" xml:id="pg_115"/> in Spanish-American affairs, a
                                            university scholar and a practical man at the same time,
                                            whose opinions, suggestions and indications shall serve
                                            as guide and norm to the men of the government who have
                                            the legal power to present laws before the Chambers. A
                                            remuneration suitable to the rank and the high mission
                                            of the adviser would be insured to him by the Dominican
                                            Government by means of a contract previously
                                            signed.</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>As to the reorganization of the national, rural or
                                            republican guard, to entrust it to an American superior
                                            officer, who should call to his aid the necessary number
                                            of officers, also American, who should all know how to
                                            speak Spanish and should be recommended, as to their
                                            capacity and morality, by the American Government. The
                                            body of officers of the guard should include a certain
                                            number of Dominican officers judged apt to occupy the
                                            position of lieutenants. For the efficient
                                            reorganization of the guard, all changes should be made
                                            that might be suggested by the commander, whose
                                            suggestions would be transmitted to the Chambers with a
                                            request for such reforms. These officers should all be
                                            subject to the military laws of the country thus
                                            reformed, should hold the effective command of the
                                            public force and should draw their salaries in
                                            conformity with contracts drawn up and signed between
                                            them and the Dominican Government, and in conformity
                                            with the laws in which such provisions may figure. The
                                            contracts should be good for four years and should be
                                            renewable with the common consent of both parties. The
                                            Dominican officers, according to the competence and good
                                            conduct of which they might give evidence, would have
                                            the right to regular promotion every four years.</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>On what, then, is the difference of opinion between the plan of
                                    the Dominican Government and that of the American Government
                                    founded? The difference appears to be subtle. The Dominican
                                    Government could not logically accept the indications of the
                                    American Government, as they were formulated, for neither the
                                    Constitutions, nor the laws, nor the will of the people
                                    permitted it. And it is certain that the object aimed at by the
                                    American Government would be realized perfectly by the plan of
                                    the Dominican Government.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Antecedents of Both
                                        Opinions</hi></p>
                                <p>In 1912 the Dominican Government requested the American
                                    Government to recommend some field officers who might be
                                    disposed to take charge of the reorganization and instruction of
                                    the Dominican Army, after a contract duly signed by them for a
                                    period of four years. The State Department was good enough to
                                    present to the Dominican Legation at Washington a list of the
                                    names of officers disposed to assume the functions offered them,
                                    designating on the list the salary that each one should receive.
                                    This first step was without results.</p>
                                <p>On January 8, 1915, the State Department presented to the
                                    Dominican Legation at Washington a memorandum, according to
                                    which: <pb facs="0201" n="116" xml:id="pg_116"/> “the United
                                    States, desirous of assisting the Dominican Republic to bring
                                    about certain reforms necessary to insure the peace and
                                    prosperity of the Republic”, suggested to it— <list>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>That by a decree it should put the collection of the
                                            internal revenues in the hands of the Treasury;</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>That the office of Controller of Finances should be
                                            officially conferred on Mr. Charles M. Johnston, and
                                            that he should be vested with exactly the same powers
                                            that the financial adviser would receive later;</item>
                                        <label>(<hi rend="italic">c</hi>)</label>
                                        <item>That the expenses of the Dominican Army be reduced, an
                                            army whose lack of discipline constituted a danger to
                                            public order, far from guaranteeing it; and it added:
                                            “that the United States would be pleased to furnish
                                            President Jiminez whatever aid he might desire to
                                            reorganize the police forces of the Republic or for the
                                            creation of a constabulary to take the place of the army
                                            and the rural guard as they are today
                                            constituted.”</item>
                                    </list>
                                </p>
                                <p>These preliminaries show that both Governments were seeking a
                                    common point to arrive at an agreement in a matter of so great
                                    importance. The thought of both is included in the plan,
                                    previously explained, of the Dominican Government, a plan which
                                    includes a general reform of the political situation of the
                                    Republic, insures peace and leaves its sovereignty safe,
                                    unnecessarily suppressed by the North American plan.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">A Historic Example</hi></p>
                                <p>When, on the occasion of the second inauguration of President
                                    Estrada Palma, grave disturbances took place in Cuba which
                                    caused the resignation of the President, the American Government
                                    intervened in the conflict. To examine the causes it appointed
                                    Secretaries Taft and Bacon to proceed to the spot and to hear
                                    the parties in litigation. The consequence of this examination
                                    was the reform of certain laws. A provisional North American
                                    Government directed the destinies of Cuba, while the consulting
                                    commission drew up those laws, and gave time for passions to
                                    cool and for moral peace to be reestablished. As soon as this
                                    came about, popular elections restored to Cuba her own
                                    government. The tact, prudence, generosity, fairness and
                                    self-respect which the American Government showed on this
                                    occasion, constitute a crown of glory for this Government and
                                    engender in the people of Cuba a legitimate sense of
                                    gratitude.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Future of the Dominican
                                        Republic</hi></p>
                                <p>No nation of America has suffered greater vicissitudes than the
                                    little nation of old Hispaniola, favored by Columbus, the cradle
                                    of America and the tomb of the great and immortal explorer.
                                    Nothing, <pb facs="0202" n="117" xml:id="pg_117"/> however, has
                                    been able to destroy its character; neither the three years of
                                    French domination, nor the twenty-two years of Haitian
                                    domination, nor the five of the last Spanish domination, nor the
                                    seventeen years of war with Haiti to establish her independence
                                    nor the two years of war with Spain to restore it. In the midst
                                    of her hazardous life, lacking in resources and exhausted by
                                    struggles, she never abandoned the lofty ideal of liberty and
                                    independence which has served her as a standard and a guide. The
                                    island in which the Republic is situated is a mine of potential
                                    wealth. The population, few in numbers, has been increasing
                                    slowly and the victory over the ground, although insufficient,
                                    has succeeded in producing the necessary elements of life to
                                    insure it a progressive development and to place it in a
                                    position to realize the objects of civilization. Its commerce is
                                    increasing from day to day; its agricultural production, in
                                    proportion to its population, is considerable; and the day is
                                    not far distant when the exploitation of its natural wealth will
                                    make of this land of revolutions a desirable country toward
                                    which the eyes of immigrants will turn.</p>
                                <p>The agricultural, commercial and industrial development of this
                                    nation, as well as its political stability, will bring it nearer
                                    day by day to the United States. Its institutions, laws and
                                    customs will go on assuming more and more the American spirit.
                                    It will make progress by means of this contact. It will aspire
                                    to a future ever more ample, in proportion as the democratic
                                    spirit of the American people extends its sphere of action over
                                    the entire world. To no great people of the earth will it cling
                                    more than to the North American people, whose future in history
                                    knows no horizon. Its safeguard lies in this. But this luminous
                                    vision does not blind its eyes to the standard which has guided
                                    it through its hazardous life, the standard of its liberty and
                                    its independence.</p>
                                <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Aspiration of the Dominican
                                        Nation</hi></p>
                                <p>Above the devastation and the heaped-up ruins which the Great War
                                    has left as the trace of its mad career, to the horror of
                                    humanity, there now passes a breath of liberty and regeneration
                                    which comforts the soul of nations and incites them to a common
                                    desire for peace and justice. Nations subjugated for long years
                                    are rising on all sides to claim their rights to
                                    self-determination. Old and new, all nations are coming together
                                    and agreeing on a convention of a League of Nations which will
                                    cement on solid foundations international justice and the peace
                                    of the civilized world. It is the highest ideal of humanity,
                                    which seems already to be converting itself into a fact real,
                                    material and tangible.</p>
                                <pb facs="0203" n="118" xml:id="pg_118"/>
                                <p>In this solemn hour of peace and concord, of justice and liberty,
                                    the people of the Dominican Republic, whose sentiments the
                                    undersigned interprets, claims the rehabilitation of its own
                                    government, its right to self-determination, to accomplish its
                                    international obligations and to write itself in the list of the
                                    League of Nations.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                                        <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-04-14">April 14, 1919</date>.</dateline>
                                    <lb/>
                                    <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Henriquez y
                                        Carvajal</hi></signed></closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>