<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-11-03T16:36:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-11-03T16:36:00-05:00" n="545" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d545">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">125.61383/158: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Chargé in Mexico</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Summerlin</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                    State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Mexico</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-11-03T15:00:00-06:36"><hi rend="italic">November
                                            3, 1919, 3 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received November 4, 1.06 a.m.</hi>]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>3256. Your 2259 October 24th, 6 p.m. To my note of October 25,
                                Foreign Office in note dated to-day makes lengthy reply of which
                                following is a summary:</p>
                            <p>A telegram received from Governor Cabrera of Puebla shows that,
                                notwithstanding repeated representations of friends and relatives of
                                Jenkins not to pursue abductors, the Government has not failed to
                                fulfill its duty in endeavoring to locate offenders, working with
                                prudence and secrecy to conform with those representations and at
                                the <pb facs="0665" n="580" xml:id="pg_580"/> same time fulfilling
                                its obligation to maintain order and supply guarantees.</p>
                            <p>With regard to ransom the note states: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                    <p>“By instruction of the President of the Republic I have the
                                        honor to assure you that not only in this case but also in
                                        any other whatsoever which unfortunately has occurred or may
                                        occur the Government of Mexico has issued and will issue
                                        such instructions as may be necessary amply to guarantee the
                                        lives and interests of all the inhabitants of the country,
                                        foreigners and Mexicans, and that it will always follow this
                                        line of conduct; but that if it be claimed in this or any
                                        other case that the Government of Mexico pay any sum as
                                        ransom the Government would be confronted by the painful
                                        necessity not to comply with such demand, declaring from
                                        today categorically that it will not pay ransom for Mr.
                                        Jenkins even though it be legally proven in the
                                        investigation being made by the authorities of Puebla that
                                        the Consul bound himself to pay any amount or that he
                                        already has paid some amount. You will easily understand the
                                        reasons of defense and morality on which my Government
                                        found[s] a statement of this character; even though it
                                        recognizes its duty to protect foreign lives and interests
                                        in the country, it thinks that such protection should be the
                                        same as that which its nationals enjoy and it is known that
                                        it never has been claimed of any government that its duty of
                                        vigilance and protection extends to assuring it individually
                                        to each inhabitant since this would be impossible. By
                                        offering to pay these ransoms in order to overcome all
                                        difficulties the government, by such an evidence of good
                                        will, instead of stopping these crimes would provoke them by
                                        awakening covetousness with its liberality and would open
                                        its doors to fraudulent combinations of sure results and for
                                        this the establishment of an understanding or agreement
                                        between a foreigner and Mexican criminals, or simply the
                                        latter devoting all their activities to the consummation of
                                        acts such as the one of which Mr. Jenkins was the victim
                                        would be sufficient. The Mexican Government cannot lend
                                        itself to facilitating these immoral acts when its first
                                        duty is to act within and compel respect for the laws. What
                                        it is disposed to do in this and in any other case is to
                                        guarantee to the victims through the courts the payment of
                                        the indemnities to which they may be entitled in accordance
                                        with our civil and criminal legislation.</p>
                                    <p>“This decision is moreover based on antecedents well known to
                                        them [<hi rend="italic">you</hi>] which are recorded in the
                                        history of international law. Very seldom in fact and only
                                        when conditions exist which are not found in the present
                                        case has government paid ransom; but no country, including
                                        the United States, would agree to pay them as a principle or
                                        rule.</p>
                                    <p>“The Mexican Government is pursuing the authors of the crime
                                        and believes their capture possible and in case the amounts
                                        which it is said were stolen from Mr. Jenkins or those which
                                        he may have paid as ransom are recovered you may be sure
                                        that they will be returned immediately to their owner since
                                        this is one of the first measures which should be taken in
                                        conformity with our penal law.</p>
                                    <pb facs="0666" n="581" xml:id="pg_581"/>
                                    <p>“Hoping that the Government of Washington will recognize the
                                        justification with which the Government of Mexico is
                                        proceeding as well as its determined wish for the friendly
                                        arrangement of all matters which occupy the attention of the
                                        two Governments.”</p>
                                </quote>
                            </p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Summerlin</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>