<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-03-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-03-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="79" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d79">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">839.51/2024</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Consul at Santo Domingo</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Edwards</hi></persName>), <hi rend="italic">Temporarily in Charge of the Legation in the
                                    Dominican, Republic, to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-03-22"><hi rend="italic">March 22, 1919</hi></date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received April 3.</hi>]</dateline>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 438</seg></opener>
                            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As of interest to the Department, and
                                with reference to your telegram of March 13—6 p.m., and my reply of
                                March 18—3 p.m.,<note n="28" xml:id="d79fn28">Neither
                                    printed.</note> I have the honor to enclose herewith copies of
                                Executive Order No. 272, issued by the Military Government of Santo
                                Domingo on March 13, 1919, providing for additional payments to be
                                made to the amortization fund for the redemption of the 1918 issue
                                of bonds for the payment of the awards of the Dominican Claims
                                Commission of 1917.<note n="29" xml:id="d79fn29">See also <ref target="#pg_103">p. 103</ref>.</note></p>
                            <p>I have [etc.]</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Clement S.
                                Edwards</hi></signed></closer>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg></opener>
                                <head><hi rend="italic">Executive Order No. 272, March 13, 1919, of
                                        the Military Government of Santo Domingo, Providing for
                                        Additional Funds for Amortization of the 1918
                                    Bonds</hi></head>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, Executive Order No. 193 of the
                                    Military Government of Santo Domingo, issued at Washington,
                                    D.C., U.S.A., by authority of the Government of the United
                                    States, under date of August 2, <pb facs="0234" n="149" xml:id="pg_149"/> 1918,<note n="30" xml:id="d79fn30"><ref target="frus1918#pg_377"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                                Relations</hi>, 1918, p. 377</ref>.</note> provides
                                    for the payment of the awards to be made by the Dominican Claims
                                    Commission of 1917, by means of bonds of the Dominican Republic,
                                    dated January 1, 1918, and payable at par on or before January
                                    1, 1938, and in paragraph 8 specifically guarantees and provides
                                    for the redemption of said bonds as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“There is hereby pledged with the consent of the
                                            Government of the United States, from the customs
                                            revenues of the Dominican Republic, such amount as may
                                            be required for the payment of the stated interest of
                                            said bonds; and, to the amortization fund for the
                                            redemption and payment of said bonds on the redemption
                                            dates hereinbefore provided, the further sum per annum,
                                            to be deposited in equal monthly installments, beginning
                                            January 1, 1918, of an amount equal to one-twentieth of
                                            the total amount of the bond issue. The sums pledged in
                                            this paragraph shall constitute an additional charge
                                            upon all customs revenues of the Republic collected in
                                            accordance with the Convention of February 8, 1907,
                                            between the United States of America and the Dominican
                                            Republic, after their application to the first four
                                            objects designated in Article I of that Convention, and
                                            before any payment is made to the Dominican Republic.
                                            Additional payments for account of the amortization fund
                                            herein provided may be made at any time by the Dominican
                                            Government in its discretion.”</p>
                                    </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="flushleft">And</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, certain bankers and others who
                                    deal in such securities have expressed the opinion that there is
                                    a possibility of the termination of the American–Dominican
                                    Convention of 1907 before the retirement of all of the bonds of
                                    1908 issued under the provisions of Executive Order No. 193
                                    above mentioned, and the technical point thus raised has in fact
                                    adversely affected the market value of said bonds; and</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, the possibility of the
                                    termination of the said American-Dominican Convention of 1907
                                    before the redemption of all of the bonds of the issue of 1918
                                    is wholly dependent upon the amount of customs revenues
                                    collected and consequently the rate at which additional amounts
                                    are applied to the sinking fund for the redemption of the bonds
                                    first issued in 1908 under said Convention, in accordance with
                                    the specific provision in Article I of said Convention reading
                                    as follows:</p>
                                <p>“<hi rend="italic">Provided</hi>, that in case the customs
                                    revenues collected by the General Receiver shall in any year
                                    exceed the sum of $3,000,000.00, one-half of the surplus above
                                    such sum of $3,000,000.00 shall be applied to the sinking fund
                                    for the redemption of bonds”; and</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whereas</hi>, in view of this contingency it
                                    is advisable and necessary to provide for additional payments
                                    for account of the amortization fund for the redemption of the
                                    bonds of January 1, 1918, so that the <pb facs="0235" n="150" xml:id="pg_150"/> market value of such bonds may be
                                    maintained at a parity with the bonds of 1908:</p>
                                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Now, therefore</hi>, by virtue of the powers
                                    vested in the Military Government of Santo Domingo, there is
                                    hereby pledged from the customs revenues of the Dominican
                                    Republic, in addition to the amount heretofore pledged in
                                    paragraph 8 of Executive Order No. 193 above mentioned, a sum
                                    equal to sixty per cent of the one-half of the surplus above
                                    $3,000,000.00 of customs revenues from imports and exports
                                    collected by the General Receiver of Dominican Customs in any
                                    calendar year which would otherwise accrue to the Dominican
                                    Government, and said additional amounts shall be applied to the
                                    purchase and retirement of the bonds of the Dominican Republic
                                    dated January 1, 1918, in the following manner:</p>
                                <p>The total of the additional amounts pledged in the preceding
                                    paragraph shall be applied, so far as practicable, to the
                                    purchase of said bonds, without distinction as to series or
                                    denominations, at prices not in excess of par value. Beginning
                                    February 1, 1920, of the total amount available on February 1st
                                    of each year, one-third shall be applied to such purchases, and
                                    of the remainder available on March 1st of each year one-half
                                    shall be so applied to such purchases, and the total amount
                                    remaining available on April 1st of each year shall be so
                                    applied to such purchases. The Secretaria de Estado de Hacienda
                                    y Comercio of the Dominican Government, by means of notices
                                    published at least once each week during the months of December,
                                    January, February and March of each year beginning with December
                                    1919, shall offer to purchase said bonds within the limits and
                                    on the dates herein specified; such notices shall be published
                                    in the <hi rend="italic">Official Gazette</hi> of the Dominican
                                    Government, in one of the daily newspapers of the city of Santo
                                    Domingo, and in one of the daily newspapers of the city of New
                                    York. Proposals to sell said bonds shall be submitted in
                                    triplicate, on the forms prescribed by the Secretaria de Estado
                                    de Hacienda y Comercio, and shall be delivered in sealed
                                    envelopes to that office before ten o’clock a.m., of the dates
                                    specified for such purchases, and no proposal submitted in any
                                    other form or manner shall be considered. Such proposals shall
                                    be opened in the Secretaria de Estado de Hacienda y Comercio at
                                    ten o’clock a.m., on the dates specified for such purchases
                                    unless such dates should fall on Sundays or legal holidays in
                                    which event the opening shall take place on the day following,
                                    and the lowest proposals shall be accepted up to the amount
                                    available on that date for such purchase; if necessary to decide
                                    between two or more equal proposals the acceptance shall be
                                    decided by lot. Any person or firm who has submitted a proposal
                                    shall be entitled to be present either in person or by
                                    representative at the opening of the proposals. All bonds so <pb facs="0236" n="151" xml:id="pg_151"/> purchased, together
                                    with the interest coupons corresponding thereto, shall be duly
                                    registered as retired in the records of the Contaduria General
                                    de Hacienda and immediately cancelled and destroyed. Any part of
                                    the additional amounts herein pledged which, for any reason, is
                                    not utilized in the purchase of bonds as herein provided shall
                                    be applied to the amortization fund for the redemption and
                                    payment of said bonds in accordance with the provisions of
                                    Executive Order No. 193 hereinbefore referred to.</p>
                                <p>The General Receiver of Dominican Customs is hereby authorized to
                                    make monthly segregations, commencing as of date January 1,
                                    1919, from the customs receipts of the Dominican Republic, of
                                    the proportional amounts representing the sixty per cent of the
                                    one-half of the surplus above $3,000,000 of customs revenues
                                    hereinbefore pledged and, on or before January 10th of each year
                                    to deposit the total of the sums so segregated during the
                                    preceding year with the Designated Depositary for the Dominican
                                    Government in the special account entitled “Dominican Republic
                                    5% Bond Issue 1918”; and such segregations and deposits shall be
                                    regularly continued by the General Receiver of Dominican Customs
                                    until all of the bonds issued under authority of Executive Order
                                    No. 193 shall have been redeemed and paid.</p>
                                <p>The good faith of the Dominican Republic is hereby irrevocably
                                    pledged to the faithfuP compliance with the foregoing
                                    provisions, and this Order shall not be revoked or impaired by
                                    any law or decree which the Government of the Dominican Republic
                                    or any authority thereof may subsequently enact or issue, or by
                                    any interpretation thereof.</p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas Snowden</hi></signed>
                                    <lb/><dateline rendition="#left">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Santo Domingo</hi>
                                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-03-13"><hi rend="italic">13 March,
                                        1919</hi></date>.</dateline>
                                </closer>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>