<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Great Britain ( (Davis) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d814</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">814</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1919-08-15T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-08-15T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-08-15T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-08-15T05:00:00-05:00" n="814"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d814">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860j.01/46: Telegram</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Great Britain</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Davis</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-08-15T11:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 15, 1919, 11 a.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received 12.40 p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2801. I have received this morning the following note: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p rend="right">“Foreign Office, Wednesday, 13th August, 1919.</p>
                        <p>My Dear Ambassador: I have received your note of last evening urging the
                            British Government with all earnestness not to withdraw our troops from
                            Batoum for the time being in view of the evident gravity of the
                            situation. As I explained to you in our conversation earlier in the
                            afternoon evacuation has already commenced at the eastern end of the
                            line. In any case, however, its duration must be sufficiently prolonged
                            to relieve us from any immediate anxiety <pb facs="0916" n="831"
                                xml:id="pg_831"/> as to the position at Batoum. Should the present
                            programme be carried out unaltered it will not be till the early part or
                            middle of October that the question of leaving Batoum will assume a
                            practical form and it may be possible at that date, should the
                            conditions in the Caucasus require it, to make arrangements which will
                            not let the place remain without any protection. In the meantime I am
                            making inquiries as to whether, consistent with the broad policy which I
                            have indicated, anything can be done to insure some degree of local
                            security and to prevent the terrible events of which your Government are
                            apprehensive. Any arrangement for this purpose would be much easier were
                            your Government in a position either themselves to put troops into the
                            Caucasus or to assure us that the mandate for Armenia would ultimately
                            be accepted by the United States. The circumstances that you described
                            to me yesterday appear to render the satisfaction of these two
                            conditions for the present out of the question and they greatly
                            complicate an issue which is in itself sufficiently difficult. Pray
                            believe me, however, that the situation is one which I am examining
                            together with our military advisers from day to day and almost from hour
                            to hour with the most intense anxiety to find a solution that will
                            relieve us from the gravest fears. I am seriously considering whether it
                            will be possible to leave political missions with sufficient escorts at
                            the principal cities along the railway and whether effective political
                            pressure cannot be put upon the governments of the local states to
                            induce them to desist from actions which could only imperil their cause
                            and might ruin their future.</p>
                        <p>I am yours sincerely,</p>
                        <p rend="right">Curzon of Kedleston.”</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Repeated to American Mission, Paris.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Davis</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
