<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-09-22T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1919-09-22T17:00:00-05:00" n="827" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d827">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">860j.01/90: Telegram</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Commission to Negotiate
                                        Peace</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1919-09-22T23:00:00+01:00"><hi rend="italic">September
                                            22, 1919, 11 p.m.</hi></date><lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received 11.40 p.m.</hi>]</dateline></opener>
                            <p>4312. Department’s 3193, September 20, 10 p.m., 3060, September 8, 7
                                p.m., 3021, September 3 [<hi rend="italic">2</hi>], 3 p.m.<note n="22" xml:id="d827fn22">No. 3060 not printed.</note></p>
                            <p>The French offer mentioned in my 3960, August 20 [<hi rend="italic">30</hi>], 11 a.m., to land troops at Alexandretta and Mersina
                                meant that an expeditionary force of about 12,000 men of all arms
                                would be moved into Cilicia and would occupy the points in southern
                                Armenia such as Marash, Malatia, and Urf a now occupied by British
                                troops. In pursuance of this plan the British and French agreed on
                                the 15th instant, that the British garrisons in Syria west of the
                                Sykes–Picot line in Cilicia and southern Armenia will be replaced by
                                a French force; that the garrisons at Damascus, Horns, Hama, and
                                Aleppo will be replaced by an Arab force; and that after the
                                withdrawal of the British forces neither the British Government nor
                                the British commander-in-chief shall have any responsibility within
                                the zones from which the army has retired.</p>
                            <p>This carries out the arrangements contemplated by the Sykes–Picot
                                agreement of 1916,<note n="23" xml:id="d827fn23">See memorandum by
                                    the Russian Ministry of Foreign Affairs on the question of Asia
                                    Minor, Feb. 21/Mar. 6, 1917, <ref target="frus1917Supp02v01#pg_502"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                            Relations</hi>, 1917, Supplement 2, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p. 502</ref>.</note> under
                                which the Syrian littoral with Cilicia and southern Armenia was to
                                be occupied and administered [by the] French. This plan will merely
                                protect the relatively few Armenians now occupying southern Armenia.
                                It is a practical impossibility for a French force to reach Russian
                                [Armenia from] Malatia which is about 300 miles from Erivan, and
                                furthermore the French force intending to occupy the posts evacuated
                                by the British in Cilicia and southern Armenia will be no more than
                                sufficient for that purpose. The above plan will be [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] therefore do nothing to prevent the
                                invasion or the massacring of Armenians in Russian Armenia.</p>
                            <p>Joint military action by our troops with the French, as mentioned in
                                your 3193, September 20th, does not seem feasible because Clemenceau
                                has already declined to consider the sending of any French troops to
                                Russian Armenia via Batum where the British withdrawal is proceeding
                                and will be completed in about 10 days. The sending [of] ammunition,
                                supplies, and volunteer recruits to the Armenian republic as
                                proposed by Senator Williams can be assured only if the railway from
                                Batum to Erivan be held by an <pb facs="0926" n="841" xml:id="pg_841"/> American military force. In that event, the
                                Armenian army, re-enforced and equipped, probably would be able to
                                successfully withstand the Turks and Tartars. Polk.</p>
                            <closer><hi rend="smallcaps">American Mission</hi></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>