<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Serbian Chargé ( (Simitch) ) to the Acting Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1919v02</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d831</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">831</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-12-17T18:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1919-01-06T22:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1919-01-06T22:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-17T18:00:00-05:00" n="831"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d831">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">860h.01/21</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Serbian Chargé</hi> (<persName type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Simitch</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content"
                            calendar="gregorian" notAfter="1919-01-06T23:59:59-04:00"
                            notBefore="1918-12-18T00:00:00+01:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">undated</hi>
                        </date>.<lb/>[<hi rend="italic">Received January 6, 1919.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary</hi>: I am instructed by my Government to
                    submit herewith the following communication:</p>
                <pb facs="0978" n="893" xml:id="pg_893"/>
                <quote>
                    <p>In accordance with the decision of the Central Committee of the National
                        Council of Zagreb which represents the State of all the Serbian Croatian and
                        Slovene provinces within the boundaries of the former Austro-Hungarian
                        Monarchy, a special Delegation has arrived at Belgrade on the 1st of
                        December. This Delegation by one [<hi rend="italic">a</hi>] solemn address,
                        presented to His Highness the Crown Prince, has proclaimed the Union of all
                        the Serbian Croatian and Slovene provinces of the former Dualist Monarchy
                        into one single State with the Kingdom of Serbia under the Dynasty of His
                        Majesty King Peter and under the regency of the Crown Prince Alexander. In
                        the reply to this address His Royal Highness the Crown Prince has proclaimed
                        the Union of Serbia with the above mentioned independent State of Slovenes,
                        Croats and Serbs into one single Kingdom: “Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and
                        Slovenes.” His Highness has accepted the regency and will form a common
                        Government. On the 17th of December His Royal Highness the Crown Prince
                        received in audience a delegation from Montenegro. This Delegation has
                        submitted to His Highness on the 26th of November the decisions of the Great
                        National Assembly of the Kingdom of Montenegro. By virtue of these decisions
                        His Majesty King Nikolas I, and His dynasty have been declared destitute of
                        all the rights upon [<hi rend="italic">to</hi>] the throne of Montenegro and
                        the Kingdom of Montenegro, united to Serbia under the dynasty of
                        Karageorgevitch, is included in the Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats and
                        Slovenes. His Royal Highness the Crown Prince has declared that He accepts
                        with pleasure and thanks these decisions. A common Government for the new
                        Kingdom has been organized on the 21st of December. The Legations,
                        Consulates and other Missions of the Kingdom of Serbia will be the
                        Legations, Consulates and other Missions of the Kingdom of the Serbs, Croats
                        and Slovenes.</p>
                </quote>
                <p>Bringing the above to the knowledge of the United States Government, the Serbian
                    Government is strongly convinced that their communication will be met
                    sympathetically:—The Union of all the nations of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes
                    in one single state, which results from the imprescriptible right of the people
                    to dispose of their destiny.</p>
                <p>I take [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Y. Simitch</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
