<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>186. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski) to Director of Central Intelligence Turner</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d186</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">186</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1980-05-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1980-05-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-05-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-05-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="186"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d186">
                <head>186. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Brzezinski) to Director of Central Intelligence Turner<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d186fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                        Brzezinski Material, Subject File, Box 15, Crisis Management: 11/78–5/80.
                        Secret. Drafted by Odom.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1980-05-29">May 29, 1980</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Crisis Management</item>
                </list>
                <p>As you perhaps know, <persName corresp="#p_OWE_1">Bill Odom</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_GRB_1">Bob Gates</persName>, and Carl Smith convened to discuss
                    your memorandum of May 7 on improving communications and other support for
                    managing such incidents as the recent rescue mission. The following improvements
                    will be made: <list>
                        <label>—</label>
                        <item>Two additional secure voice terminals will be installed in the
                            Situation Room. One already exists.</item>
                        <label>—</label>
                        <item>A program for increasing the number of secure lines into the White
                            House has been in progress for some time. As it is completed in the
                            coming year, the number of secure lines into the Situation Room will
                            increase above the present five by several. We have recently installed a
                            new dial directory with a capacity for four additional lines. In
                            emergencies we can divert circuits to use them now.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>On your recommendation that an additional private circuit from <gloss
                        target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss> be installed in the White House, we do not
                    have the space and personnel to support it in a mode separate from the present
                    terminal in the Situation Room. In crises, therefore, we shall continue to use
                    the present arrangement.</p>
                <p>On maps, graphics, and other support, we shall be delighted with any additional
                    resources you are willing to commit to this purpose. A secure video link in the
                    Situation Room Conference Room allows us at present to look at maps, charts, and
                    other graphics in the <gloss target="#t_NMCC_1">NMCC</gloss>. When we have time,
                    however, our procedures call for requests for actual maps and graphics from
                    either <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_DOD_1"
                        >DOD</gloss>.</p>
                <p>On the occasion of the rescue mission<note n="2" xml:id="d186fn2">Reference is to
                        the failed April 24 attempt to rescue the U.S. Embassy personnel held
                        hostage by Iranian revolutionaries since November 1979.</note> we did not
                    take advantage of the extant facilities in the Situation Room Conference Room,
                    but I believe that was an exception, not the rule. With those capabilities and
                    planned improvements, the next occasion should prove easier to handle.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Zbigniew Brzezinski</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0838" n="813" xml:id="pg_813"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <head>Memorandum From Director of Central Intelligence Turner to the President’s
                        Assistant for National Security Affairs (Brzezinski)<note n="3"
                            xml:id="d186fn3">Secret. Brzezinski wrote in the upper right corner of
                            the memorandum: “<hi rend="italic">WO</hi>. Reaction? It think it’s
                            worthwhile. ZB. 5–7–80.”</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1980-05-07">May 7, 1980</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Crisis Management</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>1. During the long meeting of the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> the
                        night the rescue mission aborted, vital communication with the Pentagon,
                        State and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> was carried out by <persName
                            corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold Brown</persName> and Cy Vance using the
                        President’s secure telephone in the Oval Office and through <persName
                            corresp="#p_GRB_1">Bob Gates</persName> passing information to me that
                        he had received via the secure telephone in your office. I think you will
                        agree that at a time when we were so dependent on real time information from
                        the Pentagon, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and <gloss
                            target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss>, these arrangements did not serve us well.
                        They were neither efficient nor, as it turned out, particularly
                        accurate.</p>
                    <p>2. I know that you have had <persName corresp="#p_OWE_1">Bill Odom</persName>
                        working to improve White House crisis management procedures, particularly
                        with respect to nuclear conflict and other large scale operations.
                        Nevertheless, in keeping with our conversation the week of the rescue
                        attempt, I believe several inexpensive, easy to implement changes can be
                        made to improve substantially communications to and from the <gloss
                            target="#t_SCC_1">SCC</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1"
                            >NSC</gloss> during crises of a lower order of magnitude—such as the
                        rescue attempt. These might include: <list>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Installing a secure voice conference call capability in the
                                Situation Room conference room. This would enable all of us to
                                receive information directly and simultaneously from the <gloss
                                    target="#t_NMCC_1">NMCC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                                    >CIA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss>, thus
                                saving time and improving the accuracy of information
                                received.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Providing for permanent direct secure voice channels from the
                                Situation Room to the <gloss target="#t_NMCC_1">NMCC</gloss>, the
                                    <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> Operations Center, and the
                                State Department Operations Center. These would be helpful at any
                                time, but I think you will agree could prove especially useful
                                during a crisis situation. This would also leave available two or
                                three or more regular secure voice channels for principals or staff
                                to use.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Installation of another direct link between <gloss
                                    target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss> and the Situation Room. The
                                existing link is used for the transmission of routine <gloss
                                    target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss> traffic. A second channel could be
                                used for passage of information in extremely close hold situations
                                (such as the rescue), bypassing staff <pb facs="0839" n="814"
                                    xml:id="pg_814"/> both at <gloss target="#t_NSA_1">NSA</gloss>
                                and, if you deemed appropriate, at the White House as well.</item>
                            <label>—</label>
                            <item>Arrangements should also be considered to improve <gloss
                                    target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> support to the Situation Room in
                                terms of rapid provision of maps, graphics and satellite
                                photography.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>3. I recommend that you name a small, informal working group to look into
                        these and perhaps other modest changes that might be made to improve
                        communications into and out of the Situation Room during crises. Such a
                        group might include those who are most familiar with the arrangements and
                        could effect the changes without a lot of bureaucratic red tape. Obviously,
                        your representative (presumably <persName corresp="#p_OWE_1">Bill
                            Odom</persName>) should chair the group; <persName corresp="#p_GRB_1"
                            >Bob Gates</persName> would be my representative and perhaps it would be
                        worthwhile to include Harold’s assistant, Carl Smith, and others you might
                        deem appropriate. The group should act, in my view, as quickly as possible.
                        If you think this idea has merit, please ask Bill to be in touch with
                            Bob.<note n="4" xml:id="d186fn4">Brzezinski drew a vertical line in the
                            right margin next to this paragraph and wrote: “WO proceed. ZB.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_TS_1">
                                <hi rend="strong">Stansfield Turner</hi>
                            </persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
