<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-09-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-09-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="35" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                        <head>35. Memorandum From the Director of the Office of Management and
                            Budget (Lance) to President Carter<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d35fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                Brzezinski Material, Agency File, Box 4, Defense Department: 8–9/77.
                                Top Secret. Sent for action. McIntyre signed for Lance. Brzezinski
                                forwarded the memorandum to Carter under cover of an undated
                                memorandum in which he summarized Lance’s memorandum and wrote: “I
                                believe that you should support Bert’s recommendation. I would not,
                                however, expend any significant amount of political capital in
                                blocking an FB–111H program, given our need for support on more
                                important issues such as the ratification of the Panama Canal
                                Treaty.” Carter replied by writing in the margin: “The FB–111H
                                program should be kept at a minimum.” (Ibid.)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-09-14">September 14,
                                    1977</date></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>The FB–111H Strategic Bomber</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Background on the Issue</p>
                        <p>The Air Force has again proposed to <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold
                                Brown</persName> that he initiate an FB–111H strategic bomber
                            program as part of the 1978 B–1 related budget amendment—a proposal that
                            you considered several weeks ago but finally rejected.<note n="2" xml:id="d35fn2">On September 7, the <hi rend="italic">New York
                                    Times</hi> reported: “The Air Force, seeking to salvage
                                technology designed for the B–1 bomber, has urged Defense Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold Brown</persName> to revive
                                production of the controversial FB–111 fighter and covert it into a
                                long-range nuclear manned bomber.” (Bernard Weinraub, “Air Force
                                Urges Revival of FB–111 As a Long-Range Nuclear Bomber,” <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, September 7, 1977, p.
                                6)</note> This new attempt by the Air Force to start up the FB–111H
                            program has been briefed to the Congress and has found some support
                            (Representative Jim Wright, Senators <persName corresp="#p_GB_1">Goldwater</persName> and McIntyre). Further, the Senate Armed
                            Services Committee reportedly plans to add a $20 million FB–111H program
                            for 1978. While this would only be a small step, it opens the door to a
                            $7–10 billion program that will be extremely difficult to stop. Unless
                            you and <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold Brown</persName> take a
                            strong stand against initiating the FB–111H, Congress is likely to
                            include it in the 1978 budget amendment.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Air Force Proposal</p>
                        <p>The FB–111H builds upon certain features of the current FB–111. However,
                            it is essentially a brand new aircraft (new fuselage, avionics,
                            engines). It is smaller than the B–1, would carry about half the B–1’s
                            payload, and preliminary estimates suggest that it would cost somewhat
                            more than half the cost of the B–1.</p>
                        <p>The Air Force believes that proceeding with an FB–111H development
                            program is a less expensive <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1978 near
                            term approach to retaining a penetrating bomber option than maintaining
                            B–1 development. They would shift 1978 B–1 <gloss target="#t_RD_1">R&amp;D</gloss> funds into the new program.</p>
                        <pb facs="0180" n="155" xml:id="pg_155"/>
                        <p>This is only half the story however. The Air Force will agree that the
                            FB–111 would be a less effective penetrator than the B–1. Given the
                            great uncertainty of the cost estimates for the still to be designed
                            FB–111H, this system could easily be more expensive to deploy than an
                            equally effective B–1 force. In addition, the probability that we will
                            have to exercise the production option must be assessed. Thus, the
                            appropriate question is: Is this probability small enough to make the
                            near term savings on the option ($200–250 <gloss target="#t_M_1">M</gloss> in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 78) adequate
                            compensation for the extra costs that we risk paying in the event that
                            we build the FB–111H?</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Arguments Against the FB–111H Proposal</p>
                        <p>A number of arguments can be made against initiation of FB–111H at this
                            time.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>•</label>
                            <item>A decision to begin serious development of this system could be
                                interpreted as essentially a reversal of your B–1 decision, since
                                the aircraft are similar in many ways. In terms of the primary
                                arguments made against the B–1, the only major difference is a lower
                                unit cost. This is no justification, however, since total cost of
                                fulfilling the required mission is what counts—not unit
                                costs.</item>
                            <label>•</label>
                            <item>The air-launched cruise missile has been out from under the shadow
                                of the B–1 program only a few months. Renewal of the competition
                                between the standoff and manned penetrator options should be delayed
                                for a while to maximize the seriousness with which the <gloss target="#t_ALCM_1">ALCM</gloss> program is taken.</item>
                            <label>•</label>
                            <item>The FB–111H option could adversely affect our long term <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss> negotiating posture, although
                                the near term impact of starting to develop a new penetrating
                                strategic bomber may not be great. In particular, the similarity
                                between the FB–111H and the Soviet Backfire could lead to
                                negotiating difficulties.</item>
                            <label>•</label>
                            <item>Finally, commitment to even a very small program now is sure to
                                generate enormous pressures for full-scale development and
                                production within a few years. The Air Force views the FB–111H as
                                its last chance to buy a penetrating bomber—an issue of strong
                                emotional force with the Service. There are powerful congressional
                                interests backing the program and unfavorable past experience with
                                terminating the F–111 and A–7 production lines attests to the
                                difficulties involved.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">RECOMMENDATION</p>
                        <p>In view of the above considerations, the B–1 option should be retained
                            for the next year—and for this period at least, any FB–111 initiatives
                            should be avoided. Beyond the problems the FB–111H may give us in <gloss target="#t_SALT_1">SALT</gloss>, and the fact that it is an inferior
                            choice to the B–1, it seems premature to begin consideration of a manned
                            bomber that is so <pb facs="0181" n="156" xml:id="pg_156"/> similar a
                            solution to the problem of maintaining the effectiveness of our bomber
                            force as the B–1.</p>
                        <p>I recommend that you ask <persName corresp="#p_BH_1">Harold
                                Brown</persName>, in his testimony before the House and Senate
                            Appropriations Committees now scheduled for September 15 and 20, to
                            state that the Administration does not wish to initiate the FB–111H
                            program at this time even at a minimal level. He should support
                            continued B–1 development during 1978 at the minimum level sufficient to
                            provide an option for production.<note n="3" xml:id="d35fn3">Carter
                                checked his approval of Lance’s recommendation. In a September 20
                                memorandum Brzezinski wrote Brown: “Last week <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> sent a memo to the President
                                suggesting that you should oppose any efforts by the Congress to
                                begin a development program for the FB–111H. Since this memo would
                                not have gotten to the President in advance of your testimony before
                                the Congress last Thursday, I asked <persName corresp="#p_ADL_1">David Aaron</persName> to pass on <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss>’s as well as my own concerns over this issue. The
                                President has since seen the <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss>
                                memo and has indicated that if an FB–111H program is started, ‘it
                                should be kept at a minimum.’” (Carter Library, National Security
                                Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Agency File, Box 4, Defense
                                Department: 8–9/77)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>