<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>81. Memorandum From the Military Assistant to the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (Odom) to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Brzezinski)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v04</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d81</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">81</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-08-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rectLhSs11Y4ZQ6zE" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="recBK2rfbOQodUVmw" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >SSBN</term>
                    <term ref="recK25AUjO3toNZWX" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89006714"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">ASAT</term>
                    <term ref="recMrVNgNJpQ8DjcR" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037301"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Deterrence</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic" category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general" subject="arms-control-and-disarmament" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007351" lcsh-match="exact">Arms control</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-08-22T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="81"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d81">
                <head>81. Memorandum From the Military Assistant to the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (Odom) to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (Brzezinski)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d81fn1">Source:
                        Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Subject
                        File, Box 52, <gloss target="#t_SAC_1">SAC</gloss> and <gloss
                            target="#t_NORAD_1">NORAD</gloss> 8/20–21/78 Brzezinski Trip 7–9/78. Top
                        Secret; Sensitive; Outside the System.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-08-22">August 22, 1978</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Appraisal of Your <gloss target="#t_SAC_1">SAC</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_NORAD_1">NORAD</gloss> Trip</item>
                </list>
                <p>The full impact of your personal appearance and touch with the officers and
                    troops will not be fully apparent for some time, but it was undoubtedly great. I
                    could see that, particularly in your interaction with the lower ranking officers
                    and the enlisted personnel at Ellsworth AFB.<note n="2" xml:id="d81fn2"
                        >Ellsworth Air Force Base, near Rapid City, South Dakota.</note> The <gloss
                        target="#t_SAC_1">SAC</gloss> Wing Commander said that White House interest
                    in strategic forces has never been so great as in this Administration. He felt
                    it from the beginning and sees the persistency manifested in your visit.</p>
                <p>The discussions on operational, planning, and doctrinal matters was most
                    fascinating and hard-hitting for the briefing officers. The strongest impact was
                    Sunday evening at Offutt.<note n="3" xml:id="d81fn3">August 20. Offutt Air Force
                        Base, near Omaha, Nebraska, was the headquarters of the Strategic Air
                        Command.</note> Perry and Jones were clearly nervous. General Ellis was
                    having a great time dumping the tough questions on the <gloss target="#t_JCS_1"
                        >JCS</gloss>, but when you nailed him on the implications of <gloss
                        target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>I</gloss> vulnerability, he
                    was very unhappy with the trap into which he had put himself. He merely wanted
                    to lobby you for a larger <gloss target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi rend="superscript"
                            >3</hi>I</gloss> budget, not to raise the fundamental issues about how
                    Soviet growing capabilities are making <gloss target="#t_SAC_1">SAC</gloss>’s
                    posture less relevant to the President’s crisis management and war fighting
                    needs. When I tried to pick up on “war fighting” the next day, he evaded the
                    question. So did Jones.</p>
                <p>The other officers in that evening briefing were noticeably moved. Three of them
                    told me the next day that the discussions were the most “interesting” they have
                    ever heard on this topic. Coyle, Duncan’s assistant, found them not only
                    interesting but “troubling.”</p>
                <p>Several of the one and two star generals who briefed at <gloss target="#t_SAC_1"
                        >SAC</gloss> clearly had some idea of the direction you would probe. They
                    could not tell me two months ago how long it took to plan an <gloss
                        target="#t_LNO_1">LNO</gloss> from scratch. Nonetheless, your repeated
                    underscoring of the non-<gloss target="#t_SIOP_1">SIOP</gloss> scenario and the
                    longer campaign gave them more than they could handle. The result, <pb
                        facs="0387" n="362" xml:id="pg_362"/> in their mind, was a sense of our own
                    military inadequacy for the era of strategic parity but also a sense that more
                    of what <gloss target="#t_SAC_1">SAC</gloss> is doing may not help much.</p>
                <p>One point to draw out in the question of <gloss target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi
                            rend="superscript">3</hi>I</gloss> and the longer war is the “incentive
                    structure” in the Pentagon for <gloss target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi rend="superscript"
                            >3</hi>I</gloss> budgeting. <gloss target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi
                            rend="superscript">3</hi>I</gloss> funds are taken largely from the
                    service budgets. The Air Force prefers new bombers and fighters if asked to
                    choose between them and new <gloss target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi rend="superscript"
                            >3</hi>I</gloss> costs. So do the Navy and Army dislike surrendering
                    their hardware to pay for the <gloss target="#t_NCA_1">NCA</gloss>’s <gloss
                        target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>I</gloss>. Thus, it is
                    difficult to find a sustained and powerful military interest in <gloss
                        target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>I</gloss>. This is a key
                    issue for Duncan who is chairman of the WWMCCS Council, the group which
                    addresses the overall <gloss target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi rend="superscript"
                        >3</hi>I</gloss> budget and structure of the World Wide Military Command and
                    Control System.</p>
                <p>At <gloss target="#t_NORAD_1">NORAD</gloss>, things were not as sharply focused
                    as elsewhere, but General Hill’s briefers were pleasantly appalled to have the
                    opportunity to answer many of your questions. Drawing out the Soviet <gloss
                        target="#t_SSBN_1">SSBN</gloss> threat to our <gloss target="#t_C3I_1">C<hi
                            rend="superscript">3</hi>I</gloss> and the inherent asymmetry in the
                    geography were two points they obviously had not expected the occasion to make.
                    A number of other questions you asked gave them a chance to raise buried issues
                    with <persName corresp="#p_PWJ_1">Bill Perry</persName>. The solar interference
                    with <gloss target="#t_DSP_1">DSP</gloss> coverage, for example, and the
                    escalating space activity which <gloss target="#t_NORAD_1">NORAD</gloss> is
                    asked to monitor while much of its capability is eroding are two matters of
                    considerable importance, not only for tactical warning but also for <gloss
                        target="#t_ASAT_1">ASAT</gloss> concerns and arms control verification.</p>
                <p>Although General Jones’ presence was useful in many respects in your probing and
                    questioning, it also dampened things for you slightly. At Ellsworth AFB and at
                        <gloss target="#t_NORAD_1">NORAD</gloss> the local command structure was
                    obviously as much worried about pleasing and responding to Jones as about
                    dealing with you. They will have to face Jones again and again, but not you;
                    thus they had to split their attention. Jones intimidated General <persName
                        corresp="#p_HJE_1">Hill</persName> by telling him that his small welcoming
                    ceremony for you—involving a dozen troops—showed that Hill has too many
                    unemployed personnel; otherwise he would not be able to afford the ceremony!
                    Hill asked me several times thereafter if you were offended by the ceremony. I
                    told him that you probably thought of it not as a personal thing but as a useful
                    institutional symbolism that enhances the sense of purpose and coherence in his
                    organization. I also learned that Jones did not desire to make the trip.
                    “Someone” invited him twice before he “got the message.”</p>
                <p>I cannot judge what <persName corresp="#p_PWJ_1">Bill Perry</persName> took away,
                    but your doctrinal and operational questions were not lost on him, and they
                    clearly disturbed him at <gloss target="#t_SAC_1">SAC</gloss>. I was surprised
                    that he did not challenge you more directly.</p>
                <p>In summary, you have clearly opened the doctrinal debate within the <gloss
                        target="#t_SAC_1">SAC</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_NORAD_1">NORAD</gloss>
                    circles on “deterrence” and “war fighting”, and <pb facs="0388" n="363"
                        xml:id="pg_363"/> I suspect that it will reverberate back to the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS_1">JCS</gloss> in a short time. The military reaction is
                    going to be mixed. They like your rhetoric, and they are easily compelled by
                    your logic. As the budgetary and institutional implications become clearer to
                    them—as they immediately were to Jones—they will have second thoughts, but
                    thoughts difficult for them to voice candidly.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
