<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>172. Letter From President Kennedy to Crown Prince to Crown Prince
                    Faisal</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">172</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1963-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-03-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recKiZhEx9udfFZ5F" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-03-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="172"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d172">
                <head>172. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2" type="from"
                        >Kennedy</persName> to Crown Prince <persName corresp="#p_FAAAS1" type="to"
                        >Faisal</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d172fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_KJF2"
                            >Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security Files, Countries Series,
                        Yemen, <persName corresp="#p_BE6">Bunker</persName>/<persName
                            corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName> Missions. No classification marking.
                        Attached to the source text is a note from <persName corresp="#p_BMG2"
                            >Bundy</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_BWH2">Brubeck</persName>
                        dated March 1 that reads: “For your information and files. The signed copy
                        was given to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE6">Bunker</persName> at the
                        White House this morning.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1963-03-01">March 1, 1963</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Your Royal Highness</hi>: Your letter of February 22
                    reached me at a most opportune time. I have been deeply troubled by the recent
                    course of events and I have been distressed at the difficulties that have arisen
                    between friends, over Yemen, since our cordial talks last October.</p>
                <p>I think it is clear that what is involved here is a difference over means, not
                    objectives. We agree that the Egyptian forces should get out of Yemen. We agree
                    that Yemen should not be used as a base for hostile action against Saudi Arabia.
                    We agree that the Yemenis must be allowed <pb facs="0447" n="381"
                        xml:id="pg_381"/> to make their own decisions on Yemeni affairs. And we
                    agree that Saudi Arabia’s integrity and stability must be defended against
                    external intrusions. The problem is to agree on how to achieve these things.</p>
                <p>The best way between friends to reach an understanding is through personal
                    consultations. For this reason I have sought your permission to send Ambassador
                        <persName corresp="#p_BE6">Ellsworth Bunker</persName> to you. He has a long
                    record of distinguished service to his country, he has my complete confidence,
                    and he is authorized to speak frankly on my behalf. I commend him to you with
                    the hope that you will talk with him on the same basis as you would with me.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE6">Bunker</persName> will be able to reassure
                    you of the steadfastness of our policy toward Saudi Arabia. Like you, we are not
                    a fickle people who change their policies and loyalties overnight. The United
                    States, and I personally, have a great and undiminished concern for the security
                    and integrity of Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <p>I am looking forward to hearing from you. I send my warmest personal regards. May
                    God keep you and the Saudi people and grant you peace.</p>
                <p>Sincerely,<note n="1" xml:id="d172fn1">Printed from an unsigned copy. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BE6">Bunker</persName> delivered the letter on March 6; see
                            <ref target="#d180">Document 180</ref>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
