<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>176. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v18</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">176</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1963-12-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec81XS5kv6kbKNvG" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85082846"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mediation</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-aid" subject="foreign-aid" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-12-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-07-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="176" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d176">
                <head>176. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>On March 4, 1963, during a 70-minute meeting with President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> in Cairo, Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> delivered the oral message from
                    President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> contained in <ref
                        target="#d175">Document 175</ref>. <persName corresp="#p_BJS1"
                        >Badeau</persName> also executed instructions contained in telegram 1653 to
                    Cairo, March 3, that he emphasize to <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> U.S. concern over <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> air
                    attacks on Saudi Arabia and the detrimental implications that continued <gloss
                        target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> military involvement in Yemen had on the
                    disengagement process and U.S. Congressional support for economic assistance to
                    the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. (Department of State, Central Files,
                    POL 26 YEMEN) <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> reported on the
                    conversation in telegram 1379 from Cairo, March 5. (Ibid., POL 27 YEMEN) For
                    text, see the Supplement, the compilation on Yemen.</p>
                <p>A summary of the highlights of the conversation, prepared in the Department of
                    State for the information of the White House, but not sent, reads as
                    follows:</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">“1. Yemen</hi>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p>“a. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName>
                                emphasized: <list>
                                    <item>“(1) the tolerance we had displayed toward <gloss
                                            target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> activities in Yemen;</item>
                                    <item>“(2) our determination to protect our vital interests and
                                        uphold the integrity of Saudi Arabia;</item>
                                    <item>“(3) that <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> violations
                                        of the Saudi border were prejudicial to the <persName
                                            corresp="#p_BE6">Bunker</persName>–<persName
                                            corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName> mission and pushing
                                        us perilously close to activating our commitments to Saudi
                                        Arabia.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>“Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> apparently
                                did not put forward our proposal that <hi rend="italic">the <gloss
                                        target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> make an initial cut in its
                                    forces simultaneously with a temporary Saudi suspension of
                                    support to the royalists</hi> as a means of getting a
                                disengagement process started. However President <persName
                                    corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> himself held open the
                                possibility that if the currently stepped-up <gloss target="#t_UAR1"
                                    >UAR</gloss> military offensive to end the situation succeeds
                                    <hi rend="italic">some <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                    withdrawal from Yemen might be effected</hi>.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>“b. In his reply President <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                                    >Nasser</persName> emphasized: <list>
                                    <item>“(1) The bombardments were not intended as deliberate
                                        provocation but were an integral and successful element of
                                            <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> military
                                        strategy;</item>
                                    <item>“(2) Every day of continued Yemen fighting meant loss of
                                            <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> lives and as leader
                                        of the country he could not escape responsibility;</item>
                                    <item>“(3) That the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> could
                                        not wait another five months for disengagement;</item>
                                    <item>“(4) When Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJS1"
                                            >Badeau</persName> underscored the souring political
                                        effect of these attacks, <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                                            >Nasser</persName> promised, however, to order <persName
                                            corresp="#p_AFMAH1">Marshal Amer</persName> to suspend
                                        trans-border activities pending the outcome of the <persName
                                            corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName>–<persName
                                            corresp="#p_BE6">Bunker</persName> efforts which
                                        Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName>
                                        stated would consume about two weeks.</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <pb facs="0459" n="393" xml:id="pg_393"/>
                            <p rend="flushleft">
                                <hi rend="italic">“2. <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                    Clandestine Radio</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>“Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> indicated
                                we knew the location of the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                clandestine radio and suggested termination of broadcasts which are
                                doing great harm to US–<gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                relations. <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> tacitly
                                acknowledged responsibility but gave no commitment regarding
                                termination.” (Department of State, Central Files, POL 27 YEMEN)</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>On March 5, <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> sent <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> a note suggesting that when <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> showed Kennedy telegram 1379 from Cairo
                    he also give the President the following memorandum from <persName
                        corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_KJF2"
                        >Kennedy</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> added,
                    “I’m a bit worried by <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName>’s pitch.”
                        <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName>’s proposed memorandum to the
                    President reads as follows:</p>
                <p>“<persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s reply (Cairo 1379) to your
                    warning is just about as responsive as could be expected. After justifying his
                    bombings as intended merely to cut off Saudi gun-running rather than to
                    overthrow Faysal, he in effect says he’ll hold off further attacks for a few
                    weeks to give our mediation efforts a chance.</p>
                <p>“This may in fact only postpone our confrontation with <persName
                        corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>, but it’s hard to see how he could have
                    said more. His answer also shows that our new policy has given us leverage with
                    him.</p>
                <p>“It’s a pity that <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> rested his
                    argument so heavily on our need for time for <persName corresp="#p_BE6"
                        >Bunker</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_BRJ4">Bunche</persName>
                    efforts. If these stall, <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> can argue
                    that he’s entitled to resume. But we’ll now push hardest to turn Faysal off.”
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security
                    Files, Countries Series, United Arab Republic, <persName corresp="#p_NGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName> Correspondence)</p>
                <p>On March 8, <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> sent to <persName
                        corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s office a copy of the memorandum of the
                    March 5 conversation with a letter from <persName corresp="#p_BJS1"
                        >Badeau</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                    informing him, on instructions from the U.S. Government, of the following:</p>
                <p>“Although Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BRJ4">Ralph Bunche</persName> has returned to
                    the United States, the United States Government does not consider that his
                    mission has been terminated. It has reason to believe that he will either be
                    received in Saudi Arabia or will hold discussions with Saudi Arabian
                    representatives in New York. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE6"
                        >Bunker</persName> will also continue his efforts in Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <p>“In view of the above, the United States Government considers that the United
                    Arab Republic’s commitment to cease attacks on the soil of Saudi Arabia
                    continues in operation. It considers that this commitment applies to every type
                    of indirect and direct action (including naval) and not simply to aerial
                    bombardment.” (Department of State, Central Files, POL 27 SAUD–<gloss
                        target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
