<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-03-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-03-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="182" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d182">
                    <head>182. Memorandum From the Director of Intelligence and Research (<persName corresp="#p_HRJ1" type="from">Hilsman</persName>) to Secretary of State
                            <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="to">Rusk</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d182fn0">Source: Department of State, <gloss target="#t_NEANE1">NEA/NE</gloss> Files: Lot 65 D 28, Syrian Coup.
                            Secret.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-03-08">March 8,
                            1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="to">
                        <head>INTELLIGENCE NOTE</head>
                        <item>Syrian Coup Again To Put Arab Unity to Test</item>
                    </list>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Syrian Army Revolts</hi>. A Syrian Army group headed by a
                        National Council of the Revolutionary Command has overthrown the Syrian
                        Government and assumed power. Assurances of support from a number of
                        military units around the country appear to afford the new group a good
                        chance of success. No leaders of the Council have yet been identified. The
                        tone of a proclamation defining its aims, however, indicates that the new
                        regime will be anti-Communist and will favor “Arab unity on a sound basis.”
                        It identifies the revolution with the “liberated” states (i.e., the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, Yemen, Iraq, and Algeria).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Cairo and Baghdad React With Alacrity</hi>. The <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and the new revolutionary regime in Iraq
                        greeted the Syrian coup enthusiastically. Both warned against any outside
                        interference, and Iraq has placed its Army at Syria’s disposal. <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> is likely to attempt to exploit the
                        present situation in Syria to offset his defeat there a year and a half ago
                        and to bolster his recent success in the Yemen. Unless the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and Iraq have reached a solid basis of
                        understanding on the course of Arab unity, a contest between them for
                        dominance in Syria may again develop.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Implications for Area Monarchs</hi>. Now surrounded by
                        “liberated” states, King Husayn and Crown Prince Faysal will consider their
                        positions even more precarious. They may, therefore, seek more concrete
                        assurances of support from the United States.<note n="1" xml:id="d182fn1">At
                            the March 8 Secretary’s staff meeting, Talbot “commented briefly on the
                            effects on Jordan and Saudi Arabia of the coup in Syria. Regarding
                            Yemen, he said that the royalists’ position had worsened.” (Department
                            of State, Secretary’s Staff Meetings: Lot 66 D 147) Later that day,
                            Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName> responded to a
                            question asked at a news conference by stating that the United States
                            was concerned about the independence of the Arab states, and he noted in
                            particular: “We are very much interested in the independence and
                            security of our friends in Jordan and Saudi Arabia and will be very much
                            alert to any threats against them.” For text, see <hi rend="italic">American Foreign Policy: Current Documents, 1963</hi>, p.
                            602.</note></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>