<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-05-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-05-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="232" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d232">
                    <head>232. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_KRW2" type="from">Robert W.
                            Komer</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                        President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG2" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d232fn0">Source: <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName>
                            Library, National Security Files, Countries Series, Jordan, 5/63–11/63.
                            Secret.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-05-01">May 1,
                            1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <p rend="flushleft">McGB:</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>We now have field comments on advisability of reaffirming Tripartite
                                Declaration.<note n="1" xml:id="d232fn1">Documentation is in
                                Department of State, Central File POL 26 JORDAN. A draft memorandum
                                from <persName corresp="#p_BWH2">Brubeck</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>, dated April 30,
                                “Implications of Reaffirmation of the Tripartite Declaration and
                                Presidential Response to Press Inquiries—Study Undertaken by
                                Department at President’s Request,” which apparently was never sent,
                                is ibid., <gloss target="#t_NEANE1">NEA/NE</gloss> Files: Lot 65 D
                                28, Tripartite Declaration; for text, see the Supplement, the
                                compilation on Jordan.</note>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MWBJ1">Macomber</persName> thinks Jordan doesn’t
                            need public reassurance now so prefers delay, adding that to extent fear
                            of Israeli attack on West Bank acts as a deterrent to
                            externally-inspired revolution in Jordan, such a statement tends to
                            undercut it. <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> prefers quiet
                            diplomacy too, suggests JFK letters to A-I chiefs of state, but
                            recognizes pressures for some public statement. If so, he favors pegging
                            it to substance of last para. Tripartite Declaration, but not
                            reaffirming Declaration itself. <persName corresp="#p_SAEII1">Adlai</persName> strongly advises President reaffirm substance of
                            last paragraph now.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item><p><hi rend="italic">Repercussions</hi>. Such a statement doesn’t
                                really give Israelis what they want (straight bilateral security
                                guarantee plus joint planning on how to carry it out). But it may
                                reduce heat on us from Israelis, while calming down on Hill.</p>
                            <p>Arabs will inevitably see in statement (given its present context) a
                                pro-Israeli move. So we can’t stop adverse public reactions in most
                                of Arab world, though it shouldn’t be too long-lasting or painful.
                                We can mitigate impact on Arab leaders (especially <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>) by explaining carefully
                                what we up to, and reminding them this longstanding US policy so
                                marks no change in our attitude. But we’ve got to be careful not to
                                let <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> think statement
                                gives him umbrella under which to promote revolution.</p></item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Ergo, I feel (State does too) that public statement at this time
                            unnecessary for foreign policy reasons, and will entail some adverse
                            Arab reaction. So issue turns on whether it is desirable for domestic
                            purposes here.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>If we have to say something, President’s idea of responding at press
                        conference seems best. Let’s not refer to Tripartite in any way, but say
                        something like: <pb facs="0574" n="508" xml:id="pg_508"/>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>“US remains, as it has been since 1950, deeply interested in the
                                maintenance of peace and stability anywhere in the Near East. It
                                remains strongly opposed to the use of force or threat of force
                                between any of the states in that area as well as to the violation
                                of frontiers or armistice lines.”</p>
                        </quote></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_KRW2"><hi rend="strong">RWK</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>