<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-07-07T14:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-07-07T14:35:00-05:00" n="292" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d292">
                    <head>292. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss> to
                        the <gloss type="to">Embassy in the United Arab Republic</gloss><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d292fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                            Files, POL 7 US/<persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">MCCLOY</persName>. Secret;
                            Operational Immediate. Drafted by Dickman and Gathright (<gloss target="#t_ACDA1">ACDA</gloss>); cleared by <persName corresp="#p_MKJA1">McKesson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> (substance); and approved by <persName corresp="#p_TPH2">Talbot</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-07-07T15:35:00-04:00">July 7, 1963,
                                3:35 p.m.</date></dateline></opener>
                    <p>121. Eyes only Cane for Ambassador. When you see <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>, inform him that President has asked you to state:
                        his appreciation for talking frankly at length with <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>; that he has a better understanding
                        of <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s problems and attitudes;
                        that he welcomes assurances on nuclear weapons and on Israel given to
                            <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>; that he believes further
                        frank discussions on different aspects of arms limitation in Near East would
                        be worthwhile, and that while President has not yet talked to <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> personally and has only seen his
                        reports, he has asked you to review with <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> certain points which appear to President to be of
                        great significance: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>First tell <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> we sense
                                on his part a question why we had singled out <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> for this approach. Actually this
                                not so. Our concern regarding spread of nuclear weapons is not
                                limited to Near East but is world-wide. Hopefully, at a future time,
                                there will be some broad collective basis for approaching this
                                problem. Meanwhile, it is subject of a number of separate efforts,
                                both individual and regional. We have not singled out <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. On contrary, we have pressed this
                                matter with number of countries, notably some of our closest
                                allies.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item><p>With respect to timing of our approach, we have specific
                                    reasons for approaching <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> at this time. These relate to fact that
                                    both countries are now edging into missile field and Israelis in
                                    particular are well into nuclear field. Dimona reactor is now in
                                    an advanced stage of construction and, while intended for
                                    peaceful uses, it does have potential capability of producing
                                    fuel for nuclear weapons. We want to make crystal clear our firm
                                    estimate that Israelis are not and have not decided to start
                                    developing such weapons. However, Israelis are approaching stage
                                    where their combination of technical skills and physical plant,
                                    though developed for peaceful uses, also could give them the
                                    capacity for producing a nuclear weapon within a few years if
                                    the arms race should expand into highly sophisticated
                                    fields.</p>
                                <p>Also, regardless of what <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                    believes to be our sensitivity to Israeli propaganda, we wish to
                                    make it clear that one of our greatest concerns is that by means
                                    of its current charges with respect to <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> advanced weapons development, Israelis may lay
                                    a foundation which they will believe <pb facs="0702" n="636" xml:id="pg_636"/> justifies their moving into the nuclear
                                    weapons field if they should decide to do so.</p>
                                <p>It is elemental prudence for the international community to work
                                    out a safeguards procedure in such a situation. In our
                                    continuing determination to make certain Israel does not go a
                                    nuclear route, we want to be able to say to them that if they do
                                    not, we can assure them <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> will
                                    not and vice versa.</p></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>This brings us to question of verification. The <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> has indicated that as far as
                                nuclear weapons are concerned, it has nothing to inspect and that it
                                has no intention of going into nuclear weapons field. We recognize
                                that <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>’s present nuclear facility
                                does not offer a weapons capability. But we would like to point out
                                that when <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> rejects the principle
                                of externally verified safeguards on grounds of sovereignty, it is
                                taking a position which enables Israel to reject verification on
                                same grounds and maintain that <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                is developing nuclear weapons secretly. Since <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> has very little to inspect in
                                nuclear field, it should be relatively easy for it to accept
                                principle of international safeguards as they apply to nuclear
                                weapons, and it would strengthen our hand substantially in dealing
                                with Israel.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Many countries have come increasingly to accept the application of
                                safeguards to nuclear reactors out of the common interest in
                                preventing spread of nuclear weapons. <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> would not be alone in this regard. India, which has
                                in past rejected safeguards, has accepted them for the large reactor
                                at Tarapur—first on basis that US would do verification and later
                                that <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> should do so. In the case
                                of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> primary verification role
                                need not be performed by US but could be done on a multilateral
                                basis such as <gloss target="#t_IAEA1">IAEA</gloss> or by other
                                countries.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>We recognize that question of missiles presents greater
                                difficulties for <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>, and on the
                                basis of talks with <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>,
                                we feel we have a better understanding of how <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> views its missile effort. We
                                appreciate <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>’s assurance that it
                                does not plan to develop missiles for nuclear warheads, but we
                                wonder if <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> might not wish to
                                consider how missile program may look to others and what some of its
                                effects, even though not intended, may have been.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Public disclosure of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> missile
                                program has lent itself to exploitation by others and given them a
                                handle with which to launch their propaganda campaigns. We have
                                tried to avert this and place it in proper perspective, as for
                                example in Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HWA2">Harriman</persName>’s letter of April 12 to six U.S. Senators. This
                                letter was not well received by Israel. Despite such actions on our
                                part, others will view <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>’s
                                missiles as being capable of carrying nuclear weapons and will give
                                credence to Israel’s charges. Moreover, we are concerned that Israel
                                is accelerating her own missile effort in response to <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>’s missile developments. We do not
                                know where this would lead.</item>
                            <pb facs="0703" n="637" xml:id="pg_637"/>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Our suggestion that <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> might wish
                                to consider not pressing its missile development program was made
                                with these considerations in mind. We did not have in mind any
                                public abandonment of missile effort but rather exercise of
                                restraint by <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>. Then it might be
                                more feasible to ensure that Israel also exercised restraint. We
                                would welcome any specific views <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>
                                might have on how this problem might be met.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>We fully understand <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss>’s
                                political apprehensions regarding extensive international
                                verification procedures. It is certainly not our desire to place the
                                    <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> in a sort of protectorate or
                                satellite position, and perhaps further exploration of matter might
                                yield an arrangement which would avoid adverse political
                                implications. Even we in US in our own relations with Soviet Union
                                have decided, if satisfactory arms limitations can be agreed upon,
                                to accept verification arrangements which would give assurance both
                                to ourselves and Soviet Union. Obviously, kind of verification that
                                would apply to US and Soviet Union is much more extensive than that
                                which would be adequate in case of <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and Israel where a simple, unobtrusive verification
                                arrangement, involving a very small number of technicians, would
                                suffice.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>In sum it is our belief that US and <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> share a common interest in ensuring that
                                technological development in Near East does not take what could
                                prove to be a disastrous turn. Protective war is not a solution but
                                a last resort and one that would be much more costly to the <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> and far less likely to succeed than
                                approach we are suggesting. We do not think it is necessary either
                                to permit further escalation of the arms race in the Near East or to
                                resort to protective war. We think that arms limitation with
                                assurance for both sides offers a better way. These were thoughts
                                which lay behind <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName>’s
                                visit, and we hope <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> will give
                                these matters further thought.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>If, during course of meeting, <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                        inquires whether <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> visiting
                        Israel, you may inform him that he will first report to President.</p>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>. In foregoing you will note we have
                        continued to include missiles although we have treated them separately. In
                        view of the Israeli missile effort, we do not feel we should abandon missile
                        aspect yet. End <gloss target="#t_FYI1">FYI</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>Should you perceive problems with any elements this approach, we would
                        appreciate your comments soonest. However believe foregoing will serve as
                        useful terms of reference in continuing dialogue with <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>.<note n="1" xml:id="d292fn1">In
                            telegram 120 from Cairo, July 11, <persName corresp="#p_BJS1">Badeau</persName> reported that on July 11 he made a detailed
                            presentation to <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName> of the
                            points in this telegram. <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>
                            responded that he had consulted his immediate circle, who confirmed
                                <persName corresp="#p_NGA1">Nasser</persName>’s immediate reaction
                            that inspection and verification in any form would be difficult for the
                                <gloss target="#t_UAR1">UAR</gloss> to accept because it would imply
                            reintroduction of Western control. (Ibid.)</note></p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RD3"><hi rend="strong">Rusk</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>