<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-11-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-11-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="90" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d90">
                    <head>90. Memorandum for the Record<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d90fn0">Source: Department of State, Special Group, Counterinsurgency Files:
                            Lot 68 D 451, Minutes of Meetings, November 5, 1962.
                        Secret.</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1962-11-05">November 5,
                            1962</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Minutes of Meeting of the Special Group (<gloss target="#t_CI1">CI</gloss>)</item>
                        <item>2 p.m., Monday, November 5, 1962</item>
                    </list>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>PRESENT</head>
                        <item>The Attorney General, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JJE1">Johnson</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCJA1">McCone</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HF5">Hamilton</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> vice Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GRL1">Gilpatric</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KMGVH1">General
                                Krulak</persName> vice General <persName corresp="#p_TMD1">Taylor</persName>, Mr. <persName>Wilson</persName> vice Mr.
                                <persName>Murrow</persName></item>
                        <item>Mr. <persName>Cottrell</persName> was present for Item 1.</item>
                        <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> and Mr.
                                <persName>Forrestal</persName> were present for Items 1 and
                            2.</item>
                        <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName> and Mr.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BJW3">Bowling</persName> were present for Item
                            2.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>[Here follows item 1 on Southeast Asia.]</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">2. Iran</hi></p>
                    <p>The Group discussed with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJW3">Bowling</persName> the internal security situation in Iran, and the
                        proposed outline internal defense plan for the country.<note n="1" xml:id="d90fn1">The paper was circulated to members of the Special Group
                            on November 1. (Ibid.)</note> It was noted that the plan represents
                        current rather than new programs for strengthening Iran’s internal security.
                        Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJW3">Bowling</persName> and the Ambassador
                        emphasized that Iran is not faced with a clear definable threat, and that
                        accordingly it would be difficult to identify specific targets against which
                        counterinsurgency programs should be aimed. In their opinion, the general
                        program for improving the socio/economic and security situation is the most
                        practical. Overall United States support to Iran is expected to run at the
                        level of 95 million dollars for Fiscal Year 1963. This is slightly less than
                        last year’s expenditure of 100 million dollars.</p>
                    <p>The Ambassador stressed that the first priority is the maintenance of
                        stability, under which socio/economic improvement may take place; that
                        stability is provided by the Shah, supported by the Army; and that our main
                        objective must be to support the Shah in order to gain the time required for
                        necessary reforms, and socio/economic progress. The Shah recognizes the
                        potential threats and is seeking to implement necessary reforms. His land
                        reform program is described by the Ambassador as truly revolutionary.</p>
                    <pb facs="0268" n="202" xml:id="pg_202"/>
                    <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJW3">Bowling</persName> described a shift in the
                        political situation which has occurred during the last several months.
                        Whereas in the past the Shah was allied and supported by the Army and the
                        elite versus the middle class and students, he has now through his reform
                        programs allied himself with the Army, the peasantry and the urban
                        proletariat versus the traditional elite, students and middle class.</p>
                    <p>The student problem is complicated by their inability to participate in
                        meaningful political activities, as elections are not being held during this
                        period, and participation in politics is accordingly limited to meetings and
                            discussions.<note n="2" xml:id="d90fn2">Following this meeting,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> sent <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName> a memorandum (with copies to
                                <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Kaysen</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KRF1">Robert Kennedy</persName>) that called Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName>’ presentation at the
                            meeting “one of the better snow jobs of recent memory.” He quoted
                                <persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName> as saying: “Iran is
                            the most stable country in the Middle East” and described the <persName corresp="#p_HJC2">Holmes</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_BJW3">Bowling</persName> presentation as: “(1) in general things are
                            going well in Iran; (2) existing programs are adequate, though of course
                            some more money would be welcome; (3) the present regime is being pushed
                            as hard as is feasible and is moving as fast as it can on the road to
                            reform.” <persName corresp="#p_KRW2">Komer</persName> found “such
                            euphoria hard to believe,” and advised: “if moving at the Shah’s pace
                            means just bottling up revolution, we’re again postponing the
                            inevitable. We need a ‘controlled revolution’ in Iran, and today’s
                            performance reinforces my conviction that we must promote one. We don’t
                            know where we’re going in Iran, and are inviting greater risks by
                            refusing to take lesser ones.” (<persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> Library, National Security Files, Countries
                            Series, Iran, 11/1/62–11/30/62)</note></p>
                    <p>[Here follow items 3 and 4 on unrelated matters.]</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_DTWJ1"><hi rend="strong">Thomas W. Davis,
                                    Jr.</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d90fn3">Printed from a
                                copy that bears this typed signature.</note><lb/><hi rend="italic">Executive Secretary</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>