<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of British Commonwealth and
                    Northern European Affairs (Foster) to the Deputy Under Secretary of State
                    (Matthews)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">106</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-05-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-05-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-05-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-05-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="106"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d106">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/5–2953</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Office of British
                        Commonwealth and Northern European Affairs (<persName type="from"
                            >Foster</persName>) to the Deputy Under Secretary of State (<persName
                            type="to">Matthews</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-05-29">May 29,
                            1953</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Answers to Ambassador Spender’s Questions Concerning Five-Power, <gloss
                            target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_ANZAM1"
                            >ANZAM</gloss> Military Representatives Groups.</item>
                </list>
                <p>I have checked with Charles Sullivan in Frank Nash’s office and I suggest that
                    you might wish to give Sir Percy Spender the following answers to the questions
                    he raised with you during his call on May 26:<note n="1" xml:id="d106fn1"
                        >Matthews’ memorandum of his conversation with Ambassador Spender on May 26
                        is not printed. (790.5/5–2653)</note>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Question: Where do we go from here in connection with
                                the Five-Power Staff Liaison Agency?</hi> Answer: The United States
                            recently approved the recommendations agreed to at the Five-Power
                            Military meeting at Pearl Harbor on April 6–10 and has so informed
                            Admiral Radford, U.S. member of the Group. Assuming that the other four
                            governments also approve the Group’s recommendations—and we understand
                            the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss>, New Zealand and France have
                            done so—we assume that the five Commanders will go forward as they
                            recommended. It is impossible at present to predict what form or status
                            the Five-Power Group might eventually assume, what possible new terms of
                            reference it might be given by the five governments, or what
                            relationships, if any, it might establish with other organizations. For
                            the moment, the agreement is, as Ambassador Spender knows, that the
                            Group is not to have a formal or elaborate organization but rests on an
                                <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi>, on-call, need-to-know basis. In due
                            course we would expect to hear Admiral Radford’s views on this.
                            Meanwhile we consider that the Five-Power Group is performing a very
                            useful service.</item>
                        <pb facs="0335" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Question: Is there any chance that the Five-Power
                                Group might supplant the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                                Military Representatives group?</hi> Answer: We certainly do not
                            think so. The <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> relationship rests
                            on a Treaty, and the Treaty established the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                                >ANZUS</gloss> Council. The Council obviously requires military
                            advisers. In terms of the substance of the Treaty and of the proper
                            functioning of the Council there has to be an <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                                >ANZUS</gloss> Military Representatives group. We have been very
                            pleased by the progress made by the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                                >ANZUS</gloss> Military Representatives group in which Admiral
                            Radford has been our Representative, and we understand the Australians
                            and New Zealanders have also been pleased. Those of us interested in
                                <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> are gratified by Admiral
                            Radford’s appointment to the Chairmanship of the Joint Chiefs of
                                Staff,<note n="2" xml:id="d106fn2">President Eisenhower had
                                nominated Admiral Radford for the post on May 12. He entered on duty
                                Aug. 15.</note> where he will bring with him first-hand knowledge of
                            the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> relationship.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Question: Would it be possible to establish a
                                relationship between <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> and
                                    <gloss target="#t_ANZAM1">ANZAM</gloss>?</hi> (Ambassador
                            Spender asked this question with particular reference to the forthcoming
                            Commonwealth Conference in London at which Churchill, Menzies, and
                            Holland are expected to discuss among themselves the United Kingdom
                            position vis-à-vis <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>. You will
                            recall that <gloss target="#t_ANZAM1">ANZAM</gloss> is the <gloss
                                target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss>–Australian-New Zealand military group,
                            with headquarters in Melbourne, which engages in planning for the
                            defense of the Australasian area.) Answer: The <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                                >ANZUS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ANZAM1">ANZAM</gloss> military
                            groups have certain common objectives, especially plans for the defense
                            of Southeast Asia. Moreover, certain individual Australian and New
                            Zealand military officers represent their countries in each group.
                            Again, as a matter of policy determined by the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                                >ANZUS</gloss> Council at the government level, the <gloss
                                target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> partners keep the United Kingdom
                            fully and currently informed of the plans and proceedings of the <gloss
                                target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council. Thus there exists a sound
                            basis for <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> cooperation. The question
                            whether some sort of formal relationship should be established between
                                <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> and <gloss
                                target="#t_ANZAM1">ANZAM</gloss> cannot be answered at present. We
                            should be interested to learn of any ideas that may come out of the
                            conversations in London, and on our side we shall eventually want to get
                            the views of Admiral Radford. Depending on these factors, the matter is
                            one which the Council might wish to discuss at its next meeting.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
