<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-08-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="115" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/8–2153</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Acting Secretary of State</gloss>
                            to the Secretary of Defense (<persName type="to">Wilson</persName>)</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d115fn1">Drafted in <gloss target="#t_BNA1">BNA</gloss> and cleared with <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> and G.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-08-21">August 21, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. Secretary</hi>: It is the purpose of this
                        letter to request the views of the Department of Defense on the question of
                        possible United Kingdom participation in <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>, perhaps at the military level. The question is likely to
                        be raised by the Australian and New Zealand Ministers at the forthcoming
                        meeting of the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council, which has
                        been tentatively set for September 9–10 in Washington.<note n="2" xml:id="d115fn2">Documents in file 790.5 for July, August, and September
                            of 1953 indicate that the three powers had settled upon these particular
                            dates so as to enable Casey and Webb to attend the Council meeting prior
                            to their previously scheduled attendance at the Eighth Session of the
                            UNGA, which opened in New York on Sept. 15.</note></p>
                    <p>As the Department of Defense knows, the problem of possible United Kingdom
                        participation in <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> was considered at
                        the first meeting of the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council at
                        Kaneohe in August 1952. It will be recalled in this regard that Article VIII
                        of the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Treaty authorizes the Council
                        to establish consultative relationships with other states or regional
                        organizations. The United Kingdom had expressed to each of the three
                        Governments its strong desire, based on its extensive interest in the
                        Pacific as well as on its Commonwealth ties with Australia and New Zealand,
                        to become associated in some manner with <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>, at least in an observer status.</p>
                    <p>Although the Council was sympathetically inclined toward the United Kingdom
                        position it concluded that it would be premature at this early stage in the
                        Council’s development for it to arrange for United Kingdom participation in
                            <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> or indeed to establish
                        relationships with any other states or regional organizations. The Council
                        had in mind that the participation of the United Kingdom in <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> at this time would expose the
                        enterprise to pressures from other governments seeking to participate,
                        notably the Philippines, France, Korea, Japan, and the Netherlands—pressures
                        it would be very difficult to withstand. The Council considered that the
                        irritations engendered by such pressures would militate against the growth
                        of the general spirit of the cooperation in the Pacific which it is the
                        fundamental purpose of <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> to foster.
                        The Council also had in mind the necessity of avoiding any step carrying the
                        possible implication that <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                        represented in the Pacific either a revival of “western imperialism” or an
                        instrument of “white supremacy”.</p>
                    <pb facs="0354" n="336" xml:id="pg_336"/>
                    <p>Nevertheless, recognizing the interest of the United Kingdom in the Pacific
                        area and the importance of the Commonwealth ties between Australia, New
                        Zealand and the United Kingdom, the Council agreed that there was nothing in
                        its discussions which it would have any reason to withhold from the United
                        Kingdom and it decided that the United Kingdom should be kept fully and
                        currently informed of its proceedings.</p>
                    <p>The United Kingdom Government has continued to be dissatisfied by its
                        “exclusion” from <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> and has made
                        several attempts during the past year to persuade the three <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Governments to reconsider their
                        position. Prime Minister Churchill discussed the matter with President-Elect
                        Eisenhower at New York last January and said that Prime Minister Menzies of
                        Australia had suggested the possibility of a liaison relationship between
                            <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ANZAM1">ANZAM</gloss> (the British-Australian-New Zealand Military Planning
                        Organization for the defense of Malaya and Australasia).</p>
                    <p>Another suggestion (which originated with Sir Frederick Shedden, Australian
                        Secretary of Defense)<note n="3" xml:id="d115fn3">Sir Frederick was
                            Permanent Secretary of that Department.</note> is that an officer of one
                        of the United States services, other than the separate service attaches at
                        Melbourne, might be accredited directly to the Australian Department of
                        Defense and sit, together with the senior United Kingdom Defense
                        representative, on the Australian Defense Committee when it considers <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_ANZAM1">ANZAM</gloss> matters. Sir Frederick indicated that such an arrangement
                        would be acceptable to his Department even without reciprocal access or
                        accreditation of an Australian officer to the Department of Defense in
                        Washington, which he realizes would not be acceptable to the Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff.</p>
                    <p>A third possibility is that advantage might be taken of the fact that
                        high-ranking officers of the United Kingdom services are occasionally
                        seconded to the Australian and New Zealand services; one of these officers
                        might be designated to participate in the Military Representatives group
                        accredited to the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council.</p>
                    <p>These suggestions, and there might well be others, all involve some kind of
                        United Kingdom participation in or liaison relationship with <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> at the military level. It is fully
                        appreciated that they are therefore of obvious and direct concern to the
                        Department of Defense.</p>
                    <p>For its part, the Department of State, bearing in mind not only the
                        substantial interests of the United Kingdom in the Pacific area and the
                        significance of the Commonwealth ties between the United Kingdom, Australia,
                        and New Zealand but also the importance of the Anglo-American relationship,
                        would like to find some means to meet the United Kingdom position without
                        risking the difficulties <pb facs="0355" n="337" xml:id="pg_337"/> which, as
                        noted above, influenced the Council’s decision a year ago. Apart from the
                        fact that there would be certain advantages to the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council in having a relationship with the United Kingdom,
                        the adoption of some means of meeting the United Kingdom position would
                        remove the pressures to which the three <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Governments have been subjected and would eliminate the
                        serious concern which has been felt in London over the “exclusion” of the
                        United Kingdom from <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>In view of the imminence of the forthcoming Council meeting, the Department
                        would appreciate receiving as soon as possible the views of the Department
                        of Defense concerning this problem. Officers of the Department of State
                        would of course be happy to discuss the matter with officers of your
                        Department if that were desired.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely yours,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Walter B. Smith</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>