<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-03-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-03-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="15" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Truman Library, Truman papers, PSF–Subject
                        file</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum for the President of Discussion at the 113th
                            Meeting of the National Security Council Held on Wednesday, March 5,
                            1952</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d15fn1">Prepared on Mar. 6, apparently in
                            the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Secretariat.</note></head>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Extract]</note>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1952-03-05">March 5, 1952</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The following notes contain a summary of the discussion at the 113th Meeting
                        of the National Security Council, at which you presided. Admiral Fechteler
                        attended the meeting for the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.<note n="2" xml:id="d15fn2">The meeting was attended by all the Council
                            members: President Truman; Vice President Barkley; W. Averell Harriman,
                            Director of Mutual Security; Jack Gorrie, Chairman of the National
                            Security Resources Board; and Secretaries Acheson and Lovett. Among the
                            seven others present were John W. Snyder, Secretary of the Treasury;
                            Charles E. Wilson, Director of Defense Mobilization; Walter Bedell
                            Smith, Director of Central Intelligence; Sidney W. Souers, Special
                            Consultant to the President; and Admiral Fechteler.</note></p>
                    <gap/>
                    <pb facs="0088" n="70" xml:id="pg_70"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">2. United States Objectives and Courses of
                            Action With Respect to Communist Aggression in Southeast Asia</hi>
                            (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124 and Annex to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124; Memo for <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> from Executive Secretary, same subject, dated March 4,
                            1952)<note n="3" xml:id="d15fn3">Not printed; it enclosed the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> memorandum to the Secretary of Defense
                            dated Mar. 3, cited in <ref target="#pg_55">footnote 2, p. 55</ref>.
                                (<gloss target="#t_SS2">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files, lot 63 D 351)</note></p>
                    <p>The President requested Secretary Acheson to make the first comments on
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124, particularly with respect to
                        what decisions the Council might come as to the best handling of the
                        report.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Acheson expressed the view that it would be premature to try to
                        reach a formal decision on <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124, but
                        instead the Council should discuss this and another paper he had in mind, as
                        a means of making progress without commitment. Secretary Acheson then
                        discussed briefly what he described as a “hen, chicken or egg” problem. The
                        Joint Chiefs of Staff, he pointed out, feel that they can not undertake to
                        make detailed studies of the military courses of action open to the United
                        States in Southeast Asia without first obtaining a political decision
                        regarding United States policy in that area. On the other hand, it was
                        difficult to reach a political decision without some knowledge of the
                        capabilities of the military to support certain courses of action. Secretary
                        Acheson went on to point out certain difficulties which were inherent in the
                        views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff with respect to the present report. In
                        illustration he cited their view that our allies, notably Britain and
                        France, were expected to support us if we became engaged in a war against
                        Communist China, but that we alone should undertake to run the show. He was
                        also doubtful about the British and French view of what was to be gained by
                        war against Communist China if in the course of it the British and French
                        were to lose their positions in the countries of Southeast Asia for which
                        they were responsible.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Acheson also emphasized his belief that any paper on Southeast Asia
                        should stress the contingency of a continued deterioration of the situation
                        in Indochina in the absence of any identifiable Communist aggression, and
                        should also take careful account of the possibility that the French might
                        feel compelled to get out of French Indochina. He said that he had discussed
                        this matter at considerable length in Lisbon, and had come to the tentative
                        conclusion that what the French really mean when they stress their
                        difficulties is that they cannot continue to carry their burden both in
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and in Indochina without
                        additional help from the United States. The French, he said, were also
                        seriously concerned about the ultimate effects of their losses in Indochina
                        on the whole French military manpower reserves. Accordingly, Secretary
                        Acheson <pb facs="0089" n="71" xml:id="pg_71"/> suggested that the Senior
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff be asked to undertake a
                        thoroughgoing study of the priority which should be accorded Indochina as
                        compared, for instance, to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, and what
                        the United States is really prepared to do in order to keep the French in
                        Indochina.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Acheson then produced and read from a series of assumptions<note n="4" xml:id="d15fn4">Reference is to the memorandum, <ref target="#d14"><hi rend="italic">supra</hi></ref>.</note> in the political
                        realm which he said the Joint Chiefs of Staff might take as a basis for
                        developing further military studies with regard to United States courses of
                        action in Southeast Asia. If these assumptions could be agreed upon,
                        Secretary Acheson believed that they would solve the Joint Chiefs’ problem
                        of developing studies on military courses of action in the absence of a
                        political decision.</p>
                    <p>The President then asked Secretary Lovett for his views.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Lovett explained that the Joint Chiefs of Staff views derive from
                        evidence in their possession of a lack of desire on the part of the British
                        and French to do more than conduct a perimeter defense of Southeast
                        Asia—that is, of British and French opposition to any proposal to broaden
                        the war by carrying it to Communist China. On the other hand, Secretary
                        Lovett agreed emphatically with Secretary Acheson that it would be
                        undesirable to attempt to reach a formal decision on <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124 at today’s meeting. He further agreed that the French
                        were very likely to attempt to get us to shoulder a larger part of the costs
                        of the Indochina campaign. Nevertheless, Secretary Lovett expressed strong
                        sympathy with the position taken by the Joint Chiefs of Staff that it was
                        difficult to go further into the details of military courses of action in
                        Southeast Asia in the absence of some clearer idea of the political
                        decision. Actually, said Secretary Lovett, there was nothing really
                        effective that we could do to prevent the Chinese Communists from seizing
                        Indochina if they were prepared to use military force to secure it. Not even
                        military action against Communist China itself could stop this, because a
                        considerable interval would elapse before the effect of military action
                        against Communist China would be felt on the periphery. In short, the effect
                        of a threat of war against Communist China was the hope that it would deter
                        the Chinese Communists from such a course. On the other hand, said Secretary
                        Lovett, if it is not the real intention of the Chinese Communists to seize
                        Indochina by military means, and if we wish to save Indochina over a period
                        of time, it would presumably be very sensible to spend more money, perhaps
                        even at the rate of a billion or a billion and a half dollars a year, in
                        support of resistance there. In any case, this would be very much cheaper
                        than an all-out war against <pb facs="0090" n="72" xml:id="pg_72"/>
                        Communist China, which would certainly cost us fifty billion dollars. These
                        matters ought to be explored carefully with the British and French before
                        the United States reaches any final military decisions. Secretary Lovett
                        also expressed his agreement that Indochina was most likely to go by
                        internal subversion or by other means than overt Chinese Communist
                        aggression. Since this matter was not dealt with at any length in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124, Secretary Lovett suggested that the
                        Senior <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff correct this deficiency and
                        consider what the United States could do if the situation in Southeast Asia
                        continued to deteriorate in the absence of identifiable aggression.</p>
                    <p>The Vice President asked for more details about what we were doing to assist
                        in Indonesia, Burma and Thailand.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Lovett replied that we had been giving military assistance to
                        Thailand but not to Burma or Indonesia.</p>
                    <p>The Vice President then inquired about what use might be made of Chinese
                        Nationalist forces. Do we intend, he asked, or do we plan to take such
                        forces with us into China in the event of war with China?</p>
                    <p>The answer to this, said Secretary Lovett, was “no”. The Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff have strongly recommended against the use of United States ground
                        forces inside China. We would be more likely to use the Nationalist troops
                        as guerrillas or as raiding forces. If we did so, he added, we would of
                        course have to transport such forces to their destinations.</p>
                    <p>With respect to the views of the Joint Chiefs of Staff on Southeast Asia,
                        Secretary Lovett said that he wished to emphasize three significant points
                        which they had brought out. The first of these, in paragraph 9,<note n="5" xml:id="d15fn5">Reference is to paragraph 9 of the memorandum cited in
                                <ref target="#pg_55">footnote 2, p. 55</ref>.</note> noted the grave
                        danger to U.S. security interests should Southeast Asia pass into the
                        Communist orbit. The second was the stress placed by the Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff on the undesirability of committing United States ground forces in
                        campaigns in the countries of Southeast Asia, and the undesirability of the
                        United States entering into any combined military command for the defense of
                        these countries. Thirdly, the Joint Chiefs of Staff were very emphatic
                        against the United States joining in any warning or ultimatum to Communist
                        China unless we were ready to back it up. We cannot afford to bluff.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, Secretary Lovett expressed himself as in accord with the
                        proposal of the Secretary of State that the problem be explored further and
                        that the deficiencies of the present paper be corrected. He proposed,
                        therefore, that <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124 be referred to the
                        Senior <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff and that the Joint Chiefs
                        of Staff be requested to <pb facs="0091" n="73" xml:id="pg_73"/> elaborate
                        their views on military courses of action on the basis of the political
                        assumptions which the Secretary of State had just read to the Council.</p>
                    <p>Admiral Fechteler expressed the hope that if this course were adopted by the
                        Council it would prove possible to develop an agreed set of assumptions
                        which would be realistic and would produce meaningful conclusions. Admiral
                        Fechteler expressed the view that the Joint Chiefs of Staff should join in
                        the development of the political assumptions to which Secretaries Acheson
                        and Lovett had referred.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lay traced briefly the genesis of <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        124, and pointed out that the paper had been developed out of fears widely
                        current at the end of 1951 that the Chinese Communists were about to launch
                        an overt attack on Indochina. It was for this reason, said Mr. Lay, that
                        emphasis in the paper had been on courses of action to counter identifiable
                        aggression, rather than on courses of action to counter deterioration of the
                        existing situation or to counter internal subversion in the countries of
                        Southeast Asia.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Souers suggested that the Senior <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                        Staff join with the representatives of the Joint Chiefs of Staff in working
                        out the political assumptions referred to by Secretaries Acheson and
                        Lovett.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Lovett expressed the opinion that two major problems needed a
                        thorough airing before any real answer could be given to the problem posed
                        for us by the situation in Southeast Asia. First, are the British and French
                        militarily prepared to join us in an ultimatum to Communist China, and to go
                        wherever such a course of action should lead? Secretary Lovett thought the
                        answer was “no” at present. Secondly, inasmuch as it was less likely that we
                        should face naked Chinese aggression in Southeast Asia than a deterioration
                        of the existing situation to a point where the French would throw in the
                        towel, the question we must face is, are we prepared to pick up this towel
                        at a cost, perhaps, of a billion or a billion and a half dollars a year?</p>
                    <p>Secretary Acheson explained what appeared to him to be the present British
                        and French concern about the type of action proposed in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124. In brief, this was that the courses of
                        action could easily lead to an all-out war against Communist China without
                        actually saving Southeast Asia itself.</p>
                    <p>General Smith expressed the opinion that when the chips were actually down,
                        the British and French would probably go along with us in the course of
                        action against Communist China. In general, he described the Joint Chiefs of
                        Staff comments as a highly realistic paper. It had, he felt, one deficiency,
                        namely, its tendency to imagine that the British could be held responsible
                        for saving Burma. General Smith expressed the view that while most of the
                            <pb facs="0092" n="74" xml:id="pg_74"/> fuss was currently over
                        Indochina, Burma was actually the weakest link in the chain.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Harriman asked if he was correct in assuming that while the Joint Chiefs
                        of Staff were developing their military studies the State Department would
                        parallel such studies by investigating what could be done to shore up the
                        political structure in Indochina.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Gorrie raised the question as to whether the courses of action discussed
                        at the meeting were likely to imply the need for a stepping-up of our
                        mobilization effort.</p>
                    <p>In answer to Mr. Gorrie’s question, Secretary Lovett replied that as far as
                        immediate assistance to Indochina was concerned, such assistance would have
                        to come at the expense of some other area. There simply was not enough to go
                        around. Moreover, he said that should the United States ultimately get into
                        a full-scale war with China, it would be obviously necessary to move into
                        full mobilization. Secretary Lovett also warned that there was no
                        possibility whatever of increasing the rate of production of essential
                        military end items before next December, even if we were now to determine to
                        go to full mobilization.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Wilson expressed general agreement with the statement of Secretary
                        Lovett, but nevertheless stated that in a few important cases it might well
                        be possible to step up production. However, if we were going to do so it was
                        essential to make the decision now. As an illustration, Mr. Wilson pointed
                        out that it would probably be possible to achieve a 25% increase in Sabre
                        jets in the course of the next year if we really wanted to do so.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Gorrie then inquired whether it would be necessary to step up the
                        mobilization effort if we issued an ultimatum along the lines indicated in
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124.</p>
                    <p>Secretary Lovett replied, “Unquestionably.”</p>
                    <p>Mr. Lay then stated to the Council his understanding of the action which it
                        had determined upon with respect to the present paper, namely, that the
                        Senior <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff would undertake to provide
                        a new set of assumptions on the basis of which the Departments of State and
                        Defense would develop further studies on diplomatic and military courses of
                        action in Southeast Asia in the contingency of overt aggression, and
                        secondly, that the Senior <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff would
                        undertake to provide a new report recommending courses of action to be
                        undertaken in the absence of identifiable aggression to counter continued
                        deterioration of the existing situation in Southeast Asia.<note n="6" xml:id="d15fn6">Secretary Acheson prepared a briefer account of this
                            meeting entitled “Report on <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            Meeting”. This document, dated Mar. 5, is in file
                        790.5/3–552.</note></p>
                    <pb facs="0093" n="75" xml:id="pg_75"/>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">The National Security Council:</hi><note n="7" xml:id="d15fn7">Paragraphs a-c constitute <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 614. (<gloss target="#t_SS2">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files, lot 66 D
                            95)</note>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Directed the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff to prepare
                                an agreed set of assumptions, along the lines suggested by the
                                Secretary of State, as a basis for further studies by the Department
                                of State and the Joint Chiefs of Staff, respectively, of diplomatic
                                and military courses of action to counter identifiable Communist
                                aggression in Southeast Asia.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Referred <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124 to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff for reconsideration in the
                                light of the above studies.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>Directed the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff to prepare
                                for Council consideration a report on U.S. courses of action in
                                Southeast Asia to counter continued deterioration of the existing
                                situation in the absence of identifiable Communist aggression.<note n="8" xml:id="d15fn8">The plan of action set forth in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 614 was not carried
                                    out fully. For a review of subsequent developments with regard
                                    to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 124 Series, see the
                                    memorandum from John M. Allison, Assistant Secretary of State
                                    for Far Eastern Affairs, to Acting Secretary Webb, June 25, <ref target="#pg_119">p. 119</ref>. This memorandum serves to
                                    clarify much of the intervening documentation on the
                                    subject.</note></item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>