<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-05-22T07:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-05-22T07:00:00-05:00" n="201" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d201">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/5–2254: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State (<persName type="from">Smith</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/><gloss target="#t_niact1">niact</gloss></hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-22T13:00:00+01:00">May 22, 1954—1
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_Dulte1">Dulte</gloss> 97. Eyes only Secretary. Re <gloss target="#t_Tedul1">Tedul</gloss>s 93 and 98.<note n="1" xml:id="d201fn1">Both dated May 20, <ref target="#pg_493">pp. 493</ref> and <ref target="#pg_501">501</ref>, respectively.</note> Eden left early
                        this morning for Paris and London before I had time to analyze or to speak
                        to him regarding our <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> recommendations on
                        the British text re five-power staff talks.</p>
                    <p>Since I received these comments in <gloss target="#t_Tedul1">Tedul</gloss>
                        93, you have probably seen Avis Gento 32 of 21 May<note n="2" xml:id="d201fn2"><p>This Army telegram was received in the Department of
                                State on May 28. It reads in part:</p>
                            <p>“Eden has concurred British Joint Chiefs Proposal to conduct
                                Washington five-power talks at Chief of Staff level. Propose send
                                Army chiefs. Accompanying will be advisors (major general rank) from
                                three services. Australia and New Zealand concur.</p>
                            <p>“British <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss> Geneva yesterday cabled
                                British Joint Chiefs recommending following subjects be considered
                                at Washington: <list>
                                    <item>“1. Military situation Indochina, making use of new
                                        information obtained by General Ely and team.</item>
                                    <item>“2. Courses of action in event no Indochina settlement is
                                        reached Geneva.</item>
                                    <item>“3. Courses of action in event settlement is reached
                                        Geneva.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>“Consensus working level British delegate Geneva that discussion
                                points 2 and 3 above should include consideration of: a. Immediate
                                deterrents, b. Strengthening SEA countries against internal
                                Communism, c. Strengthening SEA countries against external
                                Communism.</p>
                            <p>“Monckton believes discussions should focus on Associated States,
                                Thailand and Burma but not necessarily to exclusion of other SEA
                                countries.</p>
                            <p>“British delegate Geneva believes it necessary to consider political
                                as well as military factors during Washington talks. British
                                representatives will have brief prepared by Eden as guide.”
                                (790.5/5–2854)</p></note> reporting summary given him<note n="3" xml:id="d201fn3">Vice Admiral Arthur C. Davis.</note> by Colonel
                        Monckton, British military adviser. You will note that the British propose
                        these talks be conducted at Chief of Staff level, Australia and New Zealand
                        concurring. They intend to send to Washington the Army Chief of Staff,
                        General Harding, with advisers of major general rank from the other three
                        services. This automatically lifts talks above level of “five-power staff
                        agency”.</p>
                    <p>You will also note the comprehensive items for discussion proposed by British
                        delegation here to British Chiefs of Staff, which I assume will be
                        adopted.</p>
                    <p>Under these circumstances, I am extremely reluctant to open up again the
                        whole matter with Eden on the basis of our <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> comments, some of which I think are no longer pertinent,
                        and most of which I think should be settled by these senior staff officers
                        themselves when they first meet in Washington.</p>
                    <pb facs="0526" n="508" xml:id="pg_508"/>
                    <p>Department’s assumption that omission of informing Associated States from
                        Eden’s memo<note n="4" xml:id="d201fn4">See telegram <gloss target="#t_Dulte1">Dulte</gloss> 84, May 18, <ref target="#pg_488">p. 488</ref>.</note> is an oversight, is correct. He understands
                        they will be informed. He also understands that the information which will
                        be given by the several participants to their Asiatic proteges as to terms
                        of reference will vary. His wording is that which he proposes to use to
                        those nations that will be informed by Britain, and I told him that we would
                        probably modify it to a certain extent in speaking to the countries whom we
                        are to inform.</p>
                    <p>I have pushed this matter pretty hard with Eden because I believe that these
                        talks were desirable to lay some of the dust which has been raised about
                        disunity, and also because I believe that serious military technical
                        discussions are imperative.</p>
                    <p>So far as joint participation in staff conversations are concerned, the first
                        objective has already been accomplished by the press. The scope and
                        effectiveness of the second will depend very largely on the ability of the
                        soldiers to get down to serious business, and as we have quite enough points
                        of friction here, I would hope to be relieved of the necessity of going
                        again to Eden on this matter unless a real major issue arises.</p>
                    <p>Monckton informed us that Eden is very concerned about the leak to the
                        British press of details regarding the five-power talks and that a thorough
                        investigation is being made both at London and at Geneva to determine the
                        source.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>