<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-06T15:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-06T15:00:00-05:00" n="236" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d236">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, <gloss target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 341</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, Prepared in the Department
                            of State</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d236fn1"><p>This document is at Tab 6
                                of a group of papers entitled “Documentary History of US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Joint Study Group”.</p>
                            <p>Department of State participants not previously identified include
                                Herman Phleger, Legal Adviser; Charles C. Stelle, a member of the
                                Policy Planning Staff; William R. Tyler, Deputy Director of the
                                Office of Western European Affairs; and Edmund A. Gullion, also of
                                the Policy Planning Staff; Morris Draper, an Administrative
                                Assistant in the Executive Secretariat.</p>
                            <p>From the Department of Defense, Charles A. Sullivan was Deputy for
                                American, South Asian, and Far Eastern Affairs in the Office of
                                Foreign Military Affairs.</p></note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-07-06T16:00:00-04:00">July 6, 1954—4–5:30 p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">State-Defense Discussions Of Forthcoming
                                US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Study Group Meetings</hi></p>
                    <list type="participants">
                        <head>Participants:</head>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">State</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>The Under Secretary</item>
                                <item>Mr. MacArthur/Mr. Murphy</item>
                                <item>Mr. Bonbright</item>
                                <item>Mr. Drumright</item>
                                <item>Mr. Phleger</item>
                                <item>Mr. Stelle</item>
                                <item>Mr. Tyler</item>
                                <item>Mr. Sturm</item>
                                <item>Mr. Gullion</item>
                                <item>Mr. Draper</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Defense</hi>
                            <list>
                                <item>Admiral Davis</item>
                                <item>Mr. Sullivan</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Mr. Murphy opened the meeting.</p>
                    <p>Mr. MacArthur reviewed the recent history leading up to the US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Joint Study Group meetings. The first meeting
                        will be held July 7 at 4:00. The British will be represented by Sir Robert
                        Scott, Michael Joy and others, and we will have General Smith as our chief
                        representative.</p>
                    <p>Admiral Davis said that he and Mr. Sullivan would be the Defense
                        representatives. The Admiral said that Defense hopes these talks will be of
                        a generalized nature and not get to specific military topics for the time
                        being.</p>
                    <p>Mr. MacArthur plans to recommend that General Smith take the position
                        regarding publicity for these talks that no communiqués or background
                        statements will be issued, that they are exploratory and technical. We will
                        keep our public relations people advised, but not of the substance.</p>
                    <pb facs="0619" n="601" xml:id="pg_601"/>
                    <p>Mr. MacArthur said that the Secretary wished to emphasize item two (… terms
                        of a collective security pact …)<note n="2" xml:id="d236fn2">Ellipses in the
                            source text.</note> and leave to the British any proposals they may wish
                        to forward on the other three items.<note n="3" xml:id="d236fn3">Reference
                            is to the numbered paragraphs of the Agreed Minute of June 27, <ref target="#pg_580">p. 580</ref>.</note> The Secretary had directed Mr.
                        Phleger to prepare two papers: 1) a draft treaty, which will not be tabled
                        with the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>; and 2) a working paper
                        incorporating what we believe should be included in a possible draft treaty,
                        this paper to be tabled with the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> as
                        representing the unofficial ideas of the US half of the Study Group.</p>
                    <p>Mr. MacArthur said that the Secretary wants the British to take the
                        initiative on item 1. At an appropriate time, our position should be that we
                        would be prepared to respect an agreement on the seven points communicated
                        to the French. If there were such an agreement, we might sign with other
                        countries a declaration that the countries involved would individually
                        respect the agreement and would not use force to upset it. The Secretary
                        does not want to push the British on item 3 at this time. Item 4, he thinks,
                        will not come up in the first few meetings but at an appropriate time we
                        would urge that the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Pact countries,
                        Thailand, the Philippines, and probably France be invited to the talks.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Phleger outlined his rough draft treaty,<note n="4" xml:id="d236fn4">Text
                            of a draft of this date or earlier has not been found in Department of
                            State files.</note> showing how it uses the pertinent language from the
                        Rio Pact, the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Pact and the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Treaty. This will mean that the possible
                        signatories to the treaty, with the exception of Thailand, will have signed
                        similar language before, and that this would merely mean an extension of
                        commitments they have already undertaken in other areas of the world.</p>
                    <p>There are, he said, a number of questions: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Area:</hi> He was thinking of Southeast Asia and
                                Southwest Pacific. Should it be larger, and perhaps designed to
                                include Pakistan at some time? (The draft treaty is open-ended.)</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Parties:</hi> Who would participate besides the US,
                                    <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, France, New Zealand and
                                Australia? The Secretary thinks it might be best not to name anyone
                                as perhaps we can get in the Associated States and others.</p>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Operative Provisions:</hi> He explained how and
                                where the language was lifted, i.e., from <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> “… act to meet the common danger under respective
                                constitutional processes”, the idea of a Council from the Rio Pact.
                                He explained that the treaty would be broad since councils of
                                consultation could be called to discuss action taking place outside
                                the immediate area which could nevertheless be a threat.</p>
                            <pb facs="0620" n="602" xml:id="pg_602"/>
                            <p><hi rend="italic">Duration:</hi> The Secretary was thinking of five
                                years with a one year notice of withdrawal.</p></quote></p>
                    <p>Mr. Phleger explained in some detail the subsidiary bodies which might be
                        formed under the treaty. Admiral Davis suggested calling the “Defense
                        Committee” the “Military Committee” and cited some of the experiences of the
                        Working Group negotiating the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            Treaty.<note n="5" xml:id="d236fn5">For documentation on negotiation of
                            this treaty, see <ref target="frus1948v03#pg_1"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1948, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff., and <ref target="frus1949v04#pg_1"><hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 1949, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff.</note> Mr. MacArthur pointed out that
                        some of the difficulties encountered in preparing the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Treaty could be avoided this time.</p>
                    <p>General Smith entered at this point and the discussion was reviewed. He asked
                        Mr. MacArthur to prepare a talking paper for the meeting the next day with
                        the British, suggesting that he would like to table “a bit of paper” on
                        perhaps what precisely we meant in the seven point reply to the French.<note n="*" xml:id="d236fn6">(Mr. MacArthur explained that Mr. Phleger’s
                            “working paper” would serve this purpose.) [Footnote in the source text.
                            The reference is perhaps to a draft of Phleger’s working paper of July
                            7, <ref target="#pg_609">p. 609</ref>.]</note> He agreed that Mr.
                        Phleger’s draft treaty was very good but wondered whether the negotiation
                        for a multilateral treaty would consume months and whether we should
                        therefore try for a declaration similar to the “Declaration of Common
                            Intent”<note n="6" xml:id="d236fn7">Printed in <ref target="frus1952-54v13p1#pg_1314">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">xiii</hi>, Part 1, p. 1314</ref>.</note> handed to the British
                        in April.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Phleger pointed out that a treaty was necessary to get some solid
                        commitments and that a declaration was too easy to sign. The pattern of the
                        treaty has precedent. General Smith thought it would be good to keep the
                        Declaration idea in reserve in case things got bogged down.</p>
                    <p>In discussing the area the treaty would cover, Admiral Davis said the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> would prefer that the whole problem in the
                        Pacific be handled as one grand exercise and that India be kept out of
                        everything.</p>
                    <p>The meeting closed with a discussion of the possibility of our return to
                        Geneva when the Ministerial discussions resume. General Smith hopes to lay
                        down the problem to the Congress and get bi-partisan support for whatever we
                        may be forced to do in the way of associating ourselves with the Indochina
                        settlement.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>