<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, Prepared in the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-09T15:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-09T15:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                    <term ref="recxoy5ut8BiKquym" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006004857"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Littoral</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-09T15:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-09T15:30:00-05:00" n="242"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Secretary’s Memoranda of Conversation, lot 64 D
                    199</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, Prepared in the Department of
                        State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d242fn1">Of the participants listed below William J.
                        Galloway was Special Assistant to MacArthur.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-07-09T16:30:00-04:00"
                            >July 9, 1954—4:30–5:20 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>[Mr. Dulles]</item>
                    <item>Mr. Phleger</item>
                    <item>Mr. MacArthur</item>
                    <item>Admiral Davis</item>
                    <item>Mr. Bonbright</item>
                    <item>Mr. Tyler</item>
                    <item>Mr. Stelle</item>
                    <item>Mr. Gullion</item>
                    <item>Mr. Sturm</item>
                    <item>Mr. Galloway</item>
                    <item>Mr. Draper</item>
                </list>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Secretary reviewed the draft Southeast Asian Collective Security Pact
                        prepared at an earlier meeting (in which the Secretary was not present) and,
                        with minor changes, agreed that it could be tabled as an informal and
                        unofficial working draft at the next US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                        working group meeting Saturday, July 10.<note n="2" xml:id="d242fn2">
                            <p>The text of a U.S. working draft of a Southeast Asia security treaty,
                                dated July 9, is included among the comparative drafts in <gloss
                                    target="#t_SEAP1">SEAP</gloss> D–2, “Draft Southeast Asia
                                Collective Security Treaty”, dated Aug. 2, <ref target="#pg_686">p.
                                    686</ref>.</p>
                            <p>“<gloss target="#t_SEAP1">SEAP</gloss>”, standing for “Southeast Asia
                                Pact” was the series indicator used to denote documents prepared and
                                collected for the use of officials engaged in this project.</p>
                        </note>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The Secretary and participants were unsuccessful in defining the precise
                        geographical limits to be encompassed by the terms of the treaty. It was
                        agreed that the terminology in sub-paragraph 1 of Article III “In the area
                        of Southeast Asia and the Southwestern Pacific …” would be worked out in the
                        meetings with the British. <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>(a) the other participants had earlier decided that a better phrase
                                might be “Southeast Asia and the <hi rend="italic">Western</hi>
                                Pacific” since this would be practically limitless in scope and
                                area, as the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> seem to prefer. It
                                was tentatively agreed in the earlier meeting that including Hong
                                Kong within the all-inclusive phrase “Western Pacific”, while
                                somewhat disadvantageous to us now, might provide the opportunity
                                within five years, for example, to bring in Japan, the <gloss
                                    target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss> and Formosa, and of course all the
                                countries on the South Asian littoral.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The Secretary was not particularly happy with the idea of including Hong
                        Kong and attempted, with some difficulty, to draw a line along the preferred
                        longitudes and latitudes which would <pb facs="0633" n="615" xml:id="pg_615"
                        /> eliminate that British outpost. It was demonstrated, moreover, that areas
                        such as New Caledonia, way out on the fringes of the hypothetical line,
                        embrace a good many of the areas such as Portuguese Timor with which we have
                        little if any concern.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>In discussing the possible inclusion of France in this security
                        arrangement the Secretary voiced his reluctance to allowing France to
                        obstruct our present path. However the general consensus was that the
                        exclusion of France would be self-defeating and that several hundred
                        thousand French troops of Southeast Asia could still be counted a formidable
                        force. Furthermore, unless the French Union disintegrates, the French will
                        be obligated to protect their weaker partners (which of course is our
                        intention as well).</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
