<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-18T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-18T17:00:00-05:00" n="253" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d253">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 GE/7–1854: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Under Secretary of State (<persName type="from">Smith</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss></hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Geneva</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-07-18T23:00:00+01:00">July 18, 1954—11
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 649. Limit distribution. I think
                            <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> message to Colombo powers, Australia
                        and New Zealand (<gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 644)<note n="1" xml:id="d253fn1">From Geneva, dated July 18. In this telegram, not
                            printed, Smith had transmitted a draft message from Eden to the Colombo
                            powers. (396.1 GE/7–1854) A copy of the message as transmitted, dated
                            July 18, was handed to the Secretary by Sir Roger Makins on July 19. In
                            it the United Kingdom invited the recipient powers to join with itself
                            and the United States, in the event an Indochina agreement was not
                            reached, in issuing a declaration of intention to set up immediately an
                            interim committee to prepare early recommendations on the conclusion of
                            a Southeast Asia–Southwest Pacific collective defense agreement.
                            (751G.00/7–1854) For text, see <ref target="frus1952-54v16#pg_1434">vol.
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">xvi</hi>, p. 1434</ref>.</note> is
                        satisfactory <pb facs="0662" n="644" xml:id="pg_644"/> step forward
                        particulary since Eden is talking in terms of making declaration of
                        intention as early as Thursday, July 22 in event of failure Geneva
                        negotiations. Message itself may have salutary effect on work of conference
                        when Communist delegates become aware of <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                        approach to Colombo powers.</p>
                    <p>Should, however, conference produce settlement Eden is hoping for more time
                        and would like a delay of two or three weeks before making declaration of
                        intention. His thought is that first thing following a settlement is to get
                        Colombo powers to declare their support thereof and with this in mind is
                        suggesting to them a form of words along the lines of proposed US unilateral
                        declaration. It is clear that in this eventuality we will need to keep
                        pushing Eden for earliest possible action.</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Smith</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>