<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Public Affairs Adviser in the Office of
                    European Regional Affairs (Nunley)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d278</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">278</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="collective-security" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="collective-security">Collective Security</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recdbjtxjnHuY2yic" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ministerial meeting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-07-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-07-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="278"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d278">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 60 D 627, <gloss
                        target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 355</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Public Affairs Adviser in
                        the Office of European Regional Affairs (Nunley)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1954-07-29">July 29,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Southeast Asia Pact</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>Mr. Robert Scott, British Minister</item>
                    <item>Mr. MacArthur, Counselor</item>
                    <item>Mr. Galloway, <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. Nunley, RA</item>
                </list>
                <p>Mr. Scott called on Mr. MacArthur at 3:00 o’clock July 29 to inform him of a
                    message received July 28 from Foreign Secretary Eden concerning US proposals for
                    moving ahead with a Southeast Asia security treaty. Mr. Scott said the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> is unable to commit itself at this time to the
                    schedule proposed by the US (declaration <pb facs="0701" n="683" xml:id="pg_683"
                    /> of intention on August 7, followed by a ministerial conference about
                    September 6). Nor can it commit itself on the device of a simultaneous identical
                    announcement of intention by the founding governments. Mr. Scott explained that
                    Mr. Eden is still very keen on sounding out the Colombo Powers on associating
                    themselves with the Geneva settlement, and is apparently giving this matter
                    first priority. He said Mr. Eden is also anxious that the Colombo Powers be
                    given an opportunity fully to discuss the proposed Asian security arrangement.
                    The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> believes it would be premature at this
                    time for the US to discuss the terms of a joint announcement of intention with
                    other countries.</p>
                <p>Mr. Scott reported that there appears some possibility that both Pakistan and
                    Ceylon may be willing to join in the proposed SEA security arrangement, and Mr.
                    Scott said such a development might easily pave the way for Burmese accession.
                    Both Mr. Scott and Mr. MacArthur expressed the view that such participation
                    would be a very interesting development.</p>
                <p>Mr. MacArthur inquired about the meaning of the message as related to the
                    original agreement between Foreign Secretary Eden and Under Secretary Smith. Mr.
                    Scott expressed the view that the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> Government
                    does not intend any change in this agreement. He feels that the program of
                    completing consultations with the Colombo powers by August 7 and the holding of
                    a meeting about September 1 still stands. However, Mr. Scott was unable to
                    estimate when the US might expect a definitive position from the British
                    Government on the question of issuing an identical announcement of intention by
                    August 7. Mr. MacArthur stressed the advantages of the simultaneous announcement
                    procedure as opposed to a procedure of issuing invitations from the US and
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> to other countries, and Mr. Scott
                    expressed a personal preference for the simultaneous announcement
                        procedure.<note n="1" xml:id="d278fn1">
                        <p>In Galloway’s memorandum of a conversation held between himself,
                            Merchant, and Stelle, and Sir Robert Scott on Aug. 3, the U.S. position
                            on this issue is set forth in more detail:</p>
                        <p>“From the U.S. standpoint, the issuance by the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                                >U.K.</gloss> of formal invitations to the Colombo Powers would
                            create difficulties for the U.S. which had agreed that countries such as
                            Nationalist China, Japan, and the <gloss target="#t_ROK1">ROK</gloss>
                            would not be invited to participate as initial members in a Collective
                            Security Arrangement. Also, it was most desirable that the formation of
                            such a Collective Security Arrangement should, as far as possible, bear
                            the stamp of initiative of Asian countries, and invitations extended by
                            the U.S. and the <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> would conflict with
                            this Objective” (Conference files, lot 60 D 627, <gloss target="#t_CF1"
                                >CF</gloss> 355)</p>
                    </note> Mr. MacArthur also emphasized the fact that considerable work will have
                    to be done before an announcement can be issued and that it is extremely urgent
                    to obtain a definite British decision on the announcement procedure and
                    time-table as soon as possible.</p>
                <pb facs="0702" n="684" xml:id="pg_684"/>
                <p>Mr. Scott pointed out that Mr. Eden also has very definite views about the
                    relation of Cambodia to the defense arrangement. Regardless of Cambodia’s legal
                    capacity to join a pact, Mr. Eden feels the entire Geneva settlement was based
                    upon the presumption that Cambodia would not become a member of a collective
                    security arrangement in that area. Mr. Scott made it clear that this refers to
                    membership only and that any treaty agreed upon can still extend protection to
                    Cambodia and perhaps provide means for concrete military assistance to
                    Cambodia.</p>
                <p>Mr. MacArthur said he is committed to keep the representatives of France,
                    Thailand, and the Philippines informed of developments and also to give them a
                    working draft of a declaration of intention. He said he would stress the fact
                    that it has no official status and is a working paper only. He again referred to
                    the need for agreement on the terms of a simultaneous announcement, the
                    establishment of an informal working group, and an agreement on a place and date
                    for a September meeting before the announcement can be issued, and urged Mr.
                    Scott to seek further advice from London as soon as possible.</p>
                <p>Mr. Scott agreed to pursue this matter, but pointed out that the pressure of
                    other work (such as the Suez issue), the many problems which have arisen during
                    the past week connected with the Parliament’s adjournment tomorrow, etc., have
                    undoubtedly affected the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>’s attention to this
                    problem. This may make it difficult to clean up all the outstanding questions in
                    time to meet the August 7 deadline for a simultaneous announcement proposed by
                    the US.</p>
                <p>With respect to the proposed working group which would prepare for the
                    ministerial meeting, Mr. Scott asked whether its functions would be limited to
                    drafting provisions of the Treaty or whether it might perform other functions.
                    Mr. MacArthur said the US has conceived of the working group primarily as a
                    drafting group, but it might also afford an opportunity for a general exchange
                    of views on an interim organizational arrangement. He said the US would
                    appreciate any ideas which the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> may wish to
                    contribute on this subject.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
