<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-04T03:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-04T03:00:00-05:00" n="348" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d348">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">396.1 MA/9–454: Telegram</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in the Philippines (<persName type="from">Spruance</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Department of
                                State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d348fn1">Content of this
                            telegram indicates that it was prepared by the U.S. Delegation to the
                            Manila Conference. Telegram transmitted in four sections.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Manila</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-04T16:00:00+08:00">September 4, 1954—4
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p><gloss target="#t_Secto1">Secto</gloss> 9. Working group concluded sessions
                        September 4 with following text to be presented to Ministers on September
                        6:</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Verbatim Text</hi></p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">Southeast Asia Collective Defense
                            Treaty</hi></p>
                    <p>Preamble</p>
                    <p>The parties to this Treaty, recognizing the sovereign equality of all the
                        parties, <hi rend="italic">reaffirming the principles of self determination
                            and the right of all peoples to self government or independence</hi>,
                        (see note 1)</p>
                    <pb facs="0858" n="840" xml:id="pg_840"/>
                    <p>Reiterating their faith in the purposes and principles set forth in the
                        Charter of the United Nations and their desire to live in peace with all
                        peoples and all governments,</p>
                    <p>Desiring to strengthen the fabric of peace and freedom and to uphold the
                        principles of Democracy, individual liberty, <hi rend="italic">self
                            determination of peoples</hi>, (see note 2) the rule of law, and to
                        promote the economic well-being and development of all peoples in the Treaty
                        area,</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Noting the agreements concluded on 20th July, 1954, at the
                            Geneva Conference and declaring that any renewal of the aggression in
                            violation of the aforesaid agreements would be a matter of grave
                            international concern</hi>, (see note 3)</p>
                    <p>Intending to declare publicly and formally their sense of unity, so that any
                        potential (Communist) (see note 4) aggressor will appreciate that the
                        parties stand together in the area, and</p>
                    <p>Desiring further to coordinate their efforts for collective defense for the
                        preservation of peace and security,</p>
                    <p>Therefore agree as follows: <list>
                            <item><p>Article I</p>
                                <p>The parties undertake, as set forth in the Charter of the United
                                    Nations, to settle any international disputes in which they may
                                    be involved by peaceful means in such a manner that
                                    international peace and security and justice are not endangered,
                                    and to refrain in their international relations from the threat
                                    or use of force in any manner inconsistent with the purposes of
                                    the United Nations. (Agreed)</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article II</p>
                                <p>In order more effectively to achieve the objectives of this
                                    Treaty, the parties, separately and jointly, by means of
                                    continuous and effective self-help and (mutual aid) (see note 5)
                                    will maintain and develop their individual and collective
                                    capacity to resist armed attack (and to prevent and overcome
                                    subversive activities directed from without against their
                                    territorial integrity and political stability). (See note
                                6)</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article III</p>
                                <p>The parties undertake to strengthen their free institutions and
                                    to cooperate with one another and with other free States in the
                                    further development of economic measures, including technical
                                    assistance, designed to promote economic progress and social
                                    wellbeing and to supplement the individual and collective
                                    efforts of government toward these ends. (See note 8)</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article IV</p>
                                <pb facs="0859" n="841" xml:id="pg_841"/>
                                <p>1. Each party recognized that (Communist) (see note 9) aggression
                                    by means of armed attack in the Treaty area against any of the
                                    parties or against Cambodia, Laos, or the territory under the
                                    jurisdiction of the Free Vietnamese Government, or against any
                                    States or territory which the parties by unanimous agreement may
                                    hereafter designate, would endanger its own peace and safety,
                                    and agrees that it (would act to meet the common danger in
                                    accordance with its constitutional processes) (see note 10).
                                    Measures taken under this paragraph shall be immediately
                                    reported to the Security Council of the United Nations. (See
                                    note 11)</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article IV</p>
                                <p>2. If in the opinion of any of the parties, the inviolability or
                                    the integrity of the territory or the sovereignty or political
                                    independence of any party in the Treaty area or of any other
                                    State or territory to which the provisions of paragraph 1 from
                                    time to time apply is threatened in any way other than by armed
                                    attack or is affected or threatened by any other fact or
                                    situation which might endanger the peace of the area, the
                                    parties shall consult immediately in order to agree on the
                                    measures which should be taken for the common defense. (See note
                                    12)</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article V</p>
                                <p>The parties hereby establish a Council, on which each of them
                                    shall be represented, to consider matters concerning the
                                    implementation of this Treaty. <hi rend="italic">The Council
                                        shall set up such subsidiary machinery as may be necessary
                                        to achieve the military and other objectives of the
                                        Treaty</hi>. (See note 13) The Council is empowered to
                                    arrange with States not parties to the Treaty for cooperation in
                                    giving effect to any of the provisions of the Treaty. The
                                    Council shall be so organized as to be able to meet at any
                                    time.</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article VI</p>
                                <p>This Treaty does not affect and shall not be interpreted as
                                    affecting in any way the rights and obligations of any of the
                                    parties under the Charter of the United Nations or the
                                    responsibility of the United Nations for the maintenance of
                                    international peace and security. Each party declares that none
                                    of the international engagements now in force between it and any
                                    other of the parties or any third party is in conflict with the
                                    provisions of this Treaty, and undertakes not to enter into any
                                    international engagement in conflict with this Treaty.
                                    (Agreed)</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article VII</p>
                                <p>The parties may by unanimous agreement invite any other States in
                                    a position to further the objectives of this Treaty and to <pb facs="0860" n="842" xml:id="pg_842"/> contribute to the
                                    security of the area to accede to this Treaty. Any State so
                                    invited may become a party to the Treaty by depositing its
                                    instruments of accession with the government of (blank). The
                                    government of (blank) will inform each of the parties of the
                                    deposit of each such instrument of accession. (See note
                                14)</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article VIII (See note 15)</p>
                                <p>As used in this Treaty, the “Treaty area” is the general area of
                                    Southeast Asia and of the Southwest Pacific, not including the
                                    Pacific area north of 21 degrees 30 minutes north latitude. The
                                    parties may by unanimous agreement amend this article to include
                                    within the Treaty area the territory of States acceding to this
                                    Treaty in accordance with Article VII or otherwise to change the
                                    Treaty area.</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article IX</p>
                                <p>This Treaty shall be ratified and its provisions carried out by
                                    the parties in accordance with their respective constitutional
                                    processes. The instruments of ratification shall be deposited as
                                    soon as possible with the government of the (blank) which shall
                                    notify all of the other signatories of such deposit.</p>
                                <p>The Treaty shall enter into force between the States which have
                                    ratified it as soon as the ratifications of a majority of the
                                    signatories shall be deposited, and shall come into effect with
                                    respect to other States on the date of the deposit of their
                                    ratification. (See note 16)</p></item>
                            <item><p>Article X</p>
                                <p>This Treaty shall remain in force indefinitely, but any party may
                                    cease to be a party one year after its notice of denunciation
                                    has been given to the government of (blank), which will inform
                                    the governments of the other parties of the deposit of each
                                    notice of denunciation. (See note 17) <list>
                                        <item>Note 1: Addition proposed by the Pakistan delegation
                                            as an alternative to the additional Article IV proposed
                                            by the Philippine delegation.</item>
                                        <item>Note 2: Proposed insertion by the Thai
                                            delegation.</item>
                                        <item>Note 3: The Australian delegation proposes the
                                            insertion of this paragraph.</item>
                                        <item>Note 4: The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>,
                                            Australian, New Zealand, France, Philippine, and
                                            Pakistan delegations oppose the inclusion of the word
                                            “Communist.” This matter will be referred to the
                                            Ministers for resolution.</item>
                                        <item>Note 5: The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                                            delegation proposes the substitution of “consultation
                                            and cooperation with one another.” The Pakistan
                                            delegation proposes the substitution of “assistance” for
                                            “aid.”</item>
                                        <item>Note 6: The French delegation proposes the deletion of
                                            this language.</item>
                                        <item><p>Note 7: The Pakistan delegation proposes for the
                                                whole article: <pb facs="0861" n="843" xml:id="pg_843"/>
                                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“In order to promote economic stability and
                                                  social well-being and thereby remove a basic cause
                                                  of weakness in the Treaty area, the parties
                                                  recognize the urgent need for fuller and more
                                                  effective development of economic resources in the
                                                  area, and undertake to cooperate with one another
                                                  for the purpose. The parties appreciate the
                                                  desirability of supplementing present economic and
                                                  technical assistance available to the area and of
                                                  continuing the utilization of existing bilateral
                                                  arrangements for the purpose where they are
                                                  regarded as adequate.”</p></quote></p>
                                            <p>The French delegation proposes for the whole article:
                                                  <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“In the economic field the parties undertake to
                                                  cooperate between themselves and with other
                                                  countries animated by the same intentions.</p>
                                                  <p>“They will take collectively or individually,
                                                  the measures destined to insure economic
                                                  stability, to promote agricultural and industrial
                                                  development and equipment and to encourage social
                                                  well-being in the area defined under Article VIII
                                                  below.</p>
                                                  <p>“To this end, they will study the requests for
                                                  assistance which may be directed to them and will
                                                  back them with their authority as appropriate.
                                                  They will have recourse, as need may be, to the
                                                  adequate existing
                                            organizations.”</p></quote></p></item>
                                        <item>Note 8: The Philippine [delegation] proposes a new
                                            article to be inserted after this article and to be
                                            numbered as Article IV: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                <p>“The parties recognize and will uphold the
                                                  principle of self-determination and the right of
                                                  the peoples in the area of Southeast Asia and
                                                  Southwest Pacific to self-government or
                                                  independence.”</p></quote></item>
                                        <item>Note 9: The <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>,
                                            Australian, New Zealand and Pakistan delegations propose
                                            deletion of the bracketed word.</item>
                                        <item>Note 10: The Thai delegation proposes the substitution
                                            of the following language: “Will in that event take
                                            appropriate action to meet the common danger.”<note n="2" xml:id="d348fn2"><p>The Secretary and
                                                  MacArthur discussed this language with Prince Wan
                                                  and Ambassador Pote Sarasin late on the afternoon
                                                  of Sept. 5. Part of MacArthur’s memorandum of this
                                                  conversation follows:</p>
                                                <p>“The Secretary paid a courtesy call on Prince Wan
                                                  this afternoon. After the usual amenities, Prince
                                                  Wan made reference to the proposed Thai amendment
                                                  to Article IV of the draft Treaty. He explained
                                                  that in Thailand, people had the impression that
                                                  the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> formula
                                                  was much stronger than the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> formula, and that
                                                  while he recognized the validity of the position
                                                  put forward by the US, he attached great
                                                  importance to the Thai amendment which modifies
                                                  the existing draft by saying ‘… will in the event
                                                  take appropriate action to meet the common
                                                  danger.’ Prince Wan also said it would be helpful
                                                  if ‘would act’ could be changed to ‘will take
                                                  action.’</p>
                                                <p>“The Secretary explained the fact that as a
                                                  practical matter there was no real difference
                                                  between the two formulas, and outlined the
                                                  Congressional background on the question. He urged
                                                  Prince Wan very strongly to accept the formula as
                                                  drafted but said he would be very glad to accept
                                                  changing ‘would’ to ‘will.’ Although the Secretary
                                                  did not specifically indicate that he would be
                                                  agreeable to changing ‘act’ to ‘take action.’ he
                                                  did not rule out this change.</p>
                                                <p>“Prince Wan implied that he would not have to
                                                  press his amendment.”
                                            (790.5/9554)</p></note></item>
                                        <pb facs="0862" n="844" xml:id="pg_844"/>
                                        <item><p>Note 11: The Philippine delegation proposes
                                                substitution of the following language for the whole
                                                paragraph 1: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“1. The parties agree that an armed attack
                                                  against one or more of them in Southeast Asia or
                                                  Southwest Pacific shall be considered an attack
                                                  against them all; and consequently they agree
                                                  that, if such an armed attack occurs, each of them
                                                  in exercise of the right of individual or
                                                  collective self-defense, recognized by Article 51
                                                  of the Charter of the United Nations, will assist
                                                  the party or parties so attacked by taking
                                                  forthwith, individually and collectively with the
                                                  other parties, such action as it deems necessary,
                                                  including the use of armed force, to restore and
                                                  maintain the security of the Southeast and
                                                  Southwest Pacific area.”</p></quote></p>
                                            <p>The Pakistan delegation proposes substitution of the
                                                following language for the whole paragraph 1: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“Each party recognizes that aggression by means
                                                  of armed attack in the Treaty area against any of
                                                  the parties, or against any State or territories
                                                  which the parties, by unanimous agreement may
                                                  hereafter designate, would endanger its own peace
                                                  and safety, and agrees that it would act to meet
                                                  the common danger in accordance with its own
                                                  constitutional processes. Measures taken under
                                                  this paragraph shall be immediately reported to
                                                  the Security Council of the United
                                                  Nations.</p></quote></p></item>
                                        <item>Note 12: The French delegation proposes substitution
                                            of the following language for the whole article: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                <p>“Each of the parties will consider as endangering
                                                  peace and its own security any armed attack in the
                                                  Treaty area against any of the parties, or against
                                                  the Kingdom of Cambodia, the Kingdom of Laos, and
                                                  the State of Vietnam, or against any other State
                                                  or territory which the parties designate by
                                                  unanimous agreement. Each of the parties agrees to
                                                  take all individual or collective measures
                                                  required to face the common danger. The measures
                                                  taken under this paragraph will be immediately
                                                  reported to the Security Council.</p>
                                                <p>“Each of the parties will consider as a threat to
                                                  peace and to its own security any armed attack in
                                                  the area against a State other than the States
                                                  indicated in the preceding paragraph. The parties
                                                  agree, in such an event, to consult immediately
                                                  with each other on the measures which could be
                                                  taken individually or collectively to meet such
                                                  threats.</p>
                                                <p>“Any action other than an armed attack such as to
                                                  impair the political or territorial status of any
                                                  one of the participating States will also call for
                                                  consultation among the parties, when such action
                                                  is such as to endanger the peace of the
                                                area.”</p></quote></item>
                                        <pb facs="0863" n="845" xml:id="pg_845"/>
                                        <item><p>Note 13:</p>
                                            <p>The underlined sentence<note n="3" xml:id="d348fn3">Printed as italics.</note> has been proposed by
                                                the Australian delegation.</p>
                                            <p>The Pakistan delegation proposes the deletion of
                                                “military and other” in that sentence.</p></item>
                                        <item><p>Note 14:</p>
                                            <p>The Philippine delegation proposes the insertion of
                                                the words “United States of America” in the blank
                                                spaces.</p></item>
                                        <item><p>Note 15:</p>
                                            <p>The Philippine delegation has proposed the following
                                                substitute language for the whole article: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“As used in this treaty, the ‘treaty area’ is
                                                  the area of Southeast Asia and Southwest Pacific
                                                  within the territorial jurisdiction of the
                                                  parties. The parties may by unanimous agreement
                                                  amend this article to include within the treaty
                                                  area the territory of states acceding to this
                                                  treaty, or otherwise to change the treaty
                                                  area.”</p></quote></p>
                                            <p>The Pakistan delegation proposes the following
                                                redraft of the first sentence: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                                  <p>“As used in this treaty the ‘treaty area’ is
                                                  the general area of Southeast Asia and of the
                                                  Southwest Pacific, not including the Pacific area
                                                  north of 21 degrees 30 minutes north latitude but
                                                  including the entire area under the territorial
                                                  jurisdiction of Asian parties whether situated
                                                  within or without Southeast
                                            Asia.”</p></quote></p></item>
                                        <item><p>Note 16:</p>
                                            <p>The Philippine delegation proposes the insertion of
                                                the words “United States of America” in the blank
                                                space.</p></item>
                                        <item><p>Note 17:</p>
                                            <p>The Philippine delegation proposes the insertion of
                                                the words “United States of America” in the blank
                                                space.</p></item>
                                    </list></p></item>
                        </list></p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Spruance</hi></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>