<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Counselor of the Department of State
                    (MacArthur)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d350</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">350</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-09-05T03:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-09-05T03:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recJgxebpUYqWj25O" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007242"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Defense budget</term>
                    <term ref="recQZPaxt8vx5PcGH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002638"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Air forces</term>
                    <term ref="recSta4gcC4EmYjyi" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="reca2nYE5B4OFc8eu" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99010520"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Authorization</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-05T03:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-05T03:00:00-05:00" n="350"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d350">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/9–554</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Counselor of the Department
                        of State (MacArthur)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Manila</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1954-09-05T16:00:00+08:00">September 5, 1954—4 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>Subject:</head>
                    <item>Southeast Asia Collective Defense Treaty.</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Participants:</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Australian Foreign Minister Casey</item>
                    <item>Senator Smith</item>
                    <item>Senator Mansfield</item>
                    <item>Mr. MacArthur</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0867" n="849" xml:id="pg_849"/>
                <p>Mr. Casey opened the conversation by saying there was a problem to which the
                    Australian Government attached great importance about which he wished to speak
                    to the Secretary. He said that recently there had been a very important change
                    in Australia’s foreign policy and that Prime Minister Menzies had informed the
                    country that Australia for the first time would commit Australian forces in
                    advance of hostilities, under the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                    concept. In other words, the Australian Government would undertake in advance to
                    maintain and earmark forces for the defense of the Southeast Asia area. The
                    Australian Government was also prepared and desirous of substantially increasing
                    its defense budget. What the Australian Government wished, as a result of the
                        <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Treaty, was to be able to say that
                    under this Treaty its military obligations were X number of land forces, Y
                    number of air forces, and Z number of naval forces. In other words, it will
                    immeasurably help Australia in obtaining parliamentary authorization for
                    additional defense forces if they can say that these additional forces are
                    required to meet Australia’s contribution under <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, the Australian Government wanted to know how the US envisaged
                    military planning to be undertaken under <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                    >SEATO</gloss>. There had been military planning under <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                        >ANZUS</gloss> which to some extent had been overtaken by the planning
                    engaged in by the Five-Power Military Staff Agency which was now in abeyance.
                    There was of course the question of security, particularly with reference to
                    some of our Asian partners. But, if the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                    powers and the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> proceeded with secret military
                    planning without informing the other <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                    powers, it might become known, and would raise an important political and
                    psychological problem of a white inner-circle with an Asian outer-circle.</p>
                <p>Mr. Casey said there were several possibilities which he had tentatively been
                    turning over in his mind, but which he had not discussed with his Government.
                    The serious military planning might be conducted by <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                        >ANZUS</gloss> plus the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, and this in turn
                    raised in his mind the “revolutionary” question of whether the time might not
                    have come to invite the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> to join <gloss
                        target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>, to have a cover for four-power military
                    planning which could be applied to <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>.
                    Another possibility was to have the US alone be responsible for the planning,
                    with the US bringing in the other <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> powers
                    as appropriate in the development of <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>
                    plans. This would in effect mean that the US would constitute a one-man Standing
                    Group, although there could be on the side discrete planning with Australia, New
                    Zealand, and the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>. He had no definite
                    convictions on all these matters, but was simply letting the Secretary know the
                    kind of possibilities which had been passing through his mind.</p>
                <pb facs="0868" n="850" xml:id="pg_850"/>
                <p>With respect to machinery for <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>, Mr. Casey
                    said Australia had no desire whatsoever to build up any elaborate machinery.
                    Again, he had had some thoughts which he had jotted down at lunch-time, and
                    which he would have typed up and sent to the Secretary. These consisted of the
                    formation of a <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Military Representatives
                    Committee on the Chief of Staff or theater command level, to be served by a
                    small liaison group, which would arrange <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> meetings
                    of planners. The planners could consider forces that might be earmarked for
                        <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>, logistical planning, security
                    measures, etc.</p>
                <p>The Secretary replied that he was not familiar with the details of the planning
                    that had been undertaken by the Five-Power Military Staff Agency. He explained
                    in detail why we did not wish to establish permanent machinery, but said this in
                    no sense implied that we thought planning should not be undertaken. He mentioned
                    that there was important planning to be done in the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss> area, some of which would obviously have to be confined to
                    the countries whose security was adequate. This, in effect, was the three <gloss
                        target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> powers and the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss>. There might be other matters on which the <gloss
                        target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> powers alone would wish to make planning
                    contingencies, such as the situation which would arise if Indonesia fell into
                    Communist hands.</p>
                <p>Mr. Casey then made reference to the Australian amendment to Article V, saying he
                    understood that the US military found it generally acceptable subject to minor
                    language modifications. The Secretary replied that the US did not like the
                    Australian language because it implied that permanent machinery would be set up.
                    They particularly did not like the use of the word “machinery.” He said we had
                    given thought to this matter and believed we could meet the Australian desires
                    for Treaty language by substituting the following: “The Council shall provide
                    for consultation with regard to military planning as required by the situation
                    in the area.”</p>
                <p>The Secretary also commented that he did not like the Pakistan suggestion of
                    eliminating the term “military,” since that would imply there would be economic
                    planning and the establishment of an economic organization under the Treaty,
                    whereas the present US thinking was that the economic problems might best be
                    dealt with through the Colombo plan, if Japan were also included since it was
                    indispensable, as was Indonesia.</p>
                <p>Mr. Casey looked at the new US language and said it seemed to meet their problem
                    in terms of the Treaty draft, and he believed it would be quite acceptable. He
                    said that while this meets his problems in terms of the Treaty, he still was not
                    sure how he could say to the Australian people that under <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Australia’s military contribution would be
                    so many land forces, so many air forces, and <pb facs="0869" n="851"
                        xml:id="pg_851"/> so many naval forces, which was important to enable
                    Australia to work up its defenses appreciably.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said the problems of the US and Australia were somewhat different.
                    The US had no intention of earmarking specific forces for <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>. It believed in mobile reserve striking
                    power. Furthermore, it had no territory in the Treaty area to defend. If the US
                    started earmarking forces for here, there, and everywhere, it would run out of
                    forces very rapidly since its commitments were global. The Secretary again
                    emphasized that the US policy was based on strong mobile striking power and said
                    that obviously it would continue to have substantial mobile air and sea forces
                    in this general area and also some reserve land forces in Okinawa and Hawaii. In
                    the event of aggression, such forces would be used and deployed where they could
                    best serve the war effort. Mr. Casey nodded his assent.</p>
                <p>The subject then turned to the question of the use of the word “Communist” in
                    Article IV of the draft Treaty. Mr. Casey said he had received today a British
                    suggestion which he knew had been communicated to the US. This involved
                    eliminating the word “Communist”; defining more clearly the Treaty area; and
                    having the Treaty apply to an attack from outside the Treaty area.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said the British definition of the Treaty area raised lots of
                    complications. Would the southern part of China be interpreted as being within
                    the Treaty area? There were other questions also, and furthermore, the British
                    formula was so complicated that he believed it would be most difficult to get
                    Congressional understanding. Senator Smith said the Secretary was entirely right
                    about this. The Secretary then said he had been thinking of accepting the
                    elimination of the word “Communist” and attaching to the Treaty a reservation or
                    statement of a US understanding that insofar as the US was concerned it applied
                    only to a Communist attack. Mr. Casey said that insofar as he was concerned this
                    would be entirely acceptable, and indeed might be the best way to meet this
                    difficult problem.</p>
                <p>In a discussion of Article IV, the Secretary said he had been giving thought to
                    the question of whether Laos, Cambodia, and free Vietnam should be specifically
                    included in the text of the Treaty or whether it might be preferable to have
                    them covered in a Protocol which would indicate that their territory had been
                    unanimously designated by the Parties as being covered by the Treaty against
                    armed attack. Mr. Casey indicated that it was a point worth considering.</p>
                <p>The Secretary concluded by saying that if the Conference were to accomplish its
                    work in three days it would have to be a working conference and not a gathering
                    to make political speeches for the <pb facs="0870" n="852" xml:id="pg_852"/>
                    record. Mr. Casey heartily endorsed this and said he would do his best to chip
                    in, if there was a tendency to get into long-winded speeches, to remind the
                    Members that they had a lot of work to do.</p>
                <p>The Secretary also mentioned that he thought the best way to attack the problem
                    of going over the Treaty was to examine it Article-by-Article and then at the
                    end take up the Preamble, which raised many questions in connection with the
                    specific Articles. Mr. Casey said he thought this might be a good way to handle
                    it.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
