<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-09-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-09-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="364" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d364">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/9–1554</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Counselor of the Department of State
                            (MacArthur)</hi></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-09-15">September 15, 1954</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>Subject:</head>
                        <item>Follow-Through on Manila Pact</item>
                    </list>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>During informal discussions with other Delegations at the Manila
                            Conference, it became quite clear that they were all apprehensive in
                            varying degrees as to what the US contemplated in terms of implementing
                            the Southeast Asia Treaty. It was also apparent that they were fearful
                            that the US might view the Treaty as an end in itself and might not wish
                            to agree to steps which would make it a living reality rather than what
                            one Delegation termed “a mere scrap of paper”. The view of the other
                            seven treaty signatories is that the US took the leadership in working
                            out the Treaty, and therefore they are looking to us to show leadership
                            in implementing it and seeing to it that it becomes a living
                            thing.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>There are several points on which we must expect our other Manila Pact
                            partners to query us on in the next two or three weeks. These are: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>When the Council should hold its first meeting;</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>Level of representation;</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>Where the Council should meet;</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item>How, organizationally, we envisage implementing Article V of
                                    the Treaty providing for military and other planning;</item>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item>Economic cooperation as provided in Article III.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>The following considerations seem pertinent with respect to the above
                            five points: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">First meeting of the Council</hi>. The first
                                    question which arises with respect to this point is whether the
                                    Council should meet before or after entry into effect of the
                                    Treaty. Since the necessary ratifications to bring the Treaty
                                    into effect will probably not be completed for six to eight
                                    months, should the US take the position that there should be no
                                    Council meeting until after entry into effect of the Treaty, its
                                    Manila partners would most certainly view this with alarm and as
                                    tending to confirm their suspicion that we did not intend to
                                    breathe life into the Treaty. Therefore, it seems most
                                    important, if other of our Manila partners suggest an early
                                    meeting of the Council, that we take a positive approach by
                                    suggesting a first Council meeting perhaps about mid-November.
                                    This would give two months in which to shape our own ideas and
                                    to consult with our other Treaty partners regarding possible
                                    organizational arrangements.</item>
                                <pb facs="0928" n="910" xml:id="pg_910"/>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Level of representation at first
                                        meeting</hi>. In view of the desperately heavy demands on
                                    the Secretary’s time, particularly with respect to the critical
                                    situation in Europe which will probably require his presence in
                                    Europe in September-October and again early in December for the
                                        <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Annual Review,<note n="1" xml:id="d364fn1">Dulles arrived in Paris on Dec. 15 to
                                        attend the Fifteenth Ministerial meeting of the North
                                        Atlantic Council, Dec. 17–18. The Secretary arrived back in
                                        Washington on Dec. 20. For documentation on this meeting,
                                        see <ref target="frus1952-54v05p1#pg_549">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, Part 1, pp. 549</ref>
                                        ff.</note> it would not seem feasible to contemplate having
                                    the Secretary attend the Council meeting. Furthermore, the same
                                    considerations would probably govern with respect to the Foreign
                                    Ministers of Britain and France. In the light of these
                                    considerations, it would seem appropriate, and I believe would
                                    be understood by our Asian partners, for the Under Secretary to
                                    represent the United States.</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Place of meeting</hi>. Psychologically, it
                                    seems very important that the meeting be held in the Treaty
                                    area. Bangkok would be a logical place. Not only should such a
                                    meeting strengthen the Thai Government, but it should also give
                                    the people of Thailand, who are directly threatened by
                                    subversion, a feeling of confidence which should strengthen
                                    their will to resist Communist infiltration and subversion.
                                    Furthermore, Thailand is an Asian partner.</item>
                                <label>d.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Organizational arrangements to implement
                                            Article V</hi>. This presents a difficult problem in
                                        terms of presenting the US in a role of constructive
                                        leadership. On the one hand, security considerations would
                                        inhibit our ability to get into detailed war planning on an
                                        eight-nation basis. On the other hand, any indication to our
                                        Asian partners that the white members of the Manila Pact are
                                        engaging in secret military planning under the Treaty, to
                                        the exclusion of the Asian Members, would have the most
                                        profound political and psychological repercussions and might
                                        result in the disintegration of the Manila partnership. The
                                        Western nations would certainly be charged with undertaking
                                        planning to the exclusion of the Asians with the purpose of
                                        using Asian bodies as cannon fodder in any hostilities.</p>
                                    <p>What seems to be required is some arrangement of an <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> nature whereby military
                                        planners of the eight powers could meet together from
                                        time-to-time to exchange intelligence information, to effect
                                        such coordination and exchanges of views as might be
                                        appropriate in the logistical field, and perhaps to engage
                                        in other general military planning of a non-Top Secret
                                        character, including training and the establishment of a
                                        security system for information and documents. On the side,
                                        perhaps using the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                                        framework, any secret military planning or exchanges of
                                        views which seemed desirable from the US viewpoint might be
                                        undertaken with the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> also
                                        included. It would be imperative, however, that this type of
                                        activity, under the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                                        or any other limited umbrella, not be related under the
                                        Manila Pact in any way which might become public. In order
                                        for us to have the other Manila powers agree to the type of
                                        planning and organizational arrangements which we wish, it
                                        would seem essential that these four powers take at least
                                        more or less the same position. In this connection, it might
                                        also be possible for our US military people in the
                                        Philippines, Thailand, and Pakistan to <pb facs="0929" n="911" xml:id="pg_911"/> influence the military of
                                        these three countries in the direction of our own thinking
                                        prior to a Council meeting.</p>
                                    <p>Finally, it is quite clear that the earnest of our sincerity
                                        in implementing the Manila Pact will be judged by our other
                                        partners in light of our willingness to set up some sort of
                                        military planning arrangements of a constructive
                                    nature.</p></item>
                                <label>e.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Economic Cooperation as provided in Article
                                        III</hi>. Regarding economic cooperation, it is important
                                    that the US develop a position in the light of present studies
                                    which are taking place within the US Government, and taking into
                                    account such views of the Members and other Asian countries as
                                    may be ascertained at the Ottawa meeting of the Colombo Plan
                                    powers, and through diplomatic channels.</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>