<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>United States Summary Minutes of Bipartite Foreign Ministers Meeting With the
                    United Kingdom</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-06-28T06:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-06-28T06:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-06-28T06:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-06-28T06:30:00-05:00" n="39"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d39">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 59 D 95, <gloss
                        target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 111</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">United States Summary Minutes of Bipartite Foreign Ministers
                        Meeting With the United Kingdom</hi>
                </head>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">[Extract]</note>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        <gloss target="#t_MTL1">MTL</gloss> USUK–4</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-06-28T12:30:00+01:00"
                            >June 28, 1952—12:30–1:30 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>Present:</head>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United Kingdom</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Mr. Eden</item>
                            <item>Mr. Selwyn Lloyd</item>
                            <item>Sir William Strang</item>
                            <item>Sir Pierson Dixon</item>
                            <item>Sir Roger Makins</item>
                            <item>Mr. Scott</item>
                            <item>Sir James Bowker</item>
                            <item>Mr. Allen</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">United States</hi>
                        <list>
                            <item>Secretary Acheson</item>
                            <item>Ambassador Gifford</item>
                            <item>Ambassador Jessup</item>
                            <item>Mr. Perkins</item>
                            <item>Mr. Nitze</item>
                            <item>Miss Kirkpatrick</item>
                            <item>Mr. Battle</item>
                            <item>Mr. Ringwalt</item>
                            <item>Mr. Palmer</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <gap/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">United Kingdom Observer to the Pacific Council</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. Eden opened the conversation by assuring the Secretary that the United
                    Kingdom was not in any sense trying to “gate crash” on the question of the
                    Pacific Council. Nevertheless, he said, as a Pacific power the United Kingdom
                    would hope to have a representative present in meetings of the Pacific Council.
                    Mr. Eden mentioned that he had recently discussed this matter with Mr. Menzies,
                    who had remarked that the presence of a British representative might create
                    difficulties for the United States. The Secretary replied that he agreed in
                    principle to some sort of British representation but feared that the attendance
                    of a United Kingdom observer, at least for the present, would create
                    difficulties for all concerned, resulting as it would in other nations with
                    interests in the area, including the Filipinos, the French, and even the
                    Indonesians, requesting the presence of an observer. Nevertheless, the Secretary
                    said, he would be glad to discuss the question with Mr. Menzies and Mr. Holland
                    in the forthcoming meeting in Honolulu. Mr. Lloyd remarked that the Government
                    would have to expect severe criticism as it would go down badly here that an
                    agreement had been made to establish a Pacific Council and that the United
                    Kingdom was without representation on the Council. Mr. Eden wound up by stating
                    that the Government could at least say that <pb facs="0161" n="143"
                        xml:id="pg_143"/> the British position was well understood and that it would
                    be discussed at the next meeting of the Council.<note n="1" xml:id="d39fn1">
                        <p>In a press release of June 30, the Department announced that the Council
                            would meet in Honolulu the first week of August. For text, see
                            Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, July 21, 1952, p.
                            110.</p>
                        <p>Simultaneous announcement was made in Canberra and Wellington.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <gap/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
