<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The British Embassy to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d67</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">67</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-09-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-09-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-09-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-09-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="67"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/9–252</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">British Embassy</gloss> to the <gloss
                            type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d67fn1">Note handed the Secretary of State by Sir Oliver
                        Franks the evening of Sept. 2.</note>
                </head>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret and personal</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Text of a Message From Mr. Eden to Mr. Acheson</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I am grateful for the full information about the proceedings of the <gloss
                        target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council meeting which the United States
                    Government have supplied.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I note that the question of United Kingdom association with the Council
                        and the Military Committee was fully discussed and that it was considered
                        that the difficulties involved would outweigh the advantages. This decision
                        was apparently based on the argument that if the United Kingdom were
                        admitted to a special form of association with the Council or the Military
                        Committee other Governments particularly France, would claim, and have to be
                        granted, a special status; and that the association of the United Kingdom
                        alone would cause dissatisfaction to other Governments in the area.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>I fear that I cannot accept the validity of these arguments which betray a
                        misunderstanding of the grounds for the United Kingdom’s claim to be
                        represented on the Organisation.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I admit that if the United Kingdom claim were merely based on the strength
                        of British interests in Malaya and South East Asia generally, the French and
                        the Dutch might put forward similar claims for consideration. I am also well
                        aware of the special relationships between the United States on the one hand
                        and the Philippines and Japan on the other.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>I must, however, repeat with emphasis that the United Kingdom relationship
                        with Australia and New Zealand is in a quite different category. In
                        particular on the military side the strategic thinking and planning of the
                        Chiefs of Staff of the two countries is based on the closest liaison with
                        the United Kingdom Chiefs of Staff. Australia and New Zealand are both
                        immediately concerned in the defense of the Middle East and of Singapore and
                        Malaya, which remain nevertheless primarily United Kingdom responsibilities.
                        The defense in war of the <gloss target="#t_ANZAM1">ANZAM</gloss>
                        region—which includes Malaya and the South Pacific up to the Gilbert and
                        Ellice Islands and Fiji—is the responsibility of the Australian Chiefs of
                        Staff <pb facs="0232" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/> acting jointly with the
                        United Kingdom and New Zealand Chiefs of Staff. Above all, if either
                        Australia or New Zealand is attacked, the United Kingdom will at once and
                        without question be at war with the aggressor; this is not the case as
                        regards France, Holland, the Philippines or any other country. This last
                        consideration outweighs all the others and is, in my view, quite
                        conclusive.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>It will, I am afraid, be extremely difficult for me to explain in
                        Parliament the exclusion of the United Kingdom from both the <gloss
                            target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council and the Military Committee. I
                        understand that the Council agreed to keep the question of United Kingdom
                        representation under review. I do not suggest that a further meeting of the
                        Council should be called in the near future specifically to reconsider this
                        question; I should hope instead that in the light of the above
                        considerations you would find it possible to review the matter in
                        consultation with Mr. Casey and Mr. Webb, to whom I am sending copies of
                        this message, and that it could be arranged for a United Kingdom
                        representative to attend the forthcoming meeting of the <gloss
                            target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Military Committee.<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d67fn2">In a memorandum of Sept. 3 Kitchen wrote: “the Secretary
                            told me this morning that in handing the message to the Secretary Sir
                            Oliver remarked that Mr. Eden felt very strongly in this matter and that
                            Sir Oliver had nothing to add himself. The Secretary explained the
                            various reasons why all three of the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                                >ANZUS</gloss> countries had reached the decision not to invite the
                                <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss> to participate in <gloss
                                target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> and pointed out that in practice
                            the British would be very well informed from the standpoint of military
                            planning because of: (1) the forthcoming joint talks regarding the
                            defense of Southeast Asia, and (2) <gloss target="#t_UK1">U.K.</gloss>
                            participation in the Defense Council at Melbourne.” (790.5/9–352)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-09-02">2nd September
                            1952</date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
