<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-11-25T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-11-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="82" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">790.5/5–2853</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Report by the Staff Planners to the Military
                            Representatives to the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                            Council</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d82fn1">The file copy is an enclosure to
                            the memorandum from the Joint Chiefs to Secretary of Defense Charles E.
                            Wilson, May 15, 1953, <ref target="#pg_315">p. 315</ref>.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left"><hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi></seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Pearl
                                    Harbor</hi>, <gloss target="#t_TH1">T. H.</gloss></placeName>?,]
                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-11-25">November 25,
                                1952</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>In accordance with instructions from the Military Representatives to the
                            <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council, Staff Planners of
                        Australia, New Zealand and the United States met at Pearl Harbor, <gloss target="#t_TH1">T.H.</gloss> on Thursday, November 6th, 1952, to
                        determine possible courses of action to meet the current Communist threat in
                        Southeast Asia and in the event of further Communist aggression in this area
                        short of a general emergency.</p>
                    <p>The Report of the meeting of Staff Planners is attached.</p>
                    <p>It is recommended that the Military Representatives to the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council approve this report and
                        recommend to their respective Chiefs of Staff or equivalent that:— <pb facs="0261" n="243" xml:id="pg_243"/>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>The courses of action contained therein should be the basis of
                                    <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> military policy.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>Every endeavor be made to obtain the agreement of the United
                                Kingdom and France to such policy over as wide a range as
                                possible.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <closer><signed>
                            <list>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">R. G. Pollard</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Head of Australian Staff Planners</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">H. E. Gilbert</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Head of New Zealand Staff Planners</hi></item>
                                <item><hi rend="smallcaps">C. C. Smith</hi><lb/><hi rend="italic">Head of United States Staff Planners</hi></item>
                            </list>
                        </signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <note rend="inline" type="source">[Attachment]</note>
                        <p>[Here follow a list of persons present (12), a summary of contents, and a
                            distribution list.]</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Report No</hi>. 1</p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">i. task referred</hi></p>
                        <p>At their meeting at Honolulu, September 22–25, 1952, the Military
                            Representatives to the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council
                            referred the following immediate planning tasks to the Staff Planners:
                                <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <list>
                                    <item>“1. A review of the military situation in Southeast Asia.
                                        This is essentially an intelligence estimate to be used in
                                        planning procedures.</item>
                                    <item>“2. Develop a strategic estimate on Southeast Asia.</item>
                                    <item>“3. Determine possible courses of action to meet the
                                        current Communist threat in Southeast Asia and in the event
                                        of further Communist aggression in this area short of a
                                        general emergency.”<note n="2" xml:id="d82fn2">The quotation
                                            is from section B of the Military Representatives’
                                            Agreed Record of Proceedings, <ref target="#pg_224">p.
                                                224</ref>.</note></item>
                                </list></quote></p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">ii. definitions and
                                interpretations</hi></p>
                        <p>It is interpreted: <list>
                                <label>A.</label>
                                <item>That the phrases used in the above directive have meanings as
                                    stated hereunder: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“Short of a general emergency”—Short of global war, i.e.,
                                            short of war with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss></p>
                                        <p>“Current Communist threat”—Existing cold war conditions,
                                            wherein overt Chinese Communist aggression is limited to
                                            Korea but tension is maintained throughout Southeast
                                            Asia.</p>
                                        <pb facs="0262" n="244" xml:id="pg_244"/>
                                        <p>“Further Communist aggression”—Further Chinese Communist
                                            aggression (outside Korea) without overt Soviet
                                            participation.</p></quote></item>
                                <label>B.</label>
                                <item>That the aim of measures taken in the event of further Chinese
                                    Communist aggression will be to force the Chinese Communists to
                                    cease their aggression.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">iii. statement of position</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>The Military Representatives to the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council are concerned with the threat in
                                Southeast Asia to the security of Australia, New Zealand and the
                                United States of America and with the determination of possible
                                courses of action to meet the threat.</item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>It is considered that the determination of possible courses of
                                action to meet the threat must include estimates of force
                                requirements. Such estimates are included in broad terms in this
                                report.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>Any planning by the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> powers
                                will form only part of the overall planning by the Allies to contain
                                Communist expansion and, therefore, before detailed supporting plans
                                for a particular area can be prepared, consultation with the Allied
                                nation responsible for that area will be necessary.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">iv. assumptions</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>A.</label>
                            <item>The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">U.S.S.R.</gloss> will not intervene
                                thereby causing global war unless and until it suits her so to
                                    do.<note n="*" xml:id="d82fn3">The possibility of Soviet
                                    reaction, however, has been noted in consideration of the
                                    courses of action. [Footnote in the source text.]</note></item>
                            <label>B.</label>
                            <item>Weapons of mass destruction will not be employed by either
                                side.</item>
                            <label>C.</label>
                            <item>A resolute defense of the area where aggression has occurred is an
                                essential prerequisite to any Allied supporting action.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">v. intelligence estimate</hi></p>
                        <p>The Intelligence Estimate on which the Strategic Estimate on Southeast
                            Asia has been based is at Annex A.<note n="3" xml:id="d82fn4">Not
                                printed.</note></p>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">vi. strategic estimate on southeast
                                asia</hi></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">A. Importance of the Southeast Asia
                                Region</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>In Southeast Asia the Chinese Communist regime, as the agent of
                                the leaders of world Communism, is pursuing aggressive policies
                                designed to eliminate Western influence therein and to bring the
                                whole area under Communist control.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The maintenance of internal security and national independence in
                                Southeast Asia is of great significance because: <pb facs="0263" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/>
                                <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>The loss to the Communists of the Tonkin Delta in
                                        Indochina, which is presently the area most directly
                                        threatened, would greatly simplify continued Communist
                                        expansion in Southeast Asia while compounding the
                                        difficulties of friendly forces. It would probably lead to
                                        the collapse of Burma and Thailand, and to a dangerous
                                        weakening of internal security in Malaya, Indonesia and the
                                        Philippines.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>Communist domination of Southeast Asia would almost
                                        completely deny the Pacific littoral of Asia to the West,
                                        involving the loss of strategic materials (principally
                                        rubber and tin) of great importance to the whole
                                        non-Communist world.</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>Communist acquisition of the rice surplus areas—Burma,
                                        Indochina and Thailand—would enable the Communists to apply
                                        effective economic pressure against the non-Communist Asian
                                        countries in which rice is the principal food and which
                                        depend for their already low standard of living on
                                        importation from the rice surplus areas. The Western Powers
                                        would be forced to assume the burden of supplying
                                        food-stuffs to these rice deficit areas, or acquiesce in
                                        their reaching an accommodating agreement with the
                                        Communists.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>Communist control of Southeast Asia would markedly
                                        increase the prestige of Communist China and the Soviet
                                        Union and would strengthen the international position and
                                        the internal stability of their regimes.</item>
                                    <label>e.</label>
                                    <item>The loss of Southeast Asia, together with a deteriorating
                                        situation in the Middle East, which will almost certainly be
                                        exploited by the Soviet bloc, would have strong
                                        repercussions in India, Pakistan and Ceylon.</item>
                                    <label>f.</label>
                                    <item>Should Southeast Asia be lost, the reestablishment of
                                        Western influence in the region would be a difficult, if not
                                        insurmountable, problem.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The loss of Hong Kong would have a markedly adverse psychological
                                effect throughout Southeast Asia and would deprive the Allies of a
                                valuable beachhead and point of contact with anti-Communist elements
                                in Communist China.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>It is concluded that a Communist dominated and controlled
                                Southeast Asia would so increase the Communist threat to the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Countries that the existing and
                                potential Communist threats in the area must be countered.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The strategic and current situation in specific areas of the
                                Southeast Asia regions is examined hereunder: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Indochina</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>The mainland communications between China and
                                                Southeast Asia are channeled through the Tonkin
                                                Delta, the retention of which in friendly hands
                                                would render aggression by Chinese Communist ground
                                                forces against Southern Indochina, Thailand and
                                                Malaya very difficult.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>Bases in Southern Indochina are suitably located
                                                for operations to secure the sea communications in
                                                the Gulf of Thailand and the South China Sea.</item>
                                            <pb facs="0264" n="246" xml:id="pg_246"/>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>In Indochina the Communists already have an active
                                                native force seriously threatening the existing
                                                government. The effect of Chinese assistance to the
                                                Viet Minh has been plainly evident in their
                                                increased coordination of large scale unit action,
                                                their improved communications and the apparent
                                                adequacy of their logistic supply. Now because of
                                                the military assistance by the Chinese Communists to
                                                the Viet Minh on the one hand and by the United
                                                States to the French and Associated States on the
                                                other, Indochina has become a major battleground in
                                                the West’s struggle to contain Communism. French
                                                Union forces are currently considered capable of
                                                holding their positions in the Tonkin Delta against
                                                Viet Minh forces as presently constituted, but would
                                                be forced to withdraw if substantial Chinese forces
                                                were committed.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Burma</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Strategically, Burma is the land route from China
                                                for an invasion of the Indian sub-continent and is
                                                the back door entrance for a conquest of Thailand.
                                                It possesses potential bases for air and naval
                                                action directed against Allied sea communications in
                                                the Bay of Bengal, the Indian Ocean and the
                                                remainder of Southeast Asia.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>The Socialist dominated government of Burma is
                                                basically leftist, anti-foreign in attitude and
                                                sympathetic toward Asian “Nationalism”.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>Militarily, the Burmese Government faces serious
                                                problems. Its army is poorly trained, is equipped
                                                with old, worn-out equipment and includes groups of
                                                doubtful loyalty. Battles with the Karens and the
                                                problem of maintaining internal order have made it
                                                almost impossible to provide more than a token force
                                                to police the Northern and Northeastern Chinese
                                                border areas. As a result, these have been overrun
                                                by various bandits and outlaws and by Chinese
                                                Nationalist guerrilla groups.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Thailand</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Thailand is of strategic importance because it
                                                lies astride the communication routes to the South.
                                                It would provide useful base facilities in enemy
                                                hands for an invasion of Malaya and for operations
                                                against Allied sea communications in the Gulf of
                                                Thailand and the South China Sea.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>The potentially weak spot in Thai security, aside
                                                from the internal tensions caused by political
                                                rivalry within the military oligarchy itself, is the
                                                existence of a large, commercially dominant, alien
                                                Chinese minority which may be sympathetic to the
                                                Chinese Peiping regime.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>The Thai government, although weakened by
                                                factional intrigue and strife, has taken a fairly
                                                strong stand against Communism. However, it could
                                                not be expected to resist Communist pressure if
                                                Indochina or Burma fell.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Malaya (Including Singapore)</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Malaya’s strategic importance derives from its
                                                geographical location commanding the Strait of
                                                Malacca, the natural sea route between the Indian
                                                Ocean and the Far East. It possesses naval and air
                                                bases suitable for use for the control of sea
                                                communications in these areas and for defense.
                                                Should Communism succeed in Indochina, Burma and
                                                Thailand, it would be the last Western foothold on
                                                the mainland.</item>
                                            <pb facs="0265" n="247" xml:id="pg_247"/>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>In Malaya, terrorism carried out by the Communist
                                                “Malay Racial Liberation Army” (MRLA), 95% of whom
                                                are Chinese, poses a serious security threat to the
                                                British. British and indigenous forces have been
                                                able to maintain internal security in all major
                                                urban areas and along main lines of communication,
                                                and to checkmate the Communist attempts to prevent
                                                operation of rubber plantations, tin mines, and
                                                other basic industries. While continued guerrilla
                                                activity can be expected, some improvement in the
                                                security situation by the end of 1952 appears
                                                probable.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>e.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Hong Kong</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Hong Kong is of strategic importance because it is
                                                the only remaining beachhead in friendly hands on
                                                the mainland of China and because it forms a useful
                                                point of contact with anti-Communist elements in
                                                Communist China. Its retention has a strong
                                                psychological effect on Asian opinion.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>Maximum exploitation of existing and potential air
                                                facilities at Hong Kong would contribute
                                                significantly to gaining control of the air in the
                                                Hong Kong-Canton area.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>The British garrison, comprising approximately
                                                two-thirds of a division, with the supporting police
                                                force is capable of maintaining internal security
                                                under present conditions and of forcing the Chinese
                                                Communists to embark on a substantial military
                                                operation should they decide to occupy the Colony.
                                                The garrison is, however, not strong enough to
                                                withstand a large-scale Communist attack which,
                                                should it occur, would be successful within a very
                                                short time.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>f.</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Macao</hi></p>
                                        <p>Macao is of no strategic importance and is indefensible.
                                            Its very small garrison is not capable of putting up
                                            more than a token defense.</p></item>
                                    <label>g.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Formosa (Including the Pescadores)</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>The existing naval bases in Formosa are of value
                                                for naval operations on the China Coast. There is
                                                scope for the development of air bases useful for
                                                attacks on the Chinese mainland and for support of
                                                maritime operations in the area. In enemy hands,
                                                Formosa would facilitate a Communist advance into
                                                the Philippines. In the hands of the Chinese
                                                Nationalists, it is a continuing threat to the
                                                Chinese Communists who find it necessary to retain
                                                substantial armed forces on the adjacent
                                                mainland.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>The Chinese Nationalists are in effective control
                                                of the whole of Formosa, the security of which is
                                                safeguarded by the U.S. Seventh Fleet.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>h.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Philippines</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>The base facilities in the Philippines are of
                                                great value to the Allies for any operations which
                                                may be conducted in Southeast Asia. Their
                                                geographical relation to sea routes leading to China
                                                make them of great importance for the support of
                                                maritime operations in those seas.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>In the Philippines the internal security situation
                                                has shown marked improvement during the past year
                                                and, unless political factors intervene, prospects
                                                point to an even greater improvement by the end of
                                                1952.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <pb facs="0266" n="248" xml:id="pg_248"/>
                                    <label>i.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Indonesia, Sarawak, British North
                                            Borneo, Portuguese Timor, Brunei, and Dutch New
                                            Guinea</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>In enemy hands, these territories would provide
                                                bases for attacks to be developed against the
                                                mainland of Australia. Their geographical relation
                                                to the various sea routes in the area would make
                                                their potential base facilities valuable for the
                                                control of sea communications. They are a source of
                                                substantial quantities of strategic
                                                materials.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>The present political situation in Indonesia is
                                                unstable and internal security is precarious.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>In Sarawak, British North Borneo, Portuguese
                                                Timor, Brunei and Dutch New Guinea, the
                                                administering powers have at present no major
                                                security problems although there is a continuing
                                                possibility that such problems may arise from
                                                Communist, nationalist or bandit inspiration.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">B. Development of the Enemy
                                Threat</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Current deployment of Chinese Communist ground forces in South
                                China provides the enemy with the capability of simultaneously
                                overrunning existing friendly defense forces in Indochina, Hong
                                Kong, Macao and Burma. Deployment of air support for such offensive
                                action is readily within Chinese Communist capabilities. An analysis
                                of air facilities in South China indicates that close air support
                                would have to be deployed, at least initially, through the Canton
                                complex. The Chinese Communist Air Force has the capability of
                                attacking targets in Indochina, Burma, Thailand, Hong Kong,
                                Philippines and Formosa.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The enemy threat in specific areas of the Southeast Asia region is
                                examined hereunder: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Indochina</hi><note n="†" xml:id="d82fn5">See Chart, Appendix I to Annex A.
                                                [Footnote in the source text. Appendix I is not
                                                printed.]</note></p>
                                        <p>The Tonkin Delta of Indochina represents the key to the
                                            defense of Southeast Asia. French Union forces are
                                            currently containing the Viet Minh rebellion and are
                                            holding a defensive position known as the Hanoi
                                            Perimeter. However, the introduction of Chinese
                                            Communist forces into this campaign could drive them
                                            into the Haiphong Redoubt. It is estimated that the
                                            existing French Union forces could hold this redoubt
                                            against a mass assault for thirty days only, after which
                                            they would need complete logistic support, plus
                                            significant air and naval support.</p>
                                        <p>The French Union forces, given adequate material aid, are
                                            capable of continuing to hold the Hanoi Perimeter
                                            against the Viet Minh. However additional material aid
                                            alone would not enable them to retain these positions in
                                            the face of Chinese Communist aggression.</p>
                                        <p>Loss of the Hanoi Perimeter would enable the enemy to
                                            control strategic terrain in Indochina and would permit
                                            an enemy drive into Laos and Cambodia. Strong Communist
                                            forces in these two states would then be in a position
                                            to launch flanking attacks <pb facs="0267" n="249" xml:id="pg_249"/> against Burma and Thailand at
                                            comparatively low cost and to continue their march to
                                            Saigon. Loss of the Hanoi Perimeter would also
                                            constitute a serious threat to Malaya.</p></item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Burma</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Chinese Communist forces are now in a position to
                                                launch an effective attack against Burma
                                                irrespective of action in any other area. However,
                                                loss of the Tonkin Delta would greatly facilitate
                                                Communist seizure of Burma. Burma in enemy hands
                                                would represent a significant threat to the Allied
                                                positions elsewhere in Southeast Asia. The presence
                                                of Chinese Nationalist guerrilla groups in the
                                                Northeastern border areas of Burma provides a
                                                ready-made excuse for Chinese Communist
                                                intervention.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>The inaccessibility of Burma to friendly forces
                                                and the difficulties imposed by terrain on ground
                                                and air reinforcement are of such magnitude that
                                                Allied counter-action in Burma itself would present
                                                great difficulty.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Thailand</hi></p>
                                        <p>With Indochina and/or Burma in Communist hands, Thailand
                                            would be in a precarious position. Friendly capabilities
                                            for the defense of Thailand, in this situation, are
                                            meager. Communist possession of Thailand would result in
                                            a significant strengthening of their military position
                                            with respect to the remainder of Southeast Asia. In
                                            particular it would place them in the most advantageous
                                            position to support dissident elements in Malaya and
                                            would provide them with air base sites and facilities
                                            and a line of departure for invasion of Malaya. The
                                            Communists would also have control of the largest single
                                            source of rice in Southeast Asia.</p></item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Malaya</hi></p>
                                        <p>Communist possession of Indochina, Burma, and Thailand
                                            would inevitably result in the necessity for an all-out,
                                            last-ditch defense. In fact, Malaya represents the
                                            Allies’ final defense position in Southeast Asia. The
                                            strategic raw materials there would be a valuable
                                            addition to the enemy’s war making potential.</p></item>
                                    <label>e.</label>
                                    <item><hi rend="italic">Hong Kong</hi>
                                        <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>It is estimated that the Chinese Communists are
                                                capable of over-running the British Crown Colony
                                                under present conditions, in a very few days. The
                                                air complex at Canton, about 70 miles away, is
                                                ideally located to support an enemy attack. The
                                                Canton complex represents a vital installation for
                                                the support of Chinese Communist aggression against
                                                either Indochina or Burma. Supporting air deployed
                                                from the North to assist in such offensive action
                                                would initially have to be staged through Canton.
                                                Complete logistic support for a sustained offensive
                                                against Indochina and Burma would have to come
                                                through Canton. Hong Kong in friendly hands
                                                constitutes a potential threat to the Canton
                                                complex.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>Due to the enemy ability to overrun Hong Kong in a
                                                very few days reinforcement action must be initiated
                                                and completed before the enemy can react.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>f.</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Formosa-Philippine Islands</hi></p>
                                        <p>The major existing threat against Formosa lies in the
                                            Chinese Communist capability to launch airborne and
                                            amphibious forces against the island. It is considered
                                            that existing friendly naval forces are sufficient to
                                            cope with this threat. This Chinese Communist <pb facs="0268" n="250" xml:id="pg_250"/> capability
                                            does not now extend to the Philippines. However, with
                                            Formosa in Chinese Communist hands the Philippines would
                                            be similarly threatened.</p></item>
                                    <label>g.</label>
                                    <item><p><hi rend="italic">Other Areas</hi></p>
                                        <p>While the Philippines and Malaya remain under friendly
                                            control it is considered that no significant external
                                            military threat exists against these areas. There is a
                                            current internal threat in these areas that would be
                                            aggravated by the loss to Communism of any of the
                                            directly threatened areas in Southeast Asia.</p></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">vii. allied courses of action to meet
                                the current communist threat in southeast asia</hi></p>
                        <p>A. In the light of this study of the importance of the Southeast Asia
                            region and the development of the enemy threat, action to meet that
                            threat appears essential. Possible courses include: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Continuation and Possible Increase of the
                                            Present Military Aid and Advisory Programs</hi></p>
                                    <p>This continued aid, while not committing military forces of
                                        nations other than those involved in the specific areas,
                                        would provide the means necessary to exploit to the fullest
                                        the strengthening of national forces in the
                                    region.</p></item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Strengthening of Military Forces in the
                                        Region</hi>
                                    <list>
                                        <label>a.</label>
                                        <item><p>By the use of national and indigenous forces.</p>
                                            <p>Owing to the strategic importance of Indochina and
                                                Hong Kong, the French and British should be
                                                encouraged to build up their forces and strengthen
                                                their defenses in those areas. In Indochina the
                                                French have embarked on a program to build up the
                                                French Union forces. With increased aid and advisory
                                                assistance this strengthening could be accelerated.
                                                In this and other areas of Southeast Asia there
                                                should be a strengthening of national forces
                                                sufficient to maintain internal stability and, in
                                                the longer term, to resist Chinese Communist
                                                aggression.</p>
                                            <p>Reinforcement to meet the current threat must be by
                                                national and indigenous forces as the employment of
                                                forces from Allied nations would probably be open to
                                                misinterpretation throughout the world, particularly
                                                in Asia, as to the motive of the Allies, and might
                                                involve Chinese Communist reaction.</p></item>
                                        <label>b.</label>
                                        <item><p>By reinforcement of existing Allied forces.</p>
                                            <p>There are insufficient Allied forces presently in
                                                Southeast Asia for the requirements foreseen in the
                                                event of further Chinese Communist aggression. A
                                                general increase in the forces in Southeast Asia
                                                might provide the necessary deterrent. Additional
                                                forces within the region could constitute a
                                                strategic reserve available for assistance in
                                                threatened areas in the event of further Chinese
                                                Communist aggression.</p></item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Psychological Warfare</hi></p>
                                    <p>Psychological warfare, if effective, would have beneficial
                                        military results in strengthening the will of the
                                        non-Communist countries of the region to resist Communism.
                                        It would also weaken the hold of <pb facs="0269" n="251" xml:id="pg_251"/> the Chinese Communist government
                                        within China, thereby reducing Chinese capabilities to
                                        commit aggression.</p></item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Guerrilla Warfare</hi></p>
                                    <p>The assistance and encouragement by covert means of
                                        anti-Communist dissident elements in Communist China and the
                                        intensification of guerrilla activities, including sabotage,
                                        could weaken the Chinese Communist regime and thereby reduce
                                        the threat in Southeast Asia.</p></item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Use of Chinese Nationalists</hi></p>
                                    <p>An important source of unused military manpower in the Far
                                        East, favorably inclined towards the Allies, is represented
                                        by the Chinese Nationalists on Formosa. If agreement for the
                                        use of these forces could be reached between the Chinese
                                        Nationalists and the governments of the areas directly
                                        threatened they could be employed to assist in the defense
                                        of those areas. A progressive increase in their capabilities
                                        is being developed with U.S. assistance and further increase
                                        is desirable.</p></item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Conduct a Blockade of the China
                                            Coast</hi></p>
                                    <p>A blockade of the China coast prior to further aggression by
                                        the Chinese Communists would have no immediate effect in the
                                        reduction of their military capabilities. It would require
                                        substantial naval and air forces to implement it. In any
                                        case there would be considerable leakage through
                                        Vladivostok. It would most likely provoke Chinese Communist
                                        reaction, particularly against Hong Kong.</p></item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Determine a Coordinated Agreed Military
                                            Policy With the United Kingdom and France Applicable to
                                            the Threatened Areas</hi></p>
                                    <p>The absence of an agreed military policy with the United
                                        Kingdom and France with regard to Southeast Asia complicates
                                        the problem of implementing possible military courses of
                                        action designed to meet the threat of further aggression in
                                        the region. The courses of action contained in this paper
                                        should be the basis of <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> military policy which, it is suggested,
                                        may form the basis for wider agreement with the United
                                        Kingdom and France. A coordinated expression of that
                                        military policy, therefore, is highly desirable for planning
                                        of action to counter the existing threat or to meet further
                                        aggression should it occur in the region.</p></item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Establish a Means of Coordinating Agreed
                                            Allied Military Policy</hi></p>
                                    <p>It is considered that the first step toward the
                                        accomplishment of this purpose should be a meeting of the
                                        following: <list>
                                            <item>Commander in Chief Pacific (U.S.)</item>
                                            <item>Representative of British Defence Coordination
                                                Committee (Far East)</item>
                                            <item>Commander in Chief, French Forces, Far East</item>
                                            <item>Representative of New Zealand Chiefs of
                                                Staff</item>
                                            <item>Representative of Australian Defence
                                                Committee</item>
                                        </list></p></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <pb facs="0270" n="252" xml:id="pg_252"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">B. Conclusions</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Each of the foregoing possible courses of action, with the
                                exception of the blockade, would contribute towards meeting the
                                current threat and should be encouraged.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>A blockade of the China coast, under current conditions, would be
                                uneconomical and would not have sufficient effect on Chinese
                                Communist capabilities in Southeast Asia to warrant its
                                imposition.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The courses of action which would contribute most are: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>The build-up of national and indigenous forces in the
                                        directly threatened areas, backed by the continuation and
                                        possible increase of military aid and advisory
                                        programs.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>An increase in Allied forces in the region to provide a
                                        deterrent to further Chinese Communist aggression.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>The formulation of an agreed military policy with the United
                                Kingdom and France with respect to Southeast Asia would greatly
                                assist in the effective implementation of these courses. It would
                                also facilitate planning to meet further Chinese Communist
                                aggression. Failing complete agreement, every effort should be made
                                to obtain such an agreed policy over as wide a range as
                                possible.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">viii. allied courses of action in
                                event of further chinese communist aggression in southeast
                            asia</hi></p>
                        <p>A. The aim of Allied action in the event of further Chinese Communist
                            aggression will be to force the Communists to cease such aggression. In
                            the light of the examination of the enemy threat, consideration of
                            courses of action has been restricted to those applicable to the areas
                            directly threatened and to those more general measures against China
                            which might be necessary.</p>
                        <p>Consideration has also been given to courses of action applicable to
                            Malaya because of the particular strategic importance of that area. The
                            detailed examination of the advantages and disadvantages of courses of
                            action at Annex B<note n="4" xml:id="d82fn6">Not printed.</note> is
                            summarized hereunder: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Provide Naval and Air Support to Friendly
                                            Forces in Southeast Asia</hi></p>
                                    <p><hi rend="italic">Indochina</hi></p>
                                    <p>Provision of naval and air support to friendly forces in
                                        Indochina is feasible. It would contribute directly and with
                                        significant effect to the support of the French but would
                                        not, in itself, suffice to cause the enemy to cease his
                                        aggression.</p>
                                    <p><hi rend="italic">Burma</hi></p>
                                    <p>Provision of naval and air support to friendly forces in
                                        Burma <pb facs="0271" n="253" xml:id="pg_253"/> would be
                                        most uneconomical and, on military grounds, would not be
                                        worthwhile.</p>
                                    <p><hi rend="italic">Hong Kong</hi></p>
                                    <p>Provision of naval and air support to friendly forces in Hong
                                        Kong is feasible. It would contribute directly and with
                                        significant effect to the support of the British but would
                                        not, in itself, afford sufficient assistance to enable the
                                        British to hold Hong Kong unless the Colony had received
                                        reinforcement of ground forces before a Chinese Communist
                                        attack.</p></item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Provide Ground Forces With Appropriate
                                            Naval and Air Support to Reinforce Friendly Forces in
                                            Indochina and Burma</hi></p>
                                    <p><hi rend="italic">Indochina</hi></p>
                                    <p>Provided the French Union forces hold the Hanoi Perimeter
                                        long enough to enable reinforcement by ground forces with
                                        appropriate naval and air support, such reinforcement would
                                        prevent the loss of the Tonkin Delta.</p>
                                    <p><hi rend="italic">Burma</hi></p>
                                    <p>The provision of ground forces in support of friendly forces
                                        in Burma would not be profitable in view of its probable
                                        ineffectiveness and the effort involved.</p></item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Maintain the Security of Hong Kong by the
                                            Introduction of Appropriate Reinforcements</hi></p>
                                    <p>The defense of Hong Kong is feasible if adequate ground
                                        forces are in place prior to an attack by the Chinese
                                        Communists, if suitable land-based aircraft are in place to
                                        provide air defense and if an adequate naval task force is
                                        available to assist in air defense and provide air and
                                        gunfire support. The successful defense of Hong Kong, in
                                        addition to having psychological advantages, would have
                                        considerable effect on deterring Communist aggression
                                        elsewhere in Southeast Asia.</p></item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Conduct Air Attacks Against Selected
                                            Targets on the Chinese Mainland</hi></p>
                                    <p>Coordinated friendly attacks against selected targets on the
                                        Chinese mainland would progressively reduce the Chinese
                                        Communist ability to support large scale military operations
                                        based on South China and might well produce immediate
                                        results on the effectiveness of the <gloss target="#t_CCAF1">CCAF</gloss>. Such attacks would have the most gainful
                                        results when related to specific military
                                    operations.</p></item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Conduct a Blockade of the China
                                            Coast</hi></p>
                                    <p>A blockade as a separate course of action would have no
                                        immediate effect in the reduction of the Chinese Communist
                                        military capabilities. It would require substantial naval
                                        and air forces. In any case there would be considerable
                                        leakage through Vladivostok. It might provoke Russian
                                        reaction. In combination with other courses of action a
                                        blockade would be profitable.</p></item>
                                <label>6.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Seize a Beachkead on the Chinese
                                            Mainland</hi></p>
                                    <p>No military advantage would be gained by seizure of a
                                        beach-head on the Chinese mainland other than the deployment
                                        of the enemy effort needed to contain it.</p></item>
                                <label>7.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Seize and Hold a Beachhead on Hainan
                                            Island</hi></p>
                                    <p>The seizure of a beachhead on Hainan Island is a feasible
                                        operation with attractive strategic prospects. It would
                                        involve a continuing <pb facs="0272" n="254" xml:id="pg_254"/> logistic and maintenance problem, at times under
                                        difficult seasonal weather conditions.</p></item>
                                <label>8.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Provide Naval and Air Support to Friendly
                                            Forces in Malaya</hi></p>
                                    <p>Provision of naval and air support to friendly forces in
                                        Malaya is feasible and would contribute directly, and with
                                        significant effect, to the defense of Malaya but would not
                                        in itself suffice to cause the enemy to cease his
                                        aggression.</p></item>
                                <label>9.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Provide Ground Forces With Appropriate
                                            Naval and Air Support in Support of Friendly Forces in
                                            Malaya</hi></p>
                                    <p>The provision of ground forces with appropriate naval and air
                                        support is feasible and would enable Malaya to be
                                    held.</p></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">B. Considerations Affecting the
                                Selection of Courses of Action</hi></p>
                        <p>Courses of action to meet the current Chinese Communist threat, which
                            include the strengthening of military forces in the region, have been
                            set out above. In the event of further aggression, the action to be
                            taken to cause the Chinese Communists to cease such aggression will
                            depend on the extent to which those courses have already been carried
                            out, particularly those relating to the strengthening of the friendly
                            forces in Hong Kong and Indochina. The probable effects of Chinese
                            Communist aggression against specified areas are stated hereunder: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Hong Kong</hi></p>
                                    <p>Unless the Hong Kong garrison had been strengthened the
                                        Colony would fall in a matter of days. This would result in
                                        the loss of our only foothold on the mainland of China which
                                        provides the only available air facilities from which
                                        friendly land-based interceptors could operate. It would
                                        also remove the potential threat to the Canton complex,
                                        which is of special importance to the Chinese Communist
                                        offensive capabilities in Southeast Asia. A major effort, in
                                        particularly difficult circumstances, would be involved in
                                        the evacuation of Hong</p></item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Indochina</hi></p>
                                    <p>If a Chinese Communist attack is launched before the area has
                                        been strengthened, the French Union forces would be forced
                                        to withdraw within the Haiphong Redoubt. Successful defense
                                        of the redoubt would depend upon complete logistic and
                                        significant naval and air support from Allied sources within
                                        a few weeks. Defense of the redoubt, by itself, would have
                                        very little effect on the Chinese Communist capability to
                                        continue their advance to the South.</p>
                                    <p>The absence of suitable landing beaches, the over-taxed port
                                        facilities, the limited space within the Haiphong Redoubt
                                        and the effects of enemy air action would make reinforcement
                                        sufficient to restore the Hanoi Perimeter extremely
                                        difficult. A major effort, in particularly difficult
                                        circumstances, would be involved if evacuation became
                                        necessary.</p></item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Burma</hi></p>
                                    <p>As no adequate strengthening of the Burmese forces is likely
                                        in the foreseeable future, and as Allied naval and air
                                        support limited to the area of aggression would be most
                                        uneconomical and, on military <pb facs="0273" n="255" xml:id="pg_255"/> grounds, not worthwhile, the
                                        overrunning of Burma must be expected in the event of
                                        Chinese Communist aggression.</p>
                                    <p>Consideration of Burma points to the conclusion that the best
                                        method of forcing the Chinese Communists to cease their
                                        aggression would be by offensive action elsewhere against
                                        China.</p></item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item><p><hi rend="italic">Malaya</hi></p>
                                    <p>In the event of the loss of the foregoing areas, the
                                        strategic value of Malaya, as the last foothold on the
                                        mainland of Southeast Asia, would be greatly enhanced. As
                                        soon as it appears that the loss of the Hanoi Perimeter to
                                        the Chinese Communists might be inevitable, steps would have
                                        to be taken to accelerate measures for the defense of
                                        Malaya.</p>
                                </item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">C. Conclusions</hi></p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The Chinese Communists have the capability of overrunning Hong
                                Kong, Macao, Indochina and Burma, either separately or in any
                                combination. The best courses of action in the event of any Chinese
                                Communist aggression in Southeast Asia are listed hereunder: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>Provide naval and air support to friendly forces resisting
                                        aggression, except in Burma and Macao in the event of
                                        attacks against those areas.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>Maintain the security of Hong Kong by the introduction of
                                        appropriate reinforcements, except when Hong Kong itself has
                                        been attacked before the garrison has been adequately
                                        strengthened.</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>Conduct air attacks against selected targets on the
                                        Chinese mainland.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>Conduct a blockade of the China coast.</item>
                                    <label>e.</label>
                                    <item>Provide ground forces with appropriate naval and air
                                        support in Indochina, except when Indochina itself has been
                                        attacked before the French Union forces have been adequately
                                        strengthened.</item>
                                    <label>f.</label>
                                    <item>Seize and hold a beachhead on Hainan Island.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>While each of the courses outlined above is of value, no single
                                one will suffice to cause the Chinese Communists to cease their
                                aggression. A combination of all the courses applicable to a given
                                situation offers the best prospect of doing so.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>The effects of undertaking an appropriate combination of courses
                                of action would be: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>In the event of Chinese Communist aggression occurring
                                        before the French Union forces in Indochina and/or the
                                        garrison in Hong Kong had been adequately strengthened, the
                                        action taken would not cause the Chinese Communists to cease
                                        their aggression immediately but would progressively reduce
                                        their capability to continue the aggression.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>If the forces in Indochina and Hong Kong had been
                                        sufficiently strengthened before a Chinese Communist attack
                                        a successful defense of these areas could not be expected.
                                        Thereby the prospects of success of Allied action within a
                                        reasonable period would be considerably increased.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <pb facs="0274" n="256" xml:id="pg_256"/>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>If Allied weakness in Southeast Asia were such that the above
                                courses of action could not be successfully implemented and the
                                major portion of the area should fall to Chinese Communist
                                aggression, then a firm defense of Malaya would have to be
                                conducted. This would necessitate reinforcement of Malaya by ground
                                forces with appropriate naval and air support.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>It is clear that failure to strengthen Indochina before aggression
                                occurs and to provide adequate naval and air support in the event of
                                aggression could lead to the loss of the Southeast Asia region to
                                the Chinese Communists. It is also evident that if similar action is
                                not taken with respect to Hong Kong the Colony would be lost. It
                                would be a most difficult, if not insurmountable, task to regain
                                those areas.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">ix. force requirements</hi></p>
                        <p>Until detailed planning has been undertaken, force requirements can be
                            stated only in general terms. Forces of the order of those shown in
                            Annex C<note n="5" xml:id="d82fn7">Not printed.</note> will be required
                            to carry out the various courses of action. No estimate has been made of
                            logistic support forces required as these would vary considerably with
                            the area of aggression, the courses of action selected and the location
                            of available bases.</p>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>