<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Position Paper Prepared for the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v12p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-03-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-03-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="92"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d92">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 59 D 95, <gloss
                        target="#t_CF1">CF</gloss> 139</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Position Paper Prepared for the Secretary of State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d92fn1">Prepared for Dulles’ talks with Eden, who was in
                        Washington Mar. 4–7. For documentation on his visit, see <ref
                            target="frus1952-54v06p1">volume <hi rend="smallcaps">vi</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-03-04">March 4,
                            1953</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Interest in</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the spring of 1952 the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> began a series of
                    approaches to the US, Australia and New Zealand in connection with its desire to
                    participate in <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> at least to the extent of
                    having a <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> observer attend meetings of the
                        <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> Council. Since that time, the three
                    countries have informed the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> on many occasions
                    and at various levels that the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                    signatories appreciate <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> interests and
                    responsibilities in the Pacific; that they are bearing these interests and
                    responsibilities in mind; and that they are keeping the <gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss> currently and fully informed of <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                        >ANZUS</gloss> proceedings and plans.</p>
                <p>Although the New Zealanders have been particularly distressed by the pressure
                    directed at them by the mother country, they and the Australians have continued
                    to adhere to the decision reached by the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>
                    Council at its Honolulu meeting last August. (See “US Position”)<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d92fn2">That portion of the paper is not printed.</note> The
                    Secretary of the New Zealand Department of External Affairs<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d92fn3">A. D. McIntosh.</note> has told us that he is strongly
                    opposed to any expansion of <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss> at this
                    time. We know that the Australians have been considerably irritated by the
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> attitude, by the “inspired” stories which
                    have appeared in the British press, and by Mr. Churchill’s failure to tell
                    Canberra what line he proposed to take in New York in January and, later, to
                    render an account of the meeting. Last October Prime Minister Menzies told an
                    officer of our Embassy at Canberra that he considered one of Mr. Churchill’s
                    messages to him on this subject to be a “stinker”. Last week, Mr. Alan Watt,
                    Secretary of the Australian Department of External Affairs, visited Washington
                    and told us that his Government remains as firmly as ever of the view that
                        <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> participation in <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                        >ANZUS</gloss> at this stage would be unwise. He added that he believed Mr.
                    Eden felt even more strongly about this matter than Mr. Churchill (though this
                    has not been our impression).</p>
                <p>It has been hoped that the development of the five-power liaison group for the
                    consideration of the defense of Southeast Asia would provide the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> with a satisfactory substitute for formal
                    participation <pb facs="0298" n="280" xml:id="pg_280"/> in <gloss
                        target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>. This hope is shared by the Australian and
                    New Zealand Governments.</p>
                <p>[Here follows a résumé of developments covered in previous documentation.]</p>
                <p>If Mr. Eden presses you, you might suggest to him that the US would be willing to
                    study and to recommend for consideration by the <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1"
                        >ANZUS</gloss> Council the suggestion made by Prime Ministers Menzies and
                    Holland to Mr. Churchill at London last December (and contained in the
                    memorandum Mr. Churchill handed you at New York) that a relationship be
                    established between <gloss target="#t_ANZAM1">ANZAM</gloss> (the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>–Australian-New Zealand military planning
                    organization) and the military representatives group of <gloss
                        target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>.<note n="4" xml:id="d92fn4">No indication
                        that an <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_ANZAM1"
                            >ANZAM</gloss> relationship was raised by or discussed with Eden during
                        his visit has been found in Department of State files.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
