<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Secretary of Commerce (Weeks) to the Special Assistant to the President
                    (Cutler)</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v01p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">109</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1954-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1954-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recRAvRT7ZvyjvRU2" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Railroad</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recbcbcHDEt9ge9nZ" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110610"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fissionable material</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recQ1cbTmrLYq6IWP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources" subject="energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1954-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1954-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="109"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d109">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">450.6031/6–754</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Secretary of Commerce (<persName type="from"
                            >Weeks</persName>) to the Special Assistant to the President (<persName
                            type="to">Cutler</persName>)</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-06-07">June 7,
                            1954</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <item>Subject:</item>
                    <item>East-West Trade</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear General Cutler</hi>:</p>
                <p>In the light of recent discussions in the National Security Council, it seems to
                    me important to bring to your attention a point which I consider has been too
                    lightly passed by without sufficient consideration for all of the ramifications
                    involved.</p>
                <p>In discussions to this point we have been considering on the one hand trade with
                    China and on the other hand trade with the Soviet and iron curtain countries as
                    though the two propositions were separate and distinct. The fact of the matter
                    is that trade with China and Russia are one and inseparable and in my judgment
                    should be treated as such in any further consideration of the subject.</p>
                <p>We discuss possible deletions from the embargo, quantitative and watch lists with
                    the thought in mind that this opening up of trade with Russia will have no
                    possible effect on our <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> embargo on trade with
                    China.</p>
                <p>If we let down the bars and authorize deletions from the three lists cited above,
                    we are to this extent and degree helping build the Soviet industrial war
                    potential and additionally we must understand that to a much greater extent we
                    shall be building first the Chinese industrial potential and later her
                    industrial war potential. Every item on the list of deletions sold to Russia can
                    be transshipped <pb facs="0392" n="1182" xml:id="pg_1182"/> to China by the
                    Trans-Siberian Railroad, or by a much easier route—through the port of
                    Vladivostok.</p>
                <p>I cannot emphasize strongly enough my desire for trade and my belief that trade
                    is good. I am equally certain that we can never project our ideology and
                    viewpoint through an iron curtain and that the way to cure Communism is in some
                    manner to show the Communists that some other way of life is better.</p>
                <p>However, I am equally certain that to a day by day increasing extent a war
                    machine cannot be in being or function without an efficient industrial machine
                    back of it. Science is making such fantastic progress that this industrial
                    machine has to be continually revised and brought up to date if it is to give
                    the war potential the support it must have.</p>
                <p>Our information leads us to believe that for the foreseeable future the Communist
                    countries cannot bring their industrial machine to this necessary point of
                    perfection without materiel and assistance from the free economies which they so
                    despise.</p>
                <p>To be specific, it seems to me that we should immediately, in our thinking on
                    this general subject, link China and Russia together and talk on the subject of
                    East-West trade as though the two countries were one. This, I am sure, is the
                    practical, realistic approach. At the present time 75% of China’s total imports,
                    estimated at $1,360,000,000, are received from the Soviet bloc. Since the
                    Russians are not presently able to produce any substantial surplus of any of the
                    items on our present strategic list, it is obvious that any additional quantity
                    of any item which China receives must in the first analysis be imported by
                    Russia under the present East-West trade arrangements. It seems to follow from
                    this conclusion that whatever relaxation there may be in the present level of
                    controls between the Soviet and the Western blocs will not only serve to assist
                    in building up the Soviet potential and the China potential but also serves to
                    make China increasingly dependent upon and subservient to Moscow. What we have
                    then is a situation whereby our actions in respect to controls over trade with
                    the Soviet bloc contribute directly to frustration of the policies which we are
                    trying to implement in respect to China.</p>
                <p>This situation is not cited for the purpose of suggesting that we should adopt a
                    China policy on controls parallel with the one which we are developing in
                    respect to trade with the Soviet bloc. It does suggest, however, that greater
                    caution should be exercised in considering any further retreat from our present
                    position in <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> so long as the present
                    unfriendly relationship exists between China and the Western bloc. It also
                    suggests to me at least the desirability of a review of this aspect of the
                    problem with the U.K. Government at the highest levels since, until this
                    question is <pb facs="0393" n="1183" xml:id="pg_1183"/> resolved in a way which
                    would enlist the wholehearted support of the U.S. public, it would be extremely
                    difficult to resolve the large number of items presently in disagreement with
                    the U.K. Government.</p>
                <p>The attached copies of reports from two of the Commerce Department’s technical
                    experts who have just returned from discussions on this subject with the British
                    in Paris are illustrative of the frustrating situation in which we find
                    ourselves.</p>
                <p>I believe we may have already agreed, pursuant to the criteria agreed upon in
                    London, to delete from the embargo list items which the Soviet bloc will find
                    very useful, if not in direct military production at least in production
                    providing strong support to their major military build-up. I gave you a list of
                    a number of items which we look at in this light.</p>
                <p>In this presentation I have only in mind the security of the United States and
                    our defense position, which, from this point of view, at least, I consider it my
                    duty to bring to your attention.</p>
                <p>Respectfully yours,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sinclair Weeks</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Attachment 1]</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Director of the Power Equipment
                            Division, Department of Commerce (<persName type="from">Hand</persName>)
                            to the Deputy to the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for International
                            Affairs (<persName type="to">Smith</persName>)</hi>
                        <note n="1" xml:id="d109fn1">Marshall Smith.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                        </seg>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-24">May 24,
                                1954</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Report on Tri-Lateral and <gloss target="#t_COCOM1"
                                >CoCom</gloss> Meetings in Paris</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Tri-Lateral and <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">CoCom</gloss> discussions on
                        Electrical and Power Equipment have been completed. Results could have been
                        much more satisfactory. The purpose of this memorandum is to propose methods
                        whereby procedures can be improved and, it is hoped, with much better
                        results.</p>
                    <p>The French attended the Tri-Lateral discussions on this equipment but did not
                        take an active part. Later this caused considerable difficulty in the <gloss
                            target="#t_COCOM1">CoCom</gloss> meetings because they did not follow
                        through with a united front. The British took a very active part in
                        Tri-Lateral meetings but gave only lukewarm endorsement in the <gloss
                            target="#t_COCOM1">CoCom</gloss> meetings. A solid U.S., British and
                        French front in the <gloss target="#t_COCOM1">CoCom</gloss> meetings would
                        assure agreements on many items; as it is, <pb facs="0394" n="1184"
                            xml:id="pg_1184"/> the countries with only minor interest in some items
                        are raising major questions without active rebuttal from these three
                        countries.</p>
                    <p>Time is allotted for both the Tri-Lateral and <gloss target="#t_COCOM1"
                            >CoCom</gloss> meetings on the basis of the number of items in a
                        category. In Power Equipment there are a few minor items and a few major
                        items. As much time is spent on minor items as is spent on major items. For
                        example, more time was spent on cutting electrodes than was spent on
                        turbo-generator sets. The U.S. Delegate should have insisted on more time
                        for the major items but since even he did not understand the importance of
                        power generating equipment it received inadequate time and consequently was
                        a disagreed item.</p>
                    <p>The U.S. has a strong position in their willingness to send numerous
                        technicians to these meetings. This strength is weakened by inadequate
                        briefing in Paris. More time is required for discussions between the team
                        coordinators and the technicians. In my case the <gloss target="#t_COCOM1"
                            >CoCom</gloss> meetings were unsatisfactory because the team coordinator
                        did not use his technician to best advantage nor did he take an aggressive
                        part in the meetings. Other countries look to the U.S. for active leadership
                        in these problems but unless we act the part, other countries will continue
                        to disagree with us and with each other.</p>
                    <p>Difficulties in these discussions were caused by different interpretations of
                        the criteria. The British and others insisted on conclusive evidence that
                        there was a shortage of power equipment in the Soviet Bloc. All countries of
                        the world, even the U.S., are short of power equipment yet we were asked to
                        prove that the SovBloc did not have all the generators they needed for
                        fissionable material productions.</p>
                    <p>The feeling that we were facing opponents rather than teammates persisted
                        through all the meetings which I attended. Concessions were made on some
                        items in an effort to agree on other items but this only brought forth more
                        disagreements.</p>
                    <p>Essentially all countries, except the U.S., are represented by the same
                        individuals for all categories. This results in some rather unusual
                        situations. Cyclotrons were confused with the diffusion process in atomic
                        energy, turbine propulsion units for ships were confused with diesel
                        propulsion units, and units of large size were completely confused with
                        small insignificant units. This combined with a basic disagreement on the
                        meaning of the criteria puts many items on the disagreed list.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0395" n="1185" xml:id="pg_1185"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">[Attachment 2]</note>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Report Prepared by John F. Skillman of the Department of
                            Commerce</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1954-05-25">May 25,
                                1954</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A Report on the Trilateral Discussions Held in Paris
                            May</hi> 10 <hi rend="smallcaps">Through May</hi> 13</p>
                    <p>The following paragraphs cover impressions received in preparing for and
                        attending the Trilateral discussions in Paris participated in by
                        representatives of England, France, and the United States, covering the
                        general industrial equipment area of machinery and production equipment.
                        This report does not give the detailed outcome of the discussions of each of
                        the 41 separate items of equipment but rather is intended to cover the
                        general impressions received of the entire East-West trade discussions now
                        going on.</p>
                    <p>The small staff of the <gloss target="#t_USRO1">USRO</gloss> located in the
                        Hotel Perey in Paris are working at high speed under tremendous pressure.
                        The men with whom I dealt, including H. Gardner Ainsworth, Sidney B.
                        Jacques, Mishell George, and Jack Myerson, are sincere in their efforts to
                        carry out the Trilateral conversations successfully and are literally
                        working nights, Saturdays, Sundays, holidays, and almost around the clock in
                        their efforts to meet a very difficult schedule of meetings, one right after
                        the other, covering all the areas of materials and equipment now under
                        discussion. The attributes or criteria laid down in the original top level
                        agreements do, of course, present serious difficulties to those endeavoring
                        to retain embargo controls on important materials and equipment. These
                        criteria give all the benefit to the side of the discussion endeavoring to
                        remove controls. This in itself makes the handling of the negotiations
                        extremely difficult; therefore, I was disturbed by the additional problems
                        our negotiators are faced with, many of which seemed unnecessary.</p>
                    <p>In the first place, the Trilateral meetings I attended were held in the
                        British Embassy. It would seem to me that the offices of the French
                        Government would be more suitable since the discussions are in Paris, or
                        failing that, some neutral spot. This may seem to be a small point but it
                        must be remembered that in dealing with the British representatives, you are
                        dealing with people who have almost ironclad instructions as to their
                        position on each item and this position can only change or alter after a
                        discussion with London. Meeting in the British Embassy allows any member of
                        the British team to quickly step outside the meeting, contact London, and be
                        back in the meeting in five minutes with his new instructions, <pb
                            facs="0396" n="1186" xml:id="pg_1186"/> which gives him a decided
                        advantage over the U.S. delegation who can only contact Washington by
                        overnight cable.</p>
                    <p>Secondly, the U.S. permanent delegation, because of the tight schedule of
                        Trilateral conversations, are faced each Monday morning with a new
                        delegation of experts from the United States. In my own case, and I know in
                        the case of some others, we met our U.S. people in the Paris office for the
                        first time exactly thirty minutes before the Trilateral meeting scheduled
                        four blocks away in the British Embassy. This means that the permanent staff
                        must get acquainted with the new group of experts, analyze their abilities
                        at this type of discussion, go over their problem cases to determine if
                        there is an expert present to cover them and if he can properly cover them,
                        and whether he is the kind of expert who can handle himself well in an open
                        discussion or if he had better be used only as an advisor. Coupled with all
                        this, the permanent staff is at the same time trying to get out its cabled
                        report covering the meetings held the preceding week, and the scene thus
                        generated is one of complete harassment and confusion into which the,
                        perhaps inexperienced, U.S. expert finds it very difficult to orient himself
                        until the Trilateral conversations are almost over. It seemed to me that if
                        it is worth sending a team of experts to Paris for these conversations, it
                        is certainly worth sending them two days earlier so that they could arrive
                        perhaps on a Thursday morning and be completely ready, settled and at ease
                        by the time their meetings start the following Monday. It should be
                        remembered that all U.S. experts are not experienced travelers abroad and
                        cannot necessarily speak the French language. To have these people arrive at
                        Orly Airport with no one to meet them, with, in some cases, no message
                        whatever for them at the airport, with no French francs to take care of them
                        over the week end and with no hotel reservation, is to add unnecessarily to
                        the confusion, in my opinion.</p>
                    <p>I believe the above paragraphs cover the general impressions received from my
                        ten days’ experience in the Trilateral conversations. I would like to
                        emphasize again that, in my opinion, the staff of <gloss target="#t_USRO1"
                            >USRO</gloss>, including the three or four secretaries available, were a
                        hard-working, sincere, determined group endeavoring to gain all they could
                        in these Trilateral conversations but their work, already complicated by the
                        very difficult attributes set down at a higher level, is made unnecessarily
                        more difficult by the confusion caused as explained above.</p>
                    <p>One last thought is that I believe the staff of <gloss target="#t_USRO1"
                            >USRO</gloss> needs stiffening by some assurance that their jobs will
                        continue beyond July 1 or that some arrangement will be made to continue
                        their employment. I seemed to detect an additional nervousness on the part
                        of some because so many controls are being done away with that it <pb
                            facs="0397" n="1187" xml:id="pg_1187"/> would seem their jobs are also
                        on the way out, and while I do not believe that this affected their thinking
                        regarding controls, I do believe it is an additional worry that could be
                        eliminated.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John F. Skillman</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
