<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Study Prepared in the Economic Defense Advisory Committee</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v01p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="recgOgMaD8zVpPNiC" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="reckz6KR6qJLArS7N" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="quarantine-blockade">Naval blockade</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recwVng9pENngtbLf" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="rec2SKz4RNoMDKY9k" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040584"
                        lcsh-match="exact">East-West trade</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recYvlR57vhz2meX0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="general" subject="commodities-exchange" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85028977" lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodities</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec_world_war_ii" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-ii" subject="world-war-ii" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148273" lcsh-match="exact">World War II</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-06-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-06-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="15"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d15">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                    <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files,
                    lot 63 D 351, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 104 Series</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Study Prepared in the Economic Defense Advisory Committee</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d15fn1">According to a memorandum by Lay, dated June 12,
                        transmitting this study to the National Security Council, the <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Senior Staff had requested the <gloss
                            target="#t_EDAC1">EDAC</gloss> on Feb. 11, 1952, to prepare a study of
                        the desirability and feasibility of the initiation of a preclusive buying
                        program. A memorandum by Counselor Bohlen to Assistant Secretary Thorp of
                        June 10 indicated that the original draft had been submitted to the
                        Department of State and had been forwarded with revisions to the <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Senior Staff on June 5. (<gloss
                            target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files,
                        lot 63 D 351, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 104 Series) The Senior
                        Staff further revised the study and recommended its implementation through
                        the <gloss target="#t_EDAC1">EDAC</gloss>. According to the memorandum of
                        discussion at the 119th <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> meeting on June
                        18, 1952, Jack Gorrie, Chairman of the National Security Resources Board,
                        concurred in the recommendations of the report, but no further action was
                        indicated. (Truman Library, Truman papers)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, [<date calendar="gregorian" when="1952-06-12">June 12,
                            1952</date>.]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Report on Organized and Coordinated Program of Covert
                        Preclusive Buying</hi>
                </p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Feasibility of Preclusive Buying</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Preclusive buying may be a useful instrument to further economic defense
                        objectives in connection with a few commodities of which the supply is not
                        readily susceptible of increase in response to price rises and in situations
                        where the acquisition of limited quantities could be counted on to have real
                        effect on the Soviet productive machine. There may also be spot cases of
                        various sorts, difficult to define in advance, which may provide
                        opportunities for effective preclusive buying.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>On the other hand, if there are a number of sources of supply, if
                        production of a given commodity is readily susceptible of increase in
                        response to price rises, or if the cost of acquisition of the supply is very
                        high, any of these factors can operate effectively to prevent a workable
                        preclusive buying program. Indeed, in such circumstances the initiation of a
                        preclusive buying program may do harm to the objective of denying strategic
                        materials to the bloc by expanding the available supply or by prematurely
                        sensitizing the bloc to the fact that its supply situation in the particular
                        commodity is vulnerable.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>It must also be recognized that the wisdom of undertaking a preclusive
                        buying program depends in part on whether an adequate pool of intelligence
                        exists on which to base the program, the extent to which covert tactics and
                        particular war measures can be used in support of the program, and the
                        alternative uses to which available funds could be put in building Western
                        defenses. Despite the major intelligence effort which is being made at
                        present, we do not know as much about the import dependence and the
                        requirements <pb facs="0065" n="855" xml:id="pg_855"/> of the Soviet bloc as
                        we knew about Germany and Japan during the last war. Except in the Korean
                        area we are not employing such measures as naval blockade and ship warrant
                        systems which serve to narrow the channels in which goods move and make the
                        penalties for illegal movements evident and effective. Finally, funds for
                        prosecution of the cold war and possibly for preclusive buying are limited
                        to a much greater degree than during the war when costs were not as limiting
                        on action as they are now. The latter fact necessitates decisions between
                        alternative uses of available funds, with the resultant measurement of
                        suggested programs against stiffer standards at present than when funds are
                        relatively free. In all these respects, it would appear that the basis on
                        which to justify a large-scale preclusive buying program is not as solid
                        under present circumstances as was the case in World War II.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>A major additional point concerns the need to assure the coordination of
                        procurement programs and preclusive buying programs. There are often found
                        conflicts which are inherent in such programs. Preclusive operations may
                        raise prices to a degree which makes the procurement of a particular
                        commodity for defense needs more difficult with the limited funds available.
                        Likewise, procurement programs may positively stimulate production to such
                        an extent that preclusive purchase of additional supplies becomes a greater
                        problem. Thus particular care must be taken in analyzing situations which
                        appear to call for preclusive purchase activity.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>A further limitation on the use of preclusive purchasing under present
                        conditions is the limited degree of dependence by the Soviet bloc upon the
                        free world for essential commodities. Frequently deliveries of such
                        commodities to the Soviet bloc are tied in as an essential counterpart in an
                        East-West trade agreement. Under these circumstances, it is especially
                        difficult to employ preclusive buying operations as a means of preventing
                        deliveries.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Applicability of Suggested Studies</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>The prospective opportunities for general use of preclusive buying
                        techniques do not seem to be such as to warrant separate commodity studies
                        of the scope suggested in the Annex to the <gloss target="#t_NSRB1"
                            >NSRB</gloss> study. However, commodity studies of general usefulness in
                        economic defense work, such as the studies being done in connection with
                        decreasing the economic reliance of the West on the Soviet bloc, may lead to
                        the location of commodities which might warrant a specific program of
                        preclusive purchase. The particular fields which seem promising, once
                        identified, could thereafter be studied intensively to determine finally
                        whether a preclusive purchase program should be instituted.</item>
                    <pb facs="0066" n="856" xml:id="pg_856"/>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The Preclusive Buying Working Group of the Economic Defense Advisory
                        Committee prepared the attached inventory<note n="2" xml:id="d15fn2">Not
                            printed.</note> indicating the status of numerous studies and
                        intelligence reports relating to the topics listed by the <gloss
                            target="#t_NSRB1">NSRB</gloss>. These topics primarily concern economic
                        defense in the broad sense rather than preclusive buying exclusively. The
                        Department of State will review those studies which have been completed to
                        see whether they suggest profitable lines of action in terms of preclusive
                        purchasing programs related to particular commodities. This point will also
                        be borne in mind in the preparation of reports not yet completed. In
                        connection with the studies referred to above relating to decreasing the
                        reliance of the West on the Soviet bloc, a positive approach has been
                        developed and an Economic Defense Advisory Committee working group has been
                        established to coordinate this activity which will cover the various
                        subjects listed which appear to warrant further consideration.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Special Cases</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>The spot cases which may warrant handling on a preclusive purchase basis
                        cannot be identified in general studies of the kind discussed in previous
                        paragraphs. They will generally appear in day to day intelligence reports or
                        other information channels. They may be noted by any one of several
                        agencies. The proposed Intelligence Working Group would serve as a useful
                        forum for identifying such cases. It is suggested that these special cases
                        also be placed in the Economic Defense Advisory Committee for consideration
                        as they arise.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Decisions on whether to engage in preclusive purchasing operations, either
                        in a general field or in a specific case, should be reached in the Economic
                        Defense Advisory Committee. The agency to undertake the actual purchase
                        should be designated at that time. The agencies which might make the
                        purchases and the funds to finance them have both been considered by the
                        Working Group on Preclusive Buying, but additional study of both points
                        seems warranted if future preclusive buying is to be undertaken without
                        undue delay when the occasion for action arises.</item>
                </list>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">Recommendations</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>It is recommended that the foregoing conclusions be approved and the
                        Economic Defense Advisory Committee be directed to: <list>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>ensure the continuous review of current intelligence in order to
                                identify spot cases which may warrant preclusive treatment;</item>
                            <pb facs="0067" n="857" xml:id="pg_857"/>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>review the operational aspects and administrative arrangements
                                which would have to be made to expedite such individual preclusive
                                purchases as the Committee might recommend; and</item>
                            <label>
                                <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>
                            </label>
                            <item>reach agreement as soon as possible on the question of available
                                funds and the establishment of procedures to facilitate access to
                                such funds, in order to permit the U.S. to be in a position to move
                                quickly in specific cases.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
