<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-01-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="200" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d200">
                    <note rend="inline" type="source"><gloss target="#t_AMS1">A/MS</gloss> files,
                        lot 54 <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 291, “Reports: Misc. Reports”</note>
                    <head><hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Chairman of the Loyalty Security Board
                                (<persName type="from">Snow</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi><note n="1" xml:id="d200fn1">In a
                            memorandum to John F. Barnard of the Management Staff of the Bureau of
                            Administration, dated Feb. 18, 1953, John W. Sipes of the Office of
                            Personnel in the Bureau of Security and Consular Affairs wrote that he
                            was attaching a copy of Snow’s memorandum to the Secretary, “however I
                            do not know whether this memorandum has actually gone to the Secretary
                            but it has been given to Mr. Humelsine for delivery to the Secretary
                            when he sees fit.” (<gloss target="#t_AMS1">A/MS</gloss> files, lot 54
                                <gloss target="#t_D1">D</gloss> 291, “Reports: Misc.
                            Reports”)</note></head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-01-08">January 8, 1953</date>.</dateline></opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <item>Subject:</item>
                        <item>Report on Loyalty Security Performance—1947–1952</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0639" n="1429" xml:id="pg_1429"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">1. Establishment and Authority</hi></p>
                    <p>The Loyalty Security Board of the State Department was set up by Secretary
                        Marshall, on June 9, 1947, as the Personnel Security Board. This was six
                        months before the President’s Loyalty Order (Executive Order 9835, March 21,
                        1947) was implemented by the issuance of directives by the Loyalty Review
                        Board of the Civil Service Commission. During this six months the Board made
                        10 adverse decisions, basing its action on the McCarran Rider to the
                        Appropriation Act, which gave to the Secretary of State the power of summary
                        dismissal of employees, “whenever he shall deem it necessary or advisable in
                        the interest of the United States”. After the President’s Loyalty Program
                        was put into effect, on December 17, 1947, the Department’s Board was
                        re-named the Loyalty Security Board, and was given the function of
                        administering the Loyalty Program, under the direction of the Loyalty Review
                        Board, but still continued to administer security cases, in which no loyalty
                        issue was raised, under the authority of the McCarran Rider.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">2. Personnel and Office</hi></p>
                    <p>The original Board consisted of three members, including the undersigned as
                        Chairman. The present Board consists of 28 members within the Department and
                        13 members stationed in Germany. There are 41 State Department officers who
                        at one time or another over the five years of its existence have served as
                        members of the Board, but who, by reason of resignation, or of transfer of
                        station or function, have become unavailable, and are no longer members.
                        This makes 82 the number of State Department officers who at one time or
                        another have served on the Board. The Chairman is the only member who has
                        served throughout the period. The members have all been appointed by the
                        Secretary acting through the Deputy Under Secretary for Administration and
                        have been high-level officers of the Department. None of them have given
                        full time to the Board, and they sit on cases in panels of three. The
                        Chairman frequently sits on the panel, but by no means always; he has
                        probably sat on four-fifths of the cases.</p>
                    <p>The Board was originally served by a part-time counsel. In August, 1950,
                        however, the present full-time counsel, John W. Sipes, was substituted, and
                        in June, 1951, an assistant full-time counsel, Lawson A. Moyer, Jr., was
                        added. These counsel administer the office, draft interrogatories, write
                        letters of charges, prepare cases for hearing, and assist in the hearings.
                        The Board has an able secretarial staff, and occupies a dignified and
                        convenient suite of rooms in New State, including two hearing rooms and five
                        offices.</p>
                    <pb facs="0640" n="1430" xml:id="pg_1430"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">3. Function of the Board</hi></p>
                    <p>The Board receives investigative reports of full field investigations made by
                        the Federal Bureau of Investigation in loyalty cases, and of such
                        investigations made by the Security Division of the Department in cases in
                        which security alone is involved. These reports are submitted to panels of
                        three and are read and considered by the designated panel. Since the files
                        are objective and reflect all the information gathered, whether favorable or
                        unfavorable, cases may be decided favorably to the employee on the
                        information in the file alone. If more information is desired the panel may
                        request further investigation by the FBI or by the Security Division, or it
                        may address a written interrogatory to the employee and receive his sworn
                        reply. In case the panel is still in doubt it must prefer charges and give
                        the employee a hearing before it can recommend dismissal on matters relating
                        to either loyalty or security. It should be noted that security is an issue
                        in all cases, but the issue of loyalty arises only on a full field
                        investigation by the FBI. To an adverse decision of the panel there is
                        appeal to the Secretary of State in all cases, and a further appeal to the
                        Loyalty Review Board in loyalty cases. All decisions in which loyalty is an
                        issue, whether favorable or unfavorable to the employee, are submitted to
                        the Loyalty Review Board for post-audit. If the Review Board disagrees with
                        a favorable decision, it may, under its regulations, take over the case
                        itself, re-hear the employee, enter its own findings and make an advisory
                        recommendation to the Secretary, which in effect may sustain or reverse the
                        Loyalty Security Board.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">4. Volume of Work—Adverse
                        Decisions</hi></p>
                    <p>From its establishment through December 15, 1952, almost exactly five years
                        since the implementation of the Loyalty Program, the Loyalty Security Board
                        has received 684 loyalty cases, head count, and 61 cases involving security
                        only, or a total of 745 cases, and has disposed of all but 100 loyalty cases
                        and 10 security cases. Since many cases are considered more than once, the
                        total of decisions made by the Board, case count, is much larger, 958 to be
                        exact. During the course of this large volume of work, the Board has issued
                        285 interrogatories to employees under investigation, and has held 97
                        hearings on charges. In 77 cases the Board has requested further
                        investigation by the Federal Bureau of Investigation.</p>
                    <p>There has been some public criticism of the Board by persons unacquainted
                        with its work. Unfortunately unfamiliarity with the work of the Board at one
                        time extended even to some members of the Review Board, with the
                        consequences that some remarks by one member of that Board, intended for its
                        ears alone, and not <pb facs="0641" n="1431" xml:id="pg_1431"/> based on
                        fact, were abstracted from its records and published abroad. It is the
                        understanding of the Chairman that the Review Board is presently well
                        satisfied with the work of the Loyalty Security Board. At any rate, out of
                        575 post-audits of the Loyalty Security Board decisions, the Review Board
                        remanded but 19 cases and has reversed the State Department Board in but two
                        instances.</p>
                    <p>As a matter of fact, since its inception the Loyalty Security Board has made
                        30 adverse decisions, three on grounds relating to loyalty, 15 on grounds
                        relating to security but in cases in which loyalty was in issue, and 12 in
                        cases in which only security was involved. Some comment may be required as
                        to the small proportion of cases in which disloyalty was found. This is
                        affected by at least three factors: (1) The Department had its initial
                        housecleaning in 1947, before the Loyalty Program was set up. The 10 adverse
                        decisions of the Board during this period have to be classed as security
                        decisions, because there was no Loyalty Program in effect. Since these were
                        the outstanding bad cases of the Department, at least some of these
                        decisions would probably have been based on loyalty, had the Loyalty Program
                        been then in operation. Similar cases in other Departments of the Government
                        would have been entered in the loyalty column.</p>
                    <list>
                        <label>(2)</label>
                        <item>From time to time and especially during 1948, employees, against whom
                            charges were serious, have resigned prior to a decision by the Board.
                            During the five years the Board has lost jurisdiction of 51 cases, by
                            separation after it had received the case but prior to decision. It is
                            impossible to say how many of these cases would have led to adverse
                            loyalty decisions had the Board been able to finish its work. In at
                            least 20 of these cases charges and hearing had been voted by the
                            Board.</item>
                        <label>(3)</label>
                        <item>The original standard of judgment in loyalty cases was quite strict.
                            The Board was not permitted to find disloyalty unless “on all the
                            evidence reasonable grounds exist for belief that the person involved is
                            disloyal to the Government of the United States”. By Executive Order
                            10241, April 28, 1951, the President changed the standard so that an
                            employee could be removed if “on all the evidence there is a reasonable
                            doubt as to the loyalty of the person involved to the Government of the
                            United States”. Since from the beginning the Loyalty Security Board has
                            applied the standard of reasonable doubt to the issue of security, it
                            was, prior to April 28, 1951, much easier to find security risk than
                            disloyalty. Promptly on the change in the standard, however, the Board
                            found adversely on grounds relating to loyalty in three cases. There is
                            presently no difference between the standard applied to loyalty and that
                            applied to security. In either case if there is a reasonable doubt, the
                            Department is given the benefit of the doubt.</item>
                    </list>
                    <pb facs="0642" n="1432" xml:id="pg_1432"/>
                    <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">5. Product of the Board—“McCarthy
                            Cases”</hi></p>
                    <p>684 employees of the Department of State have been given a “full field
                        investigation” by the Federal Bureau of Investigation and processed under
                        the loyalty program. 584 of these have been passed before a panel of the
                        Loyalty Security Board, and all but 18 have been ‘cleared’ as to both
                        loyalty and security. Many of them have been cleared more than once: Some of
                        them have been reconsidered under the new standard; some of them have been
                        reconsidered owing to supplemental information received from the Federal
                        Bureau of Investigation; and 19 of them have been reconsidered on remand
                        from the Review Board for further processing. In only four cases has the
                        Review Board exercised its power to take over the case, hold a hearing, and
                        decide the case for itself; in two of these cases the Review Board sustained
                        the Loyalty Security Board, and in two of them it reversed the Board, the
                        John S. Service and the John Carter Vincent cases.</p>
                    <p>In February, 1950, Senator Joseph M. McCarthy stated publicly that there were
                        205 known Communists in the State Department. Subsequently, on February 20,
                        1950, in the Senate of the United States, he gave a list of 80 persons, 42
                        of whom were then, or subsequently, in the employ of the Department. He
                        afterward added names, so that in all there are now 61 persons whom Senator
                        McCarthy has identified as Communists or persons “loyal to the Communist
                        Party”. In 8 of these cases no loyalty issue ever arose in the Department,
                        in that the individuals were favorably processed as to loyalty by the FBI,
                        who, finding no disloyal data, returned the names to the Department without
                        full field investigation and submission to the Board. Of the remaining 53,
                        34 had been already cleared by the Loyalty Security Board (and 27 of these
                        cases post-audited by the Loyalty Review Board) before the Senator spoke.
                        Since then, six of the named persons have resigned and one has died (all
                        after clearance and favorable post-audit). All of the remaining 28 cases
                        have been reconsidered under the new standard, and with two exceptions have
                        been cleared by the Loyalty Security Board (24 have been finally and
                        favorably post-audited by the Review Board). In two cases only, as stated
                        above, has the favorable decision of the Loyalty Security Board been
                        reversed by the Review Board.</p>
                    <p>In résumé, of the 61 State Department employees named by Senator McCarthy,
                        only four have been rated ineligible for employment, two by the Loyalty
                        Security Board—Esther Brunauer and … both on security grounds—and two by the
                        Loyalty Review Board—John S. Service and John Carter Vincent, both on
                        loyalty grounds.</p>
                    <pb facs="0643" n="1433" xml:id="pg_1433"/>
                    <p>The Loyalty Security Board has from the beginning considered itself to be a
                        judicial body, and has endeavored to perform its duty honestly with due
                        regard to the evidence, with fairness to the employee, and with proper
                        appreciation of the gravity of the issues involved to the Department and to
                        the Country. It should not be overlooked that the Board has had no
                        jurisdiction to pass on the suitability of employees, as distinguished from
                        their loyalty or security.</p>
                    <p>[Here follows numbered paragraph 6 which indicates that 3 attachments
                        accompanied the memoranda: (1) “A year-by-year analysis of the adjudication
                        of cases by the Loyalty Security Board,” (2) “A step-by-step history of the
                        30 adverse decisions of the Loyalty Security Board,” and (3) “A step-by-step
                        history of the 61 cases named by Senator McCarthy who were employed at the
                        time of his charges.” None of these attachments was found with the source
                        text.]</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>