<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Discussion at the 157th Meeting of the National Security
                    Council on Thursday, July 30, 1953</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1952-54v01p2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1953-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1953-07-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rec7SplpGb7GrlXCp" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006793"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Mobilization</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="recyvYvKBWCiz1E8g" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026326"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil defense</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recc5wAbpL3cvsf8h" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85076761"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">License</term>
                    <term ref="recAsWFxRUa5DhtTM" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133456"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Television</term>
                    <term ref="recajGOY1Llc8movd" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="reciDLZ6apHdoX7uq" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="self-determination">Political settlement</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                    <term ref="recWFe7yioiL0h10x" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008205"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Satellite</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-07-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="48"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">Eisenhower Library, Eisenhower papers, Whitman
                    file</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Discussion at the 157th Meeting of the National
                        Security Council on Thursday, July 30, 1953</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d48fn1">This memorandum of discussion was prepared on July
                        31 by Boggs.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret<lb/>eyes only</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1953-07-30">July 30,
                            1953</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>The following were present at the 157th meeting of the National Security Council:
                    The President of the United States, presiding (except for the first part of Item
                    1, which was presided over by the Vice President); the Vice President of the
                    United States; the Secretary of State; the Secretary of Defense; the Director
                    for Mutual Security; the Director, Office of Defense Mobilization. Also present
                    were the Secretary of the Treasury; the Attorney General; the Secretary of
                    Commerce (for Item 1); the Assistant Secretary of Commerce (for Item 1); the
                    Director, Bureau of the Budget; the Chairman, Atomic Energy Commission (for Item
                    5); the Federal Civil Defense Administrator (for Item 5); Robert R. Bowie,
                    Department of State (for Item 5); Walter S. Delany, Office of the Director for
                    Mutual Security (for Item 1); Kenneth R. Hansen, Economic Defense Advisory
                    Committee (for Item 1); the Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff; the Director of
                    Central Intelligence; Robert Cutler, Special Assistant to the President; C. D.
                    Jackson, Special Assistant to the President; Col. Paul T. Carroll, Acting White
                    House Staff Secretary; the Executive Secretary, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss>; Marion W. Boggs, Coordinator, <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> Planning Board Assistants.</p>
                <p>There follows a summary of the discussion at the meeting and the chief points
                    taken.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. Economic Defense</hi> (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    152 and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/1;<note n="2" xml:id="d48fn2">
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/1, dated July 22, 1953, is not
                        printed. Except for the changes specified in this memorandum of discussion,
                        it was textually the same as <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/2, <ref
                            target="#d49">
                            <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>
                        </ref>.</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 806<note n="3" xml:id="d48fn3">
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action No. 806 consists of the
                        directives issued by the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> at its meeting
                        of June 4, 1953; for the memorandum of discussion at that meeting, see <ref
                            target="#pg_988">p. 988</ref>.</note>)</p>
                <p>In introducing <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/1 to the Council, Mr.
                    Cutler recalled that at its 137th meeting the Council had noted a Progress
                    Report on <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 104/2,<note n="4" xml:id="d48fn4"
                        >For the progress report under reference, dated Jan. 19, 1953, see <ref
                            target="#pg_913">p. 913</ref>.</note> and had directed that this report
                    be reviewed and recommendations prepared for Council consideration. Accordingly,
                    the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Planning Board had prepared <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152, which stated four alternative lines of
                    policy. On June 4 the Council had decided to proceed in the direction of
                    Alternative 4. The courses of action in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    152/1 were designed to carry out this decision. Mr. Cutler <pb facs="0215"
                        n="1005" xml:id="pg_1005"/> noted that about 100 pages of existing policy
                    had been compressed into a dozen pages in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    152/1, so that the paper would probably seem very general to anyone reading it
                    for the first time, but the Economic Defense Advisory Committee, which had
                    participated with the Planning Board in the preparation of the report, felt that
                    its meaning was quite clear to those who would have to implement it.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cutler then said that since the Korean armistice had been signed, it would be
                    necessary to delete paragraph 19–<hi rend="italic">a</hi> of <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/1, and to amend paragraphs 8 and 15
                    slightly. He called the attention of the Council to alternative language
                    proposed by the Department of Defense for paragraphs 6, 18–<hi rend="italic"
                        >a</hi>, 20 and 24. He also called attention to the Note by the Executive
                    Secretary, which proposed that <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 91/1,<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d48fn5">
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 91/1, in <ref
                            target="frus1950v04#pg_227">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iv</hi>, p.227</ref>.</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 104/2 and <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 122/1<note n="6" xml:id="d48fn6">For the text of <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 122/1, see <ref target="frus1952-54v14p1"
                            >volume <hi rend="smallcaps">xiv</hi>
                        </ref>.</note> would be superseded by adoption of the present report.</p>
                <p>Secretary Wilson said that his advisers in the Department of Defense felt that
                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 122/1 should not be superseded at this
                    time.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cutler then read a letter from the Secretary of Commerce which indicated that
                    the Department of Commerce would be able to carry out its export license
                    functions with respect to Hong Kong and Macao under <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 152/1 if it were adopted and <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 122/1 superseded. Should it be decided to supersede <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 122/1, Commerce would be prepared to recommend
                    any necessary revisions in export procedures with respect to Hong Kong and
                    Macao.</p>
                <p>Secretary Wilson said he believed that the Hong Kong–Macao problem was a separate
                    one.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cutler suggested that it might be desirable to consider the policy in <gloss
                        target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/1 firsthand then decide whether existing
                    reports should be superseded.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stassen called on Admiral Delany to comment on <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                        >NSC</gloss> 152/1 with particular reference to the alternative language
                    proposed by the Department of Defense.</p>
                <p>Admiral Delany said that <gloss target="#t_EDAC1">EDAC</gloss> felt that precise
                    and concise wording was needed in the new policy. He therefore preferred to say
                    that we should control exports which “clearly” contribute significantly to the
                    war potential of the Soviet bloc, rather than the less precise language proposed
                    by Defense, namely, “exports which may reasonably be shown to contribute
                    significantly to the Soviet war potential.”</p>
                <p>The Vice President asked what the real difference was between these two ways of
                    phrasing the problem.</p>
                <pb facs="0216" n="1006" xml:id="pg_1006"/>
                <p>Admiral Delany said that for example, television transmitters did not clearly
                    contribute to Soviet war potential, but by a roundabout chain of reasoning it
                    might be reasonably shown that they did so contribute.</p>
                <p>(At this point the President entered the meeting and took the chair.)</p>
                <p>Secretary Wilson thought machine tools would be a better example. Under the
                    language proposed by <gloss target="#t_EDAC1">EDAC</gloss> any agency objecting
                    to a shipment of machine tools to the Soviet bloc would have to prove clearly
                    that they were to be used militarily before the shipment could be stopped. In
                    practice this would be very difficult, since most such tools were
                    interchangeable as between military and commercial use and, moreover, the onus
                    of such proof would in most cases fall on the Department of Defense.</p>
                <p>Mr. Cutler said the language in the report was broad enough to allow us to go
                    almost as far as we wanted in permitting or restricting exports. He added that
                    without the word “clearly” in the report, the present policy would not be
                    changed very much. Admiral Delany agreed.</p>
                <p>Secretary Dulles preferred the language in the main text, i.e., the word
                    “clearly”. Our purpose was to switch from discouraging to encouraging trade. He
                    felt that anything could contribute somewhat to the war potential of the Soviet
                    bloc.</p>
                <p>The President said he was not sure he fully understood the Defense argument.</p>
                <p>Secretary Wilson said that if we went so far as to allow anything to be shipped
                    to the Soviet bloc which did not clearly contribute to their war potential, we
                    might as well use the language of the Battle Act, which referred to atomic
                    energy materials, arms, ammunition, and implements of war.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stassen said he believed he could sum up the proposed new policy by saying
                    that it would result in (1) a relaxed attitude toward non-strategic items, (2) a
                    greater concentration of control effort on a smaller number of items, and (3) a
                    decreasing reliance by the Western countries on critical imports from the Soviet
                    bloc.</p>
                <p>The President felt that we should concentrate on the question of need. If our
                    opponent needs something very badly, then that something is strategic and that
                    is something we should keep him from getting. We should not forget that we are
                    trying to induce the satellites to come over to our side by judicious use of
                    trade. We must always ask ourselves how we are helping ourselves by our trade
                    policy.</p>
                <p>The President asked why any adverb such as “clearly” was necessary. He felt that
                    each case should be solved on its merits, and <pb facs="0217" n="1007"
                        xml:id="pg_1007"/> that the policy adopted should not be too restrictive,
                    since the situation might change.</p>
                <p>Mr. Stassen asked whether Defense was agreeable to narrowing the lists of
                    strategic items.</p>
                <p>Secretary Wilson replied in the affirmative, but added that he didn’t want the
                    lists made too narrow.</p>
                <p>Secretary Weeks said that the burden of proof under present policy was on
                    Commerce to show that an item does not contribute to Soviet war potential. The
                    new policy would reverse this burden of proof. He felt that reasonable men could
                    always agree through such machinery as <gloss target="#t_EDAC1"
                    >EDAC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>The President said again that our policy was to try to detach the satellites from
                    the USSR. He believed that trade could help in carrying out this policy. Our
                    trade should be used in a broad and subtle way to weaken the Soviets.</p>
                <p>Secretary Dulles felt that our trade policy could not be absolutely rigid, and
                    that it would have to differentiate between various countries.</p>
                <p>The President wanted everyone to understand that he was not trying to give the
                    USSR anything, but that his remarks had been addressed to winning the satellites
                    away from the USSR by means of trade.</p>
                <p>Secretary Dulles agreed that we should use trade as a weapon and, in particular,
                    we should try to impress on the satellites the fact that they can get
                    commodities from us which they cannot obtain from Russia.</p>
                <p>The President said that in some cases we might not be hurting the Soviet bloc by
                    cutting off trade between the West and the satellites, because such a policy
                    might compel the satellites to beg Russia to give them what we would not.</p>
                <p>The President remarked that the present paper implied that trade was a weapon
                    only as an afterthought, whereas he felt this idea should be stated positively.
                    The purpose of our trade should be to split the Soviet world.</p>
                <p>Mr. C. D. Jackson also felt that the entire paper was pitched negatively.</p>
                <p>At the suggestion of Mr. Stassen, it was agreed to add a new objective in
                    paragraph 18, to read “to decrease, through skillful and flexible use of trade
                    controls, the political and economic unity of the Soviet bloc.”</p>
                <p>Mr. Cutler felt that the paper had achieved considerable flexibility, and read
                    paragraph 20 as an example. He also noted that the problem of getting along with
                    our allies in trade policy was an important factor.</p>
                <pb facs="0218" n="1008" xml:id="pg_1008"/>
                <p>The President said that was right, and that our allies introduced an added
                    complication that needed careful handling.</p>
                <p>Secretary Wilson asked whether it wouldn’t be desirable to refer the report back
                    to the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Planning Board for a revision in view
                    of the new ideas expressed at the meeting.</p>
                <p>The President said he felt these ideas were already incorporated in the paper if
                    a few amendments were made, such as deleting the adverb “clearly” wherever it
                    appeared. He also agreed with the suggestion made by Mr. Stassen, that
                    “readjusted” was the correct word, rather than “relaxed”, in paragraph 20.</p>
                <p>At the suggestion of Mr. Cutler, it was agreed that the Economic Defense Advisory
                    Committee should review <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 122/1 and submit to
                    the Council any revisions which it considered necessary.</p>
                <p>The National Security Council: <list>
                        <label>a.</label>
                        <item>Adopted the statement of policy contained in <gloss target="#t_NSC1"
                                >NSC</gloss> 152/1, superseding <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            104/2 and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 91/1, subject to the
                            following changes: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Page 3, paragraph 6:</hi> In the last
                                    sentence, delete the word “clearly*” and delete the footnote to
                                    which the asterisk refers.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Page 3, paragraph 8:</hi> In the first
                                    sentence, substitute for the word “once” the words “now
                                    that”.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Page 6, paragraph 15:</hi> In the last
                                    sentence, substitute for the words “to be” the words “of making
                                    them”.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Page 7, paragraph 18–a:</hi> Delete the word
                                    “clearly*” and delete the footnote to which the asterisk
                                    refers.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Page 7:</hi> Add a new subparagraph <hi
                                        rend="italic">e</hi> to paragraph 18, reading as follows:
                                    “To decrease, through flexibility in applying controls, the
                                    political and economic unity of the Soviet bloc.”</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Page 7, paragraph 19:</hi> Delete subparagraph
                                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, and revise the paragraph to read
                                    as follows: “With respect to Communist China, in the light of
                                    the Korean armistice, and pending a political settlement in
                                    Korea and a review of basic policies toward Communist China and
                                    Korea, maintain the present U.S. level of controls on
                                    transactions with Communist China and continue intensified
                                    efforts to persuade our allies to refrain from relaxing their
                                    controls on trade with Communist China.”</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Page 8, paragraph 20:</hi> In the last
                                    sentence, delete the asterisk and the footnote to which it
                                    refers, and substitute for the word “relaxed” the word
                                    “readjusted”.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Page 9, paragraph 24:</hi> Delete the word
                                    “clearly*” and the footnote to which the asterisk refers.</p>
                            </quote>
                        </item>
                        <label>b.</label>
                        <item>Directed the Economic Defense Advisory Committee to review <gloss
                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 122/1 in the light of <gloss
                                target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/1 as amended, and to submit
                            recommendations for any revision in <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            122/1 required to make it conform to <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                            152/1 as amended.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <pb facs="0219" n="1009" xml:id="pg_1009"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Note:</hi>
                    <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/1, as revised and approved by the
                    President, subsequently circulated as <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 152/2.
                    The action in b above subsequently referred to <gloss target="#t_EDAC1"
                        >EDAC</gloss> for implementation.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of significant world developments affecting United
                    States security, the report by the President’s Committee on International
                    Information Activities of June 30, 1953, the reported decline in United States
                    prestige abroad, Project Solarium, armaments and American policy, United States
                    policy on Soviet and Satellite defectors, and the National Security Council
                    status of projects.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
