<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-07T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="173" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d173">
                        <head>173. Message From <persName corresp="#p_ARB1" type="from">Robert B.
                                Anderson</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Acting Secretary of
                                State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d173fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Files: Lot
                                59 D 518; Alpha—<persName corresp="#p_AD1">Anderson</persName> Talks
                                    w/<gloss target="#t_BG1">BG</gloss> &amp; <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>. Incoming
                                Telegrams—Jan.–March 1956. Part II. Secret. Also transmitted to
                                Karachi for Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 117</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Athens</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-03-07"><hi rend="italic">March 7,
                                1956</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>REF</head>
                            <item>Outgoing No. 10<note n="2" xml:id="d173fn2"><ref target="#d167">Document 167</ref>.</note>
                            </item>
                        </list>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>We discussed the desirability of meeting <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName> at 2300 hours
                                    yesterday<note n="3" xml:id="d173fn3">March 6.</note> and
                                concluded that rather than urge an additional meeting we should put
                                the burden on him. Accordingly we advised Ali Sabry that we would be
                                glad to meet but did not at this time have additional proposals
                                other than those heretofore advanced. That we <pb facs="0349" n="321" xml:id="pg_321"/> would be pleased if <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName> desired additional
                                conversations, or had affirmative proposals for progress which he
                                could discuss with us.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Ali Sabry advised us in late afternoon that <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName> had no additional proposals
                                or information which required discussion.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>All of the points suggested in ref were quite forcibly urged
                                during the course of our meetings. We particularly urged that this
                                was perhaps the most favorable time in the foreseeable future when
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName> could assure a
                                position of leadership both on the question of the Jordan Plan and
                                the Israeli settlement. He concedes that he would win wide backing
                                from world opinion if he did this but states that the reverse would
                                be true in the Arab world.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>This morning I suggested to <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName> that we might appropriately call on
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName> on other business
                                during the next 48 hours and make these points:<note n="4" xml:id="d173fn4">See <ref target="#d191">Document
                                    191</ref>.</note>
                                <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>That we were keenly disappointed by his negative position
                                        and felt that the burden of making affirmative and helpful
                                        suggestions towards progress now rested with him.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>We hope that he might make such suggestions during this
                                        week and that they would afford the basis of our return to
                                        Cairo.</item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>To suggest that possibly after the tripartite talks in
                                        Cairo he might be in a position to advise us with reference
                                        to such affirmative steps that he now felt able to
                                        take.</item>
                                    <label>d.</label>
                                    <item>That we would remain in this area for several days and
                                        would be pleased if <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName> had any affirmative suggestions from
                                        any source which he would like to pursue with us.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item><persName corresp="#p_BHA1">Byroade</persName> will probably
                                report to you separately, however he discussed with me his
                                conversations with <persName corresp="#p_TSH1">Trevelyan</persName>
                                and in the light of these conversations and his own thinking is more
                                inclined to believe that something has occurred during the last few
                                days which has changed <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName>’s point of view towards this mission and has
                                probably alerted [<hi rend="italic">altered</hi>?] his own
                                assessment of his capabilities. He is more inclined to believe that
                                something has occurred to change <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName>’s approach than that the attitude which he
                                expressed on Monday night<note n="5" xml:id="d173fn5">See <ref target="#d164">Document 164</ref>.</note> has been in the
                                back of his mind from the beginning.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Those stationed in Cairo … are inclined to believe that <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName> is more and more
                                preoccupied with the influence of the refugees and inclined to
                                believe that Jordan and Syria would be particularly difficult for
                                him to handle on either of the issues of the <persName corresp="#p_JE1">Johnston</persName> plan or the Israeli dispute
                                because of growing restiveness among the refugees. Sources here also
                                believe that <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasr</persName> has a
                                    <pb facs="0350" n="322" xml:id="pg_322"/> growing concern about
                                the stability of the Jordanian and Syrian Governments on account of
                                the refugee problem.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Drafted 1845 hours local 7 March.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>