<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>242. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, April 5,
                    1956, 12:15 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">242</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-04-05T12:15:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-04-05T12:15:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Near East</term>
                    <term ref="recz8s8KnoGl2pvSV" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec23ea53997c6eb17" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Baghdad Pact</term>
                    <term ref="rec636TkKuD4w6mkL" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97007802"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Flood</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recLolgZHy7viyqKU" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068390"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-04-05T12:15:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-04-05T12:15:00-05:00" n="242"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d242">
                <head>242. Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State, Washington, April 5,
                    1956, 12:15 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d242fn1">Source: Department of
                        State, <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NEA1"
                            >NEA</gloss> Files: Lot 61 D 417, Omega #2. Top Secret; Omega. Drafted
                        on April 6 by <persName corresp="#p_RWM1">Rountree</persName>. A notation on
                        the source text reads: “Not cleared by the Secretary 4/9”.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1956-04-05T12:15:00-05:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 5, 1956, 12:15 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Middle East Policy</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>The Secretary</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BRW1">Ronald</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName>Rountree W. Bailey</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> said he had received
                    from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJS1">Selwyn Lloyd</persName> the latter’s views
                    concerning policies in the Near East which were discussed by the Ambassador with
                    the Secretary on April 1.<note n="2" xml:id="d242fn2">See <ref target="#d232"
                            >Document 232</ref>.</note> He stated these views presumably were also
                    those of the British Government. He had reduced to writing the substance of the
                    message <pb facs="0491" n="463" xml:id="pg_463"/> and handed to the Secretary
                    and others present copies of this document dated April 5.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d242fn3">
                        <ref target="#d243">
                            <hi rend="italic">Infra.</hi>
                        </ref>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>After reading the paper the Secretary inquired as to the reason the British did
                    not wish meetings with Saudi Arabia on the Buraimi issue to be held in New York,
                    as suggested by King <persName corresp="#p_SAA1">Saud</persName>. Sir <persName
                        corresp="#p_MSRM1">Roger</persName> replied that they felt the atmosphere in
                    New York, near the United Nations to which the Saudi Arabs had threatened to
                    bring the issue, would not be suitable. Also, the British believed there were
                    strong advantages in sending a delegation to Saudi Arabia where direct access to
                    the King would be afforded.</p>
                <p>Sir <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Roger</persName> informed the Secretary that he
                    had just received a message from London setting forth details upon measures
                    which the British were prepared to undertake with respect to the proposed
                    Economic Board and other economic matters to be discussed at the forthcoming
                    Baghdad Pact Council meeting in Tehran. A memorandum on this matter would be
                    provided to the Department later in the day.<note n="4" xml:id="d242fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> transmitted the memorandum,
                        entitled “Baghdad Pact”, to <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>
                        under cover of a memorandum on April 5. Copies of these documents are in
                        Department of State, Central Files, 780.5/4–556 and <hi rend="italic"
                            >ibid.,</hi>
                        <gloss target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Files: Lot 59 D 518, Omega—Re Baghdad
                        Pact 1956.</note> The Secretary commented that we had been giving some
                    thought to the economic aspects of the forthcoming Council meeting and were
                    formulating a response to the recent British message on this subject.</p>
                <p>The Secretary noted that in the paper which Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> had handed him the British seemed
                    concerned that many people had concluded that American and British policies in
                    the Near East were different. He commented that the flood of press material from
                    London had played up such differences. The story in the <hi rend="italic">New
                        York Times</hi> of April 5, filed by Drew Middleton, for example, emphasized
                    this aspect on the basis of information presumably obtained in London.<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d242fn5">The article was entitled “<persName
                            corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName> Will Stress Mideast to
                        Soviet”.</note> It was being said that our alliance might collapse as a
                    result of US-<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> policy differences in the Near
                    East. If the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> felt, as we felt, that it was
                    wise to avoid the impression there were vast differences between us, it would
                    appear that they had to a considerable extent control over what was said to
                    members of the press. He emphasized that it was not our effort to publicize
                    differences; in fact we were disturbed at the publicity which was emanating from
                    London.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> commented that the
                    point in the message from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJS1">Lloyd</persName>
                    concerned publicity and attitudes in the Near East area more than in the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> or the US. The Secretary responded that it would
                    be difficult to avoid such news stories being picked up in the <pb facs="0492"
                        n="464" xml:id="pg_464"/> Near Eastern states. He went on to say that, while
                    publicity regarding great differences between the US and the <gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> was harmful to our respective and joint efforts
                    in the Near East, on the other hand we did not wish to give the impression that
                    in every respect we were working together. If, for example, we claimed solid
                        US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> agreement on the Buraimi issue our
                    position in Saudi Arabia would be gravely jeopardized. We could not be
                    associated one hundred per cent with British policy which might be considered to
                    be hostile to Saudi Arabia. Such an indication of US–<gloss target="#t_UK1"
                        >UK</gloss> solidarity might imply not only that we agreed with the British
                    position at this time but also that we had been consulted by the British and
                    agreed upon their previous actions on the Arabian Peninsula. He had understood
                    that the British had intentionally not told us in advance about moves at Buraimi
                    since they realized that such advance consultation might have placed us in an
                    embarrassing situation.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> agreed with these
                    observations of the Secretary, commenting that the British did not expect to
                    achieve one hundred per cent the objective of demonstrating US–<gloss
                        target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> solidarity. They had put forth the thought as a
                    matter of general application with respect to broad policies in the area.</p>
                <p>The Secretary emphasized the importance of placing the Buraimi negotiations and
                    general <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>-Saudi relations on some basis whereby
                    the Saudis would not intensify their anti-British efforts. This, however, was
                    largely up to the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> since it was clear that a
                    mere demonstration of US–<gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> solidarity would not
                    have a useful effect in overcoming Saudi Arabian anti-British programs in the
                    Arab world.</p>
                <p>Commenting more generally on the British paper, the Secretary said that, by and
                    large, we appeared to be fairly close to agreement.</p>
                <p>Referring to the Baghdad Pact, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1"
                        >Makins</persName> alluded to a number of messages which the British had
                    received from other Pact members, disclosing doubt and frustration concerning
                    the American attitude. They felt the US was not giving sufficient support to the
                    Pact or following through in providing adequate material benefits to the Pact
                    countries. Dismay has been caused particularly in Iran and Iraq.</p>
                <p>The Secretary observed that one of the difficulties involved was that the member
                    countries did not all view the Baghdad Pact undertaking in precisely the same
                    light as the US. A similar problem existed with regard to <gloss
                        target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>, where the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss> powers desired to undertake measures enhancing their security
                    against the communists, but they also desired to gain support for their
                    positions in disputes with other Free World countries. For example, Pakistan had
                    in mind that <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> membership might be
                    extremely beneficial in its dispute with India. From the US viewpoint the
                    purpose of engaging in such pacts was to prevent aggression from the Soviet
                    Union or Communist <pb facs="0493" n="465" xml:id="pg_465"/> China. When we
                    adhered to the <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss> Pact, we felt compelled
                    to make clear this reservation. Part of Iraq’s disillusionment regarding the
                    Baghdad Pact probably derives from its desire for our support in their quarrel
                    with Saudi Arabia and Egypt. A considerable amount of the opposition among the
                    Arab states and India to the Baghdad Pact and <gloss target="#t_SEATO1"
                        >SEATO</gloss> results from their concern that the pacts were designed, in
                    part at least, to support countries in disputes with them.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> said that several of
                    the Pact countries had assumed the attitude that, having joined, they were being
                    subjected to heavy criticism by the Soviets and others who opposed their
                    membership. They therefore were asking themselves whether what they had obtained
                    from membership outweighed this criticism and pressure. They have been impressed
                    with the argument, often used, that non-Pact countries receive almost as much
                    from the US as the members. The British Government had been particularly
                    troubled by this attitude and had therefore instructed the Ambassador to convey
                    to the Secretary certain specific proposals regarding measures which might be
                    taken or announced at the Baghdad Pact Council meeting which would provide
                    substantial encouragement to the other members. These would be included in the
                    memorandum which he previously said would be sent to the Department later in the
                    day.</p>
                <p>The Secretary said he had received some indications that new orders for arms had
                    been placed by Egypt in Czechoslovakia. Considering the limited absorptive
                    capacity of Egypt, and the fact that orders obviously far exceed Egyptian
                    requirements, he wondered to what use the arms would be put. He assumed that
                    many would be passed on to other countries, such as Yemen. Receipt of additional
                    quantities also rendered it possible for Egypt to declare as surplus their own
                    Western arms which might be delivered to Saudi Arabia, the latter having
                    indicated reluctance to obtain weapons from communist countries.</p>
                <p>The Secretary noted that the communication handed to him by Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> expressed doubt as to the wisdom of
                    building up King <persName corresp="#p_SAA1">Saud</persName>, suggesting that we
                    should instead aim at a “front to protect Islam against communism.” The view was
                    expressed that in order to get King <persName corresp="#p_SAA1">Saud</persName>
                    to assume greater leadership in anti-communist policies it would appear
                    imperative to play him up as a spiritual leader of Islam and, as such, encourage
                    him to take the lead in making clear to the Arab world the dangers to Islam of
                    communist penetration. It would seem that if we were to succeed in breaking King
                        <persName corresp="#p_SAA1">Saud</persName> away from <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>, something along the lines of
                    developing his prestige in the Arab world would have to be done. The Secretary
                    thought that the word “front” appearing in the British paper connoted some sort
                    of alliance, presumably between Saudi <pb facs="0494" n="466" xml:id="pg_466"/>
                    Arabia, Iraq and possibly other Arab states. Since this is not now a practical
                    possibility, perhaps the term “movement” would be more appropriate. The
                    Ambassador agreed with the latter observation.</p>
                <p>The Secretary commented that current developments in Libya seemed to be quite
                    favorable. Aside from noting that we would be glad to endorse in the
                    Ambassadorial Committee the suggestion in the British paper regarding arms to
                    Israel, the Secretary said he had no further comments to make at this time on
                    the communication.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> said that an additional
                    point which he wished to raise concerned military planning. He thought that we
                    should of course move ahead with economic and political measures designed to
                    accomplish our objectives in the area, but that at the same time military
                    planning should be completed and held in reserve. He thought it unfortunate,
                    although necessary, that the US must take the public position that military
                    forces could not be employed in the area without Congressional approval,<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d242fn6">See <ref target="#d240fn6">footnote 6, Document
                            240</ref>.</note> since this gave disruptive elements considerable
                    comfort. He realized, however, that little could be done about it in the
                    circumstances.</p>
                <p>Referring to the imminent departure to the Near East of the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Secretary General,<note n="7" xml:id="d242fn7"
                        >U.N. Secretary-General <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjold</persName>
                        left for the Near East on April 6.</note> Ambassador <persName
                        corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> said that he had hoped to try to
                    instill in Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjold</persName> more realism
                    before he undertook his task. It appeared, however, that he would avoid Western
                    capitals. In any event, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DSPJ1">Dixon</persName> would
                    see him in New York and would have a frank talk with him. The Secretary said he
                    would also ask Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LHCJ1">Lodge</persName> to meet
                    with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HD1">Hammarskjold</persName>. He observed that
                    both the British and the US had told <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> officials
                    that if they wanted more observers, helicopters, equipment, or other forms of
                    help, we would be glad to cooperate; it was surprising that no requests had been
                    made. It appeared that they may be far less concerned than we. Perhaps their
                    evaluation of the gravity of the situation was entirely different from our
                    own.</p>
                <p>The Secretary read to Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName> a
                    proposed press announcement in connection with American representation at the
                    forthcoming meeting of the Baghdad Pact Council.<note n="8" xml:id="d242fn8"
                        >Reference is to Department of State Press Release 180 of April 6. For text,
                        see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin,</hi> April 16, 1956, p.
                        637.</note> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MSRM1">Makins</persName>
                    thought the statement excellent and expressed pleasure that the US was sending
                    such high representatives to the meeting.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
