<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>254. Telegram From the Consulate General at Jerusalem to the to the
                    Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d254</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">254</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-04-07T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-04-07T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recYjpfk1LbuFNfdP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-04-07T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-04-07T05:00:00-05:00" n="254"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d254">
                <head>254. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Consulate General at
                        Jerusalem</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d254fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 674.84A/4–756. Limited Official Use; Priority. Received at 12:01 p.m.
                        Repeated priority to Amman, Beirut, Cairo, Damascus, London, Paris, and Tel
                        Aviv.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-04-07T12:00:00+02:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 7, 1956—noon</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>402. On evening April 6 <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">Burns</persName> gave me
                    comments along following lines expressing his opinions most recent Gaza
                    incidents (Con-Gen telegram 401<note n="2" xml:id="d254fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d247fn2">footnote 2, Document 247</ref>.</note> and previous).
                    The Egyptians were clearly in the wrong during earlier stages. <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMGELM1">Burns</persName> had warned them on various occasions
                    against promiscuous shooting across border, stating that such actions would
                    doubtless at some point evoke vigorous and, for them, troublesome Israeli
                    reaction. He had expressed this view at least five different times recently,
                    either to Gohar, <persName corresp="#p_AGAH1">Amer</persName>, or <persName
                        corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>. Arguments they had given him to
                    effect that Egyptian posts must be allowed fire their discretion owing fear of
                    attack by approaching Israeli patrols (whether or not actually across D/L) were
                    not valid since Egyptians had also continued firing at Israelis in fixed
                    positions, despite <persName corresp="#p_AGAH1">Amer</persName>’s assurance to
                        <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">Burns</persName> that he would have this
                    practice stopped. He considered Egyptians themselves responsible for initiating
                    latest spiral of incidents and reprisals.</p>
                <p>While Israelis initially had strong case against Egyptians they had later thrown
                    it away, …. <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">Burns</persName> did not believe
                    Israeli slaughter of civilians on this occasion was result any high-level policy
                    decision. He considered the Israelis had simply blundered into the situation
                    through their eagerness retaliate, presumably in accordance with standing
                    orders. Thus, original Egyptian firing at patrol and killing three soldiers had
                    evolved into series retaliations and counter-retaliations, included exchanges
                    fire against villages, which had culminated in unfortunate mortaring of Gaza
                    town. Owing to population concentrated in Gaza latter action was not at all
                    analogous to shelling of frontier Kibbutz in open country, for instance,
                    although Israeli military personnel may not have borne such fine distinctions
                    very clearly in mind at the time. With regard hit on Baptist Hospital, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BMGELM1">Burns</persName> said it was not clear that hospital
                    itself was directly involved. He understood it was possibly annex to hospital in
                    some other building which was hit. Although there was some small arms fire this
                    morning situation believed generally quiet. Civil population Gaza reported under
                    control. Curfew lifted this morning until 1600 hours local time today.</p>
                <pb facs="0520" n="492" xml:id="pg_492"/>
                <p>If things remain quiet <persName corresp="#p_BMGELM1">Burns</persName> expects
                    proceed Rome April 8.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Cole</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
