<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>313. Telegram From the Embassy in Egypt to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d313</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">313</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-04-29T07:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-04-29T07:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec23ea53997c6eb17" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Baghdad Pact</term>
                    <term ref="rec75960867e175c12" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="arab-israeli-dispute">Arab-Israeli conflict</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-04-29T07:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-04-29T07:00:00-05:00" n="313"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d313">
                <head>313. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Egypt</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d313fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 684A.86/4–1956. Top Secret; Priority; Limited Distribution; Omega
                        Handling. Received at 2:36 p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Cairo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-04-29T14:00:00+02:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 29, 1956—2 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2165. Reference Department telegram 2598.<note n="2" xml:id="d313fn2">
                        <ref target="#d310">Document 310</ref>.</note> As this exchange messages has
                    revealed, I tend be more hopeful than Department that by continuing lines
                    followed since last October we should be able obtain at least minimum required
                    support from growing events of Arab world (<persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1"
                        >Nasser</persName>) for free world objectives ….</p>
                <p>Feeling, therefore, that we are again heading into period of tension, believe my
                    most useful contribution can now be to make every effort assure that <gloss
                        target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> fully understands our viewpoint, hoping that in
                    process Washington will obtain clearer understanding theirs.</p>
                <p>To do this, propose, if <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> takes
                    initiative of type envisaged by Department (and there is greater possibility
                    that he will not), to follow fairly closely presentation set forth points 1
                    through 5 referenced Department telegram, prefacing my remarks with general
                    statement US historic policy on colonialism and post-war activities in defense
                    of freedom and independence. Would plan to emphasize particularly stoppage of
                    attack against Baghdad Pact. Would like de-emphasize point 2 (d) as Egypt’s
                    present representative <persName corresp="#p_FM1">Fawzi</persName> far more
                    capable handling <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> matters than member of <gloss
                        target="#t_RCC1">RCC</gloss> and <pb facs="0615" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/>
                    shouldn’t think it appropriate to push this too far. Would like also to limit
                    2(e) to less specific suggestion, namely that he do something positive advance
                    objectives of Jordan Valley plan. Believe visit by <persName corresp="#p_JE1"
                        >Johnston</persName> should not be pressed as it appears other Embassies in
                    area agree with us that high US citizen in area publicly endeavoring secure
                    approval the project now counter-productive.</p>
                <p>In any discussion <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> now, I will be
                    vulnerable on subject high dam and Senator <persName corresp="#p_GWF1"
                        >George</persName>’s statement<note n="3" xml:id="d313fn3">On April 27,
                        Senator <persName corresp="#p_GWF1">Walter F. George</persName>, Chairman of
                        the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, declared his opposition to the U.S.
                        offer of long-term assistance for the construction of the Aswan Dam.</note>
                    may be on his mind. He might ask if we dragging our feet because of failure
                        <persName corresp="#p_AD1">Anderson</persName> mission and in order apply
                    pressure on <gloss target="#t_GOE1">GOE</gloss> for “political advantage”.</p>
                <p>If he takes this tack, I would point out we responded very quickly last November,
                    leaving him draw own conclusions re our present policy and reason therefor. We
                    must anticipate that … <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>’s
                    conclusions in this matter will have strong bearing future Egyptian-US
                    relations.</p>
                <p>If it now appears we will endeavor have <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> mediate
                    broader issues of Arab-Israeli conflict, would it not be advantageous defer
                    implementation … policy for a bit … in order avoid in short run risks we
                    foresee? <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>’s position in such an
                    effort would probably set tone for other Arab States just as it has on current
                    mission of Secretary General. <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>’s
                    intelligence, which extends inside every political party in area, will tell him
                    immediately of facts which seem against him, and I should think we would not
                    wish this state of affairs if <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> effort to be
                    made.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BHA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Byroade</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
