<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>64. Message From Robert B. Anderson to the to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v15</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d64</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">64</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="recsxQ6o7GtJ2WzZv" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="antisemitism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000750"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Jewish</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-02-01T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-02-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="64"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d64">
                <head>64. Message From <persName corresp="#p_ARB1" type="from">Robert B.
                        Anderson</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d64fn1">Source: Department of State, <gloss
                            target="#t_NEA1">NEA</gloss> Files: Lot 59 D 518; Alpha—<persName
                            corresp="#p_AD1">Anderson</persName> Talks w/<gloss target="#t_BG1"
                            >BG</gloss> &amp; <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>.
                        Incoming Telegrams—Jan.–March 1956. Part I. Top Secret. The source text
                        bears a notation that <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName> saw this
                        message.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 66</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Jerusalem</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-02-01">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 1, 1956</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Returned to Israel night of January 30. Was fearful that further delay
                        would increase Israel doubts concerning mission.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>… I met with <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName>, Kollek and <persName
                            corresp="#p_HCC1">Herzog</persName> for 4 hours afternoon of January
                            31.<note n="2" xml:id="d64fn2">The memorandum of this conversation is
                            not printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> Meetings with Israeli
                            Officials. January 1956–March 1956)</note> They were exceedingly anxious
                        to hear the results of my second conversations with <persName
                            corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d64fn3">See
                                <ref target="#d45">Documents 45</ref> and <ref target="#d46"
                                >46</ref>.</note> I reported: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> reaffirmed absence
                                of hostile intent;</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>the resolution to avoid border incidents;</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>a willingness to still consider some form direct negotiations but
                                that he felt former channel had resulted in his being misled and was
                                concerned with the <persName>Abdullah</persName> incident.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>I went over check list of items which had been discussed with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>, pointing out
                                that these represented substantially areas of agreement either in
                                detail or principle.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>that <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> had
                                indicated privately and to me that he was optimistic concerning
                                possible results of this operation.</item>
                            <label>f.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName> asked if progress had
                                been made on the real problems of refugees and boundaries. I
                                reviewed statements on both sides re refugees and said both sides
                                had evidenced flexibility and expressed hope; that we had discussed
                                possible areas of resettlement of refugees in Arab States after
                                determination of number to be repatriated by some formula. On the
                                boundary question I said I could only reiterate that both sides must
                                remain flexible although I understood clearly that to <persName
                                    corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName> the application of the
                                term meant giving up of territory.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName> then made the
                            following points: This mission offers great hope and great danger. The
                            hope lies in its succeeding. <persName corresp="#p_BGD1"
                                >Ben-Gurion</persName> tries earnestly to believe <persName
                                corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> is sincere but even with this
                            belief fears <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> may face
                            pressures from his army and other Arab leaders which will result in his
                            resorting to war in view of the flow of armaments to Egypt. <persName
                                corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName> insists that shooting on the
                            border must cease if he is really to believe in <persName
                                corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>’s sincerity. Says shooting
                            has occurred each day since I came but by miracle no one killed.
                                <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName> states his great
                            objectives are: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item>Security of his people;</item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item>the establishment and continuation of Israel;</item>
                                <label>c.</label>
                                <item>the making of an Arab-Jewish alliance.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <pb facs="0151" n="123" xml:id="pg_123"/>
                        <p>Because of the great hope which this mission holds for the achievement of
                            these objectives, he is willing to be patient, understands the necessity
                            of <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> securing
                            acceptability by his people and other Arab leaders, and states that he
                            is willing to negotiate or be patient for months or years if it is
                            possible for him to remain patient. He points out that he is misleading
                            his colleagues by not informing them of this mission thereby increasing
                            the responsibility of those who know. That there are limits beyond which
                            he cannot go, and if his colleagues cease to believe in Israel’s
                            security, it may not be possible for him to be as patient or take the
                            time necessary to achieve a settlement. He asserts that we urge him to
                            be reasonable but he can be reasonable only if the anxiety of war is
                            removed. He understands the problem <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1"
                                >Nasser</persName> faces of not immediately reopening channel of
                            communication. He wants me to give reassurance to <persName
                                corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> that security will be
                            maintained and that misunderstanding will be avoided. He feels that
                            direct communication is a necessary step to what he regards as finally
                            indispensable and that is meeting with <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1"
                                >Nasser</persName>. He stated that he was willing to concede “things
                            that <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> never dreamed of”
                            but only if he could discuss matters with him personally. In reply to my
                            question, he stated that he would never spell out the price he was
                            willing to pay for peace to any third person. He said, “If only we could
                            meet, I know there would be peace in ten days.” He stated that he wanted
                            me to clearly understand that if the anxiety of war continued, it might
                            at some point become impossible for him to continue to be patient and
                            seek peace and that this anxiety had to be measured in weeks or at best
                            a month or two.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>I replied that I understood the weight of his responsibilities and wanted
                        him to know our country was concerned with the long-term best interest of
                        Israel as a state surrounded as it is by Arab States, and he must surely
                        realize that this was more desirable than any short-term point of view. That
                        a precipitous course of action might allay anxieties temporarily but could
                        only lead to greater long-term dangers of survival. He said this was so but
                        there were limits to his holding this line.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>It seems evident that <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName>
                        regards this operation as a great personal undertaking. He feels himself on
                        the horns of a dilemma. He says, “Every child in Israel is my child. I am
                        responsible to them and history. I want so earnestly to believe in <persName
                            corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>’s sincerity, but I look in vain
                        for signs. If only the shooting at the border would cease, I could then
                        believe.”</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName> asked if I had heard the
                        broadcast from Syria stating that if work was resumed on the Banat Yacov Dam
                        that Syria, Saudi Arabia and Egypt would resort to force. I told him I had
                        not heard the broadcast, but I hoped Israel would not find it necessary to
                        do <pb facs="0152" n="124" xml:id="pg_124"/> anything which could be
                        regarded as justification for use of force during the period of our effort.
                            <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName> said he would make no
                        commitment about what his intentions were regarding Banat Yacov but again
                        stated, “You are asking me to be reasonable and I can only be reasonable if
                        my people feel secure. If they do not feel secure, then unreasonable things
                        become the reasonable.”</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName> inquired as to whether
                            <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> had discussed the
                        Jordan Valley Plan. I replied as reported in my previous telegram to
                            you.<note n="4" xml:id="d64fn4">
                            <ref target="#d46">Document 46</ref>.</note>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BGD1">Ben-Gurion</persName> seemed pleased at
                            <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName>’s attitude and stated
                        that he realized the difficulty was enhanced by the instability of the
                        Syrian Government.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>During general conversations which followed, the following points of view
                        were put forth: <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>Israel will accept any form of supervision of the Holy Places
                                suggested by Jordan.</item>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>They subscribe to the principle of border adjustments linking
                                villages to farms and making other minor corrections.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>They envision free trade without duty between adjacent Arab
                                countries and want to work towards its development although they
                                realize that prejudices now exist.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>They look forward to unrestricted transit of planes, trains and
                                other forms of communication across Israel and between Arab
                                States.</item>
                            <label>e.</label>
                            <item>They regard with favor the Secretary’s statement of the guarantee
                                of boundaries in August, but want to make clear that their people
                                would not accept the guarantee of any power exclusively and they
                                would always require sufficient weapons for what they regard as
                                legitimate self-defense. They emphasize that theirs is a
                                civilization of “in-gathering” and that the principal ingredient is
                                the morale of their people.</item>
                        </list>
                    </item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>They maintain hope for the success of this operation if we keep it moving.
                        I explained that I might now return either to Cairo or U.S., and was
                        remaining flexible which they accepted as proper.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Sharett</persName> was deeply concerned that the
                        British Ambassador to Cairo held a two and one-half hour conference with
                            <persName corresp="#p_NNNCGA1">Nasser</persName> subsequent to my
                        departure. He fears the influence of Britain and the doctrine of the
                        Guildhall speech.<note n="5" xml:id="d64fn5">Reference is to Prime Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_ERHSA1">Eden</persName>’s speech of November
                            9, 1955.</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Was prevented returning to Athens late last night due to inclement
                        weather. Now plan to return and meet <persName corresp="#p_RFH1"
                            >Russell</persName> late tonight.</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>Have been very worried about effect of reported <persName
                            corresp="#p_BER1">Black</persName> conversations …. Am pleased to
                        receive <persName corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName>’s message to <persName
                            corresp="#p_BER1">Black</persName>.<note n="6" xml:id="d64fn6">See <ref
                                target="#d60">Document 60</ref>.</note> Will discuss matter with
                            <persName corresp="#p_BER1">Black</persName> if opportunity
                        arises.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
