<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>236. Transcript of Telephone Conversation Between the President’s Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (Kissinger) and Deputy Secretary of State ) and
                    Deputy Secretary of State Rush, Washington, April 9, 1973, 5:58 p.m.,
                    Washington, April 9, 1973, 5:58 p.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve12</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d236</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">236</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-04-09T17:58:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-04-09T17:58:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-04-09T17:58:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-04-09T17:58:00-05:00" n="236"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d236">
                <head>236. Transcript of Telephone Conversation Between the President’s Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_kissinger-henry-a"
                        >Kissinger</persName>) and Deputy Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_rush-kenneth">Rush</persName>, Washington, April 9, 1973, 5:58
                        p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d236fn1">Source: National Archives,
                            <persName corresp="#p_nixon-richard-m">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, Henry <persName corresp="#p_kissinger-henry-a"
                            >Kissinger</persName> Telephone Conversation Transcripts, Box 19–2
                        [March–April 1973]. No classification marking. <persName
                            corresp="#p_kissinger-henry-a">Kissinger</persName> was in Washington. A
                        transcript of <persName corresp="#p_kissinger-henry-a"
                        >Kissinger</persName>’s and <persName corresp="#p_rush-kenneth"
                            >Rush</persName>’s earlier conversation about <gloss target="#t_uncurk"
                            >UNCURK</gloss>, April 7, is ibid.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d236fn2">
                        <persName corresp="#p_kissinger-henry-a">Kissinger</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_rush-kenneth">Rush</persName> discussed whether <gloss
                            target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> should be abolished.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-04-09T17:58:00-05:00">April 9, 1973, 5:58 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>TELCON<lb/>Secretary <persName corresp="#p_rush-kenneth">Rush</persName>/Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_kissinger-henry-a">Kissinger</persName>
                    <lb/> 5:58 p.m., April 9, 1973</p>
                <p>K: Hello.</p>
                <p>R: Hello, Henry.</p>
                <p>K: Yes.</p>
                <p>R: I’ve gone into this <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> thing in
                    considerable depth. The thing is undoubtedly an anachronism and we would
                    certainly like to avoid a <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> debate.</p>
                <p>K: Right.</p>
                <p>R: The problems that we have in doing away with it are one, the South Koreans. We
                    would have to work up a scenario where they would take — where it was to their
                    benefit to do away with <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> and then you
                    have to work up a scenario on how to do away with it and keep away from a <gloss
                        target="#t_un">UN</gloss> debate which we all want to keep away from. Now as
                    you know this thing out of the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> debate involves
                    not only the Chinese but the Russians. And of course also North Korea has had
                    the Algerians present their resolution and we have to keep them out of it
                    too.</p>
                <p>K: Oh, no, we have to have an understanding with North Korea that it won’t be
                    pursued.</p>
                <p>R: Exactly. Now the easiest way to do it would be to have, and maybe this would
                    not satisfy the Chinese, but if <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> just
                    passed a resolution dissolving themselves never to meet again, that would be</p>
                <p>K: [Omission in the original] themselves or dissolving themselves?</p>
                <p>R: They would disband or they would adjourn sine die — not to mean again and then
                    all the individual countries in <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> would
                    pull out. This would effectively do away with it but I suppose</p>
                <p>K: No, that’s not good enough for them.</p>
                <p>R: The Chinese would want to have the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> formally
                    dissolved. Now if the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss>’s formally dissolved,
                    then how do you avoid a debate? This is a problem.</p>
                <p>K: Well, unless <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> dissolves itself.</p>
                <p>R: They can’t legally do that anymore; they could disband themselves or do away
                    with themselves and let it go at that. And if no one says anything about it that
                    would be it. Just disband and individual countries could just withdraw.</p>
                <pb facs="d236-2" n="2" xml:id="d236-2"/>
                <p>K: Yeh.</p>
                <p>R: We have to work up what would be acceptable from that standpoint. What I can
                    do over here is have our people, have our own ideas, to see how can we legally
                    disband them without anything going before the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss>
                    and work up a scenario from that standpoint, not bringing in of course anything
                    about the Chinese or dealing with the Chinese because if the South Koreans think
                    we are doing this to get something on the outside or having agreed to the
                    Chinese behind their back so to speak, we’ll run into the same sort of
                    thing.</p>
                <p>K: Now can we tell the Chinese that when we said adjourn sine die that this is
                    all that <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> can do and that then the
                    countries — we would cooperate with the countries concerned in pulling out.</p>
                <p>R: We can do that. If they adjourn sine die and we cooperate with the countries
                    to pull out, they might not even disband sine die. But this, Henry, is what we
                    could try to do. I would have to really study the legalities of that more to be
                    sure that it would stand up, but we could tell the Chinese that that, we think,
                    is the best way of doing it. If it stands up legally and frankly I think they
                    should accept it and we could go ahead on that basis. Now we’d also have to
                    evidence (?) then with the Russians and with the North Koreans.</p>
                <p>K: We’ll let the Chinese deliver the North Koreans and then we’ll worry about the
                    Russians.</p>
                <p>R: Well, we could do that, but the Russians could still, as you know, cause
                    trouble and you’d have your <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> debate.</p>
                <p>K: Yeh.</p>
                <p>R: In addition to <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss>, as you know, we also
                    have the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> command there and the South Koreans I
                    understand, would be very upset if the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> Command
                    were liquidated.</p>
                <p>K: That I understand.</p>
                <p>R: And the feeling is that the only way you get the South Koreans to go along
                    with this would be to give them our assurances that we would certainly try to
                    see that the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> Command was not dissolved and that
                    there would not be an unraveling of the entire <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss>
                    picture in South Korea.</p>
                <p>K: Well the fact is that last year I was told by <persName
                        corresp="#p_johnson-u-alexis">Alex Johnson</persName> that I could tell them
                    that <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> would be abolished if they avoided
                    the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> debate.</p>
                <p>R: I think we can do that.</p>
                <pb facs="d236-3" n="3" xml:id="d236-3"/>
                <p>K: Now if you can give me something I can tell them — that accomplishes that — I
                    can say that I’ve met my commitment to them.</p>
                <p>R: Right.</p>
                <p>K: Do you see what I mean?</p>
                <p>R: Yes, well why don’t I get at the paper for you?</p>
                <p>K: Good.</p>
                <p>R: In essence it would be just what we say, but I’ll get at the paper saying that
                    we would adjourn sine die and that this is what it would be.</p>
                <p>K: But that they won’t accept.</p>
                <p>R: Then they would have to — we could vote to disband and withdraw — and the
                    members withdraw. Whether we can get that — well the members themselves I think
                    would do it.</p>
                <p>K: We could say that all <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> can do is
                    adjourn sine die and that then if they want a <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss>
                    resolution abandoning it — abolishing it we won’t oppose it.</p>
                <p>R: We would certainly say that.</p>
                <p>K: OK, that might be a way of doing it.</p>
                <p>R: If we can avoid a debate on that; we want to avoid a debate of course. But if
                    we can have a resolution of the <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss> abolishing it
                    that would be fine. If we can avoid a debate and do that.</p>
                <p>K: Right. Can you look at it again and let me know tomorrow.</p>
                <p>R: Yes, Henry, that really is the answer. Now we are willing, if the Koreans will
                    go along, and we’d sell this to the Koreans, we would approach the Koreans and
                    tell them that we think <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> has served its
                    purpose and tell the Koreans that we do not intend to touch the <gloss
                        target="#t_un">UN</gloss> Command; that we want to avoid a debate in the
                        <gloss target="#t_un">UN</gloss>; that we think a way that could accomplish
                    this would be for <gloss target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> to adjourn sine die
                    and then it might be that there would be a resolution in the <gloss
                        target="#t_un">UN</gloss> agreed to by everyone abolishing <gloss
                        target="#t_uncurk">UNCURK</gloss> with no debate. And this is what we would
                    try to do.</p>
                <p>K: OK.</p>
                <pb facs="d236-4" n="4" xml:id="d236-4"/>
                <p>R: That would be our approach.</p>
                <p>K: Good. Excellent.</p>
                <p>R: OK, Henry.</p>
                <p>K: Thank you.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
