<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-03-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-03-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="316" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d316">
                        <head>316. Memorandum From the Acting Assistant Secretary of Defense for
                            International Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_eagleburger-lawrence-s">Eagleburger</persName>) to
                            Secretary of Defense <persName corresp="#p_richardson-elliot-l">Richardson</persName>, Washington, March 15, 1973.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d316fn1">Source: Washington National Records
                                Center, <gloss target="#t_osd">OSD</gloss> Files: <gloss target="#t_frc">FRC</gloss> 330–78–0001, Philippines, 091.3, 15
                                March 1973. Confidential; <gloss target="#t_noforn">Noforn</gloss>.
                                The bottom of the memorandum is stamped, “Sec has seen. 17 Mar
                                1973.”</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d316fn2">
                                <persName corresp="#p_eagleburger-lawrence-s">Eagleburger</persName>
                                described the Muslim insurgency in the Philippines.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline>
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" when="1973-03-15">March 15, 1973</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ASSISTANT SECRETARY OF DEFENSE<lb/>WASHINGTON, D.C. 20301</p>
                        <p>15 MAR 1973</p>
                        <p>In reply refer to: 1-34141/73</p>
                        <p>MEMORANDUM FOR THE SECRETARY OF DEFENSE<lb/>SUBJECT: The Philippines and
                            Muslim Conflict (<gloss target="#t_u">U</gloss>)</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_u">U</gloss>) This memorandum summarizes the subject
                            situation for your information.</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_c">C</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_nf">NF</gloss>)
                            Ambassador Byroade and Admiral Gayler have reflected President <persName corresp="#p_marcos-ferdinand">Marcos</persName>’ fears of the
                            renewed threat to <gloss target="#t_gop">GOP</gloss> stability caused by
                            Muslim activities in Mindanao and surrounding areas. Both the Ambassador
                            and <gloss target="#t_cincpac">CINCPAC</gloss> have requested increased
                            military assistance. <gloss target="#t_dod">DOD</gloss> and State have
                            provided token assistance (expedited deliveries of selected equipment)
                            and are studying the ramifications of increased U.S. involvement related
                            to the internal situation.</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_c">C</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_nf">NF</gloss>) The
                            problem is one of religion and Muslim fanaticism. For four hundred years
                            the Muslims in the Sulu area have successfully resisted non-Muslim
                            influence. The normally hostile situation has been aggravated by
                                <persName corresp="#p_marcos-ferdinand">Marcos</persName>’ attempts
                            to restore a climate of law and order (collection of weapons) and the
                            simmering feud between the Governments of Malaysia and the Philippines
                            over sovereignty of Sabah (formerly North Borneo). The active Muslim
                            insurgents are estimated to number sixteen to seventeen thousand
                            distributed among Cotabato, Sulu, Two Zamboangas, Two Landaos, and South
                            Cotabato. Some 6,000 to 7,000 of the rebels are armed with variety of
                            rifles, machine guns, mortars, rockets and land mines. The <gloss target="#t_gop">GOP</gloss> reports Muslim munitions sources as
                            Malaysia, Pakistan and Libya.</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_c">C</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_nf">NF</gloss>)
                            Immediate and positive reaction by the U.S. in providing marked
                            increased <gloss target="#t_map">MAP</gloss> support to the <gloss target="#t_gop">GOP</gloss> is not considered warranted at this time
                            as:</p>
                        <p>- The Muslim threat cannot be considered as an immediate and real danger
                            to U.S. interests, at least at this time.</p>
                        <pb facs="d316-2" n="2" xml:id="d316-2"/>
                        <p>- Repercussions, both national and worldwide, would follow any large
                            scale U.S. assistance in suppression of a religious minority within a
                            dictatorially governed nation.</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_c">C</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_nf">NF</gloss>)
                            However, continuation of our Military Assistance Program with
                            adjustments to reflect the new <gloss target="#t_gop">GOP</gloss>
                            requirements within programmed dollar levels should be handled as a
                            routine manner without publicity.</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_c">C</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_nf">NF</gloss>) <gloss target="#t_cincpac">CINCPAC</gloss> has, with Embassy concurrence,
                            initially requested expeditious delivery of two programmed UH-1H
                            helicopters and reprogramming of the Philippine <gloss target="#t_map">MAP</gloss> program to enable delivery of five additional UH-1H’s
                            and associated gun systems. <gloss target="#t_dod">DOD</gloss> has
                            responded by air shipping the two programmed UH-1H helicopters, air
                            shipping 1140 programmed <gloss target="#t_m16">M-16</gloss> rifles, and
                            making available four excess C-47’s as replacement aircraft or source of
                            needed spare parts.</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_c">C</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_nf">NF</gloss>) The
                            provision of the five additional UH-1Hs and other <gloss target="#t_cincpac">CINCPAC</gloss> approved program changes will be
                            reviewed by State and within <gloss target="#t_dod">DOD</gloss>, and any
                            reprogramming or expediting deliveries will be kept on a “business as
                            usual” level, while maintaining a posture of non-interference in
                            internal <gloss target="#t_gop">GOP</gloss> affairs.</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_c">C</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_nf">NF</gloss>) In
                            addition to the above actions, we have received an extensive shopping
                            list presented to our Embassy by the <gloss target="#t_gop">GOP</gloss>.
                            Presumably, this list represents a <gloss target="#t_gop">GOP</gloss>
                            request for grant aid (<gloss target="#t_map">MAP</gloss>) in addition
                            to that now programmed as planned through <gloss target="#t_fy">FY</gloss> 73. We are analyzing the list and are awaiting <gloss target="#t_cincpac">CINCPAC</gloss> comments on it.</p>
                        <p>(<gloss target="#t_c">C</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_nf">NF</gloss>) Given
                            the current state of <gloss target="#t_fy">FY</gloss> 73 <gloss target="#t_map">MAP</gloss> funds, it will be extremely difficult
                            for us to do more than already programmed (although adjustments within
                            the program are possible). Nor am I certain that it would be advisable
                            for us to do more. In any event, we will be back to you after we have
                            examined the new <gloss target="#t_gop">GOP</gloss> requests.</p>
                        <p>[signed] <lb/>
                            <persName corresp="#p_eagleburger-lawrence-s">Laurence
                                Eagleburger</persName>
                            <lb/> Acting Assistant Secretary</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>