<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-01-26T17:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1976-01-26T16:43:00-05:00" n="85" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d85">
                        <head>85. Memorandum of Conversation, Washington, January 26, 1976,
                            4:43–5:30 p.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d85fn1">Source:
                                    <persName corresp="#p_ford-gerald-r">Ford</persName> Library,
                                National Security Adviser, Memoranda of Conversations, Box 17,
                                Chronological File. Secret; <gloss target="#t_nodis">Nodis</gloss>.
                                The meeting was held in the Oval Office. Brackets are in the
                                original. Article 21 of the January 1973 Paris Agreement involved
                                postwar reconstruction.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d85fn2">Members of the House Select
                                Committee on MIAs reported to President <persName corresp="#p_ford-gerald-r">Ford</persName> on their trip to
                                North Vietnam.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline>
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian" from="1976-01-26T16:43:00-05:00" to="1976-01-26T17:30:00-05:00" type="conversation-or-meeting-date">January 26, 1976, 4:43–5:30
                                    p.m.</date>
                            </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>MEMORANDUM<lb/>THE WHITE HOUSE<lb/>WASHINGTON<lb/>MEMORANDUM OF
                            CONVERSATION</p>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS:</head>
                            <item>President <persName corresp="#p_ford-gerald-r">Ford</persName>
                            </item>
                            <item>House Select Committee on <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss>’s</item>
                            <item>Cong. <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">G.V. (Sonny)
                                    Montgomery</persName> (D.-Miss.), Chairman</item>
                            <item>Cong. <persName corresp="#p_mccloskey-paul-n">Paul N. McCloskey,
                                    Jr.</persName> (R.-Calif.)</item>
                            <item>Cong. <persName corresp="#p_ottinger-richard-l">Richard L.
                                    Ottinger</persName> (D.-NY)</item>
                            <item>Cong. <persName corresp="#p_gilman-benjamin">Benjamin
                                    Gilman</persName> (R.-NY)</item>
                            <item>Angus MacDonald, Staff Director</item>
                            <item>Brent <persName corresp="#p_scowcroft-brent">Scowcroft</persName>,
                                Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_friedersdorf-max">Max Friedersdorf</persName>,
                                Assistant to the President for Legislative Affairs</item>
                            <item>Bob Wolthius, Deputy Assistant to the President for Legislative
                                Affairs</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>DATE AND TIME: Monday, January 26, 1976 4:43 - 5:30 p.m.<lb/>PLACE: The
                            Oval Office</p>
                        <p>[Small talk]</p>
                        <p>The President: Tell me about your trip.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>: It
                            was a very good trip. The attitude of the leadership was very different
                            from the early days when <persName corresp="#p_kissinger-henry-a">Kissinger</persName> used to deal with them. We were told we
                            couldn’t have US military and flags for recognizing the remains, but we
                            did it our way. We had a fine ceremony at the airport, with North
                            Vietnamese looking on. We didn’t see any bomb damage — we didn’t want
                            to. Only the bridge. It’s an old town. The only new building is the
                            Cuban hotel. We saw the Hanoi Hilton. They stressed there were no
                            Americans alive.</p>
                        <p>They discussed Article 21 of the Agreement. We met with <persName corresp="#p_pham-van-dong">Pham Van Dong</persName>. He was cordial
                            and he raised Article 21. We told him <pb facs="d85-2" n="2" xml:id="d85-2"/> of your letter and of your Asian speech [Honolulu
                            speech, December 7] about mutual gestures of good will. And we got a
                            shopping list of wants from him. It is really the JEC list.</p>
                        <p>The Committee still hasn’t taken any policy steps but we feel the ball is
                            back in our court. They have lived up to everything they have told us.
                            They let the nine go; they gave us the three bodies; we could have the
                            two marines if Kennedy would get on the ball.</p>
                        <p>The gestures should best come from you. We told them there was no way to
                            get economic or reconstruction aid. [Mentioned things which could be
                            done.]</p>
                        <p>Dong said he wanted to come to the United States and wanted more
                            Americans to come to Vietnam.</p>
                        <p>The President: Do they let Americans come freely?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>: No,
                            not now.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_gilman-benjamin">Gilman</persName>: I seriously
                            think they want better relations with us. I mentioned the oil
                            drilling.</p>
                        <p>The President: How many <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss>’s do you think
                            are left in Vietnam?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>:
                            Probably about a total of 2500-odd <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss>’s
                            but I think not more than 250 bodies could be recovered. There are many
                            problems involved — the impact, animals, vegetation, etc.</p>
                        <p>The President: Have you had any contact with the League of Families?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_mccloskey-paul-n">McCloskey</persName>: Here is a
                            resolution of the League. We meet with them Saturday.</p>
                        <p>Two other things: You would get along well with <persName corresp="#p_pham-van-dong">Pham Van Dong</persName>. He is a
                            gracious man. We thought your Hawaii speech was an affirmative speech,
                            but they said you came over and doubled the aid to Indonesia and the
                            Philippine s.</p>
                        <p>I don’t know when you would invite Dong here but you would get along with
                            him as well as you did with <persName corresp="#p_deng-xiaoping">Teng
                                Hsiao-ping</persName>.</p>
                        <pb facs="d85-3" n="3" xml:id="d85-3"/>
                        <p>We want to wrap up by September. State has a two-to-four year time frame
                            so we are in conflict with them. I urge you to hasten on the reciprocal
                            gestures. State thinks lifting the trade ban is too big a gesture,
                            but…</p>
                        <p>The President: Would they let us look for <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss>’s?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ottinger-richard-l">Ottinger</persName>: They said
                            if we would drop our hostility, they could cooperate on <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss>’s. There are two alternatives: deal on a
                            step-by-step basis or sit down with State and negotiate the whole thing
                            out. I think that is the way to go to give them some independence.</p>
                        <p>The President: Do they acknowledge they have closer ties with the Soviet
                            Union?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>: They
                            never mentioned the situation and we never saw a Soviet or a
                            Chinese.</p>
                        <p>The President: How about Laos?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>:
                            There was a mixup there. They thought at first we were coming in there
                            to spy. They told us there were no Americans alive. They had no
                            information on where they crashed. The government is pretty loosely
                            managed.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_mccloskey-paul-n">McCloskey</persName>: They badly
                            need medicine, etc.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ottinger-richard-l">Ottinger</persName>: They
                            admitted they were desperate.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_mccloskey-paul-n">McCloskey</persName>: The Lao
                            and the Thai are right across the river from each other. The question is
                            whether they will stimulate insurgency in Thailand.</p>
                        <p>The President: Is the Lao Government independent or pro-North Vietnam, or
                            pro-Chinese, or pro-Soviet?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>: I
                            think the North Vietnamese call the shots. There are some Soviets there
                            also. We did see some.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_mccloskey-paul-n">McCloskey</persName>: They are
                            not sure of their control as in North Vietnam.</p>
                        <pb facs="d85-4" n="4" xml:id="d85-4"/>
                        <p>The President: Are there <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss>’s in
                            Cambodia?</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>: Yes,
                            30. We couldn’t even make contact with them.</p>
                        <p>The President: We couldn’t either, during Mayaguez.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_gilman-benjamin">Gilman</persName>: The <gloss target="#t_jcrc">JCRC</gloss> have 23 North Vietnamese <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss>’s which we could use for exchange,</p>
                        <p>The President: I appreciate this information. Let us take a good look at
                            the situation and what can be done. I will talk to <persName corresp="#p_kissinger-henry-a">Kissinger</persName>.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ottinger-richard-l">Ottinger</persName>: He has
                            bitter memories. What we have to remember is it isn’t the same,</p>
                        <p>The President: The first thing is to get the remains back. The second is
                            to see if we can breach the relationship with the Soviet Union. The
                            Chinese are worried about that. We will look into it. In the meantime
                            there are more and more families changing status.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>: We
                            have an agreement with <gloss target="#t_dod">DOD</gloss> that there
                            will be no status changes unless requested until after our report in
                            September. The parents are the biggest problem. Some of them don’t ever
                            want a change. There is a tremendous financial difference.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_montgomery-gillespiev">Montgomery</persName>:
                            Maybe the <gloss target="#t_unhcr">UNHCR</gloss> could work with the new
                                <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss> agency in Hanoi on this <gloss target="#t_mia">MIA</gloss> data.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_mccloskey-paul-n">McCloskey</persName>: We are
                            getting some plastic surgeons to go over to help some children. They
                            give time each year to do things like this. They have done this work on
                            a doctor-to-doctor basis, not only in the US but in Latin America and
                            other areas.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_gilman-benjamin">Gilman</persName>: They went out
                            of their way to make a clear gesture of these three bodies. I think
                            through some gesture on your part we can keep the ball rolling.</p>
                        <p>The President: What would you suggest?</p>
                        <pb facs="d85-5" n="5" xml:id="d85-5"/>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_gilman-benjamin">Gilman</persName>: I think the
                            aid is best.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_mccloskey-paul-n">McCloskey</persName>: I, of
                            course, tend toward trade, but they really lack hotel facilities. There
                            are people here who would like to go in there.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_ottinger-richard-l">Ottinger</persName>: I would
                            like to resolve it all at once rather than at a snail’s pace. Give
                            recognition, get a neutral agency to go in to look for sites — let the
                            American people know these are tied together.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>