<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v04p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">129</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recIfFl6ouaEmS16p" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85068131"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="recibBhfq1Nhuo5rk" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85127749"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Steel</term>
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="recd38b75873bd4a33" type="topic" category="international-organizations" subcategory="far-eastern-commission" subject="far-eastern-commission">Far Eastern Commission</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="129"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d129">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 129</seg>
                </opener>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">755.13/4–951</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Conversation, by the Secretary of State</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d129fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WRM1">R.M.
                            Winfree</persName> of <gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-09">April 9,
                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell rendition="#top">Participants:</cell>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">The Honorable <persName>Joseph
                            Pholien</persName>, Prime Minister of Belgium</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">
                            <persName>Baron Silvercruys</persName>, Ambassador of Belgium</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">The Secretary of State</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MRD1">Robert
                                Murphy</persName>, Ambassador to Belgium</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PGW1">George
                                Perkins</persName>, Assistant Secretary of State</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell rendition="#hanging">Mr. <persName corresp="#p_WRM1">Robert
                                Winfree</persName>—<gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The Prime Minister began our meeting stating that he had just had a very
                    interesting conversation with General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1"
                        >Marshall</persName> who had told him that Europeans should not be worried
                    about the Congressional resolution limiting American troop participation in
                    Europe to four divisions.<note n="2" xml:id="d129fn2">The reference is to Senate
                        Resolution 99 in support of the President’s authority to send American
                        troops to Europe. For documentation on the debate of this subject in early
                        1951, see <ref target="frus1951v03p1#pg_1">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                                >iii</hi>, Part 1, pp. 1</ref> ff. The text of Senate Resolution 99
                        is printed in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, April 16,
                        1951, p. 637.</note> I expressed my agreement with General <persName
                        corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>, saying that Congress had not passed a
                    law on this but simply a resolution. I said that Congressional feelings on the
                    sending of additional troops to Europe would depend greatly on the progress made
                    by the Europeans themselves in their rearmament and, of course, on the world
                    situation. In general, while it was correct that Europeans should not be
                    preoccupied by this Congressional action, they themselves must make a very
                    strong effort to rearm. Mr. <persName>Pholien</persName> then asked me if he
                    could repeat General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>’s statement
                    to European correspondents who would question him on his return. I said that I
                    thought it would be best not to repeat what General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1"
                        >Marshall</persName> had told him since it might well create difficulties
                    for General <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>.</p>
                <p>Ambassador <persName>Silvercruys</persName> interjected that more American troops
                    would be sent to Europe if necessary but that a determining factor would be
                    Europe’s own effort. With this I agreed.</p>
                <p>The Belgian Prime Minister then said that his country would be faithful to all of
                    its <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> and Brussels Pact engagements. He
                    asked, however, if it would be possible for us to consult with the other <gloss
                        target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> nations before taking really decisive steps
                    such as crossing the 38th parallel or dropping the atom bomb. I replied that he
                    had raised very delicate questions which most certainly <pb facs="0312" n="270"
                        xml:id="pg_270"/> should not be discussed at any time with the press. While
                    we desired to consult with our <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> partners on
                    any moves which we might make, if the security of the United States was
                    threatened, the President might have to act promptly without consultation. The
                    Prime Minister replied that the decisions of the United States Government would
                    have a direct influence on the world situation. If the decisions we were called
                    upon to make would decide whether or not there would be war or peace, would we
                    consult with the <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> nations? I said that it
                    was very hard to reply to this question. We might have to make immediate
                    decisions. I pointed out that in the last two wars when Germany had attacked we
                    came into the conflict sometime later, after we had had time to build up our
                    defense production. If war came again, it was likely (possible) that an
                    aggressor would not take the same course and would try to destroy our productive
                    power first. If such were the case, we must act immediately.</p>
                <p>I asked the Prime Minister to recall what we had been doing in Korea; that we had
                    made no unilateral decisions but had kept all interested powers fully informed
                    and had discussed every proposed step before we took it. We had actually had
                    restrictions placed upon us by the United Nations. As the Prime Minister knew,
                    we had thought it would be wise to have the President make a public statement
                    regarding our intentions in China, emphasizing that we sought only peace and had
                    no desires of conquest. This statement had been cleared with the interested
                    powers, but, unfortunately, General <persName corresp="#p_MAD1"
                        >MacArthur</persName> had issued a statement which served only to confuse
                    the situation.<note n="3" xml:id="d129fn3">For documentation on the proposed
                        Presidential statement on U.S. aims in Korea, circulated in draft form among
                        the nations providing forces in Korea, and the subsequent statement by
                            <persName corresp="#p_MAD1">MacArthur</persName> of March 24, see <ref
                            target="frus1951v07p1#pg_252">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">vii</hi>, Part
                            1, pp. 252</ref> ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>I then spoke about Germany emphasizing that although we thought Western Germany
                    should be brought into the European community, we had consulted with our <gloss
                        target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> partners on every German issue and had
                    actually turned over the leadership on German questions to other European
                    nations. We had no desire to take any step involving Germany without the full
                    understanding and agreement of other European nations.</p>
                <p>I added that the same was true of Japan. At the moment there was no predominant
                    power in the Pacific, but there could be no doubt but that Japan could be such a
                    power. We must have the Japanese on the side of the West. In the Far Eastern
                    Commission we were presently discussing a peace treaty with Japan. We desired
                    always to consult with all our allies before taking any steps.</p>
                <pb facs="0313" n="271" xml:id="pg_271"/>
                <p>Prime Minister <persName>Pholien</persName> then inquired if we felt the same way
                    about <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName>. I replied that the <persName
                        corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName> situation was a little more difficult
                    since we did not know exactly what <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Tito</persName>
                    wanted; however, it did appear now that he wanted to talk with us.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Pholien</persName> then stated that he was going to Bonn on Sunday
                    and might possibly see <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>. He asked
                    if he should endeavor to orient <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>
                    re European thinking on Western Germany. He added that the German problem was
                    very complex and complicated and that the Belgian Government’s attitude on
                    Germany had not yet crystallized. He also stated that he had heard from a Swiss
                    merchant who had been in Poland that while Poland hates Russia, she hates
                    Germany more. I told the Prime Minister that as far as I knew <persName
                        corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName>’s attitude was good and that we wanted
                    to help with the <persName corresp="#p_PR2">Pleven</persName> plan<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d129fn4">For documentation on the French Prime Minister’s plan for a
                        European Army, proposed in 1950 and discussed at length in 1951, see <ref
                            target="frus1950v03#pg_1">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol. <hi
                                rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, pp. 1</ref> ff., and <ref
                            target="frus1951v03p1#pg_755">
                            <hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>., 1951, vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>,
                            Part 1, pp. 755</ref> ff.</note> so that Germany would not be again a
                    menace to the peace of Western Europe. So far not much had been accomplished,
                    however, Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> was
                    hopeful that meetings to provide for a European Army could be arranged and we
                    were most anxious that such meetings take place. I added that I thought he
                    should tell <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> to be reasonable and
                    to endeavor to reach agreement in any conversations which might take place. The
                    Prime Minister reiterated his opinion that this was a very complex problem. I
                    agreed and stated that we were trying to find the least difficult solution. At
                    the present time, unless Russia’s attitude changed, the defense of Europe
                    without Germany would be extremely difficult. With German participation,
                    Europe’s defense would be possible. If the Russian attitude changed, new
                    situations would arise which would have to be met.</p>
                <p>I then mentioned the <gloss target="#t_AP1">AP</gloss> report regarding the
                    cutting off of <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> aid to Belgium. Ambassador
                        <persName>Silvercruys</persName> said that he had seen a press despatch
                    several days ago from Athens on this subject—that it was a very delicate matter
                    on which <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> was very touchy.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d129fn5">The reference is to the temporary suspension of <gloss
                            target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> allocations to Belgium pending satisfactory
                        settlement of an action by which a private Belgian firm, <gloss
                            target="#t_SOCOBEL1">Socobel</gloss> (or <gloss target="#t_SOCOBEL1"
                            >Socobelge</gloss>, Société Commerciale Belge), obtained an attachment
                        order for the temporary blocking of $7 million consisting of $6 million in
                            <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName> Aid funds and $1 million
                        from the European Payments Union, which had been deposited by the National
                        Bank of Greece in a Belgian bank to pay for steel rails to be supplied by
                        Belgian firms to Greece under <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> auspices.
                        The Assistant Administrator for Program, <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                        >ECA</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_PPR1">Paul Porter</persName>, announced
                        in Washington on April 9 that the U.S. Government had informed Belgium of
                        the suspension after conferring with a foreign affairs subcommittee of the
                        U.S. House of Representatives. A member of the subcommittee, <persName
                            corresp="#p_RAA1">Abraham Ribicoff</persName>, characterized the general
                        concern felt by his colleagues in his comment: “I do not think Congress is
                        going to sit by and allow the funds we use for rehabilitating these nations
                        to be able to be reached by private creditors for 25 year old debts. This
                        seven million dollars is the straw that may break the camel’s back of the
                        entire <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>.” (Extract from the April 9
                        hearings of the House Foreign Affairs Subcommittee on Economics, quoted with
                        similar comments by other members, in telegram <gloss target="#t_Torep1"
                            >Torep</gloss> 2381 to Paris, April 12, <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                            >ECA</gloss> message files, <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 53A278,
                        Paris. This <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> file contains much of the
                        correspondence on this subject. See also Department of State files
                        655.82231, 681.82231, 117–<gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>, and
                        881.00R/4–2751.)</note> I <pb facs="0314" n="272" xml:id="pg_272"/> said
                    that we had just recently transmitted a note to the Embassy in Brussels<note
                        n="6" xml:id="d129fn6">The note, not found in <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                            >ECA</gloss> or Department of State files, was handed to the Belgian
                        Minister of Foreign Commerce, <persName>Joseph Meurice</persName>, on April
                        11 by <persName corresp="#p_HCECJ1">Huntington Gilchrist</persName>, head of
                        the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Mission in Belgium. It warned the
                        Belgian Government that unless it settled the dispute with the Greek
                        Government or restituted the blocked $7 million by April 30, the U.S.
                        authorities would make good the amount out of <gloss target="#t_ECA1"
                            >ECA</gloss> allocations to Belgium. Correspondence between Belgium,
                        Greece, and the United States concerning details of a settlement extended
                        into July, but a basic agreement was announced by the <gloss
                            target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> in Washington on June 26. For text of the
                        announcement, see Document 135.</note> for delivery to the Belgian
                    Government stating that the Belgians must release these attached funds or an
                    equal sum would be withheld from their allotment. I added that it was
                    unfortunate that this had burst into the press. The Prime Minister stated that
                    he didn’t know too much about this particular matter. He did know that Greece
                    owed a heavy debt to Belgium and that Greece had received iron and steel from
                    Belgium and had to pay for it. I replied that there was no doubt on our part but
                    that Greece owed a debt to Belgium, however, we had established credits to
                    assist Grecian recovery and <gloss target="#t_SOCOBEL1">Socobel</gloss>, the
                    Belgian firm, had attached our funds. The Prime Minister stated that <gloss
                        target="#t_SOCOBEL1">Socobel</gloss>, which was a private firm, had attached
                    these funds before a Brussels court and that the Belgian Government had no
                    influence over this court. I stated that this was not our understanding of the
                    case—that the Belgian Government had been asked to intervene and urge that the
                    attachment be dissolved. However, it was my understanding that the Belgian
                    Government had urged that the attachment be upheld. The Prime Minister again
                    stated that his Government could not intervene in this case since no government
                    could condemn a sovereign foreign state. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MRD1"
                        >Murphy</persName> then stated that he understood that the Belgian
                    Government had intervened in this case because The Hague Court of Arbitration in
                    1936 had rendered a decision favorable to the Belgians, therefore, the Belgian
                    Government, on the basis of The Hague decision, felt that it should intervene.
                    The Prime Minister said he thought the situation was now clear and when I
                    remarked that it was something that should be straightened out, he agreed. I
                    added that I often had to sign certificates certifying that certain corporations
                    were owned by foreign governments and were therefore exempt from action by our
                    courts.</p>
                <pb facs="0315" n="273" xml:id="pg_273"/>
                <p>I suggested that if the Prime Minister were questioned by the press on this
                    matter that he merely state that he had not yet seen the story and could
                    therefore make no comment.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
