<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-07-03T19:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-07-03T19:00:00-05:00" n="174" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">751.5–<gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>/6–751: Telegram</note>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 174</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                            State</gloss> to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in
                                            France</gloss>
                                    </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d174fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BEJ1">Beigel</persName> and cleared by
                                        Treasury, <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_RA1">RA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SISA1">S/ISA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_OFD1">OFD</gloss>, the
                                        Executive Office, and Defense. Passed to <gloss target="#t_OSR1">OSR</gloss> in Paris for <persName corresp="#p_KM1">Katz</persName>, repeated to London for
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SCM1">Spofford</persName>, and
                                        sent to Heidelberg for <persName corresp="#p_HGTT1">Handy</persName>.</note>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                    </seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-07-03T20:00:00-04:00">July 3, 1951—8 p.m.</date>
                                    </dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>61. <gloss target="#t_Toisa1">Toisa</gloss>. Text draft reply to
                                    Fr note<note n="2" xml:id="d174fn2">Reference is to the French
                                        note of May 30, summarized in Document 168.</note> re level
                                    of aid follows. Believe note shld be submitted before end
                                    present Govt, unless you have strong views to contrary re form
                                    or timing (<gloss target="#t_EMBTEL1">Embtel</gloss> 7578 June
                                    7, rptd London 1996, <gloss target="#t_OSR1">OSR</gloss>
                                        unnumbered).<note n="3" xml:id="d174fn3">Not printed.</note>
                                </p>
                                <list>
                                    <label>1.</label>
                                    <item>US acknowledges receipt Fr note May 30. In belief Fr note
                                        based upon certain misapprehensions US position this matter,
                                        US of opinion it wld be advisable restate principles
                                        underlying extension economic assistance to Fr
                                        1950/51.</item>
                                    <label>2.</label>
                                    <item>Postwar US assistance to Fr has provided dollar exchange
                                        finance imports into Fr and Fr Union necessary for
                                        reconstruction and economic recovery, which cld not
                                        otherwise be financed from Fr dol resources. Aid for Fr has
                                        been determined in so far as possible, on basis net dol
                                        deficit after all other Fr dol transactions were taken into
                                        account on current basis. In accordance these principles, Fr
                                        received reconstruction loan from US 1945, balance payments
                                        loan 1946, and grant assistance under Interim Aid program
                                        1947. Since April 1948, to Mar 1951, Fr was allotted $2.1
                                        billion loan and grant assistance under <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> program. In Oct 1950 US
                                        announced, subsequent to US–Fr Ministerial Talks, it wld
                                        make available out of funds appropriated under <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss> Act, up to $200 million to
                                        Fr during first half 1951. This assistance is separate
                                        distinct from value military end-items provided to or
                                        scheduled for ultimate delivery to Fr under <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>. During 49/50 and 50/51
                                        value such end-items programmed for Fr have amounted to
                                        almost half of total value entire end-item program for
                                            <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> countries.</item>
                                    <label>3.</label>
                                    <item> Although it was contemplated during Ministerial Talks
                                        October 1950 US would procure military end-items in Fr, US
                                        thereafter decided it would not for time being undertake
                                        such procurement. In deciding merge <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_MDA1">MDA</gloss>
                                        funds and apply <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>
                                        procedures to assistance provided as result October talks,
                                        US Govt indicated this action should not have effect
                                        reducing amount economic aid granted Fr during 50/51.</item>
                                    <pb facs="0449" n="407" xml:id="pg_407"/>
                                    <label> </label>
                                    <item>The US Govt noted, for example, that Fr Govt had accepted
                                        the principle discussed during Oct talks and stipulated in
                                            <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of Dec 18,
                                            1950,<note n="4" xml:id="d174fn4">For text, see <ref target="frus1950v03#pg_1446">
                                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">iii</hi>, p.
                                            1446</ref>.</note> that any such dol receipts by Fr “are
                                        to be used, not to increase reserves, but (a) to pay for
                                        imports which must be purchased with non-<gloss target="#t_EPU1">EPU</gloss> currencies and which are
                                        required to assist in preventing inflation which might
                                        otherwise result from the increased defense effort, and (b)
                                        to meet gold or dol obligations to <gloss target="#t_EPU1">EPU</gloss> arising directly or indirectly out of the
                                        Fr prod program”. The Fr Govt recognized therein that in
                                        effect it wld rec dol assistance only to cover the deficit
                                        in its dol bal payments. In agreed minute of discussions of
                                        US-Fr econ Working Group in Jan 1951,<note n="5" xml:id="d174fn5">For text of the agreed minute on
                                            economic questions, see Annex A to Document 154.</note>
                                        the US again emphasized that the result of US assist shld
                                        not take form of increases in monetary reserves. </item>
                                    <label>4.</label>
                                    <item>As was stated in the Ministerial Talks in Oct 1950, the US
                                        Govt was of opinion that it cld not become directly involved
                                        in financing internal Fr budgetary outlays associated with
                                        rearmament effort. It believed that only by means of an
                                        increase in imports into France cld US aid serve to provide
                                        increased local currency resources for the Fr Govt. In the
                                        agreed minute of the US-Fr Econ Working Group in Jan 1951,
                                        the US again stated that US was providing assistance to meet
                                        real dol requirements and not for purpose of providing local
                                        currency resources to cover Fr budget deficit.</item>
                                    <label>5.</label>
                                    <item>In agreeing to the provision of econ assistance in Oct
                                        1950, the US clearly intended, as was stated in its <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, that “assistance herein
                                        proposed is without prejudice to the level of aid to be
                                        provided to the Govt of France under the <gloss target="#t_ECACT1">Ec Act</gloss> of 1948, as amended,
                                        and to any future adjustment thereof which the US may
                                        determine is necessary or desirable”. The US Govt, at that
                                        moment and on the basis of trade forecasts discussed jointly
                                        by the two <gloss target="#t_del1">del</gloss>s, believed
                                        that the proposed assistance wld be necessary to cover a dol
                                        deficit in excess of the deficit to be covered by the
                                        provision of assistance then available under the regular
                                            <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> program.</item>
                                    <label>6.</label>
                                    <item>The US has continued to look for revisions in Fr import
                                        policy in line with its understanding, as stated in the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of Dec 18, 1950 that Fr
                                        Govt intended “to take vigorous measures to combat
                                        inflationary pressures by all appropriate means, including
                                        necessary adjustments of import and credit policies.” It has
                                        been noted, in relation to (b) under para 13 <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss> of the <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi>, that the intra-Eur trade of Fr has
                                        not given rise to gold or dol payments by Fr since Oct 1950,
                                        but that contrary to expectations Fr has been a net
                                        recipient of $65 mil from the <gloss target="#t_EPU1">EPU</gloss> during 50/51. The US Govt <pb facs="0450" n="408" xml:id="pg_408"/> has also noted that Fr gold
                                        and dol reserves have increased by $175 mil in 50/51, thru
                                        May 1951; the increase since the exchange of <hi rend="italic">aides-mémoire</hi>, in Dec 1950, has been
                                        $50 mil.</item>
                                    <label>7.</label>
                                    <item>The US never fixed an arbitrary ceiling on the amt of econ
                                        assistance it wld make avail to Fr during 50/51. As of Feb
                                        1, Fr had been allotted $195 mil out of <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> appropriation for 50/51.
                                        The Fr Govt has indicated, in its note of May 30, 1951, its
                                        understanding it wld receive further $115 mil from <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> appropriation, in
                                        conformity with so-called Snoy–<persName corresp="#p_MRE1">Marjolin</persName> formula, in addition to proposed
                                        $200 mil in assistance under <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of Dec 18, 1950. It shld be noted
                                        that US Govt clearly stated in a communication to <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> that it did not consider
                                        itself bound by <gloss target="#t_SM1">S/M</gloss>
                                            formula<note n="6" xml:id="d174fn6">Snoy–<persName corresp="#p_MRE1">Marjolin</persName> formula for
                                            determining economic aid to <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName> Plan countries. For further
                                            information, see footnote 2, <ref target="frus1950v05#pg_1279">
                                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1950, vol.
                                                  <hi rend="smallcaps">v</hi>, p. 1279</ref>.</note>
                                        subsequent to Dec 1950, in view of fact <gloss target="#t_SM1">S/M</gloss> formula no longer led to
                                        distribution of aid in proportion to deficits of
                                        participating countries. In addition to formal notification
                                        to <gloss target="#t_OEEC1">OEEC</gloss> of abandonment of
                                            <gloss target="#t_SM1">S/M</gloss> formula, <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> in making each allotment
                                        for Fr in 50/51 informed Fr Govt that economic aid figure
                                        for year as whole had not been fixed.</item>
                                    <label>8.</label>
                                    <item>US estimated, early in May 1951, that Fr wld probably
                                        require no more than $200 mil in econ aid during period Feb
                                        1–June 30, 1951. This was believed to be an accurate
                                        estimate of French dollar requirements during this period.
                                        Despite developments described para 6, US Govt decided
                                        provide to Fr full amount of $200 mil specified in <hi rend="italic">aide-mémoire</hi> of Dec 18, 1950, giving
                                        a total allotment for 50/51 of $395 mil. By so doing, US
                                        Govt indicated its strong desire assist Fr Govt in rapid
                                        implementation its military program, which was of general
                                        size and character to warrant provision of econ assistance.
                                        Nevertheless US believes that Fr Govt, in failing to take
                                        more vigorous measures to admit imports into Fr, had not
                                        taken full advantage of assistance available from US during
                                        this period.</item>
                                    <label>9.</label>
                                    <item>The US Govt hopes that foregoing review will clarify for
                                        Fr Govt the basis on which aid has been extended during
                                        50/51.</item>
                                </list>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Acheson</hi>
                                        </persName>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>