<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-09-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="317" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d317">
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">No. 317</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">Conference files, lot 59D95,
                                CF95</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Declaration by the United States, France, and the
                                    United Kingdom on the Italian Peace Treaty</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d317fn1">Issued by the Department of State as press
                                    release 866 at noon on September 26.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-09-26">September 26,
                                        1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The Governments of the United States, France, and the United Kingdom
                                have considered for some time how best to resolve, in the interests
                                of the harmonious development of cooperation between <pb facs="0760" n="718" xml:id="pg_718"/> the free nations, the problem
                                presented by the Peace Treaty with Italy.</p>
                            <p>In accordance with the desire of the Italian people, Italy, which
                                loyally cooperated with the Allies during the latter part of the war
                                as a cobelligerent, has reestablished democratic institutions. In
                                the spirit of the United Nations’ Charter Italy has invariably
                                extended to other peaceful and democratic Governments that
                                cooperation indispensable to the solidarity of the free world.</p>
                            <p>Nevertheless, although Italy has on three occasions received the
                                support of the majority of member states voting in the General
                                Assembly, it is still prevented by an unjustifiable veto from
                                obtaining membership in the United Nations in spite of the
                                provisions of the Treaty and the Charter.</p>
                            <p>Moreover, Italy is still subject under the Peace Treaty to certain
                                restrictions and disabilities. These restrictions no longer accord
                                with the situation prevailing today nor with Italy’s status as an
                                active and equal member of the democratic and freedom-loving family
                                of nations.</p>
                            <p>Each of the three Governments therefore declares hereby its readiness
                                to give favorable consideration to a request from the Italian
                                Government to remove so far as concerns its individual relations
                                with Italy, and without prejudice to the rights of third parties,
                                those permanent restrictions and discriminations now in existence
                                which are wholly overtaken by events or have no justification in
                                present circumstances or affect Italy’s capacity for
                                self-defense.</p>
                            <p>Each of the three Governments hereby reaffirms its determination to
                                make every effort to secure Italy’s membership in the United
                                Nations.</p>
                            <p>The three Governments trust that this declaration will meet with the
                                wide approval of the other signatories of the Peace Treaty and that
                                they will likewise be prepared to take similar action.</p>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>