<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-07-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="382" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d382">
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">No. 382</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">752.5/7–351</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the Deputy Assistant Secretary of
                                    State for European Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BJCH1" type="from">Bonbright</persName>) to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss>
                                </hi><note n="1" xml:id="d382fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BHMJ1">Byington</persName>.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-07-03">July 3,
                                    1951</date>.</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>The attached “Memorandum Regarding Conduct of Base Negotiations with
                                Spain” is submitted for your approval. It has been cleared by Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MFP1">Matthews</persName> and is in line
                                with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PGW1">Perkins</persName>’
                                conversations with <persName corresp="#p_SAFP1">Admiral
                                    Sherman</persName>.</p>
                            <p>In accordance with the British and French requests for further
                                consultations concerning Spain, a meeting was held with British
                                representatives, including Air Chief <persName corresp="#p_TMJB1">Marshal</persName> Sir <persName corresp="#p_EWY1">William</persName> Elliot, on June 21 and French
                                representatives, including General Murtin, on June 22, on which
                                occasions our policy and objectives were explained by <persName corresp="#p_SAFP1">Admiral Sherman</persName> and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PGW1">Perkins</persName>. On June 29 the British
                                Embassy requested that before initiating bilateral conversations in
                                Madrid, we await their views, which would receive Cabinet
                                consideration on July 5. We expect, therefore, to hear further from
                                them during this week.</p>
                            <pb facs="0868" n="826" xml:id="pg_826"/>
                            <p>In the meanwhile, we have asked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GS1">Griffis</persName> in Madrid to send us his comments on the
                                proposed procedure for negotiations.<note n="2" xml:id="d382fn2">On
                                    July 5 Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GS1">Griffis</persName>
                                    urged that <persName corresp="#p_SAFP1">Admiral
                                        Sherman</persName> come to Madrid no later than July 16.
                                    (Telegram 14, 752.5/7–551)</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>If <persName corresp="#p_SAFP1">Admiral Sherman</persName> should go,
                                it is planned that he would leave here not later than July 15 in
                                order to begin conversations with General <persName corresp="#p_FYB1">Franco</persName> prior to the latter’s
                                farewell reception on July 18 when he leaves for his summer
                                    residence.<note n="3" xml:id="d382fn3">At the bottom of the
                                    source text, next to the typewritten word “Approved”, are
                                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName>’s
                                    initials.</note>
                            </p>
                            <frus:attachment>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">[Attachment]</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum Regarding the Conduct of Base
                                        Negotiations With Spain</hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                                    </seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>,] <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-06-25">June 25,
                                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>The following course of action is recommended for the negotiation
                                    with the Spanish Government of the military operating facilities
                                    required in Spain.</p>
                                <p>
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SAFP1">Admiral Sherman</persName> or
                                    another high-ranking officer should accompany the Ambassador
                                    when the negotiations are opened. This would involve discussions
                                    with General <persName corresp="#p_FYB1">Franco</persName> to
                                    follow up his assurance to the Ambassador that base facilities
                                    in Spanish territory would be available to the U.S. and his
                                    agreement in principle of June 27 to “conversations of a
                                    defensive military character.” Subsequent discussions with high
                                    Spanish military authorities would probably then take place.</p>
                                <p>Since a high-ranking officer would undoubtedly be unable to
                                    remain to carry out the entire negotiations, these initial talks
                                    should prepare the way for a small group from Defense to
                                    continue the negotiations. As in the case of the current Azores
                                    negotiations with the Portuguese Government,<note n="4" xml:id="d382fn4">For information on this subject, see
                                        Document 352.</note> this group would be under the general
                                    direction of the Ambassador and would be assisted, as required,
                                    by the Service Attachés and by other members of the Embassy
                                    staff. It should consist of a high-ranking officer from both the
                                    Air Force and the Navy; these Departments will probably each
                                    wish to send a representative from their legal staffs and the
                                    office of the Secretary of Defense may also wish to be
                                    represented.</p>
                                <p>The Ambassador should be instructed in advance to inform
                                        <persName corresp="#p_FYB1">Franco</persName> that it is
                                    planned to send a high-ranking officer to Spain to initiate
                                    negotiations for air and naval base facilities in Spain. He <pb facs="0869" n="827" xml:id="pg_827"/> should also be
                                    instructed to ask <persName corresp="#p_FYB1">Franco</persName>
                                    to receive him and this officer.</p>
                                <p>From what is known of the Ambassador’s opinion on this subject,
                                    he would welcome both <persName corresp="#p_SAFP1">Admiral
                                        Sherman</persName>’s visit and the assistance of other
                                    officers in the technical military and legal aspects which these
                                    negotiations will involve.</p>
                                <p>The agreement itself can be set up in the same general pattern we
                                    are using in other cases. This would include a main
                                    government-to-government agreement with one or more annexes
                                    covering the more technical military, jurisdictional and other
                                    matters which are not covered in the government agreement. The
                                    details on this can be worked out with the Air Force and
                                        Navy.<note n="5" xml:id="d382fn5">President <persName corresp="#p_THS1">Truman</persName> approved this
                                        memorandum and the dispatch of <persName corresp="#p_SAFP1">Admiral Sherman</persName> to Spain at the Cabinet
                                        meeting on July 6. (Memorandum dated July 6 and letter from
                                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ADG1">Acheson</persName> to
                                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>,
                                        dated July 10, <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> files, lot 63D351, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> 72 files)</note>
                                </p>
                            </frus:attachment>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>