<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-06T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-06T20:00:00-05:00" n="433" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d433">
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">No. 433</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> message files, <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 53A278, London: Telegram</note>
                            <head>
                                <hi rend="italic">The Economic Cooperation Administrator (<persName type="from">Foster</persName>) to the <gloss target="#t_ECA1" type="to">ECA</gloss> Mission in the United
                                    Kingdom</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d433fn1">Repeated to
                                    Paris.</note>
                            </head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">
                                    <hi rend="smallcaps">secret</hi>
                                </seg>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-06T20:00:00-05:00">April
                                        6, 1951—8 p.m.</date>
                                </dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>
                                <gloss target="#t_Ecato1">Ecato</gloss> 397. Reference: <gloss target="#t_Toeca1">Toeca</gloss> 275, rptd <gloss target="#t_Torep1">Torep</gloss> 215.<note n="2" xml:id="d433fn2">Not printed.</note> I. The Situation: 1)
                                Details discussions with <persName corresp="#p_RSL1">Rowan</persName>, <persName>Clark</persName>,
                                    <persName>Hall</persName> following <persName corresp="#p_WJE1">Webb</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_FSOS1">Franks</persName>
                                meeting being sent separately.<note n="3" xml:id="d433fn3">The
                                    report on the meeting held April 4 was transmitted in telegram
                                        <gloss target="#t_Ecato1">Ecato</gloss> 398 (741.5/4–651);
                                    regarding the meetings on April 5 and 6, see the memorandum of
                                    conversation, <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>.</note>
                            </p>
                            <p>2) Brit being told:</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>a)</label>
                                <item>On present analysis here will be no direct country allotment
                                    of aid <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 51/52, this without
                                    prejudice to continued participation other <gloss target="#t_ERP1">ERP</gloss> activities.</item>
                                <label>b)</label>
                                <item>Certain end-item aid will be continued.</item>
                                <label>c)</label>
                                <item>Reconsideration present decisions wld follow changed
                                    circumstances. </item>
                                <pb facs="0971" n="929" xml:id="pg_929"/>
                                <label>d)</label>
                                <item>US not denying possible obligation that might arise from
                                    burden sharing exercise but Brit were told objective of not
                                    increasing gold and dollar reserves still major consideration in
                                    our approach to problem.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p>3) When time comes for definite public announcement, we assume Brit
                                Govt will accept responsibility of presenting possible US assistance
                                limited to mil end-items in most favorable light.</p>
                            <p>II. <hi rend="italic">What can be said:</hi> You are in better
                                position to decide what response should be made to Brit officials on
                                subject of aid, but any statements should be made in light of
                                situation as described above. We inclined believe Brit public would
                                accept decision on limited aid to Britain in whatever spirit is
                                indicated by Brit Govt. Hope treatment will be as with suspension
                                EGA aid last fall when Brit given psychological boost by this
                                evidence ability to stand on own feet. Re your statement no
                                distinction made between end-item and <gloss target="#t_AMP1">AMP</gloss> programs, presumably announcement continuation
                                end-item aid would go long way satisfy public. Some of following
                                points might be made. These and others have undoubtedly already
                                occurred to you.</p>
                            <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>Obviously, finance and production problems of meeting <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> defense requirements are being
                                    discussed both bi-laterally in terms of current economic and
                                    financial situation in UK and multi-laterally among <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> members.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>No final decision yet on quantity end-items but substantial
                                    flow in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 51/52 may be
                                    considered most likely.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>Even if it were decided in full consultation with Brit and
                                    other <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> powers that in its
                                    present econ circumstances, Brit required no direct US financial
                                    aid, such decision wld not preclude sympathetic consideration of
                                    stresses and strains in Brit econ which might develop in future
                                    but do not exist at present, including those which might arise
                                    from increase or acceleration of Brit mil program.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>If decision in 3 is adopted it will be made clear that it does
                                    not imply inadequacy of Brit effort which US recognizes as
                                    substantial and realistic.</item>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>Shld be matter of pride for Brit that within their own means
                                    they are able to mount program of this magnitude as contribution
                                    to security free world.</item>
                            </list>
                            <closer>
                                <signed>
                                    <persName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Foster</hi>
                                    </persName>
                                </signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>