<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Department of State Record of a State-Joint Chiefs of Staff Meeting Held at
                    the Pentagon, Wednesday, November 21, 1951, 10:30 a.m.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951v04p1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d454</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">454</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1951-11-21T10:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1951-11-21T10:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recaf9c7c5029dfd21" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy">Atomic energy</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communications</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology" subcategory="atomic-energy" subject="nuclear-energy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958" lcsh-match="exact">Atomic energy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-11-21T10:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-11-21T10:30:00-05:00" n="454"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d454">
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 454</seg>
                </opener>
                <note rend="inline" type="source">State-<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss>
                    Meetings, lot 64D563, box 728</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Department of State Record of a State-Joint Chiefs of Staff
                        Meeting Held at the Pentagon, Wednesday, November 21, 1951, 10:30 a.m.</hi>
                    <note n="1" xml:id="d454fn1">The source text bears the typewritten notation
                        “State Draft. Not cleared with any of the participants.” The Department of
                            State-<gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> meetings, begun in January
                        1951, were held on a regular basis with either side bringing up topics which
                        it wanted to discuss. Records of the meetings for 1951 are in lot 64D563,
                        box 728.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                        ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-head" calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1951-11-21T10:30:00-05:00">November 21, 1951, 10:30 a.m.</date>
                </dateline>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">top secret</hi>
                    </seg>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Present</hi>
                </p>
                <table cols="2" rows="10">
                    <row>
                        <cell>General <persName>Collins</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <persName>Admiral Fechteler</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>General <persName>Twining</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJCH1">Bonbright</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>General <persName>Bolte</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName>Ferguson</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>General <persName>White</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName>Lacy</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <persName>Admiral Fife</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName>Johnson</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>General <persName>Cabell</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MGC1">Marshall</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <persName>Admiral Wooldridge</persName>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName>Tufts</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>
                            <persName>Admiral Nalor</persName> [<persName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Lalor</hi>
                            </persName>]</cell>
                        <cell>Mr. <persName>Lay</persName>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Colonel <persName>Carnes</persName> [<persName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Carns</hi>
                            </persName>]</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p rend="center">General <persName>Ruffner</persName>
                </p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of an article in the <hi rend="italic">New York
                        Times</hi>, Korea, the Singapore talks, and Iran.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> Visit</hi>
                    <note n="2" xml:id="d454fn2">Regarding Prime Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s visit to the United States, see
                        Document 452.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: We would like to take up the problem of
                    preparing for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s visit. I
                    thought it would be helpful for Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>
                    to present some of the background.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>: We would like to expose our
                    preliminary views on this matter. The first thing we ought to look at, I think,
                    is the question of what we want to get from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1"
                        >Churchill</persName>. Of course we will have to look at what he wants to
                    get from us and what we can accept, what we will have to reject and what we can
                    compromise about. The major problem in our view is the kind of relationship that
                    we want with the British. We have in fact a special relationship with <pb
                        facs="1028" n="986" xml:id="pg_986"/> them. It has not worked well since Mr.
                        <persName>Bevin</persName> became ill. It has not worked at all well with
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MHS1">Morrison</persName>. The present government has
                    not been organized long enough to work out the form of the relationship but I
                    think it is working toward a closer one. The <persName corresp="#p_CWS1"
                        >Churchill</persName> visit is a good opportunity for us to shape this
                    relationship. Public opinion in the U.S. is more favorable to the U.K. now that
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> has returned to office. I
                    think we can hope for a sounder relationship with the <persName
                        corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> government than we have had with Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_MHS1">Morrison</persName>. The thing we want to avoid,
                    in our judgment, is the creation of new machinery. We have plenty of machinery
                    now. Above all, we do not want to reconstruct the <persName corresp="#p_CWS1"
                        >Roosevelt-Churchill</persName> relationship of the last war.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>: We all agree with you on
                    that.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Admiral Fechteler</persName>: There is no doubt that <persName
                        corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> wants to use the trans-Atlantic
                    telephone.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>: We are concerned that he will
                    want a Combined Chiefs of Staff in the economic and military fields. On the
                    other hand we can not be negative. We will have to have our own idea of a better
                    solution in order to head off a bad solution. We think that one thing that could
                    be developed further is the joint political-military talks that we have been
                    holding on such matters as the Yugoslav problem. These are not decision-making
                    talks but consultative talks. It has occurred to us that we might build this up
                    somewhat and hold them more often. We feel that they might be a helpful way to a
                    concert of policies and to the building of a good relationship. Of course these
                    talks would not be the only machinery. We have all kinds of machinery for
                    economic affairs, for <gloss target="#t_NAT1">NATO</gloss> affairs, and so
                    forth. There is the relationship which <persName>Elliot</persName> has with you.
                    …</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>: Hong Kong is another
                    example of a problem on which we need to develop a joint policy.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>: There seem to be two objectives
                    which we ought to try to accomplish. In the first place, we want to assist the
                    U.K. to strengthen its position and to gain additional prestige. There are some
                    areas in which the British have got to take the lead. Egypt is one of these. In
                    short we want the British to be an asset to us, not a drain on us. We want them
                    to carry the load wherever they can and especially in those areas where we can
                    not carry it. Secondly, we want the British to support us in areas where we are
                    taking the lead. Korea is a case in point. By the same token we will have to be
                    prepared to support them in some areas. I don’t think there is any one way to
                    solve all these problems.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: There is an additional problem which we will
                    have to consider, namely, the British economic problem.</p>
                <pb facs="1029" n="987" xml:id="pg_987"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>: I should have mentioned that.
                    It is a very serious and difficult problem. We have a number of people working
                    on it. We are now considering ways and means of giving support to the
                    British.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: We must expect that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> will want to talk about a Big Three
                    or Big Four meeting. He still has the view that the meetings with <persName
                        corresp="#p_S1">Stalin</persName> during the war produced good results. He
                    likes the face-to-face method of approach.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>: Of course, I am not so
                    sure the results were good.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: The point, though, is that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> believes that the results were
                    good.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Admiral Fechteler</persName>: Where would the talks be held?</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: That is a problem. The President has taken the
                    position that he is prepared to meet <persName corresp="#p_S1">Stalin</persName>
                    in Washington any time <persName corresp="#p_S1">Stalin</persName> is willing to
                    come. Of course, <persName corresp="#p_S1">Stalin</persName> will not come to
                    Washington but if he is interested in a meeting he might come to Berlin or some
                    other place where he had control over his communications. In our view it would
                    be extremely dangerous to hold conversations with <persName corresp="#p_S1"
                        >Stalin</persName> unless we had made most careful preparations. If
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> finds that he cannot obtain
                    our agreement to a Big Three or Big Four meeting, he may decide to go to Moscow
                    alone. During the election campaign <persName corresp="#p_CWS1"
                        >Churchill</persName> was pictured as a war-monger by the Labor Party. He is
                    very sensitive on this point. It would help him politically in Britain if he
                    went to Moscow in all humility. In our view, this too holds great dangers. He
                    has a propensity to speak for the Americans as well as the British. We have had
                    some experience of that during the war. The question that this raises is whether
                    a U.S. representative should accompany him on such a mission.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>: I think there would be
                    even more danger of his speaking for the U.S. in that event.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: That is a point to consider. Of course,
                        <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> rather favors the idea of
                    spheres of influence—he thinks that the world can be divided up in such a way
                    that <persName corresp="#p_S1">Stalin</persName> will agree to stay here and we
                    will agree to stay there.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>: I think there is a basic
                    difference in our points of view. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1"
                        >Churchill</persName> and the British are much more concerned than we are to
                    obtain a simple relaxation of tensions. They think it is very important to
                    reduce tensions somehow. I suppose this derives from the vulnerability of the
                    U.K. in the event of war. We feel, on the other hand, that until we have built
                    up our strength and can secure some retraction of Soviet power it is dangerous
                    to freeze an unsatisfactory situation. In other words, our objectives are
                    farther forward and longer run in character.</p>
                <pb facs="1030" n="988" xml:id="pg_988"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: Our Secretary feels that a Big Four meeting
                    would be a mistake.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>: With reference to the
                    possibility of more frequent meetings with the British on special areas, how
                    would we follow these meetings up with the French? The fact of the meetings is
                    bound to become known to them. What will their reaction be? Will we just ignore
                    their reaction or will we hold meetings with them also?</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: I think we would have to have some meetings
                    with the French. Our efforts with the French would be to underemphasize the
                    importance of our special relationship with the British.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>: In our dealings with the
                    British we must reserve the right to talk with whomever we want to about any
                    problems whatsoever.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>: We agree. For example, we have
                    got to talk with the Canadians. We did talk with them regularly for a while and
                    we soon ran out of topics.<note n="3" xml:id="d454fn3">For the records of the
                        conversations with the Canadians during May, June, and July, see <ref
                            target="frus1951v01#pg_802">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, pp.
                            802</ref> ff.</note> For that reason we found that meetings with the
                    Canadians presented no real difficulties.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Admiral Fechteler</persName>: What about atomic energy questions?</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1"
                        >Churchill</persName> will clearly want to take this range of questions up
                    with us.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>: I thought that we should adhere
                    to the position which we took in our previous talks—the talks that Mr.
                        <persName>Matthews</persName>, General <persName corresp="#p_BGAMN1"
                        >Bradley</persName>, <persName>Elliot</persName>, <persName
                        corresp="#p_FSOS1">Franks</persName> and I had.<note n="4" xml:id="d454fn4"
                        >Presumably a reference to the meeting on September 13; see <ref
                            target="frus1951v01#pg_83">vol. <hi rend="smallcaps">i</hi>, p.
                        83</ref>.</note> That position flowed from our talks with the <gloss
                        target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> and JSSC.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: We think there is an advantage to consider
                    this in the context of the joint policies needed in the event of war. I do not
                    think that Mr. <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> will be prepared
                    to accept our position. He still thinks in terms of the war-time agreement and
                    full cooperation we had at that time. He will want to return to that situation
                    if he can and probably believes that had he stayed in office, that cooperation
                    would have been maintained.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Admiral Fechteler</persName>: In his Guild <persName>Hall</persName>
                    speech <persName corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName> stated that the British
                    were entitled to special consideration in this matter because of the bases
                        problem.<note n="5" xml:id="d454fn5">For an extract from <persName
                            corresp="#p_CWS1">Churchill</persName>’s Guildhall speech on November 9,
                        dealing, <hi rend="italic">inter alia</hi>, with the question of bases in
                        East Anglia, see Folliot, <hi rend="italic">Documents on International
                            Affairs, 1951</hi>, pp. 136–138.</note> What does he mean in your
                    opinion by special considerations? Does he want financial assistance or
                    something else?</p>
                <pb facs="1031" n="989" xml:id="pg_989"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: No, I think he wants information and
                    consultation regarding all atomic matters.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Admiral Fechteler</persName>: Surely he knows our law, and that led me
                    to wonder whether he would have made this proposal public if what he had in mind
                    was information and consultation.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_NPH1">Nitze</persName>: Of course the law has now been
                    modified in some respects.</p>
                <p>General <persName corresp="#p_CGJL1">Collins</persName>: We are working on this
                    problem with State at the request of General <persName corresp="#p_EGDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName>. He has got to be able to talk with some of his staff
                    people about atomic energy matters if they are going to plan intelligently. A
                    position on this is being worked up regarding a modification of the law.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName>Matthews</persName>: It is clear that <persName corresp="#p_CWS1"
                        >Churchill</persName> is going to raise these questions since he is bringing
                        <persName>Lord Cherwell</persName> with him.</p>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of Spain and the Singapore talks.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
