<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-04-12T20:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-04-12T20:00:00-05:00" n="55" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d55">
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 55</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">
                                    <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> message files, <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 53A278, Paris: Telegram</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">The Deputy Administrator for Economic
                                        Cooperation (</hi><persName corresp="#p_BRMJ1" type="from">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Bissell</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">)
                                        to the United States Special Representative in Europe for
                                        the <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>, at Paris
                                        (</hi><persName corresp="#p_KM1" type="to">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Katz</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">)</hi><note n="1" xml:id="d55fn1">Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_BRMJ1">Bissell</persName> and cleared with
                                            <persName corresp="#p_PGW1">Perkins</persName>,
                                        Prud’homme, and <persName corresp="#p_VR1">Vernon</persName>. Sent also to the Embassy in France and
                                        to the Office of the High Commissioner for Germany at
                                        Frankfurt for <persName corresp="#p_BDKE1">Bruce</persName>,
                                        Parkman, <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName>, and
                                            <persName corresp="#p_CJ1">Cattier</persName>.</note>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#left">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">confidential</hi>
                                    </seg>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-04-12T20:00:00-05:00">April 12, 1951—8 p.m.</date>
                                    </dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>
                                    <gloss target="#t_Torep1">Torep</gloss> 2406. Subject—Possible
                                    U.S. Contribution to <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan.</p>
                                <p>1. State and <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> have been
                                    considering possibility U.S. agree provide $50–$100 million
                                    financial support for <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan. Following <pb facs="0154" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/> paragraphs present provisional views here
                                    possible form of arrangement. Purpose is to obtain reaction
                                        <gloss target="#t_OSR1">OSR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>, and Am Embassy Paris.</p>
                                <p>2. All discussions this subject have been confused by absence of
                                    clearly defined proposal. While we have not as yet worked out
                                    clearly defined proposal our provisional view of the general
                                    line of a proposal which might be considered are as follows: (a)
                                    agreed amount of <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> funds from
                                    present appropriation would be deposited with the Treasury in a
                                    permanent trust account for the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan; (b) payments from funds might be
                                    made either to individual member countries or to the High
                                    Authority but in all cases with the approval of the High
                                    Authority; (c) purpose for which fund could be drawn upon would
                                    be subject to agreement between High Authority and <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> but in general would be for the
                                    purpose of financing equipment, modernization, integration of
                                    European coal and steel industries including such items as
                                    housing for workers in coal and steel industries and other
                                    purposes directly related to the expansion and increased
                                    efficiency of production and productivity. It would not
                                    therefore be available for subsidies, equalization payments,
                                    retirement of surplus or outmoded capacity or other purposes not
                                    directly related to the expansion and increased efficiency of
                                    production and productivity; (d) the form in which the aid would
                                    be given from the trust account would depend upon the purposes.
                                    If the High Authority required dollars in order to extend local
                                    currency loans High Authority could be given free dollars with
                                    which to procure the local currency. Similarly if it needed
                                    dollars in order to make payment on a guarantee it would be
                                    given free dollars with which to procure currency to make such
                                    payment. Where the purpose is to finance shipments from the U.S.
                                    of capital equipment dollars in those cases would be program
                                    dollars made available with the approval of the High Authority
                                    to the member countries in accordance with <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> procedures; (e) in general to
                                    the maximum extent possible intra-European payments impacts
                                    would be handled within the <gloss target="#t_EPU1">EPU</gloss>
                                    framework and not through the High Authority. In other words the
                                    functions of the two institutions will to the maximum extent be
                                    kept separate.</p>
                                <p>3. Foregoing arrangement could be established under authority
                                    existing legislation. Creation trust fund out of current
                                    appropriations might however be dependent on legal establishment
                                    High Authority before July 1, 1951. If High Authority not
                                    established by then, probably necessary seek include allowance
                                    funds for this purpose in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> ‘52
                                    appropriation. In any event, arrangement could not be
                                    established without prior Congressional consultation.</p>
                                <pb facs="0155" n="113" xml:id="pg_113"/>
                                <p>4. Appreciate views <gloss target="#t_OSR1">OSR</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_HICOG1">HICOG</gloss>, AmEmbassy Paris
                                        soonest.<note n="2" xml:id="d55fn2">In priority telegram
                                        8370 to Paris, April 16, <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> informed the Department of State that
                                        he was “strongly inclined” to support the view of State and
                                            <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> that a U.S.
                                        commitment of funds to the European Coal and Steel Community
                                        prior to its formal establishment through ratification of
                                        the treaty by the member nations was “of doubtful wisdom”.
                                        (Paris Embassy files, lot 58F53, “500 Coal and Steel Pool”)
                                        In telegram <gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss> 1839
                                        from Paris, April 21, <persName corresp="#p_KM1">Katz</persName> informed <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> Administrator <persName corresp="#p_FWC1">Foster</persName> that he felt that “we shld take no
                                        initiative for present” and that he was “Impressed by
                                            <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName>’s views
                                        Frankfurt 8370”. (<gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss>
                                        message files, <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 53A278,
                                        Paris) On April 27 <persName corresp="#p_BRMJ1">Bissell</persName> informed <persName corresp="#p_KM1">Katz</persName> in telegram <gloss target="#t_Torep1">Torep</gloss> 2793 that in light of telegrams <gloss target="#t_Repto1">Repto</gloss> 1839 and 8370, <gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> had decided not to provide
                                        any contribution to the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan from fiscal 1951 funds but
                                        would seek authorization for contributions to “central
                                        institutions” from 1952 funds which would be on terms broad
                                        enough to cover possible contributions to the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan. (<gloss target="#t_ECA1">ECA</gloss> message files, <gloss target="#t_FRC1">FRC</gloss> 53A278, Paris)</note>
                                </p>
                                <closer>
                                    <signed>
                                        <persName corresp="#p_BRMJ1">
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Bissell</hi>
                                        </persName>
                                    </signed>
                                </closer>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>