<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1951-08-27T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1951-08-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="67" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d67">
                                <opener>
                                    <seg rendition="#center">No. 67</seg>
                                </opener>
                                <note rend="inline" type="source">Bonn Mission files, <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> Project, lot 311,
                                    D(51)1259</note>
                                <head>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Memorandum by the United States High
                                        Commissioner for Germany (</hi><persName corresp="#p_MJJ1" type="from">
                                        <hi rend="italic">McCloy</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">)
                                        to the Chancellor of the Federal Republic of Germany
                                        (</hi><persName corresp="#p_AK1" type="to">
                                        <hi rend="italic">Adenauer</hi></persName><hi rend="italic">)</hi>
                                </head>
                                <opener>
                                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                                        <placeName>
                                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfurt</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-27">August 27,
                                            1951</date>.</dateline>
                                </opener>
                                <p>On August 27, 1951, representatives of the Federal Government on
                                    the Committee on Coal Distribution Problems Relation to the
                                    Dissolution of the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> presented
                                    to a meeting of the Committee a plan which called for the
                                    substitution of a single central selling agency for all Ruhr
                                    coal for the existing <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss>.</p>
                                <p>From the very outset of our discussions with the representatives
                                    of the trade unions and the representatives of the Government we
                                    have made it clear that a single central selling agency for coal
                                    was <pb facs="0173" n="131" xml:id="pg_131"/> out of the
                                    question, and indeed, the representatives of the trade unions
                                    and of the government indicated that no such agency was desired,
                                    but that certain functions outside of exclusive selling which
                                    the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> performed were
                                    desirable. Moreover, and really more important, the maintenance
                                    of a single central selling agency is in direct conflict with
                                    your letter of March 14, 1951,<note n="1" xml:id="d67fn1">See
                                        telegram 7411 from Frankfurt, Document 49.</note> and with
                                    the terms of reference of the Committee.</p>
                                <p>I am really amazed that at this point the German representatives
                                    should not only again raise this subject, but in effect should
                                    repudiate the position taken in the letter of March 14, which in
                                    itself represented a compromise worked out after much labor and
                                    time, with concessions from both sides. The point is one of
                                    principle on which no further compromise is possible,
                                    particularly as it falls directly in the field relating to the
                                        <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan.</p>
                                <p>In order to remind those involved of the series of compromises
                                    and concessions which have been made following the letter of
                                    March 14, I am annexing a statement of these concessions and I
                                    urge that from here out the German representatives be instructed
                                    to act in conformity with your letter of March 14 and the terms
                                    of reference of the Committee in regard to a single central
                                    selling agency.</p>
                                <frus:attachment>
                                    <opener>
                                        <seg rendition="#center">[Annex]</seg>
                                    </opener>
                                    <head>
                                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum Prepared in the Office of the
                                            United States High Commissioner for Germany</hi>
                                    </head>
                                    <opener>
                                        <dateline rendition="#right">[<placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Frankfurt</hi></placeName>,]
                                                <date calendar="gregorian" when="1951-08-27">August
                                                27, 1951</date>.</dateline>
                                    </opener>
                                    <p rend="center">
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Committee on Coal Distribution Problems
                                            Relating to the Dissolution of the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss>
                                        </hi>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>1. In view of the apparent repudiation by the Federal
                                        Government’s representatives on this Committee and of the
                                        Chancellor’s letter of 14 March 1951, with regard to the
                                        dissolution of the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss>, and
                                        their complete disregard of the terms of reference given to
                                        the Committee, a very serious situation is presented which
                                        makes necessary a review of the developments leading up to
                                        the creation of the Committee and the considerations
                                        involved.</p>
                                    <p>2. The creation of the Committee was the outcome of a series
                                        of events, to wit: <list>
                                            <label>a.</label>
                                            <item>Exchanges of letters and several discussions took
                                                place with regard to the coal and steel industries
                                                and their reorganization between <pb facs="0174" n="132" xml:id="pg_132"/> representatives of the
                                                Allied High Commission and representatives of the
                                                Federal Government. Certain concessions were made by
                                                both sides from the positions originally taken. On
                                                14 March 1951 Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> addressed a letter to the
                                                Chairman of the Allied High Commission setting forth
                                                certain proposals which have been, in general,
                                                accepted as the basis for action.</item>
                                            <label>b.</label>
                                            <item>In that letter of 14 March the Federal Government
                                                recognized that the continuance of centralized sales
                                                organizations would be inconsistent both with the
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan
                                                and the provisions of Law 27 and proposed the
                                                liquidation of the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> to be accomplished in stages over a
                                                period of time in order to provide an orderly
                                                transition.</item>
                                            <label>c.</label>
                                            <item>My meeting extending over four hours early in
                                                March with trade union leaders including Von Hoff,
                                                Wagenfuehr, August Schmidt and Grosse in which the
                                                trade union leaders expressed their concern about
                                                problems which might arise in the coal industry as a
                                                result of the termination of centralized sales. This
                                                meeting resulted in my undertaking to include in the
                                                transitional convention of the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan Treaty
                                                specific provisions for a study by the High
                                                Authority of the problems alluded to by the unions.
                                                It was stated by the union leaders that this would
                                                satisfy their concerns. I then obtained the
                                                acceptance of Section 12 of the Transitional
                                                Convention which contains the agreed
                                                provision.</item>
                                            <label>d.</label>
                                            <item>The series of conversations between the German
                                                trade union leaders who are members of the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan
                                                delegation, Von Hoff, Wagenfuehr, and Grosse, with
                                                representatives of the French <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan
                                                delegation, of which we were kept informed, at which
                                                the German trade leaders expressed their concern
                                                that the problems to which they had previously
                                                alluded might arise within the period between July
                                                1st, the scheduled date for the commencement of the
                                                liquidation of the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss>, and the coming into force of the
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>
                                                Plan. At these meetings the German representatives
                                                again fully accepted the Chancellor’s letter of
                                                March 14 and recognized the inconsistency of central
                                                sales of Ruhr coal with the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan and
                                                addressed their attention purely to the need for
                                                other solutions of the problems of the coal industry
                                                during the interim period. These conversations led
                                                to the letter of Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> to Chancellor
                                                  <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> of
                                                19 April 1951 stating that a High Commission
                                                Committee to deal with such interim problems would
                                                be proposed.<note n="2" xml:id="d67fn2">Reference is
                                                  to a letter from <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> concerning the dissolution of
                                                  the International Authority for the Ruhr. See
                                                  Document 56.</note>
                                            </item>
                                            <label>e.</label>
                                            <item>The meeting of 6 May which I had with the trade
                                                union leaders including Imig and Grosse at which
                                                there was a reiteration of their acceptance of the
                                                Chancellor’s letter in its provision for termination
                                                of central selling but in which they expressed
                                                concern that by reason of the lapse of time, the
                                                commencement of the liquidation of the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> and its
                                                transformation into a voluntary organization of 1
                                                July would allow insufficient time for the work of
                                                the Committee proposed by <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> to deal with the interim
                                                proposals. The result of this meeting was the
                                                preparation of a memorandum by me in which I stated
                                                that in order to permit an effective <pb facs="0175" n="133" xml:id="pg_133"/> allocation system to be
                                                instituted for the period of shortage I would
                                                propose to the High Commission that the date for the
                                                commencement of the liquidation of <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> be postponed to 1
                                                October. We were informed by Dr.
                                                  <persName>Grosse</persName> that this memorandum
                                                was completely satisfactory to the unions and I was
                                                called by Von Hoff who said that this action would
                                                fully satisfy the condition laid down by the <gloss target="#t_DGB1">DGB</gloss> for its approval of
                                                the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName>
                                                Plan.</item>
                                            <label>f.</label>
                                            <item>The issuance by the High Commission of terms of
                                                reference for the Committee which included
                                                provisions barring a central sales agency for the
                                                sale of coal or coke in accordance with the
                                                Chancellor’s letter of 14 March and the decision of
                                                the High Commission.</item>
                                            <label>g.</label>
                                            <item>The luncheon meeting at my home in Mehlem in June
                                                with trade union leaders including Von Hoff, August
                                                Schmidt and Grosse at which they again affirmed
                                                their acceptance of the termination of central
                                                selling but objected to the implication which they
                                                found in the terms of reference that there would be
                                                no permanent organization able to deal with problems
                                                as they arose. This meeting and a subsequent meeting
                                                between the Economic Advisers and representatives of
                                                the Federal Government resulted in making it clear
                                                that a permanent agency consistent with the terms of
                                                reference could be maintained. The terms of
                                                reference were thereupon, with certain other
                                                amendments accepted by the German government and
                                                adopted by the High Commission.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>3. I am advised by one of my representatives on the Committee
                                        that, in spite of all of the foregoing history, the Federal
                                        Government representatives on the Committee have, from the
                                        beginning of its work, adopted an attitude completely
                                        inconsistent with the Federal Government’s proposal of 14
                                        March, the decision of the High Commission, and the terms of
                                        reference of the Committee. <hi rend="italic">They have
                                            indeed gone so far as expressly to repudiate the Federal
                                            Government’s letter of 14 March</hi>, stating that they
                                        did not feel themselves bound by it since the trade unions
                                        and industrialists had not been consulted prior to its being
                                        sent. In this they of course have repudiated in addition the
                                        agreements of the Trade Union leadership itself, which gave
                                        rise to the very creation of the Committee. They have
                                        consistently stated that they could not be bound by the
                                        provisions of the terms of reference of the Committee
                                        forbidding the creation or maintenance of a centralized
                                        sales agency.</p>
                                    <p>4. In addition, I am advised that the <gloss target="#t_DGB1">DGB</gloss>, represented by Von Hoff and August
                                        Schmidt, contrary to its previous statements, joined with
                                        various special interest groups in vigorously pressing for
                                        the maintenance of a centralized sales agency.</p>
                                    <p>5. On their side, the Allied representatives have attempted
                                        in the Committee seriously to deal with the problems raised
                                        by the Germans and have worked out a proposal, initiated by
                                        the French, which I am advised the German representatives
                                        themselves say is within the terms of reference and is
                                        “workable”.</p>
                                    <pb facs="0176" n="134" xml:id="pg_134"/>
                                    <p>6. At the meeting of the Committee on Friday, August 17, the
                                        German representatives stated that they would submit a
                                        proposal on August 29, after consultation with the Federal
                                        Government. When asked whether this proposal would conform
                                        to the terms of reference of the Committee (i.e. would
                                        eliminate monopoly selling) they stated they did not
                                        know.</p>
                                    <p>7. On August 27, 1951, the German representatives presented
                                        to the Committee a plan calling for the substitution for the
                                            <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> of a single central
                                        sales agency for all Ruhr coal. The plan provided for an
                                        Advisory Committee composed of representatives of labor,
                                        industry and consumers.</p>
                                    <p>8. The submission by the Germans of this proposal is in
                                        conflict with the terms of reference and provokes an
                                        extremely critical situation. As you know, the French
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan
                                        delegation has consistently taken the position, which we
                                        believe to be correct, that the maintenance of a centralized
                                        sales organization dominating the market for Ruhr coal is
                                        completely inconsistent with the basic principles of the
                                            <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan. It
                                        was on the basis of the German recognition of this fact and
                                        the proposals of the Chancellor’s letter of March 14 in
                                        accordance therewith that the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan was initialed and signed.
                                        Within the past week my representatives have discussed the
                                        matter in Paris with <persName corresp="#p_MJ2">M.
                                            Monnet</persName> who reaffirmed in the clearest
                                        possible terms his position that there can be no <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan if there were
                                        to be a centralized sales agency for Ruhr coal. They also
                                        discussed the French proposal with technical experts in
                                        great detail and concluded that with certain minor
                                        modifications which will be proposed, it fully satisfies the
                                        legitimate concerns of the trade unions, a fact which is
                                        indeed recognized by the German delegates in pronouncing it
                                        “workable”.</p>
                                    <p>9. In view of the decision of the High Commission that
                                        central sales must be eliminated, and of the fact that such
                                        elimination is an essential condition of the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan and indeed was
                                        proposed by the German government in recognition of that
                                        fact, the present German proposal for its continuance would
                                        in effect amount to a repudiation of all that has been
                                        cooperatively accomplished within the last year. While, of
                                        course, such a proposal could not and would not prevent the
                                        High Commission from taking the necessary action, the
                                        position of the German Government vis-à-vis the High
                                        Commission and the <persName corresp="#p_SR1">Schuman</persName> Plan countries would be materially
                                        impaired and the opponents of cooperation in the unification
                                        of Europe would be tremendously strengthened by an action of
                                        the Federal Government which accords with the position taken
                                            <pb facs="0177" n="135" xml:id="pg_135"/> by the
                                        opposition but is wholly inconsistent with the entire
                                        direction of the previous governmental policy.<note n="3" xml:id="d67fn3">At the 75th meeting of the Council of
                                            the Allied High Commission for Germany on September 27,
                                            the Council noted that the report of the Committee on
                                            Coal Distribution Problems relating to the dissolution
                                            of the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> was overdue
                                            and instructed the Economics Committee to extend to not
                                            later than October 15 the date for the submission of the
                                            report and to extend to November 1 the date upon which
                                            the first steps would be taken in the liquidation of the
                                                <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> and the
                                            decentralization of the coal marketing organizations.
                                            The Economics Committee was also instructed to submit
                                            “at the appropriate time” the regulations required for
                                            the liquidation of the <gloss target="#t_DKV1">DKV</gloss> and the progressive elimination of the
                                            centralized sale of coal. The Council agreed that a
                                            letter should be forwarded to Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> informing him
                                            of the Council decisions. (Bonn Mission files, <persName corresp="#p_MJJ1">McCloy</persName> Project, lot
                                            311, D(51)1471)</note>
                                    </p>
                                </frus:attachment>
                            </div>
                            </body></text></TEI>