<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-10-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-10-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="134" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d134">
                        <head>134. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_VVP_1">Viron P.
                                Vaky</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d134fn1">Source: National Security Council, Nixon
                                Intelligence Files, Subject Files, Chile, 1970. Top Secret;
                                Sensitive; Eyes Only.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-10-05">October 5,
                                    1970</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>40 Committee Meeting—Chile—October 6, 1970</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Your meeting will review the Chilean situation.</p>
                        <p>The meeting should concentrate on <hi rend="italic">two general
                                issues:</hi></p>
                        <p>—Action prior to the October 24 runoff, and</p>
                        <p>—What policy we should follow for the long range; and on <hi rend="italic">one specific question:</hi></p>
                        <p>—<persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s suggestion that he come
                            to Washington.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">I.</hi> The General
                            Situation</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> has continued to
                            consolidate his position. On the political front, after an initial
                            rebuff by his coalition (<gloss target="#t_UP_1">UP</gloss>) of the
                                <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss>’s request for specific
                            guarantees, <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> quickly
                            reversed the <gloss target="#t_UP_1">UP</gloss> and offered to name a
                            committee to negotiate with the <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss> on
                            the drafting of specific constitutional guarantee they desire. This
                            offer was made on the eve of the <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss>
                            governing board meeting, and thereby cut the ground out from under the
                                anti-<persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> forces. The
                                <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss> meeting is still underway.</p>
                        <p>All observers agree that at best there will be a split in the <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss>, that there is no chance the <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss> will unify <hi rend="italic">against</hi>
                            <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>, and that <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is almost sure to get the 19
                            additional votes he needs from the <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss>
                            to assure his election. There is no evidence that the military are even
                            thinking about a coup. The latest report via the Argentine Foreign
                            Minister (see cable attached)<note n="2" xml:id="d134fn2">Attached but
                                not printed is telegram 2237 from USUN, October 3, relaying the
                                following message from the visiting Argentine Foreign Minister:
                                “President <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> had, as
                                forecast in earlier report, called in leaders of Chilean armed
                                forces and in effect invited them to take over before expiration his
                                term. They had, however, categorically refused, stating that they
                                are not equipped to govern the country and that an attempt to do so
                                would lead to widespread strikes and disturbances by miners and
                                other labor elements with which they would not wish to cope.”</note>
                            is that the military, in fact, declined to stage a coup.</p>
                        <p>Other scenarios which had been reported whereby some ministers would
                            resign, the President name a military cabinet, and new elections
                            convoked have not materialized.</p>
                        <pb facs="0373" n="330" xml:id="pg_330"/>
                        <p>Economic problems continue and there is some discontent. The Communist
                            Party is reportedly moving to consolidate its position in public media,
                            education and labor.</p>
                        <p>There is, in short, confusion, much apprehension, but no cohesive
                                anti-<persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> movement. On
                            the contrary, resignation or acceptance of <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> seems to be growing.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">II.</hi> Preventing <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s Accession to Power</p>
                        <p>Immediately after the September 5 election, <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> stated that our only chance was the “Rube
                            Goldberg” <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> reelection
                            gambit. By 19 September this gambit was dead. <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> argued in effect that now our
                            only chance lay in <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> inviting
                            the military to move, either directly or by a gambit of entering the
                            cabinet. By the end of September the cabinet gambit was clearly out, and
                            if the Argentine report is to be believed any military move is out.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> now argues that our only
                            chance is to create economic deterioration and this might stir up
                                <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>, the military or the
                            populace.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> has argued that only
                                <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> can pull off anything
                            and he is moving behind the scenes to do so. In alternate cables,
                            however, he decries <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>’s lack
                            of backbone. The fact of the matter is that <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> refuses to move or lead any action. <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> is grabbing at straws, but each
                            one breaks when he grabs it.</p>
                        <p>In my own view there is now no chance that anything will happen which we
                            can either stimulate or support to prevent <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s election October 24. Maybe if things had been
                            done differently over the past several months this would not be the
                            case, but <hi rend="italic">as of October 6</hi> I think we are kidding
                            ourselves to believe there are any more gambits that we can work. Not
                            even economic deterioration is likely to achieve such a dramatic
                            turn-around in less than three weeks. Economic pressure might make sense
                            from other points of view (see below) but not solely as a means of
                            preventing <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s
                            election.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Unless we are prepared to intervene overtly and
                                physically in Chile we had better start planning for an <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> election and how we deal
                                with that situation.</hi></p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">III.</hi> Coping with an
                                <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> Government</p>
                        <p>In my view there is <hi rend="italic">some</hi> chance that within the
                            first year of his administration an <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> government could be brought to collapse or that
                            a Chilean inspired movement could overthrow him. Apart from that, I
                            think that there is at least a very good chance that an <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> government could be
                            effectively hampered, and that we could effectively limit the impact of
                            his government on the rest of the hemisphere.</p>
                        <p>But to do anything means we should have agreement as to concept,
                            objectives, strategy and a carefully orchestrated game plan. We <pb facs="0374" n="331" xml:id="pg_331"/> have none of these things now.
                            We are improvising. There is no agreement as to our fundamental
                            perception of <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>—do we
                            accommodate, oppose, or ignore? Do we let him set the pace or do we?</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s game plan will be to
                            claim legitimacy and respectability, to avoid prematurely coalescing
                            opposition to him, to reassure those concerned so that he can fragment
                            his opposition and then slice the salami bit by bit as he is able to.
                            Our game plan should be to frustrate that. We should strengthen
                            opposition, seek to coalesce it and inhibit <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s internal capacity to effect his program, and
                            place pressures on him so that he either fails or out of frustration
                            steps up his drive to a Marxist state prematurely. Opposition and
                            opportunities may then well arise which could be exploited to overthrow
                            him; or else he will fail.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, we should begin to provide some leadership to the rest of the
                            hemisphere to organize them against his tactics in the <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss> and to limit his influence elsewhere—a
                            diplomatic cordon sanitaire.</p>
                        <p>A game plan might be devised along the following lines:</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">1.</hi> Covertly.</p>
                        <p>Bank-roll <gloss target="#t_PDC_1">PDC</gloss>/Radical opposition in the
                            congress so that they can oppose his programs; bank-roll opposition
                            media so <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> cannot control
                            the press; build up assets in labor and the military both to get
                            information and to use if the opportunity arises; black operation to
                            split Socialists from Communists.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">2.</hi> Economic.</p>
                        <p>Cut aid; use economic pressure to discourage further investment and
                            assistance by international agencies. Miscellaneous measures to put
                            pressure on him—copper marketing.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">3.</hi> Diplomatic.</p>
                        <p>Cold but correct on the surface toward <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> so we do not give him an excuse to escape our
                            pressures.</p>
                        <p>Make clear quietly we do not accept <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> or his policy—he has to prove acceptability not
                            prove his unacceptability.</p>
                        <p>Wind down our bilateral programs.</p>
                        <p>Initiate immediate consultations with key states—Argentina, Brazil,
                            Colombia, Mexico, Venezuela—to build a de facto entente and to make
                            known our concerns; seek concerted action to oppose any Chilean move to
                            wreck <gloss target="#t_OAS_1">OAS</gloss>, recognize Cuba, or establish
                            a third force in Latin America opposed to us.</p>
                        <p>But we must recognize that we cannot energize the hemisphere to support
                            us without some evidence that it is in their interest to do so. We may
                            thus have to consider increased military and economic aid and <pb facs="0375" n="332" xml:id="pg_332"/> special trade treatment. We
                            cannot with one hand ask for their support and with the other hit them
                            where it hurts—as we are threatening to do now in prohibiting Argentine
                            meat imports and taxing Brazilian soluble coffee.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">In my view we need a policy decision on NSSM-97 and a
                                controlled implementation of that decision.</hi></p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital"><hi rend="roman">IV.</hi>
                            <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s Return.</p>
                        <p>In his October 1 <gloss target="#t_sitrep_1">Sitrep</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> suggests that time has come to
                            travel to Washington to participate in meetings to set our policy and
                            tactics. He proposes to meet with policy makers, to speak off the record
                            to key congressional and senatorial groups and editors.<note n="3" xml:id="d134fn3"><ref target="#d131">Document 131</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">My own view is that he ought to stay in Chile for a
                                while longer until we have our own ducks in a row at least.</hi> I
                            doubt that his lobbying all around in his “unguided-missile” way is
                            likely to be helpful right now.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>