<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-07-02T18:21:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-07-02T18:21:00-05:00" n="42" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d42">
                        <head>42. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in Chile<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d42fn1">Source: Department of State,
                                Bureau of Intelligence and Research, <gloss target="#t_INRIL_1">INR/IL</gloss> Historical Files, Chile Chronology 1970. Secret;
                                Roger Channel. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_CJH_1">Crimmins</persName>; approved by <persName corresp="#p_CWR_1">Coerr</persName>. A stamped notation on the first page reads:
                                “Special Handling.”</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-07-02T23:21:00+00:00">July
                                    2, 1970, 2321Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>106100. For <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> from <persName corresp="#p_MCA_1">Meyer</persName>. Analysis Note: In accordance
                            with arrangement made by Mr. W. Deary of <gloss target="#t_INR_1">INR</gloss> with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ETLJ_1">T.
                                Eliot</persName> of S/S on July 2, 1970 give all copies of this
                            telegram to <gloss target="#t_INRDDC_1">INR/DDC</gloss>, on July 3,
                            1970. The duty officer in <gloss target="#t_INRDDC_1">INR/DDC</gloss>
                            (R. Berg) will give a copy to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ETLJ_1">Eliot</persName>. Thank You, A.E. Wellons, <gloss target="#t_INRDDC_1">INR/DDC</gloss> on behalf of Amb. <persName corresp="#p_CWR_1">W. Coerr</persName>.</p>
                        <p>1. So that you will have full background, I want you to know that we in
                                <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>, and the Dept as a whole,
                            recommended against approval of both Phase 1 and Phase 2 of your
                            proposal for political action.<note n="2" xml:id="d42fn2">For <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s proposal, see <ref target="#d35">Documents 35</ref> and <ref target="#d39">39</ref>. In a memorandum to U. <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Alexis
                                    Johnson</persName>, June 22, <persName corresp="#p_CWR_1">Coerr</persName> presented both <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s arguments and his own arguments against
                                political action in Chile. “Exposure would have highly negative
                                effects on US interests in Chile,” he explained, “where
                                sensitivities to charges of <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>
                                intervention are already aroused.” In an addendum to the memorandum,
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CWR_1">Coerr</persName> added: “4:45 PM,
                                June 22, 1970—<persName corresp="#p_MCA_1">Meyer</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJH_1">Crimmins</persName> of <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss> joined DDC briefing of <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName> said we had been cutting
                                down on this type of U.S. activity and he had considerable concern
                                over Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s
                                proposal. He asked <persName corresp="#p_MCA_1">Meyer</persName> and
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJH_1">Crimmins</persName> if they wished
                                to defend it to him, and they said NO. Unanimous agreement against
                                Phase B. Meyer didn’t like Phase A either, because he thought it
                                would be too noticeable. General, although not definitive,
                                opposition to Phase A.” (Department of State, Bureau of Intelligence
                                and Research, <gloss target="#t_INRIL_1">INR/IL</gloss> Historical
                                Files, Chile Chronology 1970) For the subsequent decision by the 40
                                Committee on June 27, see <ref target="#d41">Document
                                41</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>2. Among other considerations, we gave more weight than you did to the
                            exposure potential and less weight to the protective attractiveness of
                            being able to say we “had done something.” We also were influenced by
                            the fact that we will be doing something which Chileans, who have ample
                            resources and a great stake in the outcome, should themselves be doing.
                            We also took account in this complex equation of the uncertain
                            effectiveness of the effort; the probability that, from the standpoint
                            of our interests in Chile, all three candidates would be negative sooner
                            or later; and the certainty that exposure would destroy any prospect of
                            mitigating <persName corresp="#p_TRR_1">Tomic</persName> or <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> post-election attitudes. In
                            brief, we believed that the potential gains were outweighed by the
                            potential costs.</p>
                        <p>3. Although our negative recommendation covered both phases, we had—and
                            have—particularly strong concerns about Phase 2. I want to reiterate the
                            point at the end of the earlier message through <gloss target="#t_CAS_1">CAS</gloss> channels.<note n="3" xml:id="d42fn3">Not found.</note>
                            Unless and until Phase 2 is authorized, no one in the Em<pb facs="0155" n="112" xml:id="pg_112"/>bassy should deal with anyone outside the
                            Embassy, including <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>, on any
                            aspect of Phase 2. This prohibition encompasses the “setting up” or
                            “conditioning” of anyone, including <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>, for an eventual role in carrying out Phase 2. The
                            Phase 2 proposal is just too explosive for any risks to be taken at this
                            time.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_JUA_1"><persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>