<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>48. Telegram From the Embassy in Chile to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">48</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-08-04T16:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-08-04T16:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">military
                        intervention</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recRWGq3CSOaqCrgp" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Disaster</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-08-04T16:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-08-04T16:00:00-05:00" n="48"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d48">
                <head>48. Telegram From the Embassy in Chile to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d48fn1">Source: Department of State, Bureau of
                        Intelligence and Research, <gloss target="#t_INRIL_1">INR/IL</gloss>
                        Historical Files, Chile Chronology 1970. Secret; Priority; Roger Channel. A
                        stamped notation on the first page reads: “Special Handling.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Santiago</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-08-04T21:00:00+00:00">August 4, 1970,
                        2100Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2979. For Asst Secy <persName corresp="#p_MCA_1">Meyer</persName> from <persName
                        corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>.</p>
                <p>1. Before addressing myself in other channels to critical questions in <gloss
                        target="#t_NSSM_1">NSSM</gloss> contingency paper<note n="2" xml:id="d48fn2"
                        >See <ref target="#d46">Document 46</ref> and <ref target="#d46fn2">footnote
                            2</ref> thereto.</note> (on which I am awaiting cable per my Washington
                    conversations last week) and to phase two possibilities, I must confess my
                    conviction that such cerebrating is largely meaningless because of the
                    restrictions the Department has imposed. Perhaps I am interpreting your
                    guidelines too stringently and the purpose of this message is to get some
                    clearer sense of what is tolerable and what is not.</p>
                <p>2. The central figure between Sept 4th and Oct 24th will be <persName
                        corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>. By direction or indirection he can
                    exercise very significant and perhaps decisive influence over his party, over
                    the military, and over public opinion. The manner in which he chooses to affect
                    these crucial sectors is central to the most basic if unstated question of the
                    contingency paper—how to stop <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>
                    from becoming or remaining President. And that is, of course, what Phase Two is
                    all about.</p>
                <p>3. The injunction is: “no one in the Embassy should deal with anyone outside the
                    Embassy including <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> on any aspect of
                    Phase Two.” This prohibition encompasses the “setting up” or “conditioning” of
                    anyone including <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> for an eventual
                    role in carrying out Phase Two.</p>
                <p>4. We have adhered scrupulously to this prohibition. You will have noted, I am
                    sure, Santiago 2881,<note n="3" xml:id="d48fn3">Not found.</note>
                    <gloss target="#t_para_1">para</gloss> 5 which reports my total rejection to the
                    attempt by <persName corresp="#p_PZE_1">Perez Zujovic</persName> to draw me into
                    a discussion of possible military intervention of some kind. I have taken other
                    (reported) actions to keep the US in the public posture of treating all
                    candidates even-handedly. Thus far US media in its totality and the Chilean
                    media with the expected exception of the Marxists-Leninists have kept us out of
                    the campaign and even the Allendistas are focusing on US companies rather than
                    the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>.</p>
                <p>5. But the fact remains that there is no rpt no way that I can realistically
                    address myself to Phase Two or to contingencies without <pb facs="0172" n="129"
                        xml:id="pg_129"/> knowing <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>’s
                    thinking. There is no practical way of gaining essential insights by playing the
                    role of an innocent observer. Politics, said Lord Cecil, are impossible to
                    follow unless you are in constant touch with all their developments. It is to
                    fly in the face of this self-evident dictum to eliminate the most knowledgeable
                    by far politician in the country and the man who holds all the decisive
                    levers.</p>
                <p>6. I am in full accord with your concerns about the manifold dangers of exposure
                    to the United States. I can only assure you that I would not run risks that
                    would jeopardize the US; I can only cite as evidence my performance of the past
                    eight years as Chief of Mission to support that general assurance. In dealing
                    with the Anaconda negotiations last year, which were not quite as “explosive” as
                    this issue, my critical decision came when the direct talks between <gloss
                        target="#t_GOC_1">GOC</gloss> and company were heading for breakdown and
                    public confrontation. At that point I went to <persName corresp="#p_FME_1"
                        >Frei</persName>. I did not rpt not go to seek to negotiate with him;
                    rather, it was to get his appreciation of the situation including what role he
                    would prefer I play and with whom.<note n="4" xml:id="d48fn4">See <ref
                            target="#d9">Document 9</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>7. I am not suggesting an analogous scenario. But I am emphasizing that paper
                    exercises have no validity unless they are based on the real world. To run
                    through hypothetical contingencies without know-ing the true intentions of the
                    controlling figure is not only intellectually dishonest but it courts real
                    disaster in that it raises the possibility of Washington decisions based on the
                    logic of what should be as distinct from what is.</p>
                <p>8. It may be suggested that we have other instruments for assessing the
                    situation. My experience of the past three years leads me to an opposite
                    conclusion. As a consummate politician <persName corresp="#p_FME_1"
                        >Frei</persName> convinces every visitor to his office that he agrees with
                    them which is one reason he is so extraordinarily popular now. And the
                    quasi-totality of Chilean military and politicians, with the notable exception
                    of the Communists, have a political perception level that is so mediocre that
                    only fools would tread on their projections of <persName corresp="#p_FME_1"
                        >Frei</persName>’s intentions. Churchill said that “true genius resides in
                    the capacity for evaluation of uncertain, hazardous and conflicting
                    information.” I would have to aspire to far more than genius to evaluate and to
                    recommend while isolating myself from the most essential information and to
                    offer appreciations uniquely based on the most hazardous of information.</p>
                <p>9. It will again be suggested that I am an “activist” who proposes action for the
                    sake of action. Let me dispose of this kind of type-casting in which the Dept
                    invariably indulges and which is at the root of the troubles flushed out in some
                    of the recent task forces. The report I did <pb facs="0173" n="130"
                        xml:id="pg_130"/> on Africa converted US policy from activism to
                        restraint;<note n="5" xml:id="d48fn5">For <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1"
                            >Korry</persName>’s report on Africa, see <ref
                            target="frus1964-68v24#d215">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1964–1968, vol. XXIV, Africa,
                            Document 215</ref>.</note> the low profile arguments I made to the
                    previous administration from here and which I have executed here are the
                    antithesis of activism;<note n="6" xml:id="d48fn6">For <persName
                            corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s reports on Chile to the <persName
                            corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName> administration, see <ref
                            target="frus1964-68v31">ibid., vol. XXXI, South and Central America;
                            Mexico</ref>.</note> the paper I did for UnderSec <persName
                        corresp="#p_REL_1">Richardson</persName> on the future relationships of the
                    US with the LDCs was criticized for its retreat from helter-skelter
                        activism;<note n="7" xml:id="d48fn7">See <ref target="frus1969-76v04#d124"
                            >ibid., 1969–1976, vol. IV, Foreign Assistance, International
                            Development, Trade Policies, 1969–1972, Document 124</ref>.</note> the
                    recommendations I have been discussing for the sharp reduction in official US
                    presence here is being opposed by bureaucrats who want to be active in
                    everything. Neither low profile nor the careful matching of real US interests to
                    US resource availability was intended to be passivism. A Chief of Mission should
                    bide his time and his resources for those rare occasions when US interest is
                    very definitely at stake. I believed and I believe that the election of
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is very possible and that it
                    will have tremendous impact on US interests in Latin America and elsewhere; I
                    believed that the highest levels of the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                    would also come to that conclusion; I believed and I believe that the <gloss
                        target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> did not rpt not have to become involved in any
                    great effort to elect another candidate and we have not. Therefore I do not rpt
                    not see any conflict between Phase One or Phase Two and my comments on <persName
                        corresp="#p_PJ_1">Parkinson</persName>’s pitch to you.<note n="8"
                        xml:id="d48fn8">See <ref target="#d32">Document 32</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>10. A final word about “conditioning”. For me that word has only one meaning
                    insofar as <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> and the present problem
                    is concerned. It was and is to make <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>
                    feel that he has an awareness of history, that he consider most carefully the
                    judgement of history if Chile were to lose its freedom for a long stretch.
                    Obviously a President of his stature, of his acuity and of his devotion to
                    democracy, will consider history’s judgments without prodding. But the pressures
                    to accept the democratic decision of an <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName> Presidency are no less strong than the pressures to
                    prevent Chile’s conversion into another Cuba. As the US Ambassador I happen to
                    be one of the few people with whom he can discuss such questions dispassionately
                    and whose responses he considers very carefully. But it has to be a discussion
                    not a deadpan interview in which I seek information and give nothing. I would
                    guess that he is puzzled by our passivity; I would guess too that it is
                    weakening his never-strong capacity for action; I would also hazard the
                    incidental judgement that the US aloofness is serving to encourage <persName
                        corresp="#p_VSG_1">Valdes</persName> in his Cuba policy for it reinforces
                    the feeling that the US no longer gives a damn what happens in Chile. Now there
                    are safe ways of transmitting to <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> my
                    interest. <pb facs="0174" n="131" xml:id="pg_131"/> And that is what I had in
                    mind when I talked on this channel of the question of confidence.<note n="9"
                        xml:id="d48fn9">See <ref target="#d43">Document 43</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>11. I have indulged in frankness and wordiness because I want you to understand
                    the problems we have in responding to the <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>
                    and to the Phase Two requirements. I did not wish to refer in other channels to
                    the gutting nature of your inhibitions without checking back with you first.
                    Hence I seek your counsel and request your approval to permit me and me alone
                    (while all your ground-rules would continue to apply to all others in this
                    Mission) to try to determine directly from <persName corresp="#p_FME_1"
                        >Frei</persName> what are his real intentions. Because I shall, of course,
                    wish to make such soundings in the most subtle manner possible, there may be
                    indirect methods of communications between us in the interim. I wish to
                    reiterate that there will be no rpt no risks of any kind since there will be no
                    rpt no suggestions of any kind offered by me without further consultation with
                    you. The purposes will be to elicit information via a logical and justifiable
                    expression of interest in Chile’s future.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_KEM_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
