<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>66. Memorandum From Viron P. Vaky of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v21</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d66</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">66</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recWaheUl1ZaxSs0G" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026421"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil war</term>
                    <term ref="recDxa7szVhIjbJXw" type="compound-subject" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Where we were</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-09-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-09-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="66"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d66">
                <head>66. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_VVP_1">Viron P. Vaky</persName> of
                    the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d66fn1">Source: National Security Council, Nixon
                        Intelligence Files, Subject Files, Chile, 1970. Secret; Sensitive.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-09-07">September 7, 1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>40 Committee Meeting, September 8—Chile</item>
                </list>
                <p>A. <hi rend="italic">The purpose of tomorrow’s meeting on Chile is to:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. Review the factual situation and its implications. (<gloss target="#t_CIA_1"
                        >CIA</gloss> is prepared to brief, and a wrap-up is attached at Tab 2.<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d66fn2">Attached but not printed is the 9-page <gloss
                            target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> Intelligence Memorandum 1461/70,
                        “Situation Following the Chilean Presidential Election,” dated September 7.
                        The full text of the memorandum is published as <ref
                            target="frus1969-76ve16#d18">Document 18 in <hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. E–16, Documents on Chile,
                            1969–1973</ref>.</note> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1"
                        >Korry</persName> has just sent in a long cable summarizing the current
                    situation. This is also worth reading and is at Tab 3).<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d66fn3">
                        <ref target="#d65">Document 65</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. Determine whether Phase 2 operations such as that which had been suggested
                    earlier to influence the congressional run-off election are realistic now.</p>
                <p>3. Determine whether there is any prospect for Chilean military action to keep
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> from taking power.</p>
                <p>4. Determine what action plan we should now follow and what further analyses we
                    need to undertake.</p>
                <p>B. <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s latest views and
                        information</hi> (Tab 3) pose some specific questions within the above major
                    categories.</p>
                <pb facs="0232" n="189" xml:id="pg_189"/>
                <p>1. He indicates Alessandri supporters may be prepared to contest the run-off and
                    not concede defeat. He indicates at one point (1–D) that <persName
                        corresp="#p_FMA_1">Frei</persName> may also move to contest the run-off, but
                    later bewails <persName corresp="#p_FMA_1">Frei</persName>’s hand-wringing.<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d66fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> wrote, “Prevent
                        recognition by Europeans,” in the left margin.</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> indicates that the high military
                    officers are concerned and he relates a specific proposal being kicked around by
                    the military commanders to foster an Alessandri–Christian Democrat deal to elect
                    Alessandri and then have Alessandri resign and in 60 days have <persName
                        corresp="#p_FMA_1">Frei</persName> elected.</p>
                <p>3. One military officer tried this out on <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1"
                        >Korry</persName>, and while he did not respond specifically he did in
                    effect give some encouragement to the military to think about “their
                    responsibilities” to find a correct and democratic solution. (See paragraph K
                    tab 3)</p>
                <p>4. <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> in effect is saying he is trying
                    to keep everything flexible and options open and to encourage Chileans who are
                    disposed to contest <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s victory to
                    stay firm. However, he holds no particular hope that these elements will be able
                    successfully to contest the run-off. He does seem to be leaning more and more to
                    encouragement and moral support of the military.</p>
                <p>5. He asks for a few specific things:</p>
                <p>a. that the Department lobby in other countries to keep them from taking action
                    implying that <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is already
                    President. (I do not see how we can do that without tipping our hand that we,
                    the US, would contest the election.)</p>
                <p>b. we provide to <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> suggestions of
                    action that could keep the Communists from consolidating the psychological sense
                    of victory.</p>
                <p>c. we show support of the military by restoring some training slots and extending
                    our Army Attaché for another nine months since he enjoys their confidence.</p>
                <p>d. he requests a [<hi rend="italic">dollar amount not declassified</hi>]
                    contingency fund “set aside” in case it is needed to support Phase 2 kind of
                    action.</p>
                <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s cable at Tab 3 is a little
                    rambling and inconsistent. He is still trying to think of something but the
                    information does not in my view resolve the questions very satisfactorily. In
                    particular, he may be operating personally with a little more commitment and
                    encouragement to the military and/or other elements than he describes in the
                    cable.</p>
                <p>C. <hi rend="italic">The conclusions we are likely to arrive at</hi> are:</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">It continues to appear very doubtful that <persName
                            corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> can be denied the congressional
                        election victory within the normal electoral framework.</hi> The Chris<pb
                        facs="0233" n="190" xml:id="pg_190"/>tian Democrats hold the key and
                        <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> indicates that they are
                    “decomposing” and that <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> is far from
                    firm. On the other hand, the indication that <persName corresp="#p_FME_1"
                        >Frei</persName> is examining the constitutional processes by which
                        <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s victory can be over turned
                    is a contradictory sign that <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> does
                    not explain. In balance, it seems to me that the chances of a coordinated
                    Christian Democrat–Alessandri effort to over turn <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName>’s election are very slim, and are hardly promotable by
                    us alone.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">It is equally dubious that the Chilean military can mount
                        any viable action against <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1"
                        >Allende</persName>.</hi> The plan given to <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1"
                        >Korry</persName> is premised on Christian Democratic cooperation but it is
                    not clear that this is realistic. There is more indication from <persName
                        corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s cable, however, of military
                    dissatisfaction than had been indicated earlier. There is still serious doubt,
                    however, that we could stimulate any such action that would not result in
                    violence, civil war, and perhaps destruction of the military as an
                    institution.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">We need to know a lot more than we do about how <persName
                            corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_EEA_1"
                            >Edwards</persName>, Alessandri and other key anti-<persName
                            corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> elements see the situation</hi>
                    and what they propose to do. Hence it is important to get the Embassy [<hi
                        rend="italic">less than 1 line not declassified</hi>] to contact them for
                    their views. (There may be some resistance from State on the grounds that <hi
                        rend="italic">we</hi> should not <hi rend="italic">push</hi> them into
                    courses of action they are not prepared to take themselves. Nevertheless, I
                    think that contact to determine their views is indispensable for us to make good
                    judgments. I also think that we can do that without triggering something that
                    won’t fly.)</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">We shall have to come to some definitive conclusions soon as
                        to the feasibility of supporting either political action to affect the
                        congressional election or a military effort.</hi> My own view is that
                    neither is very realistic or worth the risk, but we will probably have to ask
                    the Agency and State to come up with a reasonable assessment very soon.</p>
                <p>5. <hi rend="italic">We should now also begin thinking in terms of how to cope
                        with an <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> government and how
                        to limit and contain the adverse impact of such a government’s policy. This
                        means early consideration of NSSM–97.</hi>
                    <note n="5" xml:id="d66fn5">See <ref target="#d46">Documents 46</ref> and <ref
                            target="#d52">52</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>D. <hi rend="italic">I believe that we should end up with the following
                        decisions:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. Authorize the Embassy to probe the views of key elements in Chile,
                    particularly <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_EEA_1">Edwards</persName> and report these as soon as
                    possible;</p>
                <p>2. Task <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>/State to come up with final
                    recommendations on what political action to take, if any, regarding the run-off
                    and/or encouragement of military, and to do this no later than September 15.</p>
                <p>3. Review these recommendations as soon as possible thereafter;</p>
                <pb facs="0234" n="191" xml:id="pg_191"/>
                <p>4. Hold a Special Review Group consideration of NSSM–97 as soon as we have
                    reached final conclusions on point 3.</p>
                <p>E. <hi rend="italic">Attached</hi> are:</p>
                <p>1. Talking Points.</p>
                <p>2. <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> intelligence summary (which you may wish
                    to skim fairly carefully.)</p>
                <p>3. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s cable of September
                    7.</p>
                <p>4. Background on previous 40 Committee meetings on this subject.<note n="6"
                        xml:id="d66fn6">Background information is not attached was and not found,
                        but see <ref target="#d49">Document 49</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>5. I have not added the contingency paper <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>
                    prepared prior to the election. Because these ideas were designed essentially
                    for an Alessandri popular vote victory, they are not very meaningful now.<note
                        n="7" xml:id="d66fn7">See <ref target="frus1969-76ve16#d16">Document 16, <hi
                                rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, vol. E–16,
                            Documents on Chile, 1969–1973</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                        <note n="8" xml:id="d66fn8">Secret; Sensitive.</note>
                    </note>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                                ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content-and-sibling-dates"
                                calendar="gregorian" when="1970-09-07">undated</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <gloss target="#t_HAK_1">HAK</gloss> TALKING POINTS—CHILE</p>
                    <p>1. All of you should have received a <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss>
                        wrap-up of the situation in Chile as it looks after Friday’s election. I
                        would like to ask <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> to summarize the
                        situation and to brief us on Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1"
                            >Korry</persName>’s latest views.</p>
                    <p>2. I think the first point to focus on is whether there is any chance for
                        political persuasion or action to influence the Chilean congress to elect
                        runner-up Alessandri on October 24. (We expect the consensus to be that
                        there is little realistic chance; since the Christian Democrats are
                        indispensable to any vote to elect Alessandri, <persName corresp="#p_FME_1"
                            >Frei</persName>’s all out effort is indispensable. Even with it, it is
                        not certain anything would be effective; without it it would be
                        impossible.)</p>
                    <p>3. What are the prospects that the Chilean military will take some action to
                        keep <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> out of the presidency?
                        (We expect the consensus to be that such prospects are poor. <persName
                            corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> indicates they are thinking about
                        something but it is a tenuous plan, also dependent on the Christian
                        Democrats whom <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> thinks are
                        falling apart. No one can demonstrate any reasonable prospect which we can
                        support and since an attempt which fails may enable <persName
                            corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> to destroy the military institu<pb
                            facs="0235" n="192" xml:id="pg_192"/>tion in one move and thus eliminate
                        the greatest restraint on him; we ought to be leery about whether we should
                        encourage this kind of action—at least now).</p>
                    <p>4. The discussion shows that judgments about what is likely to happen and
                        what we ought to do cannot be made very confidently without more information
                        as to what the views and intentions of people like <persName
                            corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName>, Alessandri, <persName
                            corresp="#p_EEA_1">Augustin Edwards</persName> are. Ambassador <persName
                            corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> has indicated that he has begun to
                        make contact to find out. I take it there is no objection in this regard.
                        (State may have some qualms, but I think our people must be able to talk
                        frankly with the Chileans; there is no need to talk in terms of organizing
                        an operation, just to gain political intelligence.)</p>
                    <p>5. What about <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s specific
                        requests contained in his latest cable? (See B–5 in your memo. I do not
                        believe you will want to discuss these exhaustively, and I suggest that they
                        be rolled in and answered in the definitive recommendations you request in
                        the next point.)</p>
                    <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s latest cable states he is
                        trying to keep all options open. But his assessment is not hopeful. He gives
                        us little guide for any judgment as to whether any political action program
                        by us aimed at keeping <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> out
                        of power has any realistic chance. I must confess that we seem to be where
                        we were several weeks ago. The time has come to decide whether there is
                        anything we can do or whether we should move to planning for an <persName
                            corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> government so as to “limit the
                        damage.”</p>
                    <p>7. I propose that after a prompt reading of the various key elements we
                        talked about earlier, <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> and State present
                        their definitive recommendations to this Committee as to whether there is
                        anything further to pursue in this sense. If not we should shift to
                        considering NSSM–97 and our long range strategy.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
