<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-09-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-09-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="70" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d70">
                        <head>70. Memorandum for the Record<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d70fn1">Source: National Security Council, Nixon Intelligence Files,
                                Subject Files, Chile 1970. Secret; Eyes Only. Drafted on September
                                9. Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_MJN_1">Mitchell</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_PD_1">Packard</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MTH_1">Moorer</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName>. Attached to the Department of State’s copy of
                                these minutes is a note from Jim Gardner (<gloss target="#t_INRDDC_1">INR/DDC</gloss>) to <persName corresp="#p_MCA_1">Meyer</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_CJH_1">Crimmins</persName>. <persName corresp="#p_GJR_1">Gardner</persName> noted, “<persName corresp="#p_MW_1">Bill McAfee</persName>, who was there, feels
                                that minutes much understate <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName>’ pessimism about influencing Congressional
                                vote, and that they overstate passivity of State representatives in
                                face of prospects of an <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> government. We can ask that minutes, insofar
                                as they relate to State position, be corrected if you wish.”
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJH_1">Crimmins</persName> wrote on the
                                note, “This is accurate, but does not reflect the fine line as to
                                ‘whose civil war.’ Alex did not make clear the distinction between a
                                100% Chilean military action and one inspired by or based upon U.S.
                                support. I think the minutes could reflect this difference.”
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                                    Chile–<gloss target="#t_ITT_1">ITT</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> 1963–1977, Lot 81D121, Documents
                                Requested by the Department of Justice, 1970–1977)</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-09-08">September 8,
                                    1970</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Minutes of the Meeting of the 40 Committee, 8 September
                                1970</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PRESENT</head>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName>, Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MJN_1">Mitchell</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PD_1">Packard</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName>, Admiral <persName corresp="#p_MTH_1">Moorer</persName>, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName></item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MCA_1">Charles A. Meyer</persName>, Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_VVP_1">Viron P. Vaky</persName>, Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MW_1">William McAfee</persName>, Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_KTH_1">Thomas Karamessines</persName>, and
                                Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BWV_1">William Broe</persName> were also
                                present.</item>
                        </list>
                        <pb facs="0243" n="200" xml:id="pg_200"/>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Chile</p>
                        <p>a. The Chairman opened the meeting with a reference to Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s excellent cable of 7
                            September 1970<note n="2" xml:id="d70fn2"><ref target="#d65">Document
                                    65</ref>.</note> and asked for an analysis of where prospects
                            now stand for taking any kind of action which might successfully
                            preclude <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> assuming the
                            presidency of Chile following his garnering of a plurality of the
                            popular vote in the elections on 4 September.</p>
                        <p>b. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BWV_1">Broe</persName> summarized the
                            situation and highlighted some of the points in Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName>’s cable. He noted that <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> is attempting to maintain
                            flexibility and that there is some, but not much, fluidity in the
                            situation. He pointed out that <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> is an essential cog to success in any action,
                            congressional or military, to frustrate an <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> take-over and that Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_KEM_1">Korry</persName> is very pessimistic about the
                            prospects of <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> doing much
                            more than deploring <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s
                            electoral victory. He concluded that it is still too early to decide on
                            a given course of action and suggested that the Embassy and <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> field elements be requested during the
                            next week to probe all possible aspects of feasible actions and forward
                            recommendations as to what might be done.</p>
                        <p>c. In the lively discussion which followed, there was general agreement
                            that more time to assess the situation was essential. It was also agreed
                            that there is now little likelihood of success in the previously
                            proposed operation to influence the 24 October congressional run-off
                            election against <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>.</p>
                        <p>d. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HRM_1">Helms</persName>, noting that
                            congressional action against <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> was not likely to succeed, offered his personal
                            observation that once <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is
                            in office it is predictable that the Chilean opposition to him will
                            disintegrate and collapse rapidly. He expressed the view that <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> will quickly neutralize the
                            military and police after which there will be no effective rallying
                            point for opposition against him. Without advocating it as a course of
                            action, he observed that a military <gloss target="#t_golpe_1">golpe</gloss> against <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> would have little chance of success unless
                            undertaken soon. He stated that even then there is no positive assurance
                            of success because of the apolitical history of the military in Chile
                            and the presence of <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>
                            supporters in various military elements.</p>
                        <p>e. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PD_1">Packard</persName> was also strongly
                            of the view that any effective military action to prevent <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> from assuming the presidency
                            would have to occur in the very near future. He expressed the hope that
                            the Chilean military leaders would undertake such action soon on their
                            own initiative.</p>
                        <p>f. Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_JUA_1">Johnson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_MCA_1">Meyer</persName> pointed out that if <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>’s election is frustrated by a
                            military take-over, there is a strong likelihood that his <pb facs="0244" n="201" xml:id="pg_201"/> supporters would take to the
                            streets and plunge the country into full-scale civil war. They felt that
                                <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> was possibly the
                            lesser of two evils. They suggested that <persName corresp="#p_FME_1">Frei</persName> should be strongly counseled to start immediately
                            building an effective political opposition for the future before
                            important individuals who would constitute that opposition might decide
                            to leave the country.</p>
                        <p>g. The Chairman and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MJN_1">Mitchell</persName>
                            expressed considerable skepticism that once <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName> is in the presidency there will be anyone
                            capable of organizing any real counterforce against him.</p>
                        <p>h. In accord with the agreement of those present, the Chairman directed
                            that the Embassy be immediately requested for a cold-blooded assessment
                            of:</p>
                        <p>(1) the pros and cons and problems and prospects involved should a
                            Chilean military coup be organized now with U.S. assistance, and</p>
                        <p>(2) the pros and cons and problems and prospects involved in organizing
                            an effective future Chilean opposition to <persName corresp="#p_AGS_1">Allende</persName>.</p>
                        <p>i. The Chairman stated that these assessments and recommendations should
                            be available in time for 40 Committee consideration in a meeting to be
                            convened on 14 September.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed corresp="#p_CFM_1"><persName corresp="#p_CFM_1">Frank M.
                                    Chapin</persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>