<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1953-08-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1953-08-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="269" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d269">
                        <head>269. Telegram From the Station in Iran [<hi rend="italic">text not
                                declassified</hi>]<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d269fn1">Source:
                                Central Intelligence Agency. Secret. Transcribed specifically for
                                the <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi> series from microfilm
                                in the Central Intelligence Agency that no longer exists. See
                                “Sources” chapter.</note></head>
                        <dateline><placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1953-08-16">August 16, 1953</date>.</dateline>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_TEHE_1">TEHE</gloss> 705. Foll is message Shah should
                            broadcast ad infinitum, by voice and recording. Suggest he be urged
                            quickest do so in name <persName corresp="#p_CWS_1">Churchill</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_EA_1">Eden</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_SL_1">Salisbury</persName>:</p>
                        <p>“Beloved people: In past 28 months Dr <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> has been given by me greatest support and
                            encouragement in hope he would serve nation but in all this time he has
                            created nothing but greatest poverty, disunity and chaos. Has also spent
                            best part time libeling patriots and statesmen who tried help Iran.</p>
                        <p>“Have sworn upon God and holy Koran preserve constitution but <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName>’s impertinence reached point
                            where he tramps on all our sacred ideals. He’s now endangered country in
                            name welfare country and is skillfully driving country to communism.
                            Finding it impossible endure his treacherous deeds I dismissed him and
                            appointed Zahedi form cabinet in order improve bad conditions. But
                                <persName corresp="#p_MM_1">Mossadeq</persName> with well known
                            tactics twisted facts and arrested my emissary and thus hit hardest blow
                            against constitution. Thus all army officers who have taken oath
                            allegiance to Shah and country must take action unite, in this darkest
                            period history, under banner <hi rend="italic">true</hi> nationalism and
                            put end rule of mentally sick man who has written new chapter in
                            despotism. Great God who has always protected dear country ours will
                            again rescue us.”<note n="2" xml:id="d269fn2">In telegram DIR 16048,
                                August 16, the <gloss target="#t_CIA_1">CIA</gloss> reported that
                                the Department of State had no objection to British efforts to get
                                the Shah to broadcast such a message. (Ibid.)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>