<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>93. Telegram From the Embassy in Iran to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1951-54Iran</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">93</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1952-07-21T09:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1952-07-21T09:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMHJD4XLL5GtXeu" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="general">Emissary</term>
                    <term ref="recHX2dmMKjTPvh66" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="general" subject="public-diplomacy" lcsh-match="no_match">Emissary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1952-07-21T09:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1952-07-21T09:30:00-05:00" n="93"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d93">
                <head>93. Telegram From the Embassy in Iran to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d93fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Files 1950–1954, 788.13/7–2152.
                        Secret; <gloss target="#t_NIACT_1">NIACT</gloss>. Repeated to London.
                        Received at 12:47 p.m.</note>
                </head>
                <dateline>
                    <placeName>Tehran</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                        when="1952-07-21T18:00:00+03:30">July 21, 1952, 6 p.m</date>.</dateline>
                <p>309. 1. Emissary <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> called on me at 3
                    o’clock this afternoon (<gloss target="#t_Embtel_1">Embtel</gloss> 308, <gloss
                        target="#t_rptd_1">rptd</gloss> London 99).<note n="2" xml:id="d93fn2">
                        <ref target="#d92">Document 92</ref>.</note> He said that Shah had sent msg
                    to <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> thru one of <persName
                        corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName>’s lieutenants shortly before noon
                    suggesting that <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> pursue following
                    course; (a) set up cabinet at once; (b) obtain <gloss target="#t_finan_1"
                        >finan</gloss> aid from <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>; and (c) endeavor
                    to administer country with firmness on constitutional basis. Shah promised that
                    if it <gloss target="#t_shld_1">shld</gloss> become clear that new Cabinet
                        <gloss target="#t_cld_1">cld</gloss> not (<gloss target="#t_rpt_1"
                        >rpt</gloss> not) function in present situation and if members new Cabinet
                        <gloss target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> join in recommending that <pb
                        facs="0321" n="284" xml:id="pg_284"/> Majlis be dissolved he <gloss
                        target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> give such recommendation sympathetic
                    consideration.</p>
                <p>2. According to my informant <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> was
                    disturbed at this msg. He told his advisers he <gloss target="#t_cld_1"
                        >cld</gloss> not (<gloss target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> not) believe that
                    Shah was serious. Shah must know that unless he <gloss target="#t_cld_1"
                        >cld</gloss> give convincing evidence that he had power and ability maintain
                    order and to govern country he <gloss target="#t_cld_1">cld</gloss> obtain no
                        (<gloss target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> no) <gloss target="#t_finan_1"
                        >finan</gloss> assistance from <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> or
                    elsewhere. Furthermore it was mockery to talk about any Cabinet attempting to
                    function in present conditions. <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName>,
                    therefore insisted that he immediately submit his formal resignation. His
                    advisers, however, begged him for good of Iran not (<gloss target="#t_rpt_1"
                        >rpt</gloss> not) be precipitous. They suggested that he ask for immediate
                    audience with Shah in order explain situation. <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1"
                        >Qavam</persName> finally yielded and asked for audience. It was not (<gloss
                        target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> not) until 2 o’clock that reply was received
                    from Shah that he <gloss target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> receive <persName
                        corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> at 5. In meantime <persName
                        corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> had learned that Shah was having
                    protracted conferences with reps of opposition. When it became clear to
                        <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> that his visit to Shah was
                    being postponed while <gloss target="#t_HIM_1">HIM</gloss> was having
                    discussions with those who shared responsibility for stirring up revolt against
                        <gloss target="#t_govt_1">govt</gloss> he again insisted on submitting
                    resignation. His advisers however, begged him to wait until they <gloss
                        target="#t_cld_1">cld</gloss> make appeal to me.</p>
                <p>2. Emissary of <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> asked me if I
                        <gloss target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> not (<gloss target="#t_rpt_1"
                        >rpt</gloss> not) be willing to try to see Shah before Shah received
                        <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> in order to impress on Shah
                    seriousness of situation and to persuade him before too late to give <persName
                        corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> necessary powers. I replied that I had
                    gone just as far as I properly <gloss target="#t_cld_1">cld</gloss> to impress
                    upon Shah seriousness of <gloss target="#t_ME_1">ME</gloss> situation and to
                    stress necessity for decisive action. I deemed it useless and unwise intervene
                    at this juncture. Emissary of <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName>
                    said that if <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> was told no (<gloss
                        target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> no) help coming from me he <gloss
                        target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> not (<gloss target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> not)
                    call on Shah but <gloss target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> instead send his
                    resignation. I suggested that emissary urge <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1"
                        >Qavam</persName> not (<gloss target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> not) to resign
                    until latter had seen Shah once more.</p>
                <p>3. I am beginning to believe that Shah has never been really anxious for
                        <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> to succeed; that he has
                    preferred <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> to fail if success
                    meant that <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName>
                    <gloss target="#t_shld_1">shld</gloss> have any considerable powers; and that
                    for some time he has been secretly negotiating with Natl Front leaders with idea
                    of agreeing upon successor to <persName corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> who
                        <gloss target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> be acceptable to them. Unless some
                    unexpected development occurs during next two hours strong possibility <persName
                        corresp="#p_QESA_1">Qavam</persName> will resign. Shah might however, try to
                    keep him on temporarily until he can complete arrangements for a successor. I am
                    afraid that Shah’s hesitations and his surreptitious dealings with various
                    opposing groups simultaneously are undermining his own prestige and may place
                    country in great danger. My refusal to go to Shah at this moment is not (<gloss
                        target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> not) based so much my desire not (<gloss
                        target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> not) to intervene in Iranian internal affairs
                    as upon my conviction that my visit <gloss target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> serve
                    no (<gloss target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> no) useful purpose; that I <pb
                        facs="0322" n="285" xml:id="pg_285"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_wld_1">wld</gloss> find Shah evasive and vague and not (<gloss
                        target="#t_rpt_1">rpt</gloss> not) responsive to appeals either to logic or
                    patriotism.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed corresp="#p_HLW_1">
                        <persName corresp="#p_HLW_1">Henderson</persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
