<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>10. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-10-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="rectjw2jgFLXmsufI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="recbm2CDfl6YlSCnq" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recPndXY465srEpkp" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Development loan</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85048256"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Funding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-10-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-10-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="10"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                <head>10. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>) to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d10fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 797,
                        Country Files, Latin America General, volume 2, September–October 1969.
                        Secret. Sent for action. Nixon initialed for approval on all recommendations
                        on October 7. Attached but not published are Tabs A through F. Tab A is a
                        June 13 memorandum of conversation; Tab B is an August 13 memorandum from
                        the Department of State to the President; Tab C is an August 18 memorandum
                        from Volcker to the President; Tab D is an August 20 memorandum from
                            <persName corresp="#p_HTL1">Hughes</persName> to the President; Tab E is
                        a July 10 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_KH1">Kearns</persName> to
                        Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>; and Tab F is a June
                        30 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_BJM1">Beggs</persName> to Secretary
                        Rogers. Attached but not published at Annex I is a paper titled,
                        “Alternative Financing Formulas.” In a December 8 memorandum to the
                        President, Kissinger requested his support for a bill in the House of
                        Representatives for funding to complete the Pan American highway. Nixon
                        initialed his approval on December 10. (Ibid., Box 798, Country Files, Latin
                        America General, volume 3, November 1969–May 1970)</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d10fn2">Kissinger discussed the 4 proposals
                        regarding U.S. negotiations on financing the cost of the Darien Gap portion
                        of the Pan American Highway. Nixon agreed to the 4 recommendations presented
                        by Kissinger and agreed to inform President <persName corresp="#p_LRC1"
                            >Lleras</persName> of Colombia of his intentions.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1969-10-02">October 2,
                            1969</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d10-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d10-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>Pan American Highway</item>
                </list>
                <p>During his State Visit to Washington last June, President Lleras of Colombia
                    asked for assistance in completing the Pan American Highway. You told President
                    Lleras of your great interest in completing the highway and asked Assistant
                    Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MCA1">Meyer</persName> to follow up on how the
                    US might provide assistance for this purpose (Memorandum of Conversation at Tab
                    A).</p>
                <p>This issue has been carefully reviewed within the Executive departments and we
                    now have the views and recommendations of the State Department (Tab B), Treasury
                    (Tab C), and Bureau of the Budget (Tab D), the Export-Import Bank (Tab E), and
                    the Department of Transportation (Tab F).</p>
                <p>The estimated cost of construction for the Darien Gap road is $150 million: $90
                    million for the Panamanian section, $60 million for the Colombian section. Under
                    the financing formula requested by Lleras, which the State Department
                    recommends, the US would provide grant aid for 2/3 of the construction costs, or
                    $100 million. This is the same formula which was used for the Central American
                    portion of the Highway.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">All of the agencies see serious drawbacks in proceeding now
                        with assistance for the Pan American Highway under any financing
                        formula</hi>. Their principal reservations are:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—the absence of an economic feasibility study which demonstrates that the
                        benefits of the project would exceed its costs.</item>
                    <item>—this large foreign project is an easy target for critics who are calling
                        for increased domestic spending, particularly at a time when domestic
                        federal construction is being cut back by 75%.</item>
                    <pb facs="d10-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d10-2"/>
                    <item>—the danger that Congress would offset any appropriation for the Pan
                        American Highway by cutting other priority projects in the Transportation
                        and/or <gloss target="#AID1">AID</gloss> budgets.</item>
                    <item>—probable adverse Congressional reaction to an exceptionally large amount
                        of aid for an unconstitutional military government in Panama.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Treasury and Budget Bureau recommend that you not
                        authorize construction financing until an economic feasibility study can be
                        completed</hi>, recognizing that such a study may well indicate that the
                    costs far exceed the benefits. The State Department notes that there are no
                    realistic counter-offers you could make to Colombia in the event you decide not
                    to proceed with this project now, but concludes that President Lleras would
                    understand the difficult Congressional problem particularly in light of the
                    positive action taken on additionally and proposed for modernization of his Air
                    Force.</p>
                <p>Should you wish, on the basis of foreign policy considerations and your
                    commitment to President Lleras, to proceed with assistance for completion of the
                    Pan American Highway, there are several alternative financing formulas. These
                    are spelled out in Appendix I. In summary,</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—State Department proposes 2/3 grant aid by the Bureau of Public Roads,
                        with the remaining 1/3 to be financed by the Export-Import Bank if
                        requested. The Department of Transportation and the Export-Import Bank have
                        reservations about this formula but would cooperate if you decide this is
                        necessary for important foreign policy reasons.</item>
                    <item>—Treasury proposes that the Bureau of Public Roads finance only the
                        foreign exchange costs of the project—about 50%—on a concessional loan
                        basis, the remaining 50% to be financed by Colombia and Panama.</item>
                    <item>—Budget Bureau proposes that AID provide development loan funds for this
                        project, with Colombia and Panama required to contribute a share based on
                        their ability to pay.</item>
                    <pb facs="d10-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d10-3"/>
                    <item>—Department of Transportation proposes a cost-sharing formula with the
                            <gloss target="#IDB1">IDB</gloss> and other Latin nations, under which
                        the US would provide a 1/4 share.</item>
                </list>
                <p>In a related request, President Lleras asked for a “modest amount” of assistance
                    for a proposed Choco Highway which he needs to “buy off” opponents of the route
                    now proposed for the Darien Gap road. State believes that we should not be
                    directly involved in this maneuver, and, therefore, recommends that we agree to
                    provide “modest” assistance for projects in the Choco region, but not for the
                    Choco Highway itself.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">My own view is that it would be desirable on foreign policy
                        grounds for the United States to assist in the completion of the Pan
                        American Highway</hi>. Announcement of your intention to help close the
                    Darien Gap would have a dramatic political impact in the hemisphere. Closing the
                    Gap would have historical significance in terms of the physical integration and
                    ultimate development of the hemisphere. Although the immediate cost/benefit
                    ratio may not be favorable, the potential economic and political effects which a
                    completed Pan American Highway will have by the end of the century cannot be
                    foreseen. Moreover, a decision to provide such assistance would meet the
                    commitment which President Lleras feels you gave him in his talks last June.</p>
                <p>If you decide to go forward, I believe the only way to get this project off the
                    ground within the next few years is for the United States to provide at least
                    two-thirds of the construction costs on a grant or concessional loan basis. The
                    50–50 formula proposed by Treasury is not financially feasible for either
                    Colombia or Panama.</p>
                <p>Congressional considerations will bear heavily on three questions: timing of a
                    legislative request, source of funding (BPR or AID), and form of assistance
                    (grant or loan). The agency memoranda do not offer an adequate assessment of the
                    Congressional outlook. Therefore, I would suggest that you ask <persName
                        corresp="#p_HB1">Bryce Harlow</persName> to undertake careful consultations
                    with the Congressional leadership. In the meantime, I would suggest that you
                    inform President Lleras that:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—you have decided to seek legislation to permit financing two-thirds of
                        the cost of the construction of the Darien Gap Highway on a concessional
                        loan or grant basis.</item>
                    <pb facs="d10-4" n="4" xml:id="pg_d10-4"/>
                    <item>—that Congressional and budgetary considerations must be reviewed before
                        you can determine when and in what form such legislation can be
                        requested.</item>
                    <item>—you are authorizing the State Department to enter into consultations with
                        the Governments of Panama and Colombia to confirm their willingness to
                        participate in the project on the basis of a 2/3–1/3 financing
                        arrangement.</item>
                    <item>—that we are prepared to offer modest assistance for development projects
                        in the Choco region rather than for the proposed highway per se.</item>
                </list>
                <p>RECOMMENDATIONS:</p>
                <p>1. That you ask Bryce Harlow to undertake consultations with the Congressional
                    leadership on the proposal to seek financing for two-thirds of the cost of the
                    Darien Gap Highway, and to assess the outlook for such legislation in terms of
                    the timing, source and form of funding.</p>
                <p>Approve [RN checked] <lb/> Disapprove <lb/> See Me</p>
                <p>2. That you inform President Lleras of your intentions concerning assistance for
                    the Pan/American Highway as described above.</p>
                <p>Approve [RN checked] <lb/> Disapprove <lb/> See Me</p>
                <p>3. That you authorize the State Department to enter into consultations with the
                    Governments of Colombia and Panama on their willingness to participate in
                    completing the Darien Gap Road on a 2/3–1/3 financing basis.</p>
                <p>Approve [RN checked] <lb/> Disapprove <lb/> See Me</p>
                <p>4. That you reserve your decision on the timing of a legislative request, the
                    source and type of funding until you have received Bryce Harlow’s assessment of
                    the Congressional outlook and consultations with Colombia and Panama have been
                    completed.</p>
                <p>Approve [RN checked] <lb/> Disapprove <lb/> See Me</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
