<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>126. Airgram A–709 From the Embassy in Brazil to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d126</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">126</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1969-12-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recyEkENoEqK2qwfi" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2014001310"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="recKIFSXxAMFQR38X" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="religious-freedom"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026944"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Clergy</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85002415"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Agriculture</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                    <term ref="recKk4WCfGYnrejri" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85009271"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Atmosphere</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133456"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Television</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh94002193"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Corruption</term>
                    <term ref="recdZke2uFUGdGg1d" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="political-prisoners"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh86008225"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Dissident</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85006620"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Business community</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic policies</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090150"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Economic growth</term>
                    <term ref="recpVHYIdWIn3pD0E" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85027699"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Coffee</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-12-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-12-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="126"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d126">
                <head>126. Airgram A–709 From the Embassy in Brazil to the Department of State<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d126fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Files 1967–69, <gloss target="#POL1">POL</gloss> 15 BRAZ.
                        Confidential. Drafted on December 4 by Johnson; cleared in draft by
                            <persName corresp="#p_ECB1">Elbrick</persName> and the Country Team; and
                        approved by Belton. <persName corresp="#p_MEG1">Médici</persName> was
                        nominated for President by the Brazilian military on October 6. (Telegram
                        8348 from Rio de Janeiro, October 7; ibid., POL 15–1 BRAZ) He was elected by
                        the Brazilian Congress on October 25 and inaugurated on October 30.
                        (Memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_ETL1">Eliot</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, October 27; ibid.)</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d126fn2">The Médici Government stated it
                        planned to focus on improving education, health, and agriculture. Thus,
                        Chargé Belton concluded that since Médici’s goals were more in line with the
                        priorities of the U.S. Government than was the case with the Costa e Silva
                        Government, U.S.-Brazilian relations would be closer under the new
                        regime.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Rio de Janeiro</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1969-12-09">December 9, 1969</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d126-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d126-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>Assessment of Character and Attitudes of <persName corresp="#p_MEG1"
                            >Médici</persName> Government</item>
                </list>
                <p>This airgram addresses itself to the political change in Brazil since Costa e
                    Silva’s stroke at the end of August. It analyzes certain apparent aspects of the
                    Medici administration’s character and attitudes, based on early indications, and
                    where appropriate draws certain comparisons with the situation which faced us
                    previously under <persName corresp="#p_CSA2">Costa e Silva</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>
                </p>
                <p>President Medici has assembled a team of considerable technical competence, and
                    has made several brief public statements of a general nature concerning his
                    government’s viewpoint. However, program details are still unavailable. Although
                    there are hints at this stage it is still impossible to judge with accuracy how
                    the Medici government will perform in areas of special interest to the U.S. such
                    as the “democratic opening” and the struggle to overcome the country’s basic
                    economic and social problems. It would be incorrect to expect major course
                    changes in the revolution, at least in Medici’s early days. The Medici
                    administration has its base in the same sector, the military, and inherits some
                    well established, policy lines and practices (e.g., use of institutional acts)
                    from its revolutionary predecessors.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the most prominent element of change since Costa’s last months lies in
                    the strengthening of the Presidency, for whatever this development may prove to
                    be worth to the Brazilians and the U.S. Medici enjoys broader support within the
                    military than <pb facs="d126-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d126-2"/> Costa did last
                    August. In addition, the image he projects probably commands more public respect
                    than did his predecessor’s. However, the best guess is that if polled the
                    numerical majority of the country’s population would prove uninformed,
                    fatalistic or indifferent on the subject. At least at this stage, it seems
                    doubtful that Medici has regained much support for the regime among those
                    members of the educated class who have become deeply alienated as a result of
                    twists in the revolution during the past year or so, e.g., some of the
                    university youth and professors, and certain liberal elements of the clergy.
                    However, among the other politically-aware individuals with whom the Embassy
                    maintains contact, a majority probably feels some relief that potentially
                    destructive infighting with the military has been avoided. This same majority
                    probably nourishes some hope, however slight, that a new man with a clean slate
                    who owes few political debts can chart some fresh beginnings in desirable
                    directions. Business circles have reacted favorably to Medici’s choice, and the
                    (semi-controlled) press has been generally laudatory.</p>
                <p>With regard to early indications of the Medici administration’s attitudes and
                    policies, Medici has revealed publicly that he plans to assign top priority to
                    progress in agriculture, education and health. A strong and publicly-advertised
                    interest in tackling problems directly connected with living conditions in
                    Brazil could help Medici’s image, although progress in these sectors will
                    continue to came hard. With regard to a “democratic opening”, the President has
                    said that he hopes to see democracy definitively established in Brazil before
                    leaving office, but he has failed to spell out specific steps and obviously must
                    be judged on the basis of performance and not words. Congress is open but the
                    executive-legislative honeymoon is a fragile thing and the prospects of a real
                    sharing of effective power at this stage are not good. Early indications do not
                    warrant optimism concerning the abandonment of the practice of governing by
                    institutional act.</p>
                <p>Concerning the Medici administration’s attitude toward the U.S., there is every
                    reason to expect a friendly and cooperative stance as well as more efficient
                    functioning of those agencies of the government whose efforts are supposed to
                    dovetail with U.S. aid efforts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Character and Attitudes of Medici Government</hi>
                </p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">General</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Medici has assembled a team of considerable technical competence, but how he and
                    his government will perform in certain areas of special interest to the United
                    States cannot be judged with any accuracy at this early stage. In his speeches
                    to date Medici has stressed, in ideological terms, his interest in establishing
                    democracy. However, he has done this <pb facs="d126-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d126-3"
                    /> without pinning himself down to any specific further steps in a “democratic
                    opening”. Similarly, his public statements have reflected an awareness of the
                    need for fresh approaches to Brazil’s basic economic and social problems,
                    looking ahead rather than back, but as yet few details on programs have emerged.
                    His exact intentions, as well as his ability to carry his plans out, must remain
                    questions at this stage.</p>
                <p>It would be incorrect to expect major course changes in the revolution, at least
                    in Medici’s early days. Elements of similarity between the Medici administration
                    and its two predecessors far outweigh the differences. There was no civilian
                    consultation in the process by which Medici was selected; he was chosen by, and
                    has his power base in, the same military establishment as his revolutionary
                    predecessors, and he inherits some well-established policy lines and practices
                    from them.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Medici’s Position Today Stronger than Costa’s Was Last
                        August</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Speaking of the present, it can at least be said—for whatever it may prove to be
                    worth to the Brazilians and the U.S.—that the Presidency is stronger now under
                    Medici than it was in Costa’s final months. This is perhaps the most prominent
                    element of change.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Greater Unity Within Military Establishment</hi>: By far the
                    most important cause of this increased strength is the greater unity of the
                    military establishment. For the present Medici is free of the open dissent which
                    troubled his predecessor. Steps which Costa was contemplating at the time of his
                    stroke, the opening of the Congress and the promulgating of a new Constitution,
                    threatened to expand military dissent. The same steps were taken after Costa’s
                    incapacitation in the name of the ruling triumvirate, as essential parts of the
                    process of installing President Medici and bringing the military out of its
                    leadership crisis. Under such circumstances they apparently came off without any
                    significant expressions of dissent within the military.</p>
                <p>Albuquerque Lima was forced by Costa’s illness to make his prematurely and failed
                    to rally broad support. His group is quiet for the time being. The Castellistas
                    are back in the fold. Medici has received personal promises of loyalty from each
                    of the top military leaders. The selection process is finished, with no
                    elections scheduled for another five years, and the man chosen is one who
                    neither conduces nor brooks dissension within the ranks.</p>
                <p>This unity in the military establishment is not necessarily durable, however,
                    since some of the basic conditions which engendered dissatisfaction and dissent
                    in Costa’s time persist today.</p>
                <pb facs="d126-4" n="4" xml:id="pg_d126-4"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Few Political Debts</hi>: Medici is in a somewhat stronger
                    position to innovate, if he chooses, than Costa was last August. He begins his
                    term as a man who did not campaign for the job and owes few political debts. He
                    was tapped as the man who, on the basis of his personality and character as well
                    as his record, was most likely to draw wide military support and hence pull the
                    military establishment out of the emergency threat to its unity.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Somewhat Improved Capacity to Command</hi>: Some of Medici’s
                    own personality and character traits are likely to be a source of greater
                    strength for his administration. He is a hard worker and a man of consistency,
                    not given to vacillation. His personality is less abrasive than that of his
                    predecessor (although it is also more austere, less jovial). He is more capable
                    of picking good men to work for him. He should thus be able to assemble a better
                    team than Costa’s, and to operate it more efficiently. He has warned his Cabinet
                    officers to renounce public ambitions, and has established for the present
                    anyway an atmosphere of harmony within the government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Public Image Commands More Respect</hi>: As a possible further
                    source of strength, Medici’s public image is considerably better than was that
                    of his predecessor in his final months, at least as it projects in Brazil’s
                    government-inhibited press, radio, and television. Editorials, for example, are
                    almost uniformly favorable to him personally. He is usually portrayed as a man
                    of character and integrity. With the exception of Transport Minister Andreazza
                    (who has reportedly been retained on sufferance), none of Medici’s Cabinet
                    officers have been seriously tainted with charges of corruption. Currently at
                    least, the behavior of his immediate family does not engender the sort of public
                    criticism which came to be levelled at certain members of Costa’s family. On
                    these various grounds, there is reason to believe that the Medici administration
                    would command somewhat greater respect among the public than did that of his
                    predecessor.</p>
                <p>Again, this is a situation which could deteriorate rapidly. Such interest and
                    restraint as may have been engendered by the sheer novelty of the regime will
                    eventually wear off. However, past cassations as well as the more stringent
                    current ground rules are likely to render public criticism of Medici, in both
                    press and Congress, generally tamer than was the case with his predecessors.</p>
                <p>It seems likely that the numerical majority of the country’s population remains
                    either uninformed or fatalistic and indifferent concerning the
                    Presidency—considering Medici another in the line of generals and unlikely to
                    alter the revolution’s policies. The austereness and reticence of Medici’s
                    personality will be a factor hampering progress in this area.</p>
                <pb facs="d126-5" n="5" xml:id="pg_d126-5"/>
                <p>As for the young students and professors and young clergy, Medici’s military
                    predecessors had gradually alienated many of them because they regarded
                    government policies on university campuses and elsewhere as increasingly
                    repressive, and/or regarded economic and social policy as conservative and
                    unimaginative in the light of the population’s impoverishment. While some
                    Brazilians in this particular dissident category are probably withholding
                    judgment of Medici, it seems likely that most remain highly suspicious if not
                    actually hostile to the government.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, among other politically aware individuals with whom the
                    Embassy maintains contact a majority probably feels some relief that potentially
                    destructive infighting within the military has been avoided. By and large these
                    people are fairly high up on the success ladder, and they have an interest in
                    the avoidance of political disorder with economic consequences. Probably a
                    majority of them believe that some further political relaxation is in order, and
                    nourish some hope—however slight—that a new man with a clean slate who owes few
                    political debts can launch some beginnings in desirable directions.</p>
                <p>The business community specifically was relieved, not only because the succession
                    crisis was resolved fairly smoothly but also because the man selected seems
                    likely to continue the economic policies of the previous government.</p>
                <p>The round-up of suspected subversives including members of the clergy is adding
                    significantly to existing tensions between the authorities and the Church. Both
                    sides will probably go to considerable lengths to avoid a flat confrontation on
                    a national scale. However, a continuing, crescendo of accusations and
                    counter-accusations would inevitably widen the breach, with some consequent
                    effect on Medici’s general standing in the country at large.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Some Early Observations on Medici Policies in Certain Areas
                        of Interest to the U.S.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The United States is interested in seeing progress under the new administration
                    toward solving basic economic and social problems which continue to impoverish
                    large segments of the population. We would also like to see a “democratic
                    opening”, involving a dispersal of authority, diminished recourse to government
                    by institutional act, and an easing up of some of the restrictions on individual
                    rights and freedoms.</p>
                <p>With regard to the first of these two general <hi rend="italic">desiderata</hi>,
                    there are indications from his public statements and from other sources that
                    Medici’s administration is likely to place more stress on education, <pb
                        facs="d126-6" n="6" xml:id="pg_d126-6"/> agriculture, health, and other
                    areas of direct popular concern than did his predecessor. Whatever other
                    advantages, or disadvantages, such policies might have, they could make an
                    important contribution to building Medici’s level of popularity. In the last
                    analysis, demonstrable government interest—if not progress—in these sectors is
                    perhaps more important as a factor in developing support than are steps toward a
                    “democratic opening”. A widely-advertised interest in tackling problems directly
                    connected with the standard of life in Brazil can help Medici’s image, but
                    progress in these sectors will continue to come hard.</p>
                <p>As for the second, President Medici has said that he hopes to see democracy
                    definitively established in Brazil before he leaves office, but he has failed to
                    spell out specific steps and obviously must be judged on the basis of
                    performance and not words. His statements seem to suggest that his concept of
                    democracy in its broader aspects focuses on educating the public to recognize
                    and support future goals and priorities which are in the country’s best
                    interests. Medici spokesmen have told the Embassy that he intends to place
                    primary stress on reestablishing communications between the government and the
                    people, with particular focus on university students and intellectuals. This, we
                    are told, was the main reason for appointing Passarinho, a dynamic man with
                    considerable charisma, as Minister of Education.</p>
                <p>Congress is open and functioning, and this in itself is a positive
                    development—although Congress is operating after cassations and under the
                    restrictive ground rules set forth in the new Constitution. The MDB opposition
                    abstained in the Medici election, thereby maintaining its opposition to the
                    manner in which the President was selected as well as to the severely
                    retrogressive steps of the previous administration. However, by not taking a
                    position of public opposition to Medici’s selection, the MDB avoided the early
                    shattering of the prevailing “honeymoon” atmosphere, with the attendant risk of
                    repressive repercussions. Although confrontation has been avoided so far, the
                    impression borne out in speeches to date is that the opposition will continue to
                    criticize government policies and actions, on general grounds of principle (for
                    example, as undemocratic) as well as specifically.</p>
                <p>Thus the present “honeymoon” is very fragile. A fresh phase of the
                    military-civilian confrontation could come at any time, particularly if Medici’s
                    handling of outspoken opposition in Congress becomes authoritarian and
                    eventually leads to threats. A large-scale resumption of cassations would also
                    have a disturbing effect on the political atmosphere. A basic lack of
                    communication and a gulf of mistrust continue to separate the military and the
                    civilian politicians. The opposition now has its sounding board in a reopened
                    Congress, but this does not in itself signal the beginning of the sharing of the
                    effective powers of government.</p>
                <pb facs="d126-7" n="7" xml:id="pg_d126-7"/>
                <p>Prospects for the abandonment of the practice of using institutional acts as a
                    substitute for legislation do not appear good. In his inauguration speech
                    shortly after the promulgation of the new Constitution—which specifically
                    provides for the continuation of institutional act powers—Medici sought to
                    justify the continuing existence of judicial order on the “institutional” plane
                    as well as the constitutional, supposedly to preserve the gains of the
                    revolution. Less than two weeks later he demonstrated his intention to use
                    Institutional Act 5 powers in a routine manner by retiring two minor officials,
                    thereby further diminishing any hopes there may have been that Medici would
                    refrain from using his IA powers. The manner in which the existing Constitution
                    was scrapped in favor of today’s more authoritarian document is another sign
                    that Brazil is moving away from constitutionality, at least as we understand the
                    term.</p>
                <p>Finally, and perhaps most important, if Brazil under Medici is to enjoy a larger
                    measure of democracy, Medici will have to loosen some of the restraints on
                    individual freedoms which have gradually come into being as the revolution
                    continued its course: intimidation of the press, restrictions on academic
                    freedom, cassations, etc. While Brazil will never be entirely free of
                    restrictions in these areas (indeed few countries are), progress in this
                    direction rather than increasing invasions of individual liberty would be an
                    obvious requirement if Medici is to make good his promise to restore democracy
                    to Brazil during his term.</p>
                <p>Medici’s first month in office has given no basis for reliable judgments on this
                    latter score. Deep hostility toward the government will probably continue to
                    characterize those elements of the intellectual class which seek revolutionary
                    reform, or action substantially increasing academic and intellectual freedom.
                    These conditions will probably keep the terrorist movement alive, and in the
                    eyes of some in the security forces the situation will justify continuing
                    restrictive measures rather than a let up.</p>
                <p>The establishment of democracy will take firm and lasting conviction as well as
                    leadership. In one limited sense, <persName corresp="#p_CSA2">Costa e
                        Silva</persName>’s departure from the scene represented a loss—at least in
                    his last few weeks he demonstrated a dogged determination to arrange the modest
                    beginnings of a “democratic opening” in the face of some apparent opposition in
                    the military establishment itself. Medici has not had similar occasion to
                    demonstrate such determination. He is in fact largely an unknown quantity. We
                    know him as a conservative man, and a man of strong character. However, in his
                    career to date his quality of modesty has led him to shun the limelight. Since
                    he did not project himself on the national scene, his convictions and his ideas
                    for moving the country forward have not really come to light. Medici’s firm
                    control of the situation within the military and the improved position which the
                    Presidency enjoys generally throughout the country should render him reasonably
                        <pb facs="d126-8" n="8" xml:id="pg_d126-8"/> confident of his ability to
                    follow through on whatever programs he may wish to launch. However, Brazil will
                    have to wait to learn whether he possesses the conviction to put the country on
                    a new course, the imagination to innovate boldly, and the dedication and
                    leadership qualities to beat down foot-dragging and outright opposition as they
                    arise.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Medici Administration Attitude Toward U.S.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>From the U.S. standpoint, Medici appears to offer some specific advantages over
                    his predecessor. His own strong attachment and respect for the United States are
                    well known. We can assume that he will be inclined to listen sympathetically to
                    the suggestions of the new U.S. administration concerning U.S.-Brazil
                    relationships. The Cabinet officers holding dawn positions of key importance
                    from the standpoint of U.S. contacts (e.g., <persName corresp="#p_GBM1">Gibson
                        Barbosa</persName>, Passarinho and <persName corresp="#p_DNA1">Delfim
                        Neto</persName>) are men who have previously indicated an interest in and an
                    ability for cooperating with the United States to mutual advantage. The
                    Embassy’s early experience with the Medici Cabinet tends to confirm this
                    view.</p>
                <p>Early indications are that the new government’s policies, priorities, and
                    techniques are more likely to facilitate effective U.S. assistance. Delfim
                    Neto’s continuation in office suggests that the government will pursue the kind
                    of sound financial policies which render U.S. aid most effective. The
                    government’s expressed intention of focusing its efforts on progress in the
                    fields of education, health, and agriculture should mean that Brazilian
                    priorities dovetail more closely with U.S. aid objectives than was the case with
                    the previous administration. Finally, Medici’s emphasis on teamwork has
                    reportedly resulted in steps by the executive to ensure that responsibilities
                    are clearly assigned, that priorities are firmly established and pursued, and
                    that activities in such fields as economic planning and programming are well
                    coordinated. At this early stage the information must be regarded as highly
                    tentative. But if the effort succeeds, Brazil will become much easier to
                    help.</p>
                <p>Looking to the future, there is of course a possibility that some rising
                    opposition element will pick up hostility to the U.S. and economic nationalism
                    as useful cudgels with which to beat the Medici regime. Much will depend on
                    Medici’s ability to disarm the opposition by bringing about an impressive rate
                    of economic growth and tackling some of the economic and social problems most
                    directly relevant to basic living standards here—all within the framework of his
                    non-inflationary economic policy. Although there is no evidence that
                    nationalistic or anti-U.S. attitudes are important characteristics of any
                    members of the government now, in the face of an opposition threat it is
                    possible that the government might adopt certain aspects of economic nationalism
                    as a <pb facs="d126-9" n="9" xml:id="pg_d126-9"/> defensive move. Even without
                    such a threat, a lack of concrete progress in dealing with some of the thornier
                    problems in U.S.-Brazilian economic relations (e.g., soluble coffee, shipping,
                    trade barriers) could cool the Brazilian government’s attitude toward the U.S.
                    fairly quickly. The afore-mentioned characteristics of the Medici regime,
                    coupled with an active and forthcoming U.S. posture, should at least permit open
                    and fruitful discussion of these problems.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>
                            <hi rend="strong">Belton</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
