<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-09-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-09-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="224" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d224">
                        <head>224. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (Kissinger) to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d224fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 782, Country Files, Latin
                                America, Soviet Naval Activity in Cuban Waters, Vol. I (Cienfuegos).
                                Top Secret; Sensitive; Eyes Only. Nixon wrote on the third page: “I
                                want a report on a crash basis on (1) what <gloss target="#CIA1">CIA</gloss> can do to support <hi rend="italic">any</hi> kind
                                of action which will irritate <persName corresp="#p_CRF1">Castro</persName> (2) what actions we can take which we have
                                not yet taken to boycott nations dealing with Castro (3) most
                                important what actions we can take covert or overt to put missiles
                                in Turkey—or a sub base in the Black Sea—anything which will give us
                                some trading stock.” Attached but not published at Tab A is a note
                                from the Soviet Embassy, given to Kissinger during his August 4
                                meeting with Vorontsov. (Ibid.)</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d224fn2">Kissinger reported on aerial
                                reconnaissance of Cuba.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-09-18">September 18, 1970</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <pb facs="d224-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d224-1"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item>Recent Soviet Naval Activity in Cuba</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Analysis of reconnaissance flight photography over Cuba has this morning
                            confirmed the construction of a probable submarine deployment base in
                            Cien Fuegos Bay. Specifically:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>—A Soviet submarine tender is anchored next to four buoys which
                                the Soviets have placed in the Bay.</item>
                            <item>—Since September 12, submarine nets have been emplaced across the
                                approach to the deep water basin in which the mooring buoys and the
                                tender are located.</item>
                            <item>—A Soviet LST is anchored at a fuel pier and a Soviet tanker is
                                anchored in the northern bay.</item>
                            <item>—Two special purpose barges are also located in the area.</item>
                            <item>—Special construction on Alcatraz Island, an island in the Bay,
                                appears to have been completed. This includes an administrative
                                area, two single-story barracks, a soccer field, basketball court
                                and probably handball, volleyball or tennis courts. An offshore
                                wharf and swimming area are on the east side of the island and a
                                platform tower has been constructed just south of the administrative
                                area.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The foregoing situation acquires special significance in the light of the
                            conversations I had with Charge Vorontsov on August 4 in the White House
                            Map Room. You will recall that I saw Vorontsov at his request on that
                            occasion. He called me in San Clemente to say he wanted to have an
                            appointment as soon as I got back. When I saw him he was extremely
                            cordial and read a communication which he handed to me.</p>
                        <pb facs="d224-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d224-2"/>
                        <p>The text of the note which is at Tab A:</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>—Expressed Soviet anxiety over alleged attempts by Cuban
                                revolutionary groups in the United States to resume sabotage and
                                subversive activity against Cuba from the U.S. soil.</item>
                            <item>—Complained about provocative articles in the American press and
                                ambivalent statements on the part of the U.S. officials concerning
                                Cuba.</item>
                            <item>—Stressed that the Soviets were proceeding on the Cuban question
                                from the understanding with regard to Cuba that existed in the past
                                and confirmed that the Soviets expected us to adhere to this
                                understanding.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Note</hi>: The so called understanding to which
                            Vorontsov was apparently referring was arrived at during the Cuban
                            missile crisis. In essence, during the exchanges between the U.S. and
                            the Soviets in 1962 at the time of the Cuban missile crisis we were
                            given assurances that the Soviets would not locate nuclear weapons on
                            Cuban territory in return for assurances from the U.S. government that
                            we would not undertake military action to change the government of
                            Cuba.</p>
                        <p>On August 7 I stated to Vorontsov that at your request I had been
                            instructed to give him the following reply:</p>
                        <p>—The U.S. notes with satisfaction the assurance of the Soviet government
                            that the understandings of 1962 are still in force, adding “We take this
                            to mean that the Soviet Union will not emplace any offensive weapons of
                            any kind or any nuclear weapons on Cuban soil.”</p>
                        <list>
                            <item>—I stated further that you wish to point out that although we have
                                heard repeated reports of increased Soviet activity in Cuba that you
                                were exercising the utmost restraint in not increasing
                                reconnaissance activity.</item>
                            <item>—You were maintaining the understandings of 1962 which I was
                                hereby authorized to reaffirm.</item>
                            <item>—Specifically the U.S. would not use military force to bring about
                                a change in the governmental structure of Cuba.</item>
                            <item>—I then added that it had come to our attention that Soviet <pb facs="d224-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d224-3"/> long range airplanes of
                                the type suitable for nuclear bombing missions were flying with
                                increasing regularity to Cuba. While we believe these planes were on
                                reconnaissance missions we thought nevertheless that this might
                                constitute a basis for approaching the limit of our understanding.
                                It would certainly be noticed if the Soviet Union kept such
                                operations to a minimum. The same applied to Soviet naval activity
                                in <hi rend="italic">the Caribbean</hi>.</item>
                            <item>—I called Vorontsov’s attention to the fact that we had taken
                                protective measures in recent days with respect to a Soviet ship
                                which reportedly was in danger of attack from Cuban exile
                                groups.</item>
                            <item>—Vorontsov indicated he appreciated the good spirit in which the
                                observations were made and was certain that the Kremlin would be
                                very happy to receive them.</item>
                            <item>—I concluded by telling Vorontsov that the major problem now was
                                to see what concrete progress could be made in the area of
                                negotiations.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Today’s photography readout confirms that despite the exchange between
                            Vorontsov and myself the Soviets have moved precipitously to establish
                            an installation in Cien Fuegos Bay which is probably designed to serve
                            as a submarine staging base in the Caribbean. Because of the seriousness
                            of this situation I have asked CIA to provide me with a briefing at
                            12:30 today at which time we will carefully evaluate the full range of
                            photographic evidence now held in an effort to determine more precisely
                            the full scope of Soviet activity in Cuba. I am also initiating, on an
                            urgent basis, a detailed analysis of the strategic implications of this
                            development.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>