<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-03-02T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-03-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="235" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d235">
                        <head>235. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>) to President
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d235fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon
                                Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box
                                781, Country Files, Latin America, Cuba, Vol. III, 1971.
                                Confidential. Sent for information. Although not initialed by
                                Kissinger, an attached NSC routing sheet indicates that this
                                memorandum was sent to the President on March 8.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d235fn2">Kissinger reported on the
                                status of the Cuban fishing boat case.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-03-02">March 2, 1971</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <pb facs="d235-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d235-1"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item>Cuban Fishing Boat Case</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>It now appears that the problem created by the seizure of four Cuban
                            fishing boats for fishing within the 12 mile limit will be resolved
                            within the next several days. You will recall that the Coast Guard
                            seized one vessel and the Florida Marine Patrol seized an additional
                            three boats which were being escorted outside territorial waters by the
                            Coast Guard at the time. The net result was a potentially serious
                            problem between ourselves and the Cubans and also a problem of conflict
                            between state and federal authority. The affair was partially untangled
                            late last week when the State of Florida ceded jurisdiction to the
                            federal government over the three vessels it had captured providing the
                            federal government agreed to prosecute.</p>
                        <p>The Cubans, through their representatives, have now agreed to settle out
                            of court for the payment by them of $25,500 in fees and fines. This
                            amount should be paid today, but it may be several days before the
                            necessary legal procedures have been completed and the boats can
                            leave.</p>
                        <p>Although the Cuban Government has made no public declarations the press
                            has already denied that the vessels were fishing inside the 12 mile
                            limit and referred to US actions as blackmail. It is possible that the
                            Cubans will retaliate at the first opportunity, perhaps when the next
                            US-airliner is hijacked to Cuba. Charges equalling the amount of fines
                            paid in this case may be levied against the aircraft. In addition
                            charges equalling the $5,000 a day which the Cuban Government claims the
                            arrest of the four vessels has cost the Cuban economy may be levied. It
                            is also possible that the aircraft and its crew may be held for a time
                            equalling that which the Cuban vessels were held in Florida.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>