<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-08-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-08-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="262" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d262">
                        <head>262. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_JWJ1">William J.
                                Jorden</persName> of the National Security Council Staff to the
                            President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d262fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                                Materials, <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 781, Country
                                Files, Latin America, Cuba, Vol. IV, 1972. Secret; Sensitive. Sent
                                for action. The approval line was not marked.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d262fn2">Jorden reported on a
                                proposal by the Cuban Government to release the ships and crewmen
                                involved in the <hi rend="italic">Johnny Express</hi> incident of
                                December 1971.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-08-22">August 22, 1972</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <pb facs="d262-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d262-1"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                            <item>Cuban Proposal to Release Babun Ships and Crewman</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>We have received an interesting and important proposal from the Cubans
                            via the Panamanians. General <persName corresp="#p_THO1">Torrijos</persName> has sent the following message through his
                                <gloss target="#G21">G–2</gloss>, Colonel Noriega, [<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>]</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">“Visiting Cuban Alfredo Garcia informed Foreign
                            Minister <persName corresp="#p_TJA1">Juan A. Tack</persName> that Cuba
                            wanted to rid itself of the problem Cuba has had since impounding the
                            Babun ships and crews. Garcia told Tack that the Mexican Embassy in Cuba
                            was pressuring the Cubans for release but (the latter) would prefer to
                            make the release to the Panamanian Government. Garcia said if Torrijos
                            would send a delegation to Cuba to negotiate the return of the ships and
                            crews (including Captain Villa who Garcia said was under death
                            sentence), he believed that they would be released to Panama. Torrijos
                            said that if President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                            wants him to do so, he would make the request to the Cubans for release.
                            Torrijos is prepared to send a delegation to Cuba next week.”</quote>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] in making this offer,
                            Torrijos is trying to build credit with President Nixon. He feels that
                            return of the ships and crews would be of possible political value
                            during the election campaign.</p>
                        <p>[<hi rend="italic">text not declassified</hi>] The Department of State
                            has not been advised yet of the above information.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">BACKGROUND</hi></p>
                        <p>Last December, the Cubans seized two ships of Panamanian registry—the
                            LAYLA EXPRESS on December 5, 1971, and the JOHNNY EXPRESS on December
                            15, 1971. They are owned and operated by the Babun Brothers, Cuban
                            exiles. Both ships have been used in the past as mother ships for
                            infiltration raids into Cuba by exile groups. All but four crewman from
                            the ships have already been released <pb facs="d262-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d262-2"/> by the Cubans. The four still in custody are
                            all of Cuban extraction; but one, Captain Jose Villa, is an American
                            citizen. Our information is that Villa has been sentenced to 30 years in
                            prison, not to death as Garcia claimed. You will recall that Captain
                            Villa’s wife and daughter have made repeated appeals for our help in
                            securing the Captain’s release. One appeal was made in person to
                            President Nixon at Key Biscayne.</p>
                        <p>The Alfredo Garcia mentioned in the message is an identified Cuban
                            intelligence officer.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">COMMENT</hi></p>
                        <p>It may well be that the Cubans do want to liquidate this problem which
                            has been something of an embarrassment in their relations with other
                            Latin countries. They probably also feel that they have made their point
                            effectively—i.e., that ships used against them are in danger of seizure.
                            Nor has the imprisonment of Captain Villa—and the related adverse
                            publicity—done Havana much good. However, if the Cubans receive a
                            Panamanian delegation and agree to the request to release the ships and
                            men, they will certainly ask for a quid pro quo. I assume that would
                            probably be Panamanian agreement to recognize Cuba and restore
                            diplomatic relations.</p>
                        <p>In fact, I would not be surprised if this is not a Panamanian idea rather
                            than a Cuban initiative. We know that Torrijos and Tack have been moving
                            in the direction of restoring relations with Havana. (Panama voted with
                            Peru at the recent <gloss target="#OAS1">OAS</gloss> meeting to free
                            hemisphere governments from continuing sanctions against Cuba.)</p>
                        <p>It may also be that Torrijos, in making this offer, is looking ahead to
                            concessions from us in the Canal negotiations.</p>
                        <p>Despite all this, there does seem to be some prospect that Panama can
                            induce the Cubans to release the two ships as well as Captain Villa and
                            the other three men. Certainly that is desirable—especially the release
                            of Captain Villa, an American citizen, whose family has gone through
                            agonizing worry and misery. But we must recognize that we will be
                            incurring a debt to Torrijos—probably Panama’s recognition of Cuba
                            and/or concessions on canal treaty issues.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">RECOMMENDATION</hi></p>
                        <p>That we go back to Torrijos/Noriega [<hi rend="italic">text not
                                declassified</hi>] with something like the following:</p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">“We have received the message given us by Colonel
                            Noriega. Since the two ships in question are of Panamanian registry, we
                            assume that the <pb facs="d262-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d262-3"/> Panamanian
                            Government is interested in their prompt return to their rightful
                            owners. The U.S. Government is mainly interested in the release of the
                            crew members who have been illegally imprisoned. We are especially
                            desirous of securing the earliest possible release of Captain Villa. We
                            would appreciate anything President Torrijos can do toward this
                            end.”</quote>
                        <p>This puts our appeal principally on humanitarian grounds rather than
                            commercial. It also avoids a direct appeal from President Nixon to
                            Torrijos. But it does unleash the Panamanians to do what they can to win
                            the release of Villa and the others, as well as the ships. (Note: We
                            have reason to believe that the Babun ships have on occasion been used
                            in the narcotics traffic.)</p>
                        <p>Because of the sensitivity and complexity of this matter, I believe you
                            will wish to discuss it orally with the President rather than putting it
                            in memo form.</p>
                        <p>Approve suggested message to Torrijos <lb/> Approve message, as revised
                            <lb/> Disapprove <lb/> Call me on this</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>