<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>283. Intelligence Note RARN–24 Prepared in the Bureau of Intelligence and
                    Research</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d283</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">283</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-07-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Security forces</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006005376"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Extremist</term>
                    <term ref="rec2DHm7M6y3nExAB" type="topic" category="uncategorized" subcategory="general" subject="science-and-technology" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011000626" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Communication</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-07-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-07-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="283"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d283">
                <head>283. Intelligence Note RARN–24 Prepared in the Bureau of Intelligence and
                        Research<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d283fn1">Source: National
                        Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#POL1">POL</gloss>
                        23–8 DOM REP. Secret; No Foreign Dissem. Note prepared in INR/American
                        Republics by Misback, LaMazza, and <persName corresp="#p_SGH1"
                            >Summ</persName>.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d283fn2">The Bureau of Intelligence and
                        Research reported increased left-wing violence, countered by extra-legal
                        violence by the security forces, leading to fears of indiscriminate
                        repression by the Dominican Government.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-07-02">July 2, 1970</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d283-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d283-1"/>
                <p rend="center">DOMINICAN REPUBLIC: TENSIONS AND VIOLENCE BUILD AGAIN</p>
                <p>A recent resurgence in the level of violence has ushered in a new period of
                    tension in the Dominican Republic. The violence is potentially more serious than
                    past cycles because of mounting pressure on President <persName
                        corresp="#p_BRJ1">Balaguer</persName> from hardliners in the military to
                    strike out against the left, including the opposition Dominican Revolutionary
                    Party (<gloss target="#PRD1">PRD</gloss>) and especially its leader, <persName
                        corresp="#p_BGJ1">Juan Bosch</persName>. Balaguer, a skillful juggler in the
                    past, will be sorely tested to maintain order without yielding to extremists of
                    the right or left.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Rising Level of Violence</hi>. Since June 26, seven persons
                    have been killed including a policeman. In addition, one policeman and one
                    soldier have been wounded. The interaction of the security forces and left-wing
                    extremists as they try to settle their scores could well increase this casualty
                    toll. Flyers have appeared in Santo Domingo the past few days blaming Juan Bosch
                    for much of the violence and kidnappings and offering a reward for him dead or
                    alive, preferably dead. The sheets are obviously part of a scare tactic campaign
                    to intimidate but it is not yet clear whether the government is directing the
                    effort or simply condoning it.</p>
                <pb facs="d283-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d283-2"/>
                <p>The government has announced that mixed military patrols will be placed on the
                    streets in certain key areas of the capital. In the past the terrorists have
                    shied away from direct confrontation with the security forces. But even if the
                    extreme militants are cowed for a time, the violence will likely increase as the
                    country approaches the August 16 date of President Balaguer’s inauguration.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Balaguer’s options</hi>. Balaguer has accommodated pressures
                    somewhat from the right by increasing penalties for terrorist acts, and he has
                    publicly taken <persName corresp="#p_BGJ1">Bosch</persName> to task for radio
                    commentaries pushing his thesis of “dictatorship with popular support.” In a
                    July 1 press conference the President stressed that from now on the most drastic
                    measures would be taken against armed terrorists. At the same time, however,
                    intelligence reports indicate that he is trying to open behind-the-scenes
                    channels of communication with Bosch and the PRD. Balaguer might be able to
                    develop this dialogue in such a manner as to encourage the PRD not to associate
                    itself with forces fomenting public disorder. This would enable him to direct
                    police action specifically at the extremist elements.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Prospects</hi>. Balaguer’s ability to contain the situation
                    without appeasing the left or becoming indiscriminately repressive will be
                    sorely tested over the next month or so. His power to influence the
                    unpredictable Bosch is open to question. Nevertheless, Balaguer has proven that
                    he can be a skillful juggler in tight situations in the past, and can probably
                    handle the current situation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
