<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>303. Intelligence Note RARN–27</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">303</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-07-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recHhFel0suTm0rZv" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121623"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Maneuver</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="rec1Zl9FOvMzxLARV" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="terrorism"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2006005376"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Extremist</term>
                    <term ref="recl0TYMV9bsDkZVm" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85074300"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Land reform</term>
                    <term ref="recbm2CDfl6YlSCnq" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Modernization</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="tax" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Taxes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-07-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-07-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="303"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d303">
                <head>303. Intelligence Note RARN–27<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d303fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#POL1">POL</gloss> 15–1 ECUADOR. Confidential. Drafted by
                            <persName corresp="#p_STW1">Sonandres</persName> and approved by
                            <persName corresp="#p_SGH1">Summ</persName>.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d303fn2">After <persName corresp="#p_VIJM1"
                            >Velasco</persName>’s assertion of a supreme mandate, the authors of
                        this note predicted he would institute substantial fiscal and social
                        reforms.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-07-09">July 9, 1970</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d303-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d303-1"/>
                <p rend="center">ECUADOR: REFORM PERUVIAN-STYLE?</p>
                <p>On June 21, in a well-executed maneuver backed by the military, 77 year-old
                    President Velasco Ibarra assumed extraconstitutional powers as the only means to
                    unblock opposition to his programs. The old caudillo’s future in the
                    Presidential Palace (for the fifth time) is uncertain in light of the past
                    history of his chaotic regimes and the dominant Ecuadorean elite which opposes
                    his recent revenue measures and announced “restructuring.” Yet Velasco is
                    displaying unaccustomed acumen and great determination as he seeks to achieve
                    fiscal and reformist goals.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The takeover</hi>. Velasco assumed the “supreme mandate”<note
                        n="3" xml:id="d303fn3">Velasco has taken on legislative powers only. The
                        Supreme Court, civil liberties, and local and provincial government appear
                        largely unaffected. He announced he will step down at the end of his elected
                        term and hand the presidency over to the winner of the June 1972
                        elections.</note> principally to resolve the “economic crisis” he created
                    earlier this year by publicizing and exaggerating an unusually large but
                    perennial budget deficit; his constitutional alternatives were exhausted when
                    first Congress and subsequently the Supreme Court blocked his revenue-<pb
                        facs="d303-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d303-2"/>producing measures. Velasco also
                    faced pressure from the military which had urged him to settle the finance issue
                    and to crack down on extremists.</p>
                <p>The President swiftly dissolved the powerful but do-nothing Congress and replaced
                    the “absurd” 1967 Constitution by the 1946 Charter which accorded greater powers
                    to the executive. Ecuador’s volatile students were put down, at least for the
                    moment, by closing the main universities and abolishing the extremist-led
                    secondary-school student federation. To put the administration’s fiscal house in
                    order, the government has levied new taxes against the wealthier classes,
                    established controls over a money-making but ineffective autonomous agency, and
                    imposed an <gloss target="#IMF1">IMF</gloss>-approved program of foreign
                    exchange reform. Velasco also declared rent controls, in an obvious attempt to
                    woo mass support.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">A mild case of “Lima Fever.”</hi> Despite the reported absence
                    of Peruvian-style reformers in the government or military, this regime seems
                    bent on instituting substantial fiscal and social reforms. Jorge Acosta, the
                    influential Defense Minister, announced that a military-led agrarian land reform
                    in the sparsely populated east would take place and spoke approvingly of the
                    Peruvian revolution. Also of significance may be the silence of Ecuador’s two
                    leading 1972 presidential candidates, ex-President Camilo Ponce and popular
                    Guayaquil Mayor Assad Bucaram. Their stance, in contrast to the shrill criticism
                    of other politicians, strongly suggest that both foresee the possibility of
                    regime success <pb facs="d303-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d303-3"/> and want to be in
                    position later to join the bandwagon.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Modest reforms possible</hi>. Velasco and the military
                    probably lack the human and material resources to overturn the “old order” and
                    institute a thoroughgoing modernization program on the Peruvian model. The
                    realization of less ambitious aims lies within their capabilities, however,
                    particularly if Velasco avoids goading labor, business, and students into
                    forging another opposition force—something that toppled three regimes in the
                    1960’s. He will also, of course, need to retain the currently enthusiastic
                    support of the armed forces.</p>
                <p>Velasco has avoided the sort of radical moves that thrice before led to his
                    ouster. He is conscious of his advanced age and apprehensive over his place in
                    history. This time he may foresake kicking over the traces as he strives to
                    embellish his memory through enactment of at least a modicum of reform.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
