<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>392. Memorandum From Viron P. Vaky of the National Security Council to the
                    President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National Security
                    Council to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d392</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">392</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-06-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-06-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reczhNQIs9rGlNS1M" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96008124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Humanitarian assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85105939"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Poverty</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-06-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-06-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="392"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d392">
                <head>392. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_VVP1">Viron P. Vaky</persName> of
                    the National Security Council to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d392fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, NSC Institutional Files
                        (H-Files), Box H–45, Senior Review Group Meetings, Haiti and Cuba 6/11/70.
                        Secret. Sent for action. Attached but not published is the attached January
                        8 <gloss target="#NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 70 Study on Haiti. The memorandum was
                        not initialed by Vaky. The Senior Review Group did not meet on June 11;
                        Kissinger decided to ask for agency positions on the options and present
                        them to the President. (Memorandum from Vaky to Kissinger, October 14;
                        ibid., Box H–222, <gloss target="#NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 94)</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d392fn2">Vaky forwarded a copy of NSSM–70
                        Study on Haiti for Kissinger to review in preparation for the June 11 Review
                        Group Meeting. The covering memorandum, which is published here, briefly
                        describes NSSM–70 study’s key points.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-06-02">June 2, 1970</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d392-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d392-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>Review Group Meeting, June 11—Haiti</item>
                </list>
                <p>The Review Group Meeting on June 11 is scheduled to consider NSSM–70, Haiti. The
                    meeting will also cover NSSM–32 Cuba, and, therefore, you will want to keep
                    discussion of Haiti fairly brief.</p>
                <p>The NSSM was issued as a result of Governor <persName corresp="#p_RNA1"
                        >Rockefeller</persName>’s recommendation that we consider renewing aid to
                    Haiti and revising our policy toward <persName corresp="#p_DF1"
                        >Duvalier</persName>.</p>
                <p>The central issue outlined by the <gloss target="#IG1">IG</gloss> paper is what
                    if anything can and should be done now by the US a) to prepare for or influence
                    the transition to a post-Duvalier Haiti and b) to help Haiti achieve modernity
                    and satisfy humanitarian needs?</p>
                <p>The paper concludes that we can do little to influence the transition or to
                    meaningfully assist Haiti’s development while Duvalier is in power, and that we
                    should try to satisfy humanitarian needs primarily through multilateral and
                    private channels. This essentially would continue our present policy with
                    perhaps an increased effort at providing humanitarian assistance. Basically I
                    agree with the conclusions.</p>
                <p>The paper considers three options for assisting Haiti and two options (one of
                    which is deemed unfeasible) to prepare for or influence the transition to a
                    post-Duvalier Haiti. These are:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">To Assist</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—continue present policy of minimal bilateral involvement</item>
                    <item>—encourage greater multilateral participation</item>
                    <item>—increase bilateral assistance.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="d392-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d392-2"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">To Prepare for the Transition</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <item>—continue present course of minimal involvement</item>
                    <item>—increase efforts to influence the transition (seen as not
                        feasible).</item>
                </list>
                <p>(There is a contingency paper on Haiti which covers the US position during the
                    actual transition). (The pros and cons of the above options are summarized on
                    pages 4–9 of the Analytical Summary).</p>
                <p>The paper rejects three other options as “straw men,” i.e. unfeasible under
                    present or foreseeable circumstances. These are:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—termination of all US assistance</item>
                    <item>—creation of a major US bilateral aid program</item>
                    <item>—covert action to change the political structure of the country.</item>
                </list>
                <p>We believe at least one of the options rejected, that of the renewal of a
                    larger-scale bilateral aid program, should be discussed in the meeting since it
                    is seriously recommended by our Ambassador, Clinton <persName corresp="#p_KCE1"
                        >Knox</persName>. The Ambassador makes some interesting points about the
                    importance of keeping our eye on the political evolution of Haiti as a black
                    state, rather than simply considering it a problem of Duvalier’s dictatorship.
                    This long-range perspective should at least be considered.</p>
                <p>There are a few minor problems with the statements of objectives and judgments in
                    the paper. These are mentioned in your talking points.</p>
                <p>At the Review Group meeting we should get agency views on the options presented,
                    then submit the paper to the President. I do not think it is worth sending the
                    paper for any rewrites. Any amendments or discussion can probably be handled in
                    our staffing.</p>
                <p>We think that there will be agreement that the US probably cannot influence the
                    transition and that development efforts are better left to private and
                    multilateral agencies. However, I feel that we can also probably get agreement
                    that the US can and should try to do more on the humanitarian side to alleviate
                    conditions of poverty and deprivation among the people.</p>
                <pb facs="d392-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d392-3"/>
                <p>An NSC meeting on Haiti is not necessary. However, the paper should go to the
                    President because a) it is an issue raised by Governor Rockefeller and b) a
                    presidential decision is needed to help shake some of the bureaucracy’s
                    complacent biases toward Haiti.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
