<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>503. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Inter-American Affairs (Meyer) to the Acting Secretary of State () to the Acting
                    Secretary of State (Irwin))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d503</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">503</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-04-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-04-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-04-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-04-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="503"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d503">
                <head>503. Action Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for
                    Inter-American Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MCA1">Meyer</persName>) to the
                    Acting Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName>)<note
                        n="1" type="source" xml:id="d503fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#POL1">POL</gloss> 7 <gloss
                            target="#NIC1">NIC</gloss>. Confidential. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_HR2">Hines</persName>; cleared by <persName
                            corresp="#p_HRA1">Hurwitch</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BJR1"
                            >Breen</persName>, William R. Codus (S/CPR), and Von Stroebel
                        (Commerce); cleared in info by Colonel Wyrough (<gloss target="#DOD1"
                            >DOD</gloss>). Copies sent to U, J, <gloss target="#C1">C</gloss>, and
                            <gloss target="#ARACEN1">ARA/CEN</gloss>/N. Irwin approved Meyer’s
                        recommendation on April 13 and sent the attached memorandum to the
                        President. On the memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >Nixon</persName>, there is a typed note that indicates that Nixon would
                        meet <persName corresp="#p_SDA1">Somoza</persName> for dinner in June.
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d503fn2">Assistant Secretary Meyer supported
                        Nicaraguan Ambassador Sevilla-Sacasa’s request for “some sign of special
                        attention by President Nixon” for President Somoza during his visit.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-04-12">April 12, 1971</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d503-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d503-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>Memorandum for the President: Request that President Nixon receive General
                        Anastasio Somoza Debayle, President of Nicaragua</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">DISCUSSION</hi>:</p>
                <p>This year marks the 25th anniversary of President Somoza’s graduation from West
                    Point. He plans to visit the Academy around June 5 to commemorate the event.
                    During his visit to Nicaragua last December, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_SM2">Stans</persName> invited Somoza to come to Washington when
                    he was next in the United States to attend a lunch to which Secretary Stans will
                    invite American businessmen interested in investing in Nicaragua. Nicaraguan
                    Ambassador Sevilla-Sacasa is now working on the preparations for the Somoza trip
                    and has requested that some sign of special attention by President Nixon be
                    arranged for the Somoza visit to Washington.</p>
                <p>I believe this request should be met. Somoza has been a steadfast friend of the
                    United States, and has long been interested in a visit to Washington with some
                    official character to it. As a result of an agreement he recently reached with
                    the major opposition party in Nicaragua, it is clear now that Somoza will be
                    stepping down from the presidency at the end of his elected term of office on
                    May 1, 1972. Thus we cannot gracefully look forward to some “future opportunity”
                    if we turn down this request.</p>
                <pb facs="d503-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d503-2"/>
                <p>The attached memorandum to the President recommends that he receive President
                    Somoza. If he agrees, Somoza’s stay in Washington will be treated for protocol
                    purposes as a “Private Visit with a Call on the President”. The dinner for the
                    25th anniversary Class of 1946 of the U.S. Military Academy, suggested in the
                    memo to the President, would meet the desire of Ambassador Sevilla-Sacasa
                    without substantial departure from the precedence involved in the private
                    visit.</p>
                <p>Since Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> will be in Europe
                    through June 8, I would hope that your schedule will permit you to offer either
                    a luncheon or dinner in President Somoza’s honor, in addition to the luncheon
                    Secretary Stans has agreed to offer. The attached memorandum indicates that you
                    will do so if your and Somoza’s schedules can be arranged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">RECOMMENDATION</hi>:</p>
                <p>1. That you sign the attached memorandum for the President.</p>
                <p>2. That you agree in principle to schedule a social function in Somoza’s honor if
                    he is received by the President.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
