<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>51. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Kissinger) to President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">51</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85139643"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Unemployment</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Economic aid</term>
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="tariffs" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132405" lcsh-match="good_close">Tariff</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="trade-relations" lcsh-match="no_match">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="foreign-currency" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Currency</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-11-12T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-11-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="51"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d51">
                <head>51. Memorandum From the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                        (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>) to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d51fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon
                        Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 814,
                        Name Files, Senator Finch. Confidential. Sent for action. Kissinger approved
                        both recommendations for Nixon. Attached but not published at Tab I is the
                        November 10 memorandum from Finch and <persName corresp="#p_PPG1"
                            >Peterson</persName> to Nixon.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d51fn2">Kissinger forwarded recommendations
                        from the President’s Counselor <persName corresp="#p_FR1">Robert
                            Finch</persName> and Pete Peterson that the administration introduce
                        generalized tariff preferences and announce the expropriation policy to
                        coincide with some positive foreign assistance action. Kissinger indicated
                        that he agreed with Finch and Peterson that negotiating trade concessions
                        from Latin America in exchange for lifting the surcharge would be
                        counterproductive.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-11-12">November 12, 1971</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d51-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d51-1"/>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT:</head>
                    <item>Finch Trip to Latin America</item>
                </list>
                <p>Bob Finch and Pete Peterson have sent you the attached memorandum (Tab I)
                    concerning economic issues which Bob plans to discuss with the Latin Americans.
                    They asked for <hi rend="italic">your approval on two points</hi>:</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Tariff Preferences</hi>: Bob proposes to tell the Latin
                    Americans that we will introduce generalized tariff preferences legislation as
                    part of a comprehensive trade package when the climate is right, and that he
                    would like their input. Finch and Peterson note that the Latins will be quite
                    skeptical, but believe this may be the best we can do at this time. They suggest
                    that a new trade package will probably have to wait until after the NEP
                    negotiations are completed and a better unemployment situation prevails. In view
                    of your personal plans, we will have to submit generalized preferences
                    legislation—or possibly as a fallback hemispheric preferences—sooner than that,
                    even if there has to be an understanding that Congress will not act upon it
                    quickly. In the meantime, I recommend that you approve the line that Bob Finch
                    proposes to take with the Latins.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Expropriation Policy Announcement</hi>: Treasury has agreed
                    that no public announcement of expropriation policy should be made until after
                    Finch returns from Latin America. However, Treasury feels it is important to
                    give the House Banking and Currency Committee a commitment that a public
                    announcement will be made within 10 days after the Inter-American Bank
                    legislation is reported out of the Committee. Finch and Peterson recommend that
                    we authorize Treasury to give the Committee such a commitment, but that when the
                    expropriation announcement is made, it should be put in the context of some
                    positive foreign assistance action, such as passage of a new aid bill. I have no
                    objection <pb facs="d51-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d51-2"/> to this proposal, but will
                    assure that the text and timing of the expropriation policy statement are
                    cleared by you to assure that we minimize any adverse impact on your Latin
                    American plans. I, therefore, recommend your approval of the Finch/Peterson
                    proposal.</p>
                <p>The Finch/Peterson memo also notes that lifting the surcharge for Latin America
                    is essential to restoring relations. They are concerned, however, that Secretary
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJB1">Connally</persName> wants to negotiate trade
                    concessions from each Latin American country in return for lifting the
                    surcharge. I strongly support their view that seeking to negotiate trade
                    concessions from the Latins—with whom we have a huge trade surplus—as a quid pro
                    quo for lifting the surcharge would only add insult to injury and would have far
                    greater political costs than any possible economic benefits we could derive from
                    this approach. We are staffing for you separately the question of how to lift
                    the surcharge for Latin America and will have some recommendations shortly.</p>
                <p>The memo concludes by noting that Bob will be consulting with the Latin Americans
                    on the effects of the surcharge, attitudes toward economic aid issues,
                    expropriation policy, and military sales.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
