<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1969-07-15T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-07-15T00:00:00-05:00" n="521" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d521">
                        <head>521. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d521fn1">Source:
                                National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 790, Country Files, Latin
                                America, Panama, Vol. 1, January 1969–February 28, 1970. Secret.
                                Rogers signed “WPR” above his typed signature. Neither approval nor
                                disapproval was checked, but the President indicated his approval in
                                    <ref target="#d524">Document 524</ref>. Attached but not
                                published is the enclosed memorandum.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d521fn2">Secretary of State Rogers
                                reviewed the Panama Review Group’s terms for initiating Panama Canal
                                negotiations. The most important topics included the issue of
                                negotiating with the unconstitutional government in Panama City, the
                                findings of the Atlantic-Pacific Interoceanic Canal Study
                                Commission, and the expiration of U.S. rights to the Rio Hato
                                Military Training Area.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1969-07-15">July 15, 1969</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <pb facs="d521-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d521-1"/>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Canal Treaty Negotiations with Panama</item>
                        </list>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Recommendation</hi>:</p>
                        <p>That you approve the enclosed terms of reference prepared by the Panama
                            Review Group for further canal treaty negotiations with Panama and for
                            seeking an agreement with Panama for the continued use by the United
                            States Armed Forces of the Rio Hato Military Training Area.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>:</p>
                        <p>We anticipate that the Government of Panama will in the near future
                            propose the resumption of the canal treaty negotiations which have been
                            suspended since 1967. In expectation of such an initiative, the Panama
                            Review Group has undertaken a review of our canal policy with a view to
                            recommending a course of action for the United States in future
                            negotiations with Panama concerning the present canal and a future
                            sea-level canal.</p>
                        <p>Several important issues are involved. We shall need to decide whether we
                            should agree to negotiate with the unconstitutional government presently
                            in power in Panama. We must also determine what revisions may be
                            required in our treaty objectives in the light of developments since <pb facs="d521-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d521-2"/> the negotiations were
                            suspended in 1967. Recent findings of the Atlantic-Pacific Interoceanic
                            Canal Study Commission regarding the possible construction of a
                            sea-level canal in Panama are particularly relevant in this regard.</p>
                        <p>The impending expiration, on August 23, 1970, of our rights to use the
                            Rio Hato Military Training Area in Panama constitutes a special and
                            immediate problem. Rio Hato was one of the items covered by the previous
                            treaty negotiations, and provision for its continued use was included in
                            the treaty drafts agreed upon by the United States and Panamanian
                            negotiators in 1967. Because of the delays in the Canal negotiations,
                            however, it will be necessary, if we are to be assured of access to Rio
                            Hato after 1970, to make special arrangements with Panama, at least for
                            the interim period before new canal treaties are concluded.</p>
                        <p>The enclosed memorandum prepared by the Panama Review Group sets forth a
                            recommended course of action for future canal treaty negotiations and
                            for arranging the continued use of Rio Hato. The members of the Panama
                            Review Group include the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American
                            Affairs as Chairman, the Secretary of the Army, and the Special
                            Representative for United States Panamanian Relations (Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_ARB1">Robert B. Anderson</persName>). The
                            memorandum represents their views, and also those of the representatives
                            of the Department of Defense, the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and the
                            Atlantic-Pacific Interoceanic Canal Study Commission, who participated
                            in the discussions of the Panama Review Group.</p>
                        <p>I believe the Panama Review Group proposal presents a realistic approach
                            for dealing with Panama on the Canal and such related issues as Rio Hato
                            and recommend its approval.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_RWP1"><hi rend="strong">William P.
                                        Rogers</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>