<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>530. Paper Prepared by the NSC Inter-Departmental Group for Inter-American
                    Affairs Inter-Departmental Group for Inter-American Affairs</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76ve10</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d530</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">530</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-01-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rec8s7zXlcPBsGqGN" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Treaty negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cU1GPlUbqajOH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000359"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Airport</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compensation</term>
                    <term ref="recqZdNRLmmFdfX5e" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recYKTo2QC0yLpT7N" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Draft treaty</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Treaties</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-01-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-01-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="530"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d530">
                <head>530. Paper Prepared by the <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss>
                    Inter-Departmental Group for Inter-American Affairs<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d530fn1">Source: National Archives, Nixon Presidential Materials,
                        NSC Files, NSC Institutional Files (H-Files), Box H–169, <gloss
                            target="#NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> Files, NSSM 86. Secret.</note>
                    <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d530fn2">The <gloss target="#NSCIGARA1"
                            >NSC–IG/ARA</gloss> provided two basic options available to the United
                        States for negotiation with Panama over the Panama Canal: maintain the
                        existing treaties and negotiate interim measures providing substantial
                        benefits to Panama, or use the 1967 draft treaties as a starting point for
                        negotiating new treaties.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1970-01-27">January 27, 1970</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <pb facs="d530-01" n="1" xml:id="pg_d530-01"/>
                <p>SUMMARY</p>
                <table type="simple">
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>PAGE NO.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>I. Background and Essential Elements</cell>
                        <cell role="num">1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>II. Desirability of Concluding New Treaties</cell>
                        <cell role="num">12</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">A. US Interests</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">B. US Objectives</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>III. Timing with Respect to New Treaties</cell>
                        <cell role="num">13</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>IV. Negotiating Options</cell>
                        <cell role="num">15</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Introduction</cell>
                        <cell role="num">15</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Option A—Defer negotiations on abrogation of the existing treaty
                            structure and negotiate interim measures providing substantial benefits
                            to Panama</cell>
                        <cell role="num">17</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Option B—Negotiate major revisions in the 1967 draft treaties</cell>
                        <cell role="num">20</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>V. Related Treaty Issues</cell>
                        <cell role="num">23</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">A. Multinational Participation in Canal System</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">B. Tolls</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Annexes:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>A.</label>
                    <item>NSAM No. 152, April 30, 1962, Panama Canal Policy and Relations with
                        Panama</item>
                    <label>B.</label>
                    <item>Text of the United States—Panama Agreement of April 3, 1964, as Announced
                        by the <gloss target="#OAS1">OAS</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <label>C.</label>
                    <item>President’s Statement on Panama Canal, December 18, 1964</item>
                    <label>D.</label>
                    <item>NSAM 323, January 8, 1965, Policy toward the present and future of the
                        Panama Canal</item>
                    <label>E.</label>
                    <item>Statement by the President on the Progress of Treaty Negotiations with
                        Panama, September 24, 1965</item>
                    <label>F.</label>
                    <item>Office of the White House Press Secretary, Press Release, June 26,
                        1967</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="d530-02" n="2" xml:id="pg_d530-02"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">SUMMARY</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Government of Panama may soon request the United States to renew canal treaty
                    negotiations which, during the period 1964–67, resulted in three draft treaties
                    concerning the present lock canal, a new sea-level canal and defense
                    arrangements. Since then, there has been no action beyond the initialing of
                    these drafts, due primarily to political developments in Panama.</p>
                <p>Recent events in both countries give rise to the need for a re-examination of US
                    interests, objectives and the matter of timing, as well as available policy
                    options, with respect to any future canal treaty negotiations.</p>
                <p>On our part, we wish to ensure the continued availability of an adequate and
                    secure Isthmian canal system for the benefit of US and world commerce and the
                    national security of the US. We also seek to maintain an enduring, mutually
                    acceptable relationship with the Republic of Panama.</p>
                <p>There are, we believe, two basic policy options:</p>
                <p>The first would have the US defer negotiations on abrogation of the existing
                    treaty structure and negotiate <hi rend="italic">interim</hi> measures providing
                    substantial benefits to Panama. This option is premised on the judgment that the
                    US in not now in a position either to abrogate the basic treaties or to provide
                    for the termination of US operation of the existing canal at any fixed date.</p>
                <p>The second option would have the US pursue the general course defined by the 1967
                    drafts, together with significant revisions to meet developments since then.
                    This option is premised on the judgment that the deeply rooted causes of
                    friction in our relations with Panama should be dealt with <hi rend="italic"
                        >now</hi> (rather than in piecemeal fashion as in 1936 and 1955), and that
                    the areas of agreement with Panama reflected in the 1967 treaty drafts form the
                    proper basis for achieving a new political relationship with Panama regarding
                    the canal.</p>
                <pb facs="d530-03" n="3" xml:id="pg_d530-03"/>
                <p>[Omitted here are Sections I–III.]</p>
                <pb facs="d530-04" n="4" xml:id="pg_d530-04"/>
                <p rend="center">
                    <hi rend="italic">IV. NEGOTIATING OPTIONS</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This paper defines two options in treaty negotiations with the Panamanian
                    Government. There are at least two other courses of action open to the United
                    States, neither of which merits full treatment as an option.</p>
                <p>The first of these quasi-options would be to sign the 1967 draft treaties in
                    their present form. The main virtue of these drafts lies in the fact that they
                    reflect a then existing consensus in the Department of State, the Joint Chiefs
                    of Staff, and other interested components of the Executive Branch on the US
                    side, as well as considerable agreement within the Government of Panama at that
                    time. The chief reason the treaties were not submitted to Congress for
                    ratification, however, was that the difficulties these drafts were encountering
                    in Panama in a pre-election period made it most unlikely that the Panamanian
                    Government would proceed with ratification.</p>
                <p>The 1967 drafts, moreover, were written before the Canal Study Commission’s
                    tentative determination that Route 10 in Panama, adjacent to the present canal,
                    would be the most promising site for a sea-level canal. The Commission expects
                    to reach firm conclusions on its essential findings not later than June of 1970.
                    Consequently, we are now better prepared to seek definitive rights to a specific
                    sea-level canal route should we choose to do so under Option “B” below. Further,
                    the 1967 drafts contain the undesirable provision that were the US not to begin
                    construction of a sea-level canal by the end of 1999, the present canal would
                    become Panamanian property. There is now an opportunity to attempt to improve on
                    this provision.</p>
                <p>Finally, indications from the present regime in Panama are that these drafts are
                    no longer acceptable in their present form and any intent on our part,
                    therefore, to make them the basis for our future relations with Panama would be
                    unrealistic. For these reasons, we do not believe that a negotiating position
                    limited solely to the content of the 1967 drafts should be seriously
                    entertained.</p>
                <p>The second quasi-option would be to start afresh in any forthcoming negotiations,
                    without a feeling of any degree of commitment to the 1967 treaty drafts, leaving
                    it to <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ad referendum</hi>
                    strategy to determine the final <pb facs="d530-05" n="5" xml:id="pg_d530-05"/>
                    form and content of new treaties. The advantage of this course would lie in the
                    fact that we do not know precisely what the Panamanian demands will be or
                    whether either of the two following options would be fully relevant to these
                    demands. Further, both sides would be free from whatever stigma attaches to the
                    1967 drafts.</p>
                <p>On the negative side, it ill behooves the US with the experience of negotiating
                    the 1967 drafts in Panama behind us, and with our understanding of the causes of
                    friction in our present relations with Panama, to enter negotiations affecting
                    key issues in our relations without taking this experience into account. We know
                    enough now about future canal needs and about the remedies for some of the
                    irritants in our relations to be able to prepare a respectable negotiating
                    position beforehand. Failure to do so might cause misgivings in Panama about our
                    good faith.</p>
                <p>The first of the two options described below would defer negotiations on key
                    treaty issues until a later date, while offering to negotiate now interim
                    concessions desired by Panama. The second option would negotiate <hi
                        rend="italic">now</hi> those key treaty issues.</p>
                <p>The key issues were alluded to in the areas of agreement jointly announced by
                    Presidents Johnson and Robles on September 24, 1965:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The 1903 Treaty will be abrogated;</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>the new treaty will effectively recognize Panama’s sovereignty over the
                        area of the present Canal Zone;</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>the new treaty for the existing Canal will terminate after a specific
                        number of years or on the date of the opening of the sea-level canal,
                        whichever occurs first;</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>the new treaties will provide for the defense of the existing canal and
                        any sea-level canal which may be constructed in Panama; United States forces
                        and military facilities will be maintained under a base rights and status of
                        forces agreement.</item>
                </list>
                <p>No matter which option is selected, the sense of Congress should be sought before
                    negotiations begin, and it may be desirable to include Senate representation in
                    the negotiating team.</p>
                <pb facs="d530-06" n="6" xml:id="pg_d530-06"/>
                <p>Option A: <hi rend="italic">Defer negotiations on abrogation of the existing
                        treaty structure and negotiate interim measures providing substantial
                        benefits to Panama.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This option is premised on the judgment that the United States is not now in a
                    position either to abrogate the basic treaties or to provide for the termination
                    of US operation of the existing canal at any fixed date.</p>
                <p>To make this approach acceptable to Panama, the U.S. could offer to negotiate
                    interim matters that would be beneficial to Panama but would not, at least until
                    a definitive decision can be made regarding the new canal, concede changes in
                    the basic treaty structure or give up basic U.S. rights. The interim actions
                    could resolve some pressing problems for Panama and could include items of
                    benefit to the U.S. The interim measures negotiated would involve legislation,
                        <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> treaties, executive agreements, or
                    administrative action, depending upon the requirement in each case. An
                    illustrative list of possible interim measures is:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Transfer of Old France Field to Panama for use by the Colon Free
                        Zone</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Arrangement for use of New France Field by Panama as a commercial
                        airport</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Open the Canal Zone to private business under new ground rules, including
                        application of Panamanian tax, labor, social security, and customs laws; to
                        some extent this would respond to Panama’s aspiration to exercise
                        sovereignty in the Canal Zone</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Construction of a four-lane highway in the Canal Zone from Thatcher Ferry
                        Bridge to the border of Arraijan, to connect with a projected similar
                        highway in Panama</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Financial assistance in other highway projects in Panama, such as a new
                        transisthmian highway</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Transfer to Panama of certain areas and facilities such as the Cristobal
                        piers, Shaler Triangle, Kennedy Avenue, Fourth of July Avenue, and Gavilan
                        Point (border streets or areas)</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Increase direct compensation to Panama, by increasing the annuity or
                        otherwise</item>
                    <pb facs="d530-07" n="7" xml:id="pg_d530-07"/>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Agreement for the continued use by the United States of the Rio Hato
                        military training area in Panama</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Increased involvement of Panamanians in the operation of the Canal.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>Negotiation of interim measures could be identified as the first step of a
                        new U.S. policy to maximize Panamanian benefits from the canal. The goal of
                        this policy, stated or unstated, would be an open-ended U.S. presence in
                        Panama until such time in the future when we have reason to believe that our
                        national interests no longer require that we remain there. The U.S. would
                        defer definitive negotiations on the exercise of sovereignty and control
                        until vital decisions had been made about the future of the canal. In short,
                        the negotiators would know at the later date exactly what canal or canals
                        they are negotiating about, and in what time frame, so that U.S. interests
                        and objectives could be better protected.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>By the time canal decisions are made, Panama may have returned to
                        constitutional government, thereby resolving the problems presented now in
                        concluding and ratifying basic treaties with the military
                        dictatorship.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>This option might have a much better chance of Congressional acceptance
                        than fundamental revision of the 1903 Treaty relationship. Prior
                        consultation with the Congress should obviate any problems in gaining the
                        necessary legislative approval of provision of increased benefits to
                        Panama.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Through deferral of definitive negotiations until after the sea-level
                        canal decisions, the Congress will have had an opportunity to participate in
                        the sea-level canal decision and will be more likely to support treaties
                        negotiated on the basis of such decisions.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>By its willingness to negotiate from time to time, on a continuing basis,
                        interim actions beneficial to Panama, the United States would demonstrate
                        its desire to be helpful and to work with the Panamanian Government.</item>
                    <pb facs="d530-08" n="8" xml:id="pg_d530-08"/>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>If the interim changes are adequate in number and substance, and developed
                        over a period of time, the Government of Panama might have a politically
                        feasible basis for not pressing for definitive treaties until the United
                        States has made decisions on the sea-level canal.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>The interim actions could include some matters beneficial to the US, such
                        as an extension of the agreement covering use of the Rio Hato military
                        training area in Panama by US forces.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Although the interim concessions involve matters covered in the 1967 draft
                        treaty package, the U.S. bargaining position would not be weakened to the
                        point of jeopardizing future negotiations, because the basic treaty
                        concessions that Panama wants, such as sovereign rights in the Canal Zone,
                        would still remain.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>It could be difficult for any Panamanian government to agree to new treaty
                        arrangements which do not contain basic revisions of the existing treaty
                        structure. If the US should refuse to negotiate on these key concepts, there
                        is a risk of deterioration in US relations with Panama that could lead to
                        violence as in 1964.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>This approach requires the US to hold in abeyance the areas of agreement
                        announced by Presidents Johnson and Robles in 1965 which were the basis of
                        the 1967 drafts.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>Panama can be expected to assert that it is now entitled to all the
                        concessions in the 1967 drafts as a minimum, and failure to obtain these
                        could present problems to the existing regime.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Most of the interim measures contemplated were involved in the 1967 draft
                        treaty package and could be considered bargaining counters, the piecemeal
                        use of which might weaken the US position in future negotiations. There is a
                        further risk that Congress, in approving the legislation necessary to
                        achieve this option, might impose restraints that could inhibit the US in
                        later negotiations.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="d530-09" n="9" xml:id="pg_d530-09"/>
                <p>Option B: <hi rend="italic">Negotiate Major Revisions in the 1967 Draft
                        Treaties</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Discussion</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This option is premised on the judgment that the deeply rooted causes of friction
                    in our relations with Panama should be dealt with now (rather than in piecemeal
                    fashion as in 1936 and 1955), and that the areas of agreement with Panama
                    reflected in the 1967 treaty drafts, together with certain major revisions, form
                    the proper basis for achieving a new political relationship with Panama
                    regarding the canal. The option proposes significant revisions to meet the
                    problems of the 1967 drafts and developments since then, such as the tentative
                    findings of the Canal Study Commission, that have previously been discussed.</p>
                <p>The US can justifiably seek major revisions in the 1967 draft treaties in light
                    of the changed circumstances of 1970. While this option provides flexibility in
                    obtaining such changes, it is nevertheless predicated on the parameters of the
                    1967 treaty drafts:</p>
                <list>
                    <item>—abrogation of the 1903 and related treaties</item>
                    <item>—a new treaty structure encompassing the existing lock canal, rights to
                        construct a sea-level canal, and defense arrangements</item>
                    <item>—recognition of effective Panamanian sovereignty over canal and defense
                        areas</item>
                    <item>—a specified termination date for the new treaty</item>
                    <item>—the non-negotiability of US control over canal operations, and of
                        unilateral defense rights.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The following <hi rend="italic">major revisions</hi> in the 1967 drafts should be
                    sought in future canal treaties:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The US should maintain control over operation and defense of an Isthmian
                        canal system in Panama well into the 21st century.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The US should obtain definitive rights to build and operate jointly with
                        the Panamanians a conventionally excavated sea-level canal on Route 10 in
                        Panama. It would be highly desirable that <pb facs="d530-10" n="10"
                            xml:id="pg_d530-10"/> there be accompanying rights to continue the
                        operation of the existing canal when needed. (This revision might create an
                        Inter-Oceanic Authority under US majority control to operate, maintain and
                        develop a single canal system in Panama.)</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The US should obtain treaty provisions which would clearly establish our
                        rights to augment the existing canal with new or additional locks and
                        channels, instead of building a sea-level canal to meet future traffic
                        requirements.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The following are <hi rend="italic">desirable</hi> (but not essential) <hi
                        rend="italic">revisions</hi> to the 1967 drafts:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The US should obtain the general right to build a nuclear excavated
                        sea-level canal along Route 17, subject to future agreement in detail, in
                        the event nuclear excavation proves both feasible and desirable before a
                        decision is reached to construct a new canal by conventional means.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>The US should obtain rights to build a second sea-level canal along the
                        trace of the existing canal, Route 14.</item>
                </list>
                <p>To address Panamanian aspirations and to help achieve U.S. negotiating
                    objectives, new treaties should set a time limit for phasing out governmental
                    and service functions exercised by the Joint Administration in the new Canal
                    Areas (as provided for in the 1967 drafts), leaving the Joint Administration
                    exclusively concerned with canal operations thereafter. To accomplish this goal,
                    an intensive program of training Panamanians to replace US personnel would have
                    to be undertaken at an early date.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Advantages</hi>:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>With its anchor in the 1967 draft treaties, this updated option would take
                        advantage of much of the consensus on key issues previously reached between
                        the US and Panama.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>By eliminating anachronistic elements in our relationship, it would remove
                        many of the sources of friction in our dealings with Panama, and should
                        significantly improve relations between our two countries.</item>
                    <pb facs="d530-11" n="11" xml:id="pg_d530-11"/>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>The US would retain for an extended period the right to choose either the
                        sea-level or the improved lock canal alternative, and the choice of either
                        would extend US control for a long period thereafter. The ultimate choice
                        would require Congressional approval at the time, which should be more
                        acceptable to the Congress than the arrangement proposed in the 1967 draft
                        treaties.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>There would be significant economic benefits for Panama either in
                        augmentation of the old canal or in construction of a sea-level
                        canal.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The US would be in a strong bargaining position: we would be seeking a
                        sufficient number of rights to meet our probable future canal requirements
                        at a time when Panama would be attempting to achieve its own goals in a new
                        treaty relationship. Further, we would not be dissipating our bargaining
                        strength through interim concessions only to return in later years to seek
                        the rights provided in this option.</item>
                </list>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Disadvantages</hi>:</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The costs of obtaining the revisions we seek to the 1967 drafts are not
                        predictable, but are likely to be substantial no matter how skillfully we
                        negotiate. To the extent that we will be negotiating in advance of any US
                        Government decision regarding a sea-level canal, we would be required to
                        obtain a variety of rights, each with its own price tag.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Our agreement at this time to relinquish control and operation of the
                        canal some time in the future may not prove to serve US interests at that
                        future date.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>This option, even though its content and presentation would be quite
                        different from the 1967 drafts, might still encounter significant
                        Congressional opposition.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Congressional opponents will be critical of the weakness of achieving
                        control by a mere 5–4 majority representation on the Joint Canal
                        Administration.</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>The possibility of non-ratification of these treaties by the US risks
                        disillusionment in Panama and violence directed at the canal.</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="d530-12" n="12" xml:id="pg_d530-12"/>
                <p>[Omitted here is Section V and the Annexes.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
