<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-10-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-10-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="560" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d560">
                        <head>560. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_FER1">Edward Ridley Finch,
                                Jr.</persName> to the Deputy Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_IJNII1">Irwin</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d560fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Files
                                1970–73, <gloss target="#POL1">POL</gloss> PAN–US. TLE Sensitive;
                                Personal and Confidential; Nodis. An attached handwritten note
                                reads: “JDI [Irwin] has asked <gloss target="#ARA1">ARA</gloss> to
                                redraft Finch’s report to make it less sensational. He will ask
                                Finch to sign redrafted version and then send it to <gloss target="#WH1">WH</gloss> [White House] under Irwin/Pres memo.
                                This version being given only to ARA and us. Ted—do you want a TLE
                                sensitive for now?” The later version of the letter was sent to the
                                President on November 13 and is ibid., POL 2 PAN. <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s October 9 letter to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_THO1">Torrijos</persName> is ibid., Nixon
                                Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box
                                760, Presidential Correspondence, 1969–1974, Panama, President
                                    <persName corresp="#p_LBDB1">Demetrio B. Lakas</persName>.
                                Nixon’s letter to Lakas has not been found.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d560fn2">Finch recounted his
                                conversation with General Torrijos and President Lakas over topics
                                in U.S.-Panamanian relations, including narcotics, the Pan American
                                Highway, and the Panama Canal.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-10-16">October 16, 1972</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <pb facs="d560-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d560-1"/>
                        <p>Dear Jack:</p>
                        <p>Reference is made to President Nixon’s personal and confidential letter
                            to General Omar Torrijos of Panama dated October 9, 1972, delivered by
                            me at a lengthy porch conference with General Torrijos. Am pleased to
                            submit to you, as requested, this personal and confidential memo for our
                            meeting with President Nixon. This memo summarizes some of what I
                            reviewed Thursday evening, October 12th, with you, on the eve of my
                            return to U.S.A. I will bring the gift to President Nixon from the
                            Governor of the Canal Zone to Washington, D.C. when you advise me of the
                            date and time it will be convenient for us to meet with President Nixon.
                            As to the formalities as the President’s Special Envoy and Ambassador
                            for the Inaugural, these were carried out as scheduled.</p>
                        <p>The letter from President Nixon to President Lakas was presented along
                            with the President’s gift to President Lakas and he was pleased with it.
                            Lakas is a friend of the United States. He is aware and appreciative of
                            U.S. financial assistance. He is distressed over continued poverty in
                            Panama. He gives assurance that he will cooperate with the United States
                            in regards to the Johnny and Layla Express matter and the return of
                            Captain Villa. He was reminded of President Nixon’s public commitment to
                            secure Villa’s release and assures me he will follow this up. On all
                            other matters he “ducked” and referred me to General Torrijos. The
                            private conference with President Lakas lasted about 45 minutes.
                            Information concerning it was discussed in person with you and will be
                            with President Nixon, to the extent he wishes.</p>
                        <pb facs="d560-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d560-2"/>
                        <p>The conference with General Torrijos took place about 6:00 P.M. on the
                            porch of his home, in shirt sleeves, for approximately 1 1/2 hours.
                            President Nixon’s letter of October 9, 1972, with translation into
                            Spanish, and a pair of Presidential Seal cuff links were presented to
                            General Torrijos, with President Nixon’s congratulations. I thanked
                            General Torrijos for his current cooperation on the drug and narcotics
                            problems. Told him of President Nixon’s personal interest and firmness
                            of purpose in respect to traffic in dangerous drugs and asked him for
                            his public and private cooperation in the same. After discussion about
                            its effect on youth in Panama and in the United States, he agreed to
                            continue and expand his cooperation in this matter. Publicly at a press
                            conference the following day he did so for the first time. It is a
                            sensitive matter for certain reasons in Panama, but we succeeded. The
                            next subject discussed was the Pan American Highway and the cattle hoof
                            and mouth disease. General Torrijos said that Panama had taken the
                            necessary steps with regards their side of the Columbian border for a
                            health zone but that Columbia had done nothing. He wants U.S. pressure
                            on Columbia. I have taken one “opportune” step in that direction
                            already. He asked me to personally convey this message about pressure on
                            Columbia on Aftosa to President Nixon and to assure President Nixon of
                            Panama’s cooperation on this matter.</p>
                        <p>General Torrijos is an impetuous, strong, quiet man of little talk, of
                            limited legal and limited strategic military education. He asked me to
                            thank President Nixon for the five U.S. planes recently sent him. He
                            said he is sitting on a powder keg as far as the Panama Canal is
                            concerned. He said to me that he would prevent a civil confrontation at
                            the Canal border until after the election and that he had gone to the
                            University once personally quite recently, to put a stop to growing
                            student and civil unrest. He repeated his remark the U.S. and Panama are
                            sitting on a powder keg. I could not get any assurance from him that it
                            will not blow up and give us a Christmas present between election and
                            the first of the year, or soon thereafter. At this point the General’s
                            wife brought us some cold soft drinks.</p>
                        <p>General Torrijos repeated his assurance that he would keep everything
                            quiet until after the U.S. elections although I did not ask him to do
                            this. In my opinion, the situation <pb facs="d560-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d560-3"/> would blow up much sooner except for Torrijos
                            and U.S. economic aid to Panama. Torrijos dislikes Congressman Bowe and
                            said so clearly. I explained that because of President Nixon’s problems
                            with our Congress that Congressman Bowe might “turn around” and be an
                            excellent appointment for Panama and not the match that will light the
                            fuse, as to the Canal confrontation, which Torrijos thinks will happen.
                            My suggested solution is to delay the appointment of Congressman Bowe as
                            the new Ambassador to Panama until the middle of 1973. Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_SRM1">Sayre</persName> is doing a quite superb
                            professional job and the top level Panamanians trust him. We should not
                            change horses in midstream.</p>
                        <p>As President Nixon’s letter to him requested, I pressed General Torrijos
                            to stop discussing the Panama Canal issue in the U.N., <gloss target="#OAS1">OAS</gloss> and in the press. Torrijos said he had to
                            let some PR out occasionally just to let steam out of the kettle to help
                            him keep the situation cool in Panama. He stated he wants joint control
                            of the Canal by Panama and the United States. He wants U.S. Southern
                            Command eliminated. These items he constantly reverted to. In my
                            opinion, General Torrijos should be invited at once to the U.S., and
                            particularly to see NORAD, as he has no concept of ballistic missile
                            defense. He does not realize that Panama has no capability without the
                            U.S. in that regard. He was most pleased that I offered to go out in the
                            field in Panama with him. I pointed out to Torrijos Mr. <persName corresp="#p_ARB1">Anderson</persName>’s very recent excellent
                            memorandum to Panama on the proposed new Canal Treaty. He knew of it.
                            Torrijos will not move back to Treaty negotiations until the U.S. shows
                            him he is dealing with a <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"><hi rend="italic">Kissinger</hi></persName> who will <hi rend="italic">stay on
                                the job</hi> and give him some <hi rend="italic">firm</hi> and <hi rend="italic">final answers</hi>. Only on that basis is he willing
                            to negotiate a new Canal Treaty now. He definitely will not at the
                            present level of negotiations. He repeated this point. He also again
                            repeated the point about elimination of the U.S. Southern Command. There
                            are some solutions to this which I do not wish to discuss in a written
                            memorandum. Some of these were discussed with our General Underwood.
                            Torrijos is clear that <hi rend="italic">steady</hi> very high level
                            U.S. initiative is needed now. We should do so while we still have time
                            and before the year ends. Torrijos was pleased by the fact that he felt
                            that President Nixon had truly sent a Personal Envoy as Special
                            Ambassador. (He knew that my nephew was married to Tricia!)</p>
                        <pb facs="d560-4" n="4" xml:id="pg_d560-4"/>
                        <p>We next discussed the Pan American Highway, the Darien Gap, and the
                            Aftosa problem with Columbia. Torrijos has cooperated on this and
                            strongly wants U.S. pressure on Columbia now in regards to it. He said
                            so. If we go high level with a Kissinger on the U.S. side then Torrijos
                            assured me privately he would go for a new Canal Treaty as President
                            Nixon requested in his personal letter to him of October 9th. It is
                            clear that there is a country-to-country high level communications gap
                            here, apart from the policy gap. This is mainly due to the U.S. dealing
                            with Panama as though it were a communistic nation rather than an ally.
                            The U.S. has inadvertently or deliberately denied Panama the last few
                            years certain rights which we could have granted to them safely. For
                            example, sharing the unused Colon Airport, Navigational Aids on Islands,
                            etc. I cross-checked very discreetly at least a half dozen items with
                            top U.S. and top Panamanian officials. Are we deliberately holding back
                            and deliberately irritating General Torrijos and the Panamanians over a
                            period of time? This will not create a Treaty negotiation atmosphere,
                            which President Nixon wants. General Torrijos is truly irritated as are
                            the Panamanian people over a period of time. U.S. policy must be
                            clarified and we do need a Kissinger for Panama now. Delay in this
                            situation will be dangerous. Torrijos is a man who sometimes does not
                            know the consequences of what he says, privately and publicly,
                            especially in certain legal and strategic military areas. Torrijos
                            probably will decide in the next few months which way he wants to go and
                            if time continues to run against the U.S., it will be impossible to
                            avoid a future Panama Canal border confrontation.</p>
                        <p>Mrs. Finch created much good will and good PR there for the U.S. by
                            hospital visits and clinic visits, etc., which two Panamanian cabinet
                            ministers and President Takas mentioned to me.</p>
                        <p>It is a pleasure to have been of some small service to President Nixon
                            and the United States and I will await your call. I simply cannot put
                            into a memorandum all of the information which should be given to the
                            President and only some of which I had the opportunity to discuss with
                            you on the eve of my return to the United States.</p>
                        <pb facs="d560-5" n="5" xml:id="pg_d560-5"/>
                        <p>Best personal regards and will await your call. Congratulations, Jack, on
                            the great job you are doing for the U.S.</p>
                        <p>Cordially,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_FER1"><hi rend="strong">Edward R.
                                        Finch</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>