<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-26T16:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-12-26T16:35:00-05:00" n="76" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d76">
                        <head>76. Telegram 8185 from the Embassy in Argentina to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d76fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#POL1">POL</gloss> 30–2 ARG. Confidential. Repeated to USCINCSO, DIA,
                                Montevideo, Asuncion, Brasilia, and Santiago.</note>
                            <note n="2" type="summary" xml:id="d76fn2">The Embassy’s country team
                                predicted that former President <persName corresp="#p_PJD1">Peron</persName>’s return to Argentina was a positive
                                development for the nation.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Buenos Aires</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-12-26T21:35:00+00:00">December 26, 1972, 2135Z</date>
                            </dateline></opener>
                        <pb facs="d76-1" n="1" xml:id="pg_d76-1"/>
                        <p>USCINCSO for <gloss target="#POLAD1">Polad</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>Subject:</head>
                            <item>Peron’s Return in Retrospect: A Country Team Assessment</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>1. Summary: Peron may have been disappointed by the fact that the country
                            did not turn upside down upon his return. Reportedly, he felt he had
                            been misled by those of his advisers who had urged him to come—though he
                            later designated one of those advisers as Presidential candidate. Looked
                            at objectively, however, the homecoming would seem to have produced
                            gains as well as losses for Peron. His personal image certainly
                            suffered. He had no solutions and was unable to heal or prevent
                            divisions in his own camp. But if Peron the myth is no longer with us,
                            Peron the politician is. He continued to demonstrate that, whether from
                            Madrid or within the city of Buenos Aires, he retains the capability to
                            influence, though not to control, the Argentine political scene. The way
                            in which his own followers reacted to his return suggested that the
                            Peronist party also has changed. They did not pour into the streets by
                            the hundreds of thousands. Galimberti’s group talked of war, but most
                            Peronists were content to sit home and watch the leader on television.
                            This more <pb facs="d76-2" n="2" xml:id="pg_d76-2"/> passive attitude,
                            however, in no way indicates that Peronist voting strength does not
                            remain formidable. No longer a fanatical mass, the Peronists with all
                            their internal bickering and fighting, are still the largest single
                            political party in the country. At the moment, schisms and dissension
                            have resulted from Peron’s designation of <persName corresp="#p_CHJ1">Hector Campora</persName> as their presidential candidate. In the
                            final analysis, however, the party, with some losses, will probably hold
                            together as a unit and vote for Campora (if he is still the candidate),
                            thus testifying to Peron’s continued ability to impose his will upon the
                            majority of his followers. However one judges the outcome of the return
                            from the standpoint of Peron and the Peronistas, the results for
                            Argentina were clearly positive and encouraged the hope that a corner
                            has been turned. The passions which once demanded polarization are seen
                            to have cooled. Peronismo and anti-Peronismo still exist as adversaries,
                            but now that the myth has been dispelled and the worst (Peron’s return)
                            seen to be not so awful after all, perhaps they can coexist—and in the
                            same country. No action required. End summary.</p>
                        <p>2. While there is a tendency in some Argentine circles to write off
                            Peron’s return as a complete failure, the Mission believes this is a
                            rather unbalanced view. A more accurate analysis, in its opinion, would
                            show that the results of the return were a mixed bag of gains and
                            losses. Peron took himself out of the race as a candidate. His personal
                            image was tarnished. The myth was dispelled and he was seen to be an
                            aging mortal capable of choosing his words poorly and with no panaceas
                            in his suitcase. This was, by and large, inevitable. Those who had
                            waited for the black plane to bring back a mythical hero who would
                            return them to power, heal the divisions in the movement and solve the
                            economic-social problems of the country with a wave of his hand were
                            doomed to disappointment. But even Peronists whose expectations had been
                            of a more rational order may have been disappointed. Peron conducted
                            himself with marked circumspection while here. He made no real effort to
                            communicate with his followers. If they did not take to the streets,
                            neither did he order them to do so. He did not take advantage of the
                            government’s offer that he address the nation on television or at a
                            public meeting. He purposely ducked the youth rally which was to have
                            been held <pb facs="d76-3" n="3" xml:id="pg_d76-3"/> on December 15 and
                            he avoided holding a press conference with Argentine newsmen. This was
                            not, in other words, the master manipulator of the masses and of the
                            public media many Argentines remembered. And on the one occasion when he
                            did meet the press (albeit the foreign press corps), he was guilty of a
                            serious gaffe (i.e. his reference to the Paraguayan Army as the most
                            glorious in the Americas) which irritated many Argentine civilians as
                            well as military, including some of his own followers.</p>
                        <p>3. Moreover, Peron was drawn inexorably into the infighting between the
                            various sectors and leaders of the movement whose unity he was expected
                            to bring about. Bogelio Coria, Antonio Cafiero, and Alfredo Gomez
                            Morales, for example. All of whose positions suffered as a result, will
                            probably be a little less loyal, a little less enthusiastic supporters
                            than they were before his arrival. Finally, the contradictions between
                            his words and deeds was not lost on all Argentines. For example, after
                            denouncing the Argentine military dictatorship and refusing to meet with
                            Argentine newsmen because, he said, the press was controlled by the
                            government, he flew off to embrace <persName corresp="#p_SA2">Stroessner</persName>, the military dictator par excellence who
                            controls the press of his country with an iron hand.</p>
                        <p>4. Indeed, if anyone came away from the Peron visit looking really good
                            it was President <persName corresp="#p_LA1">Lanusse</persName>. There
                            could be no doubt that in the personal duel between the two, Lanusse had
                            the better of it. If during the first few days after Nov 17 Lanusse had
                            to guard his flanks against a nervous officer corps unhappy over Peron’s
                            return and uncertain Lanusse knew what he was doing, by the time Peron
                            departed Lanusse’s stock with his brother officers—and with much of the
                            Argentine population—had soared. His press conference was a notable
                            success. The military were congratulating themselves over “their”
                            successful gamble that Peron’s return would lead not to chaos, as had
                            been predicted for years, but to a diminution of his image. If Lanusse
                            can now get the country to honest elections and bring about something
                            resembling a national solution, his place in Argentine history is
                            assured. More than that, his enhanced stature makes him a potential
                            figure for the future—though not as a candidate for the March 1973
                            elections. Indeed, with reference to the latter <pb facs="d76-4" n="4" xml:id="pg_d76-4"/> point, his improved image is based at least in
                            part on a growing conviction among the people that he means what he says
                            and will not be a candidate. Lanusse has emerged as Argentina’s man of
                            the year.</p>
                        <p>4. The return was not however, a matter of all pluses for one and all
                            minuses for the other. Peron had his gains too. First of all, he did
                            come back—after most people had said he would not and after Lanusse had
                            said he didn’t have the guts. His image may have suffered during his
                            some 27 days in Argentina, but it might have suffered even more had he
                            not come. Many were saying that he had either to take up the
                            government’s challenge and come back or face a total eclipse as a
                            political figure on the Argentine stage. Even in sophisticated
                            Argentina, nothing can be more politically damaging than having one’s
                            manliness called into question. Further, while his hold on the political
                            levers was seen to be no longer altogether confident or compelling, he
                            nonetheless demonstrated that he still has a talent for political
                            maneuvering and enough clout and presence to impose his wishes not only
                            upon his own movement but on other political leaders as well. Leading
                            politicians flocked to see him upon his return and after only three days
                            in the country he had managed to convince all the significant political
                            parties to join his justicialistas in a front which was to work out a
                            coincidence of views and which incidentally backed some of his demands
                            to the government. This front eventually collapsed when the UCR left its
                            ranks, but it was replaced by the formation of an electoral alliance,
                            the Frente Justicialista de Liberacion. Granted that it is not the broad
                            alliance he had hoped for; with the exception of MID, the parties it
                            comprises are minor ones. Moreover, its cohesiveness is highly
                            questionable. Some of its components appear already to be leaving its
                            ranks because of quarrels over candidates. But if the race is a close
                            one, the votes of those who stay will not be without significance. Their
                            support, moreover, is probably more valued in the psychological sense as
                            an indication that the Peronists do not stand alone.</p>
                        <pb facs="d76-5" n="5" xml:id="pg_d76-5"/>
                        <p>5. Finally, Peron will probably succeed in imposing the candidate of his
                            choice upon his movement—if not, indeed, upon Argentina. Many—the
                            Mission included—had believed Campora’s unpopularity within the
                            movement, with its implications for fragmentation and loss of votes,
                            would dissuade Peron From giving him the nod. In the end, Peron
                            responded not to external pressures or to the logic of the situation but
                            to his own personal interests and wishes. Campora’s candidacy has
                            already caused discontent and fracturing within the movement and may
                            cause more. So far, however, the evidence does not suggest that
                            Peronismo is disintegrating. Some followers will drop away (perhaps even
                            enough of them so that Peronist chances at the polls will be seriously
                            jeopardized), and there will be a period of quarreling and ill will
                            between those who remain. The labor sector, however, already gives
                            evidence of falling in line and some of the Embassy’s Peronist contacts
                            who a month ago swore they would never vote for Campora, are now saying
                            they will, albeit sadly. When all is said and done, the majority of
                            Peronists are likely to remain within the movement and on March 11 will
                            vote for Campora, if only because Peron tells them to (assuming Campora
                            is still the candidate: the courts have not yet ruled on whether or not
                            the Aug 25 clause applies to him, and it is still possible Peron is <pb facs="d76-6" n="6" xml:id="pg_d76-6"/> using him as a stalking
                            horse). This is compelling evidence of the hold the man still has over
                            “his people”—be it for good or bad. At the same time, however, it is
                            equally clear that his word is no longer enough to guarantee victory.
                            Campora may be the candidate, but he may not win. He has the reputation
                            of being a lightweight. Indeed, this is said to be one reason Peron
                            dumped the personable paladino as his personal representative in favor
                            of Campora.</p>
                        <p>6. We believe Peron’s decision to designate Campora represented an effort
                            to solve as best he could the dilemma of how to give the nod to someone
                            else (given that he himself did not want, or cannot have, the cares and
                            responsibilities of the presidency) without in so doing creating a
                            challenger to his position as head of the movement. With Campora, who is
                            widely regarded as little more than a creature of Peron with no mind of
                            his owns he hopes to have it both ways. Campora may become President,
                            but he will do as Peron says and will not challenge him for leadership
                            of the movement.</p>
                        <p>7. Essentially, then, Campora’s appointment itself had little to do with
                            the return. Peron could have as easily appointed him from Madrid. Many
                            Peronists had felt the leader would return, if for no other reason, in
                            order to stand before his followers and put his arm around the shoulders
                            of a successor. Without this public embrace, they reasoned, many of the
                            movements disparate sectors would not accept a new candidate. In the
                            event, however, Peron left Argentina without having given that
                            embrace—though had he done so some of the fragmentation might have been
                            avoided. Presumably he will give Campora a belated public abrazo when he
                            returns in January (assuming that he does return), but by then most of
                            the damage will have been done. One can only surmise that in this, as in
                            the decision to go with Campora, Peron put his own interests above those
                            of the movement. Knowing the appointment would be unpopular and possibly
                            unacceptable to the military, he chose not to associate himself with it
                            publicly. Ostensibly, it was the justicialista Congress which designated
                            Campora: Peron simply accepted their choice. If something goes wrong, it
                            will be the muchachos, not Peron, who will take the blame.</p>
                        <p>8. The choice of Campora leads to another conclusion: That Peron’s return
                            produced no agreement with the military <pb facs="d76-7" n="7" xml:id="pg_d76-7"/> candidates. Before his arrival, the Mission,
                            along with many other observers, had believed he would not come back
                            unless some agreement had been reached or was near. It was even expected
                            that during his stay he would formalize such an accord and announce his
                            support for a candidate mutually acceptable to the military and the
                            Peronists. While the logic of the situation seemed to dictate this kind
                            of agreement, the evidence now indicates there was none.</p>
                        <p>9. The military wanted an accord, for if they are to bring about the kind
                            of stable, majority government they have promised, they need Peronist
                            participation in the elections; yet, to reduce the possibilities of a
                            “leap into the void”, they wished to have prior understandings regarding
                            programs and candidates. The lines of communication between Peron and
                            the military were open after return and there were exchanges. It was
                            even expected that Peron would meet directly with Lanusse to negotiate a
                            mutually acceptable candidate. In the end, however, nothing came of all
                            this. Peronists say it was because of military inflexibility: the
                            military would doubtless say the same of Peron. Mutual recriminations
                            aside, the heart of the matter may be that Peron concluded he did not
                            need to reach agreement in order to get his justicialistas into the
                            elections (and he definitely seems to want them to participate).
                            Intelligence sources indicated that on or about 5 December, exchanges
                            were broken by the Peronists. The military might drop dire hints about
                            cancelling elections unless there is a coincidence of views and an
                            “acceptable” candidate. In fact, however, as Peron may well have
                            surmised, they would be extremely reluctant to call off the elections at
                            this late date even if the justicialista candidate did not enjoy their
                            prior approval. In other words, as Peron probably saw it, the military
                            needed Peronist participation in the elections more than the Peronists
                            needed an accord with the military. Sensing that he could have the one
                            without the other, Peron avoided an agreement and unilaterally
                            designated. Campora, a figure for whom the military would never
                            willingly have given their prior approval.</p>
                        <p>10. Even in flying off to Paraguay and leaving the political scene in a
                            turmoil, then, Peron demonstrated that he still has <pb facs="d76-8" n="8" xml:id="pg_d76-8"/> a deft touch for keeping his adversaries
                            guessing and on the defensive and that, while he no longer controls
                            Argentina’s political destinies, he has the power to influence their
                            form and substance.</p>
                        <p>11. Whatever the results for Peron himself, or for his movement, his
                            return was without question a positive development for Argentina. When
                            it came, the country took it very much in stride, suggesting that while
                            the divisions and bitterness are still there, they exist in an
                            attenuated form. Argentina appears to be no longer an intensely
                            polarized country. Galimberti and his ilk caused some problems but did
                            not receive the support of the Peronist majority. And if the Peronists
                            turned out to be no longer the fanatical mass they once were,
                            anti-Peronist sentiment was also seen to represent a pale reflection of
                            what it once was. Admiral Rojas and other hard-line anti-Peronists did,
                            to be sure hold a number of rallies and issue statements denouncing the
                            ex-dictator’s return. Few attended the rallies or heeded the statements,
                            however. There are, in other words, still those on both sides who would
                            go to extremes, but they no longer control, or even influence to any
                            significant degree, the majority.</p>
                        <p>12. Argentina’s future is as yet by no means clear or assured. Much can
                            happen between now and the March 11 elections-and even after (and if) a
                            new government takes power, its tenure may well be precarious for some
                            time to come. Nor, needless to say, is Campora a candidate who inspires
                            much confidence. Nonetheless, the shadow which has hung over this
                            country for seventeen years is dissolving. Hopefully, Argentina is
                            entering a new era.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_LJD1"><hi rend="strong">Lodge</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>