<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. White to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1901</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d153</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">153</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-05-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-05-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recmfcinSDrMZ1ErC" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2016000766"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Decline</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-05-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-05-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="153"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d153">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">White</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy of the United States of America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-05-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 4, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1624.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to transmit herewith a report
                    made to me to-day by Mr. Jackson (to whom the instruction was addressed) with
                    reference to your No. 1189, of April 15, 1901, which was received at the embassy
                    on the 26th ultimo.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Andrew D. White.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Jackson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">White</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy of the United States of America</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-05-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 4, 1901</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the State Department’s
                        instruction No. 1189, received by me on the 26th ultimo, I have the honor to
                        submit the following report:</p>
                    <p>After more than ten years’ experience at this post, and after having had
                        frequent conversations with my colleagues and with German officials upon the
                        subject of the expulsion of former German subjects, I feel at liberty to say
                        with positiveness that there is no intention on the part of the Prussian
                        Government to discriminate against American citizens. In the question under
                        consideration it is very difficult to draw a parallel. In the first place,
                        no other treaty similar to our Bancroft treaties of 1868 exists between the
                        German Empire, or any German State, and any foreign country. In the second
                        place, obligatory military service exists in almost all continental
                        countries, <pb facs="0258" n="178" xml:id="pg_178"/> and consequently the
                        emigration of young Germans to those countries is not considerable.
                        Moreover, with many of these countries informal understandings, or even
                        formal agreements, exist, in accordance with which their respective
                        nationals are reciprocally handed over to their home authorities where an
                        attempt is made to evade military service. Where no treaty exists the
                        returned German is not considered as entitled to be protected by the
                        authorities of the country in which he has acquired nationality, and he is
                        generally punished in accordance with German law without any intervention on
                        their part. This is even the case with British subjects, the Department of
                        State being probably aware of the fact that it is the general practice of
                        the British Government to decline to intervene in behalf of a naturalized
                        subject who returns to the land of his birth. As there is no compulsory
                        military service in Great Britain, there is a comparatively large emigration
                        of Germans to that country, but, as I am informed by the British ambassador
                        here, it rarely happens that intervention is made in behalf of such a person
                        (even to ask for permission for one to spend a few weeks in Germany, on a
                        visit, or to make a cure at some watering place), although the instances
                        where they get into trouble are by no means infrequent.</p>
                    <p>The general rule is to make it unpleasant for all persons of German birth who
                        have evaded military service in their native country, whether their
                        emigration took place for the purpose of evading such service or not, upon
                        their return to Germany after having acquired another nationality, it being
                        held by the authorities, especially those in Prussia, that the sojourn of
                        such persons for any length of time causes discontent and dissatisfaction
                        among their companions of the same age who have remained at home. It is of
                        course possible that certain of the minor local officials may entertain
                        particular grudges against American citizens of German origin on account of
                        the frequency with which they have to do with annoying cases where they are
                        involved, but I am confident that these views are not shared by the superior
                        officials of the Prussian ministry of the interior, or at all generally by
                        their subordinates.</p>
                    <p>With regard to the order in the case of Albert Ehrenstroem (see
                        correspondence with Mr. George M. Murphy, consular clerk) and to the recent
                        general order, I have to state that I have been informed by the Prussian
                        ministry of the interior that attention has been merely called to what has
                        been the practice for a long time, so that persons who do not know that
                        objection exists to their renewing their residence in Germany may not be
                        subjected to hardship.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John B. Jackson</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Secretary of Embassy.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
