<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Jackson to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1901</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">174</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recx2BQCN6uKMR53J" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005907"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Emigration</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-10-25T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-10-25T00:00:00-05:00" n="174"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d174">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Jackson</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berlin</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-10-25">
                            <hi rend="italic">October 25, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1773.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As the Department is aware, efforts have
                    repeatedly been made to direct the flow of German emigration away from North
                    America, the United States, and Canada, toward the German colonies and South
                    America. It is claimed that in North America the emigrant is too readily
                    absorbed and that he loses his political and economic nationality in a very
                    short time, while in the colonies he remains a German in every sense, and in
                    South America he still retains, to a considerable extent at least, his German
                    tastes and habits. In short, the emigrant to North America is lost to Germany
                    entirely, while those who go to South America, although they may lose their
                    political nationality, continue to be purchasers in the German markets. It will
                    be remembered that arguments of this character were used in advocating the
                    passage of an emigration law in 1897.</p>
                <p>Germany is at present suffering from industrial depression, the eventual result
                    of which can not but be healthy, and the immediate effect of this is almost
                    certain to be increased emigration in the near future. The condition is such
                    that the president of the Prussian ministry (Count Bülow) has thought it wise to
                    instruct the provincial governors to collect information with regard to the
                    numbers of the unemployed and to suggest measures by which aid can be given.</p>
                <p>The Colonial Society, however, has determined to endeavor to direct the
                    emigration which it considers inevitable, and to that end it has made a
                    provisional arrangement with the Imperial Government for the establishment of an
                    information bureau for emigrants. This bureau is to be under the supervision of
                    the chancellor of the Empire, although its character will not be strictly
                    official, and information is to be furnished by it gratuitously to intending
                    emigrants, directly or through agents. The Government is to bear a part of the
                    expenses connected with this work, and is to furnish to the bureau such
                    information as may be received from its representatives abroad as may be of
                    interest to those wishing to make a home outside the limits of the Empire
                    proper. The avowed object of this enterprise is “to prevent the dissipation of
                    the energy, nationality, and capital which German emigrants take out of the
                    Empire, uselessly throughout the world, and the economic fertilization of
                    foreign countries, and to so direct German emigration that it may remain German,
                    nationally and economically, to the greatest possible extent.”</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John B. Jackson.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
