<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>message from the president of the united states, transmitting a convention
                    between the united states and great britain, to facilitae the construction of a
                    ship canal to connect the atlantic and pacific oceans, signed at washington,
                    november 18, 1901. 18, 1901.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1901</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">233</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recFftkqOQqJGLNur" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007662"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Regulation</term>
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace">Peace</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recBzwLUMaXbUZIf3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-12-04T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-12-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="233"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d233">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">message from the president of the united states,
                        transmitting a convention between the united states and great britain, to
                        facilitae the construction of a ship canal to connect the atlantic and
                        pacific oceans, signed at washington, november</hi> 18, 1901.</head>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">December</hi> 4, 1901.—Read; treaty read the first time and
                    referred to the Committee on Foreign Relations and, together with the message,
                    ordered to be printed in confidence for the use of the Senate.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">December</hi> 9, 1901.—Reported without amendment.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">December</hi> 10. 1901.—Injunction of secrecy removed.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">December</hi> 16, 1901.—Ratified; injunction of secrecy
                    removed from proposed amendments and votes thereon, and vote of
                    ratification.</p>
                <p>Amendments appear in italics.</p>
                <p>Article III was stricken out by Senate.</p>
                <pb facs="0324" n="244" xml:id="pg_244"/>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">To the Senate:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>I transmit, for the advice and consent of the Senate to its ratification, a
                    convention signed November 18, 1901, by the respective plenipotentiaries of the
                    United States and Great Britain to facilitate the construction of a ship canal
                    to connect the Atlantic and Pacific oceans by whatever route may be considered
                    expedient, and to that end to remove any objection which may arise out of the
                    convention of April 19, 1850, commonly called the Clayton-Bulwer treaty, to the
                    construction of such canal under the auspices of the Government of the United
                    States, without impairing the “general principle” of neutralization established
                    in Article VIII of that convention.</p>
                <p>I also inclose a report from the Secretary of State, submitting the convention
                    for my consideration.</p>
                <closer>
                    <seg rend="right">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Theodore Roosevelt.</hi>
                    </seg>
                    <lb/>
                    <dateline rendition="#left">
                        <placeName>
                            <placeName type="venue">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">White House</hi>
                            </placeName>, <lb/>
                            <placeName type="city">
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-12-04">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 4, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">The President</hi>:</p>
                    <p>I submit for your consideration and for transmission to the Senate, should
                        you deem it proper to do so, with a view to obtaining the advice and consent
                        of that body to its ratification, a convention signed November 18, 1901, by
                        the respective plenipotentiaries of the United States and Great Britain to
                        facilitate the construction of a ship canal to connect the Atlantic and
                        Pacific oceans by whatever route may be considered expedient, and to that
                        end to remove any objection which may arise out of the convention of April
                        19, 1850, commonly called the Clayton-Bulwer treaty, to the construction of
                        such canal under the auspices of the Government of the United States,
                        without impairing the “general principle” of neutralization established in
                        Article VIII of that convention.</p>
                    <closer> Respectfully submitted. <lb/>
                        <signed rend="right">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>, <lb/>
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-12-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">December 2, 1901</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <p>The United States of America and His Majesty Edward the Seventh, of the
                        United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, and of the British Dominions
                        beyond the Seas, King, and Emperor of India, being desirous to facilitate
                        the construction of a ship canal to connect the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans,
                        by whatever route may be considered expedient, and to that end to remove any
                        objection which may arise out of the Convention of the 19th April, 1850,
                        commonly called the Clayton-Bulwer Treaty, to the construction of such canal
                        under the auspices of the Government of the United States, without impairing
                        the “general principle” of neutralization established in Article VIII of
                        that Convention, have for that purpose appointed as their Plenipotentiaries: <list>
                            <item>The President of the United States, John Hay, Secretary of State
                                of the United States of America;</item>
                            <item>And his Majesty Edward the Seventh, of the United Kingdom of Great
                                Britain and Ireland, and of the British Dominions beyond the Seas,
                                King, and Emperor of India, the Right Honourable Lord Pauncefote, G.
                                C. B., G. C. M. G., His Majesty’s Ambassador Extraordinary and
                                Plenipotentiary to the United States;</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Who, having communicated to each other their full powers, which were found to
                        be in due and proper form, have agreed upon the following Articles:</p>
                    <pb facs="0325" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article I</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The high contracting parties agree that the present treaty shall supersede
                        the afore-mentioned convention of the 19th April, 1850.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article II</hi>.</p>
                    <p>It is agreed that the canal may be constructed under the auspices of the
                        Government of the United States either directly at its own cost, or by gift
                        or loan of money to individuals or corporations, or through subscription to
                        or purchase of stock or shares, and that, subject to the provisions of the
                        present treaty, the said Government shall have and enjoy all the rights
                        incident to such construction, as well as the exclusive right of providing
                        for the regulation and management of the canal.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article III</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The United States adopts, as the basis of the neutralization of such ship
                        canal, the following rules, substantially as embodied in the Convention of
                        Constantinople, signed the 28th October, 1888, for the free navigation of
                        the Suez Canal, that is to say: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The canal shall be free and open to the vessels of commerce and of
                                war of all nations observing these Rules, on terms of entire
                                equality, so that there shall be no discrimination against any such
                                nation, or its citizens or subjects, in respect of the conditions or
                                charges of traffic or otherwise. Such conditions and charges of
                                traffic shall be just and equitable.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The canal shall never be blockaded, nor shall any right of war be
                                exercised nor any act of hostility be committed within it. The
                                United States, however, shall be at liberty to maintain such
                                military police along the canal as may be necessary to protect it
                                against lawlessness and disorder.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Vessels of war of a belligerent shall not re victual nor take any
                                stores in the canal except so far as may be strictly necessary; and
                                the transit of such vessels through the canal shall be effected with
                                the least possible delay in accordance with the Regulations in
                                force, and with only such intermission as may result from the
                                necessities of the service.</item>
                            <label/>
                            <item>Prizes shall be in all respects subject to the same rules as
                                vessels of war of the belligerents.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>No belligerent shall embark or disembark troops, munitions of war,
                                or warlike materials in the canal, except in case of accidental
                                hindrance of the transit, and in such case the transit shall be
                                resumed with all possible dispatch.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>The provisions of this article shall apply to waters adjacent to
                                the canal, within 3 marine miles of either end. Vessels of war of a
                                belligerent shall not remain in such waters longer than twenty-four
                                hours at any one time, except in case of distress, and in such case
                                shall depart as soon as possible; but a vessel of war of one
                                belligerent shall not depart within twenty-four hours from the
                                departure of a vessel of war of the other belligerent.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>The plant, establishments, buildings, and all works necessary to
                                the construction, maintenance, and operation of the canal shall be
                                deemed to be part thereof, for the purposes of this treaty, and in
                                time of war, as in time of peace, shall enjoy complete immunity from
                                attack or injury by belligerents, and from acts calculated to impair
                                their usefulness as part of the canal.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <pb facs="0326" n="246" xml:id="pg_246"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article IV</hi>.</p>
                    <p>It is agreed that no change of territorial sovereignty or of international
                        relations of the country or countries traversed by the before-mentioned
                        canal shall affect the general principle of neutralization or the obligation
                        of the high contracting parties under the present treaty.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Article V</hi>.</p>
                    <p>The present treaty shall be ratified by the President of the United States,
                        by and with the advice and consent of the Senate thereof, and by His
                        Britannic Majesty; and the ratifications shall be exchanged at Washington or
                        at London at the earliest possible time within six months from the date
                        hereof.</p>
                    <p>In faith whereof the respective plenipotentiaries have signed this treaty and
                        hereunto affixed their seals.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">Done in duplicate at
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1901-11-18">the 18th day of November, in the year of our Lord
                                one thousand nine hundred and one</date>.</dateline>
                        <lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay.</hi>
                        </signed> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]<lb/>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Pauncefote.</hi>
                        </signed> [<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]</closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
