<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-07-30T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-07-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="269" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d269">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Adee</persName> to Signor
                                    <persName type="to">Carignani</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-07-30"><hi rend="italic">July 30,
                                1901</hi></date>.</dateline>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 694.]</seg></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your note of the 22d instant in further reference to the
                            murder of Italians at Erwin, Miss.</p>
                        <p>You communicate a copy of the record of the inquest embodying the finding
                            of the jury in this regrettable affair, and state that on account of the
                            strange wording of the document you deem it expedient to bring it to the
                            attention of the Department.</p>
                        <p>While the finding of the coroner’s jury is perhaps, as you state,
                            somewhat unusual in phraseology, it is in effect the finding customary
                            in such cases when the evidence at the inquest does not disclose to the
                            jury the authors of the homicide. The effect of the finding is to
                            devolve upon the judicial authorities of the State further investigation
                                <pb facs="0373" n="293" xml:id="pg_293"/> of the case with a view to
                            discovering and punishing the perpetrators of the crime. It leaves the
                            way open for the usual course of justice in endeavoring to ascertain the
                            “parties unknown.”</p>
                        <p>Not being advised up to the time of writing that the perpetrators of the
                            crime had been arrested, you inquire whether it might not facilitate the
                            cause of justice if the Federal Government should send a “detective” to
                            the spot for the “detection of the lynchers.”</p>
                        <p>A suggestion to substantially the same effect was made by Baron Fava
                            pending the consideration of the Tallulah incident in 1899. Baron Fava,
                            in a telegram dated September 21 of that year, expressed the hope that
                            the special agent appointed by the Department would “discover and
                            denounce the criminals.” I replied, on the same date, that “in the
                            actual status of the matter and in the absence of Federal jurisdiction
                            over an offense committed in a State,” the agent sent to Tallulah could
                            not assert any part in the local administration of justice, but was sent
                            merely to collect information for the Department’s consideration and
                            such action as might be in order.</p>
                        <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                        <p>The governor of Mississippi has assured me of his purpose to enforce the
                            laws by all means within his power, and I am informed that the
                            universally expressed sentiment of the community where the murders
                            occurred deplores the crime and shows a determination to aid in the
                            discovery and punishment of the perpetrators.</p>
                        <p>Be pleased, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Alvey A. Adee</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Acting Secretary.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>