<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Wilson to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1901</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">315</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-02-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-02-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="recwpTEN3doKKS5lb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85062894"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Settlements</term>
                    <term ref="recOAfZ9FRSJKK76a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Income tax</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007884"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Expenditures</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-02-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-02-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="315"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d315">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokyo, Japan</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-02-08">
                            <hi rend="italic">February 8, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 539.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to confirm your telegraphic
                        instruction<note n="a" xml:id="d315fna">Printed ante.</note> of the 28th
                    ultimo.</p>
                <p>On the 31st ultimo I handed to the minister for foreign affairs a signed
                    memorandum, copy of which is herewith inclosed, embodying the contents of the
                    above instruction. I also inclose a copy of Mr. Kato’s reply, in which he
                    expresses his preparedness to enter into an examination of the questions
                    indicated when a detailed expression of the views of the Government of the
                    United States shall have been received.</p>
                <p>Viscount Aoki’s note of January 15 to the British minister (quoted in inclosure
                    with Mr. Buck’s No. 398, of February 5, 1900), and his note to the French
                    minister, dated February 26, 1900 (inclosure with Mr. Buck’s No. 417, of April
                    17, 1900), seem to contain in effect such an authoritative interpretation. I
                    apprehend that the minister for foreign affairs would willingly give a still
                    more emphatic and unequivocal interpretation, which, whatever might be the
                    future rulings of law courts, would protect leaseholders from damage by making
                    the Government of Japan responsible. However, it is probable that, to end the
                    great dissatisfaction on this score, exact registration of perpetual leases in
                    terms as such and only such will be provided for by law.</p>
                <p>I believe that the Japanese Government will not concede that buildings which
                    stand on land held under perpetual lease should for that reason be exempted from
                    the house tax or from any other charges to which buildings in general are
                    liable.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to confirm also your telegraphic instruction<note n="a"
                        xml:id="d315fnb">Printed ante.</note> received the 2d instant.</p>
                <p>Accordingly, in a note dated the 5th, copy of which is herewith, I made the above
                    request to the Japanese Government.</p>
                <p>In reference to Mr. Buck’s No. 532, no reply has yet been received to his note to
                    Mr. Kato dated January 1, designed to hold the Japanese Government to the
                    foreign office’s interpretation of the last clause of article 1 of ordinance No.
                    458, which interpretation (in inclosure with Mr. Buck’s No. 526, of December 14)
                    appears to be authoritative.</p>
                <pb facs="0432" n="352" xml:id="pg_352"/>
                <p>Shortly before January 1 the British, French, and German ministers sent three
                    practically identical, notes on the same subject, but further strongly
                    protesting against the Japanese Government’s refusal to prolong the time beyond
                    December 31. Day before yesterday they received Mr. Kato’s replies. That to the
                    British minister, which I have read, points out that the clause objected to was
                    inserted as an act of grace, upon the written request of Sir Ernest Satow, for
                    the purpose of allowing ample time for absentees to secure by registration the
                    priority of such rights as subleases, mortgages, etc., already held.</p>
                <p>The Japanese Government are now engaged in preparing for presentation to the
                    present session of the Diet (which terminates on March 24) a bill whose object
                    is said to be to clear up, so far as possible, those points in all matters
                    connected with the immunities and obligations of holders of perpetual leases in
                    the former settlements, which, under the new treaties, are now uncertain or
                    disputed. What the bill will decide—which it will concede by its provisions and
                    which it will refuse by silence—of all the changes asked for by the foreigners
                    is not shown, since the authorities insist that the bill remain secret until
                    actually laid before the Diet.</p>
                <p rend="center">* * * * * * *</p>
                <p>Many months ago the French, German, and British representatives, under
                    instructions from their Governments, claimed, as well as immunity from all
                    charges against lands held under perpetual leases, immunity from the house tax
                    and from all other charges against buildings standing on such lands. Their
                    position remains unchanged. They contend that the buildings are “part and parcel
                    of the lands.”</p>
                <p>The present French position differs from the British and German in that the
                    French minister goes so far as to claim that income tax may not be levied on
                    income derived from property held under the perpetual leases, probably meaning
                    the houses included.</p>
                <p>In the German position there is a point not dwelt upon by others, based on the
                    fifth paragraph of Article XVIII of the German treaty. It is: That the perpetual
                    leaseholds may now be sold to Japanese without becoming, by the process, titles
                    in fee simple (as well as to any foreigners). If the German treaty secures this
                    right contrary to the conditions of the original leases, then Imperial ordinance
                    No. 333, of July 7, 1899, appears to conflict with that treaty. It seems that
                    this right would widen the market for selling the leases and would prevent the
                    settlement properties from getting irrevocably out of the hands of foreigners,
                    who could not own them in fee simple.</p>
                <p>The Germans rely upon paragraph 4 of Baron von Marschall’s note of April 4, 1896,
                    to secure forever, irrespective of the lapse of their treaty, any rights
                    acquired before or during its operation.</p>
                <p>Neither the British, French, nor German representative has yet received a
                    definite reply to his representations.</p>
                <p>An unfortunate misunderstanding, by which it has been widely believed that
                    buildings must always be registered, has been brought about by a mistake in Dr.
                    Loenholm’s translation of the law of registration and by the fact that there are
                    separate registry books for land and for buildings. I have the honor to inclose
                    herewith the translation of law<note n="a" xml:id="d315fnc">Not printed.</note>
                    referred to, with the mistake indicated. From that <pb facs="0433" n="353"
                        xml:id="pg_353"/> law—particularly from article 106, for example—it appears
                    that the holder of a perpetual lease to a lot who owns the house thereon is
                    quite safe in the ownership of his house without registering it. I may here add
                    that the Japanese themselves ordinarily do not register their houses if they own
                    the land upon which those houses stand.</p>
                <p>The best support of the argument that the houses and lands are regarded by the
                    treaties as one is thought to be contained in Article XXI of the French treaty.
                    But as the houses were not in existence when the leases were made, and never
                    belonged to the Japanese Government, it is difficult to understand how they can
                    be considered as properties held under (en vertu de) leases in which the
                    Japanese Government is the lessor.</p>
                <p>Since under the old system the foreign communities assessed themselves for
                    keeping the streets in order and for lighting, policing, etc., it may be claimed
                    that with the transfer of that duty to the Japanese authorities there goes also
                    a certain right to tax; and since the necessity of such expenditure depends upon
                    the buildings, house taxes may perhaps be regarded to some extent as moneys to
                    meet those expenditures. It is certain that the foreign quarters cost the
                    authorities much more than the Japanese quarters do.</p>
                <p>It is of interest to note that, even with the present taxable valuation, shrunk
                    by the settlement properties increase in value to only about one-sixth of the
                    actual value, the land tax alone would be much greater than the ground rent. I
                    hope soon to be able to give some statistics on this point.</p>
                <p>Then, if it should be decided that the land only is referred to in the treaties,
                    it is to be subject to no imposts, etc., further than those expressly stipulated
                    in the leases, i. e., than the annual rent.</p>
                <p>Under ordinance No. 458 transfers of property held under perpetual leases are
                    registered without charge.</p>
                <p>It is understood that transfers of such property by bequest are likewise
                    registered free. As the title deeds were granted to those who originally
                    received them, and to their heirs and assigns, this seems to be secured by the
                    terms of the leases.</p>
                <p>It may possibly be questioned, on the ground that registration is part of the
                    general municipal system under which foreigners have come, whether the
                    registration of mortgages upon and of subleases of property held under perpetual
                    leases should be free. Under the old treaties equitable mortgages were mostly
                    made use of, but ordinary mortgages could be registered at the consulate, the
                    parties thus acquiring a secondary protection in case the original documents
                    could not be produced. As a satisfactory degree of safety was obtained in the
                    old way, although the new way, involving, like all Japanese registration, which
                    is after the Torrens system of Australia, the courts affirming the validity of
                    the right registered, provides the greatest degree of safety, yet the imposition
                    of taxes upon any registrations in which property held under perpetual leases is
                    alone concerned seems to be an additional burden on such property and to be
                    contrary to the treaties.</p>
                <p>From what I hear I think that the Japanese Government will exempt lands held
                    under perpetual leases from all charges of every kind; but that they will not
                    admit that houses standing upon such lands are for that reason to be exempted
                    from the various charges to which any other houses are liable.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington Wilson</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0434" n="354" xml:id="pg_354"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Koto</persName>, Japanese minister for foreign
                            affairs.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Memorandum.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Pending the receipt of fuller expression of the views of his Government, the
                        undersigned chargé d’affaires ad interim of the United States, has the honor
                        to hand this memorandum to his excellency His Imperial Japanese Majesty’s
                        minister for foreign affairs.</p>
                    <p>The registration as superficies of title to perpetual leases is not
                        acceptable to the Government of the United States without some authoritative
                        interpretation of the Japanese Government that the title under that style is
                        not inferior to that of the perpetual lease.</p>
                    <p>The Government of the United States are not now prepared to concede that
                        buildings on perpetual lease are subject to taxation not specified in the
                        original lease.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington Wilson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Kato</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Wilson</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-02-02">
                                <hi rend="italic">February 2, 1901</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>The minister for foreign affairs has the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
                        a memorandum which the chargé d’affaires of the United States was good
                        enough to hand to him on the 31st ultimo, in anticipation of a fuller
                        expression of the views of the United States Government on the subject of
                        the registration of perpetual leases and the taxation of buildings on
                        perpetual lease.</p>
                    <p>Upon the receipt of such detailed expression of views, the minister for
                        foreign affairs will be prepared to enter into an examination of the
                        questions which are briefly described in the memorandum under
                        acknowledgement.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wilson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Kato</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-02-05">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">February</hi> 5, 1901</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Monsieur le Ministre</hi>: Under telegraphic
                        instructions from the Secretary of State, I have the honor to request,
                        through your excellency, on behalf of the Government of the United States,
                        that the Imperial Japanese Government be so good as to further withhold
                        their decision on the questions of property leases, their registration,
                        etc., until the Department of State can have time to prepare and forward its
                        views.</p>
                    <p>Trusting that I shall soon be able to make to your excellency more detailed
                        communication of my Government’s position on all the allied questions
                        indicated above,</p>
                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Huntington Wilson.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
