<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>note verbale.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1901</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d320</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">320</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006004"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Health</term>
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037040"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Deportation</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064675"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Imprisonment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-04-30T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-04-30T00:00:00-05:00" n="320"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d320">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">note verbale.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Japanese Legation</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-04-30">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 30, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>According to the information brought to the attention of Japanese minister by Mr.
                    Shimiza, His Imperial Japanese Majesty’s consul at Vancouver, it appears that a
                    party consisting of 13 Japanese subjects, <pb facs="0447" n="367"
                        xml:id="pg_367"/> who started from Victoria on the 15th of March last for
                    Seattle, State of Washington, arriving there on the following day, was refused
                    landing at the latter port, and after having been imprisoned in a jail from the
                    day of arrival until their reembarkation finally ordered to be deported on board
                    the vessel which had carried them thither to the place whence they came. It was
                    not disputed in any way that every one of the Japanese was in good physical
                    condition, holding a health certificate prepared by a licensed physician just
                    before his departure, and being in bona fide possession of the amount of money
                    required by law; and the only ground for the refusal of his landing and
                    subsequent deportation seems to be that he would be unable to support himself.
                    Another group of Japanese subjects of 7 in number who arrived at Seattle from
                    Vancouver on the 17th of the same month met the same fate, receiving exactly
                    similar treatment. The consul adds that upon an examination of the persons
                    concerned, which was conducted at the consulate after their deportation, they
                    were all found well clad, robust, and of sound mind.</p>
                <p>In view of the foregoing facts, the Japanese minister begs leave to say that
                    these Japanese subjects having possessed the necessary qualifications and
                    fulfilled all conditions requirid by law, he is at a loss to find the reason why
                    they should have been refused landing, inasmuch as no more qualifications or
                    conditions, by virtue of the treaty between the two countries, are to be imposed
                    on the Japanese subjects than those required of other alien citizens or subjects
                    for landing at the United States ports; and even admitting that the Japanese now
                    under consideration were refused to land at the port for the lack of certain
                    qualifications or conditions to meet the requirements of law, he can not
                    perceive any reason for the restriction of personal liberty imposed upon them
                    without due process of law by confining them in a jail, where, according to a
                    statement made by some of them, they were compelled to share company in the same
                    apartment with certain convicts under the sentence of imprisonment.</p>
                <p>Under these circumstances the Japanese minister has the honor to request that the
                    honorable the Secretary of State will have the goodness to cause investigations
                    to be made upon the matter to the end that proper measures may be taken should
                    the facts reported be found correct.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
