<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Wu to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1901</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">75</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1901-04-11T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1901-04-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98002548"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Immigration</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1901-04-11T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1901-04-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="75"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d75">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Wu</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Chinese Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1901-04-11">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 11, 1901</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 203.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In your note of the 2d ultimo, in which you did
                    me the honor to reply to my notes respecting the conduct of the customs
                    inspectors and other officials of your Government at San Francisco in the
                    enforcement of the Chinese immigration treaty and laws, you ask for more
                    specific information on the subject, in order that their conduct may be
                    investigated.</p>
                <p>The charge in my note of December 26 last was that the inspectors were generally
                    unfriendly, if not positively hostile, to all Chinese subjects applying for
                    admission to the United States. In my note of November 30 last I alleged that
                    the subordinate Treasury officials distort the language and defeat the plain
                    intent of the treaty. I respectfully submit that the facts communicated in the
                    notes cited, as well as others of previous dates, fully sustain the charges
                    made, and afford sufficient data to enable the Treasury Department to correct
                    the conduct of the officials mentioned. However, in order to comply with the
                    request contained in your note of the 2d ultimo, I asked of the imperial
                    consul-general in San Francisco further details, and I copy herewith from his
                    report: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Tang Shi Tak, who arrived here on the steamer <hi rend="italic">America
                                Maru</hi> December 22, 1900, ticket No. 34, applied for landing at
                            this port as a teacher, presenting a section 6 certificate issued by the
                            Government at Hongkong. He was denied landing. It appears that he stated
                            that he came here for the purpose of engaging in his profession as a
                            teacher; that a certain firm in this city, giving its name, had secured
                            for him a number of pupils. The Chinese inspector interviewed the firm
                            referred to and they stated that they had secured for this applicant a
                            number of pupils, giving their names and the names of their parents. The
                            inspector interviewed the various persons named and found the statement
                            to be true, excepting that the name of one person could not be found at
                            the address given, and the inspector so reported. He did not, however,
                            report that as regards the other names mentioned the statements were
                            correct. For that reason the case was denied.</p>
                        <p>Yee Sang, a returning Salinas merchant, arriving here on the steamer <hi
                                rend="italic">Doric</hi>, February 1, ticket No. 81, applied for
                            admission at this port after an absence of about <pb facs="0147" n="67"
                                xml:id="pg_67"/> one year. He was denied landing. It appeared from
                            his statement that he had been engaged in mercantile business for a
                            number of years and that his business had been closed out; that he
                            thereupon took an office and conducted the business of the defunct firm,
                            collecting their debts and settling up their liabilities for a period of
                            about a year. He then reengaged in business and continued in the second
                            business for about nine months prior to his leaving for China. Proof was
                            introduced by white witnesses that the man had been a merchant for a
                            great many years prior to his departure for China, and the testimony of
                            the white witnesses complied in all respects with the requirements of
                            the Department.</p>
                        <p>In the case of Cheong In, No. 5, steamer <hi rend="italic">Nippon
                                Maru</hi>, November 12, 1900, the applicants presented two section 6
                            certificates, which certificates were issued by the Government in
                            Hongkong, in due form of law and properly viséed. They presented these
                            certificates at this port and demanded to be landed by reason thereof.
                            The cases were investigated by the customs officials and no statements
                            contained in the certificates were in any way controverted. It appears
                            that the inspector reported that neither of these parties had any money
                            about their person, and for that reason they were denied landing at this
                            port. It did, however, appear from the investigation of the case and the
                            report of the customs officials that certain responsible firms in this
                            city were indebted to the firms of which these applicants were members
                            in China, and that upon the landing of these applicants they would
                            collect this money and would use it, among other purposes, for engaging
                            in business in this city. The amount was considerable, and the stores,
                            upon being interrogated by the Chinese inspectors, corroborated the
                            statements in every particular. The law does not require that a Chinese
                            person seeking admission at this port should be supplied with any
                            particular amount of money, and while it might be argued that a person
                            arriving here without means of any kind could not well be called a
                            merchant, that does not appear in this case, as these applicants had a
                            credit here, or, in other words, responsible firms in this city were
                            indebted to them in various amounts of money.</p>
                        <p>In the case of Woo Chung, No. 10, steamer <hi rend="italic">Coptic</hi>,
                            December 14, 1900, this applicant also presented a section 6 certificate
                            duly issued by the Government at Hongkong and claimed to be a merchant
                            and a member of the exempt class. No fact in his certificate was
                            controverted by the Government officials. In his statement he claimed
                            that what money he needed in this country for the purpose of going into
                            business would be furnished him by a certain firm in this city. That
                            firm was interrogated and corroborated the statement of the applicant,
                            and at the request of the then acting collector of this port the amount
                            of money which the applicant claimed he needed was by the firm placed in
                            the form of a certificate of deposit and exhibited to the collector, who
                            expressed himself as fully satisfied with the case and that the
                            applicant was what he claimed to be. This was a day or two before the
                            expiration of the term of office of the then acting collector, and when
                            the matter was brought up again before the present collector upon a
                            recommendation of Mr. Dunn in this case it was denied, following the
                            recommendations of Mr. Dunn in all cases, good, bad, and
                            indifferent.</p>
                        <p>Cases similar to these could be repeated as long as one had patience to
                            listen to them; but these seem to me fair examples of returning
                            merchants and section 6 cases merchants who have been unlawfully denied
                            admission at this port.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I trust that the foregoing additional facts may be brought to the attention of
                    the honorable Secretary of the Treasury, in the hope that he will issue such
                    instructions as will bring about a more rational and exact compliance with the
                    letter and spirit of the treaty stipulations entered into between the two
                    Governments.</p>
                <p>Accept, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Wu Ting-fang.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
