<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-07-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-07-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="101" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d101">
                        <head>101. Memorandum From the Director of the Office of Philippine and
                            Southeast Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_YKT1" type="from">Young</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of State for Far
                            Eastern Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_RWS1" type="to">Robertson</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d101fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files, 756D.551/7–155.
                                Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-07-01"><hi rend="italic">July 1,
                                1955</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Indonesian Army Commanders’ refusal to accept Cabinet appointed
                                Chief of Staff; No-Confidence Motion against <gloss target="#t_PNI1">PNI</gloss>–<persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> Cabinet
                                re Defense Minister Iwa</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>A most confused situation has developed in Indonesia since June 27 when
                            Territorial Commanders and General Staff refused to accept the
                            designation of Utoyo<note n="2" xml:id="d101fn2">Major General Bambang
                                Utojo was installed as Chief of Staff of the Army on June 27, but
                                Acting Chief of Staff Lubis had refused to turn over the duties of
                                the office to him.</note> (a former Territorial Commander) as Chief
                            of Staff.</p>
                        <p>The Embassy’s principal evaluation of the situation appears in tel. 2588
                                (attached):<note n="3" xml:id="d101fn3">Not attached to the source
                                text and not printed. Telegram 2588 from Djakarta, June 30,
                                concluded that the army was the “most powerful non-Communist or
                                anti-Communist force” in Indonesia. (Department of State, Central
                                Files, 756D.5/6–3055)</note> the elements appear simpler than we
                            might have supposed—although there is no certainty as to what is going
                            on. The demands of the Army to remain out of politics and to improve
                            their professional integrity were agreed to by President <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and other high officials at
                            Jogjakarta in February; the appointment of Utoyo was not in line with
                            that agreement. The Embassy credits Lubis, the Acting Chief of Staff,
                            who has asserted a degree of leadership for the Territorial Commanders,
                            with making his decision in terms of the Jogja Conference. …</p>
                        <p>President <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> according to
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_CHSJ1">Cumming</persName> was led to
                            forcing the Utoyo appointment because he misjudged the strength of Army
                            feeling and solidarity about the Jogjakarta Conference. We have no
                            indication as to why <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>
                            felt it necessary to deviate from the agreement of the Conference and
                            can only interpolate that <pb facs="0201" n="173" xml:id="pg_173"/> he
                            and Iwa intended to demonstrate strength and try to increase their
                            civilian control over the military and possibly hoped to increase the
                            stature of the <gloss target="#t_PNI1">PNI</gloss>–<persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> Cabinet.</p>
                        <p>A motion of no-confidence has been introduced in the Parliament and the
                            three sponsors are individuals who voted with the <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> Government in the last no-confidence
                            motion. Whether they will carry enough support with them (and other
                            opposition forces remain intact) to bring down the Cabinet is
                            problematical and we have no estimates as yet.</p>
                        <p>Public and particularly <gloss target="#t_Masjumi1">Masjumi</gloss>
                            rumblings suggest that a Presidential or caretaker Cabinet may be in the
                            offing. This appears to be the only reasonable solution in view of the
                            apparent intention of the Cabinet to stand with Iwa and not permit the
                            vote to be one of censure against him alone. <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> may have had such notions
                            in mind a short time ago when he publicly offered to leave the palace if
                            the people did not want him; these tactics usually invite staunch
                            endorsement. However, there has been no significant public reaction and
                            not even a government press plea that he remain. As the Ambassador
                            observes, <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> remains a
                            singular figure as far as leadership is concerned and there is no
                            evidence that he is about to leave.</p>
                        <p>Summaries suggest that the <gloss target="#t_Masjumi1">Masjumi</gloss>
                            would prefer to see a Presidential Cabinet in the interim, rather than
                            to share responsibilities by any form of coalition which would weaken
                            their condemnation of the handling of the government, going into
                            elections.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_PSA1">PSA</gloss> analyzes the possibilities as: (a)
                            the <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> Cabinet for the sake of
                            retaining power may agree to drop Iwa for the price of <gloss target="#t_Masjumi1">Masjumi</gloss> involvement in the interim
                            government and may find a compromise Chief of Staff placating the
                            military while dropping both Utoyo and Lubis; or (b) dismissal of the
                                <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> Cabinet, naming a
                            Presidential Cabinet for the interim until the election results are
                            known. Membership in a Presidential Cabinet would seem to require
                            concession to the congealed opposition against leftist-influence such as
                            Iwa’s, while solution under (a) would be based on dropping Iwa. It may
                            be overly-optimistic at this stage to expect but it seems that of the
                            most likely developments both assure some diminution of the leftist and
                            pro-Communist influences in the Indonesian government.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>