<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-10T15:48:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-10T15:48:00-05:00" n="142" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d142">
                        <head>142. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d142fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 756D.5/12–255. Secret; Limit Distribution. Drafted in <gloss target="#t_PSA1">PSA</gloss>, approved in <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, and cleared with <gloss target="#t_U1">U</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-03-10T15:48:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">March 10,
                                        1956—3:48 p.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1589. Your 1312.<note n="2" xml:id="d142fn2">See <ref target="#d130fn5">footnote 5, Document 130</ref>.</note> As reviewed during your
                            consultation, Secretary requested Defense explore legal and practical
                            possibilities supply Indonesian Regimental Combat Team on credit
                                basis.<note n="3" xml:id="d142fn3">See <ref target="#d130fn6">footnote 6</ref>, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi></note>
                            Department noted following possibilities credit: (a) establishment of
                            eligibility by certain minimum assurances under Section 106 <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> as amended via (1) sales based on
                            credit up to three years in amounts available from military services or
                            (2) on transfer under Section 103c <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss>
                            through loans up to 10 years to extent Defense could reallocate
                            appropriated funds; or (b) without legal necessity any specific
                            assurances, subject Presidential determination, up to $20 million any
                            approved terms under Section 401. Departmental view was no attempt ought
                            to be made utilize Section 401 until attempt made obtain Indonesian
                            assurances for other eligibility.</p>
                        <p>Defense now prepared sell desired equipment to Indonesia “for cash” under
                            Section 106 if Indonesia becomes eligible by giving necessary assurances
                            or by Presidential determination exempting Indonesia such assurances.
                            Unable indicate what amounts could be handled on credit terms lacking
                            list specific equipment required, but would consider further upon
                            submission. Also indicates “furnishing equipment to Government Indonesia
                            for Regimental Combat Team is not considered project sufficient military
                            priority warrant use limited <gloss target="#t_MDAP1">MDAP</gloss>
                            appropriations finance long term credit under Sections 102 and 103c even
                            if Indonesia became eligible.”<note n="4" xml:id="d142fn4">The
                                Department of Defense reply was conveyed in a letter of March 2 from
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GG1">Gordon Gray</persName> to Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>, not printed.
                                (Department of State, Central Files, 756D.5–<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/3–256)</note></p>
                        <p>Department will not take matter up with Ambassador or Military Attaché
                            Washington, despite their optimistic interest months ago, until you
                            advise whether feasible now encourage Indonesia submit assurances in
                            form unilateral declaration or otherwise. Request <pb facs="0267" n="239" xml:id="pg_239"/> your views soonest whether (a) any hope
                            getting formal program through with assurances or (b) you believe
                            consideration should be given seek Presidential determination for funds
                            under Section 401.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_HHJ1"><hi rend="strong">Hoover</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>