<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>153. Telegram From the Embassy in Indonesia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d153</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">153</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-05-01T01:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-05-01T01:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Military equipment</term>
                    <term ref="recKz0w91lnkAu1cS" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general">Presidential Determination</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-05-01T01:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-05-01T01:30:00-05:00" n="153"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d153">
                <head>153. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d153fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 756D.5/5–156. Secret; Priority; Limited Distribution.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Djakarta</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1956-05-01T14:00:00+07:30">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 1, 1956—2 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2691. <gloss target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1589.<note n="2" xml:id="d153fn2">
                        <ref target="#d142">Document 142</ref>.</note> I regret that during
                    preparation for Secretary’s visit to Djakarta reference telegram was
                    inexplicably misfiled and not brought to my attention or as far as can be
                    ascertained to attention of any Embassy officer. It has only just come to light.
                    However, my reply as of mid-March would have been that in view of then pending
                    change of government it would be best to postpone reply until composition of new
                    Cabinet was known and its political orientation could be assessed with some
                    degree of accuracy.</p>
                <p>This contemplated situation has now come about. New Cabinet now a reality and
                    broadly based on non and anti-Communist parties; it has recently received
                    unanimous approval of first Indonesian elected Parliament to go ahead with its
                    program; and this approval apparently has backing of country as a whole since
                    reports from many sources, including biased Dutch High Commissioners, indicate
                    widespread feeling of calm confidence in and approval of Cabinet
                    (notwithstanding continued security programs in chronically disaffected areas of
                    Sbatjava, Atjeh and South Sulawesi). Price of gold has dropped in terms of
                    rupiah which has appreciably hardened on free market. First Deputy Prime
                    Minister <persName>Roem</persName>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d153fn3">
                        <persName>Mohammad Roem</persName>.</note> told me last week that <persName
                        corresp="#p_SD1">Sumitro</persName>’s fiscal policies have support of <gloss
                        target="#t_NU1">NU</gloss> and right-wing <gloss target="#t_PNI1"
                        >PNI</gloss> (they already had <gloss target="#t_Masjumi1">Masjumi</gloss>
                    support) and will be continued at least for present. Moreover Prime Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> so far has lived up to
                    expectations and is proving to be different man than the <persName
                        corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> of the <persName corresp="#p_AS1"
                        >Ali</persName>–Arifin Cabinet. Evidence of this can be found, inter alia,
                    in his remarkably friendly overtures to me personally and to United States
                    generally as evidenced by his address to American Association (<gloss
                        target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 2674<note n="4" xml:id="d153fn4">Reference
                        is presumably to telegram 2669 from Djakarta, April 27, which reported that
                            <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> had been the guest of honor at
                        a dinner of the American Association. (Department of State, Central Files,
                        611.56D/4–2756) Telegram 2674 from Djakarta, April 28, concerns an unrelated
                        matter. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 756D.00/4–2856)</note>). All of
                    foregoing must be read against background of fine impression made on President
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1"
                        >Dulles</persName>; by reactions in limited circles with which he came in
                    contact to <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Burke</persName>’s visit<note
                        n="5" xml:id="d153fn5">
                        <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral Arleigh A. Burke</persName>, Chief of
                        U.S. Naval Operations, visited Indonesia April 26–27.</note> (<gloss
                        target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 2641 re conversations with Foreign
                        Minister<note n="6" xml:id="d153fn6">Telegram 2641 from Djakarta, April 26,
                        transmitted a press report of <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admiral
                            Burke</persName>’s visit, which stated that <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1"
                            >Burke</persName>, together with <persName corresp="#p_CHSJ1"
                            >Cumming</persName>, had called on Foreign Minister <persName
                            corresp="#p_RA1">Roeslan Abdulgani</persName>.</note>); <pb facs="0289"
                        n="261" xml:id="pg_261"/> and above all by ponderable and imponderable
                    reactions in broad Indonesian political circles to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>’s forthcoming visit to United
                    States.</p>
                <p>To sum up present Cabinet appears to be here to stay at least for a longer rather
                    than a shorter period and within framework of “active independent foreign
                    policy” apparently will not lean so heavily away from United States as did
                        <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName>–Arifin Cabinet but will even try
                    to warm up relationship with us.</p>
                <p>I therefore still favor giving sympathetic attention to Indonesian requests for
                    military equipment if made. However, I do not believe Indonesians prepared give
                    us assurances required under Section 106 <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss>
                    even though they may be unilateral. Department will remember that in connection
                    with Indo effort purchase sonar equipment purchase fell through because Indo
                    unwillingness make unilateral declaration although no mention made <gloss
                        target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss> (Embassy despatch 230 October 12,<note n="7"
                        xml:id="d153fn7">Despatch 230 from Djakarta, October 12, 1955, reported that
                        the Chief of Staff for Operations of the Indonesian Navy had told the U.S.
                        Naval Attaché that the Indonesian Government would be unable to buy U.S.
                        sonar equipment because it was unwilling to sign an agreement giving
                        assurances as required by the Mutual Security Act. (Department of State,
                        Central Files, 756D.56/10–1255)</note> Department’s A–83 October 24<note
                        n="8" xml:id="d153fn8">Airgram 83 to Djakarta, October 24, 1955, pointed out
                        to the Embassy that Indonesian purchase of the sonar equipment would not
                        require the signature of an agreement, but only a unilateral declaration by
                        Indonesia of the assurances embodied in Section 106 of the Mutual Security
                        Act. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 756D.56/10–1255)</note>). I believe
                    therefore that consideration should be given seek presidential determination for
                    funds under Section 401 <gloss target="#t_MSA1">MSA</gloss>. Considerations last
                    paragraph <gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 1312 still apply.<note n="9"
                        xml:id="d153fn9">See <ref target="#d130fn5">footnote 5, Document
                        130</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Despite foregoing paragraph I feel that I must enter one caveat: Overtures on
                    which <gloss target="#t_mytel1">mytel</gloss> 1312 were based were made during
                    previous Cabinet’s tenure. … It is quite possible that this has been due to
                    failure to receive any positive reaction from outside. On other hand, original
                    plans may either have run into one of political road blocks so usual in these
                    matters in Indonesia, or may have been put on ice pending formation present
                    Cabinet; they may even have been postponed to have been brought up in some way
                    in connection with <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>’s visit
                    United States.</p>
                <p>There are at least three ways in which we could take sounding to determine
                    whether plans are still alive and at least tacit support present Cabinet or its
                    inner circle.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>We could send back through channels through which approaches first made a
                        guarded expression of interest together with request for information re
                        present status, i.e. amounts involved, etc.</item>
                    <pb facs="0290" n="262" xml:id="pg_262"/>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>I could pick up abortive conversations which I had with <persName
                            corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> in 1954<note n="10" xml:id="d153fn10">In
                            a conversation with <persName corresp="#p_CHSJ1">Cumming</persName> on
                            April 6, 1954, <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> had expressed
                            interest in Indonesian employment of U.S. military instructors; see
                                <persName>Galbraith</persName>’s memorandum to Bonsai, April 8,
                            1954, <ref target="frus1952-54v12p2#pg_416">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1952–1954, vol. XII, Part
                                2, p. 416</ref>.</note> with a view to eliciting his present views
                        on acceptance of United States military assistance without strings.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>We could follow up Indonesian Military Attaché’s approach re <persName
                            corresp="#p_NMGAH1">Nasution</persName> going to United States with
                            <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> (<gloss
                            target="#t_Deptel1">Deptel</gloss> 1762<note n="11" xml:id="d153fn11"
                            >Telegram 1762 to Djakarta, March 30, reported that the Indonesian
                            Military Attaché in Washington had informed the Department of Defense
                            that <persName corresp="#p_NMGAH1">Nasution</persName> wanted to visit
                            the United States either with <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                >Sukarno</persName> or separately and requested <persName
                                corresp="#p_CHSJ1">Cumming</persName>’s views as to the desirability
                            and timing of such a visit. (Department of State, Central Files,
                            756D.5811/3–3056)</note>) extending an invitation to <persName
                            corresp="#p_NMGAH1">Nasution</persName> to visit United States some time
                        after <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> visit. Perhaps this
                        last course of action would best be preceded by prompt action along lines my
                        first suggestion above. …</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CHSJ1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Cumming</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
