<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>227. Telegram From the Embassy in Indonesia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d227</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">227</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-05-09T00:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-05-09T00:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
                    <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reccab053b473a4a56" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="world-war-i" subject="world-war-i" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85148236" lcsh-match="exact">Councils</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-05-09T00:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-05-09T00:30:00-05:00" n="227"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d227">
                <head>227. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d227fn1">Source: Department of Stale, Central
                        Files, 756D.00/5–957. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Djakarta</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-05-09T13:00:00+07:30">
                            <hi rend="italic">May 9, 1957—1 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>2744. Following is summary of principal points developed by Prime Minister
                        <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> during course of 35 minute
                    discussion this morning.</p>
                <p>Situation in Sulawesi is more serious than in Sumatra but at present looks as if
                    local leaders there will agree to central government plans for reorganization of
                    provincial military setup (see Embassy telegram cite C–46, <gloss
                        target="#t_ARMA1">ARMA</gloss> 040511 giving report from Army Attaché<note
                        n="2" xml:id="d227fn2">
                        <p>Telegram C–46 from the Army Attaché in Djakarta, May 4, reported that
                                <persName corresp="#p_NMGAH1">Nasution</persName> had relieved
                            Sumual of his command in Eastern Indonesia; it commented:</p>
                        <p>“Gen <persName corresp="#p_NMGAH1">Nasution</persName> has made decision
                            with far-reaching effects. If order is obeyed, <persName
                                corresp="#p_NMGAH1">Nasution</persName> has slowed and maybe stopped
                            the independent actions of commanders like Sumual and Hussein. If Sumual
                            chooses to fight this order, then results could be deadly not only to
                            Army but Indonesia as nation. Revolt by Sumual, coordinated with move by
                            Hussein on Sumatra, could throw Indonesia into civil war. During past
                            crisis Army headquarters has always appeared calm, but during this visit
                            officers appeared nervous and atmosphere tense.” (Department of Defense
                            Files)</p>
                    </note>). <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> said he believed that
                    Lt. Colonel Sumual was in <pb facs="0406" n="378" xml:id="pg_378"/> fact glad to
                    get out of position he found himself in as result of March 2 declaration. While
                    leaders in Sumatra had made many public statements about their demands on
                    central government they had not strongly pressed these demands in private talks
                    with <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> when he visited them last
                    month. Most public statements were largely for record and to maintain prestige.
                    They said to public that Banteng Council must be recognized but in private talks
                    this was only mentioned at end when <persName corresp="#p_DK1"
                        >Djuanda</persName> was asked: “Are you against the Banteng Council?” His
                    reply was: “No, I am not against it. I think it has served a useful purpose in
                    channeling the desires of the people and making clear their complaints. I
                    recognize the validity of many of these complaints and the government will take
                    practical steps to meet them. However, you cannot expect me officially to
                    recognize the Banteng Council or the numerous other councils set up around the
                    country”. According to <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> this was
                    accepted and discussion was not pursued.</p>
                <p>Earlier in discussion Sumatran leaders had stressed necessity of restoring
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>–<persName
                        corresp="#p_HM1">Hatta</persName> leadership. <persName corresp="#p_DK1"
                        >Djuanda</persName> replied that no one desired this more than he did, but
                    that for the time being this was not practical possibility. Cabinet would work
                    out gradually practical ad hoc steps leading to this cooperation but this would
                    take time. Sumatran leaders did not press the point.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> looks for difficulty when
                    Parliament reconvenes in view of extraordinary manner in which Cabinet was
                    formed. He complained that people are too impatient. “They want results in
                    months whereas it will take years to do what needs to be done”. However,
                        <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> said he was not pessimistic.
                    He believed it would be possible to convince majority of Parliament that it was
                    in their interest to cooperate with Cabinet and to give it time to show what it
                    can do. As <persName corresp="#p_Subandrio1">Subandrio</persName> had said
                    previously to me, <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> also remarked
                    that if this Cabinet is not given chance to succeed, military will take over. He
                    does not believe members of Parliament want this to happen and that therefore in
                    end they will cooperate.</p>
                <p>I received most favorable impression of a dedicated, practical man who would not
                    get lost in theories. The contrast between <persName corresp="#p_DK1"
                        >Djuanda</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_AS1">Ali</persName> is
                    startling and in my opinion all in favor of the former. Nevertheless I am
                    inclined believe <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName>’s appraisal
                    Sumatra situation somewhat optimistic in view other available information
                    indicating continuance extreme dissatisfaction with central government. In
                    connection <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName>’s statement concerning
                    usefulness Banteng Council, press today reports arrest of Ramawi who is
                    council’s representative in Djakarta. Finally it must be said that <persName
                        corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName>’s assurances, sincerely stated though
                    they may be, fail to take into account overwhelming impediment to solution
                    regional problem which <pb facs="0407" n="379" xml:id="pg_379"/> is <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> himself whose statements continue
                    indicate his failure recognize nature and gravity of situation.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Allison</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
