<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>239. Telegram From the Embassy in Indonesia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d239</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">239</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-07-16T23:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-07-16T23:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recGyiFfoYaZJxm1O" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040838"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic sanctions</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign currency</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic affairs</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-07-16T23:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-07-16T23:30:00-05:00" n="239"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d239">
                <head>239. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d239fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 756D.00/7–1757. Secret.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Djakarta</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-07-17T12:00:00+07:30">
                            <hi rend="italic">July 17, 1957—noon</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>139. Following are principal points of general interest covered in hour-long talk
                    yesterday evening with Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_DK1"
                        >Djuanda</persName>.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>National Council:</p>
                        <p>While <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> admitted differences
                            with President <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> over
                            council he said President had adopted a give-and-take attitude. Most
                            important was admission by President that establishment of <pb
                                facs="0426" n="398" xml:id="pg_398"/> National Council was “an
                            experiment” and that it was not of necessity permanent. Whether or not
                            National Council would survive depended upon (1) how it governed its
                            relations with the Cabinet and (2) decision of Constituent Assembly on
                            whether it should be continued or replaced by a Senate. <persName
                                corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> apparently favors the creation
                            of a Senate. Prime Minister was again most definite that council only
                            had advisory powers. According to <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>
                            correspondent from Hong Kong who interviewed <persName corresp="#p_DK1"
                                >Djuanda</persName> earlier in day, Prime Minister had been most
                            outspoken in his determination to keep council in its place.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Constituent Assembly:</p>
                        <p>In response to question as to progress being made by Constituent
                            Assembly, <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> said it did not
                            have enough sense of urgency and was being too casual. However, it has
                            reached one most important decision and while this has not yet been
                            publicly formalized, <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> says
                            it has been definitely agreed upon, namely, that Indonesia shall be a
                            secular state.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Provincial Problems:</p>
                        <p>Prime Minister confirmed <persName corresp="#p_Subandrio1"
                                >Subandrio</persName>’s statement to me last week (<gloss
                                target="#t_Embtel1">Embtel</gloss> 96<note n="2" xml:id="d239fn2"
                                >Dated July 11, not printed. (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                756D.00/7–1157)</note>) that situation in Sumatra showed glimmering
                            of hope. He referred to fact that <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                >Sukarno</persName> intends shortly to visit Central and South
                            Sumatra and he revealed that <persName corresp="#p_NMGAH1"
                                >Nasution</persName> would shortly go to North Sumatra to negotiate
                            for removal of both Gintings and Macmour whom he characterized as “weak
                            man”. Removal of Macmour would, if achieved, be great blow to Communists
                            in North Sumatra. <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> said
                            Atjeh was quiet for first time in years and greatest problem was now the
                            finding of jobs for the former guerrillas.</p>
                        <p>With respect to Sulawesi, <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName>
                            made clear that government does not intend at this time to take any
                            drastic action against Sumual but will continue attempt by persuasion to
                            reach solution. Prime Minister said that when government took step of
                            removing Sumual from office and dividing Sulawesi into four commands it
                            realized risk it was taking and was not surprised at subsequent action
                            of Sumual. Alternatives were to do nothing or to attempt by force to
                            settle matter and either of these courses would have produced worse
                            results than one followed. <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName>
                            said Sumual is an honest man but is too young and naive politically and
                            economically to cope with the people who are profiting from present
                            situation and who are using Sumual. <persName corresp="#p_DK1"
                                >Djuanda</persName> said government was sending mission to North
                            Sulawesi (announced in this morning’s press) which includes Justice
                            Minister, Industrial Affairs Minister, Ambassador to Canada Palar and
                            former Ambassador to Peking Mononutu, all of whom come from North
                            Sulawesi. In addition <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName>
                            revealed that <persName corresp="#p_HCA1">Christian</persName>
                            <pb facs="0427" n="399" xml:id="pg_399"/>Church circles in Sulawesi were
                            also being called upon to see [<hi rend="italic">use</hi>] their good
                            offices. <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> hinted strongly
                            that if these efforts failed economic sanctions would be used to bring
                            Sumual into line. Use of military force is not contemplated as of
                            now.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Economic Matters:</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> expressed considerable
                            satisfaction at results being achieved by new exchange regulations. He
                            said that report yesterday morning by Monetary Board showed that exports
                            were averaging rupiahs 30 million a day whereas prior to institution of
                            regulations they had sunk to rupiahs 5–6 million. While admitting that
                            import prices had risen he claimed that if new regulations had not been
                            instituted it would have been necessary to limit imports so severely
                            that prices would have gone up anyway for such imported goods as were
                            available. Overall result from point of view of Indonesian Government is
                            therefore good.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> confirmed that Soviet loan
                            is entirely for economic projects. He said it was almost exactly like
                            line of credit US Export-Import Bank had granted and that money would be
                            used only as projects approved. Credits granted will only be for foreign
                            currency components of approved projects and Indonesian Government will
                            have to provide rupiah expenses. This will limit use of the loan and
                                <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> apparently does not
                            anticipate great influx of either Soviet money or technicians.</p>
                    </item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>
                        <p>Conclusion:</p>
                        <p>While Embassy has had several reports that <persName corresp="#p_DK1"
                                >Djuanda</persName> is discouraged and ready to quit, nevertheless
                            throughout conversation he appeared to have no doubts about ability of
                            his Cabinet to remain in office at least for next few months. He did not
                            ignore the great difficulties facing the government but appeared
                            confident that with patience and good will they could be met. He is not
                            working for quick or dramatic solutions but is hoping that by concrete
                            practical measures the provinces can be convinced that their best
                            interests will be served by cooperating with central government. He
                            reaffirmed specifically that his goal was to bring <persName
                                corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and <persName
                                corresp="#p_HM1">Hatta</persName> together again but admitted this
                            would not be realized in near future. He admitted dissatisfaction at
                            results of his attempts to bring the army under effective discipline but
                            said he was not giving up on this. In this connection he hopes to be
                            able within two or three months to make a start, first in Kalimantan
                            then in East and Central Java, at abolishing state of war and Siege. He
                            wants to do this soon as possible so that military attention can be
                            confined to military matters and taken away from political and economic
                            affairs for which they have little training or ability.</p>
                        <p>
                            <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> is most impressive and I
                            hope he will be given time and opportunity to implement his ideas. Only
                            question still is, will <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                                >Sukarno</persName>
                            <pb facs="0428" n="400" xml:id="pg_400"/>give him that chance, or if
                            not, will <persName corresp="#p_DK1">Djuanda</persName> have strength to
                            oppose President? It is not at all certain that he will.</p>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Allison</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
