<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>265. Telegram From the Embassy in Indonesia to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">265</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-09-13T02:30:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-09-13T02:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general">Information programs</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="foreign-policy" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">United States policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec2X1BYDJjBDaemc" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment-disputes-and-property-expropriations" lcsh-match="no_match">Property</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-09-13T02:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-09-13T02:30:00-05:00" n="265"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d265">
                <head>265. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d265fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 756D.00/9–1357. Top Secret; Priority; Limit Distribution.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Djakarta</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-09-13T15:00:00+07:30">
                            <hi rend="italic">September 13, 1957—3 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>697. No distribution outside Department. Department telegram 553.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d265fn2">Telegram 553 to Djakarta, September 10, summarized the
                        Special Report on Indonesia, <ref target="#d262">Document 262</ref>, and
                        requested <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">Allison</persName>’s views on its
                        analysis of the situation and recommendations. (Department of State, Central
                        Files, 756D.00/9–1057)</note> I have studied carefully Department’s 553 and
                        530<note n="3" xml:id="d265fn3">Telegram 530 to Djakarta, September 7,
                        summarized the conclusions of <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 65–57,
                            <ref target="#d257">Document 257</ref>. (Department of State, Central
                        Files, 101.21–NIS/9–757)</note>. …</p>
                <p>While there is much in analysis and recommendations of Ad Hoc Committee with
                    which I agree, there is also much with which I disagree or about which I should
                    desire more detail before making final comment. It also seems to me that Ad Hoc
                    Committee has proceeded on certain assumptions which I believe are questionable
                    and has failed to consider certain possibilities of action which in my opinion
                    would be most helpful.</p>
                <p>I find little or no evidence in either Committee report or <gloss
                        target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 65–57 of any real consideration of the reasons
                    for the great Communist gains or for <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                        >Sukarno</persName>’s increasing reliance on Communist support. I do not
                    believe valid recommendations can be made for a cure without considering the
                    causes of the disease. Apparently Washington has not considered what the effect
                    of United States policies present and past may have had on recent Indonesian
                    developments. While certainly much of the responsibility must be taken by the
                    Indonesians themselves, I believe it would be helpful to consider also the mote
                    in our eye.</p>
                <p>While both Committee report and <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 65–57
                    recognize the key position occupied by <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                        >Sukarno</persName>, no attempt is apparently to be made to influence him to
                    change his ways. He is presumably beyond redemption. I just don’t believe this
                    is so. It will be difficult to influence him and certainly if the report of the
                    Ad Hoc Committee is adopted in full it will probably be impossible, but given
                    patience, imagination and a willingness at least to consider significant changes
                    in our over-all policy toward Indonesia and toward <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> personally, I believe there is a
                    chance that progress can be made toward reducing <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1"
                        >Sukarno</persName>’s reliance on the Communists and toward reducing
                    Communist influence in the country at large.</p>
                <p>As I read Department telegram 553 the Committee in essence recommends that we
                    keep to our present policy ….This seems to me too negative an approach and one
                    fraught with considerable danger.</p>
                <pb facs="0471" n="443" xml:id="pg_443"/>
                <p>With respect to specifics of Department telegram 553, I agree with statement that
                    if Communist gains on Java continue unchecked it will seriously affect United
                    States security interests. While I agree that approach (c) has the greatest
                    promise of the three put forward, I believe there is a further and to my mind
                    better approach which could be made. This would add to approach (c) the factor
                    of a sufficient change in United States policy toward West Irian issue and other
                    Indonesian desiderata to give the non-Communist forces some material to work
                    with and some hope of being able to convince Indonesian people that they have as
                    much to gain from friendship with United States as with <gloss target="#t_USSR1"
                        >USSR</gloss>. These are a naive, emotional, vain people and simple logic
                    and bare facts do not appeal. <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>
                    still sways them and unless we can find some way of swaying <persName
                        corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> I fear we will have but little
                    success. This swaying can be done I believe by a combination of exploiting, as
                    Committee recommends, the political and economic leverage of outer islands and
                    non-Commie forces in Java with an over-all United States policy which will make
                    it possible for <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> to believe
                    his long-range interests lie with United States rather than elsewhere. If we
                    only follow approach (c) as outlined in Committee report, we may gain
                    short-range success but we will sooner or later be faced with necessity of
                    facing up to Indonesian emotions and prejudices, which are not exclusive
                    property of <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName>, but without
                        <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> to act as the dynamic
                    leader and unifying force recognized in para 35 <gloss target="#t_NIE1"
                        >NIE</gloss> 65–57.</p>
                <p>Regarding basic factors for United States planning, I agree with (a) and (b) but
                    again point out there is no study made of causes for this situation. Agree with
                    (c). With respect to (d) my Army Attaché’s office completely disagrees and has
                    pointed to exactly an opposite trend. From personal knowledge I would hesitate
                    to judge but I am convinced that my Army Attaché’s office has … good sources
                    within Army…and has a much closer relationship of give and take with influential
                    officers. While it certainly is not decisive I find it of some significance that
                    war plan of Indonesian Army assumes Commie China as potential enemy and the
                    United States as Indonesia’s ally under certain circumstances. With respect to
                    (e) I have same comments as with regard to approach (c) above.</p>
                <p>Concerning Committee’s recommendations I would agree with general approach plus
                    additional factors mentioned above. I do not understand full implications
                    recommendation (a) and should like have clarification as to just what it means.
                    Same applies to (b). I would agree with (c) but be somewhat skeptical of
                    results.</p>
                <p>I agree with recommendation (a) on courses of action on Java with caveat that the
                    establishment of a government able and willing to pursue a vigorous
                    anti-Communist policy is most unlikely in the near term future. I remain of
                    opinion that most we can reasonably <pb facs="0472" n="444" xml:id="pg_444"/>
                    expect is a truly independent non-Communist government. The other may come
                    eventually and we should not stop working for it but should recognize that
                    premature or too vigorous insistence on an anti-Communist government may prevent
                    the establishment of a non-Communist government. We should remember that there
                    as in other cases the perfect is often the enemy of the good. While I have some
                    sympathy with first sentence of recommendation (b) it seems contradictory to
                    second sentence and I should like clarification. Has consideration been given to
                    fact that if we refuse central government’s requests for arms it may well turn
                    elsewhere but that if we meet at least some of their requests we will be in a
                    position through supply of spare parts and replacements to exercise some degree
                    of influence and control? Refusal to meet any of requests may well alienate many
                    of our good friends in Army hierarchy who devoutly hope and work for closer
                    relations with United States and who, having been trained in America, do no want
                    their military machine to be dependent upon non-American sources. Recommendation
                    (c) seems both unrealistic and unwise to me. Constant stressing of dangers of
                    Commie China or <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> soon becomes
                    counter-productive here. Non-Commie Indonesian leaders already understand extent
                    of Commie [influence?] on <persName corresp="#p_Sukarno1">Sukarno</persName> and
                    his share in creating tensions between central government and regions. Masses
                    are not interested and probably would not believe anyway. Focusing of world
                    opinion on Communist menace in Indonesia could well have opposite result from
                    what we desire. I am most skeptical of its usefulness.</p>
                <p>I fully agree with statement that abrupt termination of economic and information
                    programs would do more harm than good and concur in recommendations (a) and (b).
                    I interpret (b) to mean that while not terminating programs on Java greater
                    emphasis in planning future programs will be on outer islands as is done by
                    recent $15 million loan.</p>
                <p>. . . . . . .</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_AJM1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Allison</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
