<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-11-03T21:30:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-11-03T21:30:00-05:00" n="278" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d278">
                        <head>278. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Indonesia</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d278fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 711.5856D/11–457. Confidential.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Djakarta</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1957-11-04T10:00:00+07:30"><hi rend="italic">November 4,
                                        1957—10 a.m.</hi></date></dateline></opener>
                        <p>1135. Department telegram 986 and Embassy telegram 1114.<note n="2" xml:id="d278fn2"><p>Telegram 1114 from Djakarta, October 31,
                                    referred to plans for a visit by U.S. destroyers to Djakarta and
                                    Surabaya in early December and noted: “Indonesia is no place for
                                    United States naval vessels at this time.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 711.5856D/10–3157)</p>
                                <p>Telegram 986 to Djakarta, November 2, stated that the proposed
                                    naval visit was prompted by the desire to “strengthen US-Indo
                                    naval ties” and the belief that the objectives cited in telegram
                                    942, <ref target="#d275">Document 275</ref>, might also be
                                    served. (Department of State, Central Files,
                                    711.5856D/10–3157)</p></note> I agree that naval visits can
                            serve useful purpose under proper conditions but I am of opinion that it
                            is not suitable at present for naval vessels to visit Indonesia.
                            Situation in 1954 and 1955 mentioned in Department telegram 986 was
                            quite different than that now prevailing. If for no other reason <gloss target="#t_AP1">AP</gloss> story quoted in Department telegram
                                981<note n="3" xml:id="d278fn3"><p>Telegram 981 to Djakarta,
                                    November 1, transmitted the text of an Associated Press story
                                    datelined Pearl Harbor, which quoted remarks made by <persName corresp="#p_BAAA1">Admirals Burke</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SAFB1">Stump</persName> in interviews with
                                    newsmen. The following paragraphs of the story concerned
                                    Indonesia:</p>
                                <p>“A sifting of the great volume of reports coming to Pearl Harbor
                                    from many sources in many Asian lands leads to the conclusion
                                    that Indonesia is one of the prime targets for Communist control
                                    and may be ripe for plucking without a shot.</p>
                                <p>“Dogged by internal dissensions and armed revolts, the Government
                                    of Indonesia has accepted so many favors from native Communists
                                    that the payoff hour may not be far off, these reports
                                    indicate.</p>
                                <p>“Stubbornly neutralist after breaking all ties with the
                                    Netherlands, Indonesia rejected American offers of military aid.
                                    Because there is no alliance or even a mutual aid agreement with
                                    the United States, any direct American military intervention
                                    would be damned as imperialism and will be avoided
                                    scrupulously.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                611.90/11–157)</p></note> would make it inadvisable for any American
                            military visits to Indonesia. I deplore the aggressive tone of recent
                            statements by American military leaders which have had an adverse effect
                            here. When to these statements is added a definite reference to
                            Indonesia the situation becomes even worse. Any American military visits
                            in the near future would only be interpreted by Indonesians as pressure
                            being put on this country to get it to join <gloss target="#t_SEATO1">SEATO</gloss>. Any such pressure could only be counter-productive
                            and play into the hands of the Communists. <gloss target="#t_AP1">AP</gloss> story summarized in Department telegram 981 particularly
                            unfortunate in view of statement that Indonesia rejected American offers
                            of military aid and that there is no alliance with United States. As
                            Department is well aware, since first rejection of American military aid
                            by Indonesia the government has come a long way and is now prepared to
                            accept US military aid on a reimbursable basis. Such irresponsible
                            statements as those in <gloss target="#t_AP1">AP</gloss> story can well
                            lose us what progress we have already made up to this time.</p>
                        <pb facs="0513" n="485" xml:id="pg_485"/>
                        <p>Until US Government is prepared to do more than make what Indonesians
                            would consider idle gestures, such as visits of American ships, I do not
                            believe there should be any such visits. If on other hand, we are
                            prepared to make some agreement regarding furnishing of military aid on
                            a reimbursable basis and if US Government is prepared to take other
                            steps, showing friendship for Indonesia, the visit of naval vessels
                            could serve a useful purpose. At present they would only be an
                            aggravation.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_AJM1"><hi rend="strong">Allison</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>