<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-04-22T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-04-22T00:00:00-05:00" n="471" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d471">
                        <head>471. Despatch From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Thailand</gloss>
                            to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d471fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                                Files, 792.5/4–2255. Top Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <seg rendition="#left">No. 496</seg>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Bangkok</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-04-22"><hi rend="italic">April 22,
                                1955</hi></date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="references">
                            <head>REF</head>
                            <item>Department’s Circular Telegram 559, March 23, 1955<note n="2" xml:id="d471fn2">In telegram 559, the Chiefs of Mission to whom
                                    the telegram was sent were instructed “to have the country team,
                                    including representatives from <gloss target="#t_FOA1">FOA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_MAAG1">MAAG</gloss> (or
                                    service attachés) … prepare a report on the possibilities and
                                    requirements for U.S. assistance in increasing the effectiveness
                                    of police-type forces to deal with communist subversion and, in
                                    those countries where communist subversion has reached the stage
                                    of actual or potential large-scale insurrection, increasing the
                                    effectiveness of the regular armed forces to deal with communist
                                    subversion and insurrections.” (<hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi>
                                    700.5/3–2355) The purpose of the exercise was to provide the
                                        <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> with the information
                                    necessary to formulate a concept for U.S. assistance in the
                                    development of forces adequate to provide internal security in
                                    countries vulnerable to Communist subversion. The <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> was given the task of
                                    developing such a concept by the National Security Council on
                                    December 21, 1954. (<gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Action
                                    No. 1290–d; <hi rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi><gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss> Files: Lot 66 D 95, Records of Action by the
                                    National Security Council, 1954) For the country study on the
                                    internal security situation in Thailand, produced by an
                                    interagency working group for the <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> on January 4, 1956, see <ref target="#d484">Document 484</ref>.</note></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>U.S. Assistance in the Development of Forces Adequate to Provide
                                Internal Security in Countries Vulnerable to Communist
                                Subversion</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>There is attached as Enclosure No. 1 a paper prepared for the Operations
                            Coordinating Board in accordance with the outline contained in the
                            reference instruction. The paper was drafted by … , <gloss target="#t_JUSMAG1">JUSMAG</gloss> and the Embassy in consultation
                            with <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_USOM1">USOM</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>It will be noted that the recommendations of the paper are for
                            continuation of current efforts to improve administration, personnel and
                            training in the Thai security forces rather than for any basic changes
                            at this time in the present force basis and programs of military
                            equipment. In contrast to the situation in a number of other countries
                            vulnerable to Communist subversion, there has been underway in Thailand
                            for some time a … program designed to create Thai police-type forces
                            capable of dealing with subversive activity. It is recognized, of
                            course, that changes in the program may prove to be desirable in the
                            light of further experience with and improvements in the capabilities of
                            the Thai security forces.</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_PJE1"><hi rend="strong">John. E.
                                        Peurifoy</hi></persName></signed></closer>
                        <pb facs="0845" n="817" xml:id="pg_817"/>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">[Enclosure]</note>
                            <head>U.S. ASSISTANCE IN THE DEVELOPMENT OF FORCES ADEQUATE TO PROVIDE
                                INTERNAL SECURITY IN COUNTRIES VULNERABLE TO COMMUNIST
                                SUBVERSION</head>
                            <p rend="center">Thailand</p>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">I. State of Development of Threat
                                    of Subversion.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>A.</label>
                                <item>It is difficult to ascertain the exact extent of subversive
                                    activity in Thailand. It has been expected that, following the
                                    Communist achievements in Indo-China, they would undertake a
                                    large-scale subversive program against Thailand, but it appears
                                    that this has not yet been launched. Nevertheless, the threat of
                                    subversion is a very real one and represents a potential danger
                                    to Thailand.</item>
                                <label>B.</label>
                                <item>Principal sources of potential danger are: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>The Chinese minority throughout Thailand principally
                                            concentrated in the urban areas. (The Thai security
                                            service claims to have identified over 2,500 members of
                                            the <gloss target="#t_CPT1">CPT</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_CCPT1">CCPT</gloss>.)</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>The Viet Minh minority in the Northeast Provinces<note n="3" xml:id="d471fn3">The Government of Thailand
                                                was concerned that the Vietnamese community in
                                                northeastern Thailand might become a base for
                                                Communist activities in Thailand. Documentation on
                                                Thai efforts to encourage the repatriation of Viet
                                                Minh supporters to North Vietnam, and American
                                                encouragement of those efforts, is in Department of
                                                State, Central File 751G.00.</note></item>
                                        <label>(3)</label>
                                        <item>Infiltration from Communist China, including the Thai
                                            Nationality Autonomous area in Yunnan.<note n="4" xml:id="d471fn4">The Thai Autonomous Area in the
                                                southernmost part of Yunnan Province was established
                                                in 1953 by the Chinese Government as one of a large
                                                number of such ethnically-designated areas in
                                                China.</note></item>
                                        <label>(4)</label>
                                        <item>Chinese Communist terrorist forces from Malaya
                                            supported by elements of the Min Yuen living in the
                                            Southern border area of Thailand.<note n="5" xml:id="d471fn5">The Min Yuen were the
                                                Communist-oriented Malayan guerrilla forces which
                                                operated on both sides of the border between Malaya
                                                and Thailand.</note></item>
                                        <label>(5)</label>
                                        <item>Disaffected Thai elements in Thailand, particularly
                                            those in the Northeast, and those abroad, some of which
                                            are under Communist control.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>C.</label>
                                <item>The Communists have the capability of: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>Infiltrating agents to indoctrinate, organize and
                                            train indigenous forces.</item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item>In conjunction with the above, of infiltrating small
                                            organized units from Communist China, Laos or Malaya to
                                            conduct small-scale guerrilla operations.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                            </list>
                            <pb facs="0846" n="818" xml:id="pg_818"/>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">II. Adequacy of Indigenous
                                    Counter-Measures.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>A.</label>
                                <item><p>Recognition of the threat and will-to-act on the part of
                                        the local Government:</p>
                                    <p>The Communist threat is recognized by Thai Government leaders
                                        and many educated Thais, and counter-measures are being
                                        taken. The will to act exists in some quarters but,
                                        especially at higher levels, is usually subordinated to
                                        personal considerations. Any action is largely predicated on
                                        continued support and guidance by the U.S. In addition,
                                        action is handicapped by the ignorance and lack of ability
                                        of many highly placed officials.</p></item>
                                <label>B.</label>
                                <item>Capabilities of indigenous forces: <list>
                                        <label>(1)</label>
                                        <item>For police type preventive activities: <list>
                                                <label>a.</label>
                                                <item>The various sections of the C.I.D. responsible
                                                  for the detection and identification of the
                                                  Communist apparatus and other subversive elements
                                                  are staffed by relatively capable and experienced
                                                  police rather than intelligence officers. These
                                                  sections are further hampered by over
                                                  compartmentation and a lack of central file system
                                                  or any method of cross referencing the vast body
                                                  of accumulated but uncarded information now on
                                                  hand. Much duplication of effort ensues and seldom
                                                  can or do operational leads get the kind of
                                                  cooperative attention from the various responsible
                                                  division heads that such matters require.</item>
                                                <label>b.</label>
                                                <item>The police are fully capable of rounding up
                                                  and detaining all presently known Communist
                                                  personalities and groups, including the
                                                  approximately 40,000 Viet Minh sympathizers among
                                                  the Vietnamese refugees in the Northeastern
                                                  Provinces in the event that these became an open
                                                  threat to Thailand. (Rounding up the Vietnamese
                                                  would probably require the use of armed force.)
                                                  However, it is generally agreed that many Chinese
                                                  Communist leaders are not known to the security
                                                  services and that private and business connections
                                                  between Communist-inclined Chinese businessmen and
                                                  police officers tend to vitiate the effectiveness
                                                  of vigorous action.</item>
                                                <label>c.</label>
                                                <item>Thai legal system appears to provide adequate
                                                  means for the arrest, prosecution and enforcement
                                                  of measures against persons engaged in Communist
                                                  and other forms of subversion and sedition. The
                                                  weaknesses lie in the actual operation of the
                                                  legal system, particularly in the inefficiency and
                                                  venality of officials and cumbersome, protracted
                                                  trial procedures. However, despite any
                                                  shortcomings of the legal system, the top Thai
                                                  military-political leaders have always found means
                                                  to deal with persons they consider a threat to
                                                  their positions.</item>
                                                <label>d.</label>
                                                <item>The Thai National Police which includes the
                                                  Gendarmérie Patrol Force (border patrol) is by
                                                  statute responsible for border security as well as
                                                  internal security. The present organization of the
                                                  Municipal Police, Provincial Police and the
                                                  Gendarmérie Patrol Force (<gloss target="#t_GPF1">GPF</gloss>) has the capability of handling all
                                                  but major internal uprisings in which case the
                                                  Army would step in. The <gloss target="#t_GPF1">GPF</gloss> is not yet capable of directing and
                                                  supporting a sustained action against border
                                                  infiltration by <pb facs="0847" n="819" xml:id="pg_819"/> well organized guerrilla forces.
                                                  The <gloss target="#t_VDC1">VDC</gloss> (Volunteer
                                                  Defense Corps), which is expected to have a
                                                  strength of 18,000 by 1956, is still in the
                                                  organization and training stage and has little if
                                                  any present military capability.</item>
                                            </list></item>
                                        <label>(2)</label>
                                        <item><p>For military type action:</p>
                                            <p>With present organization and dispositions the Army
                                                is believed capable of suppressing any spontaneous
                                                uprising, particularly in the urban areas. In the
                                                conduct of field operations against organized
                                                guerrilla forces the Army has at present only a
                                                limited capability.</p></item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>C.</label>
                                <item><p>Support of counter-measures by local population:</p>
                                    <p>The Thai population is generally apathetic regarding the
                                        Communist threat. Their apathy is in part due to the
                                        debilitating influence of the climate and to the passivity
                                        engendered by Buddhism, but more importantly it is due to
                                        the lack of adequate information regarding Communist
                                        techniques and purposes. This lack of understanding can be
                                        attributed in part to the low level of education and the
                                        lack of contact with the outside world among rural Thais.
                                        However, the situation has been improving somewhat as a
                                        result of an indoctrination program undertaken by the Thai
                                        Government with <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss>
                                        initiative and support. Although the Thai people would
                                        probably volunteer little support for counter-measures, most
                                        Thais would probably obey the instruction of local
                                        representatives of the central government in supporting
                                        counter-measures, except in limited areas in which popular
                                        local leaders, disaffected with the central government
                                        succeeded in alienating the local population. The <gloss target="#t_VDC1">VDC</gloss> recruited at the village
                                        level throughout Thailand can with continued indoctrination
                                        be expected to help to create an increasing awareness among
                                        the local population of the nature of the Communist
                                        threat.</p>
                                    <p>The Viet Minh sympathizers among the Vietnamese refugees in
                                        the northeast would probably support Communist guerrilla
                                        operations in their area and would furnish a source of
                                        recruits if there were any indications of Communist success.
                                        Some Chinese would assist the Thai Government in its efforts
                                        to combat Chinese Communist subversive elements, although
                                        the majority would attempt to remain uncommitted. The hill
                                        tribes in Thailand, who have no political loyalties or
                                        awareness, would provide a limited amount of intelligence to
                                        whichever side could gain their friendship or pay them. Hill
                                        tribe areas might provide a base for guerrilla
                                        operations.</p></item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">III. Analysis of Local U.S.
                                    Programs of Assistance Which Support or Could be Adjusted to
                                    Support Indigenous Counter-Measures Outlined in II
                                Above.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>A.</label>
                                <item><p>The present <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> troop basis
                                        is designed to: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Preserve internal security.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>Deter external aggression.</item>
                                        </list></p>
                                    <p>It is believed that the present force units are adequate in
                                        organization and equipment if properly trained, led and
                                        supported. Weaknesses are lack of an honest and competent
                                        administration, training <pb facs="0848" n="820" xml:id="pg_820"/> deficiencies, a large number of
                                        incompetent and unqualified higher officers and officials,
                                        and the inability of the high command to plan, execute or
                                        support military operations.</p></item>
                                <label>B.</label>
                                <item><p>The present <gloss target="#t_GPF1">GPF</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_VDC1">VDC</gloss> training programs are
                                        designed to: <list>
                                            <label>(1)</label>
                                            <item>Increase the internal security potential of the
                                                police.</item>
                                            <label>(2)</label>
                                            <item>Provide forces to maintain border security.</item>
                                            <label>(3)</label>
                                            <item>Provide forces able to combat infiltration and to
                                                conduct successful anti-guerrilla action in the
                                                event infiltration is accomplished.</item>
                                            <label>(4)</label>
                                            <item>Provide forces (<gloss target="#t_VDC1">VDC</gloss>) to act as a reserve for the regular
                                                Army and Police forces.</item>
                                            <label>(5)</label>
                                            <item>To provide an indoctrination channel from the
                                                government to the local populace and a channel for
                                                information flow from isolated areas to the
                                                government.</item>
                                        </list></p>
                                    <p>As with the Army, it is believed that the present force units
                                        are adequate in organization and equipment if properly
                                        trained, led and supported. Present weaknesses are lack of
                                        competent administration, lack of adequate staff and command
                                        structure and, in high places, a lack of understanding of
                                        the need for same, training deficiencies, and inadequate
                                        communications personnel.</p></item>
                                <label>C.</label>
                                <item>The psychological offensive being undertaken by the Thai
                                    Government with the assistance of <gloss target="#t_USIS1">USIS</gloss> is designed to indoctrinate government
                                    officials, Buddhist monks, teachers, members of the armed
                                    services and the general public with the evils of Communism and
                                    the dangers of Communist subversion, and at the same time to
                                    arouse in the people a greater awareness and appreciation of
                                    Thailand’s national heritage as an independent nation, the
                                    efforts of the Thai Government to promote the well-being of the
                                    people, and the important role Thailand is playing as a member
                                    of the Free World. This indoctrination is necessarily a slow
                                    educational process.</item>
                            </list>
                            <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">IV. Recommendations.</hi></p>
                            <list>
                                <label>A.</label>
                                <item>That no major change in the present force basis be
                                    made.</item>
                                <label>B.</label>
                                <item>That efforts be continued to vitalize the command and staff of
                                    the military and police forces.</item>
                                <label>C.</label>
                                <item>That junior officer and specialist training (commo, intell,
                                    etc.) be emphasized in the <gloss target="#t_GPF1">GPF</gloss>
                                    and in the Thai military services.</item>
                                <label>D.</label>
                                <item>That “defense orientation” courses be continued as an integral
                                    part of the training cycle of the <gloss target="#t_GPF1">GPF</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_VDC1">VDC</gloss> and
                                    military forces.</item>
                                <label>E.</label>
                                <item>That the Thais be encouraged to continue the psychological
                                    offensive program over a period of years in order to achieve a
                                    basic appreciation of the Communist threat.</item>
                                <label>F.</label>
                                <item>That when the state of training and administration warrants
                                    it, a program to cache stacks of specialized arms and equipment
                                    for unconventional warfare be instituted.</item>
                            </list>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>