<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>487. Memorandum of a Conversation Between the Thai Ambassador (Pote Sarasin)
                    and the Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs () and the
                    Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (Sebald), Department
                    of State, Washington, March 6, 1956), Department of State, Washington, March 6,
                    1956</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v22</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d487</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">487</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1956-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1956-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec2HqULsC7KBoXeW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85113862"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="recNXXPEroL3ThjDj" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="reczUgzr2M4lUGdR7" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Embargo</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1956-03-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1956-03-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="487"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d487">
                <head>487. Memorandum of a Conversation Between the Thai Ambassador (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SP1" type="from">Pote Sarasin</persName>) and the Deputy
                    Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SWJ1" type="to">Sebald</persName>), Department of State,
                    Washington, March 6, 1956<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d487fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>/<gloss
                            target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss> Files: Lot 58 D 782, Rice—Thailand.
                        Official Use Only. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_FRH1"
                        >Foster</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date"
                            when="1956-03-06">
                            <hi rend="italic">March 6, 1956</hi>
                        </date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Disposal of U.S. Surplus Rice in Asia; Sale of Rice to Communist
                        China</item>
                </list>
                <pb facs="0885" n="857" xml:id="pg_857"/>
                <p>The Thai Ambassador called at his request to discuss the problem of the disposal
                    of U.S. surplus rice in Asia with particular reference to the recent <gloss
                        target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>–480<note n="2" xml:id="d487fn2">Public Law 480,
                        Agricultural Trade Development and Assistance Act of 1954, signed July 10,
                        1954. (68 Stat. 454)</note> Agreement with Pakistan.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d487fn3">For text of the Surplus Agricultural Commodities Agreement
                        between the United States and Pakistan, signed February 9, 1956, see 7
                            <gloss target="#t_UST1">UST</gloss> 359.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Ambassador stated that a Pakistan rice purchasing mission had been in Burma
                    negotiating for a purchase of rice there and, it was understood, had intended to
                    go on to Bangkok and purchase 50,000 tons from Thailand. Unfortunately, however,
                    the news of the U.S. Public Law 480 program for Pakistan reached the Pakistani
                    Purchasing Mission and they naturally then found it unnecessary to submit a bid
                    for Thai rice which was available.</p>
                <p>The Thai Ambassador pointed out forcefully that Thailand must export rice to get
                    the foreign exchange it needs so badly. He appreciated fully the domestic
                    political pressure on the Administration from the farmers of America and
                    understood present U.S. policy of seeking to avoid disturbance of normal
                    marketings.</p>
                <p>He pointed out, however, that famines and disasters had occurred in Asia from
                    time immemorial and that Thai prosperity depended not only on its normal
                    marketings in good times, but also on abnormal sales which seemed to be required
                    each year in some distressed area of the Far East. He stated that Pakistan in
                    the past had purchased rice from Thailand when emergency conditions there
                    required importation of food.</p>
                <p>The Ambassador stressed the increasing pressure which was being placed on the
                    Thai Government to move its rice each year, and pointed out that sufficient
                    revenue for economic development in Thailand could not be derived from receipts
                    of normal marketings.</p>
                <p>U.S. policy with regard to U.S. surplus sales in Asia was again explained to the
                    Ambassador. It was indicated that the U.S. was carefully seeking to avoid
                    interfering with normal marketings of rice in Asia, and the example of prior
                    consultation with Burmese and Thai representatives concerning the projected
                    Indonesian purchase of rice was cited.<note n="4" xml:id="d487fn4">On March 2,
                        the United States and Indonesia signed a Surplus Agricultural Commodities
                        Agreement, under which the United States agreed, inter alia, to finance the
                        sale of $35.8 million of rice to Indonesia during fiscal years 1956 and
                        1957. For text of the agreement, see 7 <gloss target="#t_UST1">UST</gloss>
                        361.</note> The U.S. was insisting in each case that purchasers of U.S. rice
                    obtain from their normal suppliers a quantity of rice not less than that
                    purchased in previous years. This stipulation, it was hoped, would minimize the
                    impact of U.S. entrance into the rice market, and carry out the assurances given
                    to both Burma and Thailand <pb facs="0886" n="858" xml:id="pg_858"/> by Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_BCF1">Charles Baldwin</persName> during his recent
                    mission to these countries.<note n="5" xml:id="d487fn5">Regarding the visit of
                        the <persName corresp="#p_BCF1">Baldwin</persName> rice mission to Rangoon
                        in May 1955, see <ref target="#d8">Document 8</ref>. Regarding the
                        subsequent visit of the mission to Thailand, see <ref target="#d473"
                            >Document 473</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Ambassador raised the question of selling rice to Communist China, pointing
                    out that China had been in times past one of Thailand’s largest rice customers.
                    He indicated his awareness that Thailand had placed rice on its <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> embargo list, but expressed his understanding
                    that rice was not a strategic material and could be removed voluntarily at any
                    time from the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> embargo list. He stated that
                    Communist Chinese goods were finding their way into Thailand via Hong Kong, and
                    that at present this trade was resulting in a loss of Thai foreign exchange.</p>
                <p>The fear was expressed to the Thai Ambassador that the sale of Thai rice to
                    Communist China could give the Chinese Communists a political hold over
                    Thailand. Such an economic leverage could severely restrict Thai freedom of
                    action in determining its national interest.</p>
                <p>The Thai Ambassador indicated his appreciation of the danger to Thailand in this
                    regard, but indicated his distress that no other alternative appeared possible
                    at this time. Communist China needed Thai rice, Thai rice must be sold, yet
                    Thailand’s traditional Free World customers were receiving their requirements
                    from the United States at a subsidized price which Thailand could not possibly
                    hope to match.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
