<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-04-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-04-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="92" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d92">
                        <head>92. Memorandum From the Officer in Charge of Indonesian and Pacific
                            Island Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HPE1" type="from">Haring</persName>) to the Director of the Office of Philippine and
                            Southeast Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_YKT1" type="to">Young</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d92fn1">Source:
                                Department of State, Central Files, 656C.56D/4–1155. Top
                                Secret.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1955-04-11"><hi rend="italic">April 11,
                                1955</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Meeting on April 8, 1955 with <gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>—Mr.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MR2">Murphy</persName> to discuss <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> recommendations for revising US
                                policy on the Western New Guinea issue<note n="2" xml:id="d92fn2">See the enclosure, <ref target="#d91"><hi rend="italic">supra.</hi></ref></note></item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>The following Departmental officers participated:</head>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MR2">Murphy</persName> and Mr. Goodyear,<note n="3" xml:id="d92fn3">John Goodyear, Special Assistant to the Deputy Under Secretary
                                    of State.</note></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>—Mr. Bowie and Mr.
                                    <persName>Schwartz</persName>,<note n="4" xml:id="d92fn4"><persName>Harry Schwartz</persName>, member of the Policy
                                    Planning Staff and <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Planning
                                    Board Assistant.</note></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName>,</item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>—Mr. <persName>Key</persName> and
                                Mr. <persName>Popper</persName>,<note n="5" xml:id="d92fn5"><persName>David H. Popper</persName>, Director of the
                                    Office of United Nations Political and Security
                                Affairs.</note></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName></item>
                            <item><gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> and myself.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>On the grounds that there might be some possibility of influencing the
                            Indonesians to minimize the West New Guinea issue, and <pb facs="0175" n="147" xml:id="pg_147"/> that we are losing the support of the
                            Australians and Dutch, <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss> felt we
                            should take the occasion of the review of our policy toward Indonesia to
                            move off the neutrality position. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName> said that neutrality favored the Indonesians
                            especially in that it implied that we felt a dispute existed as to the
                            area. He wished to have a position that would be helpful in our
                            relations with the Australians and the Dutch before the next <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> and that would forestall
                            deterioration of our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ANZUS1">ANZUS</gloss>, and other relations where we work
                            so closely with these countries. He conceded that neither the Dutch nor
                            the Australians were likely to go so far as to withdraw from these
                            activities with us and that their other interests might outweigh
                            immediate considerations on the New Guinea problem, but that as a
                            continuing irritant on which we failed to respond to them we were
                            damaging our relations with them with effects on “our whole European
                            complex”.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MADII1">MacArthur</persName> noted that what we
                            do vis-à-vis Indonesia has vast implications to keeping that country of
                            80 million out of Communist hands and even wider implications as to the
                            whole <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss> area which is already
                            turbulent.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> described the
                            neutral policy which had been successfully held thus far as the best
                            possible course we could follow. He said he knew the Australian and
                            Dutch Ambassadors here very well and that they seemed to understand our
                            position and the other issues involved. It is in their own interest that
                            an inflammatory issue, such as West New Guinea, not blow up and incite
                            the Indonesians to move away from the relatively favorable developments
                            we expect to come out of their forthcoming national elections. Nothing
                            could more damage the Dutch and the Australians than to have the
                            Indonesians more unsettled and go toward the Communists for support; New
                            Guinea interests would be insignificant in comparison to those
                            problems.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RWS1">Robertson</persName> said he saw no need
                            for a US hand in the matter at all; the Dutch by signing Article II of
                            the <gloss target="#t_RTC1">RTC</gloss><note n="6" xml:id="d92fn6">Reference is to the Charter of Transfer of Sovereignty (from the
                                Netherlands to Indonesia), one of several agreements included in the
                                Round Table Conference Agreement, which was accepted at the Round
                                Table Conference at The Hague, November 2, 1949, and went into force
                                on December 27, 1949. For text, see 69 UNTS 3.</note> conceded that
                            there was a dispute, and if our position of neutrality actually
                            suggested that a dispute existed it was no more than the Dutch
                            themselves said when they signed the Article; we do not have to take a
                            position that no dispute exists and we can look to revision of the US
                            policy on New Guinea when and if the Communist threat or other factors
                            cause us to do it.</p>
                        <pb facs="0176" n="148" xml:id="pg_148"/>
                        <p>There was common agreement among <gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_SP1">S/P</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_C1">C</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_FE1">FE</gloss>, and <gloss target="#t_IO1">IO</gloss>
                            that no approach should be made to the Indonesians at this time and that
                            we should not be revising our policy at this time.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_G1">G</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MR2">Murphy</persName> suggested prefacing the draft paragraph with the
                            words: “Since general elections are due in Indonesia in late 1955, we
                            should await their outcome, in the meantime,” maintaining our
                            neutrality, etc.</p>
                        <p><gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>—Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BW1">Barbour</persName> indicated he would like to discuss that
                            suggestion with others in <gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>