<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>153. Memorandum From Acting Secretary of State Rush to the President’s
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs ( to the President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs (Kissinger))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d153</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">153</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe">CSCE</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recvoN4ztaer4BBF6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh99005236"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Employment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-05-23T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-05-23T00:00:00-05:00" n="153"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d153">
                <head>153. Memorandum From Acting Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RKW1"
                        type="from">Rush</persName> to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="to"
                        >Kissinger</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d153fn1">Source:
                        National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential
                        Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 248, Agency Files,
                            <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_MBFR1"
                            >MBFR</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Limdis1">Limdis</gloss>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-05-23">May 23, 1973</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Soviet Draft of a <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> Final
                        Declaration</item>
                </list>
                <p>In response to your request to Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWJJ1"
                        >Stoessel</persName>, he called in separately <gloss target="#t_FRG1"
                        >FRG</gloss> Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_SB6">von Staden</persName> and
                    the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss> and French Ministers (<persName
                        corresp="#p_SR3">Sykes</persName> and de La Gorce) on May 21, to invite the
                    views of their Governments on both the substance of the January Soviet draft of
                    a final <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> declaration and the tactics for
                    dealing with it. All three undertook to be back in touch with us soon.</p>
                <p>This was the first occasion on which the Department has mentioned the Soviet
                    draft to other Governments. In passing on to the three <pb facs="0510" n="475"
                        xml:id="pg_475"/> Embassies copies of the attached annotated text containing
                    the Department’s comments on various passages, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SWJJ1"
                        >Stoessel</persName>: <list>
                        <item>—underlined the confidentiality of this consultation;</item>
                        <item>—referred to the circumstances under which the draft was received by
                            all four of the Allies, noting that, for our part, we had taken no other
                            action than an internal study of the draft;<note n="2" xml:id="d153fn2"
                                >An undated, annotated version of the Soviet draft with comments by
                                the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff is ibid., <persName
                                    corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> Office Files, Box 77,
                                Europe, <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, Moscow Trip, <gloss
                                    target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>—reported that the Soviets had asked you, during your recent visit to
                            the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, for reactions, and had
                            expressed understanding for your response that you wished first to
                            consult with our Allies;</item>
                        <item>—noted that the draft, while clearly contrary in various respects to
                            Allied positions, seemed to have been somewhat overtaken by events at
                            the preparatory talks in Helsinki; nevertheless, we would wish to be
                            prepared to deal with the possibility that the Soviets may table this
                            draft or something like it as early as the initial <gloss
                                target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> meeting of foreign ministers
                            anticipated in late June; and</item>
                        <item>—invited their views on the substance of the draft, the advisability
                            and method of proceeding with possible broader Alliance consultations,
                            what response might be given the Soviets should they again raise this
                            matter during <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s visit to
                            Washington in June, and how the Allies should treat this or other
                            similar documents placed on the table at the initial <gloss
                                target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> ministerial.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SB6">Von Staden</persName> was quite familiar with the
                    Soviet draft, which he confirmed was received from the Soviets in Bonn. The
                    Germans had not consulted with other Allied Governments, and had replied simply
                    that many points in the draft were unacceptable. To his knowledge, the matter
                    was left at that.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SB6">Von Staden</persName> expressed concern at this
                    evidence of a Soviet effort to bypass the essentially inductive approach to
                        <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> discussions devised with some effort
                    at <gloss target="#t_MPT1">MPT</gloss> and, speaking personally, cautioned that
                    a quadripartite response to the Soviets would be adversely received not only by
                    our other Allies but also by the wider circle of Western and non-aligned <gloss
                        target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> states.</p>
                <p>British Minister <persName corresp="#p_SR3">Sykes</persName> noted that
                    preliminary British comments on the draft had been given earlier to Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName>,<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d153fn3">Not found.</note> but undertook to bring these up to date.
                    Speaking personally, he saw no objection to an initial discussion of the Soviet
                    draft in the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Council, which he thought
                    should probably be followed rather quickly by broader Western consultations in
                    Helsinki.</p>
                <pb facs="0511" n="476" xml:id="pg_476"/>
                <p>French Minister de La Gorce was apparently not familiar with the Soviet draft,
                    nor any French-Soviet consultations concerning it, but undertook to obtain
                    reactions from Paris.</p>
                <p>The attached copy of the Soviet draft containing Departmental annotations<note
                        n="4" xml:id="d153fn4">Attached but not printed.</note> has been updated to
                    take into account recent developments in the Helsinki talks. Also attached is
                    the latest version of the Allied draft of a <gloss target="#t_CSCE1"
                        >CSCE</gloss> declaration of principles of inter-state relations,<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d153fn5">Attached but not printed.</note> which is still rather
                    heavily bracketted. Without a significantly greater effort of will in Allied
                    capitals, this draft is not likely to be in <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1"
                        >shape</gloss> for presentation to the Soviets by the time of the <persName
                        corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> visit to Washington.</p>
                <p>Further, we would also anticipate objections from at least some Allies to our
                    providing this Allied text to the Soviets prior to the conference. Most of the
                    Allies appear to favor a minimum of substantive discussions at the initial
                    meeting of foreign ministers and the employment in the second phase of the
                    conference of the “bottom up” or inductive approach employed successfully at
                        <gloss target="#t_MPT1">MPT</gloss>. Thus, we believe most would prefer not
                    to table Allied texts at the outset, particularly if the Soviets could be
                    persuaded to exercise similar restraint.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RKW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Kenneth Rush</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
