<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>155. Transcript of Telephone Conversation Between the President’s Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (Kissinger) and the Assistant Secretary of State
                    for European Affairs () and the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                    Affairs (Stoessel))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d155</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">155</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-06-02T12:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-06-02T12:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recydYSQ1GmGAh8yu" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                    <term ref="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe">CSCE</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-06-02T12:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-06-02T12:45:00-05:00" n="155"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d155">
                <head>155. Transcript of Telephone Conversation Between the President’s Assistant
                    for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from"
                        >Kissinger</persName>) and the Assistant Secretary of State for European
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SWJJ1" type="to">Stoessel</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d155fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName> Telephone Transcripts
                            (<gloss target="#t_Telcon1">Telcon</gloss>s), Box 20, Chronological
                        File. No classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1973-06-02T13:45:00-04:00">June 2, 1973, 1:45 p.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_HK1">HK</gloss>: Hello, Walt?</p>
                <p>AS: Hello, Henry.</p>
                <p>K: <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> complains to me that our guy
                    in Helsinki is leading the charge on the troop movement,<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d155fn2">No record of <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName>’s conversation with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName> has been found. Telegram 99029 to Helsinki, May 23,
                        reported that <persName corresp="#p_VYM1">Vorontsov</persName> had “raised
                        the issue of prior notification of major military movements” in a
                        conversation with <persName corresp="#p_SWJJ1">Stoessel</persName> on May
                        22. Speaking for <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_VYM1">Vorontsov</persName> said that Moscow assumed “that
                        there is full understanding by the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> of the
                        Soviet view that such notification should not be included in the security
                        mandate. It appeared still to be causing difficulties in Helsinki, however,
                        and Moscow would like the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> to do what it
                        could to remove this stumbling block. <persName corresp="#p_SWJJ1"
                            >Stoessel</persName> agreed that we had a clear understanding of the
                        Soviet view on this subject.” (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy Files)</note> now I promised <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, I promised <pb facs="0514" n="479"
                        xml:id="pg_479"/>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> and I promised <persName
                        corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> that we would get off troop movements
                    and stick to maneuvers.</p>
                <p>AS: <persName>Henry</persName>, we have and I just saw him this morning—indicated
                    they have reached agreement there on a formulation which is satisfactory to the
                    Soviets.</p>
                <p>K: Oh really?</p>
                <p>AS: Yeah, so I think we are okay, just a second, Henry, let me check this.
                        <persName>Henry</persName>, I’m sure that is true.</p>
                <p>K: Okay, I’ll tell him Monday.<note n="3" xml:id="d155fn3">At 1:50 p.m. on June
                        2, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> phoned <persName
                            corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>. A transcript of their telephone
                        conversation reads in part: “<gloss target="#t_HK1">HK</gloss> [<persName
                            corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>]: First on troop movements, I am
                        told you don’t know what the hell you are talking about. They’ve already
                        settled it. AD[<persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>]: In what
                        way? I just received a telegram on Friday signed by <persName
                            corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> that I need to approach you, but
                        you were in Iceland. <gloss target="#t_HK1">HK</gloss>: Our people tell me
                        that on Saturday morning that they got a tele—they seemed to have settled it
                        today. AD: You are just telling me what I am telling you but I am telling
                        you what exactly what was yesterday or even today, so in what way is it
                        settled? <gloss target="#t_HK1">HK</gloss>: I haven’t looked at it, but that
                        they say they and you agreed on a formulation that’s acceptable.” (Ibid.,
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Henry A. Kissinger</persName> Telephone
                        Transcripts (<gloss target="#t_Telcon1">Telcon</gloss>s), Box 20,
                        Chronological File)</note>
                </p>
                <p>AS: Yeah, really it shouldn’t be a problem. They agreed to have the second phase
                    study this question and make reports on it.</p>
                <p>K: Now, look there is another idea—first of all can I get your comments on our
                    draft communiqué<note n="4" xml:id="d155fn4">
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> is referring to the draft
                        communiqué for <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName>’s forthcoming
                        visit to the United States. Regarding the final communiqué, see <ref
                            target="#d163">Document 163</ref>.</note> soon?</p>
                <p>AS: Yeah, we are working on that right now, we’ll get that over this
                    afternoon.</p>
                <p>K: Good, if I could have it this afternoon, I would appreciate it, because I may
                    have a meeting on it tomorrow.</p>
                <p>K: Now, here is another idea that I discussed with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> this morning<note n="5" xml:id="d155fn5">No record of
                        this conversation has been found.</note>—has to do with the <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> thing. They would consider setting a fixed
                    date for the <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> if we put into the communiqué
                    a phrase saying that <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> and the
                    President agreed on the desirability of concluding the European Security
                    Conference this year.</p>
                <p>AS: Yeah, all phases.</p>
                <p>K: On the desirability, you know. But I won’t see him until next week—can you
                    think about that?</p>
                <p>AS: Yeah, I think still this would cause some problems—we could just say on
                    desirability concluding the <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> as soon as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>K: That of course—</p>
                <pb facs="0515" n="480" xml:id="pg_480"/>
                <p>AS: They were worried they were going to string this thing out and use <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> to weigh the thing. Then we’ll think about
                    that one.</p>
                <p>K: Do you want to see if we can come up with something?</p>
                <p>AS: Yeah.</p>
                <p>K: Okay.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is discussion of matters other than the European security
                    conference or <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
