<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>26. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">26</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1970-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1970-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recAynYh8uzxYGQRH" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh95009928"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Strategic weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reductions</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        >Tactical nuclear forces</term>
                    <term ref="recydYSQ1GmGAh8yu" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">European security</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-06-09T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-06-09T00:00:00-05:00" n="26"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d26">
                <head>26. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d26fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                        Files 1970–73, POL <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–<gloss
                            target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Exdis1"
                            >Exdis</gloss>. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_REL1"
                            >Richardson</persName> on June 10. The conversation took place during
                        lunch at the Soviet Embassy. On June 16, <persName corresp="#p_HMJA1"
                            >Hillenbrand</persName> forwarded a copy to <persName corresp="#p_ERF1"
                            >Ellsworth</persName>. In an attached letter, <persName
                            corresp="#p_HMJA1">Hillenbrand</persName> wrote: “Our telegraphic
                        summary of that conversation was somewhat abridged because—as you will see
                        from the full <gloss target="#t_Memcon1">memcon</gloss> enclosed—the Under
                        Secretary’s remarks, while illustrative in nature, do break new ground and
                        go somewhat beyond what has thus far been agreed among the Allies. I am not
                        sure how you would wish to handle those elements of the <persName
                            corresp="#p_REL1">Richardson</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                            >Dobrynin</persName> exchange which we left out of the telegraphic
                        summary. The best course might be to wait and see whether the Soviets play
                        them back to the Allies. If they do, you could then confirm, if appropriate,
                        that the ideas in question were put forward on an illustrative basis but not
                        as the formal position of the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> government.”
                        (Ibid., DEF 6 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1970-06-09">June 9,
                            1970</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_REL1">Elliot L.
                            Richardson</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>After preliminary remarks, I handed <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> the <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>
                        guidelines.<note n="2" xml:id="d26fn2">See <ref target="#d28">Document
                            28</ref>.</note> He then asked me a serious of questions which I
                    answered in substance as follows: The <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    allies have no fixed views as to the composition of the group of countries which
                    should participate in <pb facs="0102" n="67" xml:id="pg_67"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> negotiations. I illustrated a possible
                    grouping on our side as comprising the countries having forces in Central Europe
                    and including the <gloss target="#t_UK1">UK</gloss>, France, <gloss
                        target="#t_FRG1">FRG</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>, plus, say,
                    one country from each of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> flanks, e.g.,
                    Norway and Italy. Two or more neutrals might perhaps be included as observers.
                    With respect to the forces and weapons systems included, I said that this might
                    depend in part on the definition of “strategic weapons” agreed to in <gloss
                        target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>: if this definition were ultimately to
                    exclude forward-based aircraft, IR/<gloss target="#t_MRBM1">MRBM</gloss>s and
                        <gloss target="#t_SLCM1">SLCM</gloss>s, then the latter could be covered in
                    the <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> talks. In any case, reductions could
                    optimally embrace a total combat slice from forward ground troops back to
                    supporting aircraft and tactical nuclear forces. Alternatively, initial
                    negotiations might focus on troop strength per se. In response to my remark that
                    the subject is, in many respects, at least as complex as <gloss
                        target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1"
                        >Dobrynin</persName> pointed out that, in the case of <gloss
                        target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>, we are dealing merely on a bilateral basis,
                    whereas here much greater additional complications would be introduced by the
                    necessity for each of us to get our allies’ agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> asked how we could propose that
                    there be no political preconditions on <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>
                    when, as he understood it, we had been putting preconditions on a possible
                    Conference on European Security. I explained that in the case of the <gloss
                        target="#t_CES1">CES</gloss> we have wanted to assess progress in the
                    Quadripartite talks, the bilateral talks between the <gloss target="#t_FRG1"
                        >FRG</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, <gloss
                        target="#t_GDR1">GDR</gloss> and Poland, <gloss target="#t_SALT1"
                        >SALT</gloss>, etc., in order to assure that the <gloss target="#t_CES1"
                        >CES</gloss> was not held simply for propaganda effect but rested rather on
                    a basis of genuine progress toward détente. In the case of <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>, however, we consider the subject as one
                    meriting negotiation on its own terms without reference to progress or the lack
                    of it in any other context.</p>
                <p>To the question why we made a distinction between the “forum” and the
                    “participants,” I said that both words were used in order to reflect our
                    awareness of such possible alternatives as dealing with the matter through a
                    specially convened ad hoc body or, conceivably, through a commission or
                    subcommittee established at a <gloss target="#t_CES1">CES</gloss>. (I had
                    previously identified useful progress in exploratory talks on <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> as one of the things which, in some
                    combination with the others mentioned above, could help to justify holding a
                        <gloss target="#t_CES1">CES</gloss>.) In response to a crack by <persName
                        corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> that our military representatives must
                    be pretty lazy because they’ve had all the time since Reykjavik and still
                    haven’t produced an <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> model, I said that
                    nothing would speed them up so much as to have a full-dress conference set for
                    next October 15. <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> said that this
                    would be a little too soon even for the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.
                    In general, however, his questions were straightforwardly directed toward
                    eliciting information and in no sense reflected a negative attitude.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
