<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>334. Telegram From Secretary of State Kissinger to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d334</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">334</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1975-08-02T01:40:00-05:00" notAfter="1975-08-02T01:40:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe" type="topic"
                        category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe">CSCE</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026379"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Human rights</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recH8UKNUTXoDXkax" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85044163"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Environment</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="rece5d418c38338517" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        >Disarmament</term>
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1975-08-02T01:40:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1975-08-02T01:40:00-05:00" n="334"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d334">
                <head>334. Telegram From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA1" type="from"
                        >Kissinger</persName> to the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d334fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files. Limited
                        Official Use; Immediate.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Helsinki</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1975-08-02T06:40:00+00:00">August 2, 1975,
                        0640Z</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <gloss target="#t_SECTO1">Secto</gloss> 8109. Department pass to all <gloss
                        target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> capitals. Subject: <gloss target="#t_CSCE1"
                        >CSCE</gloss> III:Final day.</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Summary</hi>. <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> closed
                        at 6:00 pm on August 1, following signing of Final Act<note n="2"
                            xml:id="d334fn2">For text of the <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>
                            Final Act, see Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>,
                            September 1, 1975, pp. 323–350.</note> by thirty-five heads of state or
                        government. Highlights of final day were President <persName
                            corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>’s speech, which was considered by many
                        conference delegates as most forceful expression of Western view during
                        three days of speeches, delayed appearance of Portuguese President Costa
                            Gomes,<note n="3" xml:id="d334fn3">General Francisco da Costa
                            Gomes.</note> apology by Maltese for their behavior during last days of
                        the negotiations, and circulation by Cyprus of a statement in reply to
                        Turkish reservation on Cypriot representation. Full verbatim records will be
                        pouched to Department (<gloss target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/RPM) when
                        available. <hi rend="italic">End summary</hi>.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Portugal: Portuguese President Costa Gomes, who had postponed his
                        appearance from July 31 for reasons of “force majeur,” gave standard review
                        of conference results, but stressed Portugal’s “new path,” and stated that
                        Portuguese foreign policy was now based on full <pb facs="1010" n="975"
                            xml:id="pg_975"/> respect for the principles of sovereign equality,
                        non-intervention in the internal affairs of others, and the recognition of
                        the right of all peoples freely to dispose of themselves.</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>: President <persName corresp="#p_FGR1"
                            >Ford</persName>’s speech, which was considered by many to be strongest
                        statement of Western view of <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> heard
                        during Stage III, emphasized that both sides have to benefit from détente,
                        and that <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> results would be a yardstick
                        by which performance will be measured. The President stressed the deep
                        devotion of the American people and their government to human rights and
                        fundamental freedoms and said the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> intends
                        to participate fully in turning the results of the conference into a living
                        reality. Like Wilson, Schmidt, and <persName corresp="#p_GdEV1"
                            >Giscard</persName>, he noted that <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>
                        results are also applicable to Berlin. The President closed by stating that
                        history will judge the conference not by what is said but what is done to
                        carry out the promises of <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <item>Malta: In absence of <persName corresp="#p_MD2">Mintoff</persName>, who
                        was reportedly ill, Deputy Prime Minister Buttigieg concentrated on
                        Mediterranean aspects of <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> and Maltese
                        role in ensuring that Mediterranean interest in the conference was fully
                        reflected. Buttigieg apologized to all present “for any offense we may have
                        given during the exciting days in Geneva.” All that Maltese did, he said,
                        was “in a good cause,” and any animosity was due more to “our inexperience
                        than to any bad intention.”</item>
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <item>Netherlands: Prime Minister Van Den Uyl was somewhat reserved but
                        expressed hope that Basket III results would promote better understanding
                        among peoples, and admitted that “some optimism” might be justified. He
                        underlined that results of <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> would have
                        to be implemented if conference was to have any meaning, and looked for
                        progress now in <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> negotiations.</item>
                    <label>6.</label>
                    <item>Monaco: Minister of State Saint-Mleux<note n="4" xml:id="d334fn4">Andre
                            Leon Saint-Mleux.</note> stressed need for protection of environment in
                        the Mediterranean.</item>
                    <label>7.</label>
                    <item>Norway: Prime Minister Bratteli<note n="5" xml:id="d334fn5">Trygve
                            Bratteli.</note> reviewed conference results, expressed hope they would
                        be implemented, and looked forward to continuation of multilateral process
                        begun by <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>8.</label>
                    <item>Romania: In a long speech in which he departed considerably from his
                        prepared text, <persName corresp="#p_CN4">Ceausescu</persName> brought out
                        the principal elements of Romanian foreign policy: equal rights and
                        sovereignty of all states, renunciation of aggression or intervention in the
                        affairs of other countries, banishment of the threat or use of force, and
                        peaceful settlement of disputes. He called for further steps toward
                        disarmament and cooperation, but qualified his endorsement of Basket III
                        results, noting that information should serve the cause of friendship among
                        peoples. <pb facs="1011" n="976" xml:id="pg_976"/>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CN4">Ceausescu</persName> thought <gloss
                            target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> results would be conducive to the
                        elimination of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and the Warsaw
                        Pact.</item>
                    <label>9.</label>
                    <item>Liechtenstein, San Marino: These countries gave standard review of
                        conference results, emphasizing role of small states in <gloss
                            target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>.</item>
                    <label>10.</label>
                    <item>Luxembourg: Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_TG1">Thorn</persName>
                        also stressed role of smaller states at <gloss target="#t_CSCE1"
                            >CSCE</gloss>, and recalled that implementation of results would be real
                        test of the success of the conference.</item>
                    <label>11.</label>
                    <item>Holy See: Archbishop Casaroli<note n="6" xml:id="d334fn6">Archbishop
                            Agostino Casaroli.</note> read personal message addressed to the
                        conference by Pope Paul VI expressing hope for the success of the <gloss
                            target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss> enterprise, “in the name of God.”</item>
                    <label>12.</label>
                    <item>Cypriot interpretive statement: In response to Turkish reservation on
                        Cypriot representation circulated to the conference on July 31,<note n="7"
                            xml:id="d334fn7">Not found.</note> Cyprus circulated a formal
                        interpretive statement that participation in <gloss target="#t_CSCE1"
                            >CSCE</gloss> was on the basis of the full equality of states, and that
                        Turkish statement that it will not apply <gloss target="#t_CSCE1"
                            >CSCE</gloss> results to relations with Cyprus “is of no effect.”</item>
                    <label>13.</label>
                    <item>Signing: Following last speech, all thirty-five heads of state or
                        government gathered at broad horseshoe-shaped table and signed single
                        original copy in all six languages of the Final Act of the conference.
                        Completion of signing ceremony brought long round of applause. Finnish
                        President <persName corresp="#p_KU1">Kekkonen</persName> made brief closing
                        statement, and adjourned the <gloss target="#t_CSCE1">CSCE</gloss>.</item>
                </list>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Kissinger</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
