<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-10-04T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-10-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="344" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d344">
                        <head>344. National Intelligence Estimate<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d344fn1">Source: Central Intelligence Agency, NIC Files, Job
                                79–R01012A. Secret. The Central Intelligence Agency and the
                                intelligence organizations of the Departments of State and Defense,
                                the <gloss target="#t_NSA1">NSA</gloss>, the <gloss target="#t_AEC1">AEC</gloss>, and the Department of the Treasury participated in
                                the preparation of this estimate. The Director of Central
                                Intelligence submitted this estimate with the concurrence of all
                                members of the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Intelligence
                                Board, with the exception of the representatives of the <gloss target="#t_FBI1">FBI</gloss> who abstained on the grounds that
                                it was outside their jurisdiction. The estimate superseded <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11/20–73, which was not
                                found.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1973-10-04">October 4, 1973</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="flushleft">
                            <gloss target="#t_NIE1">NIE</gloss> 11/12–73</p>
                        <p rend="center">SOVIET AND EAST EUROPEAN ATTITUDES TOWARD <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>
                        </p>
                        <p rend="center">Principal Judgments</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>’s engagement in <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> negotiations has come as a byproduct
                            of its broader détente policies, and the Soviet leaders view <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> itself as a vehicle for furthering
                            these policies. They perceive that the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                            Government is under various pressures to achieve fairly rapid results,
                            and they hope this will give them a negotiating edge.</p>
                        <p>Neither in <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>, nor in their broader
                            détente policies for that matter, are the Soviets working for a
                            fundamental reconciliation between East and West nor are they interested
                            in underwriting West Europe’s stability and security. They have no
                            intention of allowing East-West relaxation to lead to an attenuation of
                            Soviet authority or Communist Party control in Eastern Europe. The
                            Soviets would see much greater disadvantages than potential gains in an
                            agreement which substantially altered present force levels or combat
                            capabilities on either the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> or
                            Warsaw Pact sides. A central and recurring theme in negotiations will be
                            the claim that the Warsaw Pact does not have a significant military edge
                            over <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> in Europe and cannot agree
                            therefore to making unequal cuts in its forces. The Soviets will hold
                            hard to the position that the existing relationship of forces should
                            remain essentially unchanged.</p>
                        <p>The Soviets would have a decidedly negative first reaction to a Western
                            proposal calling for them to withdraw one of their tank armies, with men
                            and equipment, while the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> would have
                            flexibility as to the kinds of units to be withdrawn and the disposition
                            of equipment. The Soviets would also refuse to accept the proposition
                            that a common ceiling for Warsaw Pact and <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> ground forces should be the goal of follow-on
                            negotiations. The Soviets might even question whether proposals of this
                            kind were bona fide. And they might, in anticipation of such proposals
                            or in response to them, attempt to alter the bargaining framework by
                            bringing forward their own counterproposals.</p>
                        <pb facs="1039" n="1004" xml:id="pg_1004"/>
                        <p>However they play these issues, they will not want the negotiations to
                            break down or become indefinitely stalemated. Perhaps their tactic would
                            be to attempt to force the Western side to scale down its overall
                            requirements and to make concessions with respect to the separate
                            elements of its proposals. They could, for example, seek a quid pro quo
                            in <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> armored forces in return for any
                            reduction in their tank formations. They would also want to explore the
                            possibility of tradeoffs involving <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                            tactical nuclear forces in Europe.</p>
                        <p>It will be the aim of the Soviets to have a minimum of collateral
                            constraints attached to a reductions agreement. They would, in
                            particular, oppose measures which could effectively restrict their
                            ability to move forces into or within Eastern Europe. They are sure to
                            contend that the requirements of verification should be met to the
                            fullest extent possible by “national technical means.”</p>
                        <p>Although the Soviets believe that they are in a strong bargaining
                            position in <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>, they will want to
                            appear reasonable and to keep the negotiations progressing. How much or
                            how little “give” there will be in their negotiating position will
                            depend partly on their assessment of the urgency of the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> need to achieve early agreement. The
                                <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> is likely to recognize, at the
                            same time, that the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and its European
                            allies will regard its position in negotiations as a test of the
                            genuineness of its interest in détente. And as negotiations proceed, the
                            Soviet position will probably be influenced by “linkages” which will be
                            set up between <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> and other matters,
                            such as <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> and East-West trade.</p>
                        <p>The outcome of the first phase of negotiations will, of course, be
                            conditioned by the interaction of the positions of the two sides in the
                            negotiating process. In the end, however, the Soviets would probably be
                            prepared to accept an agreement based on the following ingredients: <list>
                                <item>—reductions limited to <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> and
                                    Soviet forces in Central Europe</item>
                                <item>—an order of magnitude of 10 to 15 percent applying to
                                    reductions of ground forces</item>
                                <item>—some asymmetry in terms of larger numerical Soviet troop
                                    reductions than <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss> troop
                                    reductions, with compensating <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                                    withdrawal of some tactical nuclear elements</item>
                                <item>—a minimum of collateral restraints and verification
                                    provisions.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>They would also see advantages in agreeing to follow-on negotiations,
                            especially because of their desire to secure reductions in West German
                            forces. But they would not agree to having the goals of a further phase
                            (e.g., a common ceiling) laid out in advance.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is the body of the estimate.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>