<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>353. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d353</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">353</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Ministerial meeting</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recwBHUin5Stz6rON" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002434"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Alliance</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="recfkRWjb8Vcm4Gga" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005004553"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Warheads</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="353" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d353">
                <head>353. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>In December 1974 and January 1975, the Ford administration discussed at the
                    highest levels when and whether to introduce a nuclear option at the mutual and
                    balanced force reduction (<gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>) talks in
                    Vienna. At the beginning of December 1974, in response to Secretary <pb
                        facs="1069" n="1034" xml:id="pg_1034"/> of Defense <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName>’s letter of December 3 (<ref
                        target="#d352">Document 352</ref>), Secretary of State <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> discussed with <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName> the timing for introducing a
                    nuclear option. At a meeting on December 7 with President <persName
                        corresp="#p_FGR1">Ford</persName>, President’s Deputy Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs <persName corresp="#p_SB3">Scowcroft</persName>, and <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> said: “At <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, I
                    would hold the nuclear package for now. About March would be best. I think
                        <persName corresp="#p_BLI1">Brezhnev</persName> might be ready to move on
                        <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> in preparation for the summit.”
                    (Library of Congress, Manuscript Division, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> Papers, Box CL 431, Subject File, <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName>, <persName>James R.</persName>,
                    Memoranda of Conversation) <persName corresp="#p_LJ3">Jan Lodal</persName> of
                    the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff wrote in his log on December 7:
                        “<persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> met this morning. <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> talked <persName corresp="#p_SJR1"
                        >Schlesinger</persName> out of telling the rump <gloss target="#t_NPG1"
                        >NPG</gloss> session that we were considering reducing nuclear weapons. He
                    also talked him out of moving on <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> until
                    March.” (Ford Library, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Program Analysis
                    Staff, <persName corresp="#p_LJ3">Jan Lodal</persName> Convenience Files, Box
                    70, Daily Log)</p>
                <p>On December 10, <persName corresp="#p_LJ3">Lodal</persName> sent a White House
                    telegram (<gloss target="#t_TOHAK1">Tohak</gloss> 2) to <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, who was en route to the December
                    12–13 <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Ministerial meeting in Brussels. The
                    telegram reads in part: “Two items concerning nuclear elements in <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> showed up in the press today from Brussels.
                    You should be aware of them. Upon arrival in Brussels on December 9, <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName> had the following exchange with
                    newsmen, in part: ‘Q: Mr. Secretary, what do you see as the focus of the
                    ministerial meetings at this time? A: The focus of the ministerial meetings will
                    be to achieve a long range strategy for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.
                    [omission in the original] I might mention the result of the Vladivostok
                    conference. I think from the standpoint of Western Europe that the results are
                    interesting not only in terms of the agreement between the United States and the
                    Soviet Union to have equality in terms of the number of central strategic
                    systems, but perhaps more significant is the willingness of the Soviet Union to
                    abandon a position that it has maintained for some years that would require
                    forward based systems to be included in considerations with regard to central
                    strategic systems. Forward based systems were dropped from any discussion with
                    relation to the central strategic systems, and to the extent that there will be
                    any discussion of forward based systems, it would take place within the
                    discussions going on [regarding] mutual and balanced force reductions. This has
                    been a matter of concern to our European allies for some years, and therefore it
                    is particularly noteworthy that the results of the Vladivostok conference have
                    given them cause to rejoice on this particular issue. In addition, I might say
                    that the decision to establish a common ceiling with regard to strategic
                    delivery vehicles would be a harbinger of a decision to accept a common ceiling
                    with regard to forces in Central Europe.’” <persName corresp="#p_LJ3"
                        >Lodal</persName> commented: “<persName corresp="#p_SJR1"
                        >Schlesinger</persName> may have been trying to reassure the Europeans that
                    no <gloss target="#t_FBS1">FBS</gloss> deal was made with the Soviets as per
                    your conversation on December 6. However, his remarks are certain to be
                    interpreted by some <pb facs="1070" n="1035" xml:id="pg_1035"/> as an admission
                    that we agreed with the Soviets to discuss <gloss target="#t_FBS1">FBS</gloss>
                    in <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>. As you may know, there has been a good
                    bit of speculation on this point in the European press for the past week or so.
                    In addition to <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName>’s comments,
                    the Netherlands’ Defense Minister Vredeling told the Eurogroup that the Dutch
                    would propose to the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> ministerial meeting
                    Thursday that ‘the alliance’s tactical nuclear weapons be considered a
                    bargaining counter’ in the <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> talks. West
                    German Defense Minister <persName corresp="#p_LG1">Leber</persName> objected to
                    this proposal, calling it ‘bad and unwise.’ He commented that ‘if the East wants
                    to bring up such a point, it should say what it is willing to reduce.’ All of
                    this has been reported in the press.” On December 11, <persName corresp="#p_SB3"
                        >Scowcroft</persName> wrote to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> in telegram <gloss target="#t_TOHAK1">Tohak</gloss>
                    11: “I mentioned the <hi rend="italic">Schlesinger</hi> comments about <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> to the President (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Hakto</hi> 1). The President agrees completely with you that such talk
                    should stop, and I am so informing <persName corresp="#p_SJR1"
                        >Schlesinger</persName>.” (Both in the Ford Library, National Security
                    Adviser, Presidential Trip Files, Box 7, December 14–16, 1974, Martinique,
                        <gloss target="#t_TOHAK1">Tohak</gloss> 12/10–13/74)</p>
                <p>Telegram 492 from the United States delegation to the <gloss target="#t_MBFR1"
                        >MBFR</gloss> talks, December 10, recommended “that the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> decide to introduce Option 3 into the <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> negotiations in the near future and begin
                    specific consultations with the Allies on it by the beginning of January with a
                    view to introducing Option 3 in Vienna early in the next round.” Telegram 271497
                    to the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> delegation to the <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> talks, December 11, responded: “The Secretary
                    has read <gloss target="#t_Reftel1">reftel</gloss>. He will consider arguments
                    presented therein further and review the matter in Washington. Meanwhile, he
                    wants no discussion of Option III with foreign representatives. The Secretary
                    has noted speculation that dropping of the <gloss target="#t_FBS1">FBS</gloss>
                    in <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> by Soviets in Vladivostok involved some
                    deal on use of Option III or even understanding on unilateral <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">US</gloss> nuclear cuts in Europe. This is of course totally
                    false. It also makes timing of any use of Option III that much more sensitive.”
                    (Both ibid., Presidential Country Files for Europe and Canada, Box 1, Austria,
                    from SecState–<gloss target="#t_Nodis1">Nodis</gloss>)</p>
                <p>On December 20, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> gave a deep
                    background briefing at a <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> negotiations?
                    Secretary: I have told my associates never to discuss this in the negotiations.
                    One should not make compromises on matters of national interest until thirty
                    seconds before midnight. The <persName corresp="#p_NS3">Nunn</persName>
                    amendment was not a wise move. If the Soviets know we are being forced to
                    withdraw our nuclear weapons, they will not give in.” The memorandum continues:
                    “Question: When do you expect an <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>
                    agreement? In the spring? Secretary: I gave no April one deadline to our <gloss
                        target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> colleagues in Brussels. The timing is bad as
                    it is too soon after Vladivostok to see a conclusion of the negotiations.”
                    (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                    Files, <gloss target="#t_P1">P</gloss>–7425337)</p>
                <pb facs="1071" n="1036" xml:id="pg_1036"/>
                <p>On January 16, 1975, the Verification Panel met to discuss Option III. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName> also attended. <persName
                        corresp="#p_LJ3">Lodal</persName> described the meeting in his daily log:
                    “We had an <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_VP1">VP</gloss> meeting in the afternoon. I met briefly with
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> before the meeting
                        (<persName corresp="#p_SB3">Scowcroft</persName> and then <persName
                        corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName> joined later). <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> started off by saying, ‘Can you tell
                    me what this meeting is all about?’ He wanted to know what the political
                    situation was—why was <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName> all of
                    a sudden getting excited about <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SB3">Brent</persName> and I explained that he wanted to take out
                    warheads from Europe. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> snidely
                    remarked, ‘Take the <gloss target="#t_nucs1">nucs</gloss> out of Europe—he’s
                    really the tough guy.’ <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName> then
                    came in and digressed about what <persName corresp="#p_IFC1">Ikle</persName>
                    would talk about. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> said that if
                        <persName corresp="#p_IFC1">Ikle</persName> had suggested it, the one thing
                    we would be sure about is that the idea was no good. He then asked a couple of
                    questions about what the <persName corresp="#p_NS3">Nunn</persName> Amendment
                    issue was, and I explained. <persName corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName>
                    told him he had to make a decision. <persName corresp="#p_SJR1"
                        >Schlesinger</persName> came to the meeting itself, which went very well.
                        <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> went through the major
                    options. <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName> indicated his
                    willingness to go along with Option III. <persName corresp="#p_RSR1"
                        >Resor</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_DJ1">Dean</persName> did not
                    know what our air manpower position was when asked directly by <persName
                        corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>—extremely embarrassing. We came out
                    of the meeting with a fairly clear consensus that we would play Option III and
                    try to get the tank army for it, but not agreement to the common ceiling.
                    Everyone agreed we would have to pitch in [to?] Europeans to get agreement to
                    the common ceiling.” <persName corresp="#p_LJ3">Lodal</persName>’s log
                    continues: “<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> was quite humorous
                    at the <gloss target="#t_VP1">VP</gloss> meeting—joking with <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName> by saying that ‘if people who know
                    something about the issues start coming to these meetings, it will disrupt the
                    entire process.’ <persName corresp="#p_SJR1">Schlesinger</persName> also did
                    well—after pointing out that <persName corresp="#p_LG1">Leber</persName> is the
                    German peacetime commander-inchief, he said this was an idea which ‘would
                    receive some support in this country.’ <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName> said he thought we were already there. It was quite a
                    humorous exchange.” (Ford Library, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Program
                    Analysis Staff, <persName corresp="#p_LJ3">Jan Lodal</persName> Convenience
                    Files, Box 70, Daily Log)</p>
                <p>The minutes of the Verification Panel meeting included the following “summary of
                    conclusions”: “It was agreed that: Defense will prepare a new Option III
                    package; an <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Meeting will be scheduled the
                    week of January 20, 1975; [and] the options to be decided by the President are:
                    play Option III for a Soviet tank army and agreement on a common ceiling for
                    Phase II; [or] play Option III for both a Soviet tank army and a common ceiling
                    in Phase II, but the Europeans must agree to take token Phase I reductions.”
                    (Ibid., <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Institutional Files (H-Files), Box
                        <gloss target="#t_H1">H</gloss>–110, Verification Panel Meeting Minutes,
                    Originals)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
