<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>371. Editorial Note</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v39</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d371</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">371</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">editorial-note</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1969-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1976-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reca29000439682274" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Warsaw Pact</term>
                    <term ref="rechQxXfPBmLXmMRi" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092473"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Naval forces</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recWYSm1K6WFkq0n5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093871"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Ocean</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recJclekZAp3yKmD5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006576"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Research</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067435"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Foreign policy</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1976-02-19T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-04-04T00:00:00-05:00" n="371" subtype="editorial-note"
                type="document" xml:id="d371">
                <head>371. Editorial Note</head>
                <p>During the spring and summer of 1976, the issue of data on military manpower for
                    the Warsaw Pact and North Atlantic Treaty Organization became a key point of
                    discussion in the Mutual and Balanced Force Reduction talks in Vienna. A member
                    of the <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> staff wrote in an undated memorandum
                    to Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> in May
                    1976: “Potentially a more interesting development [in the <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> talks] than either the Soviet response to
                    Option III or their counterproposal is the continued strong interest by the
                    Soviets in resolving the question of what forces should be covered by an <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> agreement and how these forces should be
                    divided between ground and air. Since last summer, this has been the Soviets’
                    primary preoccupation and they keep returning to it at every opportunity. In the
                    process they’ve given us many indications that when these discussions reach the
                    right stage, they will be prepared to put some specific numbers on the table.
                    Earlier in these discussions, Pact negotiators seemed to agree with ours that
                        <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> should cover all active duty military
                    manpower and should exclude reservists, para-military forces, and civilians, as
                    well as naval forces. The principal point of contention was how to divide the
                    active military between ground and air forces.” During the last round of
                    negotiations, the memorandum noted, “the Soviets withdrew their ‘draft <pb
                        facs="1126" n="1091" xml:id="pg_1091"/> definition’ and argued: that Pact
                    units are not fully manned; that only combat and combat-related forces should be
                    covered by <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>; that Pact active military
                    forces performing functions performed by civilians for <gloss target="#t_NATO1"
                        >NATO</gloss> should be excluded; that military personnel in schools, clubs,
                    institutes, etc., should be excluded; and that the <gloss target="#t_FRG1"
                        >FRG</gloss> Standby Readiness Reserve is actually an active military force
                    and should either be covered by <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> or the
                    Pact should be compensated by excluding a force of similar size.”</p>
                <p>The memorandum continued: “These developments indicate that the Soviets are
                    maneuvering to reduce or eliminate the disparity perceived by the West in the
                    manpower of the two sides. From their remarks in Vienna and intelligence
                    reports, we expected them to follow up at the end of the last session by tabling
                    data, based on their new ‘counting rules,’ which would show a markedly different
                    picture of the force relationship than does ours. However, they did not do this
                    and in the discussions near the end of the session Pact negotiators exhibited a
                    good deal of confusion and uncertainty about the whole process.” (Ford Library,
                    National Security Adviser, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Staff for Europe,
                    Canada and Ocean Affairs, Convenience Files, Box 52, Mutual and Balanced Force
                    Reductions, 1976)</p>
                <p>According to a history of the <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> talks
                    prepared by the Department of State, on June 10, 1976, “the Warsaw Pact tabled
                    figures claiming that it had 987,300 troops in the [<gloss target="#t_MBFR1"
                        >MBFR</gloss>] reductions area—805,000 ground forces and 182,300 air force
                    personnel. These figures were only a few thousand more than what the West had
                    declared as <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> force totals in the reductions
                    area, but some 174,700 fewer than <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    estimates of Warsaw Pact strength. The Pact military manpower in the reductions
                    area became the central unresolved issue in the negotiations.” (Department of
                    State, Office of the Historian, <hi rend="italic">Mutual and Balanced Force
                        Reduction (<gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>) Talks</hi>, 1973–1989,
                    Research Project No. 1553, May 1989, page 10)</p>
                <p>The delegation to the <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> talks reported in
                    telegram 351, July 3: “At the June 29 informal session of the Vienna force
                    reductions negotiations, Soviet <gloss target="#t_rep1">rep</gloss> Khlestov
                    refused to answer questions posed by Western reps concerning data tabled by the
                    East June 10, stating that the East was unwilling to discuss these data until
                    the West had tabled comparable figures for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                    forces in Central Europe.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1">RG</gloss>
                    59, Central Foreign Policy Files)</p>
                <p>On September 29, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and Soviet
                    Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName> discussed the
                        <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> data issue at a bilateral meeting in
                    New York during the session of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> General
                    Assembly. A memorandum of their conversation reads in part: “<persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: We did not receive a reaction to our
                    latest proposals [in Vienna]. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>:
                    Not to your proposals but to your giving the numbers. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: You [<hi rend="italic">We</hi>?]
                    suspect probably the <pb facs="1127" n="1092" xml:id="pg_1092"/> United States
                    is holding it. Maybe your brotherly ministry. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>: Sometimes we have problems relating to brother
                    ministries, sometimes problems regarding allies. We have two problems. One is
                    our [your?] figures with respect to your forces differ from our figures on your
                    forces. We have to at some point discuss what is included. The second problem is
                    France refuses to be included in the numbers. We are looking for a way to
                    exclude France but still give you a meaningful number. The numbers we have
                    aren’t significantly different from what we had in 1974, so you can use those.
                    Your intelligence can tell you. The basic problem is the French. We can give you
                    a figure that leaves out France but allows you to compensate for French forces
                    so we can’t use French forces to evade the overall obligation. <persName
                        corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: When can we get an answer? <persName
                        corresp="#p_HWG1">Hyland</persName>: October. It would be helpful if we
                    could discuss theirs. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: Could we
                    begin discussing the basis of your figures? <persName corresp="#p_KGM1"
                        >Korniyenko</persName>: Not before your figures. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>: That’s what I thought. <persName corresp="#p_HWG1"
                        >Hyland</persName>: Our figures haven’t changed much. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SHH1">Sonnenfeldt</persName>: We are using different criteria to
                    make the count. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>: The problem
                    the Foreign Minister is making is they won’t discuss their criteria until they
                    get our figures. <persName corresp="#p_KGM1">Korniyenko</persName>’s pithy
                    remark [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]. <persName corresp="#p_SHH1"
                        >Sonnenfeldt</persName>: I understand. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                        >Kissinger</persName>: We will give you the figures during October.
                        <persName corresp="#p_GAA1">Gromyko</persName>: All right. All right.”
                    (Memorandum of conversation, September 29; Ford Library, National Security
                    Adviser, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and <persName
                        corresp="#p_SB3">Scowcroft</persName> West Wing Office Files, Box 33, <gloss
                        target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>, Gromyko File (33), 9/29/76)</p>
                <p>On December 15, the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> representative to the
                        <gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> talks, <persName corresp="#p_RSR1"
                        >Stanley Resor</persName>, tabled Western data in Vienna and, on December
                    16, he made a statement on behalf of the Western participants at the plenary
                    session of the talks: “The Western figures are as follows: (a) The total number
                    of uniformed active duty military ground force personnel of Western direct
                    participants in the area of reductions was 731,000 as of January 1, 1976. This
                    represents an increase of approximately 14,000 in the total figure for these
                    participants owing to more precise compilation since the negotiations began. (b)
                    The combined total number of uniformed active duty military ground and air force
                    personnel of the Western direct participants in the area of reductions was
                    921,000 men as of January 1, 1976. I would now like to make clear the basis on
                    which these figures have been computed. All active duty military personnel in
                    the ground and air forces of the Western direct participants in the area of
                    reductions have been counted. Only active duty military personnel are included.
                    Naval personnel, as well as reservists, civilians, and the personnel of other
                    uniformed organizations equipped with weapons are excluded from these
                    figures.</p>
                <list>
                    <item>“As regards Warsaw Pact forces, Eastern participants will recollect that,
                        in November 1973, the West tabled its figure of 925,000 men for <pb
                            facs="1128" n="1093" xml:id="pg_1093"/> Warsaw Pact ground forces. The
                        West now confirms that, on the basis of revised computations, the Western
                        estimate of Warsaw Pact ground force manpower in the area shows an increase.
                        This increase is somewhat larger than the 14,000 man increase in Western
                        manpower of which I have just referred. The current Western estimate to the
                        disparity between Western and Eastern ground force manpower is more than
                        150,000 men in favor of the East. The West has also told the East that the
                        total of Warsaw Pact air force manpower was somewhat larger than the total
                        of Western air manpower.</item>
                    <item>“As noted, on June 10, the Soviet Representative presented a different set
                        of figures on Eastern military personnel in the area, based on counting
                        rules whose details the East has not yet elaborated. The fact that there is
                        a large discrepancy between the totals which the East has tabled and Western
                        estimates of Warsaw Pact military manpower in the area leads the West to
                        believe that the two sets of figures now on the table—the figures presented
                        by the East and those presented by the West—were not formulated according to
                        the same counting rules. Western participants believe that there is some
                        rational explanation for this discrepancy and that it is in the interest of
                        both sides to enter on a cooperative effort to identify the sources of this
                        discrepancy. I have just made clear the counting rules the West used in
                        compiling its data. Western participants now need to be fully clear about
                        what counting rules the East has used for compiling Eastern data.”
                        (Department of State, Office of the Historian, <hi rend="italic">Mutual and
                            Balanced Force Reduction (<gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>)</hi>
                        Talks, 1973–1989, Research Project No. 1553, May 1989, pages 40–43)</item>
                </list>
                <p>After <persName corresp="#p_RSR1">Resor</persName> tabled the data, Khlestov
                    raised the issue of the exclusion of French forces in Germany from the Western
                    manpower figures. He told <persName corresp="#p_RSR1">Resor</persName> that
                    “Eastern representatives were not prepared to discuss data and counting rules
                    until after they had had an opportunity to analyze this data. But at first
                    sight, this data on Western forces did not conform to Eastern estimates of these
                    forces. Soviet <gloss target="#t_rep1">rep</gloss> said that when the West had
                    previously tabled its figures on ground force manpower, it had not limited these
                    figures only to the forces of the Western direct participants. He asked why
                        <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_rep1">rep</gloss> had emphasized that Western data was for the
                    forces of Western direct participants only. <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>
                    <gloss target="#t_rep1">rep</gloss> confirmed that data consisted only of the
                    forces in the reduction area of the Western direct participants in the Vienna
                    negotiations.” (Telegram 621 from the delegation to <gloss target="#t_MBFR1"
                        >MBFR</gloss>, December 15; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG1"
                        >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy Files) The discussion of data on
                    manpower, including how to organize it, continued at the <gloss
                        target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss> talks well into the summer of 1977.
                    (Department of State, Office of the Historian, <hi rend="italic">Mutual and
                        Balanced Force Reduction (<gloss target="#t_MBFR1">MBFR</gloss>)</hi> Talks,
                    1973–1989, Research Project No. 1553, May 1989, pages 10, 44–48)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
