<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>1. Memorandum for the Record</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-01-19T09:45:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-01-19T09:45:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recD05lTT61lKX9at" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132819"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Fiscal</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recT9SDfSZeFRiMti" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85055692"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Gold</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-01-19T09:45:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-01-19T09:45:00-05:00" n="1"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1">
                <head>1. Memorandum for the Record<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d1fn0">Source:
                        Eisenhower Library, Post-Presidential Papers, 1961-1969, <persName
                            corresp="#p_KJF2">John F. Kennedy</persName> 1960-1961 (2). No
                        classification marking. Drafted by Wilton B. Persons, Assistant to President
                            <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>. The meeting was held
                        in the Cabinet Room of the White House. A shorter memorandum of this meeting
                        is in a memorandum from Clark M. Clifford to President <persName
                            corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName>, January 24. (Department of State,
                        Rusk Files: Lot 72 D 192, White House Correspondence, 1/61-11/63)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-01-19T09:45:00-05:00">January 19, 1961, 9:45 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>[Here follows discussion of seven unrelated issues.]</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">8. Coordination and Development of Basic Economic, Fiscal and
                        Monetary Policies</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> indicated that he and his
                    people had been thoroughly briefed and asked if Secretary Anderson had anything
                    further to give them. Secretary Anderson made a strong recommendation that
                    public statements on matters as delicate as the balance of payments situation
                    should be confined to the President and his Secretary of the Treas-ury only.
                    This would mean that the government would be speaking with one voice and this
                    would be very helpful to an understanding by foreign governments of the United
                    States position. Secretary Anderson further recommended that communications with
                    the Federal Reserve System be kept in the family and particularly in cases where
                    there were differences of opinions.</p>
                <p>The President referred to the morale effect of separating military families
                    brought about by the recent order made in an effort to alleviate the balance of
                    payments situation.<note n="1" xml:id="d1fn1">Reference is to the directive
                        issued by President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> on
                        November 16, 1960. For documentation on the preparation and issuance of this
                        directive, see <ref target="frus1958-60v04#pg_135">
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1958–1960, vol. IV, pp.
                            135</ref>–<ref target="frus1958-60v04#pg_140">140</ref>
                    </note> He pointed out that this was done as a quick move to do something
                    concrete to stop the flow of gold and to show our Allies that we meant business.
                    He expressed the hope that further study of this complicated matter would
                    indicate that other and less drastic means could be used for accomplishing this
                    purpose. He stated, however, that the situation could deteriorate to the point
                    where even more radical measures might become necessary but expressed the hope
                    that the Defense Department would minimize as much as possible the <pb
                        facs="0028" n="2" xml:id="pg_2"/> effects on dependents of military men. For
                    example, he discussed the possibility of returning a full division to the United
                    States, pointing out that this would require careful preparation before it was
                    done. He also stated that American troops had been sent to Europe originally as
                    an emergency move to give Europe a chance to recover from the devastation of war
                    and that from the point of view of the United States we would be much stronger
                    militarily if we brought some of these troops home and had them located as a
                    central reserve.</p>
                <p>The President indicated that, in his opinion, the State Department should bring
                    back some dependents but thus far State has been recalcitrant. He pointed out
                    that the soldier does not want to be made the goat in this matter and he felt
                    this reaction was justified. The President also stated that there are several
                    agencies of the government which could pick up some of the burden.</p>
                <p>Secretary Anderson pointed out that gold erosion is still going on at a rate
                    which we cannot afford—reporting $225 million from January 1, 1961, to January
                    19, 1961.</p>
                <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_KJF2">Kennedy</persName> asked if there is any
                    change in the gold balance among our Allies, and Secretary Anderson pointed out
                    that all of our Allies have dollar surpluses—except Japan which has recently
                    changed its reserve ratio. Secretary Anderson emphasized that the key to the
                    gold problem is confidence on the part of other nations in the stability of the
                    dollar and our willingness and ability to handle our fiscal affairs wisely. At
                    this point, the President pointed out that he had had a study made as to the
                    effect of <gloss target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss>’s programs on the outflow of gold
                    and found this to be minimal.<note n="2" xml:id="d1fn2">The <gloss
                            target="#t_ICA1">ICA</gloss> study has not been found.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Secretary Anderson indicated that the British had been very helpful in the gold
                    situation and had worked with us very closely. He also pointed out that the
                    Treasury Department keeps a “watch officer” on duty 24 hours a day on this
                    particular matter.</p>
                <p>[Here follows a brief discussion of the Presidential transition process.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
