<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>181. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">181</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receerh07ZS3xzI6L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Export</term>
                    <term ref="rec9GcohNRY3T8qu9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recy5FvpH0k4sOWVY" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002007885"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Finance</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy" subject="financial-and-monetary-affairs" lcsh-match="no_match">Financial questions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-03-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-03-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="181"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d181">
                <head>181. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d181fn0"
                        >Source: Department of State, Central Files, 398.14/3-2061. Official Use
                        Only. Drafted by <persName>Martin</persName> on March 21.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1961-03-20">March 20,
                            1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Preparations for <gloss target="#t_EPC1">EPC</gloss> Meeting and <gloss
                            target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> Council Discussions</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRV1">Robert V. Roosa</persName>, Under
                        Secretary of Treasury for Monetary Affairs</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWW1">Walter Heller</persName>, Chairman,
                        Committee of Economic Advisers</item>
                    <item>Mr. Arthur W. Marget, Board of Governors, Federal Reserve</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_BJN1">Jack N. Behrman</persName>, Deputy
                        Assistant Secretary of Commerce</item>
                    <item>Mr. R. Henry Rowntree, Chief, Economics Division, Export-Import
                        Bank</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">John Leddy</persName>, Assistant Secretary
                        for International Affairs, Treasury</item>
                    <item>Mr. George Willis, Director, Office of International Finance,
                        Treasury</item>
                    <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_MEW2">Edwin M. Martin</persName>, Assistant
                        Secretary, State</item>
                </list>
                <p>(I received a message late Friday, March 17, from Mr. Willis of Treas-ury that
                    Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRV1">Roosa</persName> would have a meeting on Monday
                    to consider new international financial arrangements. On Monday morning I
                    received a message from Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">Leddy</persName> that
                    the meeting had been called because of concern by Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> that a working group set up by <gloss
                        target="#t_CEA1">CEA</gloss> under Mr. Triffin to prepare for <gloss
                        target="#t_EPC1">EPC</gloss> meeting might get involved in international
                    financial planning of the sort which was properly the responsibility of the
                        <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss>.)</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRV1">Roosa</persName> opened the meeting by saying
                    that he and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> were
                    concerned with two points. The first was that in any international discussions,
                    formal or informal, it was imperative that the US representatives speak with a
                    single voice derived from coordinated positions. If there were to be any actual
                    negotiations, they would presumably be handled by representatives of State and
                    Treasury.</p>
                <p>The second point was that, insofar as the United States took a substantive
                    position on international financial questions in the course of the <gloss
                        target="#t_EPC1">EPC</gloss> meeting, it was important that these
                    substantive positions be coordinated through the <gloss target="#t_NAC1"
                        >NAC</gloss>, which was the established mechanism for this purpose. I
                    inquired if it weren’t possible that some of the issues involved were similar to
                    those on which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SFAJ1">Southard</persName> was seeking
                    guidance for use in <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> discussions of expansion
                    of its resources. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRV1">Roosa</persName> agreed that
                    this was the case. It was, therefore, important not only to have instructions
                    for <gloss target="#t_EPC1">EPC</gloss> meeting but also for Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SFAJ1">Southard</persName> on this particular subject.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HWW1">Heller</persName> indicated that the Triffin
                    group, to which Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRV1">Roosa</persName> had made
                    reference, would be meeting, starting Tuesday morning, March 22, <pb facs="0428"
                        n="402" xml:id="pg_402"/> to deal with the question of the coordination of
                    internal financial policies of member governments. Its mandate was confined to
                    this subject.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that there were two other subjects on which policy guidance was
                    needed. One was the international financial mechanisms which were needed to deal
                    with problems with particular reference to the role of the <gloss
                        target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> and to the possibility of the US becoming a
                    member of the <gloss target="#t_EMA1">EMA</gloss>. This was clearly a <gloss
                        target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> problem. It was left that Mr. <persName
                        corresp="#p_SFAJ1">Southard</persName> would be asked to prepare a paper on
                        <gloss target="#t_IMF1">IMF</gloss> aspects and State and Treas-ury on
                        <gloss target="#t_EMA1">EMA</gloss> aspects.</p>
                <p>It was also felt that there would need to be a consideration of how better
                    exchanges of views could be organized, particularly among a more limited group
                    of countries than <gloss target="#t_EPC1">EPC</gloss> within <gloss
                        target="#t_OECD1">OECD</gloss> framework. It was felt that this paper should
                    be drawn on the assumption that the US would not be able to join the <gloss
                        target="#t_EMA1">EMA</gloss> as it now exists. It was agreed that State and
                    Treasury would collaborate on this paper. I proposed that the first step might
                    be to send some ideas to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_TJW2">Tuthill</persName> for
                    comment. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">Leddy</persName> agreed and asked that
                    Mr. Abrams or Mr. Renner<note n="1" xml:id="d181fn1">Manuel Abrams, Officer in
                        Charge, Economic Organization Affairs, and John C. Renner, both in <gloss
                            target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_RA1">RA</gloss>.</note>
                    get in touch with him with respect to such a telegram as well as preparation of
                    the paper.</p>
                <p>It was generally felt that the first problem would be the most likely subject for
                    discussion in <gloss target="#t_EPC1">EPC</gloss> and the other two might be
                    more useful for informal conversation outside the meetings. It was agreed,
                    however, that no formal decision could be taken on this point until the papers
                    had all been seen.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that the three papers have relationships with each other and that
                    it will be necessary to examine them together to ensure that they are properly
                    related.</p>
                <p>It was agreed that this informal group, representing the <gloss target="#t_NAC1"
                        >NAC</gloss> agencies at a higher level than the staff committee, but not an
                        <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> body, would deal with paper #2 and with
                    the coordination problem. It was agreed on my suggestion that we should wait
                    until after the coordination had been achieved before deciding which parts of
                    the package needed <gloss target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> approval.</p>
                <p>It was felt that the three papers should be ready for examination within two
                    weeks.</p>
                <p>Neither Exim nor Commerce representatives played any part in the discussion. The
                    Federal Reserve representative spoke strongly in favor of an active <gloss
                        target="#t_NAC1">NAC</gloss> role in the whole matter. The conversations
                    were entirely friendly, though Mr. <persName corresp="#p_RRV1">Roosa</persName>
                    was firm on the need for clear US positions, even for exploratory
                    conversations.</p>
                <pb facs="0429" n="403" xml:id="pg_403"/>
                <p>(Immediately after the meeting I informed Mr. Renner of what had transpired and
                    asked him to get in touch with Mr. <persName corresp="#p_LJM2">Leddy</persName>.
                    I also confirmed that he was attending the meeting of the Triffin group and
                    suggested in view of the subject matter, he might want to take someone from
                        <gloss target="#t_E1">E</gloss>. He indicated he had already been in touch
                    with Mr. Goldstein.)<note n="2" xml:id="d181fn2">Mortimer D. Goldstein,
                        Assistant Chief (E/<gloss target="#t_FN1">FN</gloss>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
