<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1963-08-28T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1963-08-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="30" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d30">
                        <head>30. Letter From <persName corresp="#p_GJK1" type="from">John Kenneth
                                Galbraith</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2" type="to">Kennedy</persName><note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d30fn0">Source: Kennedy Library, National Security Files,
                                Subjects Series, Balance of Payments and Gold. Personal; Secret.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GJK1">Galbraith</persName>, who had been
                                succeeded by <persName corresp="#p_BCB1">Chester Bowles</persName>
                                as Ambassador to India in July 1963, was serving as a consultant to
                                the White House.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1963-08-28">August 28,
                                    1963</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dear Mr. President</hi>: This is the first of two
                            papers that I am sending you on the balance of payments problem.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>The companion paper is concerned with problems and remedies.<note n="1" xml:id="d30fn1">Reference presumably is to <ref target="#d31">Documents 31</ref> and <ref target="#d32">32</ref>.</note> This deals with the more serious question,
                                as I measure matters, of how to handle the problem. There is at
                                present no mechanism for enforcing the continuing action on the wide
                                front that the problem requires. Since I must speak frankly about
                                persons and departments, I plead that this particular memorandum be
                                held in strict confidence.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>The heart of the matter is that for everyone concerned with the
                                balance of payments problem it is subordinate to another concern.
                                For the Council of Economic Advisers, it is subordinate to the
                                domestic economy. Tobin, although his views were not typical, was
                                perilously close to the conclusion that there is no problem at all.
                                Other members, in fighting off measures which were considered, in my
                                view quite correctly, to have a bad domestic impact, failed to
                                develop a solidly affirmative position. All economists unduly
                                emphasize international liquidity, which is a fashionable
                                conversation piece of the economists’ union. The State Department,
                                though it suffers from the effect of a weak balance of payments
                                position on its bargaining position, is primarily concerned with
                                protecting trade, troops and aid. The Commerce Department views the
                                trade balance largely as an opportunity to get more money for trade
                                promotion and foreign tourist travel. These are negligible in their
                                possibilities. The Treasury has responsibility for the problem as a
                                whole, but until recently its sacred cow has been the capital
                                market. Even now, the checking of long-term capital outflows, and
                                the stopping of avenues of escape around the proposed tax, is being
                                handled in a highly unwilling way.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The picture is not entirely black. Bob McNamara has made a loyal and
                            substantial effort to ease the problem. On the dollar-saving side, his
                            is the only area of substantial achievement.</p>
                        <p>Now as to remedies. Something over a year ago I urged you to set up a
                            Cabinet Committee to have jurisdiction over this problem and to be
                            responsible for its solution.<note n="2" xml:id="d30fn2">Not further
                                identified.</note> This hasn’t worked. It has been a place where
                            those responsible have sought to shift the buck. There is no further
                            hope for action here.</p>
                        <pb facs="0102" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/>
                        <p>I gather you have been sufficiently pressed as regards the Treasury and
                                <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName>. The Treasury hasn’t
                            done well. It waited too long on long-term capital movements. It is
                            subject to the banker syndrome, which is to foresee disaster but prefer
                            inaction. However, the Treasury cannot exercise real jurisdiction over
                            the other Government Departments. The latter will always find it easier
                            to organize against <persName corresp="#p_DCD1">Dillon</persName> than
                            to follow his lead. An appeal to you is inherent in the situation, so
                            the problem comes to your office in any case.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, I see no alternative to better organization of the Executive
                            Office for continuing pressure and action. This means, I believe, that
                            you must have someone of stature, fully seized of the seriousness of the
                            problem, who will do in this critical matter what Bundy does for you on
                            foreign policy and Sorensen on domestic policy. (You might reflect that
                            nothing in the areas they so competently now cover is as important as
                            the balance of payments, yet neither can function with real confidence
                            on this issue.) Such a solution will cause sadness in the Treasury and
                            the Council of Economic Advisers. But every President since Roosevelt
                            has had to have an economist or economic figure who was his man to help
                            him in combatting the excessive parochialism of departmental policy.
                            (Currie served Roosevelt in this way, <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">David
                                Bell</persName> so served Truman, and Randall and Gabriel Hauge so
                            served <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName>.) The man is
                            all-important. <persName corresp="#p_KC2">Carl Kaysen</persName>, who is
                            perhaps the ablest all-around economist in the country, is unfortunately
                            susceptible to the economists’ union. As a result, he is overly
                            impressed by the international liquidity escapism. In any case, you need
                            someone full time. I suggest that, whatever the implications, you attach
                                <persName>Charles Hitch</persName> to the White House Office for
                            nine months for this job. He is highly intelligent, has a pragmatic view
                            of the issue, takes it seriously, and you can rely completely on his
                            judgment. He would act largely through you, but he would command respect
                            as your adviser. This need not be a permanent assignment. He need stay
                            only until the present bleeding is decisively reversed.</p>
                        <p>As I argue in the accompanying memorandum, the present trend can be
                            reversed. It is this, as well as the urgency of doing so, that leads me
                            to urge that the powers of the President be decisively engaged.</p>
                        <p>Yours faithfully,</p>
                        <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_GJK1"><hi rend="strong">John Kenneth
                                        Galbraith</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d30fn3">Printed
                                    from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>