<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>95. Memorandum From Secretary of State Rusk to President to President
                    Kennedy</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v09</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1961-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1961-03-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="rec1K4XtTHBIl41Sv" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="rec8PCbWGrkAaOOXZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001000124"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developed countries</term>
                    <term ref="recoKawZ2IOcE8nyB" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recAOW4GlCG25M6cu" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040989"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Education</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1961-03-10T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1961-03-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="95"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d95">
                <head>95. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RD3" type="from"
                        >Rusk</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2" type="to"
                        >Kennedy</persName>
                    <note n="0" type="source" xml:id="d95fn0">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 700.5-<gloss target="#t_MSP1">MSP</gloss>/3-1061. No classification
                        marking. A March 6 draft, attached to the source text, is identical to the
                        text printed here, except for the first paragraph that makes no mention of
                        the upcoming Monday meeting. In the margins of the March 6 draft are the
                        following handwritten comments: “Hand carried to Pres. by Sec 3/6/61” and
                        “Revised &amp; sent 3/10 to W[hite] H[ouse]”.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1961-03-10">March 10, 1961</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>New Proposals for the Foreign Aid Program</item>
                </list>
                <p>In anticipation of our Monday meeting to discuss the report on Reorganization of
                    Foreign Assistance, and its accompanying proposals,<note n="1" xml:id="d95fn1"
                        >Neither the report nor its accompanying proposals nor a record of the
                        meeting on Monday, March 13, has been found. A March 8 memorandum from
                        Battle to <gloss target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss>-<gloss target="#t_RO1"
                            >RO</gloss> indicates that this White House meeting with the President
                        would concern foreign aid. (Ibid., 800.0000/3-861) Participants at the
                        10:05-10:50 a.m. meeting on March 13 were the President, Secretary <persName
                            corresp="#p_RD3">Rusk</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BCB1"
                            >Bowles</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_BDE1">David Bell</persName>, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BMG2">McGeorge Bundy</persName>, Sorensen, and <persName
                            corresp="#p_RWW1">Rostow</persName>. (<persName corresp="#p_KJF2"
                            >Kennedy</persName> Library, President’s Appointment Books)</note> I
                    want to take this opportunity to restate my own deep concern and strong
                    convictions on the historic situation in which we now find ourselves.</p>
                <pb facs="0236" n="210" xml:id="pg_210"/>
                <p>I feel certain that this concern and these convictions are widely shared by all
                    those who have worked to produce these new proposals. The scale, shape, and
                    direction of the new proposals are themselves based on an awareness of the
                    increasing seriousness of the world situation. But we are also aware that both
                    public opinion and political sentiment on Capitol Hill require the highest level
                    Presidential leadership if our proposals are to attract the necessary
                    support.</p>
                <p>Unquestionably, the need for the intelligent use of foreign assistance continues
                    and is likely to increase. In three underdeveloped continents we have reached a
                    watershed where the holding operations of the past are clearly inadequate and
                    where new initiative of a dramatic and positive kind are essential. Even if the
                    Soviet threat did not exist, these requirements would be present and should
                    impel us and other economically developed countries to adopt new policies. But
                    the Soviet threat itself is taking on new forms, specifically including the
                    availability of massive sums for trade and aid to be expended as Soviet
                    political aims dictate.</p>
                <p>Here at home the political and public climate for the aid program has been
                    allowed to deteriorate just at the time when a more sophisticate understanding
                    and a stronger long-term commitment is needed.</p>
                <p>Part of this is the result of years of fraudulent justifications of the program
                    as a short-term, anti-communist, quick-results proposition. Part of it is the
                    understandable effect of boredom with the old symbols, maladministration and
                    waste, neo-isolationism, and the protectionism produced by the economic distress
                    inside our own economy.</p>
                <p>I believe that most of us who have worked on this program feel that we have come
                    to an important crossroads. In all likelihood, a fresh, positive aid program,
                    scaled to the requirements, and presented with persist-ence and boldness, has a
                    much better chance of Congressional approval and popular acclaim than another
                    round of the old Mutual Security bill with the now standard figures on military
                    assistance, “defense support”, “special assistance”, and all the rest.</p>
                <p>We are facing a period much like 1940, when Lend Lease would never have been
                    thought politically possible by ordinary politicians, but when farsighted
                    leadership and Presidential initiative achieved a breakthrough. This is also a
                    time like 1947, when neither the Congress nor the country was supposed to be
                    ready for the Marshall Plan, but when a similar energy and influence provided
                    the national momentum we needed.</p>
                <p>The accompanying proposals have been drafted under the assumption that the top
                    leadership in the new Administration throughout the White House, Cabinet, and
                    sub-Cabinet levels, can and will be mobilized to undertake the important
                    assignments in public education which will be an essential prerequisite to the
                    program’s enactment. In practical terms, this will require a major public effort
                    in the months of April and <pb facs="0237" n="211" xml:id="pg_211"/> May between
                    the presentation of your aid message and the presentation of the detailed
                    program on Capitol Hill.</p>
                <p>These considerations are uppermost in my mind at the moment, and I am sure that
                    my colleagues share them. I think it is essential that they be appreciated and
                    understood at the outset, for without them the program itself will be in trouble
                    and indeed would not have been devised.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RD3">
                            <hi rend="strong">Dean Rusk</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
