<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Tower to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1900</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d1006</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">1006</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1900-06-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1900-06-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recf86eb164d9633fe" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general">Arbitration</term>
                    <term ref="recbJ9XzDvelnf09P" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="protocol"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000299"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Protocol</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-06-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-06-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="1006"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d1006">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Tower</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Embassy of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">St. Petersburg</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-06-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 26, 1900</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 256.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Upon the receipt on the 20th of June of your
                    telegram, I called upon the Count Mouravieff, imperial minister for foreign
                    affairs, with whom I had already reached the understanding that all evidence
                    heretofore submitted by the Government of the United States to the Russian
                    Government in connection with the seizure by Russian armed ships of American
                    vessels should be presented in full at the arbitration. I informed M. de
                    Mouravieff of the instructions I had just received, which obliged me to ask for
                    a specific provision in the protocol as to the admission of this testimony. He
                    expressed some surprise and reminded me that he had discussed that question with
                    me in detail, and that he had repeatedly declared that the admission of all the
                    testimony on both sides was provided for by the clause in the protocol, which
                    reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>The arbitrator shall take cognizance of the claims for indemnity which
                            have been presented to the Imperial Government of Russia by the
                            Government of the United States on behalf of the parties in
                            interest.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>But as I answered that my later instructions were direct and that I must
                    therefore request of him an express statement as to the intention and
                    understanding of the Imperial Government in this matter, he agreed to an
                    interchange of notes with me which should completely remove any doubt as to the
                    point raised by the United States, declaring at the same time that Russia is
                    quite as anxious to submit her whole case to the arbitrator as we are, and he
                    appointed the hour of 12 o’clock upon the following day, Thursday, the 21st of
                    June, for the signing by himself and me of the protocol.</p>
                <p>His sudden death, however, on the morning of the 21st instant has temporarily
                    checked further proceedings, though the subject is one with which the Count
                    Lamsdorff, the present gerant of the ministry for foreign affairs, is entirely
                    familiar, and I have no doubt the few remaining details will be readily carried
                    out by him.</p>
                <p>I received your telegram of the 23d of June authorizing me to use my discretion
                    in regard to making French the language of the arbitration. But as I expect to
                    have the honor of seeing you in Washington within a short time, I will leave
                    that question open, with your permission, until I may be able to discuss it with
                    you personally.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Charlemagne Tower.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
