<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Goodnow to Mr. Cridler.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1900</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d271</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">271</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1900-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1900-08-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-08-02T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-08-02T00:00:00-05:00" n="271"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d271">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Goodnow</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Cridler</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Consulate-General of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Shanghai</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-08-02">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 2, 1900</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 285.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to confirm my dispatch of July 31: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>Shanghai taotai says Tsungli Yamen instructed him to tell me my cipher
                            message 22d July will not be delivered Conger. If I will send message in
                            English Tsungli Yamen will decide regarding delivery that message after
                            seeing it.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>On the 22d of July I gave the Taotai a cipher message to Mr. Conger telling the
                    anxiety with which all were waiting authentic news. I asked him to answer me
                    fully, giving date in cipher and such details of persons in our legation that
                    there would be no question as to the authenticity of the message. On the morning
                    of the 31st of July the Taotai’s private secretary came to me and delivered
                    verbally the message as I wired to you, and asked me then to give him an English
                    message at that time. I told him that 1 did not care to do business in that
                    informal fashion and would prefer that the Taotai write me so important a matter
                    as a message from the tsungli Yamen. The secretary left promising to bring me
                    this in writing. About 2 o’clock <pb facs="0360" n="262" xml:id="pg_262"/>
                    another secretary appeared, asking me as from the Taotai not to forward to you
                    anything of the message given to me that morning. “As they were afraid you would
                    be very angry and as His Excellency Sheng had wired the Tsungli Yamen asking
                    them to deliver the message.” I answered that of course I must send you the
                    message as I received it. Li Hung-chang also told me the same afternoon that he
                    had wired the Tsungli Yamen urging them to deliver my message, and he also hoped
                    that I would not feel bounden to transmit the message to you.</p>
                <p>Several messages have been taken by Sheng, by Li, and by the Taotai from consuls
                    here for their ministers. To all the others the reply has been given that no
                    word has been received from Pekin with reference to their message, and it was
                    apparently through indiscretion that the Taotai told me this.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to be, sir, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John Goodnow</hi>,<lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Consul-General, Shanghai.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
