<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-10-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-10-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="336" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d336">
                        <head>[Untitled]</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-10-18"><hi rend="italic">October 18,
                                1900</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p rend="center">[Communicated to Minister Wu for transmission, October 18,
                            1900.]</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">His Majesty Kwang Hsu, Emperor of
                                China, greeting:</hi></p>
                        <p>It has afforded me much pleasure to receive your imperial majesty’s
                            telegraphic letter of October 14, which has been delivered by your
                            majesty’s minister in Washington.</p>
                        <p>I cordially share your majesty’s wish that there may be a peaceful
                            settlement of all questions between China and the powers whose interests
                            and nationals have so grievously suffered wrong in your majesty’s
                            dominions, and that the outcome may be the complete effacement of ill
                            feeling between them. The desire of this Government that such a
                            settlement may be brought about speedily has been made known to all the
                            powers, and I trust that negotiations may begin so soon as we and the
                            other offended governments shall be effectively satisfied of your
                            majesty’s ability and power to treat with just sternness the principal
                            offenders, who are doubly culpable, not alone toward the foreigners, <pb facs="0394" n="296" xml:id="pg_296"/> but toward your majesty, under
                            whose rule the purpose of China to dwell in concord with the world has
                            hitherto found expression in the welcome and protection assured to
                            strangers.</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">William McKinley</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>