<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Hay to Mr. Townsend.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1900</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d35</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">35</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1900-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1900-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85034079"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Criminal</term>
                    <term ref="recZm50eBUL0UJnQP" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038411"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diseases</term>
                    <term ref="recf388f47d4e50787" type="topic" category="department-of-state" subcategory="buildings-foreign" subject="embassy">Embassy</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-04-24T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-04-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="35"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d35">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hay</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Townsend</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-04-24">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 24, 1900</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 41.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The Department will be pleased to have you report
                    to it in full the facts in the matter of the inclosed complaint of Paul Edwards
                    that he was arbitrarily and summarily expelled from Belgium.</p>
                <p>You will notice that Mr. Edwards states that he reported the fact of his
                    expulsion “to the American embassy of Brussels, but received no assistance in
                    any form.”</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay</hi>.</signed>
                </closer>
                <pb facs="0142" n="46" xml:id="pg_46"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Edwards</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">London, England</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-03-28">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 28, 1900</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>I, Paul Edwards, an American citizen, beg to lay before your Department the
                        following facts:</p>
                    <p>That on or about the 20th day of March, 1900, I was in the city of Brussels,
                        Belgium, for the purpose of placing my 15-year-old son into a college of
                        that city. That I did so place my son in a college there, and about that
                        time the united press of that city published laudable notices of my arrival
                        in that city; that the press had on former occasions published much about my
                        life and work as a healer in other countries; that this great notoriety
                        given me by the press caused several persons to call at my hotel and seek my
                        presence and aid; that I did aid them as a healer to the best of my ability,
                        but asking no fee or pay for the same.</p>
                    <p>I was in possession of a passport issued by the Hon. Joseph Choate, of
                        London, during the present month (March, 1900); that soon after my arrival
                        in Brussels I submitted the said passport to the proper authorities, which
                        was duly noted on their books, and was told that there were no other
                        formalities to observe under the Belgian law. Next day I was waited on three
                        times by the police and given various annoyances by different Government
                        officials, all of whom seemed to be hostile and offensive toward me.</p>
                    <p>I was then sent for by the commissary of police, who told me he was
                        instructed by the minister of justice to make a special report on my
                        presence in Belgium. I again offered all the information possible concerning
                        myself and my business in Brussels.</p>
                    <p>The next day I received a note at my hotel from the minister of justice
                        commanding me to appear before him at 2 o’clock that day. I then took an
                        interpreter and proceeded to the office of the said minister, and to my
                        surprise found that he had already made out the papers for my expulsion from
                        Belgium within twenty-four hours. The minister then and there accused me of
                        having been in Belgium in the year 1869, and accused me of having two
                        aliases, and gave me the two names he charged me then (in 1869) bearing.</p>
                    <p>I saw that the minister was so convinced that I was some one else (or at
                        least he pretended to so believe) that I asked him to listen to facts and
                        told him that the present was my first visit to his country (which was
                        true), but he was beyond all possibility of reason and began to show anger,
                        ordering me to sign papers I knew nothing of, or their contents. I exhibited
                        my passport to quiet the passion of the minister, but he at first refused to
                        see it and later, on pretense of wishing it for another purpose, he asked
                        for it and seized it as an act of spite. I begged him to return me my
                        passport as I wished to go immediately to the United States embassy, but he
                        positively declined to return it, saying he did not care what steps I might
                        take, and that he had a right to withhold the document even though it were
                        issued by an American ambassador. During this time the minister for justice
                        was steadily becoming impassioned and was extremely rude, at times shouting
                        nothing but the word “Go!” “Go!” “Go!”</p>
                    <p>He loudly commanded me to <hi rend="italic">instantly</hi> name the route I
                        should take out of Belgium, and when I told him that was impossible he
                        actually threatened to arrest me in his office. I then for the first time
                        defied him to arrest me or name an offense against me. I demanded to know if
                        I were considered a criminal or if I had broken any law of Belgium. I told
                        him that if I were a law-breaker my place was before the courts and not
                        before him.</p>
                    <p>The minister said I was <hi rend="italic">not</hi> a <hi rend="italic"
                            >criminal</hi>, but that he <hi rend="italic">would</hi> not or <hi
                            rend="italic">need</hi> not give me any reason for my expulsion from
                        Belgium. The said <hi rend="italic">minister</hi> then loudly and harshly
                        forbade that any person should see me at my <hi rend="italic">private rooms
                            in the hotel</hi> and commanded that I should even send away all who may
                        call. In his anger he even told my interpreter to consider herself expelled,
                        but later on, seeing his mistake, recalled the expulsion of that person, who
                        is in fact a <hi rend="italic">British subject</hi>.</p>
                    <p>On arriving at a great state of excitement the minister suddenly arose as if
                        to assault me, and loudly commanded me to leave his office <hi rend="italic"
                            >at once</hi>. “Now you get out” were his exact words. And this ended
                        the scene in the office of the minister for justice of Belgium. On my
                        leaving his presence the minister thrust my passport over the desk to me and
                        I took it.</p>
                    <p>The minister spoke in English, and there was but one other person present
                        beside my interpreter and myself. This other or fourth person was a servant
                        or errand man, and declared that he could neither speak or understand
                        English. This fourth person was the man who brought the minister’s summons
                        to me the day before and required an interpreter to make his business known
                        to me, as he could neither speak or understand English.</p>
                    <pb facs="0143" n="47" xml:id="pg_47"/>
                    <p>I went from there to my rooms and saw some friends, but within the next few
                        hours the minister caused no fewer than four policemen to wait upon me,
                        endeavoring to thoroughly overawe me by force.</p>
                    <p>I could not impress the minister with any reason, for he was not in a state
                        to reason. I know the importance and gravity of this statement. I will add,
                        however, that the person above referred to as the minister for justice was
                        according to his own statement the <hi rend="italic">first assistant
                            minister for justice</hi>, but declared that he was acting under orders
                        of the <hi rend="italic">minister in chief</hi> or minister of justice in
                        fact.</p>
                    <p>All of the above facts were witnessed by M. C. Gaine, who was there for the
                        purpose of interpreting if that were necessary.</p>
                    <p>I reported the bare fact of my expulsion to the American embassy at Brussels,
                        but received no assistance of any form.</p>
                    <p>As to my conduct while in Brussels I am pleased to refer to the following
                        persons who were wholly aware of all I did: Mr. George Phillpotts, 28 Rue du
                        Grand Hospice (English); Hon. Charles De Roos, judge of the tribunal of
                        commerce, Liege, Belgium; Mr. A. Ceuleneer, distiller, Brussels; Mr. Edouard
                        Deby, barrister and doctor of philosophy, Brussels; Mr. Gustave Lemaire,
                        editor-in-chief of Etoile Beige, Brussels; Mr. Gustave Basquin, chief
                        inspector of railways, Brussels; Madame Martha Chateau de Josaphat,
                        Brussels; Mr. Auguste Vierset, secrétaire de rédaction de Petit Bleu,
                        Brussels; the Hon. John D. Ruys, consul of the Dutch Government, Brussels;
                        Mr. Erskine Heucken, editor Messager de Brussels (who saw the ambassador of
                        the United States on my behalf); Baron Chazal, 12 Place Royale, Brussels;
                        Lieutenant Colonel retraite Paul Cuvelier and Madame Cuvelier, Brussels; Mr.
                        Frank Fouson, an editor on Messager de Brussels; Mr. Q. Herbos,
                        Brussels.</p>
                    <p>All of these people are of the most respectable standing, and, furthermore,
                        while in Brussels I treated many deputies, judges, and members of the
                        nobility, all of whom were most astonishingly benefited thereby. All the
                        persons above mentioned were treated by me by the process of mental healing,
                        using no medicine whatever, thereby not coming in conflict with the medical
                        laws of Belgium.</p>
                    <p>Since my arrival in London I see it stated in the public press that the
                        minister for justice expelled me at the instance of the medical profession
                        of Belgium, but this seems too narrow for serious consideration. I do not
                        here prejudice my right to lay a monetary claim against the Government of
                        Belgium at some time in the near future.</p>
                    <p>The various officials told me that they did not care for or respect a
                        passport issued by the United States, among whom were the minister of
                        justice and the chief of police at Brussels.</p>
                    <p>The honorable Secretary of State is hereby referred to the accompanying press
                            clippings<note n="1" xml:id="d35fn1">Not printed.</note> bearing further
                        upon this affair. I believe the entire press of Belgium supports me and
                        denounces the authorities.</p>
                    <p>I have traveled much in my profession, that of a healer of diseases, in which
                        work I use no medicines, and have never been considered amenable to any law,
                        medical or otherwise; nor did the Belgian authorities claim that I had
                        broken their laws. I have visited France, Mexico, England, Italy, the United
                        States, and other countries, and nowhere has my conduct or work been
                        offensive. I am 47 years of age, sober and law-abiding. I have received
                        almost unlimited attention from the public press all over the world, and can
                        not account for the action of the Belgian Governernment, except prejudice
                        against English and Americans, toward which persons the officials of Belgium
                        seem very rude at the present time.</p>
                    <p>I was told by the chief of police of Brussels that he was aware that his
                        Government was making a mistake in my case, yet the order of expulsion would
                        be carried out. I am certain I have the sympathy of the whole Belgian people
                        outside of the officials. No fewer than three barristers tendered me their
                        services gratis, and Mr. Edouard Deby actually presented a petition to His
                        Majesty the King for the annulment of the order of expulsion.</p>
                    <p>All of which is most respectfully submitted for the consideration of the
                        honorable the Secretary of State for the United States of America.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul Edwards</hi>,</signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">American Citizen.</hi>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
