<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-09-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-09-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="353" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d353">
                            <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hill</persName> to Mr.
                                        <persName type="to">Herdliska</persName>.</hi></head>
                            <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Circular telegram.]<note n="1" xml:id="d353fn1">Also to the United States representatives
                                        at Berlin, London, Paris, Rome, St. Petersburg, and
                                        Tokyo.</note></seg></opener>
                            <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-09-21"><hi rend="italic">September 21,
                                        1900</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                            <list>
                                <item>Part 1. On September 17 the Chinese minister presented copy of
                                    a circular telegram from Prince Ching, announcing appointment as
                                    plenipotentiary conjointly with Earl Li Hung Chang to negotiate
                                    peace, <pb facs="0404" n="306" xml:id="pg_306"/> and requesting
                                    the United States minister at Pekin be instructed to open
                                    negotiations. The following reply has been handed to-day to
                                    Chinese minister: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>The Government of the United States accepts the
                                            plenipotentiary authority of Earl Li Hung Chang and
                                            Prince Ching as prima facie sufficient for the
                                            preliminary negotiations looking toward the return of
                                            the Imperial Chinese Government and to the resumption of
                                            its authority at Pekin, and toward the negotiation of a
                                            complete settlement by the duly appointed
                                            plenipotentiaries of the powers and of China.</p>
                                        <p>To these ends the United States minister in Pekin will be
                                            authorized to enter into relations with Earl Li and
                                            Prince Ching as the immediate representative of the
                                            Chinese Emperor.</p>
                                    </quote></item>
                                <item>Part 2. On September 17 the Russian chargé delivered a
                                    memorandum, inquiring, first, whether the United States intends
                                    to transfer its legation from Pekin to Tientsin; secondly, if
                                    full powers of Prince Ching and Li Hung Chang are recognized by
                                    the United States as sufficient; and, thirdly, if the United
                                    States is prepared to charge its representatives to enter
                                    forthwith upon preliminary negotiations with the
                                    plenipotentiaries of the Chinese Emperor. The following
                                    memorandum in reply has been sent to the Russian chargé to-day: <list>
                                        <label>1.</label>
                                        <item>The Government of the United States has not any
                                            present intention to withdraw its legation from
                                            Pekin.</item>
                                        <label>2.</label>
                                        <item>The Government of the United States accepts the
                                            plenipotentiary authority of Earl Li Hung Chang and
                                            Prince Ching as prima facie sufficient for the
                                            preliminary negotiations looking toward the return of
                                            the Imperial Chinese Government and to the resumption of
                                            its authority at Pekin, and toward the negotiation of a
                                            complete settlement by the duly appointed
                                            plenipotentiaries of the powers and of China.</item>
                                        <label>3.</label>
                                        <item>To these ends, the United States minister in Pekin
                                            will be authorized to enter into relations with Earl Li
                                            and Prince Ching as the immediate representatives of the
                                            Chinese Emperor.</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>Part 3. On September 18 the German chargé communicated by note
                                    the Imperial Germin circular proposing that, as prerequisite to
                                    any negotiation, the Chinese Government deliver the real
                                    responsible authors of crimes against international law recently
                                    perpetrated in China. To this the following note has been handed
                                    German charge to-day:<note n="1" xml:id="d353fn2">Printed, <ref target="#pg_341">p. 341</ref>.</note></item>
                            </list>
                            <p>You will communicate all foregoing to minister for foreign affairs,
                                inviting information of the replies of his Government in the three
                                cases.</p>
                            <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Hill</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Acting.</hi></signed></closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>