<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Hay to Mr. Conger.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1900</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d516</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">516</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1900-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1900-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recAIUyroxylCct6R" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85104183"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Police</term>
                    <term ref="recSGyPwUYTaLPhEi" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="organization-and-management"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038182"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Consular service</term>
                    <term ref="rec6knwDvEj45PVa0" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006257"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Inspection</term>
                    <term ref="recyPPCmNUqutA6sc" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="buildings-foreign"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051395"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Consulate</term>
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                    <term ref="reccWlk0Umrr1N5Gp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2004007589"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investigation</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-01-08T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-01-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="516"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d516">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hay</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Conger</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-01-08">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 8, 1900</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 221.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I inclose herewith a copy of a dispatch from Mr.
                    Martin, the United States consul at Chinkiang, reporting the unlawful punishment
                    of Chinese employees of an American citizen in his consular district by a
                    Chinese chief of police named Yang Sze Chên, and stating that he has acquainted
                    you with the case.</p>
                <p>Mr. Martin’s appeal to the responsible authorities for the degradation and
                    adequate punishment of the chief of police, whose unjustifiable action has
                    brought discredit upon the good fame of Chinese authority, appears to be so
                    reasonable and just that it is not supposed that any representations made by you
                    to insure Fang’s chastisement, and to cause such order to be given through the
                    provincial viceroy as will cause the local authorities to recognize the receipt
                    of the consul to intervene whenever charges may be laid against the dependents
                    of an American merchant would be without proper effect. Indeed, it is thought
                    probable that any suggestion you may make in the case will have been anticipated
                    by the voluntary action of the Chinese Government in spontaneously reprobating
                    the offense and visiting due penalty on the offender.</p>
                <p>If this has not been done you will express your deep regret at being obliged to
                    reopen the matter by making a formal request for simple justice.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">John Hay.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Martin</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hill</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Consular Service</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Chinkiang</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-11-18">
                                <hi rend="italic">November 18, 1899</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 49.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have to report that on October 23, 1899,
                        Hon. E. H. Conger, United States minister to China, arrived at this port in
                        the gunboat <hi rend="italic">Monocacy</hi> on his tour of inspection. After
                        spending some time in examining the manner in which the records of this
                        consulate are kept and consular work done, I, at his request, started with
                        him to visit Nankin and Wuhu, both treaty ports in this consular district,
                        in which are many American missionaries.</p>
                    <p>Mr. R. Willis, Her British Majesty’s consul here, kindly took charge of
                        United States interests during my absence. While I was away from Chinkiang,
                        as above stated, a Chinese chief of police at this port (who, though
                        appointed here less than sixty days ago, had gained before I left a
                        reputation for being intensely antiforeign), went into the “hong,” or place
                        of business, of Mr. D. A. Emery, a United States citizen, and took therefrom
                        one of his shroffs and placed a cangue on his neck. When Mr. Emery was
                        informed he sent another of his shroffs (or clerk), a man about 25 years
                        old, with his Chinese card to request the release of the man arrested, and
                        to inform the chief of police if he wanted any of his employees to get them
                        through the United States consul. On hearing this message from a foreigner
                        the chief of police ordered the messenger to be beaten with bamboos. So
                        outrageous was the order, his underlings (known as runners) refused to do
                        so. He himself then stepped out from his desk, ordered him forced on his
                        knees and bent over, his trousers taken down, and across the back of his
                        legs about 12 inches above the knees he flogged him for some time, then
                        again ordered his runners to proceed, which they did until 1,300 blows were
                        thus given, causing the blood to run from both legs, and, as the blows were
                        continued within a radius of a few inches, it literally dug the flesh out,
                        leaving two holes. He then ordered a cangue put on his neck, and after
                        recovering from his faint forced him to march around the city, led by a
                        chain.</p>
                    <pb facs="0495" n="397" xml:id="pg_397"/>
                    <p>No charge was or is preferred against this shroff; his sole crime seems to
                        have been that he would dare come to his police station with a foreigner’s
                        message and card. His action caused so much excitement among, the Chinese in
                        the Chinese city that late in the evening a crowd estimated at about 2,000
                        gathered around the police station and threatened to pull it down. For a
                        time a serious riot seemed imminent, and the danger was avoided only by the
                        taotai of the city sending for the two men thus illegally detained and
                        ill-treated, and turning them over to the prefect.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Willis, acting in United States interests, on hearing what had occurred
                        sent Wan Bing Chung, our interpreter, to the taotai with his card to make
                        inquiries. He returned to Mr. Willis and reported that the taotai was
                        extremely vexed about the matter, and had already sent a telegram to the
                        provincial judge at Soochow, who appointed this chief of police to his
                        position.</p>
                    <p>This outrage caused almost an entire suspension of business in Chinkiang for
                        two days, and has alarmed the foreigners of all nationalities along the
                        river ports contiguous to Chinkiang.</p>
                    <p>On my return to the consulate I at once investigated the matter, finding it
                        as above stated. Inclosures Nos. 355, 356, and 357 are copies of the
                        dispatches sent by Mr. Willis to the taotai concerning the matter.</p>
                    <p>On Saturday, November 10, the next day after my return from Wuhu, I had it
                        made known verbally to the taotai he had better come to the consulate.
                        Monday, November 12, he appeared. On being questioned why he allowed this
                        man Yang Sze Chen, chief of police, to escape from the city after his
                        dismissal from office, he said this man was a man of rank, holding the
                        metropolitan degree, and therefore could not be confined. Moreover, from a
                        Chinese standpoint, he had committed no crime.</p>
                    <p>Question. Do you mean to say a Chinese official can take an inno’cent man
                        charged with no crime and flog him almost to death, and not be amenable to
                        punishment?</p>
                    <p>Answer. Only removal from office for being guilty of a miscarriage of
                        justice.</p>
                    <p>Question. Do you mean to tell me a man holding a literary degree can not be
                        confined or punished for crime?</p>
                    <p>Answer. Not until he is degraded by taking his degree from him.</p>
                    <p>Question. This, then, is your excuse for not fulfilling your promise to
                        Consul Willis to keep him here until this matter is settled?</p>
                    <p>Answer. Yes.</p>
                    <p>He then said, “Consul, I have no excuse for this man doing as he has done. I
                        will do all I can to help you in this matter; do not make it too hard for
                        me. I went beyond my authority in dismissing him from office before I
                        received permission, he having been appointed by the provincial judge.”</p>
                    <p>Question. But on receipt of your telegram the judge ordered you to dismiss
                        him, did he not?</p>
                    <p>Answer. Yes, and he ordered me to tell him to go to Soochow, where the case
                        would be investigated.</p>
                    <p>I then informed him I had no desire to embarrass him; I only wanted justice
                        done; but as this man could not be punished while holding a literary degree,
                        and that he ignored all officials in Chinkiang, I must insist on his being
                        returned to Chinkiang and his degree taken from him, thus degrading him and
                        rendering it impossible for him to hold office again.</p>
                    <p>Answer. I will have him brought back.</p>
                    <p>Question. Who has authority to degrade him?</p>
                    <p>Answer. The governor of the province or the viceroy.</p>
                    <p>Then I informed him I would make the demand for his degradation to the
                        viceroy. He then requested, for his own sake, to be permitted to telegraph
                        my demand to the viceroy and governor, which he promised to do that day.
                        That was five days ago. He has not been returned to Chinkiang yet.</p>
                    <p>I stated the matter verbally to Hon. E. H. Conger, United States minister,
                        during the few minutes the gunboat <hi rend="italic">Monocaey</hi> was
                        coaling at this port before proceeding on his voyage to Shanghai.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Wm. Martin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Consul.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Willis</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Taotai Chang</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chinkiang</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-11-07">
                                <hi rend="italic">November 7, 1899</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 355.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Yesterday I received a serious complaint from
                        the United States merchant, D. A. Emery, stating that on the 5th instant
                        (Sunday) the Chinese chief of police, Yang Sze Chen, at this port wanted to
                        arrest one of his shroffs, Yang Kwei Sam, without <pb facs="0496" n="398"
                            xml:id="pg_398"/> the usual authority of the United States consul. The
                        arrest was made under the plea that this shroff enticed another man’s wife
                        away from her husband.</p>
                    <p>The chief of police, accompanied by several runners, went to the said
                        merchant’s hong and ordered the arrest of Yang Kwei Sam, who happened to be
                        away, and another shroff named Chang Chung Hsuan spoke to the chief of
                        police of Yang’s absence and, without any cause, this man Chang Chung Hsuan
                        was then and there arrested and forthwith taken to the Pau Chia station.
                        Without listening to any reasoning a cangue was put on him with the order
                        that he must produce Yang Kwei Sam. While this was proceeding, D. A. Emery
                        sent his compradore’s son, named Yu Kai Ping, and his office boy, with his
                        card to tell the chief of police to release the shroff Chang Chung Hsuan and
                        to remind him that if he wished to arrest any of his employees to apply for
                        them in the usual way through the consul. However, as soon as the chief of
                        police saw that a foreigner sent his men to ask for the release of Chang
                        Chung Hsuan, he at once stepped down from the tribunal and himself bambooed
                        Yu Kai Ping 1,300 times, after which a cangue was placed on his neck, and he
                        was taken out on the West gate street for exposure.</p>
                    <p>The office boy ran away, and so escaped punishment.</p>
                    <p>The action of the chief of police is entirely unwarranted, both as regards
                        the manner of arrest and punishment meted out to the man arrested. Neither
                        of these two men had been guilty of any crime, and even had they been, as
                        they were in foreign employ they should not have been seized without my
                        consent.</p>
                    <p>The chief of police has by this action shown himself to be absolutely
                        unfitted for his position. I would accordingly request that you will at once
                        order his immediate dismissal from office, and that you will see that he is
                        not allowed to leave Chinkiang pending further investigation.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Consul Martin and the American minister, Mr. Conger, are expected here in
                        a day or two, and I prefer to leave the ultimate settlement of this case in
                        their hands.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">R. Willis</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">In charge of American interests.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Willis</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Taotai Chang</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chinkiang</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-11-08">
                                <hi rend="italic">November 8, 1899</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 356.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With reference to the seizure and beating of
                        shroffs Chang Chung Hsuan and Yu Kai Ping, belonging to United States
                        merchant Emery’s hong, it is reported to me by Mr. Emery that the shroff Yu
                        Kai Ping has been so severely beaten that his life is endangered. This case
                        is so serious that I must request you to at once arrest the Pao Chia Chü
                        Yang Ssu Chên pending settlement of the case.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">R. Willis</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">In charge of American interests.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Willis</persName> to <persName
                                type="to">Taotai Chang</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Chinkiang</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1899-11-09">
                                <hi rend="italic">November 9, 1899</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 357.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have just heard with very great surprise
                        that the Pao Chia Chü Yang Ssu Chen left this port last evening. His action
                        was so outrageous that I laid considerable stress on the necessity for his
                        detention here pending the settlement of the case. In my letters of the 7th
                        and 8th instant I put this on record, and at our interview yesterday
                        afternoon you informed me more than once that you were fully aware of the
                        importance of keeping him here, and assured me that it was impossible for
                        him to leave the port. It is certain that he could not have done so without
                        the connivance of the officials, and I now write to inform you that I
                        consider you to have been guilty of breach of faith toward me, and that I
                        hold you personally responsible for his escape.</p>
                    <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">R. Willis</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">In charge of American interests.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
