<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Choate to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1900</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d661</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">661</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1900-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1900-01-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="detainees" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="detainees">detained</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-01-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-01-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="661"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d661">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Choate</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy, London</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-01-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">January 5, 1900</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 227.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to report that since my dispatch
                    No. 226, of January 2, I received your cipher cable of the 3d [2d], and on the
                    same day I had an interview with Lord Salisbury, and on the 4th instant I sent
                    you an account of it by cipher cable. It was not until after my interview,
                    however, that I received by mail your instructions Nos. 262 and 263, of December
                    21, with the documents annexed, relating to the shipments of Flint, Eddy &amp;
                    Co. by the <hi rend="italic">Mashona</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi>, and
                    of Mr. R. W. Geldart by the <hi rend="italic">Beatrice</hi>. The information
                    conveyed by these documents is not as full as it might be, as Flint, Eddy &amp;
                    Co. do not inclose copies of their bills of lading, and Mr. Geldart sends
                    neither invoice nor bill of lading.</p>
                <p>By their aid, however, and with a view of giving Lord Salisbury such information
                    as I had received, I have to-day prepared and sent to him a note referring to
                    our interview, and adding such details as I had, of which note I inclose a copy.
                    I have assumed that these very small shipments are but a small part of the goods
                    belonging to American citizens which are involved in the seizures, and have made
                    my request for restitution broad enough to cover all there are.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph H. Choate.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Choate</persName> to the <gloss
                                type="to">Marquis of Salisbury</gloss>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">American Embassy</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                                    >London</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-01-04">
                                <hi rend="italic">January 4, 1900</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">My Lord</hi>: Since our interview of yesterday, in
                        which I stated the views of my Government in regard to the seizure by H. M.
                        S. <hi rend="italic">Partridge</hi> of certain flour shipped by American
                        citizens on the British vessel <hi rend="italic">Mashona</hi> for Delagoa
                        Bay, I have received certain papers throwing further light on the case.</p>
                    <p>Your Lordship will remember that upon the understanding which you confirmed
                        that the <hi rend="italic">Mashona</hi> was seized by the British
                        authorities for a violation of the municipal laws of Great Britain, for
                        trading with the enemy, and that the seizure or detention of the flour was
                        incidental to the seizure of the vessel, my Government’s view was that the
                        flour, to which no such offense could be imputed, could not under the
                        circumstances of the case, as understood by it, be admitted to be subject to
                        capture because not contraband of war, and I therefore asked for its prompt
                        restitution to the American owners.</p>
                    <pb facs="0642" n="544" xml:id="pg_544"/>
                    <p>Your lordship seemed much impressed by the supposed fact that the flour was
                        marked Z. A. R., which might mean the South African Republic, but you
                        courteously took my request under consideration. I also represented to your
                        lordship that if the seizure had been made on account of the flour carried
                        by the ship my Government could not recognize the validity of the seizure
                        under any belligerent right of capture of provisions and other goods shipped
                        by American citizens in ordinary course of trade to the port of a neutral
                        State. So that in any aspect of the case, so far as the circumstances have
                        been communicated to my Government, nothing appeared to justify the seizure
                        of the goods complained of. The seizure not being of the flour as
                        contraband, your lordship very naturally refrained for the time being from
                        formulating your views on the subject of provisions as contraband.</p>
                    <p>The papers which. I have now received show that Flint, Eddy &amp; Co., a very
                        reputable firm of merchants, doing business in New York, American citizens,
                        shipped on the <hi rend="italic">Mashona</hi>, property belonging to them,
                        consisting of 400 bags of flour, 5 cases canned soup, and 25 cases Quaker
                        oats, marked on the invoice F. B. &amp; Co., Delagoa Bay—no mark Z. A. R.
                        appeared thereon—consigned to order and invoiced to F. Bridler &amp; Co., a
                        firm of merchants doing a large local business there, believed by the
                        shippers to be a German firm and not citizens of either the Transvaal
                        Republic or the Orange Free State. The value of this particular invoice is
                        not large, but the interruption to the business of the shippers is very
                        serious.</p>
                    <p>The same firm shipped on the <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi>, which your
                        lordship understood to be in the same category as the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Mashona</hi>—a British vessel, seized for a violation of the municipal
                        law of Great Britain, for trading with the enemy—65 cases canned goods and
                        libbys, 40 cases lard, 20 bags peas and beans, and 1 case containing lemon
                        squeezer and nail pullers, and 1 case hardware—all marked on the invoice in
                        the same way, F. B. &amp; Co., Delagoa Bay, no mark Z. A. R. appearing
                        thereon, invoiced to the same firm here described as of Lourenço Marquez,
                        and also consigned to order.</p>
                    <p>These goods are drawn against, and are invoiced for account and risk of the
                        consignees, but the goods not being delivered, the loss will naturally rest
                        upon the American shippers, the actual owners thereof.</p>
                    <p>Messrs. Flint, Eddy &amp; Co. shipped other goods belonging to them on the
                            <hi rend="italic">Mashona</hi> for account of Fowlie &amp; Boden,
                        London, of which I have no particulars, but they are probably included in
                        the seizures, and there may be other American shippers having goods on the
                            <hi rend="italic">Mashona</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi>, and
                        also involved. I of course make the same request for the restitution of
                        Flint, Eddy &amp; Co.’s goods by the <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi> as for
                        those upon the <hi rend="italic">Mashona.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>By the <hi rend="italic">Beatrice</hi>, according to my information just
                        received, Mr. R. W. Geldart, of New York City, an American citizen, shipped
                        an invoice of beer and lard belonging to him to a Portuguese firm in
                        Lourenco Marquez, and that the same, by order of Her Majesty’s Government,
                        has been discharged into lighters at East London without Mr. Geldart’s
                        consent, whereby the liability of the ship and of the insurers of the goods
                        ceased, and in respect to this transaction I am instructed to request a
                        statement of the facts and of the grounds for taking the cargo out of the
                        ship. Mr. Geldart’s shipment was one of a series under a monthly order
                        commencing last March.</p>
                    <p>Your lordship will be so kind as to regard my request for restitution to
                        embrace all merchandise shipped by American citizens on the <hi
                            rend="italic">Mashona</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Maria</hi> which may
                        have been detained or seized, and as I receive further particulars I will
                        transmit them to you.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph H. Choate.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
