<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Hardy to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1900</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d783</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">783</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1900-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1900-04-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="rec9aDoDi7sluDnsm" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="civil-rights"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026371"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil rights</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-04-05T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-04-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="783"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d783">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hardy</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Athens</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-04-05">
                            <hi rend="italic">April 5, 1900</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 33, Greek series.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith further
                    correspondence in the case of L. Economopoulos, all previous notes between Mr.
                    Romanos and myself having been forwarded in my No. 32 of March 22 last.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Arthur S. Hardy.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Romanos</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hardy</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-03-18">
                                <hi rend="italic">March 18</hi> (<hi rend="italic">G. S</hi>.), <hi
                                    rend="italic">1900</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: I hastened to transmit your note of
                        February 20 to my colleague of the department of war.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Tsamados informs me that he deeply regrets that he can not release L.
                        Economopoulos from military service.</p>
                    <p>In fact, Mr. Minister, the soldier in question, before acquiring American
                        citizenship, should have obtained permission to abandon his Greek
                        nationality according to the forms required by our civil code and discharged
                        his military obligations to the country of his birth.</p>
                    <p>I take this occasion to renew, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. Romanos.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hardy</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Romanos</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Athens</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-04-03">
                                <hi rend="italic">April 3, 1900</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: I hasten to reply to your note of
                        March 18/31 last, in which you say that the American citizen Economopoulos
                        can not be released from military service because before acquiring American
                        citizenship he should have obtained permission to abandon his Greek
                        nationality and discharged his military obligations to the country of his
                        birth. Permit me to call your excellency’s attention to the fact that this
                        answer does not meet the circumstances of the case.</p>
                    <p>As a matter of fact, Economopoulos <hi rend="italic">has</hi> changed his
                        nationality, and has become a citizen of the United States in accordance
                        with the provisions of its laws. This fact is not in dispute, and the
                        question at issue therefore is What, under these circumstances, can the
                        Greek Government legally require of him on his return to Greece to make, in
                        good faith, a brief visit on his parents.</p>
                    <p>If I understand correctly the rulings of Greek courts hereinafter cited
                        Economopoulos, being an American citizen, can not be held for service in the
                        Greek army; for according to the well-known decisions dated June 14, 1886,
                        to be found in the <pb facs="0739" n="641" xml:id="pg_641"/> Collection of
                        Opinions and Sentences of the Legal Council on Doubtful Administration,
                        pages 290 and 291, it is a recognized principle that only a Greek subject
                        can be so held. No. 16, above referred to, is as follows:</p>
                    <p>“Vu que, conformément à ce que le Conseil de Révision admet, l’interjetant a
                        légalement acquis la qualité de sujet étranger, eté en conequence,
                        l’autorité Hellénique ne peut plus le saisir et l’obliger à remplir une
                        obligation, bien que cette obligation existe avant sa naturalisation, car on
                        n’est soumis au service militaire envers l’Etat qu’à la condition d’avoir la
                        qualité de sujet Hellénique, conformément à l’Article 6 de la loi 15
                        (Article 7 de la loi en vigueur) et l’Etat d’autre part a cessé d’avoir sur
                        l’inter jetant l’autorité à le contraindre à remplir telle obligation. La
                        raison que l’interjetant est soumis à poursuite pénale n’importe pas, vu que
                        les lois pénales s’étendent sans distinction sur toutes les personnes
                        résidant dans le pays (Article 3 de la loi civile). Pour cela elle modifie
                        etc. &amp; exempte etc.”</p>
                    <p>No. 17 states the case still more clearly.</p>
                    <p>The question was “Whether one acquiring a foreign allegiance is regarded as a
                        foreigner if he was a minor when he asked permission therefor?” and the
                        opinion declares that it was immaterial whether he was a minor or not,
                        “because he was able even without such permission to change his nationality,
                            <hi rend="italic">subject only to the penalty prescribed by the penal
                            code.</hi>” It is clear that according to your own law a minor can
                        change his nationality without the royal assent, <hi rend="italic">subject
                            only to the penalty prescribed by the penal laws</hi>. That
                        Economopoulos is liable to that penalty I willingly admit, though in its
                        application it is to be hoped that the long and unwarrantable service to
                        which he has been compelled will be taken into account.</p>
                    <p>In the case of Emmanuel C. Catechi, released in 1890, which I had the honor
                        to cite to your excellency as a precedent, the request of my predecessor,
                        Mr. Snowden, was based upon the foregoing decision, and in view of its clear
                        applicability to the case of Economopoulos I must renew my request for his
                        release from military service, whatever may be his liability under the penal
                        code.</p>
                    <p>It further appears, as I am informed, that when a former subject surfers the
                        penalty prescribed by the penal laws for a change of nationality without
                        royal assent he loses his civil rights.</p>
                    <p>If then Economopoulos, being subject only to the provisions of the penal code
                        according to the above opinion, be turned over to the civil law and
                        subjected to its penalties, he thereby loses his civil rights and can not
                        therefore be liable for military service, since it is a recognized principle
                        that the protection of a State and obligation thereto go hand in hand. The
                        latter can not be enforced if the former is denied.</p>
                    <p>In my former requests I have appealed solely to the friendly spirit which has
                        marked the settlement of such cases in the past. To these precedents, which
                        I cited, your excellency’s reply makes no reference. Am I to understand that
                        they are disavowed?</p>
                    <p>If so, there still remains the opinion of the council above quoted, which
                        asserts the essential question to be whether the appellant “legally acquired
                        foreign allegiance <hi rend="italic">according to the laws of that foreign
                            State.</hi>” Of this there is no dispute in the case of Economopoulos. I
                        have therefore the honor to renew my request for his release <hi
                            rend="italic">from military service</hi> on the ground of his legally
                        acquired American citizenship, and his exemption under the above judgment
                        from obligation for military duty.</p>
                    <p>I seize this opportunity to renew, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. S. Hardy.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
