<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-01-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-01-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="883" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d883">
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Buck</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">United
                                        States Legation</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-01-16"><hi rend="italic">January 16,
                                1900</hi></date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: As a matter of some interest, I have the
                            honor to report that the steamship transport <hi rend="italic">Grant</hi>, with the Forty-eighth Regiment United States Infantry
                            (colored), under command of Col. William P. Duvall, arrived in Yokohama
                            on the 11th instant, remaining some days to coal, and departing
                            yesterday for Manila.</p>
                        <p>By the courtesy of the Japanese Government Colonel Duvall was permitted,
                            on Saturday, the 13th instant, to take his regiment ashore <pb facs="0856" n="758" xml:id="pg_758"/> with arms and hold a dress
                            parade and drill on one of the public squares of the city, much to the
                            gratification of American citizens there and to the pleasure of the
                            people of Yokohama of all nationalities. I had the pleasure of
                            witnessing the parade and drill. Considering the fact, as stated by
                            Colonel Duvall, that his men had not had their rifles in hand since
                            leaving San Francisco, twenty-two days before, and of course had done no
                            regimental marching or drilling, the execution of the march and manual
                            of arms was astonishingly good. The regiment was in good health and
                            spirits, and the soldierly bearing and general appearance of the men
                            were all that could be desired.</p>
                        <p>This, as I am informed, is the first armed body of soldiers of any
                            nationality ever permitted to land and parade at any port in Japan. Such
                            a marked courtesy extended to our troops is very gratifying, and it was
                            hardly to be expected.</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">A. E. Buck.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>