<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mr. Buck to Mr. Hay.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1900</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d888</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">888</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1900-06-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1900-06-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recOAfZ9FRSJKK76a" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064772"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Income tax</term>
                    <term ref="recBqMssH5ULmL32L" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85132836"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Tax</term>
                    <term ref="rec2HPZNpQil9Rnjj" type="topic" category="department-of-state"
                        subcategory="personnel-civil-service"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026387"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Civil Service</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1900-06-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1900-06-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="888"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d888">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Buck</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Hay</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Tokio, Japan</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-06-29">
                            <hi rend="italic">June 29, 1900</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 444.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inclose herewith a copy of a
                    communication to me from Dr. F. Anderson, surgeon in charge of the United States
                    naval hospital at Yokohama, date of the 17th instant, with copies of <pb
                        facs="0861" n="763" xml:id="pg_763"/> correspondence between him and the
                    chief of the Yokohama revenue administration bureau, concerning making returns
                    and paying income tax by the officers and enlisted men of the United States Navy
                    and Marine Corps stationed at the hospital. I also inclose a copy of a note
                    addressed by me to the Japanese minister for foreign affairs upon that
                    subject.</p>
                <p>In conversation with the minister in respect to the officers and enlisted men at
                    the hospital being subject to the income tax, he expressed the desire, in
                    determining the matter, to take into consideration also the claims of a like
                    nature made by the surgeons in charge of the German and British hospitals, which
                    would cause some delay.</p>
                <p>While I, as yet, have no response to my note, I am of opinion that the chief of
                    the revenue officials of Yokohama will not further press the matter of obtaining
                    return of the incomes in question pending the decision of the Government, as I
                    presume instructions have been given to that effect.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">A. E. Buck.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Dr. <persName type="from">Anderson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Buck</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Naval Hospital</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Yokohama, Japan</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-06-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 17, 1900</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to submit for your
                        consideration the question of the obligation of officers and enlisted men of
                        the United States Navy and Marine Corps stationed at this hospital to make
                        returns of income and pay taxes thereon in accordance with the provisions of
                        the income-tax law of the Japanese Empire, now in operation.</p>
                    <p>In April last some blank forms for making return of income were left at this
                        hospital, together with printed explanatory remarks. According to these
                        “remarks,” it seemed to me evident that no person connected with the
                        hospital came within the provisions of this law, and therefore none of these
                        blank forms were filled out. Some weeks later some officers and men on duty
                        at this hospital and in the active service of our Government received postal
                        cards requesting them to fill out at once these blank forms and make return
                        of income.</p>
                    <p>As the officer in charge of the hospital, I accordingly addressed the letter,
                        a copy of which is hereto appended and marked “A,” to the director of the
                        Yokohama revenue administration bureau. In response to this letter I was
                        called upon by Mr. Tojo, the chief of the Yokohama taxation office, who
                        stated that the translation of the word “active” as used in the “Remarks”
                        was not a correct translation of the Japanese word, and that only officers
                        and men in “actual” service would be exempt from taxation. I therefore
                        requested that an official letter be sent me stating clearly the meaning of
                        the law. On June 15 the letter, in Japanese, a translation of which I have
                        obtained and appended hereto, marked “B,” was sent to me. A copy of my reply
                        is appended and marked “C.” According to this translation, officers and men,
                        during war time only and at the seat of war, are exempt from taxation. This
                        interpretation practically excludes all foreign officers and men from
                        exemption.</p>
                    <p>In my opinion, officers and enlisted men on duty at this hospital are not
                        legally subject to an income tax, and I do not feel justified in complying
                        with the provisions of the law myself, nor authorizing those under my charge
                        to do so, in the absence of any definite instructions from my Government.
                        The officers and men on duty here are not here voluntarily, but in
                        accordance with orders from the Navy Department, which they are compelled to
                        obey.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, permit me to call your excellency’s attention to the text of
                        article 5, subscription 1, of the income-tax law of Japan, and to article 1,
                        paragraph 4, of the treaty now in force between the United States and Japan.
                        I have the honor to inclose copies of the extracts above referred to.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">F. Anderson</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Surgeon, U. S. Navy, in charge of Hospital.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0862" n="764" xml:id="pg_764"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure A.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Anderson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Saito</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Yokohama, Japan</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-05-23">
                                <hi rend="italic">May 23, 1900</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Some time ago blank forms for return of
                        income were left at this hospital, and to-day postal cards were received
                        addressed to officers and men stationed here requesting that these blank
                        forms be filled out and returned.</p>
                    <p>All the persons so addressed are officers or enlisted men in the naval
                        service of the United States on active duty. They are stationed here by
                        orders of the United States Government, and are liable to be ordered away at
                        any time.</p>
                    <p>According to paragraph 6, article 5, of “Remarks” accompanying these blank
                        forms, being naval men in active service, their incomes are not taxable, nor
                        are they required to make return of salary.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">F. Anderson</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Surgeon,
                                etc.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure B.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Saito</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Anderson</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-06-15">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">June</hi> 15, 1900</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am in receipt of your communication under
                        date of May 23, relative to a notice of the amount of income. Salaries to be
                        received by military men (army and navy) while in active service, as
                        provided in item 1, article 5, of the income-tax law, means the salaries to
                        be received by the army and navy men at the seat of war or at the places to
                        be considered as the seats of war, and while the rendering of “Jungun” into
                        the English “active service,” in the remarks appended to the paper of notice
                        lately distributed by the Yokohama tax office, may not be a proper
                        rendering, still the spirit of the revenue law is that no tax will be levied
                        upon the salaries to be receivable in the cases as indicated above. Military
                        men (army and naval), although under commission, unless they come under the
                        cases above stated, are under obligation to pay taxes as officials in civil
                        service, as provided in articles 1 and 2 of the revenue law.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">S. Saito.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure C]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Anderson</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Saito</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Yokohama</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-06-17">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 17, 1900</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am in receipt of your communication of the
                        15th instant, relative to the construction which your bureau places upon the
                        wording of that portion of the incometax law of Japan which exempts the
                        salaries of persons in the army or navy while on active service.</p>
                    <p>I understand you now to hold that this exemption applies to such persons only
                        when they are engaged in active hostilities. My understanding of the
                        provisions of this law has been that the exemption applied to all in active
                        service under a commission or under the orders of the military departments
                        of any government.</p>
                    <p>In view of the provisions of the treaty between the United States and Japan,
                        the question is one of such importance that I have considered it necessary
                        to refer it to the United States minister at Tokyo and the Navy Department
                        of the United States at Washington, and I would ask you to be good enough to
                        suspend all action in the matter until I receive the instructions of my
                        Government.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Subinclosure D.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Extract from translation of income-tax law of Japan, as
                            published by the Yokohama tax bureau.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>Art. V. Income tax is not levied on the following incomes:</p>
                    <p>1. Salaries of persons in the army or navy while on active service.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="italic">Extract from treaty between the United States and Japan,
                            signed November 22, 1894.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Art. 1, par. 4. They (the subjects or citizens of each of the two high
                        contracting parties) shall not be compelled, under any pretext whatever, to
                        pay any charges or taxes other or higher than those that are, or may be,
                        paid by native subjects or citizens or subjects or citizens of the most
                        favored nation.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0863" n="765" xml:id="pg_765"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Buck</persName> to Mr. <persName
                                type="to">Siuzo</persName>.</hi>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">United States Legation</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Tokyo</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1900-06-25">
                                <hi rend="italic">June 25, 1900</hi>
                            </date>.</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 211.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Referring to our conversation on the 21st
                        instant respecting the question whether an income tax should be levied upon
                        the salaries of the surgeons and enlisted men of the United States Navy now
                        assigned to duty at the United States marine hospital at Yokohama, in order
                        that this question raised by the surgeon in charge of the hospital may be
                        presented with more particularity, I have the honor to respectfully submit
                        for the consideration of your excellency the grounds upon which the claim of
                        exemption from income tax is based.</p>
                    <p>It is claimed that the surgeon in charge, assistant surgeon, and enlisted men
                        of the Navy, temporarily on duty at the hospital in Yokohama, are on active
                        service there by assignment of the United States Navy Department, subject to
                        transfer to some other hospital or to some naval vessel at any time by the
                        order of the Department, as much so as if they were on duty on a ship of war
                        or in the discharge of their official duties at some United States naval
                        hospital in some foreign country at the seat of war; that they are, strictly
                        speaking, not domiciled in Japan and have acquired no residence here; that
                        the hospital is the property of the United States, erected on land held
                        under perpetual lease granted by the Imperial Government to the United
                        States for hospital purposes, and that the surgeons and enlisted men now on
                        duty there are to be regarded as free from any legal requirement to pay an
                        income tax as though they were on board a United States ship of war in the
                        harbor; that they have no business or occupation in Japan other than their
                        official duties at the hospital and derive no income because of their being
                        stationed for the time and on duty in Japan, their only income being their
                        salaries from their Government, and that it is believed that under the
                        circumstances the income-tax law of the Imperial Government was not intended
                        to apply in such case.</p>
                    <p>Article V, paragraph 1, of the income-tax law, under which levy is sought to
                        be made upon the officers and men at the hospital, provides that the income
                        tax is not to be levied on “Salaries of persons in the army or navy while on
                        active service.” While it would seem that this provision was intended to
                        apply to persons in the army and navy of the Imperial Government only, as it
                        could not be contemplated that officers and enlisted men of the army or navy
                        of any other power could, while in service in the discharge of any official
                        duties whatever, have their residence and be domiciled in legal sense within
                        the territory of the Empire—yet should it be contended that the law does so
                        apply, since the surgeon and men are really “on active service,” exemption
                        is claimed.</p>
                    <p>For these reasons the surgeon in charge does not feel justified in complying
                        with the request made by the tax officials to make return of income for
                        himself or authorizing the officers and men under his charge to do so in the
                        absence of instructions from his Government, and he has consequently
                        informed the chief of the Yokohama revenue administration bureau that the
                        question is one of such importance that he has to request that no further
                        steps be taken to enforce the levy of the tax pending instructions for which
                        he has applied.</p>
                    <p>Whatever may be the conclusion of the Imperial Government respecting the
                        question raised I venture to respectfully suggest that pending such
                        conclusion, and as also pending instructions from my Government, the levy of
                        the income tax upon the surgeons and enlisted men at the United States
                        marine hospital be stayed, if consistent.</p>
                    <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">A. E. Buck.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
