<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1970-08-18T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1970-08-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="152" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d152">
                        <head>152. Paper Prepared by the Defense Program Review Committee Working
                                Group<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d152fn1">Source: Washington
                                National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_OSD1">OSD</gloss> Files:
                                FRC 330–73A–1971, 381, Defense Planning <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71. Top Secret. Previous drafts of this paper were
                                discussed at the <gloss target="#t_DPRC1">DPRC</gloss> meetings of
                                July 17 and August 10 and a special meeting, attended by <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, held on July 28 at the
                                Western White House in San Clemente to discuss the defense budget.
                                See <ref target="#d145">Documents 145</ref>, <ref target="#d149">149</ref>, and <ref target="#d148">148</ref>,
                                respectively.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1970-08-18">August 18,
                                1970</date>.</dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center">DEFENSE PLANNING 1971–76</p>
                        <p rend="center">I. Introduction</p>
                        <p>The last National Security Council review of this subject occurred in
                            September 1969 when the results of <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>–3 were considered.<note n="2" xml:id="d152fn2">The <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> met on September 10, 1969, to
                                discuss the response to <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss> 3,
                                submitted 5 days earlier. See <ref target="#d45">Documents 45</ref>
                                and <ref target="#d49">49</ref>.</note> Subsequently, the President
                            issued five-year fiscal guidance and selected a strategy which calls for
                            military capabilities for an initial defense of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Europe <hi rend="italic">or</hi> a joint defense of
                            Asia (Korea <hi rend="italic">or</hi> Southeast Asia) together with
                            support of Asian Allies against non-Chinese attacks plus a minor
                            contingency (<gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27, October 11,
                                1969).<note n="3" xml:id="d152fn3"><ref target="#d56">Document
                                    56</ref>.</note></p>
                        <p>During the past year, the economic and fiscal projections on which <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 was based have changed
                            substantially for the entire planning period, as illustrated by: <list>
                                <item>—revenues in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 have been
                                    reduced $7 billion because of the Tax Reform Act of 1969<note n="4" xml:id="d152fn4">The Tax Reform Act of 1969 (P.L.
                                        91–172), which cleared both Houses of Congress on December
                                        22 and was signed by <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> on December 30, was the most
                                        comprehensive revision of the tax code since the
                                        implementation of the income tax in 1913. The measure
                                        provided for annual tax cuts totaling $9.1 billion and
                                        long-term tax reform expected to generate $6.6 billion in
                                        additional revenues. (<hi rend="italic">Congress and the
                                            Nation, 1969–1972</hi>, pp. 2–3, 79–85)</note> and
                                    softness in the economy;</item>
                                <item>—costs of non-defense programs in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 are $24 billion higher because of
                                    Administration initiatives ($11 billion), higher costs in
                                    formula-controlled programs, Congressional changes to
                                    Administration proposals, higher interest costs, and less rapid
                                    decline in inflation (totalling $13 billion);</item>
                                <item>—costs of defense programs in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 are $3 billion higher because of increased
                                    pay costs, the decision in <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–53<note n="5" xml:id="d152fn5"><ref target="#d139">Document 139</ref>.</note> to provide a
                                    Volunteer Service, and less rapid decline in inflation;</item>
                                <pb facs="0587" n="558" xml:id="pg_558"/>
                                <item>—a $23 billion budget deficit is projected for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 rather than a surplus.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>Table 1 shows the current projections of the costs of defense and
                            non-defense programs, estimates of federal revenues, and the resulting
                            budget deficits. These projections <hi rend="italic">include no new
                                Presidential initiatives beyond those announced to date by the
                                Administration</hi>. Past experience would indicate that new
                            initiatives add from $1–3 billion in the first year (<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72) and $5–15 billion in succeeding
                            years. The budgetary projections shown in Table 1, together with current
                            estimates of the behavior of the economy under current policies, call
                            for a reevaluation of defense and non-defense programs.</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 1</p>
                        <p rend="center">Federal Budget Projections</p>
                        <p rend="center">(Then-Year $ Billions)</p>
                        <table cols="9" rows="8">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    71</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    72</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    73</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    74</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    75</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    76</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Federal Revenues</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$198</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$214</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$231</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$253</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$280</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$306</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Federal Expenditures</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Defense<note n="6" xml:id="d152fn6"><gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 budget, adjusted for pay and price
                                        increases and Volunteer Service (<gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–53). [Footnote in the
                                    original.]</note></cell>
                                <cell role="num">74</cell>
                                <cell role="num">79</cell>
                                <cell role="num">80</cell>
                                <cell role="num">81</cell>
                                <cell role="num">83</cell>
                                <cell role="num">85</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Non-Defense base</cell>
                                <cell role="num">138</cell>
                                <cell role="num">147</cell>
                                <cell role="num">158</cell>
                                <cell role="num">165</cell>
                                <cell role="num">174</cell>
                                <cell role="num">185</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Announced initiatives<note n="7" xml:id="d152fn7">Includes <hi rend="italic">only</hi> initiatives announced to date;
                                        not new ones. Figures are <hi rend="italic">net</hi> with
                                        increases offset by $2.2 billion reduction each year in
                                        proposed program reforms. [Footnote in the
                                    original.]</note></cell>
                                <cell role="num">1</cell>
                                <cell role="num">11</cell>
                                <cell role="num">13</cell>
                                <cell role="num">15</cell>
                                <cell role="num">18</cell>
                                <cell role="num">21</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Total</cell>
                                <cell role="num">213</cell>
                                <cell role="num">237</cell>
                                <cell role="num">251</cell>
                                <cell role="num">261</cell>
                                <cell role="num">275</cell>
                                <cell role="num">291</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Margin</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$15</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–$23</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–$20</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–$8</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+$5</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+$15</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>The following sections of this paper describe the relevant economic
                            considerations for alternative federal budgets, the range of defense and
                            non-defense programs consistent with those budgets, and the implications
                            of these program changes.</p>
                        <p rend="center">II. Economic Analysis</p>
                        <p>Given the projections of Federal outlays above, the range of possible
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 budgets is $220–$240 billion,
                            though the lower end would require some very substantial and severe
                            budget reductions. The relevant issues are: <list>
                                <item>—Would budget expenditures within this range be consistent
                                    with reasonable stability of the economy?</item>
                                <pb facs="0588" n="559" xml:id="pg_559"/>
                                <item>—Would budget expenditures within this range be consistent
                                    with satisfaction of high-priority non-Federal claims for
                                    resources?</item>
                                <item>—Would budget expenditures within this range be consistent
                                    with the Administration’s credibility upon which its leadership
                                    depends?</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The answers to these questions depend in part on tax and monetary policy.
                            The questions are discussed on the assumption of no general tax
                            increase, which means revenues around $210–$215 billion in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. The answers also assume that the
                            monetary authorities have a basically similar perception of economic
                            conditions and needs, and respond in an expected and appropriate way.
                            Based on these assumptions, the $220–$240 billion expenditure range can
                            be structured at three budget levels: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Expenditures in excess of $235 billion</hi>
                                    are probably inconsistent with achievement of high-priority
                                    goals for housing construction and for State and local
                                    expenditures, including expenditures for environmental
                                    improvement.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Expenditures between $225 and $235
                                        billion</hi> are probably consistent with achievement of
                                    high-priority non-Federal goals and with economic stability, but
                                    they involve certain risks which would be smaller, the lower in
                                    the range actual expenditures are. These <hi rend="italic">risks</hi> are: <list>
                                        <label>a.</label>
                                        <item>Recommendation of a deficit of, for example, $20
                                            billion would so contradict popular notions of economic
                                            soundness and statements of the Administration as to
                                            create doubts about the Administration’s ability or
                                            desire to manage its economic affairs and would,
                                            accordingly, raise questions about the Administration’s
                                            leadership.</item>
                                        <label>b.</label>
                                        <item>The announcement of a deficit of $20 billion would
                                            generate an expectation of inflation which, even though
                                            not “really” justified, would at least temporarily set
                                            back the decline of long-term interest rates and the
                                            revival of housing and State and local
                                            investment.</item>
                                        <label>c.</label>
                                        <item>The Federal Reserve might exaggerate the extent to
                                            which the budget deficit requires monetary restraint to
                                            offset it, and consequently hold the real economy below
                                            the levels that are feasible and would be achieved if
                                            the budget deficit were smaller.</item>
                                        <label>d.</label>
                                        <item>The estimate that a $235 billion budget is consistent
                                            with achieving other goals assumes that the economy will
                                            be allowed to rise to its potential by mid-1972. If the
                                            Federal Reserve, out of concern with inflation,
                                            stretches the recovery out over a longer period, there
                                            will be less real resources in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72, and our ability to meet both a $235
                                            billion budget and greater goals will be correspondingly
                                            reduced.</item>
                                        <label>e.</label>
                                        <item>The higher expenditures are in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72, the higher they are likely to be in
                                            subsequent years when total claims on resources are
                                            likely to be greater than in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71 and 72. A large budget in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72, therefore, endangers
                                            the achievement of other goals in later years (for
                                            example, projected revenues for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 73 are $231 billion, see Table
                                            2).</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <pb facs="0589" n="560" xml:id="pg_560"/>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Expenditures below $225 billion</hi> raise a
                                    risk of another kind. This is the risk that monetary policy
                                    could not stimulate expansion of non-Federal expenditures <hi rend="italic">fast enough</hi> to prevent a lag in the
                                    recovery of the economy to its potential.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>On the assumption of no general tax increase, the foregoing
                            considerations lead to an expenditure target in the $225–$230 billion
                            range in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72, yielding a deficit around
                            $10–$15 billion. These considerations, of course, have to be balanced
                            against the benefits of some $8–$13 billion of Federal programs that
                            would be sacrificed in getting the budget down to this range.</p>
                        <p>The safe level of budget expenditures could be raised by increasing
                            taxes. However, it is generally believed that such a step would be
                            extremely unpopular—i.e., inconsistent with the public’s priorities—and
                            most unlikely to be approved by Congress. Planning for the expenditure
                            side of the budget should proceed on the assumption of no tax increase
                            until the impossibility of a satisfactory solution on that basis has
                            been demonstrated.</p>
                        <p>The receipts, outlays, and surplus (or deficit) for two feasible budgets
                            are shown in Table 2.</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 2</p>
                        <p rend="center">Two Feasible Federal Budgets</p>
                        <p rend="center">(Then-Year $ Billions)</p>
                        <table cols="9" rows="9">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    71</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    72</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    73</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    74</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    75</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    76</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">High Budget</hi></cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Receipts</cell>
                                <cell role="num">198</cell>
                                <cell role="num">213</cell>
                                <cell role="num">231</cell>
                                <cell role="num">253</cell>
                                <cell role="num">280</cell>
                                <cell role="num">306</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Outlays</cell>
                                <cell role="num">213</cell>
                                <cell role="num">232</cell>
                                <cell role="num">251</cell>
                                <cell role="num">261</cell>
                                <cell role="num">275</cell>
                                <cell role="num">289</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Surplus (deficit)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">(15)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">(19)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">(20)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">(8)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">5</cell>
                                <cell role="num">17</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Low Budget</hi></cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Receipts</cell>
                                <cell role="num">198</cell>
                                <cell role="num">212</cell>
                                <cell role="num">230</cell>
                                <cell role="num">252</cell>
                                <cell role="num">279</cell>
                                <cell role="num">305</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Outlays</cell>
                                <cell role="num">211</cell>
                                <cell role="num">225</cell>
                                <cell role="num">240</cell>
                                <cell role="num">252</cell>
                                <cell role="num">267</cell>
                                <cell role="num">280</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Surplus (deficit)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">(13)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">(13)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">(13)</cell>
                                <cell role="num">0</cell>
                                <cell role="num">12</cell>
                                <cell role="num">25</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p rend="center">III. Defense Options</p>
                        <p>The projections of total Federal budgets and the economic analysis cited
                            above point up the need to examine the alternative levels of defense
                            budgets. This section describes the impact of several alternative
                            defense budget levels on defense strategy and national security
                            interests and commitments, and highlights the management and timing
                            problems associated with large reductions.</p>
                        <pb facs="0590" n="561" xml:id="pg_561"/>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">A. Review of Current Planning</hi></p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Budget Guidance</hi></p>
                        <p>For planning purposes, <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 specified
                                <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> budgets for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71–75. Since <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27, there have been two major changes in the
                            assumptions on which these budgets were based: (1) there have been pay
                            and price increases due to greater than expected inflation; and (2)
                                <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–53 added provisions for a
                            Volunteer Service. The <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 budget,
                            these changes, and the resulting current projections are shown in Table
                            3.</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 3</p>
                        <p rend="center">Projections of Defense Outlays for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71–76</p>
                        <p rend="center">(Then-Year $ Billions)</p>
                        <table cols="8" rows="5">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    71</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    72</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    73</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    74</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    75</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    76</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$76</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$76</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$75</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$75</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$76</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$77<note n="8" xml:id="d152fn8">Not given in <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>-27; based on
                                        extrapolation from <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 74-75.
                                        [Footnote in the original.]</note></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Increased inflation</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">+1</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+2</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+3</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+4</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+5</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Volunteer Service</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">+2</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+3</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+3</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+3</cell>
                                <cell role="num">+3</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Current Projection</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$74</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$79</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$80</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$81</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$83</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$85</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Thus, simply to keep defense costs within <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 levels, about an overall 10% reduction in
                            programmed forces, procurement, manpower, etc., would be required in the
                            out-years. In <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72, cuts of about $3
                            billion would be required. In addition, defense might be forced to
                            absorb further reductions to keep Federal deficits within the bounds
                            noted in Section II.</p>
                        <p>As a result, a major review is needed to display the potential impacts of
                            alternative reductions in defense budgets. Because orderly planning of
                            even a $3 billion reduction in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 will
                            have major impacts in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71, decisions on
                            defense planning targets are needed soon. Should actions on a <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 defense budget cut of $5 billion or
                            more be delayed until January 1971, the transition problems will become
                            almost unmanageable, as is discussed in Section D.</p>
                        <p>The current projections in Table 3 are based on the assumptions in Table
                            4 for the war in Southeast Asia. <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>
                            budgets in the future will be very sensitive to changes in these
                            assumptions. For example, increasing or decreasing the planning level of
                            260,000 men in South Vietnam by 50,000 men by the end of <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71 would increase or decrease the
                            incremental cost of the war in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 by
                            $500 million. Increasing or decreasing tactical air sorties by 4,000 per
                            month and B–52 sorties by 200 per <pb facs="0591" n="562" xml:id="pg_562"/> month would also change the war costs by about
                            $500 million. The remaining sections of this paper do not vary the
                            assumptions in Table 4.</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 4</p>
                        <p rend="center">Southeast Asia Assumptions</p>
                        <p rend="center">(End-Year Deployments and Average Sortie Rates)</p>
                        <table cols="5" rows="7">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    70</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    71</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    72</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    73</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Actual</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Budget</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Projected</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Projected</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Men in <gloss target="#t_SVN1">SVN</gloss></cell>
                                <cell role="num">424,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">260,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">152,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">43,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Men in Thailand</cell>
                                <cell role="num">42,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">34,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">20,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Fighter-Attack sorties/month</cell>
                                <cell role="num">20,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">14,600</cell>
                                <cell role="num">10,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">3,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>B–52 sorties/month</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,400</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,200</cell>
                                <cell role="num">900</cell>
                                <cell role="num">300</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Incremental Cost of the War (outlays in then-year $
                                    billions)</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">$12  </cell>
                                <cell role="num">$8  </cell>
                                <cell role="num">$4  </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>The current projections in Table 3 assume that a Volunteer Service is to
                            be created and that it will cost as much as was indicated in <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–53. The remaining sections of this
                            paper do not vary this assumption. However, <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–53 may need re-evaluation in conjunction with this
                            review of total defense budgets. If the defense budget is reduced
                            significantly, the resulting force levels may be lower than those
                            assumed in <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–53, and the costs of a
                            Volunteer Service might therefore be lower. In view of the total Federal
                            budget situation, it may also be appropriate to review the goal of a
                            Volunteer Service and the timing of spending to achieve it.</p>
                        <p>Two alternatives are available for reducing spending on the Volunteer
                            Service from <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–53 levels. The first
                            would defer spending in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 except for
                            that which is already committed (e.g., the 20% first term pay raise
                            effective in mid-<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71). This alternative
                            would save about $1.4 billion in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72
                            outlays. A second alternative would slow the pace of spending designed
                            to achieve a Volunteer Service while allowing additional actions in
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 to improve pay and benefits
                            (primarily for first termers), and improve recruiting and retention for
                            active and reserve forces. This alternative might save $0.4–0.7 billion.
                            Both alternatives would be designed only for delaying attainment of the
                            Volunteer Service. However, the first alternative could be interpreted
                            as cancelling the commitment made by the President in April,<note n="9" xml:id="d152fn9">See <ref target="#d139">Document 139</ref>.</note>
                            since there would be much less overt action taken toward the objective
                            in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. The second alternative would
                            allow the implementation in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 of a
                            number of specific actions designed to move toward a Volunteer Service,
                            and would help maintain credence in the President’s commitment. <pb facs="0592" n="563" xml:id="pg_563"/> If adopted, savings from these
                            alternatives would be additive to the illustrative reductions in forces
                            and budgets shown in Table 10.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Strategy Guidance</hi></p>
                        <p>For planning purposes, the following strategy guidance was established
                            after the <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>–3 review of strategic
                            and general purpose forces: <list>
                                <label>a.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">Strategic Forces</hi>. <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16<note n="10" xml:id="d152fn10"><ref target="#d39">Document
                                        39</ref>.</note> directed that planning for strategic forces
                                    would be based on the following sufficiency criteria: <list>
                                        <item>“a. Maintain high confidence that the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> second-strike
                                            capability is sufficient to deter an all-out attack on
                                            our strategic forces.</item>
                                        <item>“b. Maintain forces to insure that the Soviet Union
                                            would have no incentive to strike the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> first in a
                                            crisis.</item>
                                        <item>“c. Maintain the capability to deny to the Soviet
                                            Union the ability to cause significantly more deaths and
                                            industrial damage in the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> in nuclear war than they would
                                            suffer.</item>
                                        <item>“d. Deploy defenses which limit damage from small
                                            attacks or accidental launches to a low level.”</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <label>b.</label>
                                <item><hi rend="italic">General Purpose Forces</hi>. <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 directed that planning for
                                    general purpose forces would be based on strategy 2 of <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>–3. In addition to providing
                                    forces for a “minor contingency” and a “strategic reserve,”
                                    strategy 2 provides that: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                        <p>“The United States would be prepared for an initial
                                            defense of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Europe
                                                <hi rend="italic">or</hi> a joint defense of Asia
                                            (Korea or Southeast Asia). The forces are designed so
                                            that major operations in one theater must be conducted
                                            at the expense of the major capability in the other,
                                            leaving a reduced capability in the non-war theater. For
                                            example, we could assist our allies in Asia against a
                                            non-Chinese attack while simultaneously providing an
                                            initial defense of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, but we could not conduct an initial
                                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> defense and a
                                            joint defense of Asia simultaneously. If initially
                                            engaged in Asia, by disengaging we would have the
                                            capability for an initial defense of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.”</p>
                                    </quote></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The President has also announced a policy for assisting Asian nations
                            against conventional aggression: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“We shall furnish military and economic assistance when requested
                                    and as appropriate. But we shall look to the nation directly
                                    threatened to assume the primary responsibility of providing the
                                    manpower for its defense.</p>
                                <p>“This approach requires our commitment to helping our partners
                                    develop their own strength. In doing so, we must strike a
                                    careful balance. If we do too little to help them—and erode
                                    their belief in our commitments—they may lose the necessary will
                                    to conduct their own self-defense or become disheartened about
                                    prospects of development. Yet, if we do too much, and American
                                    forces do what local forces can and should be doing, we promote
                                    dependence rather than independence.</p>
                                <pb facs="0593" n="564" xml:id="pg_564"/>
                                <p>“In providing for a more responsible role for Asian nations in
                                    their own defense, the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine means not only a more effective
                                    use of common resources, but also an American policy which can
                                    best be sustained over the long run.” (Message to Congress,
                                    February 18, 1970)<note n="11" xml:id="d152fn11">A reference to
                                        President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>’s
                                        First Annual Report to the Congress on United States Foreign
                                        Policy for the 1970s, issued on February 18. (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, 1970</hi>, pp.
                                    115–190)</note></p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>This guidance was the initial product of the comprehensive review of
                            national security policy initiated by this Administration. In evaluating
                            the alternative defense programs discussed in the next section of this
                            paper, it is important to note that the strategy guidance itself is
                            under review. At the President’s direction, the <gloss target="#t_DPRC1">DPRC</gloss> is preparing studies of the strategy guidance in order
                            to define its implications and to re-evaluate its adequacy in relation
                            to our national security interests.</p>
                        <p>It may be necessary to modify the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16 strategic sufficiency criteria. For example, the United
                            States no longer has clear strategic superiority over the Soviet Union;
                            in some areas (for example, total mega-tonnage and numbers of <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>s) the Soviets have superiority. Since
                            the Soviets have an assured destruction capability, we cannot rely on a
                            favorable strategic balance to assist us in managing crises such as
                            Berlin and Cuba. In addition, the Soviets may be developing a capability
                            to make an initial strike, then threaten <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> cities with their remaining weapons, which would be
                            hardened so that we could not destroy them. Therefore, it might be
                            desirable to change the sufficiency criteria to include an increased
                            capability for strategic warfighting.</p>
                        <p>On the other hand, our strategy and foreign policy have assumed that the
                            Soviet Union, in a first or second strike, could do unacceptable damage
                            to the United States and its allies. A Soviet initial strike which
                            withheld enough weapons to hold our population hostage would be a
                            dangerous tactic. While <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> strategic
                            forces could not be used reliably for destroying hardened Soviet
                            missiles, they would provide the President with a variety of nuclear
                            options short of all-out retaliation against Soviet cities. Some believe
                            that a <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> capability to destroy
                            hardened Soviet missiles would threaten the overall Soviet deterrent and
                            thus could provide a stimulus to the strategic arms race.</p>
                        <p>The <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 strategy for general purpose
                            forces needs to be reevaluated and clarified as a basis for force
                            planning. For example, the strategy includes the concept of curtailing
                            operations in Asia and re-deploying selected forces to Europe if
                            necessary for an initial defense of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. This concept is subject to considerable uncertainty.
                            The <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 strategy does not specify
                            how far forward we would want to defend in Europe, or what defense
                            perimeter we would want to <pb facs="0594" n="565" xml:id="pg_565"/>
                            maintain in the Pacific in a war with the Soviet Union. We may also wish
                            to reconsider the requirement that we be able to meet Chinese aggression
                            in Southeast Asia with <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> land forces,
                            because providing for this contingency is a large restriction on our
                            planning flexibility. Large differences in force levels depend on these
                            factors.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">B. Alternative Defense
                            Programs</hi></p>
                        <p>The alternatives that follow should be considered illustrative only and
                            representative of what could be done at various budget levels.</p>
                        <p>If, for example, we were to reduce <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss>
                            funding to an <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss>-only level, we
                            could maintain one additional active Army division, two additional
                            tactical fighter wings, an additional attack carrier with its associated
                            aircraft, and an additional one-third of an amphibious task force. Such
                            action would increase our general purpose force capability at the
                            expense of meeting the fourth <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16
                            sufficiency criterion.</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Strategic Force Alternatives</hi></p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">General</hi>. The strategic forces needed to implement
                            any set of strategic sufficiency criteria are subject to uncertainty
                            about the threat, differing views on the amount of redundancy and thus
                            confidence that is needed, and various interpretations of the scenarios
                            against which we should design our forces. For example, we currently
                            maintain an assured destruction capability in each of three forces:
                            bombers, <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>s, and <gloss target="#t_SLBM1">SLBM</gloss>s. This Triad concept hedges against
                            Soviet development of counters to our forces and against unexpected
                            failures in our forces. As the Soviet counterforce capability improves,
                            one or more of these systems may become vulnerable, making it an
                            attractive target in a crisis. We must then either make the investment
                            necessary to restore its survivability, or remove it, abandoning the
                            Triad concept. In the latter case, to maintain the same total confidence
                            in our assured destruction capability, compensating improvements in the
                            reliability, survivability, and penetrability of the remaining strategic
                            forces would have to be made. To maintain the same total destruction
                            capability, the level of these remaining forces would have to be
                            increased. The adequacy of alternative strategic force postures must be
                            assessed in light of the inherent uncertainties and different possible
                            design assumptions.</p>
                        <p>Some of the illustrative programs described below show major reductions
                            in continental air defense forces. Appendix A gives a more complete
                            discussion of objectives and alternatives for air defense programs.<note n="12" xml:id="d152fn12">Seven appendices are attached but not
                                printed: A. Continental Air Defense, B. Theater Nuclear Forces, C.
                                Alternative Safeguard Programs, D. Non Visible Bomber Force
                                Reductions, E. Anti-Submarine Warfare, F. Tactical Air Force Levels,
                                G. <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>—Strategy Forces and Burden
                                Sharing.</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0595" n="566" xml:id="pg_566"/>
                        <p>Four alternative illustrative forces considered below are summarized in
                            the following table, with end-<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 70
                            forces shown for comparison:</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 5</p>
                        <p rend="center">Comparison of Illustrative Strategic Forces<note n="13" xml:id="d152fn13">Out-year objectives. In most cases these force
                                levels would be obtained by end-<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                72. [Footnote in the original.]</note></p>
                        <table cols="7" rows="13">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell rendition="#nowrap"><hi rend="italic">End <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 70</hi></cell>
                                <cell><gloss target="#t_JSOP1"><hi rend="italic">JSOP</hi></gloss></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Current Program</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Limited Reduction Program</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Reduced Program</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Strategic Forces</hi></cell>
                                <cell cols="6"/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Bombers</cell>
                                <cell role="num">540</cell>
                                <cell role="num">503</cell>
                                <cell role="num">503</cell>
                                <cell role="num">443</cell>
                                <cell role="num">346</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Titans</cell>
                                <cell role="num">54</cell>
                                <cell role="num">36</cell>
                                <cell role="num">36</cell>
                                <cell role="num">—</cell>
                                <cell role="num">—</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Minuteman</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Polaris/Poseidon Subs</cell>
                                <cell role="num">41</cell>
                                <cell role="num">41</cell>
                                <cell role="num">41</cell>
                                <cell role="num">41</cell>
                                <cell role="num">41</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Air Defense Interceptors</cell>
                                <cell role="num">650</cell>
                                <cell role="num">627</cell>
                                <cell role="num">579</cell>
                                <cell role="num">410</cell>
                                <cell role="num">266</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Surface-to-Air Missiles</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,570</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,685</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,370</cell>
                                <cell role="num">290</cell>
                                <cell role="num">290</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Planned Safeguard Sites</cell>
                                <cell role="num">12</cell>
                                <cell role="num">12</cell>
                                <cell role="num">12</cell>
                                <cell role="num">8</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4<note n="14" xml:id="d152fn14">Could be seven if a
                                        light area defense of <gloss target="#t_CONUS1">CONUS</gloss> were deployed rather than a four-site
                                        defense of three Minuteman fields and the National Command
                                        authority. [Footnote in the original.]</note></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Cost of Strategic Forces</hi><note n="15" xml:id="d152fn15"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 $
                                        billions. [Footnote in the original.]</note></cell>
                                <cell cols="6"/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 Outlays</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">$15</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$12</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$11</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$10</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 76 Outlays</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">$14</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$12</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$11</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$ 9</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Average Annual Outlays <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    72–76</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">$15</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$11</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$10</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$ 9</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>a. <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Recommended
                                Objective Forces</hi>. This alternative (<gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss>) was developed by the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> in consideration of <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16, with no specific fiscal restraints. It represents
                            the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> view of attainable forces with a
                            prudent level of risk. These strategic forces would cost about $15
                            billion in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. The <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss> objective levels include the B–1
                            starting in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 77, the Undersea
                            Long-range Missile System (<gloss target="#t_ULMS1">ULMS</gloss>) in
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 78, and the rebasing of 140
                            Minuteman III into hard rock silos (3,000 <gloss target="#t_psi1">psi</gloss>) by <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 77. The <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss> forces are intended to meet all the
                                <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16 strategic sufficiency
                            criteria.</p>
                        <p>b. <hi rend="italic">Current Program</hi>. This alternative was developed
                            under fiscal guidance consistent with <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 and would cost about $12 billion in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. It would contain about the same
                            offensive forces as the <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss>, but the
                            Minuteman hard rock silo program would be replaced with a hardening
                            program to upgrade existing silos, and <gloss target="#t_ULMS1">ULMS</gloss> would become operational in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 80 versus <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 78. The
                            forces under this alternative are still designed to meet all the
                            strategic sufficiency criteria. If <pb facs="0596" n="567" xml:id="pg_567"/> the Soviet strategic threat increased at rates
                            above those projected in intelligence estimates for planning, and we did
                            not adapt to such changes, some of the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16 sufficiency criteria might not be met in the late
                            1970s. The substitution of a hardening program for Minuteman III in
                            existing silos versus rebasing Minuteman III in hard rock silos could
                            result in as many as 150 fewer survivors (375 fewer <gloss target="#t_RV1">RV</gloss>s) in the late 1970s. Possibly less than
                            100 missiles would survive. Air defense capabilities would be as
                            described for the Current Program option in Appendix A.</p>
                        <p>c. <hi rend="italic">Limited Reduction Program</hi>. As part of an annual
                            overall defense reduction of $3 billion in outlays, strategic forces
                            could be reduced by about $0.6–0.7 billion from the Current Program. The
                            eight-site Safeguard deployment plan would provide a light area defense
                            of the country and some protection of Minuteman. This planned deployment
                            would provide the basis for emphasizing National Command Authority
                                (<gloss target="#t_NCA1">NCA</gloss>) and Minuteman defense or could
                            be a step towards a 12-site defense level deployed at a reduced rate.
                            Damage limiting capability against aircraft attacks, small missile
                            attacks, and accidental missile launches would be reduced with this
                            program. Thus, the fourth <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16
                            sufficiency criterion might have to be changed. The first three <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16 sufficiency criteria should be met
                            with limited risk against the greatest threat projected in the National
                            Intelligence Projections for Planning (<gloss target="#t_NIPP1">NIPP</gloss>). An independent assured destruction capability in
                            each of the three force components should be maintained through the mid
                            1970s. The phase out of 36 Titans would result in the loss of 325
                            megatons and our only missile warheads with yields of over 1.2 megatons.
                            However, there would be no significant loss in counter-force capability
                            because of the limited accuracy of Titan. The current capability to use
                            bombers against the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> would be
                            retained, though at the cost of a temporary degradation in some Single
                            Integrated Operational Plan (<gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss>)
                            tasks against the Soviet Union. However, our flexibility to use
                            strategic bombers for conventional operations would be reduced.</p>
                        <p>All strategic bombers would continue to be included in the <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss>. They would continue to be targeted
                            against all categories of targets including urban industrial targets,
                            key military installations, and nuclear threat targets such as heavy and
                            medium bomber bases, command and control facilities, submarine bases,
                                <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss> sites, and hardened nuclear
                            storage sites. Our capability to execute the <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> would be decreased because of the lower force levels;
                            we would lose up to 240 (264 megatons) high-yield gravity weapons out of
                            about 2,000. Strategic bombers could be diverted to other than the
                                <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> commitment, but <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> effectiveness would be reduced if
                            this were done. The direct effect on the <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> would be a function of the size and the location of
                            the force that was diverted. For example, current support of Southeast
                            Asia causes <pb facs="0597" n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/> degradation of 20
                            alert (out of about 170) and 20 non-alert (out of about 280) B–52
                            sorties from Guam. These sorties are responsible for targets in
                            Communist China and North Korea. Elimination of these 40 sorties, with
                            no compensating retargeting, would result in 38 <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> targets (out of about 270 targets covered by bombers)
                            being completely uncovered.</p>
                        <p>The air defenses in the early 1970s would have approximately the same
                            capabilities as those described for the Austere option in Appendix A,
                            but the retention of 410, instead of 266, interceptors would provide
                            some additional confidence against light bomber attacks. In the mid to
                            late 1970s, the air defenses would have approximately the same
                            capabilities as the fourth or “Expanded” option in Appendix A, when the
                            Over-the-Horizon (OTH) radar<note n="16" xml:id="d152fn16">A radar
                                system that uses atmospheric reflection and refraction phenomena to
                                extend its range of detection beyond the line of sight.
                                Over-the-horizon (OTH) radars may be either forward scatter or back
                                scatter systems.</note> and <gloss target="#t_AWACS1">AWACS</gloss>
                            aircraft become operational.</p>
                        <p>d. <hi rend="italic">Reduced Program</hi>. Under this alternative, annual
                            outlays for strategic forces would be reduced by about $2 billion
                            (including related intelligence and <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> reductions) as compared with the current program.
                            There would be either a very light (seven-site) area defense system
                            against <gloss target="#t_ICBM1">ICBM</gloss>s or a four-site system
                            that could defend portions of four Minuteman fields. Alternately, if
                                <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> terminated installation of
                            Safeguard at Minuteman sites by 1 July 1971, a reinforced <gloss target="#t_NCA1">NCA</gloss> site complex could be installed by
                            mid-1978. If the seven-site light area defense of the country were
                            chosen, rather than the four-site system which could defend portions of
                            four Minuteman fields (or alternatively the <gloss target="#t_NCA1">NCA</gloss> and three Minuteman fields), it would be necessary to
                            cancel the Malmstrom site already authorized and underway and the
                            Whiteman site for which authorization is now being sought before
                            Congress. Also, it is unlikely that long leadtime funding for the
                            additional sites could be obtained until 1972 in light of Congressional
                            opposition to the concept of the area <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> defense. Under those conditions, the full operational
                            capability of the system could not be obtained until <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 80, at which time the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> could possibly have the missile
                            capability to penetrate such a defense.</p>
                        <p>The reduced program would not fully maintain the Triad concept, because
                            an independent retaliatory capability in the land-based missile force
                            would not be assured beyond the mid-1970s, and the number of bombers
                            would also be reduced. The capability of the land-based missile force
                            would be reduced in the mid to late 1970s as Minuteman survivability
                            against the estimated Soviet threat decreased. However, the capability
                            of the sea-based missile force would be increased as Poseidon <pb facs="0598" n="569" xml:id="pg_569"/> missiles with <gloss target="#t_MIRV1">MIRV</gloss>s were deployed. Thus, Soviet
                            incentives to concentrate on <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> would
                            be increased since a larger proportion of our overall surviving
                            capability would be in sea-based missiles. The reduced Minuteman
                            survivability would result in less damage-limiting capability, and there
                            would be reduced confidence that Soviet incentive to strike first was
                            sufficiently low. Our flexibility to use strategic bombers in
                            conventional conflicts while maintaining <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> alert would be severely reduced. Sufficient bombers
                            would be available for strategic attacks on China only by accepting a
                            temporary loss in capability against the Soviet Union. Simultaneous
                            attacks against the Soviet Union and the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> would have reduced coverage. If <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> funding were used for defense of Minuteman, the fourth
                                <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16 sufficiency criterion would
                            not be satisfied. The reduced air defenses would provide approximately
                            the same capabilities as described for the Austere option in Appendix A
                            in the early 1970s. In the mid to late 1970s the capabilities would be
                            essentially those described for the third or “Austere and OTH”
                            option.</p>
                        <p>All strategic bombers would continue to be included in the <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss>. They would continue to be targeted
                            against all categories of targets as under the Limited Reduction
                            Program. Our capability to support the <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> tasks will be affected because of the lower force
                            levels; we would lose 628 (690 megatons) high yield gravity weapons out
                            of about 2,000 in the total bomber force loading. In addition to this
                            permanent reduction of <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> weapons,
                            continued support of the war in Southeast Asia would create further
                            temporary <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> degradation. While
                            strategic bombers could be diverted to other than the <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> commitment, there would be a
                            resulting reduction in <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss>
                            effectiveness based on the size and the location of the force that was
                            diverted. In a crisis, we would be forced to execute the <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> with a reduced bomber contribution.
                            In addition to targets currently uncovered because of the diversion of
                            bombers to Southeast Asia, some additional targets requiring accurate
                            weapon delivery and some more non time-sensitive targets would be left
                            untargeted (e.g., nuclear storage sites and submarine bases).</p>
                        <p>Support of the war in Southeast Asia is currently being performed by
                            specially modified B–52 C–F aircraft. If the bomber force levels in the
                            Reduced Program were reached prior to the desired end of B–52 bombing in
                            Southeast Asia, we would have to use B–52 G/H aircraft to fly Arc Light
                            missions. This would necessitate modification of some of the B–52 G/H
                            aircraft. For example, at least 21 months would be required to modify 60
                            aircraft at a cost of $24 million.</p>
                        <p>e. <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>. The <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss> or Current Program would have no significant effect on
                                <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss>. The Limited Reduction Program
                            and the Reduced Program, with reductions in Safeguard and retirement of
                            Titan and some B–52s, might weaken our bargaining position, but the
                            reduced forces, <pb facs="0599" n="570" xml:id="pg_570"/> instead of
                            being destroyed, could be retained in non-operational status to mitigate
                            any adverse impacts. Alternatively, in order to minimize the effect of
                            strategic bomber reductions on the <gloss target="#t_US1">US</gloss>–<gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> negotiating
                            position, we could keep a force of about 500 bombers in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. To reduce costs, four bomber
                            squadrons could be deactivated and the 65 aircraft, together with
                            reduced ground and flight crews, could be redistributed from these units
                            to the remaining B–52 bases. There would be an attendant loss of 24 out
                            of about 170 <gloss target="#t_SIOP1">SIOP</gloss> day-to-day alert
                            sorties; however, in times of emergency, manning and basing would be
                            adequate to generate virtually all bomber aircraft to an alert status in
                            about 48 hours (compared to 24 hours with the current program). Such an
                            increased alert status could be maintained for short periods of up to 30
                            days. The <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 savings for this
                            alternative would be $0.2 billion, as compared with $0.3 billion for the
                            Limited Reduction Program or $0.4 billion for the Reduced Program.
                            Neither of the alternatives with strategic force reductions is based on
                            any presumption of a <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> agreement
                            which would cause an alteration in force planning. A <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> agreement, as contemplated by <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>s 69 and 73,<note n="17" xml:id="d152fn17">For the texts of <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 69, “Strategic Arms Limitation Talks,” July 10,
                                and <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss> 74, “Detailed Statement of
                                Provisions of <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> Position,” July 22, see <ref target="frus1969-76v32#d94"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume XXXII, <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> I, 1969–1972, Documents
                                    94</ref> and <ref target="frus1969-76v32#d100">100</ref>.</note>
                            could allow reductions in strategic forces beyond those in the Reduced
                            Program. As examples, if <gloss target="#t_ABM1">ABM</gloss> spending
                            were reduced to <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> only, <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 outlays could be reduced about $0.8
                            billion; if bombers were reduced by about 100 below the Reduced Program,
                                <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 outlays would be cut $0.3
                            billion. However, annual savings over the longer term cannot be
                            projected with certainty until a complete agreement is reached.</p>
                        <p>f. <hi rend="italic">Additional Considerations</hi>. If <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> strategic forces were reduced, the
                            Soviet Union might perceive itself to have achieved a position of
                            relative strategic advantage and, so believing, embark on even more
                            aggressive courses of action. On the other hand, the Soviets might be
                            satisfied with a rough strategic balance, and <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> reductions could provide them with the opportunity to
                            devote a greater share of their economic resources to priority
                            non-defense programs or to general purpose defense programs.</p>
                        <p>If the planned Safeguard program were reduced to a four-site defense of
                            Minuteman under the Reduced Program, it would not be possible to meet
                            the fourth <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16 sufficiency
                            criterion. Such action would deprive us of the added flexibility in
                            crises involving a Chinese nuclear threat, which is one of the major
                            purposes of the Safeguard program.</p>
                        <p>While we currently maintain sufficient forces to provide an independent
                            retaliatory capability in each of three offensive force components <pb facs="0600" n="571" xml:id="pg_571"/> (the Triad concept),
                            reductions in strategic forces would make it unlikely that an
                            independent retaliatory capability could be maintained in the Minuteman
                            force. A more vulnerable Minuteman force could increase the Soviet’s
                            incentive to strike first and possibly violate the second <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–16 sufficiency criterion.</p>
                        <p>The reduced strategic defensive force levels in the Limited Reduction and
                            Reduced Programs would require coordination with the Canadian
                            Government. Diplomatic efforts would be needed to preserve Canada’s
                            participation in the air defense of North America.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">General Purpose Force Alternatives</hi></p>
                        <p>The general purpose forces required to meet the broad goals described in
                                <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 are subject to
                            uncertainties concerning the size and quality of the threat, the
                            availability and quality of allied forces, and the performance of our
                            own forces. There are also varying views concerning the specific
                            interpretation to be placed on the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 goals and the degree of risk acceptable in implementing
                            them. Table 6<note n="18" xml:id="d152fn18">Attached but not printed is
                                Table 6, entitled “Range of <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                                Force Requirements in Mid-1970s.”</note> shows a range of force
                            requirements for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, for the Pacific
                            against the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss>, and for minor
                            contingencies. The higher forces are those recommended by the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> for meeting the requirements of <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 with a prudent level of risk.
                            Moving toward the lower levels introduces additional risk by making
                            favorable assumptions for some of the following issues: <list>
                                <label>(1)</label>
                                <item>Whether French forces are included with <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> forces.</item>
                                <label>(2)</label>
                                <item>Whether forces are sized to give a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> commander confidence of defeating the Pact or
                                    sized to match capabilities, giving neither side assurance of
                                    success, and perhaps deterring the Pact from initiating military
                                    actions.</item>
                                <label>(3)</label>
                                <item>Whether allied air <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> forces
                                    can be relied upon for area <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss>.
                                    In all cases, allied escorts must be relied upon for convoy
                                    protection during the first month of a war.</item>
                                <label>(4)</label>
                                <item>The percentage of <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>
                                    tactical aircraft assumed active in a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> war.</item>
                                <label>(5)</label>
                                <item>The size of the enemy force that can be sustained in
                                    combat.</item>
                                <label>(6)</label>
                                <item>The quantity of tactical aircraft allocated for deep
                                    interdiction missions.</item>
                                <label>(7)</label>
                                <item>The relative quality of <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                                    and enemy forces.</item>
                                <label>(8)</label>
                                <item>The capabilities of allied forces.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The land forces, tactical air forces, and naval forces which support
                            sea-based tactical air forces shown in Table 6 for different theaters
                            will not add to give total forces because simultaneity is not assumed.
                            For other naval forces, a war with the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> would probably be a two ocean war, and area <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> forces and escorts must be provided for
                            both the <pb facs="0601" n="572" xml:id="pg_572"/> Atlantic and Pacific.
                            On the other hand, an Asian conflict with the Chinese would have little
                            impact on the naval balance between the Atlantic and Pacific. Therefore,
                            these naval forces are displayed as allocated between Atlantic and
                            Pacific in a ratio of 2 to 1.</p>
                        <p>Table 7<note n="19" xml:id="d152fn19">Attached but not printed is Table
                                7, entitled “<gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Forces Available in
                                Mid-1970s To Meet Requirements Under Alternative Illustrative
                                Programs.”</note> compares the capability of the forces in each of
                            the five alternative general purpose force programs described below to
                            the requirements shown in Table 6. In Table 7, the columns headed <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> show for each alternative the force
                            levels that can be deployed to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            within 90 days, while simultaneously retaining peacetime deployments in
                            the Pacific and withholding the forces shown for Minor Contingencies and
                            Strategic Reserve. The columns headed Pacific show the maximum
                            deployments possible to a war with the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> in Korea or Southeast Asia while retaining the
                            capability to reinforce <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>In the reduced force alternatives, older <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> escorts would be retired in numbers consistent with the
                            reductions in aircraft carriers needing protection. The reduced programs
                            would continue to rely on allied, <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                            naval reserve, and Coast Guard escorts for convoys. The <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss>, current planning, and all reduced
                            programs provide escorts for naval forces (e.g., aircraft carriers,
                            amphibious groups, and underway replenishment ships), but do not provide
                            active escorts for military or economic support shipping. Thus, the
                            escort force levels shown in the reduced force alternatives represent no
                            change in force planning factors from previous plans, but the resulting
                            escort levels provide less flexibility in meeting possible requirements
                            of the strategy.</p>
                        <p>Each of the alternatives for reduced forces would retire <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> aircraft carriers. However, using
                                <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> aircraft on <gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss>s could restore <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> capability lost with the <gloss target="#t_CVS1">CVS</gloss> reductions. There would, however, be displacement of
                            tactical aircraft by <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> aircraft on
                                <gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss>s and a resultant reduction in
                            sea-based tactical air capability. Currently, because of the limitations
                            of the S–2 <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> aircraft, <gloss target="#t_CVS1">CVS</gloss>s are only marginally effective for
                                <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss>. None of the illustrative
                            reductions described below would alter our planning for nuclear
                            submarines. The Reduced and Low <gloss target="#t_GPF1">GPF</gloss>
                            options would reduce land-based patrol aircraft about 10%.</p>
                        <p>Since <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71 is a year of transition,
                            decisions for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 should set the basis
                            for our plans for the 1970s. In addition to defense budget issues, it is
                            important to consider the possibility of changes to to the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 strategy guidance. All of the
                            alternative general purpose forces considered below are based on
                            attempting to satisfy the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27
                            strategy and are evaluated with respect to their ability to meet it. It
                            would be possible, however, to consider different degrees of <pb facs="0602" n="573" xml:id="pg_573"/> emphasis on various force
                            components and to develop different general purpose programs at the same
                            budget levels, with or without changes in the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 strategy. Trades between tactical air forces, naval
                            forces, and land forces could be made, as well as trades between
                            strategic and general purpose forces, as discussed in the previous
                            section. For example, a roughly equal cost trade would be one Army
                            division with its associated initial support increments for one-third of
                            an amphibious task group or three Air Force F–4 wings. Moreover, as is
                            discussed later, trades could be made between expensive procurement
                            programs and the retention of additional forces with less expensive
                            modernization programs. Thus, all the alternatives discussed below
                            should be considered only illustrative; other mixes of forces could be
                            developed at the same budget levels.</p>
                        <p>The following table summarizes the five illustrative forces considered in
                            the next section, and for comparison, the end-<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 70 forces:</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 8</p>
                        <p rend="center">Comparison of Illustrative General Purpose Forces<note n="20" xml:id="d152fn20">Out-year objectives. In most cases these
                                force levels would be obtained by end-<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. [Footnote in the original.]</note></p>
                        <table cols="7" rows="14">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">End <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                        70</hi></cell>
                                <cell><gloss target="#t_JSOP1"><hi rend="italic">JSOP</hi></gloss></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Current Program</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Limited Reduction Program</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Reduced Program</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Low Program</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">General Purpose Forces</hi></cell>
                                <cell cols="6"/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em">Active Divisions</cell>
                                <cell role="num">20⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">19⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">16⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">16⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">16⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">14⅓</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em">Total Divisions</cell>
                                <cell role="num">29⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">28⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">25⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">25⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">25⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">23⅓</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em">Fighter Attack Aircraft<note n="21" xml:id="d152fn21">Includes active and reserve. [Footnote in
                                        the original.]</note></cell>
                                <cell role="num">5,800</cell>
                                <cell role="num">6,100</cell>
                                <cell role="num">5,300</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4,900</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4,400</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4,100</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em"><gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss>s/<gloss target="#t_CVS1">CVS</gloss>s</cell>
                                <cell role="num">15/4</cell>
                                <cell role="num">16/8</cell>
                                <cell role="num">13/4</cell>
                                <cell role="num">14<note n="22" xml:id="d152fn22">Total carriers;
                                        the mix of <gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss>s and <gloss target="#t_CVS1">CVS</gloss>s to be determined; four
                                            <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> air groups would be
                                        retained, possibly operating from <gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss>s. [Footnote in the original.]</note></cell>
                                <cell role="num">12</cell>
                                <cell role="num">12</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em">Escorts</cell>
                                <cell role="num">240</cell>
                                <cell role="num">265</cell>
                                <cell role="num">204</cell>
                                <cell role="num">172</cell>
                                <cell role="num">169</cell>
                                <cell role="num">169</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em">Amphibious Task Forces</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1⅔</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1⅓</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em">C–5A</cell>
                                <cell role="num">20</cell>
                                <cell role="num">111</cell>
                                <cell role="num">78</cell>
                                <cell role="num">78</cell>
                                <cell role="num">78</cell>
                                <cell role="num">78</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em">C–141</cell>
                                <cell role="num">275</cell>
                                <cell role="num">275</cell>
                                <cell role="num">275</cell>
                                <cell role="num">275</cell>
                                <cell role="num">275</cell>
                                <cell role="num">195</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Cost of General Purpose Forces</hi><note n="23" xml:id="d152fn23">Cost in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 $ billions. Includes incremental cost of
                                        the war in Southeast Asia, as shown in Table 4. [Footnote in
                                        the original.]</note></cell>
                                <cell cols="6"/>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    72 Outlays</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">$58</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$49</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$47</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$46</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$44</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    76 Outlays</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">55</cell>
                                <cell role="num">42</cell>
                                <cell role="num">39</cell>
                                <cell role="num">36</cell>
                                <cell role="num">32</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell rend="padding-left: 1.5em">Average Annual Outlays (<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72–76)</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">55</cell>
                                <cell role="num">43</cell>
                                <cell role="num">41</cell>
                                <cell role="num">37</cell>
                                <cell role="num">35</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <pb facs="0603" n="574" xml:id="pg_574"/>
                        <p>a. <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> Recommended
                                Objective Program</hi>. This alternative (<gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss>) was developed by the <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> in consideration of the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 strategy guidance with no fiscal restraints. It
                            represents their view of a prudent level of risk, and the general
                            purpose forces, including the cost of the war in Southeast Asia, would
                            cost about $58 billion in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. Of the
                            total divisions, 16 are active Army and 3 are active Marine divisions,
                            and there are 26 Air Force, 16 Navy, and 3 Marine tactical fighter
                            wings. With these force levels, the higher range of requirements shown
                            in Table 6 could be met for all theaters, but not simultaneously. <gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss> deployments and commitments could
                            remain at current levels, as could the commitment of Navy ships to
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>b. <hi rend="italic">Current Program</hi>. This alternative was developed
                            under fiscal guidance consistent with <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 and would cost about $49 billion in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. Compared to the <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss>, this alternative would have three
                            fewer Navy carrier wings and three fewer Air Force fighter attack wings.
                            Peacetime forward deployments would be reduced by one wing in both
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and the Pacific. <gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss> deployments to Southeast Asia would be
                            reduced by one (as is currently planned), and the commitment of Navy
                            ships to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> would have to be reduced
                            somewhat. Compared to the <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss>, the
                            Current Program would involve increased levels of risk in meeting the
                                <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 strategy because of the
                            reduced levels of active forces and increased reliance on strategic
                            warning, an earlier decision to mobilize, and reserve readiness. With
                            the forces in this alternative, a total of 16 divisions (14 Army and 2
                            Marine) and 31 tactical fighter attack wings (six on <gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss>s) could be deployed to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> within 90 days, compared to the
                            ranges of 14 to 17 divisions and 27 to 42 tactical fighter attack wings,
                            shown as requirements in Table 6. With regard to Pacific areas, the high
                            side of the requirements range could be met for all but naval forces,
                            which would exceed the low side of the range of requirements, causing
                            increased risk. As in the <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss>, active
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                            <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> escorts would be sufficient for
                            meeting only naval forces escort requirements.</p>
                        <p>c. <hi rend="italic">Limited Reduction Program</hi>. This program would
                            reduce general purpose forces by about $2.3 billion annually from the
                            Current Program. With the reduction in amphibious task forces, a
                            division-sized amphibious assault capability would be lost in one
                            theater. (There would be a one-brigade assault capability in the
                            Atlantic and a two-brigade capability in the Pacific, with a “swing” of
                            one brigade between oceans being possible within about 30 days.) Changes
                            in current deployments would be the same as for the Current Program. In
                            addition to planned land force reductions in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>, one division would withdraw from Korea in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71 and two-thirds in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 73 (one brigade would be left), and one
                            attack carrier would withdraw from Southeast Asia in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71.</p>
                        <p>The general purpose forces in the Limited Reduction Program would be
                            sufficient to meet the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27
                            strategy, but at greater risk than in the Current Program. Two fewer
                            fighter attack wings could be <pb facs="0604" n="575" xml:id="pg_575"/>
                            deployed to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> or the Pacific by M+90
                            than under the Current Program, but capabilities would still be greater
                            than the low side of the range of requirements in Table 6 (with
                            acceptance of risks and favorable assumptions previously discussed)
                            except for Navy escorts. This alternative maintains <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> modernization programs at the expense
                            of retiring older, less capable <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss>
                            forces. This would result in a degraded <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> capability, especially during the early 1970s. The
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> force would have a marginal
                            capability to contain the Soviet submarine threat in the Atlantic; sea
                            lines of communication in the Pacific might be exposed during a <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> war. As in the current program, full
                            reliance would have to be placed on some 315 allied, 35 naval reserve,
                            and 15 Coast Guard escorts for point defense of convoys (<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Allies have about 225 escorts,
                            Pacific Allies about 90).</p>
                        <p>d. <hi rend="italic">Reduced Program</hi>. This program would make a $3
                            billion annual reduction in outlays for general purpose forces. Support
                            and modernization levels for the forces would also be reduced relative
                            to the Limited Reduction Program. Forward deployments would be the same
                            as in the Limited Reduction Program, with the exception of a decrease of
                            one more tactical air wing for the Pacific and one more in Europe. Both
                            reductions would not have to be made in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72, but it would be desirable to do so.</p>
                        <p>This program would involve more risk than the Limited Reduction Program,
                            but capabilities for <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and Asian
                            conflicts would exceed the low side of the requirements range in Table 6
                            (with acceptance of risk and favorable assumptions previously discussed)
                            except for the capability to deploy one additional air wing. The <gloss target="#t_ASW1">ASW</gloss> escort level would involve about the
                            same level of risk as in the Current Program. As in the Limited
                            Reduction Program, full reliance would have to be placed on allied,
                            naval reserve, and Coast Guard escorts for point defense of convoys.</p>
                        <p>e. <hi rend="italic">Low Program</hi>. This program would result in an
                            annual $5 billion reduction in outlays for general purpose forces. It
                            would be desirable to accelerate the withdrawal of the ⅔ division from
                            Korea to <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 instead of <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 73. These reductions would make it
                            desirable to change the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27
                            strategy by reducing forces available for deployment to Asia, because
                            the extremely heavy reliance upon strategic warning, coupled with severe
                            reductions in forces, would provide no flexibility of response except at
                            the expense of a marginal <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> initial
                            defense posture. This change could be consistent with the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine only if our Asian Allies
                            develop their self-defense capability at an accelerated rate.</p>
                        <p>f. <hi rend="italic">Additional Considerations</hi>. The five general
                            purpose forces programs discussed above reflect a progressive
                            degradation of capability in meeting elements of the approved strategy.
                            Compared to the <gloss target="#t_JSOP1">JSOP</gloss> program, which the
                                <gloss target="#t_JCS1">JCS</gloss> designed to provide the
                            capability of meeting all elements of the strategy at a prudent level of
                            risk, the Current <pb facs="0605" n="576" xml:id="pg_576"/> Program and
                            Limited Reduction should meet the various strategy elements with some
                            increased risk, primarily involving reliance on strategic warning, an
                            early decision to mobilize, and on reserve readiness. These plans call
                            for greater reliance on ready reserves in the 1970s than in the 1960s.
                            Yet it may be difficult to maintain even current levels of reserve
                            readiness as we move toward a Volunteer Service, since the draft is a
                            major stimulus to participation in the reserves. The Reduced Program
                            would involve increased risks, particularly for tactical air and naval
                            forces, but also for land forces, as support and modernization would be
                            curtailed significantly. While the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 strategy could be supported under the Reduced Program
                            at substantial risk, it probably could not be supported under the Low
                            Program, since our potential future commitment of forces to Asia would
                            have to be reduced.</p>
                        <p>Force modernization would be progressively reduced with decreased funding
                            for general purpose forces. At the Reduced Program level, many
                            modernization programs previously delayed as a result of Southeast Asia
                            funding would be eliminated. On the other hand, many high cost
                            modernization programs are included in all alternatives, although they
                            are slipped or reduced in some cases. For example, the B–1, <gloss target="#t_ULMS1">ULMS</gloss>, DD–963, S–3A, F–14, and F–15 are
                            included in all alternatives. It would be possible at equal cost to
                            replace some of these programs with less costly ones to retain more
                            operational forces. For example, if the DD–963 and <gloss target="#t_DLGN1">DLGN</gloss> programs were replaced with less
                            expensive destroyer and missile escort programs, it would be possible to
                            retain one more active Army division or two to three more F–4 fighter
                            attack wings. We could keep such additional forces at the expense of
                            adopting more austere procurement programs under any budget level, but
                            there would be the potential increased risk in the performance of the
                            less expensive systems against the Soviets.</p>
                        <p>As the total general purpose forces are reduced, our ability to maintain
                            overseas deployments would be degraded. Major end-<gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 70 deployments and <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72
                            changes thereto that would be necessary under the various general
                            purpose force alternatives are shown in the following table. In addition
                            to these changes, an additional two-thirds of a division would be
                            withdrawn from Korea in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 73 under all
                            cases except the Low Program, where it would come out in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72.</p>
                        <p>It should be noted that large sections of the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>–Warsaw Pact front are manned by our allies, and not by
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> forces. Currently these allied
                            forces are not adequate in size, nor adequately equipped, to defend
                            conventionally against a Warsaw Pact offensive for 90 days. In
                            considering <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> force levels in Europe,
                            it should therefore be emphasized that the outcome is greatly dependent
                            on our allies’ performance and is not solely dependent upon the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> force structure. Another consideration
                            for <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> force planning is that since the
                            opening weeks of a <pb facs="0606" n="577" xml:id="pg_577"/> war in
                            Europe would be critical, forward deployed forces are much more
                            important than long-term reinforcement capability.</p>
                        <p>Reductions in overall force posture and forward deployments could lead
                            potential aggressors to conclude that they could pursue their objectives
                            with less risk, thereby leading to more aggressive foreign policies and
                            hostile initiatives. Rapid and precipitous reductions in deployment
                            might preclude orderly and fruitful consultation with allies.</p>
                        <p>Our commitments of naval and tactical air forces to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> would have to be changed under the
                            various reduced programs, as is shown in Table 9 on page 20. The
                            reductions in the commitments of naval forces would be politically
                            significant, since they would continue the series of reductions in
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> committed forces that have
                            been going on for the last two years. The change in commitment of
                            tactical air forces under the Low Program would also cause concern on
                            the part of our allies about our ability to support the current <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> strategy.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here are Table 9, “Illustrative General Purpose Force
                            Deployments in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72,” and Table 10,
                                “<gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Defense Planning
                            Questionnaire (<gloss target="#t_DPQ1">DPQ</gloss>) Commitments and
                            Changes That Would Be Required As Result of Reduced Programs.”]</p>
                        <p>In general, the force reductions included in the Current Program should
                            present no unmanageable foreign policy problems. The reductions in
                            deployments included for the Low Program would present more serious
                            political problems. The cut in Korean-based forces, if accelerated as
                            shown, could cause the Asian Allies to have misgivings about the
                                <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine and its
                            implementation. The cuts in the Low Program, particularly if combined
                            with major strategic force cuts, could undermine Japanese confidence in
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> security guarantees and cause a
                            change in the direction of Japanese security planning. On the other
                            hand, some believe that American force cutbacks have been anticipated
                            and probably discounted by our allies and our potential opponents alike
                            for some time.</p>
                        <p>g. <hi rend="italic">Other Mission Changes</hi>. All of the illustrative
                            reduction options include changes in other defense missions, such as
                            intelligence, communications, and research and development. The combined
                            $7 billion reduction of reduced strategic forces and low general purpose
                            forces includes a $0.6 billion cut in other missions. The reduction in
                            intelligence programs would cut only marginal programs, but it would
                            thereby reduce flexibility to respond to new requirements. The
                            reductions in research and development would hold the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 level about even with that for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71. Some believe that reduced programs
                            could require increased intelligence programs, because the reduced
                            programs plan increased reliance on strategic warning. Similarly, it
                            could be necessary to expand <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss>
                            efforts to provide hedges against the decreased capabilities in the
                            reduced programs.</p>
                        <pb facs="0607" n="578" xml:id="pg_578"/>
                        <p>h. <hi rend="italic">Support to Other Nations</hi>. The <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine relies on increases in
                            support for our allies as a partial substitute for <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> forces. This Support to Other Nations
                            includes the Military Assistance Program (including Foreign Military
                            Credit Sales) funding in the <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> budget
                            for procurement of war reserve stocks for our allies, and on-going
                            combat support of allied forces in <gloss target="#t_SEA1">SEA</gloss>.
                            All alternatives provide for continued support of South Vietnamese
                            combat forces at declining levels of activity through the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72–76 period ($2.6<gloss target="#t_B1">B</gloss> in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 declining to
                                $1.1<gloss target="#t_B1">B</gloss> by <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 75–76). All alternatives provide <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss>/FMCS at $1.0–1.1<gloss target="#t_B1">B</gloss> per
                            year ($0.3–0.4 above <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 70–71 levels) and
                            a total of approximately $2<gloss target="#t_B1">B</gloss> in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 73–76 for building war reserve stocks of
                            ammunition and equipment for <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> allies.
                            Given current Congressional attitudes and problems with Support to Other
                            Nations authorizations, it may prove difficult to win Congressional
                            authorization for these increases.</p>
                        <p>B. <hi rend="italic">Total Defense Program Alternatives</hi></p>
                        <p>Table 10A shows alternative defense budgets and alternative combinations
                            of strategic and general purpose forces programs. The reductions shown
                            for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 are from the current defense
                            budget projections in Table 3. Table 11 summarizes illustrative force
                            changes and other impacts associated with each of the strategic and
                            general purpose forces illustrative alternatives discussed above. The
                            impacts of any case in Table 10A can be determined by referring to the
                            appropriate sections of Table 11. For example, Case D2 is described by
                            the right column of Strategic Forces and the next to the last column of
                            General Purpose Forces. For all cases in Table 10A, reducing the
                            Safeguard program to research and development only would produce an
                            additional $0.8 billion reduction in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                            72 (an $11.5 billion reduction in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                            72–80). An additional $0.4–1.4 billion reduction could be obtained by
                            deferring the Volunteer Service.</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 10A</p>
                        <p rend="center">Alternative <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> Programs
                            and Budgets</p>
                        <table cols="4" rows="9">
                            <row>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Case</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Strategic Forces Programs</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">General Purpose Forces Programs</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Budget Changes from Current
                                        Planning</hi><note n="24" xml:id="d152fn24">Includes
                                        appropriate changes to support programs and Other Mission
                                        Programs (such as intelligence and research and
                                        development). [Footnote in the
                                    original.]</note><lb/>(Outlays in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 $ Billions)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>A</cell>
                                <cell>Current</cell>
                                <cell>Current</cell>
                                <cell role="num">0</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>B1</cell>
                                <cell>Reduced</cell>
                                <cell>Current</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>B2</cell>
                                <cell>Current</cell>
                                <cell>Reduced</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–3</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>C</cell>
                                <cell>Limited</cell>
                                <cell>Limited</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–3</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Reductions</cell>
                                <cell>Reductions</cell>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <pb facs="0608" n="579" xml:id="pg_579"/>
                            <row>
                                <cell>D1</cell>
                                <cell>Current</cell>
                                <cell>Low</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–5</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>D2</cell>
                                <cell>Reduced</cell>
                                <cell>Reduced</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–5</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>E</cell>
                                <cell>Reduced</cell>
                                <cell>Low</cell>
                                <cell role="num">–7</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">C. Evaluation of National Security
                                Impact and Possible Effects of Defense Programs</hi></p>
                        <p>Decisions regarding <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> strategic and
                            general purpose force levels must be made in the context of national
                            security interests and commitments and the possible effects various
                            defense programs would have. In the past decade the strategic balance
                            between the United States and the Soviet Union has shifted from one of
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> nuclear superiority to one of
                            nuclear parity. Some believe the Soviets will attempt to achieve nuclear
                            superiority. Whereas a decade ago the strategic balance appeared to
                            constitute a real constraint on the Soviets, these advantages may no
                            longer pertain in the future. Despite <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> nuclear superiority, the United States has assumed for
                            at least eight years that the Soviets have a strong second-strike
                            capability. Thus, Soviet advances leading to rough numerical parity may
                            not change the impacts of this long-held assumption.</p>
                        <p>It is within this broader context that the preceding illustrative
                            reductions between <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 70 and <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 of up to 25% in active divisions, 25%
                            in carrier decks, 20%–25% in fighter attack aircraft, 35% in strategic
                            bombers, and 50% in air defense fighters must be weighed. Some believe
                            that our potential adversaries, under economic pressures substantially
                            like those which confront the United States, would use <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> force reductions to justify comparable
                            reductions in their armament investments. Others hold that our
                            adversaries would see in <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> defense
                            program reductions an opportunity to acquire military advantages and
                            greater freedom for political initiatives.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here is Table 11, “Comparison of Illustrative Forces and
                            Implications on Strategy and Commitments.”]</p>
                        <p>Any major changes in <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> force levels
                            will be visible to allies and enemies alike. The chance will exist that
                            our capabilities, intentions, and resolve might be misinterpreted.
                            Reductions in <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> military forces will
                            be used by factions within the Soviet Union and elsewhere to argue for
                            further testing of our abilities and commitments to our allies.
                            Historical precedents, such as Berlin—1948, Korea—1950, Berlin—1961,
                            Cuba—1962, and Vietnam—1961–1965, suggest that Communist aggression may
                            be induced, in part, by reduced <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                            force levels. At the times of the Berlin and Cuban missile crises, the
                            Soviets apparently perceived the United States as having the capability
                            to pre-empt their strategic weapons, which may have been the major
                            factor in their decisions not to escalate those crises further. Since
                            the Soviets now have rough strategic parity with the United States, the
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> strategic forces could form less
                            of a deterrent to Soviet escalation in a crisis. We may <pb facs="0609" n="580" xml:id="pg_580"/> therefore be more dependent on our general
                            purpose forces to handle crisis situations.</p>
                        <p>The <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine calls for
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> allies to assume a greater
                            burden of their defense, particularly with respect to ground forces.
                            Thus, reductions in <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> forces do not
                            necessarily reduce total free-world capabilities if our allies increase
                            their own capabilities and strengthen regional security arrangements.
                            There are, however, major political barriers to substantial increases in
                            the military forces and budgets of our <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Allies. Increases in allied capability in Asia will be
                            dependent, for at least several years, on increased <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> materiel support.</p>
                        <p>Our allies already have considerable capability as indicated below. They
                            generally, however, spend a lesser share of <gloss target="#t_GNP1">GNP</gloss> on defense than does the United States. Thus,
                            consideration can be given to increased allied defense spending,
                            especially with <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> assistance, and at
                            least the question of what is the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                            and allied fair share of defense should be raised.</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 12</p>
                        <p rend="center">Selected <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> and Allied
                            Defense Forces</p>
                        <table cols="5" rows="7">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><gloss target="#t_US1">U.S</gloss><note n="25" xml:id="d152fn25">Based on current planning for <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 73. [Footnote in the
                                        original.]</note></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Other <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss></hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">Japan</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic">S. Korea</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Ground Forces, Active Manpower</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">1,000,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">200,000</cell>
                                <cell role="num">600,000</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Fighter/Attack Aircraft</cell>
                                <cell role="num">5,200</cell>
                                <cell role="num">2,500</cell>
                                <cell role="num">400</cell>
                                <cell role="num">230</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Naval Escorts</cell>
                                <cell role="num">200</cell>
                                <cell role="num">232</cell>
                                <cell role="num">35</cell>
                                <cell role="num">6</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Submarines</cell>
                                <cell role="num">85</cell>
                                <cell role="num">119</cell>
                                <cell role="num">10</cell>
                                <cell role="num">—</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Defense Exp. as % of <gloss target="#t_GNP1">GNP</gloss></cell>
                                <cell role="num">6.5%</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4.5%</cell>
                                <cell role="num">0.9%</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4.0%</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Defense Exp. per Capita</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$380</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$78</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$11</cell>
                                <cell role="num">$6</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>It has been suggested that reduced conventional forces for defense of
                            Europe are made more acceptable by the fact that we can, if necessary,
                            fall back on tactical nuclear weapons for European defense. For the past
                            decade, we have maintained forces designed to avoid primary reliance on
                            tactical nuclear weapons against the more likely conventional threats in
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. We would continue to do so
                            under the Reduced or Low Programs considered in this paper. (Against the
                            unlikely threat of mobilization by the Pact with no corresponding <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> mobilization, our conventional forces
                            would be inadequate to prevent the Pact from making a deep penetration
                            into Western Europe, but nuclear weapons would not be likely to provide
                            a more favorable outcome.) We maintain tactical nuclear forces primarily
                            to deter the Pact from starting a nuclear conflict and to cause them to
                            be uncertain as <pb facs="0610" n="581" xml:id="pg_581"/> to our
                            response if they mount any type of aggression. Thus, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>’s nuclear forces assist in preventing
                            the Pact from making a confident assessment that they could achieve a
                            favorable outcome in any conflict, even one that started with only
                            conventional weapons. Our nuclear forces also provide a capability to
                            engage in a nuclear conflict and destroy Pact forces if deterrence
                            fails. Reliance on tactical nuclear forces in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Europe for waging war (as opposed to deterring war)
                            would provide little assurance that the ultimate war outcome would be
                            favorable to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>. Both sides have
                            significant inventories of survivable tactical nuclear weapons. An
                            exchange would result in heavy destruction to both sides, with the
                            ultimate outcome highly uncertain. The military and civilian losses in a
                            tactical nuclear exchange are likely to be considerably larger than in
                            conventional conflict. Therefore, such a strategy would not lead to
                            reductions in conventional force requirements.</p>
                        <p>In Asia, our long-range plans call for the Asian Allies to develop more
                            effective armed forces and alliances for self-defense. Our experiences
                            in Korea and Vietnam show that it takes years of steady effort and a
                            reasonable degree of security to achieve a self-defense capability. A
                            deliberate plan of phased reductions with reserve capability to respond
                            to crises, coupled with extensive diplomatic efforts and <gloss target="#t_MAP1">MAP</gloss> programs, is essential to effective
                            implementation of the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                            Doctrine in Asia.</p>
                        <p>We have also maintained forces designed to avoid reliance on the use of
                            nuclear weapons to counter the more likely conventional threats in Asia.
                            Such a policy could be continued under the Current Program or the
                            Reduced Program. (In the event of concurrent major <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> and Soviet aggression, which the <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27 guidance does not provide for,
                            adequate conventional forces would not be available in Asia.) The more
                            likely threats in Asia, with the exception of Korea, have been and
                            continue to be insurgencies rather than large overt attacks with a
                            relatively well defined battle line. Against such threats, nuclear
                            weapons would have limited tactical utility at best. Tactical nuclear
                            forces are maintained primarily to deter the use of nuclear weapons by
                            the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> and to cause them to be
                            uncertain as to our response if they mount any type of large overt
                            attack. Thus, our nuclear forces oriented toward Asia assist in
                            preventing Asian communists from making a confident assessment that they
                            could be successful in an overt attack. Such forces also provide a
                            capability to counter Asian communist aggression if deterrence
                            fails.</p>
                        <p>The issue arises whether tactical nuclear powers (as opposed to a major
                            strategic nuclear strike) would provide an adequate hedge or option
                            against the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> in cases where general
                            purpose forces appear insufficient. As the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> develops its nuclear weapons and delivery <pb facs="0611" n="582" xml:id="pg_582"/> capabilities (IR/<gloss target="#t_MRBM1">MRBM</gloss>s in particular) such a strategy
                            becomes increasingly less attractive. Because of the concentration of
                                <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> forces and the difficulties of
                            support and supply, a tactical nuclear campaign in Korea or Southeast
                            Asia against the <gloss target="#t_CPR1">CPR</gloss> when it has the
                            ability to retaliate is not likely to be to <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> advantage. Such a situation should exist by the the
                            mid-1970s at the latest. Thus, while reliance on tactical nuclear
                            weapons might appear to be an attractive alternative to modifying our
                            Asian strategy (e.g., by redefining potential lines of defense) when
                            conventional forces appear to be inadequate, tactical nuclear forces
                            actually are not a reasonable alternative for conventional defenses.
                            Thus, under the Low Program it would be more appropriate to modify the
                            strategy rather than rely on tactical nuclear forces.</p>
                        <p rend="flushleft"><hi rend="italic">D. Transition Problems</hi></p>
                        <p>The problems of transition to lower defense budgets and force levels fall
                            into two categories, those relating to foreign policy and relations with
                            our allies and those relating to the management of reductions within
                                <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss>. As discussed below, there will
                            be serious transition problems in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71
                            and <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 even if the defense budget is
                            maintained at current planning levels. During this period, we are
                            already planning major reductions in defense programs for two reasons:
                            (1) we plan reduced activity in Southeast Asia, and (2) we are reducing
                            our post-war baseline forces in keeping with the strategy and budgets in
                                <gloss target="#t_NSDM1">NSDM</gloss>–27. Further reductions will
                            magnify these already serious transition problems. The severity of the
                            transition problems will depend on the extent of the reduction and the
                            lead-time available for phasing. The most critical aspect of the
                            transition problem is timing. To make large reductions, action must
                            start soon to minimize management problems within the Defense Department
                            and to allow time to explain strategy and force changes to both Congress
                            and foreign governments to maintain their confidence in Administration
                            policies.</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Foreign Policy Considerations</hi></p>
                        <p>The possible adverse effect on <gloss target="#t_SALT1">SALT</gloss> of
                            reductions in strategic forces prior to any agreement has been discussed
                            earlier. Also mentioned earlier was the need for a deliberate transition
                            plan, coordinating our planned force and deployment changes with
                            diplomatic efforts to preserve the confidence of the allies in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>’s continuing effectiveness and to
                            induce the allies to make compensating increases in their commitments to
                            match our reductions.</p>
                        <p>Vietnamization is a keystone in the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Doctrine. But flexibility to slow or stop
                            currently planned reductions in activity levels to meet unexpected
                            developments in Southeast Asia is severely constrained at defense
                            budgets $6 billion below the currently planned level. The force <pb facs="0612" n="583" xml:id="pg_583"/> reductions shown for the
                            reduced and low general purpose force levels depend on meeting the
                            currently programmed schedule of withdrawals from Southeast Asia (see
                            Table 4). For example, the higher levels of Vietnam activity cited on
                            page 5 would cost a total of $1 billion. Offsetting such an increase
                            within the defense budget would require additional force or procurement
                            reductions, such as inactivation of a <gloss target="#t_CONUS1">CONUS</gloss> division committed to <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> ($500 million), retirement of two <gloss target="#t_CVA1">CVA</gloss>s ($200 million), and cancellation or
                            deferral of major procurement such as nuclear frigates and the B–1
                            bomber. Thus, at reductions as large as $6 billion, the President’s
                            options to slow programmed cuts in Vietnam force and activity levels
                            would be sharply limited, unless he were willing to accept substantial
                            reductions in our capability to reinforce <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> Personnel
                                Management Problems</hi></p>
                        <p>To bring about a $6 billion reduction in the defense program in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72, it would be necessary to reduce
                            defense manpower levels by over 700,000 during <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71 and another 500,000 during <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 (see Table 13). This total reduction of 1,200,000
                            personnel in two years is about 500,000 more than would be necessary
                            under current planning. It may not be possible to reduce manpower this
                            rapidly. If this were so, for each 100,000 reduction not made by the end
                            of <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71, an additional $1 billion of
                            procurement and <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> budget authority
                            would have to be cut to reach the <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72
                            outlay target.</p>
                        <p rend="center">TABLE 13</p>
                        <p rend="center">Total <gloss target="#t_DOD1">DOD</gloss> Manpower</p>
                        <p rend="center">(Millions at End Year)</p>
                        <table cols="5" rend="width: 70%" rendition="#center-block" rows="3">
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    69</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    70</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    71</hi></cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                    72</hi></cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Current plans</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4.9</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4.4</cell>
                                <cell role="num">4.0</cell>
                                <cell role="num">3.7</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>$6 billion reduction</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell role="num">4.4</cell>
                                <cell role="num">3.7</cell>
                                <cell role="num">3.2</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>These large and rapid reductions would cause a number of serious problems
                            which would affect the attractiveness of military careers, and would
                            make it more difficult to attract and retain career personnel. The
                            following are possible resulting consequences:</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>a.</label>
                            <item>A combination of involuntary discharges and reduced promotion
                                opportunity for military personnel would be necessary. For example,
                                to maintain “normal” promotion opportunity, over 100,000 (of a total
                                of 1.1 million) senior enlisted men would have to be forced out in
                                    <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72. This could be partly
                                alleviated by forced retirement of some of the 130,000 enlisted
                                personnel with over 20 years service. Legislation may be required to
                                release regular officers, temporarily increase officer grade
                                structure, and obtain severance pay for career enlisted men.</item>
                            <pb facs="0613" n="584" xml:id="pg_584"/>
                            <label>b.</label>
                            <item>About 200,000 men would be released early from service while over
                                100,000 others are being drafted to meet Vietnam requirements in
                                    <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 71.</item>
                            <label>c.</label>
                            <item>There would be a 30–40% increase in transfers of military
                                personnel, with attendant personal hardships and reduced combat
                                readiness.</item>
                            <label>d.</label>
                            <item>There would be involuntary assignments to Vietnam for second or
                                third tours, particularly in special skills. For example, about
                                2,000 (12% of the total) Infantry, Armor, and Engineer Captains and
                                Majors would have return tours in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss>
                                71.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Effect of Defense Reduction on National
                            Economy</hi></p>
                        <p>The reductions in defense manpower, coupled with reduced procurement
                            programs and the 40–50 base closures that would be necessary, would
                            cause large economic dislocations. In addition to the defense personnel
                            reductions, employment in defense products industries would fall by
                            700,000 (200,000 more than under current planning). Thus, the total
                            reduction in defense-related jobs would reach nearly 2,000,000 (700,000
                            more than under current planning), or about 2% of the nation’s labor
                            force. Even if the decision to reduce were made today, the phasing of
                            the reduction would not be sufficiently gradual that these workers could
                            be immediately absorbed into other sectors of the economy. As a result,
                            unemployment might be 0.2–0.3% higher by the end of 1971 than at current
                            defense planning levels.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Timing Considerations</hi></p>
                        <p>All of the impacts described above would be alleviated by a more gradual
                            phasedown of manpower. This would result from either a smaller budget
                            reduction or from deferral of the uncommitted Volunteer Service spending
                            as part of whatever reduction must be made. Conversely, all of these
                            effects would be exacerbated by a delay in decision, whatever the
                            magnitude of reduction that must be made. For example, a delay until
                            January 1971 in deciding to reduce defense by $6 billion in <gloss target="#t_FY1">FY</gloss> 72 would mean that manpower reductions
                            would be smaller in that year and that reductions of an additional $2
                            billion in procurement and <gloss target="#t_RD1">R&amp;D</gloss> budget
                            authority would be needed to reach the outlay target.</p>
                        <p>[Omitted here are Section IV, which outlines non-Defense program options,
                            and Section V, which includes a table representing 12 combined Defense
                            and non-Defense budgetary options.]</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>