<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-12-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1969-01-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="69" subtype="editorial-note" type="document" xml:id="d69">
                        <head>69. Editorial Note</head>
                        <p>During the autumn of 1969, President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and his Assistant for National Security Affairs
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> searched for ways
                            of achieving a negotiated settlement to the war in Vietnam by
                            escalating, or by giving the appearance of escalating, the war, thereby
                            encouraging the North Vietnamese to be more conciliatory in the Paris
                            peace talks. In his memoirs, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> stated, “After half a year of sending peaceful
                            signals to the Communists, I was ready to use whatever military pressure
                            was necessary to prevent them from taking over South Vietnam by force.
                            During several long sessions, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> and I developed an elaborate orchestration of
                            diplomatic, military, and publicity pressures we would bring to bear on
                            Hanoi.” (<hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_NRM1">RN</persName></hi>, pages 393, 398)</p>
                        <pb facs="0283" n="254" xml:id="pg_254"/>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>’s memoirs include a
                            slightly different version of events. “<persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> tried to play for all the marbles; and as was not
                            infrequently the case, he began it with a maneuver that appeared
                            portentous though it reflected no definitive plan. In short, he was
                            bluffing.” Specifically, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> recalled that the administration tried to
                            create the impression that the November 1 anniversary of the United
                            States’ halt on bombing North Vietnamese targets “was a kind of
                            deadline.” The President, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> wrote, “dropped less than subtle hints that
                            his patience was running out and that if no progress had been made in
                            Paris by November 1, he would take strong action. So far as I could
                            tell, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> had only the vaguest
                            idea of what he had in mind.” (<hi rend="italic">White House Years</hi>,
                            pages 304–305)</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, in a manifestation of
                            linkage, gave Soviet Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> the impression that they were about to escalate
                            the war on the assumption that the Soviets could and would pressure
                            their North Vietnamese clients to reach a settlement in Paris. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> held a meeting with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> on September 27. According to
                            the memorandum of conversation, President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>, by prearrangement, called during the meeting.
                            Once the conversation was completed, <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>, “To us Vietnam was the critical issue. We were
                            quite prepared to discuss other subjects, but the Soviet Union should
                            not expect any special treatment until Vietnam was solved.” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>, after expressing regret
                            “that all our efforts to negotiate had failed,” informed <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> that President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> “had told me in his call that the
                            train had just left the station and was now headed down the track.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> responded that he
                            hoped it was an airplane and not a train and would leave some
                            maneuvering room. I said the President chooses his words very carefully
                            and that I was sure he meant train.” (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, President’s Trip Files, Box 489,
                                <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> 1969 [Part 2]) The full
                            memorandum of conversation, which <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> sent to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> under a covering memorandum, October 1, is
                            published in <ref target="frus1969-76v12#d85"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                    Relations</hi>, 1969–1976, volume XII, Soviet Union, January
                                1969–October 1970, Document 85</ref>. See also <ref target="frus1969-76v06#d125">ibid., volume VI, Vietnam, January
                                1969–July 1970, Document 125</ref>.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> called <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> after the latter’s meeting
                            with <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>. According to the
                            transcript of the telephone conversation, the President asked <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> if <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName> clearly understood “the fact
                            we are going the hard route?” <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> assured <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> that the Soviet Ambassador understood as <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> “had been very tough on him.”
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> then summarized
                            their conversation. “<persName corresp="#p_DAF1">D[obrynin]</persName>
                            had asked what <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K[issinger]</persName>
                            thought of the Sino-Soviet problem” and “whether he thought they (the
                            Soviets) were going to attack the Chinese. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">K</persName> had replied that, as a historian, he thought the
                            Soviets were considering it.” Later during their conversation, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> discussed the merits and timing of “making the
                            tough move” regarding the war in <pb facs="0284" n="255" xml:id="pg_255"/> Vietnam. (National Archives, <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, President’s Trip Files, Box 489, <persName corresp="#p_DAF1">Dobrynin</persName>/<persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> 1969 [Part 1])</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>