<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-06-20T13:10:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-06-20T13:10:00-05:00" n="45" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d45">
                    <head>45. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d45fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName>’s
                            Correspondence, Lot 78D300, Box 3, Congress. Limited Official Use.
                            Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_WRR_1">Wyrough</persName>. The meeting
                            took place in <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName>’s office.
                            Sent to <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> under a June
                            21 covering memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-06-20T14:10:00-04:00">June 20, 1974, 2:10
                            p.m.</date></dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> called upon Senator
                            <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName> on Thursday, June 20 at
                        2:10 p.m. in order to report on developments in Panama Canal treaty
                        negotiations. Present in addition to the principals were Deputy Assistant
                        Secretary for Congressional Relations <persName corresp="#p_JKB_1">Kempton
                            Jenkins</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_WRR_1">Richard
                            Wyrough</persName>, Special Adviser, Office of Panamanian Affairs, Dr.
                        James Lucier of Senator Helms’ office and an administrative assistant from
                        Senator <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName>’s office.</p>
                    <p>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> referred to his
                        earlier promise to keep Senator <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName> informed of developments affecting Panama Canal
                        treaty negotiations. He remarked that we have not yet begun substantive
                        discussions but that we have reached agreement on the major issues embodied
                        in the Joint Statement of Principles.</p>
                    <pb facs="0154" n="129" xml:id="pg_129"/>
                    <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName> referred to his
                        Resolution of March 29 and suggested that while many changes might be
                        possible United States sovereignty must be retained. With regard to the
                        Resolution he emphasized the ease with which he obtained the co-sponsors,
                        that other senators told him subsequently that the Resolution reflects their
                        view point, and that a treaty based upon the Principles would be defeated if
                        presented to the Senate for its ratification.</p>
                    <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName> referred to Panama’s
                        unstable political record and minimized the importance of Panamanian
                        nationalist pressures in favor of Panamanian sovereignty. He observed that
                        General <persName corresp="#p_THOE_1">Torrijos</persName> was attempting to
                        create political interest in a problem which lacked wide support in Panama.
                        On the other hand he observed that he receives frequent expressions of
                        concern from the Canal Zone over the direction which negotiations appear to
                        be taking.</p>
                    <p>Senator <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName> suggested the
                        desirability of finding an alternative to the sovereignty solution embodied
                        in current negotiations. He said that he would discuss several such
                        proposals during the June 23 NBC T.V. program which will look at the canal
                        question, and identified “home-rule” as one of these alternatives. He
                        promised to list them for Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName> by letter.<note n="2" xml:id="d45fn2">Not
                            found.</note></p>
                    <p>In concluding the meeting Senator <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName> referred to his role in helping to gain the
                        election of the Administration. He commented that although he wishes to see
                        it remain in office “it will lose if it submits a draft treaty as envisioned
                        by the Joint Statement of Principles.”</p>
                    <p>In departing, Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BE_1">Bunker</persName>
                        reaffirmed his intent to keep Senator <persName corresp="#p_TJS_1">Thurmond</persName> informed. The meeting adjourned at 2:20 p.m.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>