<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1974-10-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1974-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="56" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d56">
                    <head>56. Presidential Determination No. 75–4<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d56fn1">Source: National Archives, Ford Library, National
                            Security Adviser, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Latin American
                            Affairs Staff Files, 1974–77, Box 6, Panama—Political, Military (1).
                            Confidential.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1974-10-29">October 29, 1974</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">MEMORANDUM FOR THE SECRETARY OF STATE</p>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Waiver of Section 3(b) of the Foreign Military Sales Act, as
                            Amended—Panama</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Pursuant to the authority vested in me by Section 3(b) of the Foreign
                        Military Sales Act, as amended, I hereby waive the provisions of Section
                        3(b) of the Foreign Military Sales Act, as amended, with respect to sales,
                        credits or guaranties to the Government of Panama. Reasonable assurances
                        have been received from the Government of Panama that future violations of
                        Section 3(b) of the Act will not occur.<note n="2" xml:id="d56fn2">In an
                            October 23 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Ford</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> recommended
                            granting Panama a waiver of Section 3(b) stating that “General <persName corresp="#p_THOE_1">Omar Torrijos</persName>, the Chief of
                            Government, informed our Ambassador that the April 17 seizure was
                            carried out by the patrol boat commander on his own initiative.”
                                <persName corresp="#p_KHA_1">Kissinger</persName> noted that failure
                            to grant the waiver would “precipitate a serious deterioration between
                            the [Panamanian National] Guard and U.S. forces in Panama as well as
                            between our two Governments,” adding, “Congressional reaction to
                            Panama’s recent recognition of Cuba has been light and I do not
                            anticipate any significant degree of criticism if this waiver is
                            granted.” (Ibid.)</note></p>
                    <p>You are requested on my behalf to report this waiver to the Speaker of the
                        House of Representatives and to the Chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations
                        Committee, as required by law.</p>
                    <p>I have concluded, pursuant to Section 654(c) of the Foreign Assistance Act of
                        1961, as amended, that this determination and waiver shall be classified
                        “Confidential” and shall not be published in <hi rend="italic">The Federal
                            Register.</hi> Such publication would be harmful to the national
                        security of the United States in view of the serious and delicate
                        negotiations now going on between the United States and the Government of
                        Panama concerning a new Panama Canal treaty.</p>
                    <p rend="right"><hi rend="strong"><persName corresp="#p_FGR_1">Gerald R.
                                Ford</persName>
                        </hi></p>
                    <p rend="center">Justification for Presidential Waiver of Section 3(b) of the
                        Foreign Military Sales Act, as Amended</p>
                    <p>On April 17, 1974, Panama seized an American fishing vessel for having
                        engaged in fishing more than twelve miles from the Panamanian <pb facs="0180" n="155" xml:id="pg_155"/> coast but within Panama’s claimed
                        200-mile territorial sea. Section 3(b) of the Foreign Military Sales Act, as
                        amended, requires the suspension of all sales, credits and guaranties under
                        the Act to any country which has so seized an American fishing vessel. Such
                        suspension is to remain in effect for a period of one year from the date of
                        the seizure in question. The President is authorized to waive this
                        suspension either (a) if reasonable assurances are received from the country
                        concerned that future violations of Section 3(b) will not occur or (b) if
                        the President determines that such a waiver is important to the security of
                        the United States.</p>
                    <p>The United States Ambassador in Panama has discussed the matter of the
                        seizure with a senior official of the Government of Panama, who has informed
                        the Ambassador that the commander of the patrol boat which effected the
                        April 17 seizure had acted on his own initiative, and that as a matter of
                        policy Panama would not rely upon seizures of foreign fishing boats to
                        implement its territorial sea claims. These representations constitute
                        reasonable assurances that future violations of U.S. fishing rights will not
                        occur.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>