<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>117. Memorandum From the Representative to the United Nations (Bush) to
                    President ) to President Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d117</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">117</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-06-07T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-06-07T00:00:00-05:00" n="117"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d117">
                <head>117. Memorandum From the Representative to the United Nations (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BGHW1" type="from">Bush</persName>) to President <persName
                        corresp="#p_NRM1" type="to">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d117fn1">Source: National Archives, <persName
                            corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials, <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Box 301, Agency Files, <gloss
                            target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, Vol. VII. No classification marking.
                        “The President has seen” is stamped on the memorandum. Attached memoranda
                        indicate that this memorandum was sent to the National Security Council on
                        June 9, to <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> on June 17, and
                        to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> on June 21.
                        Another memorandum, dated June 11, noted that <persName corresp="#p_WWM1"
                            >Marshall Wright</persName> had said that <persName corresp="#p_BGHW1"
                            >Bush</persName>’s report was a personal opinion. Although Wright had no
                        objection to the Security Council meeting elsewhere, there would be
                        logistical and budgetary problems in moving General Assembly meetings.
                            <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName> initialed his approval
                        of a covering memorandum to the President, June 21, recommending a favorable
                        response to holding Security Council meetings abroad but less so for General
                        Assembly meetings. The June 21 memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_KHA1"
                            >Kissinger</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> is
                        stamped “The President has seen,” and bears a handwritten note from
                            <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> reading: “Good. Keep it
                        up!”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New York</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-06-07">June 7, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">PROGRESS REPORT ON SUGGESTION ABOUT MOVING <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss> AROUND</p>
                <list>
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <item>The Secretary General publicly endorsed the concept of Security Council
                        meetings abroad from time to time.</item>
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <item>Friday the French Ambassador, the President of the Security Council in
                        July, told me he would like to schedule the July meeting (to deal with Oman)
                        in Geneva—Progress!</item>
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <item>There is resistance at some layers in the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                            >UN</gloss> for having General Assembly Meetings abroad, namely due to
                        cost, old habits, inconvenience of New York-based people, etc. I’ll keep
                        plugging away at it. If they can hold Olympics around the world, they ought
                        to be able to hold General Assembly Meetings.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
