<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1972-10-05T15:14:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1972-10-05T15:14:00-05:00" n="133" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d133">
                        <head>133. Telegram From <gloss type="from">the Embassy in France</gloss> to
                            the <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d133fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 3 <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. Confidential; Immediate; Exdis.
                                Repeated to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, London, Moscow,
                                and Panama City.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1972-10-05T20:14:00+00:00">October 5, 1972,
                                2014Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>18969. Subject: Possible Security Council Meeting in Panama. Ref State
                                181193.<note n="2" xml:id="d133fn2">In telegram 181193 to Paris,
                                October 4, the Department advised Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_WAK1">Watson</persName> that <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> had intended to discuss the
                                Panamanian initiative with <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Schumann</persName> in New York, and urged him to arrange a
                                meeting to explain <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> objections to
                                Security Council meetings away from headquarters. “Major powers must
                                be concerned with precedent that would be established if country
                                having an issue with one of them were to use its fortuitous
                                membership on the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>, and its
                                presidency of the Council in a particular month, to move that forum
                                to a locality from which it can bring pressure to bear on a
                                permanent member. This a point that we also intend to make to the
                                    <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.” (Ibid.)</note>
                        </p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Have just returned (accompanied by Pol Couns) from talking with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Schumann</persName> re possible
                                    <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting in Panama. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Schumann</persName> had a notetaker on his
                                side. I asked him directly how committed he was. He replied
                                “completely.” He said that at his dinner for Latin Americans, “all
                                of them” asked him if France was prepared to support meeting in
                                Panama, to which he replied “If all of you ask, why should France
                                refuse?”</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Explaining you had intended raise matter with him directly, I went
                                on and pointed out how seriously we viewed the matter of having the
                                    <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meet in a country with which
                                we were having active negotiations and whose Permanent
                                Representative stated that the purpose of having this meeting in
                                Panama was to focus public attention in the US on the Canal issue.
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Schumann</persName> was completely
                                stunned, stating that he had thought that Panama and the US were on
                                the best possible terms and he had no idea we “had any trouble” with
                                them. He immediately said “I must disentangle myself from myself. I
                                have been uncautious and it will take time.” I also told him that if
                                the French were having delicate negotiations with one of their
                                former colonies such as Morocco and some country suggested that the
                                    <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meet in Rabat, they would find
                                it as unpalatable as we find facing a possible meeting in
                                Panama.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Schumann</persName> was clearly upset,
                                stating that he had had several excellent visits with you as well as
                                a visit with the President and Dr. <persName corresp="#p_KHA1">Kissinger</persName>. He stated that relations between our two
                                countries have never been better and that he was extremely sorry
                                that he had been so “uncautious.” He then stated that the Latin
                                Americans at the dinner had cited the Addis Ababa meeting as the
                                precedent for having the meeting in Panama. We of course pointed out
                                to him inter alia that <pb facs="0290" n="253" xml:id="pg_253"/>
                                there had been active African matters on the <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> agenda and it was the <gloss target="#t_OAU1">OAU</gloss> that issued the invitation, not a single country.
                                He went on to say that he had been against Addis Ababa meeting
                                because of the precedents, and that the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> was very serious in seeking French support to
                                prevent <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> meeting in Panama.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>I took the liberty of suggesting various means for <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Schumann</persName> to reverse his position,
                                along lines <gloss target="#t_REFTEL1">reftel</gloss>s, and he told
                                me he would think it over and be in touch. If I don’t hear from him
                                soon, I will contact him again early next week, unless you suggest
                                otherwise.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>
                                <hi rend="italic">Comment:</hi> In all my dealings with <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Schumann</persName> I have never seen him so
                                visibly shaken, concerned and apologetic.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_WAK1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Watson</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>