<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>322. Memonradum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d322</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">322</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-01-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-01-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-01-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="322"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d322">
                <head>322. Memonradum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d322fn1"
                        >Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss
                            target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 6 <gloss target="#t_CHIC1">CHICOM</gloss>.
                        Secret; Noforn; Exdis. Drafted January 26 by <persName corresp="#p_FHJ1"
                            >Feldman</persName>; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_AJA1"
                            >Armitage</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_DPS1">De Palma</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_STP1"
                            >Shoesmith</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_PJT1">J. Theodore
                            Papendorp</persName>; and approved in <gloss target="#t_SS1"
                        >S/S</gloss>-S on February 1.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-01-20">January 20, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">M. Pierre Harmel</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_FONMIN1">FonMin</gloss> of Belgium</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DVE1">Vicomte Etienne Davignon,</persName> DirGen for
                        PolAffairs, Belgian <gloss target="#t_FONMIN1">FonMin</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LW2">Walter Loridan</persName>, Belgian
                        Ambassador to US</item>
                    <item>M. Paul Noterdaeme, Chef de Cabinet, Belgian <gloss target="#t_FONMIN1"
                            >FonMin</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DAR1">M. Roland d’Anethan</persName>, Director of
                        Western European and North American Affairs, Belgian <gloss
                            target="#t_FONMIN1">FonMin</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>M. Rene Lion, Deputy Chief of Mission, Belgian Embassy</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PH1">M. Hugo Paemen</persName>, Press Officer, Belgian
                            <gloss target="#t_FONMIN1">FonMin</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Marshall Green</persName>, AsstSec for East Asian
                        &amp; Pacific Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DPS1">Samuel De Palma</persName>, AsstSec for
                        International Organization Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_STP1">Thomas P. Shoesmith</persName>, Country Director
                        for Republic of China Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PJT1">J. Theodore Papendorp</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_EUR1">EUR</gloss>/FBX</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_FHJ1">Harvey Feldman</persName>, <gloss
                            target="#t_IOUNP1">IO/UNP</gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>Alec Toumayan, OPR/LS</item>
                </list>
                <p>After welcoming Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName>
                    and his suite, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName> noted that the US
                    was concentrating very hard on the <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss>
                    problem and although we had not yet reached any decisions, we were actively
                    considering alternatives. We would be very pleased to hear the Foreign
                    Minister’s views.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> began by mentioning that
                    Belgium’s views on the matter were not determined by domestic political
                    difficulties or a need to deal with parliamentary pressures. Rather Belgium
                    feels that the Albanian resolution is a bad presentation of the <gloss
                        target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> issue, and yet if <pb facs="0603" n="566"
                        xml:id="pg_566"/> matters take their present course before long the Albanian
                    resolution will pass, Peking will be seated in the Security Council and Taiwan
                    will be expelled from the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> entirely. If, after
                    that, the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> should attempt to use force to
                    seize Taiwan, and if the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> and Japan or others
                    went to Taiwan’s assistance, they would find themselves opposed by the <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> then took up the matter of
                    the Important Question procedure, saying that there is no longer any certainty
                    that the <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> will again receive majority support
                    in the Assembly. The vote in favor of the <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> is
                    narrowing steadily, and Belgium believes that Canada, Italy, Austria and others
                    will not maintain their present position of supporting it. A shift of even a few
                    votes would put the <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> in jeopardy, and it would
                    be an act of carelessness not to have other alternatives available to meet the
                    situation.</p>
                <p>There are points that must be avoided in any new approach to the <gloss
                        target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> problem, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1"
                        >Harmel</persName> continued. What must be avoided are: accepting Peking by
                    expelling Taiwan; calling for <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> admission as a
                    new member (since it will refuse to do this); calling for Taiwan to apply as a
                    new member (since its application would be vetoed). The crux of the matter,
                    however, is Taiwan’s insistence that it is the only legitimate government of
                    China and its refusal to give up its Security Council seat. Obviously Taiwan is
                    a state, but equally obviously it is not a great power and thus is not entitled
                    to a Security Council seat. Taiwan’s insistence that it is such a state only
                    gives weapons to the supporters of the Albanian resolution. Sooner or later
                    diplomatic action must be taken to make the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                    understand that it is in its interest to remain in the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss>, but to acquiesce in a dual representation formula under which
                    the Security Council seat would go to the <gloss target="#t_PRC1"
                    >PRC</gloss>.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> noted that the legal basis
                    for a dual representation resolution could be, briefly: (1) the <gloss
                        target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> is one of the five major states described in
                    Article 23 of the Charter; (2) the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>, though
                    changed in size and scope, remains a state with all the attributes of
                    sovereignty and therefore should remain a member of the <gloss target="#t_UN1"
                        >UN</gloss>.</p>
                <p>As far as Belgium is concerned, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1"
                        >Harmel</persName> continued, it has no great desire to be in the forefront
                    on this issue. If the US, Japan, Australia and the other countries more
                    immediately concerned say that something can be done along these lines, Belgium
                    is willing to play its part fully; it does not insist on the exact wording
                    suggested, or even this specific approach. Belgium would like to find a way out
                    of the impasse. If the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> continues to claim to
                    be the sole legitimate government of China, and digs its own grave, “we will
                    attend the funeral and shed some—but not all the tears.” It is not too soon to
                    look for a way out. If support for the Important Question drops, and
                    particularly if Canada, Austria and Italy change their position (as is likely),
                    there will be great pressure on the Benelux countries to do the same.</p>
                <pb facs="0604" n="567" xml:id="pg_567"/>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName> thanked Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> for his thoughtful and well-stated
                    views. He noted that if dual representation were tried, there would be
                    difficulties with the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> as well as the <gloss
                        target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>. The old line <gloss target="#t_GRC1"
                        >GRC</gloss> leaders will be thoroughly opposed. Although there is some
                    recognition of a need for a change lower down the line, even those leaders would
                    find it difficult to go along. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName>
                    asked Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STP1">Shoesmith</persName>’s views on the
                    question, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_STP1">Shoesmith</persName> rated the
                    chance of <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> acceptance at about 5%.
                    Continuing, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName> pointed out that
                    even if one could get <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> acquiescence in dual
                    representation, the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> would continue to refuse
                    to join the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> as long as Taiwan remained in the
                    organization. He asked how Minister <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1"
                        >Harmel</persName> would view this development.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> observed that the Belgian
                    Government would shed no tears if the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>
                    refused to take an offered seat. What mattered most of all was that the seat not
                    be vacated through <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> expulsion, and that both
                    Chinese parties understood that despite their claims and counterclaims, the
                    issues would have to be resolved peacefully, under the control and protection of
                    the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>. He noted that changes do occur over time;
                    once the West Germans emphasized the Hallstein doctrine with no flexibility at
                    all, and now they themselves say they do not oppose separate <gloss
                        target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership for the two Germanies. If the Albanian
                    resolution passes, there are no options for the future; if some other solution
                    is put forward, the options remain open.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DPS1">De Palma</persName> mentioned the difficulty of
                    keeping the General Assembly from bowing to <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>
                    pressures. Dual representation or some other formula short of the Albanian
                    resolution might well become interim stages on the way to ultimate passage of
                    the Albanian resolution by the Assembly. This raises the question of whether it
                    is better at all to put forward short-term formulas since they would not be a
                    final solution. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DPS1">De Palma</persName> also noted
                    that the Belgian draft does not mention the principle of universality at all,
                    and asked Minister <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> whether he
                    thought universality might be a first step toward dual representation.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> thought not; universality
                    would create problems for the West Germans and others. Combining <gloss
                        target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> and universality might complicate matters
                    and yet not prevent the Albanian resolution from making progress. It would be
                    best to keep the two problems separate. <persName corresp="#p_DVE1">Vicomte
                        Davignon</persName> observed that if one put forward the principle of
                    universality, one would still have to contend with the view that the <gloss
                        target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> is not China.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName> expressed concern that if we just
                    stick with our present policy, the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> will get
                    in on its own terms. The US Government would come in for a great deal of
                    domestic criticism. Most people in the US would prefer to see a dual
                    representation solution and there would be support for the Belgian position. But
                    the <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> is bound to be opposed. <pb facs="0605"
                        n="568" xml:id="pg_568"/> It is hard enough for them to move over time to
                    accept dual representation; all the harder for them to accede to the <gloss
                        target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> taking the Security Council seat and to make so
                    great a shift in policy in the course of one year. If the US and others
                    attempted to persuade them to do so, and if they refused, this would impair the
                        US–<gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> relationship. At any rate, Mr.
                        <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName> continued, the results of the
                    voting on the Albanian resolution at the last Assembly have persuaded the
                    Nationalists to begin thinking the unthinkable.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> observed that unfortunately,
                    we do not have several years available to educate the <gloss target="#t_GRC1"
                        >GRC</gloss>. He expressed grave doubts that they can be persuaded of
                    anything, and noted that they still talked of re-capturing the mainland by
                    military means—an attitude which he called an “abyss of unreality”. If the
                        <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> is willing to exist outside of the
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, well and good; that is what would happen
                    if they continued on their present course.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName> noted that no one on Taiwan
                    realistically expects to recapture the mainland militarily any more, and added
                    that some are even coming around to viewing with relative understanding the US
                    position on seeking better relations with Peking. But, he added, the present
                    situation demands a great leap in their thinking all at once, and this is most
                    difficult for them.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> said that Belgium is prepared
                    to continue sharing views with the US on this matter. If studies are to be made,
                    Belgium will be happy to cooperate. But, he observed, it is now January and if
                    nothing has been decided by July, it will then be too late—the situation will
                    pass from our control. Belgium would like to participate in working out a
                    solution—and does not believe that half-way measures like the Study Committee
                    are of use any longer. However, Belgium will not take any separate initiatives
                    and will act only as a member of a group. He noted that last year, when they
                    floated their draft resolution, they encountered more opposition from the East
                    Europeans, and particularly the Soviet Union, than from their Western
                    allies.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_DPS1">De Palma</persName> asked if Belgium had
                    continued to discuss dual representation formulas with other countries in the
                    period since the General Assembly, and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1"
                        >Harmel</persName> replied they had not.</p>
                <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName> again expressed great thanks to
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> and his party.</p>
                <p>(In a subsequent luncheon conversation with Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName>, Mr. <persName corresp="#p_GM2"
                        >Green</persName> requested that the Belgians convey to us the reactions of
                    other countries to the <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> proposal.
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_HPCJM1">Harmel</persName> said his government
                    would do so.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
