<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-02-17T16:57:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-02-17T16:57:00-05:00" n="330" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d330">
                        <head>330. Telegram From the <gloss type="from">Department of State</gloss>
                            to <gloss type="to">Certain Posts</gloss><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d330fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59, Central Files
                                1970–73, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 6 <gloss target="#t_CHIC1">CHICOM</gloss>. Secret. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_FHJ1">Feldman</persName>; cleared by <persName corresp="#p_AJA1">Armitage</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_FJAJ1">John A. Froebe, Jr</persName>., and <persName corresp="#p_STP1">Shoesmith</persName>; and approved by Deputy
                                Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HMF1">Herz</persName>.
                                Sent to Canberra, Tokyo, and Wellington and repeated to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, Taipei, and Hong Kong.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-02-17T21:57:00+00:00">February 17, 1971,
                                2157Z</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>26614. Subject: <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss>: Consultations in
                                <gloss target="#t_NY1">NY</gloss> with Australian, New Zealand and
                            Japan <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Missions.</p>
                        <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Deptoffs <persName corresp="#p_JAS1">Jenkins</persName> (<gloss target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss>/ACA), <persName corresp="#p_STP1">Shoesmith</persName> (<gloss target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss>) and <persName corresp="#p_FHJ1">Feldman</persName> (<gloss target="#t_IOUNP1">IO/UNP</gloss>)
                                held consultations in <gloss target="#t_NY1">NY</gloss> Feb 10 with
                                officers of Australian, New Zealand, and Japanese <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Missions.<note n="2" xml:id="d330fn2">Telegram 18209 to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>,
                                    February 3, informed the Mission that <persName corresp="#p_JAS1">Jenkins</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_STP1">Shoe-smith</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_FHJ1">Feldman</persName> would be in New York
                                    for a continuation of exploratory discussions. (Ibid., <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> Presidential Materials,
                                        <gloss target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Files, Agency Files, Box
                                    300, <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss>, January–May 1971,
                                    Vol. VI)</note>
                                <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> personnel accompanied.
                                Following is summary these meetings. <gloss target="#t_SEPTEL1">Septel</gloss> reports meeting with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Liu</persName>, <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> Permanent Representative.<note n="3" xml:id="d330fn3">The meeting with Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LC1">Liu</persName> was reported in telegram
                                    27069, February 18. (Ibid., RG 59, Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 6 <gloss target="#t_CHIC1">CHICOM</gloss>)</note>
                            </item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Deptoffs met with <persName corresp="#p_MC2">Charles
                                    Mott</persName>, Australia <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Feb
                                10. <persName corresp="#p_MC2">Mott</persName> began by noting
                                    <gloss target="#t_GOA1">GOA</gloss> in process of reviewing
                                    <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> and he therefore under
                                instructions listen but unable outline <gloss target="#t_GOA1">GOA</gloss> views. Deptoffs stressed <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> has not reached firm decisions on <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> policy but wished hold full and
                                frank consultations with key allies (particularly Japan, Australia
                                and New Zealand, in addition <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss>)
                                for mutual exploration of situation and discussion of possible
                                alternatives. Hopefully, consultation process would establish
                                parameters and lead to consensus on best course of action. Also
                                noted <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> did not see this as
                                necessarily remaining a bilateral consultation process with US
                                consulting separately with <gloss target="#t_GOA1">GOA</gloss>,
                                    <gloss target="#t_GNZ1">GNZ</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss>, etc. and then reporting views to <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>; we assumed individual countries
                                would wish to consult with each other and with <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_JAS1">Jenkins</persName> began substantive
                                discussion by describing our view of Peking’s attitude. Noted our
                                belief <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> definitely wishes join
                                    <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss>, but for foreseeable future
                                will insist upon prior <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss>
                                expulsion. <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> doubtless optimistic
                                this will happen 1971 or 1972, wishes no change in manner in which
                                issue presented to <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> (<gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> and Albanian Res), and will exert
                                great pressure, particularly on countries with whom it has
                                relations, to vote against <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> and for
                                    <gloss target="#t_AR1">AR</gloss>. Over next several months,
                                countries negotiating <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss>
                                recognition may find this part of price. Peking probably fears US
                                and allies will attempt new tactics to deprive it of victory almost
                                in its grasp, probably expects this will be dual representation <pb facs="0630" n="593" xml:id="pg_593"/> formula, and will make
                                every effort prevent this tactic from succeeding.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_STP1">Shoesmith</persName> discussed <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> attitudes noting that realistically
                                we see only slim chance of its acquiescing in any substantial change
                                from present <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> policy and
                                tactics. However, we believe possibility of such change is more than
                                just theoretical. <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> has not yet
                                made final decision or attempted to define limits beyond which it
                                will not accept compromise. In addition, discussion of various
                                alternatives to present policy is taking place within govt and KMT.
                                We consider these circumstances moderately encouraging, and are
                                holding frank talks with <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> to
                                encourage further process of objective and careful examination of
                                all facets of situation. We have given <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> our estimates of adverse <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> situation, will discuss specific alternatives and
                                have stressed importance of not underestimating impact loss of
                                    <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> membership (whether through
                                expulsion or withdrawal) not only on <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> interests but on policy concerns of friendly
                                governments wishing maintain close relations with and support for
                                    <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>. <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> has told us they believe <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> should be vigorously pressed at next <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> and that they regard Security
                                Council seat as matter of prime importance.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_FHJ1">Feldman</persName> noted <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> situation adverse and that tide
                                running against us. If policy unchanged, many countries which voted
                                for <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> in 1970 likely to abstain in
                                1971 and <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> opponents probably
                                already number 54, increase of 2 over last vote. Vote probably will
                                be very close. Hard to predict outcome at this point, but most
                                likely only three or four votes will separate winners and losers.
                                Noting list certainly not exhaustive, <persName corresp="#p_FHJ1">Feldman</persName> summarized theoretical alternative dual
                                representation and universality resolutions including general
                                advantages and disadvantages of each. Noted that any alternative
                                formula put forward must be seen by <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> as reasonable and equitable attempt at solution of
                                    <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> problem and not as
                                gimmick to block <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> entry. If
                                decision ultimately made to follow one of these alternatives,
                                language should be worked out through consultation process to find
                                most saleable and durable formula as far as Assembly concerned, and
                                one which protects strategic concerns in area. In addition, would
                                have to find answers to following questions: How deal with Security
                                Council seat? Maintain present <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> and
                                attempt get two-thirds vote for new <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> formula or drop <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> and seek passage by simple majority? Put forward new
                                    <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> formula stating that
                                resolution to expel <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> requires
                                two-thirds vote instead of present formula that any proposal change
                                China’s <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> representation requires
                                two-thirds vote?</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName corresp="#p_MC2">Mott</persName> expressed appreciation
                                for full presentation, expressed particular gratification for
                                observation that final policy decisions should be based upon
                                consensus view major concerned allies. <persName corresp="#p_MC2">Mott</persName>, who had taken full notes, said his mission
                                would be reporting to Canberra in detail.</item>
                            <pb facs="0631" n="594" xml:id="pg_594"/>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Deptoffs lunched with Minister <persName corresp="#p_YN1">Yoshida</persName> and Kagami of Japan <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> mission Feb 10, explaining purpose of their visit to
                                    <gloss target="#t_NY1">NY</gloss> for discussions with
                                Australia, <gloss target="#t_NZ1">NZ</gloss> and <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> Missions and noting <persName corresp="#p_HMF1">Herz</persName> visit to Tokyo preceding week.
                                In general luncheon discussion, <persName corresp="#p_YN1">Yoshida</persName> expressed personal view that separate
                                universality resolution might prove troublesome but suggested that
                                philosophic basis could be established simply by having dual <gloss target="#t_REP1">rep</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_RES1">res</gloss> pay homage to universality
                                principle in preamble. <persName corresp="#p_YN1">Yoshida</persName>
                                principally concerned, however, to emphasize importance he
                                personally attaches to retaining <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss>
                                formula at least for one more year, either in present or amended
                                form as suggested para 5 above, as essential safeguard against
                                passage of <gloss target="#t_AR1">AR</gloss>. He also alluded to
                                “serious problems which <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss>
                                poses for <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss>” and, although he not
                                specific, seemed to have in mind conflicting forces within Japanese
                                government and LDP. In connection with handling of <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss> seat, <persName corresp="#p_YN1">Yoshida</persName> said these problems so difficult that he
                                thought <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> might have to abstain on
                                new resolution. <persName corresp="#p_YN1">Yoshida</persName> also
                                seemed to feel that for similar reasons it might be difficult for
                                    <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> to take lead in developing
                                support for some new approach to <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> problem.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Deptoffs met with Ambassador <persName>Scott</persName>, Small and
                                    <persName>Williams</persName> of <gloss target="#t_NZ1">NZ</gloss> Mission and Hensley of <gloss target="#t_NZ1">NZ</gloss> Embassy Washington Feb 10 pm, making presentation
                                essentially similar that given Australia. In following discussion,
                                New Zealanders noted their assessment <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> situation closely parallels our own. Hensley
                                indicated that <gloss target="#t_GNZ1">GNZ</gloss> primary concern
                                is to avoid expulsion or withdrawal of <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss> since this likely generate strong public pressures
                                in <gloss target="#t_NZ1">NZ</gloss> to recognize <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> and cease support for <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>. Over time, Hensley suggested, such
                                development could threaten bring Taiwan under <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> control, thus weakening security
                                situation in East Asia. <gloss target="#t_GNZ1">GNZ</gloss>,
                                therefore, would not wish to see <gloss target="#t_GRC1">GRC</gloss>
                                position lost because no new approach made to protect it. Fact that
                                    <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> would not agree to some new
                                approach, Hensley stated, would not be “fatal disadvantage” if such
                                approach would buy time to deal with problem of public opinion. New
                                Zealanders saw problems with universality <gloss target="#t_RES1">res</gloss> but also (though independently since we had not
                                mentioned <persName corresp="#p_YN1">Yoshida</persName>’s remarks)
                                thought preambular language of dual <gloss target="#t_REP1">rep</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_RES1">res</gloss> might bow in universality
                                    direction.<gloss target="#t_GNZ1">GNZ</gloss> had not thought of
                                quite as many variant dual <gloss target="#t_REP1">rep</gloss> reses
                                as the six listed by Deptoffs, but since meeting between Hensley and
                                Deptoffs (reported State 19896),<note n="4" xml:id="d330fn4">Dated
                                    February 5. (Ibid.)</note> has been giving consideration to
                                rather different style scenario under which two separate reses would
                                be introduced in tandem, one seating <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> and one maintaining place for <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss>. Idea was that countries would have
                                complete and free choice: they could vote for both reses, or only
                                for “country of their choice.” <pb facs="0632" n="595" xml:id="pg_595"/>
                                <gloss target="#t_NZ1">NZ</gloss> offs did not know whether
                                    <persName corresp="#p_TRW1">Wellington</persName> intended that
                                both reses be introduced by same set of co-sponsors and agreed with
                                Deptoffs that this approach would not preclude Albanian <gloss target="#t_RES1">res</gloss> being introduced in its traditional
                                form. Parliamentary handling of two parallel reses, therefore, would
                                be quite tricky and perhaps ultimately uncontrollable. This led to
                                general discussion of whether US and allies would have to get out in
                                front in handling dual <gloss target="#t_REP1">rep</gloss>
                                <gloss target="#t_RES1">res</gloss> or whether it might be
                                preferable let others carry the ball. General view was that if dual
                                    <gloss target="#t_REP1">rep</gloss> was to succeed, US and
                                allies would have to make major effort in its behalf.
                                    <persName>Scott</persName> stated his view that even those
                                countries which strongly favored dual <gloss target="#t_REP1">rep</gloss> solution are “waiting for Godot” and would take no
                                action until US intentions became clear.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>
                                <persName>Scott</persName> noted he returning to <persName corresp="#p_TRW1">Wellington</persName> Feb. 13 for
                                consultations and would discuss matter with Ministry. Both sides
                                expressed desire hold further meetings in near future.</item>
                        </list>
                        <closer>
                            <signed>
                                <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">
                                    <hi rend="strong">Rogers</hi>
                                </persName>
                            </signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>