<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>369. Memorandum From Secretary of State Rogers to President to President
                    Nixon</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">369</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1971-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1971-07-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">General Assembly</term>
                    <term ref="recidWOHtiPejGOPp" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005737"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Expulsion</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recHpD1vNO9Akm2Gx" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Diplomatic relations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-07-03T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-07-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="369"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d369">
                <head>369. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1"
                        type="from">Rogers</persName> to President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        type="to">Nixon</persName>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d369fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                        Central Files 1970–73, <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> 6 <gloss
                            target="#t_CHIC1">CHICOM</gloss>. Secret; Nodis. Drafted by <persName
                            corresp="#p_FHJ1">Feldman</persName> and cleared by Assistant
                        Secretaries <persName corresp="#p_DPS1">De Palma</persName> and <persName
                            corresp="#p_GM2">Green</persName>.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1971-07-03">July 3, 1971</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss>—Estimate of Chances for Success of
                        Dual Representation</item>
                </list>
                <p>The purpose of this memorandum is to bring to your attention circumstances which
                    have a bearing on your decision on Chinese Representation policy, as well as our
                    current estimates of the chances of passing a Dual Representation resolution at
                    the next General Assembly.</p>
                <p>We have had consultations with a limited number of countries on the Dual
                    Representation formula under consideration. None have stated a final position
                    and none have conducted a thorough canvass, but the following is a brief summary
                    of their immediate reaction:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Australia</hi>—Would support Dual Representation; prefers a
                    different formula; believes the Security Council seat should be offered the
                        <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> in the resolution; believes Dual
                    Representation unlikely to pass.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Belgium</hi>—Would support Dual Representation but believes
                    the resolution must offer the Security Council seat to Peking; expressed no view
                    on chances for passage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">France</hi>—Would not support Dual Representation; believes it
                    has a slight chance of passage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Japan</hi>—Would support the Dual Representation formula we
                    are considering; agrees it is desirable not to mention the Security Council
                    seat, but senior Foreign Ministry officials fear inclusion of such a provision
                    may be necessary for passage.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Netherlands</hi>—The Dutch Foreign Office has said it will
                    be unable to express an opinion before the new Dutch Government, to be formed at
                    the end of July, has had an opportunity to study our proposal; the Dutch believe
                    that the odds are probably against passage, particularly if the Security Council
                    seat is not mentioned.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">New Zealand</hi>—Would support Dual Representation but prefers
                    another formula; considers giving the Security Council seat to Peking essential
                    to success.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Thailand</hi>—Agrees Dual Representation is probably the only
                    alternative to <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> expulsion but fears the
                    resolution might not pass in any case.</p>
                <pb facs="0756" n="719" xml:id="pg_719"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">United Kingdom</hi>—Would not support Dual Representation;
                    strongly doubts it can pass.</p>
                <p>In our earlier estimates, at the time <gloss target="#t_NSSM1">NSSM</gloss>–107
                    was submitted in January and later when the National Security Council met in
                    March to discuss it, we gave our judgment that a suitable Dual Representation
                    formula could command strong majority support in the Assembly. At the time, we
                    foresaw a 20–25 vote majority in favor of Dual Representation. These estimates
                    were conditioned on the assumptions that the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss>
                    would begin lobbying actively for Dual Representation in the spring, would
                    co-sponsor the resolution, and that the resolution would contain language
                    (unopposed by us) to the effect that the Security Council seat would go to
                    Peking. I must caution that given present uncertainty regarding these
                    assumptions, the earlier estimates of a sizeable majority for Dual
                    Representation cannot now be relied upon.</p>
                <p>In part due to our delay, the situation has changed over time. Peking has managed
                    to create a bandwagon psychology by establishing or reestablishing diplomatic
                    relations with seven countries in the last six months. Also, the steps we
                    ourselves have taken toward normalization of trade and travel with Peking during
                    this period probably have led many countries to assume that we are emphasizing
                    our bilateral relations with the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> and
                    deemphasizing <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss>.</p>
                <p>It is extremely difficult to offer a reasonably hard estimate of the chances for
                    success now, particularly since we have been unable to consult widely on the
                    basis of a specific proposition and country positions are in process of change
                    in many cases. (“Hand-holding” consultations were necessary in some cases just
                    to gain more time.) However, we have formulated tentative in-house estimates,
                    and have compared notes with Australia and Japan. The latter, in particular, has
                    undertaken a world-wide canvass.</p>
                <p>The Japanese contacted 105 countries and received 69 replies, but at least
                    37—well over half—were the personal observations of middle-level Foreign
                    Ministry officials and therefore cannot be considered hard data. Of these 69
                    countries, about 25 might favor Dual Representation, about 26 might oppose and
                    18 were uncertain. The Japanese have formed their own in-house estimate for the
                    Assembly as a whole and believe Dual Representation might pass by about three
                    votes. This estimate assumes we will not make an all-out effort. Oddly, some
                    medium-level <gloss target="#t_GOJ1">GOJ</gloss> officials feel Dual
                    Representation might have a better chance if the Security Council seat were <hi
                        rend="italic">not</hi> mentioned in the resolution because certain friends
                    of the <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> might vote against it under those
                    circumstances. Our own analysis of their data does not support that judgment. Of
                    the countries checked by the Japanese, ten told them a Dual Representation
                    resolution must include language awarding the seat to Peking and only one felt
                    otherwise.</p>
                <pb facs="0757" n="720" xml:id="pg_720"/>
                <p>The Australian estimate is that Dual Representation might pass by about two
                    votes—but only if the Security Council seat were to go to Peking. If the Council
                    seat issue is finessed, the Australians believe the resolution is bound to
                    fail.</p>
                <p>Our own estimate is somewhat more optimistic—but only if the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> co-sponsors and begins soon to lobby
                    intensively, and only if the resolution (with our acquiescence) states that the
                    Council seat should go to Peking. Under these circumstances, we believe Dual
                    Representation could get a majority of 5–7 votes in its favor. This is still a
                    much smaller margin than we had estimated in March. If the <gloss
                        target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> does not co-sponsor, and if the Council seat is
                    not included, we believe the resolution could lose by up to 20 votes, <hi
                        rend="italic">even if the <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> lobbies hard
                        in its favor</hi>.</p>
                <p>I must emphasize the tentative nature of these forecasts. The closeness of the
                    vote in these three estimates—a majority of 2, or 3, or 5—shows that if you give
                    the go signal for Dual Representation, we will have to make a very big effort
                    and even then there can be no firm assurance of success.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">
                            <hi rend="strong">William P. Rogers</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
