<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1971-08-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1971-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="391" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d391">
                        <head>391. Memorandum From the Assistant Legal Adviser for East Asian and
                            Pacific Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SR2" type="from">Starr</persName>) to the Assistant Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_GM1" type="to">Green</persName>) and the Deputy
                            Assistant Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_BWG1">Brown</persName>) for East Asian and Pacific Affairs<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d391fn1">Source: National Archives, RG 59,
                                    <gloss target="#t_EA1">EA</gloss>/<gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> Files: Lot 75 D 76, Exdis, 1971. Confidential;
                                Exdis. Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_SR2">Robert I.
                                    Starr</persName>.</note>
                        </head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1971-08-05">August 5, 1971</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss>—Important Question</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>In our <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> guidance to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> (State 139831)<note n="2" xml:id="d391fn2">
                                <ref target="#d388">Document 388</ref>.</note> we did not indicate
                            whether the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> considers that a
                            proposal to deprive the <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> of
                            representation in the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> would constitute
                            an important question under paragraphs 2 or 3 of Article 18 of the
                            Charter. The <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> may press for an
                            explicit mention in any <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> resolution of
                            Article 6 and/or Article 18(2), and in any case they may seek <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> support for the position that action to
                            expel the <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> would come under paragraph
                            2 rather than paragraph 3 of Article 18. The question of the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> position on Article 18 may also be
                            posed by other delegations in New York as we get into the <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> issue.</p>
                        <p>Our <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> guidance to <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> states only that: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p>“We believe it is best that the <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss>
                                    Resolution not explicitly be tied to Article 18(2) (expulsion or
                                    suspension of rights of members), since this Article necessarily
                                    involves Article 5 or 6 (of the <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> Charter). On the other hand, it is unnecessary
                                    to tie the <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> explicitly to
                                    Article 18(3) (Assembly action to create a new category of
                                    important questions in addition to those cited in 18(2)). In
                                    order to preserve maximum tactical maneuverability, it is best
                                    to leave it open to delegations to decide for themselves whether
                                    they are supporting the resolution as an affirmation of Article
                                    18(2), or as a decision to add a new category as per Article
                                    18(3).</p>
                                <p>“… There should be no great problem in getting <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> sanction for this <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss>, though they may press for
                                    explicit mention of Article 6 and/or Article 18(2), and it is
                                    easy enough to explain its meaning to press and public.”</p>
                            </quote>
                        </p>
                        <p>Relying simply on Article 18, without indicating whether we believe
                            paragraph 2 or paragraph 3 is involved, may create a false impression
                            that our <gloss target="#t_IQ1">IQ</gloss> position is based on
                            paragraph 2. A speech by Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_PCH1">Phillips</persName> on the <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss>
                            issue in last year’s <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> debate (Tab
                                A)<note n="3" xml:id="d391fn3">Attached but not printed. <persName corresp="#p_PCH1">Phillips</persName>’ speech is printed in
                                Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, December 14,
                                1970, pp. 733–735.</note> contained references to the Charter
                            provisions on expulsion of a member and <pb facs="0810" n="773" xml:id="pg_773"/> led to a critical article in the <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi> by Harvard Professor Jerome Cohen (Tab B).<note n="4" xml:id="d391fn4">Attached but not printed; “China: A New
                                    <gloss target="#t_US1">U.S.</gloss> Move,” <hi rend="italic">The
                                    New York Times</hi>, November 18, 1970, p. 47.</note> Cohen read
                            the Phillips speech as contending that a simple majority decision of the
                                <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> to seat the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> and expel the <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> would constitute a Charter violation.</p>
                        <p>Cohen argued that such an interpretation, if accepted, would deprive the
                                <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> of flexibility for achieving a
                            political solution. He also noted that, should the Assembly reject that
                            interpretation and decide to settle the representation question by
                            simple majority vote, the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> position
                            would brand such action as illegitimate.</p>
                        <p>We had considered sending a clarifying letter to the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi>, in order to avoid the buildup of expectations that the
                                <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> would consider as illegal
                            adoption of last year’s Albanian resolution by less than a two-thirds
                            majority vote and without a Security Council recommendation. However, it
                            was agreed that further journalistic speculation would be more harmful
                            than beneficial, and a letter was sent instead to Professor Cohen making
                            it clear that the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> did not intend the
                            implications suggested by Cohen in his article. In the letter we made it
                            clear that the reference in the Phillips speech to Articles 6 and 18(2)
                            of the Charter did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> involve an assertion that
                            these provisions would apply as a matter of law. Rather, the references
                            were intended mainly for purposes of analogy—to buttress our position
                            that the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss>
                            <hi rend="italic">should</hi> consider the <gloss target="#t_CHIR1">Chirep</gloss> issue an important question, and not to argue that
                            it <hi rend="italic">necessarily must do</hi> so under the Charter.
                            (That letter has been reproduced in the April, 1971 issue of the <hi rend="italic">American Journal of International Law</hi>) (Tab
                                C).<note n="5" xml:id="d391fn5">Attached but not printed; <hi rend="italic">The American Journal of International Law</hi>,
                                Vol. 65, No. 2 (April 1971), pp. 396–397.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>I believe we would find it extremely difficult to make a persuasive legal
                            case for the proposition that expulsion of the <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> would involve Articles 6 and 18(2) of the Charter,
                            particularly in view of our position that seating the <gloss target="#t_PRC1">PRC</gloss> involves representation, and not
                            membership. Moreover, there are sound reasons of policy for avoiding a
                            situation in which the <gloss target="#t_USG1">USG</gloss> would have to
                            brand as illegal <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> action to deprive
                            the <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> of representation by less than a
                            two-thirds vote and without a Security Council recommendation. Such a
                            position would deny us necessary flexibility in dealing with the
                            essentially political issues involved.</p>
                        <p>Accordingly, if pressed and if we believe it necessary to take a more
                            forthcoming position, we should concede that the <gloss target="#t_UNGA1">UNGA</gloss> has discretion to decide whether or
                            not depriving the <gloss target="#t_ROC1">ROC</gloss> of representation
                            should be considered an important question. In other words, paragraph 3
                            and not paragraph 2 of Article 18 would be viewed as controlling.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>