<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>455. Report Prepared in the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1969-76v05</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d455</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">455</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1973-08-31T23:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1973-09-30T22:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="recKLzO66LIpHkUp2" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="peace"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037292"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Détente</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85085144"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Military assistance</term>
                    <term ref="rectqbCKMJaN5yPfG" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">U.S. policy</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">Bilateral relations</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1973-09-30T22:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1973-08-31T23:00:00-05:00" n="455"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d455">
                <head>455. Report Prepared in the Department of State<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d455fn1">Source: Department of State, Bureau of Public Affairs,
                        Office of the Historian. Top Secret; Nodis. This is Research Project No.
                        1034, prepared in the Historical Studies Division of the Historian’s Office.
                        As noted in the Foreword to the 172-page report (not printed): “This study
                        was undertaken in response to a request from the Bureau of International
                        Organization Affairs. The research and writing were done by Louis J. Smith
                        under the immediate direction of Homer L. Calkin, Chief of the Special
                        Studies Branch, Historical Studies Division.” The study focuses on
                        Department of State efforts and relied on materials now in the National
                        Archives, RG 59, Central Files, but does not take into account documentation
                        from the White House or National Security Council.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date
                            ana="#date_imprecise-inferred-from-date-rules" calendar="gregorian"
                            notAfter="1973-09-30T23:59:59-04:00"
                            notBefore="1973-09-01T00:00:00-04:00" when="1973-09">September
                            1973</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">UNITED STATES EFFORTS TO SECURE DUAL REPRESENTATION FOR CHINA IN
                    THE UNITED NATIONS (NOVEMBER 1970–OCTOBER 1971)</p>
                <p rend="center">SUMMARY</p>
                <p>On August 2, 1971, Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">William P.
                        Rogers</persName> announced that the United States would support a dual
                    representation solution to the Chinese representation problem at the upcoming
                    26th session of the United Nations General Assembly. The Secretary’s
                    announcement marked a departure from a policy which had endured for more than
                    twenty years. For the first time since the Chinese representation question had
                    become an annual fixture in the General Assembly, American officials dropped
                    their opposition to the seating of the People’s Republic of China and
                    concentrated upon preserving a place in the United Nations for the Republic of
                    China. In part, the revision of American policy was prompted by the climate of
                    opinion which had developed in the General Assembly in favor of seating the
                    People’s Republic of China. In a larger sense, the adoption by the United States
                    of a dual representation policy was part of the <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >Nixon</persName> administration’s continuing effort to adjust to the
                    reality of mainland China without severing American ties with the Government on
                    Taiwan. On July 15, President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                    dramatically underscored his desire to achieve a détente with the People’s
                    Republic of China by announcing his intention to visit Peking. In making his
                    announcement, the President offered the assurance that the United States did not
                    intend to improve its relations with the People’s Republic of China at the
                    expense of old friends. Secretary <persName corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName>’
                    subsequent announcement of a policy favoring membership in the United Nations
                    for both Chinese Governments was in the spirit of the President’s assurance.</p>
                <pb facs="0951" n="914" xml:id="pg_914"/>
                <p>The change in policy which the Secretary announced on August 2 had been under
                    active consideration in Washington for more than eight months. On November 19,
                    1970, the National Security Council had requested interdepartmental studies
                    treating China policy in general and the Chinese representation question in
                    particular. The studies had to take into account Premier <persName
                        corresp="#p_CE1">Chou En-lai</persName>’s vigorous campaign to break the
                    diplomatic isolation which the People’s Republic of China had known during the
                    period of the “Cultural Revolution”, a campaign which bore important fruit on
                    November 20, 1970 when a majority of the members of the General Assembly voted
                    for the first time to seat the representatives of the Peking Government in the
                    United Nations (the Republic of China retained its place because of the General
                    Assembly’s determination that any change in the representation of China
                    constituted an “Important Question” and required a two-thirds majority to
                    effect). Also, American officials were inclined to encourage the People’s
                    Republic of China to play a larger, more normal diplomatic role. Specialists
                    throughout the United States Government agreed that it would be very difficult
                    and unwise to continue to exclude Peking’s representatives from the United
                    Nations. At the same time, those participating in the policy review agreed that
                    the United States should continue to support the international position of the
                    Republic of China. A dual representation approach to the problem of China’s seat
                    in the United Nations offered an obvious answer. Dual representation was an idea
                    which had enjoyed some support in the General Assembly in years past as an
                    equitable solution which would contribute to a more universal organization. The
                    arguments for and against a change to a dual representation policy were laid out
                    for President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> by his advisers at a
                    meeting of the National Security Council on March 25, 1971.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d455fn2">See <ref target="#d342">Document 342</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Similar policy reviews were taking place in other capitals. American officials
                    were most interested in the conclusions being reached in Japan, Australia, and
                    New Zealand, which had been the closest associates of the United States in the
                    previous strategy of defining Chinese representation as an “Important Question”.
                    They were also concerned about Belgium, which was the country most prominently
                    identified with the concept of dual representation, and about Great Britain,
                    which was hinting that it intended to throw its considerable weight behind the
                    “Albanian” resolution to give the Chinese seat to Peking. Conversations on
                    Chinese representation with these countries could not be postponed until the
                    policy review had been completed in Washington. As early as December, 1970,
                    cautious and non-committal discussions had begun. By the middle of March, there
                    was general agreement <pb facs="0952" n="915" xml:id="pg_915"/> among the
                    specialists in Washington, Wellington, Canberra, and Tokyo that a dual
                    representation approach offered the best hope of preserving a place in the
                    United Nations for the Republic of China. The Belgian Government indicated that
                    it was anxious to play a part in promoting a dual representation resolution.
                    Only the British, among the allies initially sounded, expressed no sympathy for
                    what they saw as a “two-China” solution.</p>
                <p>Before a dual representation policy could be adopted, the Republic of China had
                    to lend at least tacit approval to the idea. Less than two weeks after the vote
                    on the Albanian resolution at the 25th General Assembly, Secretary <persName
                        corresp="#p_RWP1">Rogers</persName> began the task of persuading the Taipei
                    Government that a new approach to Chinese representation was necessary. At
                    first, the line taken by officials in Taipei was that, with a redoubled effort,
                    the usual Important Question strategy could be made to prevail again. Gradually,
                    however, indications grew that the Government of the Republic of China
                    recognized the situation and would make a realistic effort to preserve its place
                    in the United Nations. In April, Robert D. Murphy, former Under Secretary of
                    State for Political Affairs, traveled to Taipei as the personal representative
                    of President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName> to discuss Chinese
                    representation with President <persName corresp="#p_CKS2">Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName>. Ambassador Murphy told <persName>Chiang</persName> that
                    the United States intended to continue to honor its treaty commitments and to
                    provide military assistance to the Republic of China. Thus reassured,
                        <persName>Chiang</persName> implied that he could accept a dual
                    representation resolution which did not affect the Republic of China’s seat on
                    the Security Council. Murphy assured <persName>Chiang</persName> that the United
                    States would oppose any effort to deprive the Republic of China of its Security
                    Council seat. <persName>Chiang</persName>’s conversation with Murphy set a
                    standard for the remarkable flexibility which the Republic of China demonstrated
                    throughout the dual representation effort. American officials recognized,
                    however, that the flexibility of the Republic of China was never more than
                    tactical, being based on the calculation that Peking might reject any dual
                    representation resolution and would certainly refuse an offer which did not
                    include the Security Council seat.</p>
                <p>The Republic of China’s cooperation was essential to the process of developing a
                    dual representation policy. American officials recognized that the commitment to
                    defend the Republic of China’s seat in the Security Council might not be
                    possible to sustain, but they were willing to make an effort. A full-scale
                    canvass of opinion among the members of the General Assembly was required to
                    determine the type of dual representation formula which would command the
                    support necessary to succeed. Until July, however, the White House restrained
                    the State Department from discussing the Chinese representation question with
                    more than a handful of close allies. The President’s announcement on July 15 of
                    his intention to visit Peking made it evident <pb facs="0953" n="916"
                        xml:id="pg_916"/> that the decision on Chinese representation had to be
                    timed to coordinate with a larger reordering of <gloss target="#t_US1"
                        >U.S.</gloss> policy on China. The President’s announcement freed the
                    Department to move forward with the dual representation initiative.</p>
                <p>The lobbying effort in support of the dual representation approach began
                    immediately after the Secretary’s announcement of policy on August 2. Department
                    specialists were aware that time was short by then. Nonetheless, they had to
                    struggle with the difficult cosponsorship problem before they could formulate a
                    definite dual representation resolution and lobby in support of an established
                    position. The key to unraveling the co-sponsorship problem lay in the matter of
                    China’s Security Council seat. Many of the countries important to the dual
                    representation effort indicated that they would not co-sponsor unless the dual
                    representation resolution contained a recommendation that the People’s Republic
                    of China be given the seat in the Security Council. Although the Republic of
                    China remained opposed, United States officials finally decided that they would
                    have to support a “complex” dual representation resolution. On September 10,
                    telegrams announcing the American decision went to potential co-sponsors, and
                    the co-sponsorship problem fell into place. The most encouraging development
                    occurred on the day on which the dual representation resolution was submitted to
                    the United Nations Secretariat, along with a revised Important Question
                    resolution. On that day, September 22, the Government of Japan put aside the
                    serious domestic problems occasioned by the controversy over Chinese
                    representation and agreed to join the list of co-sponsors.</p>
                <p>Once the resolutions were formulated, and the co-sponsors established, the State
                    Department could turn its full attention to the business of building support for
                    the dual representation initiative. An intense, world-wide campaign was mounted
                    in conjunction with the other principal co-sponsors, and it was maintained until
                    the votes were taken on October 25. The effort was mounted in the face of
                    daunting odds and narrowly failed.</p>
                <p>The sponsors of the Albanian resolution were able to build upon a base which had
                    been established over the years and upon momentum carrying over from the
                    majority support they had enjoyed at the 25th General Assembly. They profited
                    from Peking’s continuing campaign to improve its bilateral relations and from
                    the reiterated insistence that the People’s Republic of China would never enter
                    the United Nations under the terms of a dual representation resolution. The
                    adamant stance taken by the People’s Republic of China did much to offset the
                    appeal which dual representation had for those countries concerned with equity
                    and a universal world organization. A number of conservative countries, on the
                    other hand, had no interest in pursuing <pb facs="0954" n="917" xml:id="pg_917"
                    /> the ideal of universality at the expense of welcoming representatives from
                    Peking into the United Nations. Those supporting dual representation had little
                    time to alter preconceptions and establish the credibility of an untested
                    proposition. Throughout the lobbying campaign, United States officials had to
                    work against the widespread suspicion that President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                        >Nixon</persName>’s forthcoming trip to Peking had been paved by a secret
                    understanding with regard to Chinese representation. In the circumstances, the
                    remarkable thing about the effort to preserve a place for the Republic of China
                    in the 26th General Assembly was not that it failed, but that it failed so
                    narrowly.</p>
                <p>[Omitted here are the body of the paper, pages 6–133, and Annexes I–V.]</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
