<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>200. Memorandum of Telephone Conversation Between the Under Secretary of
                    State (Ball) and the President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    () and the President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    (Bundy))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d200</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">200</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-11-21T12:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-11-21T12:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recuUFhBncrUg6V07" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85015466"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Bombers</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-11-21T12:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-11-21T12:00:00-05:00" n="200"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d200">
                <head>200. Memorandum of Telephone Conversation Between the Under Secretary of State
                        (<persName corresp="#p_BGW1" type="from">Ball</persName>) and the
                    President’s Special Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName
                        corresp="#p_BMG2" type="to">Bundy</persName>)<note n="0" type="source"
                        xml:id="d200fn0">Source: Department of State, <persName corresp="#p_BGW1"
                            >Ball</persName> Files: Lot 72 D 272. Telephone Conversations—Cuba. No
                        classification marking.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1962-11-21T12:00:00-05:00"
                            >November 21, 1962, noon.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: I had a talk with Jack McCloy this
                        morning.<note n="1" xml:id="d200fn1">See <ref target="#d199">Document
                            199</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: So did I.<note n="2"
                        xml:id="d200fn2">No record of <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>’s
                        conversation has been found.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: I have a feeling that we may be
                    running down two somewhat divergent tracks here.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: I have exactly the same worry and
                    was about to call you about it.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: I wonder if we shouldn’t get Jack
                    down here for 4 p.m. and try to resolve this before we head into a long week
                    where there can be no resolution.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: Let’s talk about your track.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: There are two schools of thought
                    over here. One of them would be to try to bring this to some kind of a
                    conclusion, even though the formulation would differ from the formulation of
                    yesterday along this line: that if we can be assured either through appropriate
                        <gloss target="#t_UN1">UN</gloss> verification arrangements or through our
                    own means that all offensive weapons are removed and not reinstituted, then Cuba
                    has no fear of an invasion. That suggests that we are not going to invade as
                    long as we keep ourselves … .</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: Not going to invade on this
                    ground. We are always going to have to reserve on other grounds. To form
                    language for that is not too tough.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: Yes. Something along this line “As
                    a party to solemn treaty commitments.” (<persName corresp="#p_BGW1"
                        >Ball</persName> reads draft of this morning.)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: Yes. This is my track, to be
                    honest with you. That is what I would like to do. Does anyone think that we are
                    really going to get much more than that?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: I have Martin here at the moment,
                    for example. He says the Latins will die; they will come to a very bad
                    conclusion—that we shouldn’t give any kind of pledge except on a condition of
                    adequate verification and safeguards which of course we are never going to
                    get.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: That isn’t much of a pledge. It
                    seems to me [what] I would say to Martin, and he would say to his Ambassadors,
                    would be “We have said what we always have said.” What we did was to reiterate
                    our existing <pb facs="0535" n="507" xml:id="pg_507"/> policy in return for
                    which we got 30 bombers and 40 missiles out of there, etc. Those who aren’t
                    going to be satisfied with anything short of an invasion of Cuba aren’t going to
                    have their views changed by the character of the noises we make while we’re not
                    invading Cuba, either.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: I think that may be. We ought to
                    settle pretty solidly on it, however.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: I agree to that. I don’t think
                    there is any doubt what the <gloss target="#t_USUN1">USUN</gloss> thinks; if we
                    ask them without <persName corresp="#p_SAEII1">Stevenson</persName>, we create
                    trouble. If we ask <persName corresp="#p_SAEII1">Stevenson</persName>, we get
                    filibuster.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: What we can do is try to get it on
                    … .</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: Where is the Secretary on
                    this?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: I talked to him earlier. I haven’t
                    had time. I don’t think we would have difficulty with him on this, but I am not
                    sure. I’d hate to speak for him on this.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: I’m pretty clear this is the line
                    the President will want to go on. He wants to get a reasonable sort of “well
                    this is all we can give you, because this is all you can give us with the
                    Russians”, and then go on with them to wider topics and let Fidel simmer while
                    over the next six weeks … I think the President would like to or be prepared to
                    trade a certain thickening of our assurance against a certain thickening of
                    their affirmation that they are leaving.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: Then the language I suggest “so
                    long as we can be assured either …” you don’t think that would be too bad?</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: No. That is the sort of thing we
                    could give to <persName corresp="#p_KVV2">Kuznetsov</persName> to chew on at the
                    end of the day today. Then there would be a hassle in which it is clear that we
                    say to him “Look, we can do this better if your people would do what you haven’t
                    been able to get them to do. The best we can do in the light of what we
                    initially said is to say that as long as we’re satisfied, we’ll be satisfied.”
                    Which isn’t bad at all.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: All right. I think we ought to be
                    prepared.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: Why don’t you prepare a paper on
                    that framework, and if anyone in the Department wants to argue the case for a
                    more rigorous assertion of interlocking declarations, it is even possible that
                    we could present them both to <persName corresp="#p_KVV2">Kuznetsov</persName>
                    and say “Look if you can get this …”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: I am sure he would want the
                    alternative because I think they have really given up on the first one.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: That’s right and it seems to me a
                    question of if you spend a day on that or not. I don’t frankly see the point in
                    it.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: Let me get it up both ways.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: You had better have it out with
                    your Secretary.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: Of course, I will.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: I know <persName
                        corresp="#p_MNRS1">McNamara</persName> if, in fact, the trend line of Soviet
                    presence in Cuba is downward, he doesn’t see much point in trying to bargain <pb
                        facs="0536" n="508" xml:id="pg_508"/> for something we are never going to
                    get and would be perfectly willing to give something that perhaps went a shade
                    beyond what the President actually gave yesterday. One way to go at this would
                    be for <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1">McCloy</persName> to begin with <persName
                        corresp="#p_KVV2">Kuznetsov</persName> “Didn’t you read the President’s
                    press conference?”</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BGW1">Ball</persName>: I think that’s right. Of course
                        <persName corresp="#p_KNS2">Khrushchev</persName> may want something in the
                        <gloss target="#t_SC1">SC</gloss>. I think <persName corresp="#p_MCJJ1"
                        >McCloy</persName> has probably indicated … .</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">Bundy</persName>: That doesn’t break my heart. (He
                    mentioned <persName corresp="#p_SAEII1">Stevenson</persName>’s “rough time” with
                        <persName corresp="#p_KVV2">Kuznetsov</persName> yesterday.)<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d200fn3">As described in <ref target="#d199">Document
                        199</ref>.</note> We perhaps ought to meet a few minutes before 4 over here
                    to see what we’ve got. You might send over what you’ve got in advance.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
