<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>231. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Bundy) to the Under Secretary of State () to the Under Secretary of
                    State (Ball))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1961-63v11</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d231</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">231</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1962-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1962-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recjZMVWaEjJKMgQF" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="economic-sanctions"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85042665"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Trade embargo</term>
                    <term ref="recIJ42jRCW9DxFlH" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005773"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Medical supplies</term>
                    <term ref="recCP2IC3LozXMzXn" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2022004495"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Surveillance</term>
                    <term ref="recwXdagbfSBlXglR" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="law-of-the-sea">International waters</term>
                    <term ref="recl1U5J9GBlgvmjh" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general">Military contingency planning</term>
                    <term ref="recWa3XmQPfPNRhkx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85121579"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="recSkg5rdjWW1fsS7" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85126307"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Spare parts</term>
                    <term ref="recXok31u2ezCmhNk" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="recdQFWhBa87w3zAK" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029120"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Communism</term>
                    <term ref="recz6YHYRY8K7jQX1" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85107443"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Propaganda</term>
                    <term ref="recWvvPjLhJgF9yYo" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005616"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Training</term>
                    <term ref="recAlkNJ122vPe7Jb" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007241"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Armed forces</term>
                    <term ref="rec9FMZD7j350k99B" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038202"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Diplomats</term>
                    <term ref="recUkDvsgHuU90wRT" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85110385"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Radio</term>
                    <term ref="rec2p8MfOFI4NR3V8" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129492"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Submarine</term>
                    <term ref="recAsWFxRUa5DhtTM" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85133456"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Television</term>
                    <term ref="reczKUnfSubMJ9Ff6" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85129663"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1962-12-06T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1962-12-06T00:00:00-05:00" n="231"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d231">
                <head>231. Memorandum From the President’s Special Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BMG2" type="from">Bundy</persName>) to the Under
                    Secretary of State (<persName corresp="#p_BGW1" type="to">Ball</persName>)<note
                        n="0" type="source" xml:id="d231fn0">Source: Department of State, <gloss
                            target="#t_SS1">S/S</gloss> Files: Lot 65 D 438, ExCom Meetings,
                        December 4, 1962. Top Secret; Sensitive.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1962-12-06">December 6, 1962</date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>We agreed that I would send you a summary of the informal comments made on the
                    draft memorandum on “Future Policy toward Cuba”<note n="1" xml:id="d231fn1">The
                        draft memorandum printed as an attachment was attached to a copy of this
                        memorandum in the Kennedy Library, National Security Files, Meetings and
                        Memoranda Series, Executive Committee, Meetings, Vol. III, 33-37,
                        12/6/62-12/17/62.</note> which was discussed in the Executive Committee on
                    Tuesday, December 4th.<note n="2" xml:id="d231fn2">Discussion of the draft
                        memorandum was not included in the summary record, see <ref target="#d226"
                            >Document 226</ref>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>First, it was generally agreed that there should be a reorganization of our
                    machinery for Cuban action. In particular, there seemed to be general support
                    for the idea of an Office of Cuban Affairs which could be public and above
                    board, and which might do a more effective job with free Cubans and others
                    concerned with the hopes for post-<persName>Castro</persName> Cuba. You and I
                    agreed after the meeting that you would explore the availability of a
                    particularly well-qualified individual to head this office.</p>
                <p>With respect to the draft memorandum itself, the following general comments were
                    made: <pb facs="0615" n="587" xml:id="pg_587"/>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>The memorandum is correct in recommending that no general policy be
                            approved or set in motion until the current discussions with the Soviets
                            on Cuba have developed somewhat further.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>The proposed action in the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> should
                            not be framed sharply until we know more clearly what kind of resolution
                            is likely to obtain unanimous or nearly unanimous support. Our current
                            posture in the <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> is so strong that we
                            should not weaken it for marginal advantages.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Paragraphs 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 of the draft statement seemed
                            approximately correct; paragraph 7 needed further development in order
                            to distinguish desirable from undesirable travel to Cuba; paragraph 8
                            should make it clearer that it is Cuban funds whose transfer needs to be
                            surveyed and controlled if possible; paragraphs 9 and 10 need to be
                            spelled out carefully in cooperation with the other agencies primarily
                            concerned.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The covert annex was considered only very briefly, but the preliminary sense of
                    the meeting was that covert activities should be concentrated upon improvement
                    in the collection of intelligence for the immediate future, and that we should
                    not plan early sabotage activities.</p>
                <p>Other items in the covert annex were not properly considered.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BMG2">
                            <hi rend="strong">McG. Bundy</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">
                        <hi rend="strong">Attachment</hi>
                    </note>
                    <note n="3" xml:id="d231fn3">See <ref target="#d231fn1">footnote 1</ref>. Top
                        Secret. Drafted on December 3, although no drafter is indicated.</note>
                    <head>Draft Memorandum for President <persName corresp="#p_KJF2"
                            >Kennedy</persName>
                    </head>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Future Policy toward Cuba</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Policy</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Our ultimate objective with respect to Cuba remains the overthrow of the
                        Castro regime and its replacement by one sharing the aims of the Free World.
                        Our immediate objectives are to weaken the regime; frustrate its subversive
                        intentions; further reduce its influence in the Hemisphere; and increase the
                        cost to the Bloc of sustaining the regime (or split the regime off from the
                        Bloc).</p>
                    <p>A policy of containing, undermining, discrediting and isolating the Castro
                        regime through the exercise of all feasible diplomatic economic, <pb
                            facs="0616" n="588" xml:id="pg_588"/> psychological and other pressures
                        will achieve these immediate objectives and could create propitious
                        conditions in Cuba for further advance toward our ultimate objective.</p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Courses of Action</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The following overt<note n="4" xml:id="d231fn4">For the program of covert
                            actions please see Annex A. [Footnote in the source text. A typed note
                            in the margin of the source text reads: “This annex will be circulated
                            to ExCom members at a meeting called to discuss the memo.”]</note>
                        courses of action should be undertaken: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>
                                <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss> action: condemning the Castro
                                regime for its duplicity; extending the trade embargo to all items
                                except foodstuffs, medicines and medical supplies; further limiting
                                air and sea communications between the Hemisphere and Cuba;
                                authorizing air and other surveillance; and warning Cuba against
                                continued promotion of subversive and sabotage activities.</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Establishment of Caribbean security arrangements through
                                ministerial level meetings of the Caribbean countries for the
                                purposes of reaching agreement on increasing the intensity of
                                surveillance of coastal and international waters; increased
                                surveillance and control of land boundaries; increased control over
                                subversive activities within national boundaries; systematic
                                exchange of intelligence information; and, development of procedures
                                for coordination of military contingency planning for
                                emergencies.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Application of the four-point shipping restrictions <gloss
                                    target="#t_re1">re</gloss> Cuba.</item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>Inclusion by <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> of Cuba on the
                                list of countries to which shipment of <gloss target="#t_COCOM1"
                                    >COCOM</gloss> list (strategic) items is prohibited.</item>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>Discussion of Free World industrial nations from shipping crucial
                                spare parts and equipment to Cuba, not on the <gloss
                                    target="#t_COCOM1">COCOM</gloss> list.</item>
                            <label>6.</label>
                            <item>Persuasion of non-Bloc nations to limit their airlines service to
                                Cuba and to withhold transit rights to Soviet aircraft serving
                                Cuba.</item>
                            <label>7.</label>
                            <item>Persuasion of Latin American nations to limit the travel of their
                                nationals to Cuba and to intensify measures to prevent agents and
                                groups of international communism from carrying on their subversive
                                activities.</item>
                            <label>8.</label>
                            <item>Persuasion of appropriate <gloss target="#t_OAS1">OAS</gloss>
                                organs to study urgently the transfer of funds to the other American
                                Republics for subversive purposes, the plan of subversive propaganda
                                and the utilization of Cuba as a base for training in subversive
                                techniques; and to make recommendations to the member states
                                regarding counter-measures.</item>
                            <label>9.</label>
                            <item>Maintenance of currently enhanced <gloss target="#t_VOA1"
                                    >VOA</gloss> mediumwave facilities beamed to Cuba and adoption
                                by <gloss target="#t_VOA1">VOA</gloss> of a more aggressive line
                                toward Cuba.</item>
                            <pb facs="0617" n="589" xml:id="pg_589"/>
                            <label>10.</label>
                            <item>Facilitation of Cuban exiles’ entry into the United States Armed
                                Forces for training, and formation of reserve units
                                thereafter.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="flushleft">
                        <hi rend="italic">Timing</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>We should surface our program of isolating and weakening Cuba when it becomes
                        clear that our discussions on Cuba with the Soviets are unlikely to be
                        fruitful. Actions with respect to Cuba which may contribute substantially to
                        creating a situation calling for United States military action should be
                        withheld until the Soviet combat units have been removed from Cuba or
                        efforts to persuade the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss> to remove them
                        have failed.</p>
                </frus:attachment>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <note rend="inline" type="source">
                        <hi rend="strong">Annex A</hi>
                    </note>
                    <note n="5" xml:id="d231fn5">Top Secret. Drafted on December 1 although no
                        drafter is indicated.</note>
                    <head>Covert Courses of Action</head>
                    <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Support fully the efforts of certain Cuban exiles, who are associated
                            with the original aims of the 26 July movement and who believe that the
                            Castro regime can be overthrown from within, in order that they may: a)
                            cause a split in the leadership of the regime at the national or
                            provincial levels; and, b) create a political base of popular opposition
                            to the regime.</item>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Continue to support the Cuban Revolutionary Council in its efforts to
                            maintain a degree of order and unity in the Cuban exile
                            community.</item>
                        <label>3.</label>
                        <item>Assist selected Cuban exile groups to encourage the Cuban people to
                            engage in minor acts of sabotage.</item>
                        <label>4.</label>
                        <item>Utilize selected Cuban exiles to sabotage key Cuban installations in
                            such a manner that the action can plausibly be attributed to Cubans in
                            Cuba.</item>
                        <label>5.</label>
                        <item>Sabotage Cuban cargo and shipping, and Bloc cargo and shipping to
                            Cuba.</item>
                        <label>6.</label>
                        <item>Encourage the defection of Cuban diplomats, officials and delegates
                            abroad.</item>
                        <label>7.</label>
                        <item>Continue to assist and guide Cuban exiles in their radio broadcasts to
                            Cuba.</item>
                        <label>8.</label>
                        <item>Encourage and assist Cuban exiles in developing a capability to launch
                            balloons carrying leaflets and other propaganda materials from
                            international waters to Cuba.</item>
                        <pb facs="0618" n="590" xml:id="pg_590"/>
                        <label>9.</label>
                        <item>Develop more fully a clandestine “Voice of Free Cuba” radio capability
                            either in Cuba or from a submarine in international waters.</item>
                        <label>10.</label>
                        <item>Develop more fully a capability for covertly intruding upon Cuban
                            television broadcasts.</item>
                        <label>11.</label>
                        <item>Unless future developments warrant change, emphasize the following
                            themes in covert propaganda output: a) the need to return to the
                            original aims of the Cuban revolution; b) the Castro regime’s betrayal
                            of these aims; and, c)<persName>Castro</persName>, as a pawn in the
                            Soviet expansionist game, having subordinated Cuba’s national interests
                            to those of the <gloss target="#t_USSR1">USSR</gloss>.</item>
                        <label>12.</label>
                        <item>Assist, through subsidy if necessary, non-Bloc importers of Cuban
                            sugar to find alternative sources of supply.</item>
                    </list>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
