<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>229. Memorandum From Willam B. Quandt of the National Security Council Staff
                    to the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Brzezinski))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v09Ed2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d229</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">229</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-03-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-03-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recSaEMkYGbM62K53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85064698"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="rec7JIWfjVoMs1M5p" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2018001956"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Normalization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-03-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-03-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="229"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d229">
                <head>229. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_QWB_1">Willam B. Quandt</persName>
                    of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d229fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box 55, Middle East: Peace Talks
                        Between Egypt and Israel, 1–3/79. Secret. Sent for information. A stamped
                        notation reads: “<gloss target="#t_ZB_1">ZB</gloss> has seen.”</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-03-21">March 21, 1979</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Unresolved Issues (U)</item>
                </list>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Subphasing of withdrawal.</hi> Israel is sticking with the
                    position of not withdrawing from the Alma field until the end of the nine-month
                        period.<note n="2" xml:id="d229fn2">When discussing the issue of Israeli
                        withdrawal from the Sinai oil fields with <persName corresp="#p_LSW_1"
                            >Lewis</persName> on March 20, <persName corresp="#p_BM_2"
                            >Begin</persName> “articulated with great animation his resistance” to
                        reducing the 9-month withdrawal period. “Israel, he said, does not want to
                        activate the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> oil supply agreement if it
                        is not absolutely necessary.” On the oil supply agreement, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> added that his “only quarrel” with
                        the present formulation “is that he prefers two distinct periods of ten and
                        five years duration, rather than a single period of fifteen years. <persName
                            corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> said he strongly prefers the latter,
                        thus allowing [the] 1975 [<gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> oil]
                        Commitment to [former Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak] <persName
                            corresp="#p_RY_1">Rabin</persName> to fade into the history books. I
                            [<persName corresp="#p_LSW_1">Lewis</persName>] told <persName
                            corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> there was absolutely no chance that
                        we would agree to an extension to twenty years of the <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> commitment and <persName corresp="#p_BM_2"
                            >Begin</persName> replied he had no intention of requesting one.”
                        (Telegram 5599 from Tel Aviv, March 20; National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Bureau of Near Eastern and South Asian
                        Affairs, Files of <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Alfred L.
                        Atherton</persName>, Lot 80D166, Box 8, Pre-Signing Negotiations: Cairo, Tel
                        Aviv, Washington &amp; New York, 3/20–26/79)</note> Egypt says this is
                    contrary to the concept of subphasing and has suspended its agreement to send an
                    Ambassador one month after the completion of the interim withdrawal. This
                    morning, Roy, Hal and I developed a possible compromise proposal: withdrawal
                    from the oilfield in six months; arrangements to insure continued supply of oil
                    to Israel until normalization of relations begins; exchange of Ambassadors on
                    schedule. The six month figure is eminently defensible. We <pb facs="0829"
                        n="794" xml:id="pg_794"/> referred to the subphasing as discussed at Blair
                    House. That means four or six months, depending on which set of talks is
                    referred to. A message to <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> will
                    probably be needed. (S)</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Agreement on Oil.</hi> The Israelis have
                    submitted a counterdraft<note n="3" xml:id="d229fn3">The text of the Israeli
                        counter-draft has not been found. On March 18, the United States amended the
                        draft text of the oil supply agreement from the originally proposed fifteen
                        year guarantee. Under the new formulation, the agreement would become
                        effective for a five-year period “commencing blank months following the
                        entry into force of the treaty of peace between Egypt and Israel, and shall
                        be extended for an additional period commencing at the end of that five-year
                        period and ending ten years later, at which time the arrangement will
                        terminate.” (Telegram <gloss target="#t_Tosec_1">Tosec</gloss> 30001/67721
                        to Tel Aviv, March 19; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                        59, Central Foreign Policy File, P850050–2617)</note> which would include a
                    price subsidy formula and an option to extend the guarantee almost indefinitely.
                    (C)</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Memorandum of Agreement on Assurances.</hi> Senator
                        <persName corresp="#p_CFF_1">Church</persName> has said that anything more
                    than what we have in our draft would virtually constitute a treaty and would
                    require Senate approval. The Israelis are asking for significant changes.
                    (C)</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Unilateral Steps Letter.</hi>
                    <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> wants to discuss this with the
                    President. His initial reaction suggests that we will have problems.<note n="4"
                        xml:id="d229fn4">On March 20, <persName corresp="#p_LSW_1">Lewis</persName>
                        presented <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> with a draft version
                        of the letter for <persName corresp="#p_KM_1">Khalil</persName> on
                        unilateral actions Israel would take guaranteeing freedoms for the
                        Palestinians of the West Bank and Gaza. In response, <persName
                            corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> stated that he would take up the
                        matter with <persName corresp="#p_CJE_2">Carter</persName> in Washington and
                        that “he wished at this time only to remind us that during his discussion
                        with President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_2">Carter</persName> on this issue,
                        the President had asked only about the prevailing repeat prevailing
                        situation on the West Bank and Gaza regarding freedom of movement, freedom
                        of political activity, etc. <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>
                        stressed that it is the particulars of the prevailing situation—which will
                        continue to obtain in the future—which should be conveyed on his behalf by
                        President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_2">Carter</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>.” (Telegram 931 from Jerusalem, March
                        20; National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                        Foreign Policy File, P850011–1318) For the final version of the letter from
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJE_2">Carter</persName> to <persName
                            corresp="#p_KM_1">Khalil</persName>, signed March 26, see <ref
                            target="#d238">Document 238</ref>.</note> (C)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
