<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>287. Memorandum From Robert Hunter of the National Security Council Staff to
                    the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs ( of the National
                    Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs (Brzezinski))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v09Ed2</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d287</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">287</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-08-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="near-east" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="near-east">Middle East</term>
                    <term ref="rec6XfF2Oe1IjakB2" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85018579"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Cables</term>
                    <term ref="recvMZKA8yxNgdF29" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85143088"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Veto</term>
                    <term ref="recnh2EQDroagrN9x" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh96003162"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arab</term>
                    <term ref="rec2BhKQJFZQOflnk" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="refugees"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007585"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Refugees</term>
                    <term ref="rec5qieZtvCCeYwS5" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85106517"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Press conference</term>
                    <term ref="recQ5xJqddmHqhjNl" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85077024"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Limitation</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-08-20T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-08-20T00:00:00-05:00" n="287"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d287">
                <head>287. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_HR_1">Robert Hunter</persName> of
                    the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName>)<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d287fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security
                        Affairs, Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box 51, Middle East: 8–12/79.
                        Secret; Sensitive; Outside the System. Sent for information. In an undated
                        handwritten note, <persName corresp="#p_BZK_1">Brzezinski</persName> set out
                        a list of short points under the headings of “substance” and “process.”
                        (Ibid.)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1979-08-20">August 20, 1979</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Middle East Trip: the Way Forward (U)</item>
                </list>
                <p>As you will have seen from <persName corresp="#p_SRS_1">Bob Strauss</persName>’
                    reporting cables to the President,<note n="2" xml:id="d287fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d283">Documents 283</ref>, <ref target="#d285">285</ref>, and
                            <ref target="#d286">286</ref>.</note> the trip produced even more
                    negative reactions to our <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Resolution plan
                    than we expected in calculating the price to be paid. The Israeli reaction went
                    about as far as thought; but all of us were unprepared for the vehemence with
                    which <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> flatly opposed the idea of a
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>-introduced resolution—or indeed <hi
                        rend="italic">any</hi> resolution at this time. <persName corresp="#p_SRS_1"
                        >Strauss</persName> had an Ambassador with him at all times who later
                    prepared the cables for his signature. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName>’s reasoning was as follows:</p>
                <p>—any resolution which scares the Israelis is a mistake—and the <gloss
                        target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> resolution would do so;</p>
                <p>—there is a good chance for progress in the autonomy talks, and in the
                    Egyptian-Israeli relationship which needs to underpin anything else, provided
                    they are left alone and the process is not disrupted by our (unnecessary)
                    actions; and</p>
                <p>—even if a resolution were accepted by the <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>,
                    this would <hi rend="italic">not</hi> be desirable, since it would lead to the
                    entry of disruptive elements into the talks themselves before they are
                    well-established; in fact, <persName corresp="#p_SA_1">Sadat</persName> said,
                    this (acceptance of the resolution) might be the worst outcome of all. (S)</p>
                <p>To be sure, Israel and Egypt have different interests from us in this process
                    (and in major respects from each other). But to be opposed publicly and
                    forcefully by <hi rend="italic">both</hi> Camp David parties increases the
                    dangers of the Resolution course (while, ironically, making it somewhat easier
                    to get off this course—if that were desired—since this is in fact, if not in
                    perception, no longer just an “Israel vs. <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>”
                    issue). (S)</p>
                <p>Conversations with our local Ambassadors (<persName corresp="#p_AAL_1"
                        >Atherton</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_LSW_1">Lewis</persName>,
                        <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1">West</persName>, and Veliotis) also helped to
                    cast doubt on 1) the likelihood of <gloss target="#t_PLO_1">PLO</gloss>
                    <pb facs="0960" n="925" xml:id="pg_925"/> acceptance of any resolution we could
                    reasonably support—especially following the <gloss target="#t_PNC_1">PNC</gloss>
                    meeting in Damascus;<note n="3" xml:id="d287fn3">In telegram 5410 from Damascus,
                        August 16, the Embassy conveyed a report on the August 12 meeting of the
                        Palestinian Central Council in Damascus. (National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D790372–0360)</note> and 2) the benefits to be achieved with Jordan and
                    Saudi Arabia (though, to be sure, the costs of a <gloss target="#t_UN_1"
                        >UN</gloss> veto with these and other Arab countries remain). (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SRS_1">Bob Strauss</persName> has left <persName
                        corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_SA_1"
                        >Sadat</persName> with the understanding that we are at the moment going
                    forward with a resolution that will indicate support for 242 and 338, affirm
                    Palestinian rights, and deal with the refugees in some general way. (Despite
                    press reports to the contrary, <persName corresp="#p_SRS_1">Strauss</persName>
                    impressed upon <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName> that he could not
                    promise to recommend to the President against moving forward). Both, however,
                    have high expectations that their own personal appeals to the President will
                    have an effect, in getting our position changed. Both appealed for a
                    face-to-face meeting with the President (<persName corresp="#p_KM_1"
                        >Khalil</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BM_2">Begin</persName>) before we
                    proceed; and both urged that the President not destroy through this act what he
                    has built up in the Camp David process. (S)</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">What next?</p>
                <p>I discussed with Bill this evening the thinking that went on today in Washington.
                    It parallels ours on the plane, to wit:</p>
                <p>—we should not go forward with a resolution of our own;</p>
                <p>—we should seek to get the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> business behind us
                    this week, instead of trying to stretch it out. (S)</p>
                <p>Bill’s three options seem best (and parallel to ours):</p>
                <p>—seek a postponement (the attached cable<note n="4" xml:id="d287fn4">Not found
                        attached. In telegram 4641 from Beirut, August 20, <persName
                            corresp="#p_DJG_1">Dean</persName> relayed a conversation he had with
                            <persName corresp="#p_TG_1">Tueni</persName> in which <persName
                            corresp="#p_TG_1">Tueni</persName> stated that he had called on
                            <persName corresp="#p_AY_1">Arafat</persName> on August 19 to “probe his
                        receptivity” to a postponement in <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                        consideration of a resolution on Palestinian rights. <persName
                            corresp="#p_TG_1">Tueni</persName> told <persName corresp="#p_DJG_1"
                            >Dean</persName> that he had found <persName corresp="#p_AY_1"
                            >Arafat</persName> “very receptive” to a postponement “in the event
                        nothing constructive could be achieved at this time.” (National Archives,
                            <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        P850029–2494)</note> indicates an inclination in Beirut on that point as
                    well; if your meeting Tuesday<note n="5" xml:id="d287fn5">August 21.</note>
                    morning goes in this direction, following up on this conversation with <persName
                        corresp="#p_TG_1">Tueni</persName> should be done urgently);</p>
                <p>—Go for a neutral “consensus” statement out of the <gloss target="#t_UNSC_1"
                        >UNSC</gloss>;</p>
                <p>—simply veto. (S)</p>
                <p>My own sense is that we should pursue them in the order stated. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_SRS_1">Strauss</persName>’ inclination is to give a press
                    conference tomorrow, indicating that we will not put in a resolution (indicating
                    that we had been exploring several, but met negative reactions in both Israel
                    and <pb facs="0961" n="926" xml:id="pg_926"/> Egypt—emphasizing the latter, in
                    order to move this as much as possible away from a “<gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >U.S.</gloss>-Israel” matter). He could outline whatever option we have
                    selected, and stress our concern with the peace process as the best way of
                    achieving Palestinian legitimate rights. (S)</p>
                <p>We would need to be doing our diplomacy quickly (with seeking a postponement
                    being the “least cost” way out). This includes:</p>
                <p>—communication with the Kuwaitis (and Beirut);</p>
                <p>—approach to the British (on postponement);</p>
                <p>—instructions for damage limitation to <persName corresp="#p_WJC_1"
                        >West</persName> and Veliotis (who have basic background and have asked for
                    Wednesday appointments, pending whatever decision is reached in Washington);</p>
                <p>—communications to Israel and Egypt, Congressional contacts etc. (S)</p>
                <p>I am appending a broader options paper<note n="6" xml:id="d287fn6">Attached but
                        not printed. A revised version is also attached but not printed.</note> put
                    together by <persName corresp="#p_SHH_1">Hal Saunders</persName> on the plane
                    (and which he will revise for tomorrow). Option 3 is the one presented here.
                    (C)</p>
                <p>P.S. <persName corresp="#p_SRS_1">Strauss</persName> and Ben Epstein arranged
                    with <persName corresp="#p_KT_1">Teddy Kollek</persName> for an invitation to
                        <persName corresp="#p_YAJ_1">Andy Young</persName> to visit Jerusalem, “to
                    see how people can live together.” It will be sent privately in the near future.
                    (C)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
