<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1985-02-11T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1985-02-11T00:00:00-05:00" n="180" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d180">
                    <head>180. Letter From the Administrator of the United States Agency for
                        International Development (<persName corresp="#p_MPMP_1">McPherson</persName>) to the Under Secretary of the Treasury for
                        Monetary Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_SBW_1">Sprinkel</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d180fn1">Source: Department of State, Files
                            of the Under Secretary of State for Economic Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_WWA_1">W. Allen Wallis</persName>, Chrons; Memo to the
                            Secretary/Staff and Departmental/Other Agencies; Memos to the Files;
                            White House Correspondence, 1987–1987, Lot 89D378: Memos—to other
                            Agencies. No classification marking. Copies were sent to <persName corresp="#p_WWA_1">Wallis</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MCRT_1">McCormack</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_MD_1">Mulford</persName>. A stamped notation at the top of the memorandum
                            reads: “WAW HAS SEEN.” A different stamped notation at the top of the
                            memorandum reads: “Received Under Secretary’s Office February 12,
                            1985.”</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1985-02-11">February 11, 1985</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <salute>Dear Beryl:</salute>
                    </opener>
                    <p>As you know, the Agency for International Development is administering a
                        large and growing volume of balance of payments assistance. When such
                        assistance is provided as cash grants or in the form of commodity import
                        programs, this funding often involves macroeconomic and other conditionality
                        designed to maximize prospects that stabilization and adjustment objectives
                        will be achieved. In other cases, <gloss target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss>
                        <pb facs="0516" n="471" xml:id="pg_471"/> conditionality concentrates on
                        sectoral objectives; but, in these instances as well, achievement of
                        sectoral aims is usually connected with macroeconomic policy
                        considerations.</p>
                    <p>Until recently, A.I.D. agreements providing for balance of payments financing
                        often cited the need for the country to come to agreement with the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> or to adhere to the provisions of an
                        existing agreement. The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> will still
                        decide to impose policy conditions such as the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> might require in appropriate circumstances, but passage of
                        the Kemp-Kasten amendment has altered the situation in some respects.<note n="2" xml:id="d180fn2">The <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1984
                            foreign assistance supplemental and the Foreign Operations Appropriation
                            for <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 1985 included an amendment
                            specifying that assistance could not be withheld “solely” on the basis
                            of the policies of international financial institutions. The amendment
                            was known as the Kemp-Kasten amendment for Representative <persName corresp="#p_KJ_1">Jack Kemp</persName> (<gloss target="#t_R_1">R</gloss>–NY) and Senator <persName corresp="#p_KRW_1">Robert
                                Kasten</persName> (<gloss target="#t_R_1">R</gloss>–WI). In a
                            September 26, 1984, letter to <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_KJ_1">Kemp</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_KRW_1">Kasten</persName> explained that the
                            amendment was “aimed at preventing appropriated economic assistance from
                            being denied because a nation has not reached an agreement with the
                            International Monetary Fund.” (Department of State, Files of the Under
                            Secretary of State for Economic Affairs, <persName corresp="#p_WWA_1">W.
                                Allen Wallis</persName>, Lot 89D378: State-Treasury Lunches)</note>
                        We in the Agency feel that it is more important than ever to coordinate
                        closely with the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> to make certain that
                        we understand the reasoning behind the provisions in their objectives and to
                        work jointly with the Fund, the Bank, and other donors towards achieving the
                        best possible results. We are concerned with short term stabilization and
                        are also anxious that policy reforms and other measures be designed to
                        promote sound economic growth over the medium and longer term. Since Fund
                        programs increasingly take the medium and long term into consideration,
                        there is a growing need for coordination with the Bank and major donors.</p>
                    <p>All of this raises two issues that have troubled us for some time and that
                        now have become more acute; namely, A.I.D.’s restricted access to the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> and our limited role in <gloss target="#t_USG_1">U.S.G</gloss>. deliberations regarding <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> programs.</p>
                    <p>In the field, our Mission personnel often have excellent relations with
                            <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> representatives, but Fund teams are
                        by no means always prepared to make contact. Here in Washington, my people
                        feel that there are unnecessary barriers placed in the way of their contacts
                        with <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> counterparts.</p>
                    <p>Given our responsibilities in designing conditions and in administering
                        balance of payments programs, I feel strongly that our relationship with the
                        Fund needs to be further strengthened and regularized. This should be
                        helpful to the Fund and to other <gloss target="#t_USG_1">U.S.G</gloss>.
                        agencies as well as to us. If nothing else, a more systematic and timely
                        exchange of information would be of value. I consider it essential to the
                        improvement of coordination between A.I.D. and the Fund that key members of
                        my <pb facs="0517" n="472" xml:id="pg_472"/> staff be permitted informal
                        access to their technical counterparts in the Fund. I will make certain that
                        this privilege is used with discretion and will not result in any pressure
                        or interference with the work of the Fund staff.</p>
                    <p>It is also true that A.I.D. has often had little more than a perfunctory role
                        to perform in <gloss target="#t_USG_1">U.S.G</gloss>. deliberations on
                            <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> programs here in Washington, even
                        in the case of countries where there are significant A.I.D. programs. The
                        principal difficulty in this respect is that A.I.D. representatives gain
                        access to relevant deliberations too late to be able to make the useful
                        contributions their experience would sometimes make possible.</p>
                    <p>I think it would be worthwhile for all concerned to involve A.I.D. more
                        systematically in <gloss target="#t_USG_1">U.S.G</gloss>. consideration of
                            <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> programs for certain countries.
                        This would contribute to A.I.D.’s ability to determine the optimal amounts
                        of <gloss target="#t_BOP_1">BOP</gloss> assistance and to design appropriate
                        conditionality for our programs. It also would improve our ability to judge
                        the relationship and compatibility of A.I.D., other U.S.G., and <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> programs with respect to resource
                        transfers and conditionality packages. Further, I believe that given greater
                        opportunity we can make suggestions that will result in improvements in
                            <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> agreements.</p>
                    <p>Perhaps we could add this to our list of topics for discussion the next time
                        we get together. Meanwhile, Dick Derham will be sending a copy to Dave
                            <persName corresp="#p_MD_1">Mulford</persName> and may follow up with
                        preliminary talks since their offices would have the principal action on
                        coordination.</p>
                    <p>Sincerely,</p>
                    <closer><signed><persName corresp="#p_MPMP_1"><hi rend="strong">M. Peter
                                    McPherson</hi></persName><note n="3" xml:id="d180fn3"><persName corresp="#p_MPMP_1">McPherson</persName> signed “<persName corresp="#p_MPMP_1">MP McPherson</persName>” above his typed
                                signature.</note></signed></closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>