<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>193. Memorandum from Secretary of the Treasury Baker to President Reagan to
                    President Reagan</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v38</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">193</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1985-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1985-10-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recprkqi9dIeoip4s" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036130"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Debt</term>
                    <term ref="recGV5iJwHKxZYFEb" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy">Financial stability</term>
                    <term ref="recOWsM3ry8STSsK3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036647"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Democracy</term>
                    <term ref="recg8kFbuhxjgS7Cx" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic policies</term>
                    <term ref="rec14HP3WEhVvFEi9" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92001220"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Private sector</term>
                    <term ref="recXe3hjASdIXoUSz" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85066112"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Inflation</term>
                    <term ref="rec9WWJ4AW3ovypvP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85011127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Balance of payments</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006812"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recjcAQL1g5hKP7b4" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041628"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Contacts</term>
                    <term ref="recXPv0zy7j1zEBXW" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090650"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Negotiations</term>
                    <term ref="recJX4PfqEjKmVobe" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85017602"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Budget</term>
                    <term ref="recWWVFNMUXe07vmZ" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85036456"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Deficit</term>
                    <term ref="recEe8ikdAbvcrXbA" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="foreign-investments" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067736" lcsh-match="ambiguous_close">Foreign investment</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investment</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1985-10-29T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1985-10-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="193"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d193">
                <head>193. Memorandum from Secretary of the Treasury <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1"
                        >Baker</persName> to President Reagan<note n="1" type="source"
                        xml:id="d193fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                            >RG</gloss> 56, Records of the Office of the Secretary of the Treasury,
                        Official Files of the Executive Secretariat, 1985, UD–11W, 56–88–79, Box 62,
                        Memo/Ltr for the President, Jan–Dec ’85. Confidential. “<gloss
                            target="#t_FYI_1">FYI</gloss>” was typed at the top of the
                        memorandum.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1985-10-29">October 29, 1985</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Initiative on <gloss target="#t_LDC_1"
                            >LDC</gloss> Debt Problem</item>
                </list>
                <p>This memorandum summarizes the status of our initiative regarding <gloss
                        target="#t_LDC_1">LDC</gloss> debt.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Background</p>
                <p>In preparing for the IMF/World Bank annual meetings, it was apparent that we
                    faced a deteriorating international economic and political climate, particularly
                    in Latin America, which could have led to radical proposals to deal with the
                        <gloss target="#t_LDC_1">LDC</gloss> debt problem and severe criticism of
                    the United States. Garcia of Peru and Fidel Castro were visibly trying to
                    recreate interest in some form of “debtors’ cartel.” While their proposals were
                    generally viewed as extreme, responsible <gloss target="#t_LDC_1">LDC</gloss>
                    leaders were nonetheless showing a declining interest in resisting the
                    politicization of the debt issue.</p>
                <p>As I discussed with you and <persName corresp="#p_RDT_1">Don Regan</persName>, it
                    was essential that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> present constructive
                    proposals at the meetings which would respond to <gloss target="#t_LDC_1"
                        >LDC</gloss> concerns and defuse a potentially explosive situation.
                    Accordingly, we worked closely with <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George
                        Shultz</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_VPA_1">Paul Volcker</persName>
                    to develop the proposals which the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                    presented at the Seoul meetings.<note n="2" xml:id="d193fn2">See <ref
                            target="#d192">Document 192</ref>.</note> The “Program for Sustained
                    Growth” which I outlined builds on the case-by-case approach of the global debt
                    strategy adopted in 1982/83 and initiates the next phase by focusing on the
                    fundamental economic reforms necessary to achieve long-term, non-inflationary
                    growth in the principal debtor countries.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">The Program</p>
                <p>The Program for Sustained Growth incorporates three essential and mutually
                    reinforcing elements: <list>
                        <label>○</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">First and foremost</hi>, adoption by the principal
                            debtor countries of comprehensive short and long-term economic and
                            structural policies to promote non-inflationary growth and financial
                            stability. The focus <pb facs="0548" n="503" xml:id="pg_503"/> is on
                            strengthening the economic foundation essential for preserving democracy
                            in the key Latin countries which are having difficulty in obtaining
                            financing from private markets. These countries are being asked to
                            implement growth-oriented economic policies that will enhance reliance
                            on market forces and the private sector. In this next phase, they would
                            be expected not only to bring inflation and their balance of payments
                            under control (as in the first phase); but also to adopt “supply-side”
                            policies for longer term growth—policies that would re-attract flight
                            capital and foreign investment, reduce the relative share of public
                            investment, and provide market-incentives for long-term growth.</item>
                        <label>○</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Second</hi>, a continued central role for the <gloss
                                target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss>, complemented by increased and more
                            effective lending by the multilateral development banks (MDBs). We are
                            seeking reforms by the World Bank and Inter-American Development Bank
                                (<gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>) which would permit a 50
                            percent increase in disbursements by the institutions to the principal
                            troubled debtors over the next three years—<hi rend="italic">conditioned
                                upon</hi> the adoption by these countries of market-oriented
                            policies for growth.</item>
                        <label>○</label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Third</hi>, increased lending by the commercial banks
                            (both <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and foreign) in support of
                            sound economic programs by the roughly 2½ to 3 percent annually or about
                            $20 billion over the next three years, would reduce the risks to the
                            banks by encouraging the sound policies by the borrowers necessary to
                            improve the quality of outstanding loans. The banks have not been asked
                            to write a blank check. The increase in lending is itself to be
                            conditional—it would only take place in a context where conditions one
                            and two above had been met.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Initial Reactions</p>
                <p>The initial reaction to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> proposals has
                    been quite positive. We have avoided the politicization of the debt issue. And
                    there is broad recognition among the countries, commercial banks and
                    international institutions that there is no real alternative to a cooperative
                    approach in which each must do its part for all to reap the benefits from
                    increased growth. We are moving ahead quickly to build on the momentum that has
                    been achieved by obtaining commitments by each participant.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">Next Steps</p>
                <p>In this context, we are seeking implementation of specific measures that provide
                    a clear signal that each participant is willing to meet its
                        responsiblities.<note n="3" xml:id="d193fn3">Treasury staff developed a
                        paper, “Program for Sustained Growth: Next Steps,” which provided more
                        detail on the next steps for the international debt strategy outlined by
                            <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName> at Seoul. <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJW_1">Conrow</persName> forwarded the paper and its annexes
                        to <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName> under an October 25
                        covering memorandum. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss>
                        56, Records of the Office of the Secretary of the Treasury, Official Files
                        of the Executive Secretariat, 1985, UD–11W, 56–88–79, Box 66, Memo to the
                        Secretary, October ’85)</note>
                </p>
                <list>
                    <label>○</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Principal debtors</hi>. Our initial contacts will be with
                        Argentina to determine their willingness to adopt a comprehensive program
                        for growth that could be supported by the international community. Mexico
                        has <pb facs="0549" n="504" xml:id="pg_504"/> already begun negotiations on
                        a new <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> program which will require
                        courageous action by the government. We will follow the negotiations closely
                        in order to be in a position to be as helpful as possible.</item>
                    <label>○</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Commercial banks</hi>. <persName corresp="#p_VPA_1">Paul
                            Volcker</persName> and I have been in contact with the banks regarding
                        their participation. We anticipate a general statement of support in the
                        near future although our plan leaves to the banks the means to implement the
                        commitments to provide additional financing.<note n="4" xml:id="d193fn4">In
                            an October 18 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1"
                                >Baker</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MD_1">Mulford</persName>
                            summarized discussions held with bankers on October 17 on the <gloss
                                target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> international debt strategy rolled out
                            at Seoul. <persName corresp="#p_MD_1">Mulford</persName> attached an
                            October 18 covering note to the memorandum for <persName
                                corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName> detailing that after the
                            meeting, two bankers criticized the OCC, “claiming its actions and
                            attitudes are a major impediment to the success of your program.”
                            (Ibid.) In an October 23 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1"
                                >Baker</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MD_1">Mulford</persName>
                            summarized reactions of the banking community to the <persName
                                corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName> debt proposal voiced at the
                            Annual Convention of the American Bankers Association held in New
                            Orleans October 21. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                                >RG</gloss> 56, Records of the Office of the Secretary of the
                            Treasury, Official Files of the Executive Secretariat, 1985, UD–11W,
                            56–88–79, Box 57, [illegible] ’85)</note>
                    </item>
                    <label>○</label>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">International institutions</hi>. The World Bank and <gloss
                            target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss> have been told that <gloss
                            target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> support for capital increases is
                        contingent upon adoption of reforms that improve the efficiency and quality
                        of their operations. The <gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss> replenishment
                        negotiations are scheduled to begin in January and provide a first test of
                        the willingness of Latin countries to implement fundamental reforms in the
                        institutions and their economies.</item>
                </list>
                <p>At this stage, the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> proposals do not require
                    increased budget commitments—and we have made none. However, if all participants
                    do their part and an increase in quality lending materializes, a capital
                    increase for the <gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss> and World Bank will be
                    necessary in due course. The timing and scope of the capital increases will
                    depend on negotiations and Congressional action on the budget deficit. It is our
                    intention that replenishments for the institutions should result in budget
                    outlays which are lower than current <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                    commitments. Any costs to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> would be
                    substantially less than the consequences of dealing with a threat to the
                    stability of the banking system.</p>
                <p rend="sectiontitleital">In Sum</p>
                <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> proposals have served to strengthen our
                    leadership role in the world economy and provide a positive approach to
                    achieving sustained global growth. The successful implementation of the program
                    should serve to ameliorate the political and social pressures in Latin America
                    arising from the perception that the only solution to the debt problem was
                    prolonged austerity and reduced living standards.</p>
                <p>I am encouraged by the initial reactions. But, as of course you know, we are
                    still a long way from having “solved” the third-world debt problem.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
