<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1981-01-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1981-01-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="259" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d259">
                    <head>259. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_NHR_1">Henry Nau</persName> of
                        the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for
                        National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_ARV_1">Allen</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d259fn1">Source:
                            Reagan Library, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Subject File, [Security Assistance] Foreign Aid
                            (January 1981). Confidential. Sent for information. A handwritten note
                            on the memorandum reads: “RVA: <persName corresp="#p_DT_1">Tim
                                Deal</persName> is on standby for this meeting. J.”</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1981-01-29">January 29, 1981</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Meeting Friday, January 30, 1981, 3:00 p.m. on Foreign Aid
                            Retrenchment</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The attached paper<note n="2" xml:id="d259fn2">Not attached.</note> outlines
                        the <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Stockman</persName> recommendations for
                        foreign aid retrenchment which will be discussed at the meeting Friday
                            afternoon,<note n="3" xml:id="d259fn3">January 30.</note> 3:00 p.m. The
                        highlights are as follows (see page 5–6 for best overview of the numbers): <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Security Assistance is excluded. <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> tells me this was done intentionally to indicate
                                that they did not seek to propose increases or decreases in the
                                    <gloss target="#t_FMS_1">FMS</gloss> credit, <gloss target="#t_IMET_1">IMET</gloss> or <gloss target="#t_MAP_1">MAP</gloss> accounts. I had Bob <persName corresp="#p_KR_1">Kimmitt</persName> check on whether State or Defense intended
                                to raise the possibility of enhancement of the security assistance
                                budget. His memo and recommendations are attached.<note n="4" xml:id="d259fn4">Not attached.</note></item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Every other major program takes some reduction with multilateral
                                programs being cut back more than bilateral programs.</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Nevertheless, the most important bilateral programs for
                                implementing foreign policy objectives are also cut substantially. <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>PL–480 is cut by ½ in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss>
                                        82 and eliminated altogether after <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 82 (The Egyptian Ambassador has already
                                        called about the PL–480 cuts after the story in Thursday’s
                                            <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>).<note n="5" xml:id="d259fn5">See John M. Goshko, “Huge Cutback
                                            Proposed in Foreign Aid,” <hi rend="italic">Washington
                                                Post</hi>, January 29, 1981, p. A1.</note></item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>Economic Support Fund (excluding Egypt and Israel) is cut
                                        by $100 m in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 82 (the
                                        contingency fund is eliminated) and increases only slightly
                                        thereafter to the same level in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 85 that <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName> proposed for <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 82 (meaning a real decline from <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName>
                                        <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 82 levels).</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <label>4.</label>
                            <item>By contrast to PL–480 the bilateral <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> account, which involves long-term project
                                assistance for basic human needs (agriculture, health, etc.) and is
                                therefore less flexible and useful for supporting new foreign policy
                                initiatives, is not cut but increases by 3 percent annually from
                                    <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 82 on.</item>
                            <pb facs="0703" n="658" xml:id="pg_658"/>
                            <label>5.</label>
                            <item>All of this leads me to make the following points which you may
                                wish to pursue at the meeting Friday: <list>
                                    <label>a.</label>
                                    <item>The President has given priority to budget reductions. We
                                        must all cooperate. Foreign aid has become an unpopular
                                        program because it has been divorced increasingly from
                                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> national security and
                                        foreign policy objectives. In the short-run, therefore, if
                                        more popular domestic programs must be cut, foreign aid too
                                        will have to be cut.</item>
                                    <label>b.</label>
                                    <item>However, short-term cuts must reflect the policy
                                        priorities of the new Administration, not continuing
                                        priorities of the previous Administration <list>
                                            <label>1.</label>
                                            <item>The proposed cuts for <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 81 must take into account the funds
                                                that have already been obligated by the <persName corresp="#p_CJEJ_1">Carter</persName>
                                                Administration, since cuts at this point must come
                                                from unobligated funds. I am told, for example, that
                                                the $211 m proposed cut in the <gloss target="#t_AID_1">AID</gloss> budget will have to
                                                come heavily from Central and South America, a clear
                                                priority region for the new Administration.</item>
                                            <label>2.</label>
                                            <item>Is it not possible to cut <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss> VI completely for <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 81, since a
                                                renegotiation of the replenishment is not likely to
                                                be accomplished before the end of the fiscal
                                                  year?<note n="6" xml:id="d259fn6">An unknown hand
                                                  bracketed this sentence in the left-hand
                                                  margin.</note></item>
                                            <label>3.</label>
                                            <item>Only modest amounts have been cut from the <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 81 budget for
                                                multilateral banks (except <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss>) and international organizations and
                                                no cuts have been proposed for the Peace Corps? Have
                                                we looked at these accounts critically
                                                enough?</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <label>c.</label>
                                    <item>In the longer-run (<gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 83
                                        on), the need to cut foreign aid is less persuasive. Support
                                        for foreign aid can be rebuilt by linking this aid more
                                        closely to visible <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                                        security and commercial interests. Indeed, as new directions
                                        are set for American foreign policy in the Indian Ocean and
                                        Southwest Asia, the Caribbean, Central America, and other
                                        areas, it will be imperative that we have adequate foreign
                                        assistance resources to support American objectives. <list>
                                            <label>1.</label>
                                            <item>Is it wise, therefore, to eliminate PL–480 aid
                                                unless we increase proportionately <gloss target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss> funds?</item>
                                            <label>2.</label>
                                            <item>It is also misleading to show the <gloss target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss> account excluding
                                                Egypt and Israel only. <gloss target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss> funds are currently earmarked for
                                                Greece, Turkey, Spain, and other countries as well.
                                                Some 85% of ESF-money is locked in. The contingency
                                                fund of $100 m. is desperately needed, not only in
                                                  <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 82 but in the
                                                out-years as well.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>As Bob Kimmitt points out, you can expect <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> to support the retention of the <gloss target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss> contingency fund. On economic assistance,
                        State is internally divided between <persName corresp="#p_HRD_1">Hormats</persName> and, to a lesser extent, <persName corresp="#p_RMM_1">Rashish</persName>, who believe that <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Stockman</persName>’s proposals go too far too fast
                        in the case of the <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss> and multilateral
                        bank reductions, and <persName corresp="#p_BJL_1">Buckley</persName>, who
                        favors bilateral flexibility (hence PL–480 and <gloss target="#t_ESF_1">ESF</gloss>) even if it means cutting severely into <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> support of the banks.</p>
                    <pb facs="0704" n="659" xml:id="pg_659"/>
                    <p>In my view, the cutback of the banks is unfortunate but necessary. When
                        resources are tight and the security threat is more pressing, bilateral aid
                        must take priority. <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss> invests
                        predominantly in India, Bangladesh and Pakistan. The first two are not high
                        on the list of immediate <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> security
                        interests. The World Bank, by contrast, invests primarily in Brazil, Mexico,
                        Indonesia and South Korea. These are all important countries from the
                        standpoint of <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> security interests. If
                        anything therefore, we should favor the World Bank and the General Capital
                        Increase (<gloss target="#t_GCI_1">GCI</gloss>) rather than continue <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss> at the expense of <gloss target="#t_GCI_1">GCI</gloss>. This is the opposite of what <persName corresp="#p_SDA_1">Stockman</persName> recommends (see pages 7–8 of attached paper).</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>