<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-11-17T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-11-17T00:00:00-05:00" n="282" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d282">
                    <head>282. Memorandum From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">Shultz</persName> to President Reagan<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d282fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George Shultz</persName> Papers, Official Memoranda (08/13/1982);
                            NLR–775–25A–54–2–1. Confidential.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-11-17">November 17, 1982</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Resources for Foreign Policy</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>The failure of Congress to enact any of our regular <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss>–83 legislation on foreign assistance has created an intense
                        squeeze on resources for security and economic assistance. Unless we obtain
                        some improvement in our funding level during the lame duck session, we will
                        be unable to carry out the foreign policy and national security initiatives
                        to which you are committed.</p>
                    <p>We currently face a shortfall of $2.0 billion plus in the current Continuing
                        Resolution from your <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss>–83 request.
                        Operating with this level of funds: (1) jeopardizes the peace process in
                        Israel and Egypt; (2) poses chronic problems for our relations in Portugal,
                        Spain, Turkey and Pakistan; and (3) risks gutting the <gloss target="#t_CBI_1">CBI</gloss> program. If you were to receive an urgent
                        appeal for additional aid from a key ally, the current level of resources
                        would not allow you to respond positively.</p>
                    <pb facs="0746" n="701" xml:id="pg_701"/>
                    <p>State, working with Treasury, Defense and other agencies has developed a
                        comprehensive legislative game plan to push for as much legislative action
                        as the traffic will bear. This will involve consultations with the Senate
                        Foreign Relations Committee and the House Foreign Affairs Committee to see
                        whether the stalled <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss>–83 authorization
                        bills could go to the floor. However, irrespective of the progress on the
                        authorization track, we must give priority attention to the appropriations
                        process with emphasis on the House Appropriations Subcommittee on Foreign
                        Operations. Our hope is that we can use a markup by either the House or
                        Senate Committee at least as a basis for enhancing foreign aid funding in
                        the 2nd Continuing Resolution.</p>
                    <p>Without your direct and visible involvement, particularly in the
                        appropriations process, we will have no chance of rectifying this grim
                        situation—given current hostilities toward foreign aid. At this point, we
                        are not even certain our supporters like <persName corresp="#p_KJ_1">Jack
                            Kemp</persName> will press for a markup in the House. On the Democratic
                        side, only Chairman <persName corresp="#p_LR_3">Long</persName> is even
                        mildly interested in a markup.</p>
                    <p>Your involvement is necessary to get some momentum and to help forge a
                        coalition among Republican members who favor security assistance and those
                        Democrats who prefer economic aid. A direct appeal from you would underscore
                        the urgency of the situation and bring the two sides together.</p>
                    <p>I strongly recommend that you participate in two events: a meeting with key
                        conservatives led by <persName corresp="#p_KJ_1">Jack Kemp</persName> for
                        reassurance on our commitment to the multi-lateral development banks (and to
                        fulfill a commitment made last year by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> that such a meeting would occur).
                        This meeting may have to await your return from South America.<note n="2" xml:id="d282fn2"><persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> traveled
                            to Brazil, Colombia, Costa Rica, and Honduras from November 30 to
                            December 4.</note> Secondly, an appearance by you—no matter how brief—at
                        the White House Situation Room briefing for the full House Subcommittee will
                        pay significant dividends. This briefing is slated for November 30.<note n="3" xml:id="d282fn3">There is no record in the President’s Daily Diary
                            of a meeting in the White House Situation Room on November 30. (Reagan
                            Library)</note></p>
                    <p>I regret the necessity of intruding on your crowded schedule. In light of
                        Congressional realities, however, I fear that without your personal
                        participation our efforts to improve this difficult situation are unlikely
                        to succeed.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendation</p>
                    <p>That you agree to participate in our legislative game plan as outlined
                            above.<note n="4" xml:id="d282fn4"><persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> did not indicate approval or disapproval of the
                            recommendation.</note></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>