<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1984-01-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1984-01-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="310" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d310">
                    <head>310. Memorandum From <persName corresp="#p_LR_1">Richard Levine</persName>
                        of the National Security Council Staff to the President’s Assistant for
                        National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_MFRCB_1">McFarlane</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d310fn1">Source:
                            Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_WDC_1">David Wigg</persName>
                            Files, Unfoldered, Unfoldered Subject File, Food Aid. Confidential. Sent
                            for action.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1984-01-12">January 12, 1984</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Food Aid</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>In response to your request that we explore food and developmental aid
                        options to feed the world’s hungry, <persName corresp="#p_PJM_1">John
                            Poindexter</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_RRW_2">Roger
                            Robinson</persName> and I met. John asked that I develop terms of
                        reference for an NSSD,<note n="2" xml:id="d310fn2">For the text of National
                            Security Study Directive 1–84, “U.S. Third World Hunger Relief,”
                            February 27, 1984, see <ref target="frus1981-88v41#d218"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XLI,
                                Global Issues II, Document 218</ref>.</note> followed by an
                            NSDD<note n="3" xml:id="d310fn3">For the text of National Security
                            Decision Directive 143, “U.S. Third World Hunger Relief: Emergency
                            Assistance,” July 9, 1984, see <ref target="frus1981-88v41#d221"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XLI,
                                Global Issues II, Document 221</ref>.</note> laying out how <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and Western aid programs could be improved
                        to feed the world’s hungry. This, of course, is no small undertaking. Hunger
                        has been with us throughout history, and there is no “silver bullet” to
                        eliminate it and its consequences. Since WWII, a complex structure of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> and Western programs has been built to
                        deal with the hunger problem. Despite dramatic growth in the world’s
                        population, due in part—ironically—to better nutrition and health care,
                        world food production has also risen dramatically due to the “green
                        revolution” of new wonder grains.</p>
                    <p>The first step in conducting an <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> review
                        of the developmental and food aid issue would be the codification of
                        existing <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> studies in this area. <gloss target="#t_USDA_1">USDA</gloss>, for instance, is now conducting a large
                        study on the worldwide hunger issue. I would then set up a small,
                        professional working-level group to establish the terms of reference for the
                        study, leading to a formal <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> with
                        corresponding agency dedication to the review. Since I will be gone through
                        the end of this month, I would begin this effort in early February with a
                        view to issuing an <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> 3 weeks
                        thereafter. The completion time for the study would be 2 to 3 months.</p>
                    <p>The whole area of global hunger has actually been the subject of numerous
                        studies, but perhaps with concerted interagency effort some fresh and
                        relative approaches could be found. Potential strategies, however, may
                        require increased funding.</p>
                    <pb facs="0813" n="768" xml:id="pg_768"/>
                    <p>Apart from the <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss>, there is the more
                        immediate question of increasing food aid to those countries—principally in
                        Africa—now experiencing a severe drought.<note n="4" xml:id="d310fn4">For
                            documentation on <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> policy toward the
                            African famine crisis, see <ref target="frus1981-88v41#d203"><hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XLI,
                                Global Issues II, Documents 203</ref>–<ref target="frus1981-88v41#d259">259</ref>.</note> An additional
                        $100–200 million in <gloss target="#t_PL_1">P.L.</gloss> 480 would be,
                        unlike the $1 billion figure proposed earlier, of some real benefit to these
                        people. However, we should realize that the current size of our food and
                        developmental aid programs was shaped through the budget process where these
                        issues were fought out. In most cases, the Administration selected the “high
                        option” on these food aid funding issues. To now evince support for more
                        food aid funding will send a very curious message to the bureaucracy and
                        knowledgeable members of the <persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Hill</persName>,
                        and intensify requests from the international community. For instance, in a
                        recent “off-the-record” conversation with <gloss target="#t_USDA_1">USDA</gloss> Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_ADG_1">Amstutz</persName>, he expressed wonderment at the fact that we were
                        even considering increasing food aid, given the fact that his budget
                        requests for loan guarantees were recently trimmed by billions. I say all
                        this not to be a spoiler; I just want to give you a full picture of the
                        departure that a new food aid initiative would be from recent
                        deliberations.</p>
                    <p>If the President desires to take immediate steps to combat the hunger
                        problem, a $100–200 million <gloss target="#t_PL_1">P.L.</gloss> 480
                        program, as an <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 84 supplemental program,
                        should be considered. This supplemental would bring our <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 84 program up to our requested <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 85 program level of $1.7 billion. <gloss target="#t_USDA_1">USDA</gloss> might have some alternative food aid
                        approach, such as credits, to do much the same thing. Certain <gloss target="#t_OMB_1">OMB</gloss> staffers have alternative approaches
                        stressing greater private sector participation in concessional grain export
                        financing. Thus, in order to speedily move ahead to address the present
                        issue of the severe drought in Africa, I believe we should ask that the
                        President approve our tasking the <gloss target="#t_SIGIEP_1">SIG–IEP</gloss> to review such a <gloss target="#t_PL_1">P.L.</gloss>
                        480 supplemental, or its equivalent, on a 2-week turnaround. The <gloss target="#t_SIGIEP_1">SIG–IEP</gloss>’s report could then be considered
                        at a BRB meeting you could convene. A complicating factor to increased
                            <gloss target="#t_PL_1">P.L.</gloss> 480 funding would be its impact on
                        domestic program growth, or foreign assistance cuts when the <persName corresp="#p_HMC_1">Hill</persName> reviews it.</p>
                    <p>Messrs. <persName corresp="#p_RRW_2">Robinson</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_WF_1">Wettering</persName> concur.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">RECOMMENDATION</p>
                    <p>That you sign the attached memo to the President.<note n="5" xml:id="d310fn5"><persName corresp="#p_MFRCB_1">McFarlane</persName> did not
                            indicate his approval or disapproval of the recommendation. Attached but
                            not printed at Tab I is the undated memorandum to the President.
                            Attached but not printed at Tab A is an undated memorandum from
                                <persName corresp="#p_MFRCB_1">McFarlane</persName> to <persName corresp="#p_RDT_1">Regan</persName>.</note></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>