<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1987-08-05T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1987-08-05T00:00:00-05:00" n="379" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d379">
                    <head>379. Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of the Treasury for
                        Legislative Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HJ_1">Harman</persName>) to
                        Secretary of the Treasury Baker<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d379fn1">Source: Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 56, Executive Secretariat, Congressional Files, 1987,
                            56–90–29, Box 39, Memos to the Secretary, International Affairs,
                            July–Aug ’87. No classification marking. Sent for action. David Malpass
                            initialed for <persName corresp="#p_HJ_1">Harman</persName>.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1987-08-05">August 5, 1987</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>Status of <gloss target="#t_MDB_1">MDB</gloss> Authorization
                            Legislation</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Action Forcing Event</p>
                    <p>Chairman <persName corresp="#p_SGFJ_1">St Germain</persName> wants to see
                        greater Administration and Republican visibility in support of the <gloss target="#t_MDB_1">MDB</gloss> authorizations before he allows a full
                        Committee markup. It is important that we honor the authorization process
                        for as long as possible in order to avoid objections to placing the
                        legislation in the Continuing Resolution.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Background</p>
                    <p>In recent years <gloss target="#t_MDB_1">MDB</gloss> replenishments have been
                        authorized through annual Continuing Resolutions rather than regular order.
                        We expect that to be the outcome this year as well.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, we must go through the motions of supporting the normal
                        Congressional authorization process in case a) the Authorization Committees
                        actually want to take a bill to the floor, or b) they acknowledge their own
                        inability to produce legislation and thereby indicate they will not object
                        to the Appropriation Committees using the C.R. as the vehicle for
                        authorizing as well as funding the MDBs.</p>
                    <p>The Senate Foreign Relations Committee has reported out a bill (S.1274) that
                        provides authorization for <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        participation in <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss> VIII, the Asian
                        Development Fund (<gloss target="#t_ADF_1">ADF</gloss>), the African
                        Development Bank (AFDB), and approval of the Inter-American Development Bank
                            (<gloss target="#t_IDB_1">IDB</gloss>) capital merger. Authorization to
                        join <gloss target="#t_MIGA_1">MIGA</gloss> and to approve changing the
                            <gloss target="#t_IBRD_1">IBRD</gloss> Articles (to lower the Articles
                        veto threshold) is not in the Senate bill. We do not believe the Committee
                        will take the Foreign Aid Authorization bill to the floor, and do not expect
                        them to object to the C.R. approach with the Senate Appropriations
                        Committee.</p>
                    <p>The House Banking <hi rend="italic">Subcommittee</hi> on International
                        Development Institutions and Finance (chaired by Walter Fauntroy) has
                        reported out a bill (<gloss target="#t_HR_1">H.R.</gloss> 2403) by a 10–2
                        vote that authorizes all of the Administration’s <gloss target="#t_MDB_1">MDB</gloss> requests. <persName corresp="#p_SGFJ_1">St
                            Germain</persName>, who has never been an <gloss target="#t_MDB_1">MDB</gloss> fan, is showboating and has probably been trying to
                        position himself to deal with <pb facs="0968" n="923" xml:id="pg_923"/> you
                        on issues of interest to him in exchange for his scheduling an <gloss target="#t_MDB_1">MDB</gloss> markup.</p>
                    <p><persName corresp="#p_SGFJ_1">St Germain</persName> and his staff say they
                        will not schedule a markup due to: <list>
                            <label>a)</label>
                            <item>lack of Administration interest in legislation (i.e., Secretary
                                    <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName> has not called me
                                on this); and</item>
                            <label>b)</label>
                            <item>lack of Republican support to the MDBs (wants to see a Floor Whip
                                count of Republicans).</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>He is also saying he will object to providing the <gloss target="#t_MDB_1">MDB</gloss> authorization requests through the C.R. approach.</p>
                    <p>On substance, <persName corresp="#p_SGFJ_1">St Germain</persName> has no
                        basis to argue lack of Administration interest in the MDBs, and a House
                        Floor Count of Republicans is not necessary for him to schedule a Full
                        Committee markup. We will deliver Republicans in Full Committee, just as we
                        did in Subcommittee.</p>
                    <p>St Germain’s resistance to holding a markup may lessen as outside issues such
                        as <gloss target="#t_FSLIC_1">FSLIC</gloss> and housing progress.
                        Nevertheless, it is now appropriate to increase the visibility of
                        Administration support for the MDBs.</p>
                    <p>Attached at Tab A is a letter from you to <persName corresp="#p_SGFJ_1">St
                            Germain</persName> that indicates the MDBs are one of your top
                        priorities and asks him to schedule a markup early in September.<note n="2" xml:id="d379fn2">The August 5 letter is attached but not printed.</note>
                        In addition, we also recommend the following to indicate visible and strong
                        Administration support: <list>
                            <label>○</label>
                            <item>A Presidential letter to all members of Congress shortly after
                                their summer recess indicating strong support for <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss> and the MDBs generally. It could
                                be argued that the timing for such a letter, on the eve of the
                                President’s speech to the Bank/Fund annual meetings, is
                                    propitious.<note n="3" xml:id="d379fn3">In a September 18
                                    memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_BHH_1">Howard
                                        Baker</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName> wrote that he believed it would be
                                    worthwhile for <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> to
                                    send a letter to members of Congress requesting support for
                                    funding the MDBs and the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                                    share of the replenishment of <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss> VIII. A copy of this memorandum is in the
                                    Washington National Records Center, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 56, Executive Secretariat, Congressional Files,
                                    1987, 56–90–29, Box 33, White House Folder (September) ’87. A
                                    draft of the letter is attached to the memorandum. <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> addressed the joint
                                    meeting of the <gloss target="#t_IMF_1">IMF</gloss> and World
                                    Bank Boards of Governors on September 29. For the text of his
                                    address, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName></hi>, <hi rend="italic">1987</hi>, Book II, pp.
                                1089–1094.</note></item>
                            <label>○</label>
                            <item>A meeting between you and Chalmers Wylie and other Republican
                                members of the Banking Committee, not only to demonstrate support
                                for <gloss target="#t_IDA_1">IDA</gloss>, but to urge them to stand
                                firm on keeping <gloss target="#t_MIGA_1">MIGA</gloss> in the bill
                                without “killer” conditions.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Depending on how this issue progresses, you may want to consider later a
                        meeting with House Republicans. The above action suggests at least one
                        meeting and two letters. We believe that this level of involvement is
                        appropriate, and necessary to demonstrate Administration support for the
                        institutions and create pressure for the authorization and appropriation
                        process to progress.</p>
                    <pb facs="0969" n="924" xml:id="pg_924"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Recommendations:</p>
                    <p>That you sign the attached letter urging a markup and authorize sending a
                        copy to all members of the House Banking Committee.<note n="4" xml:id="d379fn4"><persName corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName> initialed
                            his approval of this and the subsequent recommendations. See footnotes 2
                            and 3, above. <persName corresp="#p_ZRB_1">Zoellick</persName>’s August
                            5 handwritten note below the recommendations reads: “The Secretary
                            suggested that <persName corresp="#p_MD_1">David Mulford</persName>
                            handle the last function, if possible. RBZ.”</note></p>
                    <p>That you approve our efforts to generate a Presidential letter in order to
                        show broad Administration interest in these authorizations.</p>
                    <p>That you agree to a meeting with Chalmers Wylie and other Republicans on the
                        House Banking Committee at an appropriate time in September, if
                        necessary.</p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>