<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1988-04-16T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1988-04-16T00:00:00-05:00" n="396" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d396">
                    <head>396. Action Memorandum From the Acting Assistant Secretary of State for
                        Economic and Business Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_LAP_1">Larson</persName>) to Secretary of State Shultz<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d396fn1">Source: Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_SGP_1">George Shultz</persName> Papers, Executive
                            Secretariat Sensitive (04/14/1988–04/24/1988); NLR–775–17–38–5–7.
                            Confidential. A stamped notation on the memorandum reads: “Treat as
                            original.” Drafted by Clayton Rubensaal (<gloss target="#t_EBTDCOFPFPD_1">EB/TDC/OFP/FPD</gloss>) on April 13;
                            cleared in <gloss target="#t_EBTDCOFPFPD_1">EB/TDC/OFP/FPD</gloss>,
                                <gloss target="#t_EBOFP_1">EB/TDC/OFP</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EBTDC_1">EB/TDC</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_E_1">E</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_ARA_1">ARA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_EAPEP_1">EAP/EP</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_NEAECON_1">NEA/ECON</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_AFEPS_1">AF/EPS</gloss>, and
                                <gloss target="#t_EURRPE_1">EUR/RPE</gloss>. The initials “RWM” are
                            stamped and written at the top of the memorandum. Tab A, <gloss target="#t_USTR_1">USTR</gloss>’s TPSC Paper, and Tab B, the text of
                            the 1983 International Coffee Agreement, were not found
                        attached.</note></head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1988-04-16">April 16, 1988</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <list type="subject">
                        <head>SUBJECT</head>
                        <item>International Coffee Agreement: Renegotiation</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">ISSUE FOR DECISION</p>
                    <p>Whether to enter into negotiations toward a new International Coffee
                        Agreement (<gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>).</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">BACKGROUND</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> was a principal architect of the
                        first <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> in 1962, and we have remained a
                        member largely for foreign policy reasons. The Fourth <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> expires September 30, 1989. Formal ICO
                        consultations on renegotiation probably will begin between the April 25–29
                        meeting of the ICO’s governing council<note n="2" xml:id="d396fn2">The ICO
                            Council was scheduled to meet in London April 25–29.</note> and its next
                        session in late September. The Trade Policy Staff Committee will meet April
                        21 to consider the following <pb facs="1004" n="959" xml:id="pg_959"/>
                        options on how we should proceed: A) decide now to renegotiate the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>, <gloss target="#t_B_1">B</gloss>) decide
                        now not to participate in the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> after
                        September 1989, or <gloss target="#t_C_1">C</gloss>) delay a decision on
                        whether to renegotiate.<note n="3" xml:id="d396fn3">In a May 25 memorandum
                            to <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_MD_1">Mulford</persName> reported that the TPSC had been
                            unable to decide whether the United States should participate in
                            renegotiation of the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>. Treasury
                            opposed <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> participation in
                            renegotiation of the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> on economic
                            grounds, but <persName corresp="#p_MD_1">Mulford</persName> recommended
                            that Treasury ultimately accede to State’s position on foreign policy
                            grounds, provided that: “(1) Negotiating instructions clearly hold
                                <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> negotiators to positions that
                            would remove the worst features of the current ICA; and (2) it is
                            understood that, if our positions prevail in the negotiations, we will
                            be expected to join the agreement and Executive Branch approval should
                            be routine.” <persName corresp="#p_MPMP_1">McPherson</persName>
                            initialed his agreement with the recommendation and wrote: “Mr. <gloss target="#t_SEC_1">Sec</gloss> this is my position—I went through the
                            1983 discussions but I wanted you to see it before it went back to David
                            Mulford.” <persName corresp="#p_BJA_1">Baker</persName> wrote “<hi rend="italic">PmP</hi>: I agree” at the bottom of the memorandum on
                            June 6. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 56,
                            Records of the Office of the Secretary of the Treasury, Congressional
                            Correspondence, 1988, UD–10, 56–10–1, Box 38, Memos to the Secretary,
                            International Affairs, May/June 88)</note></p>
                    <p>Coffee is an extremely important export for many developing countries of
                        interest to the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> Central American and
                        other producers’ dependence on coffee export earnings is high and they
                        consider stability in coffee prices encouraged by the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> vital to their social and economic
                        development. Because they acknowledge that the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> could not function without effective <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> participation, the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> is an important factor in our relations
                        with them.</p>
                    <p>Our withdrawal from the Coffee Agreement would cause the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> to collapse because the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>, with about 30% of the market, would no
                        longer enforce export quota provisions. The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> would be blamed for disregarding the economic plight of
                        developing countries. Many would experience an export earnings decline,
                        which would exacerbate debt-servicing, reduce ability to import merchandise
                        and encourage requests for additional balance of payments assistance. <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> withdrawal would complicate the
                        Administration’s Central American, <gloss target="#t_CBI_1">CBI</gloss> and
                        other regional initiatives.</p>
                    <p>At the same time, key consumer country governments and the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> coffee trade believe that serious
                        weaknesses in the present Agreement preclude extension of the current <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> and require renegotiation. At a minimum,
                        the following issues must be resolved to conclude an acceptable Agreement:
                        A) supply must be made more responsive to demand for the specific types of
                        coffee consumers prefer and industry requires; <gloss target="#t_B_1">B</gloss>) the incentive for producers to sell outside their quotas to
                        non-member countries at discount prices must be eliminated.</p>
                    <p>In addition, <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> reliance on negotiated
                        export quotas has shortcomings in terms of overall Administration policy on
                        commodity agreements. In all other cases we have opposed economic provisions
                        involving any restraint of trade or production. The <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>’s negotiated <pb facs="1005" n="960" xml:id="pg_960"/>
                        export quotas do not fully reflect supply availability nor do they allow
                        much adjustment in response to changing market conditions.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">ESSENTIAL FACTORS</p>
                    <p>The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> National Coffee Association (NCA)
                        supported <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> participation in past Coffee
                        Agreements but this year resolved that “the interests of the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> coffee consumer and industry are best
                        accommodated by free and unrestricted trade in coffee.” The NCA Resolution
                        also stated that, should the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                        nonetheless decide to remain a member, a new Agreement must address serious
                        weaknesses in the current <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>, i.e.
                        discount sales to nonmembers and nonavailability of the types and origins of
                        coffee sought by consumers. Although the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> trade in fact is almost equally divided on the question of
                        continued membership, it is nearly unanimous in agreeing that, at least,
                        solutions must be found to these two specific problems. Preliminary views of
                        key European governments and coffee trade also emphasize the importance of
                        tackling these issues in the renegotiation.</p>
                    <p>We have not yet sought agreement among interested bureaus, or with other
                        agencies, on specific <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> objectives for
                        negotiations toward a new <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>. However,
                        until <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> members formally have begun to
                        exchange views on the shape of a new <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>,
                        it would be premature to limit our options regarding whether or on what
                        terms we would be willing to participate in a new Agreement. This month’s
                        ICO Council session will provide a clearer picture of the forces at play,
                        information on which we can base a more realistic interagency appraisal.</p>
                    <p>There is general agreement within the <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss>
                        that, although future <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> participation
                        should not be a foregone conclusion, the importance of the Coffee Agreement
                        to friendly producing nations requires at least a good-faith effort to make
                        it work. Most important now is our commitment to discuss the possibility of
                        a new <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>. Any indication that the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> might do otherwise would be extremely hard
                        to defend after 25 years of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> support for
                        the Agreement. In conveying a decision to enter negotiations toward a new
                        Agreement, we would make clear our dissatisfaction over the terms of the
                        current <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>, and our refusal at this time
                        to consider its extension. This decision, however, would also convey our
                        willingness to work within the ICO toward an Agreement which satisfies our
                        industry’s needs as well as our foreign policy objectives.</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">RECOMMENDATION</p>
                    <p>I recommend that you support the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                        entering negotiations toward a new ICA.<note n="4" xml:id="d396fn4"><persName corresp="#p_HM_1">Maura Harty</persName> drew a line
                            through the recommendation, wrote “X per <gloss target="#t_GPS_1">GPS</gloss>” on the “Approve” option line and under the
                            recommendation wrote: “The recommendation should read: ‘I recommend that
                            you support the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> entering
                            negotiations toward a sound, new <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss>
                            that eliminates present defects.’ Per Harty-Wong telecon 4/19/88.” At
                            the end of the <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>
                            administration, the <gloss target="#t_ICA_1">ICA</gloss> renegotiations
                            were ongoing and the issue of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                            participation had not been resolved.</note></p>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>