<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>84. Minutes of a Meeting</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1981-88v38</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">84</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1982-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1982-02-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recmuOYE0cUMJaVom" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general">North-South issues</term>
                    <term ref="recu8AAwYTqYy4jwP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general">Economic crisis</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recpsy9g4OzCC8tNU" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="agriculture"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050184"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Food</term>
                    <term ref="recSTYazcpaaKyKWX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh89002579"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Commodity</term>
                    <term ref="recVkDb919jcUwdDB" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006518"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Prices</term>
                    <term ref="recyQwssZrUcxu4Pw" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-investment"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="recrPHlux2x5007fL" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040767"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign aid</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >NSC</term>
                    <term ref="recKrzVuLHn3WbqNd" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85105939"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Poverty</term>
                    <term ref="recAgu4u4GprMJCKN" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037341"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Developing countries</term>
                    <term ref="recEMIGGiQlEVEzeH" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87004890"
                        lcsh-match="exact">International trade</term>
                    <term ref="recMUnjFFCJDg31jy" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="foreign-investment" subject="investment" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2005001770" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Investment</term>
                    <term ref="rechrPce7erABw7F0" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" subject="interest-rate" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85067245" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Interest rates</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-02-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-02-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="84"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d84">
                <head>84. Minutes of a Meeting<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d84fn1">Source:
                        Department of State, Bureau of Economic Affairs, Office of Economical and
                        Agricultural Affairs Files, Official Economic Summit Files, 1975–1991, Lot
                        93D490: Versailles Summit—Preparatory Meeting February 27–28, 1982. No
                        classification marking. The meeting was held to prepare for the Versailles
                        Economic Summit. No drafting information appears on the minutes. A different
                        set of notes on this meeting, written by <persName corresp="#p_SBW_1"
                            >Sprinkel</persName>, is in the Reagan Library, Executive Secretariat,
                            <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> Trip File, Versailles Summit 1982
                        Preparatory Meeting—February 27–28.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Celle St. Cloud, France</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1982-02-28">February 28, 1982</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="center">SUMMIT PREPARATORY MEETING</p>
                <p>[Omitted here is discussion not focused on North-South issues.]</p>
                <p>FRANCE—Main North-South issues will include role of LDCs in economic crisis and
                    GNs. Underdevelopment is aspect of industrial country crisis. Helping them is a
                    selfish way to help ourselves, <pb facs="0275" n="230" xml:id="pg_230"/> not
                    only economically but also politically. The <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss>
                    Caribbean Basin Initiative is going in the right direction. On GNs, three steps
                    are necessary: 1) it has to begin, 2) it has to protect frontiers/walls between
                        <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> and Specialized Agencies (SAs)—issues in
                    SAs could not be taken up in general forum, 3) two problems important besides
                    energy—food and stabilization of commodity prices. We cannot believe the there
                    is nothing new on North-South issues. The French President will be back from
                    long trip to Africa and will have visited <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                    officials, etc. before Summit. We hope that GNs will begin before Summit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> COMMISSION</hi>—Third world is too
                    important to ignore. We cannot repeat what was done at Cancun or we will lose
                    credibility.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    </hi>—We do not agree that there has been no progress on North-South relations.
                    Perhaps some background is helpful. We began last year with some significant
                    differences of view. We worked hard on a common paper that eventually developed
                    a consensus view. We agreed that two aspects were most important: 1) economic
                    revival of our economies and the world economy, coupled with sound domestic
                    policies in the LDCs; 2) concessional aid for the poorest countries aimed at
                    helping them eventually to participate in the world economy. We placed different
                    emphases on these two points but we all agreed that both were important. On the
                    substantive front, the <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> did not wait. It
                    moved forward to develop a comprehensive view of its development policy which
                    the President presented before and at Cancun. Since then, we have completed the
                    formulation of our policy toward multilateral banks, which will ultimately free
                    up more concessional resources for the poorest countries. We announced only a
                    week ago our Caribbean Basin Initiative.<note n="2" xml:id="d84fn2">For the text
                        of <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>’s February 24 remarks on
                        the Caribbean Basin Initiative to the Permanent Council of the Organization
                        of American States, see <hi rend="italic">Public Papers: <persName
                                corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>
                        </hi>, <hi rend="italic">1982</hi>, Book I, pp. 210–215.</note> Look at this
                    program. It is a practical example of the principles we articulated at Cancun.
                    It shows how world economic measures—trade and investment—can work together with
                    foreign aid to promote self-sustaining growth. And it involves costs which this
                    Administration is nevertheless willing to incur even in the difficult domestic
                    economic circumstances we face. Now, on top of all this, we adopted a helpful
                    attitude toward GNs. Don’t forget, we never believed these discussions would be
                    worth much. But because our friends and the LDCs seemed to want them, we went
                    along. We asked only that these talks be structured in such a way to prevent
                    damage to the institutions where the real development action would take place.
                    Our Ambassador in New York took the initiative after Cancun. Our President spent
                    numerous hours on this subject and chaired a long <pb facs="0276" n="231"
                        xml:id="pg_231"/>
                    <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss> meeting in December.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d84fn3">See <ref target="#d79">Document 79</ref>.</note> And what
                    has happened. We have not one response from the <gloss target="#t_G77_1"
                        >G–77</gloss>. Maybe GNs has lost its appeal for others. Don’t expect us to
                    revive it. But we are not waiting; we are moving ahead on what counts. Maybe GNs
                    will ripen again later.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">FRANCE</hi>—Why did <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss> not
                    accept <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> compromise?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    </hi>—Why did LDCs not accept <gloss target="#t_EC_1">EC</gloss> text?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">FRANCE</hi>—Can we find new ways to move forward; new steps
                    toward GNs?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">CANADA</hi>—If there is a hint of loss of interest in GNs, it
                    will collapse. So <persName corresp="#p_TPE_1">Trudeau</persName> and Lopez
                    Portillo decided there could be no hint of loss of resolve.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">GERMANY</hi>—If current situation continues, West will lose
                    its credibility. On replenishment of the banks, we regret the recent
                    developments. It is not of our making. We should not spend much time on
                    North-South issues.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">JAPAN</hi>—There is no answer yet from South. Facing this
                    situation, what can we as the North do? There is not much to do then at this
                    Summit.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">CANADA</hi>—Trudeau’s position before Delhi was that we needed
                    one last-minute surge of adrenaline.<note n="4" xml:id="d84fn4">The Government
                        of India hosted a <gloss target="#t_G27_1">G–27</gloss> conference in New
                        Delhi February 22–24, which focused on building a consensus within the
                            <gloss target="#t_G77_1">G–77</gloss> on a Global Negotiations position,
                        South-South cooperation, and India’s leadership within the <gloss
                            target="#t_G77_1">G–77</gloss>. Telegram 2296 from New Delhi, February
                        6, outlined a recommended <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> strategy for
                        the meeting. (Department of State, Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic
                        Telegrams, D820067–0919) Telegram 4347 from New Delhi, March 3, reported on
                        the meeting. The Embassy noted that the “U.S. was reportedly identified as
                        main obstacle to launching GNs, but we believe, from what we have heard,
                        that consultations had positive benefit of making clear the firmness of
                            <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> position on GNs.” (Department of
                        State, Central Foreign Policy File, Electronic Telegrams,
                        D820115–0234)</note> He addressed Cancun participants. He acknowledged great
                    efforts in New York and the openmindedness of the <gloss target="#t_US_1"
                        >U.S.</gloss>, the spirit of compromise it has shown. <persName
                        corresp="#p_TPE_1">Trudeau</persName>’s diagnosis is mildly cautious and
                    optimistic, as a result of <gloss target="#t_US_1">U.S.</gloss> efforts. There
                    is no report yet from Delhi. <persName corresp="#p_SMB_1">Smith</persName>,
                    however, is reported to be very gloomy. How Delhi events will percolate at
                        <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> is the question. Perhaps efforts should
                    be coordinated to create an upbeat note after Delhi.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">FRANCE</hi>—French President will insist on a clear position
                    on GNs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_UK_1">UK</gloss>
                    </hi>—This is where discussion must focus at Versailles. We must get these
                    things right for communique.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    </hi>—There should be no doubt about the <gloss target="#t_US_1">US</gloss>
                    commitment to help the poorest countries and alleviate poverty. But we will not
                    do this in ways that we know have not worked. A recent study commissioned by <pb
                        facs="0277" n="232" xml:id="pg_232"/> our Treasury Department examines the
                    policies that have been successful in developing countries.<note n="5"
                        xml:id="d84fn5">Presumably a reference to the paper, “Economic Outlook of
                        the Non-OPEC Developing Countries,” prepared by the Treasury Department’s
                        Office of Developing Nations’ Finance and distributed on January 29. A copy
                        of the paper is in the Reagan Library, <persName corresp="#p_BNA_1">Norman
                            Bailey</persName> Files, International Economics File, International
                        Debt (01/29/1982).</note> Those countries that have not allowed money supply
                    to grow unchecked, that have exercised budgetary discipline, that have not
                    subsidized interest rates, controlled prices and maintained unrealistic exchange
                    rates, that have participated aggressively in international trade, welcomed
                    foreign capital and encouraged savings—these are the countries that have
                    succeeded. We must do everything we can to encourage policies that we know work.
                    Aid is important but it has never helped when other conditions were not
                    right.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
