<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>115. Telegram From the Embassy in India to the Department of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d115</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">115</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1978-11-13T01:53:00-05:00" notAfter="1978-11-13T01:53:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="recX5END45BT2ZRv9" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2008004738"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Scientific</term>
                    <term ref="recN222dd4YgVLuoR" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh87005039"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Energy</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85092958"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear energy</term>
                    <term ref="recNBw28OYo4OUEUr" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh97005991"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Plenary</term>
                    <term ref="recvGhoVS9AdREJDT" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="general" subject="treaties-and-international-agreements" lcsh-match="no_match">Agreements</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1978-11-13T01:53:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1978-11-13T01:53:00-05:00" n="115"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d115">
                <head>115. Telegram From the Embassy in India to the Department of State<note n="1"
                        type="source" xml:id="d115fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss
                            target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                        D780467–0026. Confidential; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1"
                            >Exdis</gloss>. Also sent Immediate to Vienna and to Bombay and
                        Islamabad.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>New Delhi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            when="1978-11-13T06:53:00+00:00">November 13, 1978, 0653Z</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>17392. Vienna for USIAEA. Subject: Indo-US Nuclear Relations: Decisions Taken at
                    New Delhi Meetings November 10–11.</p>
                <p>1. Deputy to the Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_NJ_2">Nye</persName>,
                    Assistant Secretary <persName corresp="#p_PTR_1">Pickering</persName>, and
                        <gloss target="#t_ACDA_1">ACDA</gloss> Assistant Director <persName
                        corresp="#p_VDC_1">Van Doren</persName> met with <gloss target="#t_GOI_1"
                        >GOI</gloss> reps in New Delhi November 10–11 for further discussions of
                    Indo-US nuclear relations. The Indian side was headed by <persName
                        corresp="#p_SV_1">V. Shankar</persName>, Principal Secretary to the Prime
                    Minister, Foreign Secretary <persName corresp="#p_MJ_1">Jagat Mehta</persName>,
                    and IAEC Chairman <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Homi Sethna</persName>, and
                    included other representatives of <gloss target="#t_MEA_1">MEA</gloss> and the
                    Indian atomic establishment. Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1"
                        >Goheen</persName>, Bombay Consul General <persName corresp="#p_CWF_1"
                        >Courtney</persName>, and <gloss target="#t_Pol_1">Pol</gloss> Counselor
                        <persName corresp="#p_SHB_1">Schaffer</persName> also participated on the US
                    side. This message deals with agreements reached at the <pb facs="0361" n="316"
                        xml:id="pg_316"/> November 11 meeting on the earlier Indian proposal for the
                    establishment of an experts committee on safeguards. These agreements were made
                    on an ad referendum basis, and the Indian side will now submit them to Prime
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> for his approval. Given
                    the range of representation on the Indian side and the acceptance without demur
                    by all of them of the action taken we would expect prompt approval by <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName>. A septel covers other aspects of the
                        sessions.<note n="2" xml:id="d115fn2">Telegram 17390 from New Delhi,
                        November 13, provided further details about the discussions at the November
                        10–11 meetings. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                        Central Foreign Policy File, D780466–1170)</note>
                </p>
                <p>2. The two sides agreed to the establishment of a committee to be called the “Ad
                    Hoc Scientific Advisory Committee on Safeguards Questions”. It would have the
                    following terms of reference:</p>
                <p>1. To examine the options available within the concept of safeguards on all
                    nuclear activities.</p>
                <p>2. To survey the types of safeguards being applied in various countries and their
                    impact on the nuclear <gloss target="#t_RD_1">R&amp;D</gloss> and energy
                    programmes of those countries in terms of national priorities, needs and
                    interests.</p>
                <p>3. To seek to determine whether there is an appropriate <gloss target="#t_IAEA_1"
                        >IAEA</gloss> safeguards programme consistent with paragraphs (1) and (2)
                    and without hindrance to the progress of nuclear energy programmes.</p>
                <p>4. Composition of the Committee. The two sides agreed that the Committee will
                    comprise five experts. There will be one Indian expert. (We told the Indians
                    that we assumed that this would be <persName corresp="#p_SH_2">Sethna</persName>
                    and they seemed to agree.) The Indians will choose a second expert of different
                    nationality. Similarly, the US will have one expert and will select another. We
                    told the Indians that our expert would probably be <persName corresp="#p_TG_1"
                        >Gerald Tape</persName>. Both sides agreed on <gloss target="#t_IAEA_1"
                        >IAEA</gloss> Director General <persName corresp="#p_ES_1">Eklund</persName>
                    as Chairman of the Committee, to serve in his personal capacity. The Indians
                    could not agree that the selections that they and we would make would be subject
                    to the concurrence of the other side, as we had suggested. It was decided
                    instead that we and the Indians would consult about each other’s choices. (The
                    impliction of this was that each side would be satisfied with the other’s
                    choice.) In our discussions with the Indians we stressed the advantages of a
                    balanced membership. We reiterated to them that we would have difficulties with
                    the selection of certain nationals, mentioning specifically the Argentines and
                    Brazilians. They appeared to appreciate this, though <persName corresp="#p_SV_1"
                        >Shankar</persName> stated several times that the Committee’s composition
                    should be on a scientific and not a political basis.</p>
                <pb facs="0362" n="317" xml:id="pg_317"/>
                <p>4. The decisions reached at the November 11 meeting have been included in an aide
                    memoire prepared by the Embassy for submission to the <gloss target="#t_GOI_1"
                        >GOI</gloss>. The aide memoire reads as follows:</p>
                <p>Begin text:</p>
                <p>At meetings held at the Ministry of External Affairs in New Delhi November 10–11,
                    1978, the United States and Indian sides agreed to the following in connection
                    with the establishment at Indian initiative of an Ad Hoc Scientific Advisory
                    Committee on Safeguards Questions:</p>
                <p>1. The two sides will refer the proposals developed at the meetings to their two
                    govts for approval. These include terms of reference for the Committee as
                    follows: (see para 2 above for text of terms of reference)</p>
                <p>2. When these proposals are approved by the Indian <gloss target="#t_Govt_1"
                        >Govt</gloss>, Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName>
                    will write to President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>
                    indicating that fact; the United States will then respond.</p>
                <p>3. Following approval, the Ambassadors of the two countries accredited to the
                        <gloss target="#t_IAEA_1">IAEA</gloss> at Vienna will be authorized to
                    approach Director General <persName corresp="#p_ES_1">Eklund</persName> to
                    request him to serve as Chairman of the Committee in his personal capacity.</p>
                <p>4. If sufficient progress has been made by that time, the US and Indian
                    representatives to the <gloss target="#t_INFCE_1">INFCE</gloss> Plenary Session
                    in Vienna in late November 1978 will consult further about implementation of the
                    proposals agreed to in connection with the Committee. Among the subjects of such
                    consultations will be the selection, one by each side, of the additional two
                    experts. Additionally, the Embassy of the United States in New Delhi will
                    consult with the <gloss target="#t_Govt_1">Govt</gloss> of India on these
                    subjects.</p>
                <p>5. Arrangements regarding the establishment of the Committee will be completed by
                    Christmas 1978.</p>
                <p>6. The Committee will submit its report to the two govts on an advisory basis by
                    August 1979.</p>
                <p>7. Unless there are overriding considerations, the financing of the operation of
                    the Committee will be through each govt bearing the cost of its own
                    representative and of its nominee while the other costs will be shared equally
                    by the two govts.</p>
                <p>8. The <gloss target="#t_Govt_1">Govt</gloss> of India will handle press
                    briefings in New Delhi about the November 10–11 meetings. For that purpose, the
                    following statement was developed:</p>
                <p>Availing of the opportunity of the presence of American officials in connection
                    with the Indo-U.S. Sub-Commission on Science &amp; Technology, a meeting of
                    officials of the two govts was held as part of the ongoing dialogue between the
                    two countries on questions relating to their continuing nuclear cooperation.
                    They considered a proposal for the appointment of an ad hoc committee of
                    scientists with a view <pb facs="0363" n="318" xml:id="pg_318"/> to examining
                    certain general questions regarding safeguards and related matters.<note n="3"
                        xml:id="d115fn3">In a November 14 memorandum to <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1"
                            >Brzezinski</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_TTP_1">Thornton</persName>
                        commented on the establishment of the Committee: “The results of <persName
                            corresp="#p_NJ_2">Joe Nye</persName>’s trip to India are a very pleasant
                        surprise; evidently <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> is doing
                        (by his standards) his best to find a way out. It is still much too early to
                        count chickens however. Mrs. <persName corresp="#p_GI_1">Gandhi</persName>
                        will be sure to make a major issue out of any Indian concessions. In talking
                        to State today I urged them to make sure that all relevant US agencies were
                        on board on our accepting the idea. The India Desk, at least, hadn’t seen
                        any reason to consult with <gloss target="#t_DOE_1">DOE</gloss>—whose
                        equipment, after all, will be subject to inspection by the proposed group.”
                        (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Staff Material, North/South,
                        Thornton Subject File, Box 100, Evening Reports: 11/78–1/79)</note>
                </p>
                <p>End text</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Goheen</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
