<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-02-28T14:51:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-02-28T14:51:00-05:00" n="130" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d130">
                        <head>130. Telegram From the Embassy in India to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d130fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, P840128–1809. Secret; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>New Delhi</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1979-02-28T19:51:00+00:00">February 28, 1979,
                                1951Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>3416. For Secretary From <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName>. White House for <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>. Subject: Meeting With P.M. <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName>.</p>
                        <p>When <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Bob Goheen</persName> and I met with
                                <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> for 45 minutes at 7:30
                            p.m., we found him spirited and full of talk. He has been defending
                            himself today against allegations that he is taking a U.S. line on
                            various issues, and he gave us his best non-aligned defense.</p>
                        <p>1. I complimented him on his balanced approach to Indochina (it was
                            revealed today that he has urged the Vietnamese to withdraw from
                            Cambodia) and I told him that I knew President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> would be pleased in light of
                            his comments to me last Saturday.<note n="2" xml:id="d130fn2">In his
                                February 24 memorandum for the record (see <ref target="#d129fn5">footnote 5, Document 129</ref>), <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> recorded <persName corresp="#p_CH_1">Carter</persName>’s instructions to him: “Try to obtain from
                                the Prime Minister or <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName> the nature of assurances that might have
                                been given with respect to the scope and time limit of the Chinese
                                action.” In the right-hand margin next to this sentence, <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> wrote: “This just with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>.” <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> also noted: “The
                                President indicated that I should encourage the Prime Minister to
                                move toward a balanced reaction with respect to the fighting in
                                Indo-China.” <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName>
                                underlined the words “balanced reaction” and, in the right-hand
                                margin next to this paragraph, wrote: “Yes! No cop outs for <gloss target="#t_NAM_1">NAM</gloss> leaders.”</note> He countered <pb facs="0401" n="356" xml:id="pg_356"/> that the two situations were
                            unrelated and not comparable, with the Chinese far more at fault and the
                            Vietnamese having been wrong but in a good cause. He finally agreed that
                            the two adventures, whether or not related, posed a dangerous threat of
                            escalation. He implied but did not say that he had counseled restraint
                            on the Soviets but he said they would not long stand by and watch
                            Vietnam punished.</p>
                        <p>2. <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> urged that SALT be
                            “clinched” as soon as possible. He reiterated that the US-Soviet
                            relationship is the most important, and strongly in need of bolstering.
                            He said President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> and
                                <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> should meet
                            promptly, but doubted that <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> could travel to the United States. He indicated
                            that <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s condition may not
                            permit him to fly.</p>
                        <p>3. Although <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> described it as
                            a disagreement among friends, <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> gave us a good working over on the nuclear supply
                            issue. He added the Framatome sale to the usual litany of
                                discriminations.<note n="3" xml:id="d130fn3">The French reactors
                                sold to China would be engineered and built by Framatome. See <ref target="#d121fn7">footnote 7, Document 121</ref>.</note> The
                            nuclear issue is topic no. 1 in the local press, and he is being pressed
                            to take increasingly harsh positions to defend himself (today he said
                            that of course he would not permit inspections in India by another
                            country). I think we can keep the issue from boiling over for a few
                            weeks, but not for long.</p>
                        <p>4. On Pakistan, he said he met with President <persName corresp="#p_ZM_1">Zia</persName> at Kenyatta’s funeral and tried to warm up the
                                relationship.<note n="4" xml:id="d130fn4">See <ref target="#d112fn7">footnote 7, Document 112</ref>.</note> He feels he made no
                            progress, especially since Pakistan appears hell bent on the nuclear
                            option. I told him the President hoped he would make an extra effort to
                            develop a closer relationship in light of India’s strong position in the
                            region. He gave us the usual treatment on arms sales to the Paks and we
                            gave him the usual answers.<note n="5" xml:id="d130fn5">In his February
                                24 memorandum for the record, <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> noted: “The President indicated that I
                                should urge Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> to take the initiative in seeking a closer
                                relationship with Pakistan. The President said that even though the
                                Indians may feel that President <persName corresp="#p_ZM_1">Zia</persName> is not in a strong position, that should not
                                prevent them from taking initiatives toward further conciliation.”
                                In the right-hand margin next to this paragraph, <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> wrote: “A theme with
                                one and all—<hi rend="italic">privately</hi>.”</note></p>
                        <p>5. Like almost everyone here, <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> is deeply worried over the risk of escalation in
                            Indochina. He wonders how China can back off from what he regards as a
                            foolish and high risk endeavor. It is no help that <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName> was in Peking when the attack
                            started, but it is the substance of the dangerous situation that
                            concerns him most.<note n="6" xml:id="d130fn6">See <ref target="#d124fn7">footnote 7, Document 124</ref>. According to
                                his February 24 memorandum for the record, <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> “explained to the
                                President the adverse Indian reaction to the commencement of the
                                China attack at the time that <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName> was in Peking, and he said he understood
                                that this would cause apprehension among the Indians.”</note></p>
                        <pb facs="0402" n="357" xml:id="pg_357"/>
                        <p>6. <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName>’s respect and affection
                            for President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> will carry
                            him through specific disappointments, but his testy and feisty mood
                            tonight was a good reminder that he is a friend but not an ally.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_GRF_1"><hi rend="strong">Goheen</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>