<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>139. Memorandum of Conversation</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1977-80v19</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">139</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1979-04-24T11:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1979-04-24T11:30:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="south-and-central-asia" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="south-and-central-asia">South Asia</term>
                    <term ref="recqBa61v9UU0I2bD" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85093127"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Nuclear weapons</term>
                    <term ref="recZTSSF1kSCUEIrt" type="topic" category="warfare"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2009000043"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Invasion</term>
                    <term ref="recTXAFCynsVZOT6y" type="compound-subject"
                        category="bilateral-relations" subcategory="south-asian-relations"
                        >Sino-Indian relations</term>
                    <term ref="rectP6U9b173tdSs7" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="confidence-building-measures">Safeguards</term>
                    <term ref="rec5Zq5iTuWG2mE3w" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="energy-and-natural-resources"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005720"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recpotPshsDR78MFp" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="recoBEF2CtED5Jpb5" type="topic" category="science-and-technology"
                        subcategory="atomic-energy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85141276"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Uranium</term>
                    <term ref="recqSlWTgXqtdfG3Z" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85007355"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Arms race</term>
                    <term ref="recAZ6vp0KaSfYUeW" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament"
                        subcategory="nuclear-nonproliferation">Spent fuel</term>
                    <term ref="recw0DB5rAUpxfn0X" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85125696"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Sovereignty</term>
                    <term ref="recWYzYke7oYOWxG0" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002006218"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Public opinion</term>
                    <term ref="recJ9z9SORjaCLZG1" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85001321"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Aircraft</term>
                    <term ref="rec2TpelnZJkuY6rO" type="topic"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="arms-transfers"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh91001417"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Arms sales</term>
                    <term ref="recooe4dhYZz894vH" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="general" subject="national-security-interests" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85090122" lcsh-match="exact">National security</term>
                    <term ref="rec00812a40defabcb" type="topic" category="global-issues" subcategory="peace" subject="peace" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005610" lcsh-match="exact">Peace</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1979-04-24T11:30:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1979-04-24T11:00:00-05:00" n="139"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d139">
                <head>139. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d139fn1"
                        >Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material,
                        Subject File, Box 37, Memcons: President: 4–5/79. Secret. The meeting took
                        place in the Cabinet Room. After his meeting with <persName
                            corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1"
                            >Vajpayee</persName> met with <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1"
                            >Brzezinski</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Goheen</persName>,
                        and <persName corresp="#p_TTP_1">Thornton</persName> in <persName
                            corresp="#p_BZ_1">Brzezinski</persName>’s office from 11:30 a.m. to
                        12:30 p.m. to discuss multilateral issues. (Memorandum of Conversation,
                        April 24; Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Staff Material,
                        North/South, Thornton Country File, Box 93, India: Presidential
                        Correspondence: 1–5/79)</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                            from="1979-04-24T11:00:00-05:00" to="1979-04-24T11:30:00-05:00">April
                            24, 1979, 11–11:30 a.m.</date>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Meeting with Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1"
                            >Vajpayee</persName> of India</item>
                </list>
                <list type="participants">
                    <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">President Jimmy Carter</persName>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Cyrus Vance</persName>, Secretary of
                        State</item>
                    <item>Dr. <persName corresp="#p_BZ_1">Zbigniew Brzezinski</persName>, Assistant
                        to the President for National Security Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Robert Goheen</persName>, U.S. Ambassador to
                        India</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_TTP_1">Thomas Thornton</persName>, National Security
                        Council</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Atal Bihari Vajpayee</persName>, Foreign
                        Minister of India</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MJ_1">Jagat S. Mehta</persName>, Foreign Secretary,
                        Ministry of External Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_PN_1">N.A. Palkhivala</persName>, Ambassador of
                        India</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_DPP_1">P.P. D’Souza</persName>, Joint Secretary,
                        Ministry of External Affairs</item>
                    <item>
                        <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">A.B. Gokhale</persName>, Minister, Embassy of
                        India</item>
                </list>
                <p>The President and Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1"
                        >Vajpayee</persName> spent a few minutes in the Oval Office for
                    picture-taking and <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName> gave the
                    President a letter from Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Desai</persName>.<note n="2" xml:id="d139fn2">Telegram 104660 to New Delhi,
                        April 26, transmitted the text of <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                            >Desai</persName>’s April 19 letter to <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"
                            >Carter</persName>, which, besides discussing regional issues and
                        Pakistan’s clandestine nuclear program, expressed <persName
                            corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName>’s appreciation that the <gloss
                            target="#t_NRC_1">NRC</gloss> had approved the most recent shipment of
                        16.8 tons of uranium, and his appreciation for the release of the next
                        shipment of 19.6 tons. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1"
                            >RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D790190–0786)</note> They
                    then joined the rest of the party in the Cabinet Room. (U)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> thanked <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1"
                        >Vajpayee</persName> for bringing the letter and said that he found his
                    correspondence with <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> of greater
                    benefit than with almost any other world leader. He values <persName
                        corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName>’s advice and counsel. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> then said that we are confronted with
                    matters of great political and strategic importance. The United States has no
                    interest in gaining a leading role in South Asia and will defer to India on most
                    matters of regional importance. We are however deeply concerned about an
                    Indo-Pakistani nuclear weapons race. The President said that American policy has
                    been set forth in his correspondence with Prime <pb facs="0424" n="379"
                        xml:id="pg_379"/> Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> and
                    is also reflected in US laws with which the Government of India is familiar. We
                    do not seek to impose our will on other countries but the law (which the
                    President signed himself) governs our ability to engage in nuclear cooperation.
                    India will have to decide how it wants to proceed, whether it wishes to go into
                    plutonium reprocessing or even peaceful nuclear explosions. That is India’s
                    decision to make. Pakistan, the President said, clearly intends to develop a
                    nuclear explosive capability and we have been much tougher on Pakistan than on
                    India. The President said he was eager to see direct consultations on these
                    matters between India and Pakistan. He is well aware of the attempts India has
                    made to improve relations and hopes that India will make still more. The United
                    States is friends with both India and Pakistan but we do not want to become a
                    mediator. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> said he had been disconcerted at the
                    distortion of <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>’s important trip
                    to China by the invasion of Vietnam. He hoped that this lack of Chinese
                    sensitivity would not damage Sino-Indian relations. He pointed out that while
                        <persName corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName> was here he was very
                    enthusiastic about improved relations with India and expected much from Foreign
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>’s visit. <persName
                        corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName> hoped that the new governments in both the
                    countries would develop new relations of cooperation and understanding. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1"
                            >Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that he had been personally criticized in India and the
                    Indians had been very offended by the comparison the Chinese drew to the 1962
                    invasion. India however has not lost hope for the relationship. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> agreed that the Vietnamese episode had been
                    a wet blanket and it was certainly not India’s fault. Criticism of Foreign
                    Minister <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName> was unjust. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> suggested that the Chinese sought to improve relations with India in order
                    to undercut the USSR.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> replied that he did not think this was the
                    case. <persName corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName> had made frequent positive
                    statements and seems to feel that the time had come for the strengthening of
                    Sino-Indian relations. <persName corresp="#p_DX_1">Deng</persName> had been very
                    enthusiastic and talked of solving long term disputes. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> interjected that the Chinese were modernizing their defense forces and
                    this caused particular concern to India when coupled with their assertion of the
                    right to punish neighbors. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> replied that we are not trying to justify
                    the Chinese action. We had done our utmost to prevent it and still think that it
                    was a mistake. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> expressed indignation that the Chinese had not even told him that they
                    were going to launch an invasion. (S)</p>
                <pb facs="0425" n="380" xml:id="pg_380"/>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> replied that they should have done so and he
                    would make no apologies for them. He hoped however that damage to the
                    Sino-Indian relationship would not be permanent. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> then addressed regional questions and asked if the United States was
                    thinking in terms of new military arrangements. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> said we were not and have no inclination to
                    play a greater leadership role in southern Asia. We look on India as the
                    strongest and most influential nation in the area and will most often defer to
                    Indian suggestions. We will not always agree with India. We have close
                    friendship with Pakistan and other regional states and we have nuclear concerns
                    over which we strongly disagree with India. It is important however that we
                    understand each other and that these disagreements not stand in the way of our
                    overall relationships. (S)</p>
                <p>Concerning Tarapur, the <hi rend="italic">President</hi> said that he could not
                    predict the future but India must realize that if there is no agreement on
                    safeguards, further cooperation on Tarapur would be impossible. There are other
                    sources to which the Indians could turn for fuel including the Soviet Union.
                    Canada, Australia and others share our views on nuclear explosions; perhaps
                    other countries may have different views. The President said he hoped it would
                    not come to a cut-off but he could not circumvent the law. The decision was up
                    to India. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> objected that the US law is retrospective. (sic) (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> said that he does not agree with that
                    interpretation, as he had told Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Desai</persName>. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> said that India was grateful for the most recent installment of uranium
                    and hopes supply will continue not only until 1980 but to 1993.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> warned against going on false premises. The
                    United States wants to avoid difficulties and still hopes that India and
                    Pakistan, working directly together and without US involvement, can reach a
                    mutual understanding. If they are unsuccessful in devising a safeguard
                    arrangement Pakistan will certainly move to develop a nuclear explosive and this
                    will put India in a very difficult situation. South Asia could become embroiled
                    in a nuclear arms race which would be very embarrassing to India’s international
                    position. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that India did not embark on a nuclear arms race against China
                    and the Pakistanis should show similar self-restraint. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> emphasized that we have done everything
                    possible [<hi rend="italic">3 lines not declassified</hi>].</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> said however that the United States could do still more. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>
                    </hi> noted that he had told the Foreign Minister that our talks with Pakistan
                    are continuing and that it is in their interest to work with us. (S)</p>
                <pb facs="0426" n="381" xml:id="pg_381"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> said that the Pakistani nuclear program had no military justification and
                    that the Pakistan economy could not sustain it. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> agreed completely on both points. He then
                    mentioned that Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_DM_1">Desai</persName> had
                    said that Israel was the motivation for the Pakistani program but the President
                    disagreed. In his view, India is the focus of Pakistan’s problem. The President
                    thought that if India were to put its spent fuel under safeguards Pakistan would
                    be challenged to do the same and that would have a calming effect. This effect
                    would be felt even in South Africa, South Korea, Taiwan and other countries that
                    are within six months of a nuclear explosive capability. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> noted that we have established a unique
                    relationship with the Soviets in restraining nuclear weaponry. Never before have
                    two countries agreed on something like this and we are continuing to work to
                    expand the area of agreement. There are however 10 or 12 countries who could
                    build nuclear weapons almost immediately. They are waiting to see what happens
                    in India and Pakistan. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> said he knew that India had disavowed
                    nuclear explosions, but if Pakistan conducted a test India would find it hard to
                    keep to that line. That is a situation that must be avoided. The President
                    admitted that doing this without impinging on India’s sovereignty and pride
                    poses an almost insoluble problem. The decision is India’s whether it will seek
                    to get fuel for Tarapur elsewhere and perhaps become involved in a nuclear arms
                    race. The President suggested that he might have a better view of this matter
                    because he can see what is happening in other countries. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> stressed his hope that this difference of
                    opinion will not detract from the precious relationship we have with India in
                    other areas. He urged <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>, in his
                    public statements, to say what he was telling him—that we are not trying to
                    abuse India. This is a continuing problem not only with India but with Germany,
                    France, Argentina, Brazil and other countries. We are eager to help in any way
                    that we can. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> reminded the President that India had to cope with the democratic public
                    opinion. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> recognized this and admitted that we do not
                    have a solution. The decision rests with India. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> raised the question of storage of spent fuel at Tarapur but the President
                    suggested he discuss that elsewhere since he was not familiar with the technical
                    issues. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> complained that in the nuclear area the United States was again following
                    a policy of parity between India and Pakistan. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> objected that it was hard for him to talk
                    about balancing relations. He said that if General <persName corresp="#p_ZM_1"
                        >Zia</persName> were in the room he would <pb facs="0427" n="382"
                        xml:id="pg_382"/> tell him that our relations with India are warmer. He went
                    on to say that he does not equate the two countries in his mind and on this
                    issue the Pakistanis are clearly moving towards a nuclear explosive capability.
                    (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName>
                    </hi> then raised the problem of military hardware, notably the American offer
                    of F–5Es to Pakistan.<note n="3" xml:id="d139fn3">See <ref target="#d315fn6"
                            >footnote 6, Document 315</ref>.</note> He said that Pakistan does not
                    need armaments for their problem is political and economic. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> responded that he would not attempt to
                    compare what the Pakistanis have and what India has recently purchased. It is
                    not a matter for us to decide, and all countries should practice restraint. He
                    agreed with <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName> that military
                    forces, as the Iranian case had shown, did not protect a government from its
                    people. He noted that the American military’s mission was world peace, not
                    protecting him from the American people. (S)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>
                    </hi> pointed out that we have continually refused to sell the Pakistanis
                    advanced or long range aircraft such as the A–7, F–16 or F–18. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> pointed out that his first decision in the
                    arms sales area was to reverse a commitment that had been made to sell A–7s to
                        Pakistan.<note n="4" xml:id="d139fn4">In the margin of an April 2, 1977,
                        memorandum from <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName>,
                            <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> indicated his decision to
                        exclude A–7’s from a potential aid package for Pakistan. See <ref
                            target="#d240fn4">footnote 4, Document 240</ref>.</note> He pointed out
                    that the F–5 is a defensive, short range aircraft. When we have sold it to Egypt
                    the Israelis have not particularly objected. (S)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">President</hi> concluded by saying that he was pleased to
                    have had this chance to talk with <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1"
                        >Vajpayee</persName> and promised to read <persName corresp="#p_DM_1"
                        >Desai</persName>’s letter with great care. He expressed his great
                    admiration for <persName corresp="#p_VAB_1">Vajpayee</persName> personally and
                    said that both he and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>
                    were always glad to consult with him. The President said that the relationship
                    with India was precious to him and he wants it to be still closer and firmer.
                    (S)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
