<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-01-10T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-01-10T00:00:00-05:00" n="166" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d166">
                        <head>166. Letter From President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> to Indian Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_GI_1">Gandhi</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d166fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                Brzezinski Material, Country File, Box 28, India: 1–3/80. No
                                classification marking. Telegram 9356 to New Delhi, January 12,
                                directed the Embassy not to deliver this version of the letter to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GI_1">Gandhi</persName> because of
                                complications caused by the Indian statement at the January 11
                                    <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss> emergency special session
                                on Afghanistan. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D800021–0275)
                                According to telegram 122 from <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss>, January 12, the Indian representative, noting the
                                Soviet assurances to India that the Afghan Government had requested
                                Soviet military assistance, stated: “We have no reason to doubt
                                assurances, particularly from a friendly country like the Soviet
                                Union with whom we have many close ties.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D800020–0439) Telegram 10597 to New Delhi, January 13, and telegram
                                10917 to New Delhi, January 14, directed the Embassy to revise
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s letter in view
                                of the Indian statement at the <gloss target="#t_UNGA_1">UNGA</gloss>; see <ref target="#d166fn3">footnotes 3</ref>,
                                    <ref target="#d166fn4">4</ref>, and <ref target="#d166fn5">5</ref> below. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, D800023–0560 and
                                D800024–0521, respectively)</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-01-10">January 10, 1980</date></dateline>
                            <salute>Dear Madame Prime Minister:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>When I last wrote to you, after the 1977 general elections, I observed
                            that the essence of a democracy is its free electoral system.<note n="2" xml:id="d166fn2"><persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s
                                1977 letter to <persName corresp="#p_GI_1">Gandhi</persName> was not
                                found.</note> Now, nearly three years later, the people of India
                            have again demonstrated to the world the strength and vitality of their
                            democratic institutions—and have clearly shown their faith in you. I
                            warmly congratulate you upon your assumption of office.<note n="3" xml:id="d166fn3">Telegram 10917 to New Delhi, January 14, directed
                                the Embassy to change the last line of this paragraph to read: “I
                                congratulate you sincerely upon your assumption of office.” See <ref target="#d166fn1">footnote 1</ref> above.</note></p>
                        <p>I have asked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Goheen</persName> to
                            carry this letter to you, with my hope that it marks the beginning of an
                            active and candid dialogue. We have much to discuss with each other.
                            Because India and America are democracies with a free and active press,
                            the underlying policies each of our countries pursues may not always be
                            clear to the other. By communicating directly with each other, I hope
                            that there never will be any doubt about our actual positions. Should
                            any concern arise, I hope that you will contact me or Ambassador
                                <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Goheen</persName> directly.</p>
                        <p>Strengthening Indo-American relationships is a goal I set at the very
                            beginning of my Administration. We engaged with the Government of India
                            in continuing discussions on a wide range of international and regional
                            issues. Beyond the ties of democratic philosophy that bind our two
                            nations, we have striven to add flesh to our bilateral relationship. As
                            you know, we have resumed both military sales and economic development
                            assistance to India. The work of the Indo-US Joint Commission and its
                            four subcommissions has expanded greatly, and our <pb facs="0481" n="436" xml:id="pg_436"/> two countries are engaged in many
                            cooperative projects in such areas as solar energy and agricultural and
                            medical research. Trade between us continues to grow, as does cultural
                            and scholarly exchange. I want to see this process continue in the years
                            ahead.</p>
                        <p>With the exception of the tragic and dangerous situation in Afghanistan,
                            I am struck by the improvement in relations among the nations of South
                            Asia over the past five years or so. We have fully supported the major
                            role that India has taken in bringing this about. I sincerely hope that
                            this process—in which you have played such an important part—will
                            continue, and that India will make further progress toward reducing
                            tensions, resolving outstanding issues with its neighbors, and
                            encouraging regional stability.</p>
                        <p>In this regard, America cannot help but look with grave disquiet and
                            concern at the recent Soviet invasion of Afghanistan and the overthrow
                            of the <persName corresp="#p_AH_1">Amin</persName> Government by Soviet
                            troops. Soviet actions in Afghanistan and the continued presence there
                            of Soviet military forces directly engaged in operations against the
                            people of Afghanistan have serious consequences both for the region and
                            the world as a whole. I know that as the leading power in the region,
                            and as a nation that traditionally has opposed external interference in
                            the affairs of the area, India too is concerned about developments in
                            Afghanistan and their implication for the stability of the region. I am
                            eager to receive your thoughts on this question.<note n="4" xml:id="d166fn4">Telegram 10917 to New Delhi, January 14, directed
                                the Embassy to change the last two sentences of this paragraph to
                                read: “I assume that as the leading power in the region and as a
                                nation that traditionally has opposed external interference in the
                                affairs of the area, India too must recognize the serious
                                consequences of developments in Afghanistan and their implication
                                for the stability of the region. I will be interested to receive
                                your personal thoughts on this question.” The telegram also directed
                                that the revised letter be dated January 14 and delivered to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_GI_1">Gandhi</persName>. See <ref target="#d166fn1">footnote 1</ref> above.</note></p>
                        <p>Pakistan is obviously and understandably concerned. We are prepared to
                            respond to Pakistan’s needs in the context of the events in Afghanistan.
                            I am fully aware of India’s concerns, but I feel the changed
                            circumstances require understanding on both our parts. The U.S. also
                            intends to be more responsive to Indian requests for military equipment,
                            including high technology items that India cannot produce itself. I will
                            ask Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Goheen</persName> to keep in
                            close touch with you on these questions.</p>
                        <p>We are seeking neither alignment with any nation in the region nor
                            confrontation between any nation and the Soviet Union. I am firmly
                            convinced that the nations of South Asia bear the responsibility for
                            their own security. The United States seeks no position of special
                            influence there. We welcome a non-aligned South Asia that seeks equally
                                <pb facs="0482" n="437" xml:id="pg_437"/> good relations with the
                            Soviet Union and the United States, a South Asia free of all external
                            manipulation. But I believe strongly that Soviet actions in
                            Afghanistan—what is, for all practical purposes, their occupation of a
                            sovereign member of the Non-Aligned Movement—strike directly at policies
                            that both our countries have pursued in recent years. It is vitally
                            important that we fully understand each other’s views and actions.</p>
                        <p>The most difficult bilateral issue we face is the future of our nuclear
                            relationship. We are well aware of each other’s positions on this
                            question. The resolution of our differences is a matter that we shall
                            want to pursue further with your Government as soon as you find it
                            convenient. In the meantime, I am prepared to issue an Executive Order
                            authorizing the first of the two pending exports for the Tarapur
                            reactors if the Nuclear Regulatory Commission does not act favorably and
                            expeditiously. I shall also direct that the Executive Branch submit a
                            favorable recommendation to the <gloss target="#t_NRC_1">NRC</gloss> on
                            the second application. I have asked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Goheen</persName> to discuss with you the
                            difficulties that we may encounter with these exports and ways in which
                            they might be met.<note n="5" xml:id="d166fn5">Telegram 10597 to New
                                Delhi, January 13, directed the Embassy to revise the preceding
                                three sentences to read: “In the meantime, we would be prepared to
                                issue an Executive Order authorizing the first of the two pending
                                exports for the Tarapur reactors if the Nuclear Regulatory
                                Commission does not act favorably and expeditiously and if your
                                government would agree to provide the assurances which had been made
                                available to us earlier. I would also direct that the Executive
                                Branch submit a favorable recommendation to the <gloss target="#t_NRC_1">NRC</gloss> on the second application. I have
                                asked Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_GRF_1">Goheen</persName> to
                                discuss this with you.” See <ref target="#d166fn1">footnote 1</ref>
                                above.</note> The nuclear issue is especially difficult because both
                            of our countries base their positions on principles sincerely held. I
                            hope this token of our good faith will be the first step towards a
                            solution that satisfies all of our common concerns.</p>
                        <p>Finally, I would like to repeat my hope that this might be the first
                            letter in a regular correspondence. I earnestly seek your views on the
                            many concerns that our two nations share. I recognize that during the
                            history of our relations with India there have been too many occasions
                            when both nations talked but neither listened to what the other was
                            saying. I am as eager to listen as to talk, and to build a future
                            relationship of mutual trust and understanding between us.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_CJE_1"><hi rend="strong">Jimmy
                                    Carter</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>