<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-01-19T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-01-19T00:00:00-05:00" n="20" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d20">
                        <head>20. Briefing Memorandum From the Assistant Secretary of State for Near
                            Eastern and South Asian Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>) to the Under Secretary of State for Political
                            Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_HPC_1">Habib</persName>)<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d20fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                P770025–0305. Secret. Drafted by Douglas B. Archard (<gloss target="#t_NEAPAB_1">NEA/PAB</gloss>) on January 18. An unknown
                                hand initialed the memorandum for <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-01-19">January 19, 1977</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p rend="center"><hi rend="italic">Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName>’ Views on Present Situation in Bangladesh
                                and Recommended U.S. Programs (Summary of Dacca 246)</hi><note n="2" xml:id="d20fn2">Telegram 246 from Dacca, January 14, transmitted
                                    <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName>’s extended
                                report. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59,
                                Central Foreign Policy File, D770014–1034)</note></p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">POLITICAL SETTING</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName> has been favorably
                            impressed by General <persName corresp="#p_ZM_1">Zia</persName>.<note n="3" xml:id="d20fn3">General <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Ziaur
                                    (Zia) Rahman</persName>. When <persName corresp="#p_SASM_1">Sayem</persName> took office in November 1975, <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zia</persName> took over <persName corresp="#p_SASM_1">Sayem</persName>’s former position as Chief
                                Martial Law Administrator.</note> While not charismatic, he is
                            sensible, hard working, incorrupt and a dedicated patriot. His policies,
                            statements and actions are right, but as with virtually everything in
                            Bangladesh, follow-through at lower levels of the government falls
                            short. The Army is <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zia</persName>’s power
                            base. While not totally cohesive, it is by far the strongest political
                            force in the country. <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zia</persName> clearly
                            commands wide support in the army, but there are other contenders for
                            power which would be strengthened if the economic progress of the past
                            year were to falter.</p>
                        <p>We cannot be certain how long <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zia</persName>
                            will remain in office or how repressive his government might become. We
                            should, given the fragility of political institutions and traditions,
                            avoid a commitment to him or any other single individual. Thus far there
                            has been no significant opposition to <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zia</persName>’s tightening of authoritarian control. Most people
                            are more interested in adequate food, jobs and price stability than in
                            elections under present circumstances. <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zia</persName> probably has several years to show what he can do.
                            By then, and by one means or another, he will have to (a) legitimize his
                            own regime or return to a government which, directly or indirectly, is
                            accountable to the people or (b) become more repressive to retain power
                            against what is likely to be rising opposition.</p>
                        <p>In foreign policy Zia is conservative, non-communist but pragmatic. He
                            seeks good relations with everyone but leans ideologically <pb facs="0119" n="74" xml:id="pg_74"/> toward the U.S. and U.K.
                                <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zia</persName> would like us to
                            undertake responsibility for Bangladesh’s defense. <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName> has stressed that efforts to
                            draw us too closely into these matters would not only fail, but would
                            endanger the broad base of support for economic assistance within the
                            U.S. Government. He believes <persName corresp="#p_RZ_1">Zia</persName>
                            now understands this and that this, in part, explains the recent
                            spreading of his international options, as by his successful trip to
                            China.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">ECONOMIC BACKGROUND</p>
                        <p>Bangladesh shows clear signs of economic life. The Government has
                            expanded the scope for private enterprise, controlled smuggling,
                            encouraged exports, checked rampant inflation, and—taking advantage of
                            good weather—produced a record rice crop.</p>
                        <p>But the pace of economic development measured by industrial production
                            (still ten percent below 1969/70) and project implementation is
                            disappointing. Also, family planning requires more vigorous action if
                            Bangladesh is to survive. Population is growing at about three percent
                            annually while agricultural production is growing at only one
                            percent.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">U.S. PROGRAMS</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Our Objectives:</hi>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName> suggests two <gloss target="#t_USG_1">USG</gloss> objectives in Bangladesh: first, to do
                            what we can to contribute to stability in South Asia (and Bangladesh is
                            undoubtedly its most vulnerable area) and, second, to fulfill our
                            humanitarian desire to help these “poorest of the poor.” Except for
                            these objectives, we have no vital or even very important interests
                            there.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Program Recommendations:</hi> For these reasons, the
                            major U.S. role should continue to be in the field of economic aid. This
                            and three other areas require urgent attention.</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Military Equipment and Training:</hi>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName> recommends we not get
                            into a grant <gloss target="#t_MAP_1">MAP</gloss> or concessional sales
                            program. He recommends the U.S. initiate the same type of limited
                            military sales and other programs in Bangladesh as in other nations of
                            South Asia. This would require a Presidential Determination. This would
                            allow the sale of limited noncombat items available as excess U.S.
                            equipment at reduced prices. He recommends establishing a small Defense
                            Attache office.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss>
                                Activities:</hi>
                            <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName> recommends immediate
                            assignment of a third <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> officer,
                            upgrading of <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> Bangladesh from
                            resource allocation group eight to at least group seven, and doubling of
                            the present cultural exchange program.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Office Building:</hi> He urges moving ahead rapidly
                            with construction of a new chancery. The Foreign Service Inspectors said
                            last year that the Dacca Embassy was one of the worst in the world. He
                            asks that <pb facs="0120" n="75" xml:id="pg_75"/> everything possible be
                            done in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 77 so that construction can
                            actually start at the beginning of the next fiscal year.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_PL480_1">PL 480</gloss>
                                Negotiating Instructions:</hi> To better encourage a vigorous <gloss target="#t_BDG_1">BDG</gloss> food grain procurement program,
                                <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName> requests prompt
                            transmittal of <gloss target="#t_PL480_1">PL 480</gloss> negotiating
                            instructions.</p>
                        <p rend="sectiontitleital">Current Status of Recommendations</p>
                        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Presidential Determination (PD):</hi> We have
                            recently sought a PD for Bangladesh but encountered objections from L,
                            H, and <gloss target="#t_DODISA_1">DOD/ISA</gloss>, partly on the
                            grounds that the new Administration should make the decision. As soon as
                            possible we will again seek a Determination.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Excess Equipment:</hi> With a PD, Bangladesh would be
                            eligible for purchase of excess U.S. equipment. The <gloss target="#t_BDG_1">BDG</gloss> turned down our offer of a minesweeper
                            which we offered them as a hydrographic research ship. (They asked for
                            it to use as a minesweeper but we and <gloss target="#t_DOD_1">DOD</gloss> do not favor this.) We are still looking for another
                            ship for hydrographic purposes.</p>
                        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Third <gloss target="#t_USIS_1">USIS</gloss> Officer
                                and Upgrading Resource Allocation Group:</hi> USIA’s Deputy
                            Assistant Director for <gloss target="#t_INA_1">INA</gloss> will discuss
                            the recommendations with <persName corresp="#p_MEE_1">Masters</persName>
                            in Dacca this February.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Increasing Cultural Exchange Program:</hi>
                            <gloss target="#t_CU_1">CU</gloss>’s current planning figure for the
                                <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 78 Bangladesh cultural exchange
                            program would almost double the current level.</p>
                        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">New Dacca Chancery:</hi> NEA is working closely with
                                <gloss target="#t_FBO_1">FBO</gloss> to ensure that all possible
                            steps are taken prior to availability of construction funds in <gloss target="#t_FY_1">FY</gloss> 78.</p>
                        <p>4. <hi rend="italic"><gloss target="#t_PL480_1">PL 480</gloss>
                                Negotiating Instructions:</hi> We are attempting to get <gloss target="#t_USDA_1">USDA</gloss> to provide the Embassy with
                            instructions. <gloss target="#t_USDA_1">USDA</gloss> has dragged its
                            feet due to a desire to get more food in the package than Embassy Dacca
                            wished.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>