<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1977-02-14T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1977-02-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="231" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d231">
                        <head>231. Letter From Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> to Pakistani Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_BZA_1">Bhutto</persName><note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d231fn1">Source: National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File, P770030–2355.
                                Confidential. Drafted on February 3 by <persName corresp="#p_LP_1">Lande</persName> and Jan Kalicki in <gloss target="#t_SP_1">S/P</gloss>; approved by <persName corresp="#p_AAL_1">Atherton</persName>. In the upper right-hand corner of the
                                first page of the letter, an unknown hand wrote: “Orig given to Pak.
                                    <gloss target="#t_Amb_1">Amb</gloss>. by Mr <persName corresp="#p_CW_1">Christopher</persName> Feb 14.”</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1977-02-14">February 14, 1977</date></dateline>
                            <salute>Dear Mr. Prime Minister:</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>My predecessor has brought me fully up to date on our past consultations
                            regarding non-proliferation issues, in the context of the close and
                            friendly bilateral relationship our two Governments have enjoyed over
                            several decades. I would like to take this opportunity to reaffirm my
                            interest in continuing this relationship which has been of benefit to
                            both countries.</p>
                        <pb facs="0615" n="570" xml:id="pg_570"/>
                        <p>As you know, President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> is
                            deeply concerned about the implications of sensitive technology
                            transfers, including reprocessing, for the non-proliferation objectives
                            which are of fundamental importance on a worldwide basis. At the same
                            time, we recognize the importance of the legitimate needs of others
                            being fulfilled as they forego capabilities for which we can see no
                            valid basis.</p>
                        <p>It is in this general context that I would like to suggest that we resume
                            confidential discussions of alternatives to your Government’s
                            reprocessing plans. In light of your upcoming elections,<note n="2" xml:id="d231fn2">In telegram 227 from Islamabad, January 8, the
                                Embassy reported that during a January 8 address to the Pakistan
                                National Assembly, <persName corresp="#p_BZA_1">Bhutto</persName>
                                announced that general elections for the National Assembly would be
                                held on March 7 and elections for provincial assemblies on March 10.
                                (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central
                                Foreign Policy File, D770008–0153)</note> I propose we consider
                            opening consultations in mid- or late March unless you believe it would
                            be useful to open these earlier. Pending these talks, I would hope that
                            your Government would take no further steps to carry out the
                            reprocessing project. For our part, we will do all we can to avoid
                            making this a public issue between our two countries.</p>
                        <p>I hope that you share my feeling about the importance of resolving this
                            issue to the satisfaction of both countries. I look forward to receiving
                            your ideas as to the next steps in this dialogue.</p>
                        <p>Sincerely,</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_VCR_1"><hi rend="strong">Cyrus
                                    Vance</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>