<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-01-23T02:35:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-01-23T02:35:00-05:00" n="47" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d47">
                        <head>47. Telegram From the Embassy in Bangladesh to the Department of
                                State<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d47fn1">Source: National
                                Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign
                                Policy File, D800039–0560. Confidential; Immediate; <gloss target="#t_Exdis_1">Exdis</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Dacca</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1980-01-23T07:35:00+00:00">January 23, 1980,
                                0735Z</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>461. Subject: Bangladeshi Abstentions on Sanctions. Ref: A) State
                                333770<note n="2" xml:id="d47fn2">See <ref target="#d44fn5">footnote
                                    5, Document 44</ref>.</note> B) Secto 130003<note n="3" xml:id="d47fn3">Not found.</note> C) State 0069.<note n="4" xml:id="d47fn4">See <ref target="#d45fn2">footnote 2, Document
                                    45</ref>. </note></p>
                        <p>1. C–Entire text.</p>
                        <p>2. I believe our credibility requires that we demonstrate in some
                            tangible way to President Zia our displeasure at his failure to support
                            US on sanctions. Deciding how to do this is complicated by our
                            continuing interest in development and stability in Bangladesh and our
                            interest in the continuation of Bangladesh’s moderate stance as an
                            Islamic nation and as a participant in international deliberations. For
                            these reasons I would not propose that aid or food levels be affected
                            but I would suggest a rebuke in regard to another of Zia’s objective:
                            his desire for close rapport with President <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>. Since the basis for that rapport has been
                            destroyed, we might just as well let Zia know.</p>
                        <p>3. I propose that this be done by sending a fairly direct and sharp
                            response to Zia’s long and excessive request to the President for
                            various forms of aid (State 315730).<note n="5" xml:id="d47fn5">Telegram
                                315730 to Dacca, December 8, 1979, transmitted the text of Zia’s
                                November 12 letter to <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, in which Zia reiterated his requests for more
                                food and other types of assistance. (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D790566–0221) In response to Zia’s letter, telegram 321056 to Dacca,
                                December 13, 1979, the Department informed the Embassy: “It does not
                                appear likely however, that we will be able to respond positively in
                                any significant way.” (National Archives, <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy File,
                                D790573–0488)</note> We can’t meet his inflated requests anyway and
                            rather than giving him a polite and indirect response, I suggest we tell
                            him briefly we can give him no aid above planned levels and that food
                            assistance will depend entirely on <gloss target="#t_BDG_1">BDG</gloss>
                            performance. (We should leave ourselves leeway to support necessary food
                            reforms.) The letter should also turn down his request for military
                            assistance. I do not repeat not suggest that we explicitly interrelate
                            our response with Bangladesh’s vote. The letter may circulate beyond
                            Zia. He will nonetheless understand that the letter’s sharp and direct
                            tone is the result of his refusal to help us on sanctions. I believe Zia
                            is realist enough to <pb facs="0172" n="127" xml:id="pg_127"/> respect a
                            country which takes firm actions in accordance with its interests.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <signed><persName corresp="#p_SDT_1"><hi rend="strong">Schneider</hi></persName></signed>
                        </closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>