<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1980-02-29T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1980-02-29T00:00:00-05:00" n="482" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d482">
                        <head>482. Memorandum of Conversation<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d482fn1">Source: Carter Library, National Security Affairs,
                                Staff Material, North/South, Thornton Country File, Box 97, Sri
                                Lanka: Presidential Correspondence: 1/80–1/81. Secret; <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>.</note></head>
                        <opener>
                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date ana="#date_undated-inferred-from-document-content" calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1980-02-29">undated</date></dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Sri Lankan Finance Minister’s Call on the Secretary</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>Sri Lankan Finance Minister Ronnie de Mel met with the Secretary February
                            29 as special envoy of President Jayewardene. Meeting lasted 30 minutes.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> was unaccompanied.
                            Howard <persName corresp="#p_SHB_1">Schaffer</persName>, <gloss target="#t_NEAINS_1">NEA/INS</gloss> Director, was notetaker.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> recalled that
                            Jayewardene’s government had adopted a pragmatic and practical policy in
                            many areas, including the economy, which had successfully grown as a
                            result. The time had now come for it to be more practical and pragmatic
                            in its foreign policy. It had studied with great care President
                                <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>’s State of the Union
                            message, particularly the reference to the US’ desire to cooperate with
                            the states of the South Asian region.<note n="2" xml:id="d482fn2">In his
                                January 21 State of the Union message to Congress, <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> proposed that the United
                                States help South Asian countries “develop a capability to withstand
                                Soviet pressures in a strengthened framework for cooperation in the
                                region. We want to cooperate with all the states of the region in
                                this regard—with India and Pakistan, with Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and
                                Nepal.” <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> noted: “We
                                are also pursuing the possibility of gaining access to military
                                facilities in the region in time of trouble. We are prepared to work
                                closely with our friends in the region, on a cooperative basis, to
                                do whatever is required to ensure that aggressors would bear heavy
                                costs so that further aggression is deterred.” (<hi rend="italic">Public Papers:</hi>
                                <hi rend="italic"><persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>,
                                    1980–81</hi>, Book I, pp. 171–172) See also <ref target="#d16">Document 16</ref>.</note> The <gloss target="#t_GSL_1">GSL</gloss> had decided to respond positively to the President’s
                            invitation.</p>
                        <pb facs="1142" n="1097" xml:id="pg_1097"/>
                        <p>While Sri Lanka would remain in the non-aligned movement and “basically
                            non-aligned”, it now wished to play a different role in the area. As a
                            small country equally friendly with all regional states, it could play a
                            useful role in working out some form of consultative process among them
                            in the face of Soviet aggression. This would include efforts to improve
                            relations between the South Asian countries, especially between India
                            and Pakistan. President Jayewardene was prepared to take the initiative,
                            de Mel said. The Secretary said he was pleased that Sri Lanka was
                            prepared to play such a catalytic role at this time, and noted that it
                            was particularly well qualified to do so.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> said there was a second,
                            more difficult aspect to the <gloss target="#t_GSL_1">GSL</gloss>’s new
                            approach. The <gloss target="#t_GSL_1">GSL</gloss> had made a decision
                            to work in closer association with the US than it had in the past. While
                            the form that the implementation of this decision would take had still
                            to be evolved, he could say that Sri Lanka was prepared to be responsive
                            to the President’s State of the Union message statement (which he
                            quoted) regarding the US “pursuing the possibility of gaining access to
                            military facilities in the region in time of trouble.” He could tell the
                            Secretary in confidence that in the event of open confrontation Sri
                            Lanka would have “only one friend, the United States.” It was prepared
                            to give the US access to naval and other facilities in such an event.
                            (de Mel did not specifically mention US-Soviet open confrontation but
                            from the context of his discussion it is clear that that is what he
                            meant. He later told <persName corresp="#p_SHB_1">Schaffer</persName>
                            that the Sri Lankan offer specifically included use of the port of
                            Trincomalee.)</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> said that it was very
                            important that the offer be kept secret. (Comment: He is dead right. A
                            leak could be very damaging to the Jayewardene government. End
                            Comment.)</p>
                        <p>The Secretary stated that the Sri Lankan decision was a very important
                            one. He said the President—to whom he would relay it at once—would
                            appreciate it and find it of great significance.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> said that in coming to
                            its decision to change its foreign policy approach the <gloss target="#t_GSL_1">GSL</gloss> had taken many aspects into
                            consideration. He sought to link the move to take a more active role in
                            the area with the decision to become more closely associated with the
                            US. By seeking to bring about better understanding among the regional
                            countries and encouraging “common thinking”, Sri Lanka could make them
                            more understanding of its policy of closer friendship with the US.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> touched on the Sri
                            Lankan approach to the Indian Ocean Zone of Peace. Noting that Sri Lanka
                            is chairman of the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss>
                            <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi> committee, he said the <gloss target="#t_GSL_1">GSL</gloss> would have to continue to make noises
                                <pb facs="1143" n="1098" xml:id="pg_1098"/> there.<note n="3" xml:id="d482fn3">Sri Lanka chaired the <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> Indian Ocean Zone of Peace (<gloss target="#t_IOZP_1">IOZP</gloss>) Ad Hoc Committee, which
                                promoted demilitarization of the Indian Ocean. Also on the committee
                                were representatives from Mozambique, Madagascar, and Indonesia.
                                Telegram 142646 to <gloss target="#t_USUN_1">USUN</gloss>, May 31,
                                transmitted an interagency-approved scope paper that provided
                                background on the <gloss target="#t_IOZP_1">IOZP</gloss>: “The
                                proposal to turn the Indian Ocean into a zone of peace originated in
                                a 1971 <gloss target="#t_UN_1">UN</gloss> resolution sponsored by
                                Sri Lanka. In 1972, an ad hoc committee was set up to prepare the
                                way for implementation of an <gloss target="#t_IOZP_1">IOZP</gloss>,
                                and work has proceeded slowly toward that goal ever since. Until
                                recently, we refused to join the committee because substantively we
                                opposed the concept itself and tactically we saw little danger of
                                the committee’s work producing tangible results. Last year, however,
                                this picture changed. The committee finally set a date for an <gloss target="#t_IOZP_1">IOZP</gloss> conference (1981), and its
                                membership was substantially widened to include the Soviet Union and
                                several major maritime users—including many of our <gloss target="#t_NATO_1">NATO</gloss> allies.” (National Archives,
                                    <gloss target="#t_RG_1">RG</gloss> 59, Central Foreign Policy
                                File, D800266–0477)</note> He noted that Jayewardene does not
                            believe that the <gloss target="#t_IOZP_1">IOZP</gloss> concept is a
                            feasible proposition. There must be a balance of power in the Indian
                            Ocean area, and this balance must include the land forces stationed in
                            the region. In this connection, he said that the only way that the
                            Soviet drive toward warm water ports could be dealt with was through
                            counter-balancing naval forces in the Indian Ocean.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that we had hoped three years ago to be able to limit
                            naval forces in the area. It is now necessary for us to maintain an
                            over-the-horizon naval force to balance the Soviets. We had told the
                            Soviets that there was no longer a basis for continued discussion of the
                            reduction of naval forces in the Indian Ocean until circumstances change
                            in that part of the world.<note n="4" xml:id="d482fn4">For documentation
                                on U.S. efforts to promote arms limitation in the Indian Ocean, see
                                    <ref target="frus1977-80v18"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations</hi>, 1977–1980, vol. XVIII, Middle East Region;
                                    Arabian Peninsula</ref>. U.S.-Soviet discussions on the issue
                                were suspended in February 1978.</note></p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> said that Jayewardene
                            also wished to convey to the President and the Secretary his favorable
                            reaction to the President’s State of the Union message statement about
                            the importance of steady growth of US economic assistance to the South
                            Asian countries. He spoke of the difficulties world-wide inflation has
                            caused for Sri Lanka’s development plans. Citing Sri Lanka’s democratic
                            traditions, human rights record, pragmatic economic programs and
                            stability, he urged that the US do what it can in providing increased
                            assistance to help Sri Lanka meet inflation-induced shortfalls.
                                <persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> gave the Secretary
                            a copy of a letter he had brought from Jayewardene to the President
                            which focused on this.<note n="5" xml:id="d482fn5">See <ref target="#d483">Document 483</ref>.</note> He also urged greater
                            US private investment in Sri Lanka.</p>
                        <p><persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> made no specific mention
                            of Jayewardene’s plan to call a meeting of regional countries to appeal
                            for Soviet withdrawal from Afghanistan.<note n="6" xml:id="d482fn6">See
                                    <ref target="#d481">Document 481</ref>.</note> He told <persName corresp="#p_SHB_1">Schaffer</persName> afterwards that if the
                            President <pb facs="1144" n="1099" xml:id="pg_1099"/> responded
                            favorably to the message he had passed to the Secretary, the <gloss target="#t_GSL_1">GSL</gloss> would be prepared to send emissaries
                            to other South Asian states. He did not say what their specific mission
                            would be.<note n="7" xml:id="d482fn7">In a March 1 memorandum to
                                    <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName> summarized his meeting with
                                    <persName corresp="#p_DMRJG_1">De Mel</persName> and noted: “The
                                decisions taken by Sri Lanka are a major change of position on their
                                part.” <persName corresp="#p_CJE_1">Carter</persName> initialed
                                    <persName corresp="#p_VCR_1">Vance</persName>’s memorandum.
                                (Carter Library, National Security Affairs, Brzezinski Material,
                                Subject File, Box 23, Evening Reports (State): 3/80)</note></p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>