<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-01-13T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-01-13T00:00:00-05:00" n="232" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d232">
                    <head>No. 232.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">McLane</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-01-13"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 13, 1887</date>.
                            (Received January 25.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 346.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to send herewith copy of a
                        letter received from Mr. Richard King, domiciled in the United States, but
                        temporarily residing at No. 20 Boulevard Montmartre, Paris, who applies for
                        a passport. Mr. Ring is not a full American citizen; he has only declared
                        his intention of becoming one. According to the regulations he is not
                        entitled to a passport. Upon his insistence that he could not do without it,
                        and that it would not be proper to apply for one at the British embassy, I
                        advised him to make his application in writing, which I promised to submit
                        to your consideration.</p>
                    <p>I would not have done so if your circular of June 29, 1885, with reference to
                        changes in Articles XI and XXIV of the Consular Regulations had not led me
                        to believe that in certain cases protection might be extended to one
                        domiciled in the United States. As in the case of Mr. King protection can
                        only be extended in the shape of a passport, I beg to be informed whether I
                        can properly issue one to him, and, if so, whether the same will be a
                        qualified one and in what sense.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Robert M. McLane.</hi></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 346.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">King</persName> to Mr.
                                    <persName type="to">McLane</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>20 <hi rend="smallcaps">Boulevard Montmartre</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Paris</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-01-08"><hi rend="italic">January</hi> 8,
                                1887</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: In accordance with the verbal instructions
                            given me at your office this day I have the honor to request that a
                            passport may be granted me as an American citizen, having taken out and
                            declared my intention to become a citizen of the United States. I may
                            say that I made the declarations (necessary) the 20th August, 1883, copy
                            of which was handed in by me for your perusal this day. I had then and
                            still have every intention of taking out my final papers. For your
                            information I may add that I am a Canadian by birth and have resided in
                            the United States on and off for a period of about ten years.</p>
                        <p>I propose making a journey shortly to Russia to represent an American
                            firm there, and should I be unable to obtain the necessary passport I
                            would be (with deep regret) obliged to destroy my declaration of 1883,
                            and once more become a British subject. Under these peculiar
                            circumstances, and, further, my interests being entirely in arid with
                            the United States, I trust that you may be enabled to grant my
                            request.</p>
                        <p>Apologizing for the length of my letter and awaiting an early reply, for
                            which please accept my thanks in advance,</p>
                        <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Rich’d King.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>