<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 405.Mr. Ferrara to Mr. Bayard.</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1887</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d405</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">405</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1887-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1887-07-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recMjLDCnI9cLa32M" type="topic" category="international-law"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85029378"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Compliance</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-07-18T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-07-18T00:00:00-05:00" n="405"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d405">
                <head>No. 405.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Ferrara</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>.</hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Italy</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-07-18">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 18, 1887</date>. (Received July
                        18.)</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Secretary of State</hi>:</p>
                <p>In virtue of several proclamations issued by the President, the last of which
                    bears date of the 22d of April last, and has reference to the ports of the
                    Netherlands and to certain ports in the East Indies, the collection of tonnage
                    dues has been suspended as regards merchant vessels, whatever may be their
                    nationality, coming from the ports designated in the aforesaid proclamations,
                    provided that the countries to which such vessels belong do not levy upon
                    American merchant vessels higher duties than they do upon their own.</p>
                <p>The Government of the King has just informed me that, in the ports of Italy,
                    United States vessels and their cargoes, as well as those sailing under any
                    other flag, are required to pay only the same duties and imposts as Italian
                    vessels, and it instructs me, at the same time, to take the necessary steps to
                    the end that Italian merchant vessels may enjoy the benefits granted by the
                    proclamations aforesaid.</p>
                <p>I consequently have the honor to beg your excellency to be pleased to cause the
                    necessary measures to be taken in order that Italian vessels coming from the
                    ports mentioned in the proclamations referred to may be freely allowed to enter
                    the ports of the United States without being subjected to the payment of tonnage
                    dues.</p>
                <p>Thanking you in advance for your kind compliance with this my request. I avail
                    myself, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">E. Ferrara.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
