<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-07-26T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-07-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="406" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d406">
                        <head>No. 406.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Bayard</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Ferrara</persName>.</hi></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of State</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-07-26"><hi rend="italic">July</hi> 26,
                                1887</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to acknowledge the
                            receipt of your note of the 18th instant, in which you refer to the
                            proclamation of the President, of the 22d April last, under section 11
                            of the shipping act of June 19, 1886, suspending the collection of
                            tonnage dues on vessels entering our ports from those of the Netherlands
                            in Europe and from certain Dutch East Indian ports, and say, that “in
                            the ports of Italy, United States vessels <pb facs="0746" n="652" xml:id="pg_652"/> and their named cargoes, as well as those sailing
                            under any other flag, are required to pay only the same duties and
                            imposts as Italian vessels,” which facts, your Government understands,
                            entitle Italian vessels coming from said-named Dutch ports to the
                            benefits of the proclamation.</p>
                        <p>The proviso in the proclamation, excluding certain vessels from the
                            benefits, reads as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                                <p><hi rend="italic">Provided</hi>, That there shall be excluded
                                    from the benefits of the suspension hereby declared and
                                    proclaimed, the vessels of any foreign country in whose ports
                                    the fees or dues of any kind or nature imposed on vessels of the
                                    United States, or the import or export duties on their cargoes
                                    are in excess of the fees, dues, or duties imposed on the
                                    vessels of such foreign country, or their cargoes, or of the
                                    fees, dues, or duties imposed on the vessels of the country in
                                    which are the ports mentioned in this proclamation, or the
                                    cargoes of such vessels.</p>
                            </quote></p>
                        <p>While the facts given in your note may place Italian vessels from said
                            Dutch ports outside of the above proviso, the actual statement does not
                            precisely meet the terms of the proviso. It is, you will perceive, not
                            only requisite that the country whose vessels seek to enjoy the
                            privilege stated in the proclamation should not discriminate in its
                            ports in favor of its own vessels as against vessels of the United
                            States, but also that it should not discriminate in its ports against
                            vessels of the United States, and in favor of the vessels of the country
                            in which the ports named in the proclamation may be situate.</p>
                        <p>If, therefore, Italy makes no discrimination of any sort, such as
                            described in the proclamation, against American vessels, the Department
                            would be glad of an express statement, such as might be suggested by the
                            terms of the proviso.</p>
                        <p>The Department will, however, transmit a copy of your note to the
                            Treasury, with the request that if no such discrimination as that
                            described in the proclamation is made by Italy, Italian vessels may be
                            permitted to enjoy the benefits of the proclamation, when coming from
                            the ports therein designated. Accept, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">T. F. Bayard.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>