<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-03-01T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-03-01T00:00:00-05:00" n="53" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d53">
                    <head>No. 53.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Trail</persName>
                            to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Rio de
                                    Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-03-01"><hi rend="italic">March</hi> 1, 1887</date>.
                            (Received April 9.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 74.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: On the morning of the 25th ult. I received at
                        Petropolis the following cable: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Use good offices for extending concession to Pedro Segundo American
                                Cable Company.</p>
                            <p rend="right"><hi rend="smallcaps">Bayard.</hi></p></quote></p>
                    <pb facs="0153" n="59" xml:id="pg_59"/>
                    <p>To which I replied on the 28th: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>Telegram received; action taken with representative.</p></quote></p>
                    <p>The company’s resident agent informed me that the concession would expire
                        March 4th, and that he had not yet received instructions from New York
                        concerning an extension of the concession, As but a week remained from the
                        time the Department’s telegram reached me to the date of the expiration of
                        the concession, I deemed it advisable to cable reply, thus informing the
                        company that the request for an extension had been made in time. Had the
                        agent been away from the city and the petition not put in by the 3d of March
                        the enterprise would have been considered as finally abandoned.</p>
                    <p>I used my “good offices” by addressing a note to the minister of foreign
                        affairs, a copy of which is hereto annexed, and by requesting the French
                        legation to furnish me with information concerning the French line in the
                        West Indies, the said information for the use and at the request of the
                        company’s representative.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles B. Trail.</hi></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No. 74.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Trail</persName> to Baron
                                    <persName type="to">de Cotegipe</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United states</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Rio de Janeiro</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-02-28"><hi rend="italic">February</hi> 28,
                                    1887</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I am informed that the concession granted
                            to the Dom Pedro Segundo and American Cable Company will expire the
                            early part of the coming month. As your excellency is well aware, this
                            company has been unable to carry out its plans within the allotted time,
                            owing to the opposition, it has met with from rival companies, and
                            latterly an additional delay was caused by the unsatisfactory condition
                            of the French line, with which the Dom pedro Segundo is to connect in
                            the West Indies.</p>
                        <p>The company petitions the Imperial Government for an extension of its
                            concession, and I am just in receipt of a cablegram from the honorable
                            Secretary of State, at Washington, which expresses the earnest desire
                            that Imperial Government may be pleased to grant the extension asked
                            for.</p>
                        <p>The present telegraphic rates between Brazil and the United States are so
                            enormously high that the public can indulge in this means of
                            communication only at rare intervals, and thus the business interests of
                            both countries suffer from the deprivation, in part, of what is
                            elsewhere one of the ordinary agents of commerce. The laying of another
                            line—competition—could not fail to remedy this state of affairs.</p>
                        <p>The United States Government could not but deeply regret to see the
                            forced abardonment of an enterprise that promised to bring Brazil into
                            closer connection with it. The interest manifested in this undertaking
                            by prominent Brazilians, and the fact that the necessity for the line
                            was fully recognized when the consession was originally granted, lead me
                            to hope that the favor of an extension will be granted at an early
                            day.</p>
                        <p>The present condition of the company and the matter in detail will be
                            respectfully presented to the proper Imperial department in a petition
                            now being prepared by the company’s representative in Rio de Janeiro,
                            Prof Orville A. Derby, for which I solicit your careful
                            consideration.</p>
                        <p>I avail, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles B.
                            Trail.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>