<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1886-11-08T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1886-11-08T00:00:00-05:00" n="63" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d63">
                    <head>No. 63.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hall</persName> to
                            Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName></hi>.</head>
                    <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States in Central America</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-11-08"><hi rend="italic">November</hi> 8, 1886</date>.
                            (Received December 1.)</dateline>
                        <seg rendition="#left">No. 582.]</seg></opener>
                    <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: Your instruction No. 379 of the 12th of
                        August, inclosing a copy of an interest-bearing bond purporting to have been
                        issued by Nicaragua in 1856, was received at the legation during my absence
                        in Honduras. Upon my return, in September, I addressed a note to the
                        minister for foreign affairs of Nicaragua, requesting such information as he
                        might be able to give as to the genuineness of the bond in question. I now
                        inclose a copy and translation of his reply, in which is transcribed a
                        communication upon the subject from the minister of the treasury.</p>
                    <p>It is alleged that no record exists of the decree of the 28th August, 1856,
                        under which the supposed bond is said to have been issued, nor any of the
                        bond itself. The minister infers from the dates mentioned that it is the
                        work of the so-called Walker Government, whose acts have never been
                        recognized by any Government of Nicaragua since that time.</p>
                    <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                    <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry C. Hall.</hi></signed></closer>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 582.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hall</persName> to Señor
                                    <persName type="to">Castellon</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States in Central
                                        America</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-09-22"><hi rend="italic">September</hi> 22,
                                    1886</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Minister</hi>: I beg leave to annex hereto a
                            copy of an interest-bearing bond, No. 69, for $200, purporting to have
                            been issued in virtue of a decree of the Government of Nicaragua of the
                            28th August, 1856; it bears date of November 1, 1856, and is made
                            payable at the Bank of Louisiana at New Orleans in gold or silver coin
                            or the equivalent.</p>
                        <p>Inquiry having been made at the Department of State in regard to this
                            bond, the matter has been referred to me for such information as I may
                            possess or may be able to obtain in regard to its genuineness or
                            validity. If your excellency will kindly furnish me with any information
                            on the subject to enable me to answer the inquiry of the Department, I
                            shall be very greatly obliged.</p>
                        <p>Renewing, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Henry C. Hall.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 582.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="smallcaps">Republic of Nicaragua</hi>.</head>
                        <p rend="flushleft">$200.]</p>
                        <p rend="right">[$200.</p>
                        <p>No. (69). Know all men by these presents that the Republic of Nicaragua
                            is indebted to the bearer hereof in the sum of $200, for value received,
                            which the said Republic promises to pay at the Bank of Louisiana, in the
                            city of New Orleans, in gold or silver coin, or their equivalent in
                            other currencies, in twenty years from the date hereof; and also to pay
                            an interest thereon at the rate of 6 percent, per annum, payable at the
                            bank aforesaid, at the end of each and every year upon the delivery of
                            the warrants in the margin hereof.</p>
                        <p>This bond is transferable by delivery, and the holder shall have the
                            right to give it in payment at par for one-half of the amount he may owe
                            the Government for any customs, dues, taxes, or local contributions
                            which may be laid or levied by the Republic of Nicaragua.</p>
                        <pb facs="0170" n="76" xml:id="pg_76"/>
                        <p>In witness whereof, the agents (<hi rend="italic">commissariat</hi>) of
                            the said Republic of Nicaragua sign these presents with their secretary,
                            who countersigns the same and affixes hereto the seal of the said
                            republic, in pursuance of a decree of said republic, dated on the 28th
                            day of August, A. D. 1756, duly deposited and recorded in the office of
                            William Christy, notary public, in the city of New Orleans, the 28th day
                            of October, 1856.</p>
                        <closer>
                            <dateline rendition="#left">Done at <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>,
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" when="1856-11-01">this 1st day of
                                    November, 1856</date>.</dateline>
                            <lb/>
                            <signed><hi rend="smallcaps">Mason
                                    Pilcher</hi></signed>,<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">S. F.
                                    Slatter</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Agents</hi></signed>.<lb/>[<hi rend="smallcaps">seal.</hi>]<lb/><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">C. W.
                                    Muncaster</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Secretary.</hi></signed></closer>
                        <frus:attachment>
                            <head>[Coupon.]</head>
                            <p>$12. Republic of Nicaragua, $12. Government bond No. 69 for $200
                                interest warrant for $12, payable at the Bank of Louisiana, New
                                Orleans, on the 1st day of November, 1808, fixed.</p>
                            <closer><signed>C. W. M., <hi rend="italic">Secretary.</hi></signed></closer>
                            <postscript>
                                <p>Coupons from 1857 to 1876, inclusive. The 1857 is cut off.</p>
                            </postscript>
                        </frus:attachment>
                    </frus:attachment>
                    <frus:attachment>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 3 in No.
                                582.—Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Castellon</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Hall</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Relations of Nicaragua</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Managua</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1886-10-18"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 18, 1886</date>.</dateline></opener>
                        <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: I have the honor to inform you that having
                            transcribed to the minister of the treasury your esteemed note of the
                            22d September, together with a copy of the bond accompanying it, I have
                            received the reply, of which the following is a copy:</p>
                        <p>“I have had the honor to receive the communication that you were pleased
                            to address me on the 8th inst., in which is transmitted the note of the
                            minister of the United States, dated the 22d of September, inquiring as
                            to the authenticity and validity of the supposed bond of this Republic
                            issued, as it is pretended, in conformity with a decree of the
                            Government of Nicaragua of the 28th of August, 1856. A textual copy of
                            the bond accompanies the above-mentioned note.</p>
                        <p>“The mentioned decree is not known to the Government, nor does it exist
                            on the records of our loans, nor is the obligation to which it refers a
                            legitimate debt of the Republic. By the dates that are cited I perceive
                            that it must be the work of the filibusters of Walker, who were here
                            about that time, and whose history of depredation and rapine is well
                            known. Of course the foreign usurpers never had any right to compromise
                            the credit of this Republic.”</p>
                        <p>In transcribing to you the foregoing note of the minister of the treasury
                            I have the honor to renew, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">F. Castellon.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </frus:attachment>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>