<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 674.Mr. Winchester to Mr. Bayard..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1887</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">674</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1887-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1887-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reciONa4gBw16QbEo" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="immigration"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85026205"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Citizenship</term>
                    <term ref="recVSPQM8CicmOme2" type="topic" category="human-rights"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85023418"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Children</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85051619"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Fraud</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-09-26T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-09-26T00:00:00-05:00" n="674"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d674">
                <head>No. 674.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Winchester</persName> to Mr.
                            <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Berne</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-09-26">
                            <hi rend="italic">September</hi> 26, 1887</date>. (Received October
                        8.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 154.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: The two preceding dispatches from this legation
                    submitted cases involving the right of naturalized citizens to passports, and I
                    am again placed under the necessity of seeking the advice of the Department
                    touching a question covering a large number of cases in Switzerland, and
                    presented in a recent application for a passport. A few days since Mr. Nathan
                    Seligman applied through the consul at St Galle for a passport. The following
                    facts appear in his sworn statement: He was born in Bavaria, October 30, 1844;
                    emigrated to the United States in 1865, arriving at New York 2d of July, 1865;
                    was naturalized January 24, 1880; resided in Switzerland since February,
                    1880.</p>
                <pb facs="1164" n="1070" xml:id="pg_1070"/>
                <p>Two things in this record are noticeable. First, Mr. Seligman did not become
                    naturalized until be bad been in the United States nearly fifteen years, three
                    times the period required by the statute; and, secondly, that he must have taken
                    the first steamer leaving port after he obtained his citizenship, for his
                    certificate bears date January 24, 1880, and he states that he has resided in
                    Switzerland since February, 1880, Mr. Seligman’s purpose in coming abroad was to
                    take charge of and manage a large embroidery house at St. Galle as a branch of a
                    house in New York city. The embroidery exportation from Switzerland to the
                    United States is very large, St. Galle having the most extensive and celebrated
                    manufactory of that class in Europe. It is well known that a majority of the
                    houses engaged in that business at St. Galle are the property of naturalized
                    American citizens, and are either branches with head establishments in the
                    United States or <hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>. This is not confined to the
                    embroidery business and to St. Galle, but may be found at other places in
                    Switzerland and in other enterprises. The resident partners here acquire such
                    property holdings as may be necessary to their interest, and in some instances
                    these are very considerable; remove their families from the United States,
                    purchase homes here, rear and educate their children here, and to all intents
                    and purposes are permanently domiciled here. So far they have been accorded all
                    the privileges and immunities that attach to the possession of a passport
                    attesting their American citizenship. They are as a rule very reputable men,
                    both personally and in business, beyond any impeachment. Some of these houses
                    have existed for many years, and have built up a very large and profitable
                    business. From time to time, some at long intervals, others at shorter, the
                    managers of the houses here visit the American head house, or branch, as it may
                    be, for business ends or mere pleasure, but it is in every sense a visit of
                    short duration, and always made with <hi rend="italic">animus revcrtendi</hi>.
                    Another feature common in these cases is the one indicated in Mr. Seligman’s—the
                    failure to invest themselves with American citizenship until their interests
                    demand a return to Europe, and then, and not until then, are they brought to a
                    realization of the benefits and blessings of this high privilege. Mr. Seligman’s
                    passport was issued to him, and it may look-in referring the matter now, as a
                    case of “locking the stable after the horse is gone,” but there are many other
                    horses left in the stable, and it is for their benefit the legation desires to
                    be instructed.</p>
                <p>The inability of the Department to act hypothetically or to lay down any general
                    rule which could with safety or justice be applied to a class of cases without
                    consideration of the special facts in each, is well recognized, and with no
                    such, view is this dispatch written. The sole object is to have the opinion of
                    the Department as to the correctness of the legation in granting Mr. Seligman a
                    passport, that it may serve in a measure to guide and assist in the
                    consideration of similar cases that will arise in the near future. In the
                    application of Mr. Seligman it was stated, in pursuance of the blank forms
                    furnished by the Department, that he “last left the United States” in 1886, but
                    this in effect was destroyed by the further statement that followed, in
                    conformity with the blank form, that he “had resided in Switzerland since 1880,”
                    and the letter of the consul at St, Galle, transmitting the application, said
                    that Mr. Seligman, with his family, had visited the United States for a few
                    months in 1886. Mr. Seligman also declared in his application that he was
                    temporarily, residing at St. Galle, and that he intends to return to the United
                    States in two years with a purpose of residing and performing the duties of
                    citizenship there.” When a man of good character and fully entitled <pb
                        facs="1165" n="1071" xml:id="pg_1071"/> to credence makes such a statement
                    under oath, what discretion itself the legation? When the two years expire, he
                    finds that some unforeseen and unavoidable contingencies prevent him carrying
                    out the “intent” to return, in good faith entertained and declared two years
                    previously, and he is again ready to renew the “intent” and the passport at the
                    same time, and the same process will be repeated <hi rend="italic">ad
                        infinitum/</hi> When the “intent” not to return is not shown by a residence
                    abroad for a period fixed by treaty, it is very difficult to determine.</p>
                <p>In a previous dispatch allusion is made to the entire absence of any serious
                    consideration being given to the sworn statements in a passport application that
                    characterize many persons who stand before the world and their fellow-citizens
                    as clear-conscienced as a saint, and it is this strange condition which
                    surrounds the question and its treatment with so much difficulty. It is
                    impossible for the legation to act intelligently or correctly in a simple view
                    of the sworn declarations made by an applicant for a passport, if he fails to
                    consider circumstances within his knowledge that impair if not contradict the
                    affiant’s statements. A passport not being an abstract or absolute right of the
                    citizen, but a privilege determined by circumstances that are infinite,
                    variable, and transient, it imposes a very ungracious obligation on the
                    Government agent abroad to see that it is not made through him an instrument of
                    imposition either upon his own Government or upon the Government where the party
                    is domiciled. Feeling that the instructions of the Department, saying, “too much
                    care can not be exercised in granting passports, especially to persons
                    representing themselves as naturalized citizens,” and “the Department expects
                    its agents abroad, to whose discretion the issuance of passports is confided,
                    will exact unequivocal declarations of a positive intent to return to the United
                    States, there to continue the domicile contemplated by the statutes, and that
                    business visits to the United States are not evidence of such domiciliary
                    intent,” were eminently proper and requisite for the checking of a most shameful
                    and growing abuse, I have striven to execute them in letter and spirit. Many
                    applications for passports have been refused to parties who regarded they had
                    established a prescriptive right to them, and doubtless complaint of their
                    unexpected hardships may reach the Department. In many cases the blank forms
                    used by them contained all the <hi rend="italic">pro forma</hi> declarations,
                    but I was constrained to think, from other facts disclosed or made known to me,
                    that the affiant himself could not believe his own declarations, and that he
                    merely expected to have others believe them. Vigilance has been exercised to
                    guard against such impositions, and firmness in resisting such solicitations.
                    American citizenship should not be trifled with in this manner; it should not be
                    invaded by fraud or false representations, for it carries with its possession
                    all the privileges and protection a great Government can give to its
                    citizens.</p>
                <p>Respect for a passport is indispensable for the safety of our citizens traveling
                    abroad, and nothing can so fatally impair that respect as the experience and
                    observation of foreign governments that it is abusively obtained or lightly
                    given to all who ask. The boon of citizenship is the most precious which our
                    country can confer on the stranger from a foreign land. But it loses its
                    honorable significance when improperly acquired, or perverted to wrong purposes.
                    The only efficient and wholesome check on the abuses to which our naturalization
                    laws are being constantly subjected is a steady and unflinching scrutiny of all
                    the applications for passports by naturalized citizens as to the length of their
                    absence from the United States, and other circumstances; <pb facs="1166"
                        n="1072" xml:id="pg_1072"/> going-to prove an <hi rend="italic">animus
                        manendi</hi>. This may partially succeed in suppressing the flagrant and
                    scandalous abuse in common practice, and without such severity of treatment it
                    will continue to increase. The many active and unscrupulous men who have
                    illustrated how easily it can be done is a constant encouragement for others to
                    follow their example. The Department, in its instructions bearing on this
                    question, has gone only so far as to exact from the applicant for a passport,
                    when a naturalized citizen, “an unequivocal declaration of a positive intent to
                    return to the United States,” without indicating within what period this intent
                    should be consummated. A mere declaration of “intent to return” might be said to
                    come under the class of obligations denounced by the law for uncertainty, and it
                    operates rather adversely to the end sought to be accomplished, in accepting a
                    declaration that few hesitate to make, on the theory that its fulfillment is
                    left entirely at their pleasure. The consuls in Switzerland have all with one
                    accord, without any instructions from the legation, in all passport applications
                    from naturalized citizens, placed the intent to return at two years. They have
                    done so, it is supposed, from the fact of two years being the period of a
                    passport’s legal existence, whilst it has not been the purpose of the legation
                    to refuse a renewal of passport in cases where this intent is not carried out at
                    the expiration of the two years, it has been deemed best to permit the practice
                    to continue and leave it to the applicant to show, when applying for a renewal
                    of passport, why he has not returned and for what reason his stay abroad is
                    prolonged. Is it not possible to fix some period within which such parties shall
                    return, unless the failure to do so can be satisfactorily explained? Is the
                    abandonment of citizenship to be established by nothing less than an open act of
                    renunciation? Is it not practicable, even under our imperfect legislation, to
                    hold a residence abroad in the country of one’s nativity or contiguous country
                    being the same in principle under such circumstances that a purpose of change of
                    allegiance can be fairly assumed, works practical expatriation! It is high time
                    that our legislatures were doing something to rescue our naturalization laws
                    from the disgraceful perversion to which they are subjected, and to cause those
                    who seek the high privileges they confer to realize that imperative duties are
                    likewise assumed, and that they shall in practice, as well as in theory, take
                    upon themselves I the full responsibilities of their new and exalted
                    citizenship.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Boyd Winchester.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
