<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-10-24T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-10-24T00:00:00-05:00" n="679" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d679">
                        <head>No. 679.<lb/><hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Frey</persName> to Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName></hi>.</head>
                        <opener><seg rendition="#center">[Translation.]</seg></opener>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of Switzerland</hi>,<lb/><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-10-24"><hi rend="italic">October</hi> 24,
                                1887</date>. (Received October 26.)</dateline></opener>
                        <p>Mr. <hi rend="smallcaps">Secretary of State</hi>: Referring to the note
                            which the Swiss chargé d’affaires <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi> at
                            this capital had the honor to address to you on the 4th of July last,
                            and by which he acknowledged the receipt <pb facs="1172" n="1078" xml:id="pg_1078"/> of your note of July 1 in relation to the
                            protection of Swiss citizens by United States consuls in foreign
                            countries, I have the honor to inform you that I have received
                            instructions from my Government to convey to you its warmest thanks for
                            your aforesaid note of July 1 and for the friendly sentiments therein
                            expressed. Although the federal council is unable fully to share the
                            view stated in your note with regard to the nature and scope of the
                            relation between the protecting state and persons commended to its
                            protection, it has nevertheless been glad to be informed, in a definite
                            manner, by your note what your interpretation of the relation in
                            question is.</p>
                        <p>While the federal council now considers this matter as settled, it
                            desires to return its thanks for your kindness in expressing your
                            willingness to authorize the consular representatives of the United
                            States to use their good offices in future in behalf of Swiss citizens,
                            of which kindness the federal council proposes to avail itself, if there
                            shall be any necessity therefor.</p>
                        <p>I gladly avail, etc.,</p>
                        <closer><signed><hi rend="smallcaps">E. Frey.</hi></signed></closer>
                    </div>
                </body></text></TEI>