<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 92.Mr. Hall to Mr. Bayard..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1887</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">92</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1887-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1887-06-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="reckLQalsfRO3AT43" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2003003664"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Constitution</term>
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006887"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Publication</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00005791"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Foreign relations</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recSbJDXr0mWQQ76Q" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85005274"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Welfare</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-06-27T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-06-27T00:00:00-05:00" n="92"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d92">
                <head>No. 92.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hall</persName> to Mr. <persName
                            type="to">Bayard</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of the United States,<lb/>Central
                                America</hi>
                        </placeName>,<lb/>
                        <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-06-27">
                            <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 27, 1887</date>. (Received July
                        14.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 672.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: It was publicly announced early this morning that
                    President Barillas had yesterday signed a decree declaring himself dictator of
                    Guatemala. Later, I received a note from the minister for foreign affairs
                    confirming the statement and accompanying copies of the decree and of the
                    President’s address to the country.</p>
                <p>Upon the receipt of the minister’s note I telegraphed you to the effect that
                    dictatorial powers had been assumed by the President of Guatemala, and that the
                    constitution had been suspended by a, decree issued on June 26 by the President
                    and Council of Ministers.</p>
                <p>I have the honor to inclose copies and translations of, the documents above
                    mentioned. The printed translation of the decree from the office of the La
                    Estrella is very imperfect, but as there is hardly time to prepare another to
                    send by this mail, I venture to inclose it; it is at least intelligible and in a
                    convenient form.</p>
                <p>I have had no opportunity to learn how this measure has been received by the
                    Guatemalan public; in this capital there is to-day much excitement, but there
                    has been no turbulence nor violence.</p>
                <p>The publication of all newspapers has been suspended.</p>
                <p>I am, etc.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry C. Hall.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 1 in No. 672.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Montúfar</persName> to Mr.
                                <persName type="to">Hall</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Relations</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-06-27">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 27, 1887</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: The President of the Republic
                        dictated yesterday a decree by which he assumes the supreme power of the
                        nation, the constitutional regimen, in consequence, being suspended.</p>
                    <p>The motives he had for issuing such an important measure are to be found in
                        the decree itself, and in a proclamation which he addresses to his
                        fellow-citizens.</p>
                    <p>I transmit copies of both, and I have the pleasure to manifest to your
                        excellency that during the short period in which the extraordinary powers
                        that he assumes remain in force he will endeavor to cultivate, as
                        heretofore, the happily existing relations with all the civilized peoples of
                        the world without deviating a line from the general principles of
                        international rights nor from the solemn obligations imposed by
                        treaties.</p>
                    <p>This opportunity affords me, etc.,</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lorenzo Montúfar.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
                <pb facs="0222" n="128" xml:id="pg_128"/>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure 2 in No. 672.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Manuel Lisandro Barillas, General of Division and
                            President of the Republic of Guatemala, to his fellow-citizens:</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>The executive power has to-day dictated a decree demanded by public utility
                        and necessity.</p>
                    <p>On the 11th of December, 1879, the political constitution founded upon public
                        rights, and in conformity with the reforms implanted by modern ideas, was
                        promulgated. That constitution destined, the greater part of it, to survive
                        many years, and serving as the basis of the progress of the country, was
                        amended on the 20th of October, 1885.</p>
                    <p>The amendments were made at a time of agitation and transition, and without
                        the calmness required for a work of so great magnitude and importance. The
                        legislators, guided by a desire to restrict the executive power, prescribed
                        rules which place him under the necessity of absolute submission. The
                        difficulties were augmented by the legislatures of the present and last
                        year, which passed a considerable number of the most restrictive and
                        impracticable laws. Some of these laws take from the executive powers
                        indespensable for government, of which not even the amendments of 1885 had
                        deprived him.</p>
                    <p>I do not aspire to absolute power, but it is essential that I should have the
                        authority required for fulfilling the high mission that the people have
                        confided to me. There can be no government without a revenue, and there can
                        be no revenue if the executive power is without the means of maintaining and
                        developing it.</p>
                    <p>The public credit, the economic element, which every government must sustain,
                        even at the cost of great sacrifices, has suffered greatly. I came into
                        power through the glorious revolution of 1871, whose programme I am obliged
                        to defend, and I can not do it under the pressure of measures which detain
                        me at every stop and lead me towards a most odious reaction.</p>
                    <p>I do not wish a dictatorship; I aspire that the people which has honored me
                        with its confidence shall be free, and for the same reason I have decreed
                        the convocation of a constituent assembly.</p>
                    <p>Neither do I wish to endanger the liberal triumphs obtained by the
                        legislators of 1879, which should be our guide. I propose only that the
                        Constituent Congress which I invoke to-day shall revise the amendments of
                        1885. That high body will meet on the 1st of October of the present year, so
                        that the power which I assume, in virtue of Article 1 of the Decree issued
                        to-day, is transitory.</p>
                    <p>Guatemalans: The great work of the Juno revolution is yours. Let us defend it
                        and not permit its destruction by the intrigues and machinations of the
                        reactionists. I am a son of the people, and I do not forget their troubles
                        and their sacrifices and I shall not permit them to be repeated.</p>
                    <p>Fellow-citizens, I count upon you, Rely upon me and upon the persons whom I
                        have designated to aid me in the Government, and be assured that my only
                        ambition is your happiness and the welfare of our beloved country.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">M. L. Barillas.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <lb/>
                        <dateline rendition="#left">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Guatemala</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-06-26">
                                <hi rend="italic">June</hi> 26, 1887</date>.</dateline>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
