<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>No. 95.Mr. Hall to
                            Mr. Bayard..</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1887</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">95</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1887-07-12T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1887-07-12T23:59:59-05:00"/>
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recxWdyCerq3Icxus" type="topic" category="human-rights" subcategory="general" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85038376" lcsh-match="exact">Discrimination</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy" subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements" lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411" lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1887-07-12T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1887-07-12T00:00:00-05:00" n="95" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d95">
                <head>No. 95.<lb/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Mr. <persName type="from">Hall</persName> to
                            Mr. <persName type="to">Bayard</persName>
                    </hi>.</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Legation of
                                    the United States in Central America</hi>,<lb/>
                            <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-07-12">
                            <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 12, 1887</date>.
                            (Received July 28.)</dateline>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 684.]</seg>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir</hi>: With further reference to your instruction No.
                        468, of the 13th ultimo, and to my dispatches No. 652 and 679, the latter
                        dated the 5th instant, I have the honor to inclose a translation of a note,
                        received today, from the minister for foreign affairs of Guatemala,
                        transmitting a decree signed yesterday, but not yet published, placing
                        American vessels, as nearly as possible, upon the same footing with the
                        vessels of the Spanish line of the Marquis de Campo.</p>
                <p>In the ratification of the contract by the Assembly it was made optional with
                        the Executive to reduce the rebate to 3 per cent.; this has been done, and
                        the same rebate will now be conceded to all regular lines touching at
                        Guatemalan ports of the Pacific, except the through steamers between Panama
                        and San Francisco 5 to these a rebate of 29/10 per cent. is conceded. The
                        coasting steamers of the Pacific Mail Company running no farther than some
                        of the ports of Mexico will enjoy the full rebate.</p>
                <p>There still remains the above-mentioned discrimination against the through
                        steamers of the Pacific Mail Company, but it is relatively a trilling matter
                        compared with the former.</p>
                <p>The present Guatemalan cabinet by this act of justice has shown a disposition
                        to remedy the unfriendly discrimination established by the Assembly at the
                        time of the ratification of the contract.</p>
                <p>I have, etc.,</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry C. Hall.</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Inclosure in No.
                            684.—Translation.]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Señor <persName type="from">Montufar</persName> to
                                Mr. <persName type="to">Hall</persName>
                        </hi>.</head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Department of Foreign Affairs</hi>,<lb/>
                                <hi rend="italic">Guatemala</hi>
                            </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1887-07-11">
                                <hi rend="italic">July</hi> 11,
                                1887</date>.</dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Mr. Minister</hi>: I have the honor to transcribe to
                            you the decree issued under this date by the President, the contents of
                            which are the following: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p rend="center">“Manuel Lisandro Barillas, President of the
                                    Republic of Guatemala:</p>
                            <p>Considering that it is indispensable that a just equilibrium be
                                    established between the several steamship companies which now or
                                    may hereafter perform regular service with our ports, to the end
                                    that the competition in freight and passages, from which great
                                    benefits have been derived, and greater still may hereafter be
                                    obtained for the agricultural, commercial, and other interests
                                    of the country may be maintained; therefore I decree.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 1.</p>
                            <p>All foreign merchandise imported by the vessels belonging to any
                                    company, which vessels shall make regular direct voyages,
                                    touching at our ports of the Pacific, shall be entitled to a
                                    rebate of 3 per cent. from the present tariff of duties.</p>
                            <pb facs="0226" n="132" xml:id="pg_132"/>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 2.</p>
                            <p>A rebate of 29/10 per cent. from the duties on articles imported
                                    in vessels of the lines already established, or that may
                                    hereafter be established, regularly between Panama and San
                                    Francisco, Cal.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 3.</p>
                            <p>In order that a company may enjoy the referred-to concessions,
                                    there must be solicited of the minister of public works (<hi rend="italic">fomento</hi>), accompanying an itinerary,
                                    tariff of freights and passages, with details of conditions, and
                                    guarantying the regularity of the voyages in such manner as may
                                    be deemed opportune.</p>
                            <p rend="center">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Article</hi> 4.</p>
                            <p>The concessions granted by this decree, which in no way modify
                                    the concessions previously granted to some steamship companies,
                                    shall commence to have effect on the 1st day of September next,
                                    1887.</p>
                            <p>Given in the National Palace of Guatemala the 11th day of July,
                                    1887.</p>
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">M. L. Barillas.</hi>
                            </p>
                            <p>The Secretary of State in the Department of Fomento:</p>
                            <p rend="right">
                                <hi rend="smallcaps">Salvador
                                Barutia.”</hi>
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>And in having the honor to make it known to you, it is a pleasure to
                            offer you the assurances of my consideration and esteem.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Lorenzo
                            Montufar.</hi>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
