<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>127. Despatch From the Embassy in Italy to the to the Department of
                    State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d127</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">127</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1957-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1957-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recieOBiY284bnHpv" type="topic" category="politico-military-issues"
                        subcategory="alliances">Western alliance</term>
                    <term ref="national-security-council" type="topic"
                        category="politico-military-issues" subcategory="national-security-council"
                        >National Security Council</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="rec7v2u7pee7zv59o" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="rec7g4kEoiXWBjoX3" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="u-s-soviet-russian-relations"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh88007931"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Soviet Union</term>
                    <term ref="united-nations" type="topic" category="international-organizations"
                        subcategory="united-nations">United Nations</term>
                    <term ref="rec7gDTXJIboMqxjj" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="elections"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85041557"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Elections</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1957-03-28T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1957-03-28T00:00:00-05:00" n="127"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d127">
                <head>127. Despatch From the <gloss type="from">Embassy in Italy</gloss> to the
                        <gloss type="to">Department of State</gloss>
                    <note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d127fn1">Source: Department of State, Central
                        Files, 033.1100–NI/3–2857. Confidential.</note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#left">No. 1280</seg>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Rome</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1957-03-28">March 28, 1957</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <list type="references">
                    <head>REF</head>
                    <item>Embassy’s despatch 1256 dated March 26, 1957<note n="2" xml:id="d127fn2"
                            >In despatch 1256, the Embassy provided a full account of the Vice
                            President’s schedule and activities during his visit to Rome. (<hi
                                rend="italic">Ibid.,</hi> 033.1100–NI/3–2657)</note>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <list type="subject">
                    <head>SUBJECT</head>
                    <item>Conversations during Visit of Vice President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1"
                            >Nixon</persName>
                    </item>
                </list>
                <p>During the visit of Vice President <persName corresp="#p_NRM1">Nixon</persName>
                    to Rome it was not planned that he broach any substantive matters with the
                    officials of the Italian Government with whom he talked. Inevitably, however,
                    the Italian officials themselves brought up subjects on which they believed the
                    Vice President either should be informed or could be helpful. Listed below are
                    points of interest in this connection.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">1. Consultation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gronchi</persName>, Prime Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_SA1">Segni</persName> and Foreign Minister <persName
                        corresp="#p_MG1">Martino</persName> all brought up the long-standing Italian
                    desire to be consulted promptly on matters affecting the Western alliance or any
                    substantial part of it. They emphasized the necessity that Washington be
                    convinced of the justice of the Italian claim, pointing out that United States
                    prestige in Italy suffers when we neglect them in favor of prior or exclusive
                    consultation with the British and French. The Vice President replied that he
                    would take this up with President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1"
                        >Eisenhower</persName> and with the National Security Council upon his
                    return to Washington.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">2. African Economic Development</hi>
                </p>
                <p>President <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gronchi</persName> spoke at some length on
                    the need for European cooperation with the newly independent African states. He
                    pointed out Italy’s special position in this regard in the sense of cultural and
                    geographic propinquity; furthermore, Italy’s colonial period now being history,
                    Italians enjoy the confidence of the African peoples.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gronchi</persName> brought up the desirability of
                    creating an international organization for financing economic development of the
                    African states, in order to avoid the fear of domination which could be aroused
                    by a single nation (i.e., U.S.) program. He thought that this organization could
                    include the European nations, and that the USSR should be <pb facs="0445"
                        n="407" xml:id="pg_407"/> invited to join. If the Soviet Union refused to
                    participate, such refusal would be to its discredit; if it joined, the other
                    nations would have a better opportunity to keep track of Russian activities in
                    Africa. <persName corresp="#p_GG2">Gronchi</persName> did not mention the United
                    Nations in connection with his idea.</p>
                <p rend="flushleft">
                    <hi rend="italic">3. Italian Political Situation</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Prime Minister <persName corresp="#p_SA1">Segni</persName> produced a few
                    thoughts on the internal political situation including his doubt that socialist
                    unification could be achieved before the next political elections. When these
                    elections take place, it is <persName corresp="#p_SA1">Segni</persName>’s belief
                    that the <gloss target="#t_PCI1">PCI</gloss> will suffer a loss of 10%, and that
                    if the socialist parties run together they, too, will lose ground. If the <gloss
                        target="#t_PSI1">PSI</gloss> and the <gloss target="#t_PSDI1">PSDI</gloss>
                    run separately, however, each should make a slight gain.</p>
                <p>Senate President Merzagora, in discussing Italy’s internal situation, said that
                    he expects the social and economic development programs of the last 10 years to
                    bear significant fruit during the course of the next 5 years. Once past the next
                    political elections, the <gloss target="#t_PCI1">PCI</gloss> will diminish
                    rapidly as an effective force in Italian politics as people begin to appreciate
                    the benefits of 10 years of Center government achievements. (It is, perhaps, of
                    interest that none of the Italian leaders mentioned the <persName
                        corresp="#p_VE1">Vanoni</persName> Plan.)</p>
                <p rend="right">For the Ambassador:</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BNW1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Niles W. Bond</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Counselor of Embassy</hi>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
