<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>61. Letter From the Ambassador to Italy ( to Italy (Luce) to the President’s
                    Special Assistant for National Security Affairs () to the President’s Special
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (Cutler))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1955-57v27</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d61</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">61</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1955-01-14T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1955-01-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="rec3PTghsOWbo9hD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="labor"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh90004091"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Labor</term>
                    <term ref="recmaQ3gdQeqBxn2G" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85040804"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Economic development</term>
                    <term ref="receYZXmZSuptfeyg" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="foreign-aid">PL 480</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-01-14T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-01-14T00:00:00-05:00" n="61"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d61">
                <head>61. Letter From the <gloss type="from">Ambassador</gloss> to Italy (<persName
                        corresp="#p_LCB1" type="to">Luce</persName>) to the President’s Special
                    Assistant for National Security Affairs (<persName corresp="#p_CRL1"
                        >Cutler</persName>)<note n="2" type="source" xml:id="d61fn2">
                        <p>Source: Eisenhower Library, Clarence Francis Records. Top Secret.
                            Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LCB1">Luce</persName> was in Washington
                            for consultations.</p>
                        <p>At a meeting of the Operations Coordinating Board on January 12,
                                <persName corresp="#p_CRL1">Cutler</persName> had asked for guidance
                            with regard to an impending dinner engagement with <persName
                                corresp="#p_LCB1">Luce</persName>. Under Secretary <persName
                                corresp="#p_HHJ1">Hoover</persName>, Department of State
                            Representative and Chairman of the <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss>,
                            replied that he believed <persName corresp="#p_LCB1">Luce</persName>
                            wished to discuss a plan for assistance to Italy, but that he had
                            informed <persName corresp="#p_LCB1">Luce</persName> that such a
                            suggestion would require study and more money than he believed would be
                            available. [<hi rend="italic">3½ lines of text not declassified</hi>]
                            (Department of State, <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> Files: Lot 61
                            D 385, <gloss target="#t_OCB1">OCB</gloss> Preliminary Notes)</p>
                    </note>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian"
                                when="1955-01-14">January 14, 1955</date>.</hi>
                    </dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Dear General</hi>: You are aware of my firmly held opinion
                    that we are at a decisive juncture in Italian affairs, one which holds out
                    promise of much progress against the Communists if we and the Italian Government
                    can exploit the successes achieved during the last year. The turmoil within the
                    Communist Party over <persName corresp="#p_TP2">Togliatti</persName>’s
                    leadership is adequate proof that the Italian Government’s anti-communist
                    actions and the progress of free labor are hurting the party badly.</p>
                <p>I believe with the President that this is a situation where we should, as he puts
                    it, “support success.”</p>
                <p>What I believe to be required is the following: <list>
                        <label>1.</label>
                        <item>Full and rapid implementation by the Italian Government of its
                            sweeping December 4 anti-communist program;<note n="3" xml:id="d61fn3"
                                >For excerpts from the Council of Ministers’ communiqué announcing
                                the program, see <ref target="#d67">Document 67</ref>. The complete
                                text of the communiqué was sent to the Department of State in
                                telegram 2141 from Rome, December 6, 1954. (Department of State,
                                Central Files, 765.00/12–654)</note>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="0252" n="214" xml:id="pg_214"/>
                        <label>2.</label>
                        <item>Willingness and preparation on our part to give serious consideration
                            to assisting the Italians with the economic development program they are
                            presently working out, provided that during the next two or three months
                            they make a good start in implementing the December 4 program. This U.S.
                            assistance is an essential concomitant to Italy’s ability to carry out
                            even more vigorous anti-communist measures. To this end, we should
                            endeavor to scrape together from various sources a “package” of
                            assistance of various kinds which we might agree to extend (subject to
                            negotiations) either on the occasion of the <persName corresp="#p_SM1"
                                >Scelba</persName> visit<note n="4" xml:id="d61fn4">Prime Minister
                                    <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> was scheduled to
                                visit the United States in March.</note> or whenever we considered
                            it appropriate thereafter. In my view such a package would consist
                            principally of Eximbank loans, <gloss target="#t_PL1">PL</gloss>
                                480,<note n="5" xml:id="d61fn5">Agricultural Trade Development and
                                Assistance Act of 1954 (Public Law 480), approved July 10, 1954; for
                                text, see 68 Stat. 454.</note>
                            <gloss target="#t_OSP1">OSP</gloss> and possibly other forms of aid. (I
                            am, incidentally, seriously concerned that the <gloss target="#t_FOA1"
                                >FOA</gloss> contingency fund be cut drastically by the
                            Administration or in Congress.) This aid package would not be extended
                            however until we were fully satisfied both with the validity of the
                            economic program the Italians had worked out, and with the adequacy of
                            the Italians’ own efforts in this field.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>As you are aware the time element is important if we are to exploit success. If
                    we can move ahead on the above basis, however, I am convinced that there is real
                    hope of achieving in the next few years a truly significant, perhaps even a
                    definitive victory against the Communist Party in Italy.</p>
                <p>Sincerely yours,<note n="6" xml:id="d61fn6">
                        <persName corresp="#p_CRL1">Cutler</persName> replied to <persName
                            corresp="#p_LCB1">Luce</persName>’s letter on January 18, assuring her
                        that the points she had raised would be brought before the <gloss
                            target="#t_NSC1">NSC</gloss> Planning Board. (Eisenhower Library,
                        Clarence Francis Records)</note>
                </p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_LCB1">
                            <hi rend="strong">Clare Boothe Luce</hi>
                        </persName>
                        <note n="7" xml:id="d61fn7">Printed from a copy that bears this typed
                            signature.</note>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
