<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1955-03-28T11:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1955-03-28T11:00:00-05:00" n="71" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d71">
                        <head>71. Draft Memorandum of a Conversation, Department of State,
                            Washington March 28, 1955, 11 a.m.<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d71fn1">Source: Department of State, Central Files,
                                765.13/3–2855. Secret. Prepared by Lieutenant Colonel Walters, a
                                member of the U.S. Delegation to the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Standing Group in Washington. A note, dated March
                                30 and attached to the source text, indicates that this draft was
                                cleared by <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName> and seen
                                by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_DJF1">Dulles</persName>.</note></head>
                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right"><hi rend="italic"><placeName>Washington</placeName>
                                    <date calendar="gregorian" type="conversation-or-meeting-date" when="1955-03-28T11:00:00-05:00">March 28, 1955, 11
                                        a.m.</date></hi></dateline></opener>
                        <list type="subject">
                            <head>SUBJECT</head>
                            <item>Visit of Premier of Italy <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Mario
                                    Scelba</persName> with Secretary of State</item>
                        </list>
                        <list type="participants">
                            <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                            <item>The Prime Minister of Italy</item>
                            <item>The Secretary of State</item>
                            <item>The Foreign Minister of Italy</item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LCB1">Luce</persName></item>
                            <item>Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_BM1">Brosio</persName></item>
                            <item>Ambassador Magistrati</item>
                            <item>Assistant Secretary of State <persName corresp="#p_MLT1">Merchant</persName></item>
                            <item>Minister Canali (Interpreter for Italian side)</item>
                            <item>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_JGL1">Jones</persName> (<gloss target="#t_WE1">WE</gloss>)</item>
                            <item>Lt. Col. Walters (Interpreter for U.S. side)</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The Secretary opened the meeting by saying how happy he was to welcome
                            Premier <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> and how glad he was
                            to have an opportunity of talking over a number of different problems.
                            Since their last meeting a number of events had taken place, in
                            particular, a happy solution of the Trieste problem had been reached.
                            The Italian ratification of the Paris Accords had taken place at a
                            psychological time and had contributed materially to the recent
                            ratification of these accords by the French Assembly. He felt that the
                            role of Premier <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName>’s
                            Government was significant and it enabled us to envision a future in
                            which the Italian nation is destined to play a great part. He felt that
                            the role of Italy would be increasingly important and that his
                            Government welcomed this development.</p>
                        <pb facs="0282" n="244" xml:id="pg_244"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> thanked the Secretary
                            and said how happy he was to meet him again. Many events had taken place
                            since their last meeting at Villa Carminati in Milan and a successful
                            conclusion had been given to a number of matters that had been
                            considered at that time.<note n="2" xml:id="d71fn2">For a record of the
                                    <persName>Dulles</persName>–<persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> meeting of May 3, 1954, see <ref target="frus1952-54v08#pg_419"><hi rend="italic">Foreign
                                        Relations,</hi> 1952–1954, vol. VIII, p. 419</ref>.</note>
                            The Trieste question had finally been solved after being an irritant
                            ever since the end of World War II. Italy had played her part in solving
                            the various international problems which had arisen. She had given her
                            full cooperation in the matter of European collaboration. He was happy
                            to have this meeting with the Secretary and to be able after these
                            events had occurred to examine the new situation now existing. He again
                            wished to thank the Secretary for all he had done to help in solving the
                            Trieste problem and he wished also to pay a warm tribute to the friendly
                            and practical attitude of Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_LCB1">Luce</persName>.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary then said that he would be happy to follow any line of
                            conversation which the Prime Minister might <gloss target="#t_CARE1">care</gloss> to suggest. He hoped that they could at some point
                            talk about the future in Europe in terms of moving forward from the
                            ratification of the Paris Accords towards a greater measure of unity in
                            Europe.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> mentioned that both the
                            French and Italian Parliaments in ratifying the Paris Accords expressed
                            the hope that some talks might be held with the East on the whole
                            question of East-West relations. While one might not necessarily expect
                            concrete or fruitful results from such discussions, it might be wise not
                            to give the Russians the psychological advantage of presenting this
                            problem as one of refusal to talk, on the part of the West, on questions
                            of East-West problems and limitation of armaments.</p>
                        <p>In the matter of limitation of armaments the Secretary said he knew how
                            close this matter was to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName>’s heart. He believed that the pattern established
                            under the Brussels Treaty<note n="3" xml:id="d71fn3">The Treaty of
                                Economic, Social, and Cultural Collaboration and Collective
                                Self-Defense among the United Kingdom, France, Belgium, and
                                Luxembourg was signed on March 17, 1948.</note> constituted a first
                            major practical effort to limit and control armaments, and this pattern
                            might lend itself to constructive action. He would like to have the
                            Prime Minister’s opinion on this matter. The Prime Minister agreed with
                            the Secretary and said that this was important psychologically in Italy
                            where the Communists had such strong representation.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Martino</persName> said that
                            just before he left for the United States the Italian Ambassador in
                            Bonn, Mr. <persName>Grazzi</persName>, came to see him and told him that
                            Chancellor <persName corresp="#p_AK1">Adenauer</persName> would like the
                            Secretary informed that he is now in a somewhat difficult position in
                            his own country because of a movement in public opinion, that he would
                            feel compelled to talk of the necessity of conversations with the East
                            to <pb facs="0283" n="245" xml:id="pg_245"/> explore means of unifying
                            Germany. The Chancellor is convinced that unification will not be easy.
                            The Chancellor felt that however great the attractiveness of this search
                            for unity, he would not like to leave the solidarity of the Western camp
                            but that the German Government wanted talks to take place with the East
                            perhaps in the form of a Four-Power conference in order to solve the
                            problem of unification and reach general agreement. The Chancellor felt
                            that the limitation and control of armaments could take place only in
                            such a framework and only in that way might it be possible to unify
                            Germany. He wanted the Secretary to know his position that he would now
                            find it necessary to speak publicly regarding the desire of the German
                            Government in this direction.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary then said that he was appearing on the following day before
                            the Senate Foreign Relations Committee<note n="4" xml:id="d71fn4"><persName>Dulles</persName>’ statement to the Senate Committee
                                on Foreign Relations, made on March 29 on behalf of the Paris
                                Accords, is printed in Department of State <hi rend="italic">Bulletin</hi>, April 11, 1955, p. 605. The Senate ratified the
                                agreements on April 1; President <persName corresp="#p_EDD1">Eisenhower</persName> signed them on April 7.</note> as the
                            U.S. had not yet ratified the Paris Agreements. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> jokingly remarked, “You are the
                            ones at fault there.” The Secretary then said that he would like to read
                            to the Prime Minister what he planned to say and would be interested to
                            hear whether the Prime Minister thought this was appropriate and fitted
                            in with their ideas on this subject. The Secretary then handed his
                            proposed statement to Minister Canali who read it aloud in Italian to
                            the Prime Minister. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName>
                            then said he felt it was an excellent statement and Foreign Minister
                                <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Martino</persName> added that it
                            accurately reflected the Italian point of view also. Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> added that he felt it was
                            extremely timely and he was appreciative of this. The Secretary said he
                            thought the Prime Minister had expressed some thoughts along this line
                            in Ottawa and Montreal. The Prime Minister said that he had been in
                            agreement with the Canadian Government but that the press had inflated
                            what he had actually said and this poor reporting had given rise to some
                            misunderstanding. The Premier said he felt something should be done to
                            satisfy the European Parliament who had asked on the occasion of the
                            ratification of the Paris Agreements, that following these, something be
                            done to lessen international tension.</p>
                        <p>Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Martino</persName> said it
                            was a matter of satisfying public opinion. The Canadian Government
                            apparently felt the same way and Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PLB1">Pearson</persName> had mentioned that at the new [<hi rend="italic">next</hi>] <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> meeting<note n="5" xml:id="d71fn5">The North Atlantic Council met in Paris, May
                                9–11.</note> it might be well to suggest that a rather broad agenda
                            be set up so that public opinion could be informed that the <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Council was discussing <pb facs="0284" n="246" xml:id="pg_246"/> this matter collectively and
                            this would avoid private initiatives by individual nations. The Prime
                            Minister signified his agreement with what the Foreign Minister had
                            said.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said he felt the next <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            meeting could be important and would be important. The instruments of
                            ratification would have been deposited. The Germans would be there for
                            the first time and we could look ahead and chart new prospectives with
                            more hope.</p>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> said that the Canadian
                            Government regretted the limited agenda for the next <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Council meeting. They felt that in
                            one day it would be impossible to engage in any serious discussions of
                            the numerous problems involved, and the Italians themselves shared this
                            point of view. The Secretary said we felt it should last longer than one
                            day. The Prime Minister then said that it might be profitable if the
                                <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Council were to study methods
                            and ascertain the modalities for preparing talks with the USSR. The
                            Secretary asked on what particular subjects, and the Prime Minister
                            replied, on the question of East-West relations and disarmament.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary said that certain aspects of East-West relations were of
                            interest to all <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> nations. The
                            unification of Germany was a matter of concern to all but there was a
                            field of special responsibility of the United Kingdom, France and the
                            United States as they retained under the Accords the rights of occupying
                            powers insofar as the unification of Germany is concerned. He felt that
                            probably about that time or shortly before the meeting, a conference of
                            three or four powers could be held to draw up a common point of view as
                            they had certain legal responsibilities that were not general. He felt
                            that the entire Council would have an opportunity to discuss matters of
                            interest to the whole <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Alliance. In
                            the matter of disarmament and limitation of armaments the Secretary felt
                            that as indicated in his proposed statement to the Senate Foreign
                            Relations Committee, we felt that the greatest hope at present for
                            progress lies in taking the Brussels pattern and ascertaining if it
                            could be extended to the East. There were two aspects to this question
                            which we should bear in mind: (1) the Federal Republic would not be
                            willing to discuss this matter merely in terms of German rearmament, as
                            this would reopen an issue that had already been settled, but rather to
                            talk about it in terms of the whole <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> position, perhaps again using the Brussels pattern.
                            They would not want the discussions to lead to the isolation or
                            neutralization of Germany. As a second point the Secretary felt that we
                            would have a certain amount of clearance and understanding with the U.N.
                            Commission which was working in London on this subject now. He could not
                            foresee the outcome of their work but he felt that we should be careful
                            not to cross wires on this problem.</p>
                        <pb facs="0285" n="247" xml:id="pg_247"/>
                        <p>Mr. <persName corresp="#p_SM1">Scelba</persName> felt he had several
                            questions in this connection in order to clarify the matter in his own
                            mind. Firstly, a meeting with the Germans, French and British would be
                            considered entirely natural, particularly now that they were in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> and in view of the fact that the
                            foregoing powers had certain special rights as occupying powers. Italy
                            was not involved in these matters. The establishment of Germany’s
                            equality and participation in <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>
                            presents additional problems in East-West relations concerning
                            unification of Germany, disarmament and Austria. In these, Italy was
                            interested and could participate. He wondered how these questions would
                            be discussed, whether with a fixed agenda or else without formal agenda.
                            He felt that the exclusion of Italy from talks on these subjects would
                            not be considered favorably by the Italians. He would also like to know
                            if such conversations as might be held with the East would be on a
                            particular question, or would cover a broad framework of East-West
                            problems. His second main question was as to where would these matters
                            be discussed and where would decisions be arrived at. In <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>, or elsewhere? This was important for
                            them as Italy was a member of <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss>.
                            They also felt that in relations with the East a common agreement was
                            important for the West and that separate initiatives of individual
                            states should be avoided. Individual actions were always dangerous as
                            the Russians consistently used this in an attempt to drive a wedge
                            between the Western countries. The Prime Minister said that he felt that
                            in thrashing out the <gloss target="#t_SHAPE1">shape</gloss> and form of
                            any efforts in this field, <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> would
                            be an appropriate forum particularly now that the Germans would be in
                            it. The Secretary said jokingly that the Prime Minister had certainly
                            succeeded in asking a difficult question early in the meeting. The Prime
                            Minister said that it was important to arrive at a decision as to how to
                            proceed in this matter as the method used would have important
                            psychological repercussions. The Secretary said that he fully recognized
                            the importance of the question that the Prime Minister had brought up.
                            He felt that the time was passing when a few countries could presume to
                            speak for many. That had perhaps been necesary during the war but it was
                            an era that was diminishing. On the other hand it seemed that in the
                            problem of East-West relations where for the purpose of dealing
                            practically with these matters it might be necessary for certain
                            countries who are charged with a special responsibility arising from the
                            recent war to discuss the appropriate means of handling such a difficult
                            question. He felt that in the matter of the liberation of Austria and
                            the unification of Germany that there was a primary responsibility on
                            Germany and Austria themselves and on the four occupying powers. He did
                            not by any means believe that this meant that the opinion of others
                            would be ignored. It had been a practice, at least insofar as the
                            Western occupying powers were concerned to consult and exchange views
                            with the <pb facs="0286" n="248" xml:id="pg_248"/>
                            <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> Council in handling these
                            particular problems and he believed that the notes which were exchanged
                            in the past were usually presented in advance to the Permanent Council.
                            He felt that this practice should be continued and developed and that
                            they might take advantage of the next ministerial meeting to have oral
                            discussions on this subject.</p>
                        <p>Insofar as the other question was concerned, that of disarmament in
                            Europe, this was of obvious interest to all <gloss target="#t_NATO1">NATO</gloss> powers. He did not think it would be practical to deal
                            with all aspects of this question through the United Nations of which
                            Italy was not a member. In addition to this there were other aspects of
                            disarmament such as those in the atomic field which might be of special
                            interest to another group of states. Every one of these problems
                            presented, in a manner of speaking, special sub-problems as to which
                            nations were directly concerned and should participate in discussion on
                            them. He did not feel it would be easy to make a generalization. The
                            Soviets were continually trying to bring the Chinese Communist regime in
                            on all discussions and we might have to face a situation where their
                            efforts to enlarge the area of discussion and the participants of such
                            discussions would be unacceptable to us. The Prime Minister’s question
                            had posed a difficult problem. He would like to add that at Moscow in
                            1947 they had spent many fruitless hours on trying to determine who
                            should attend the German peace conference. This was never settled. Some
                            of the South American countries felt they should participate because
                            they had declared war on Germany. To sum up, he felt that every aspect
                            should be weighed separately to see how the problem could best be dealt
                            with and which states should participate.</p>
                        <p>The Secretary wanted to make quite clear at this phase that we recognized
                            the growing interest of Italy in these problems and that Italy by her
                            conduct had qualified herself for this type of participation. The
                            Secretary then indicated that it would be necessary to leave in order to
                            reach the White House in time for the meeting with the President. The
                            Prime Minister said he hoped he would have occasion to discuss these
                            matters at the same level again before his departure as they were rather
                            important to Italy.</p>
                    </div>
                    </body></text></TEI>