<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-05-07T17:00:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-05-07T17:00:00-05:00" n="10" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d10">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.51/142</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The <gloss type="from">Secretary of
                                        State</gloss> to the Ambassador in Russia</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FDR1" type="to"><hi rend="italic">Francis</hi></persName>)</head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-05-07T17:00:00-05:00"><hi rend="italic">May 7,
                                            1917, 5 p.m.</hi></date></dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1386. Your 1239, May 1, 8 p.m. Secretary of the Treasury replies to
                                your telegram May 1 as follows:</p>
                            <p>The act of Congress authorizes the Secretary of the Treasury to lend
                                money to foreign governments making war on Germany on such terms and
                                conditions as he thinks necessary or desirable, but he must take
                                back an obligation from the foreign government to <pb facs="0058" n="8" xml:id="pg_8"/> which the loan is made, bearing 3½ per
                                cent interest and having a maturity to be agreed upon. In order to
                                negotiate such a loan it is necessary for some representative of the
                                Russian Government in the United States to be empowered by the
                                Russian Government to sign the necessary agreement or agreements
                                containing the terms and conditions under which the loan is made,
                                and also to execute the note or obligation of the Russian Government
                                to the United States. After the loan is thus made, the
                                representative of the Russian Government in the United States should
                                have power to open an account with the Treasurer of the United
                                States, or with banks in the United States designated by the
                                Secretary of the Treasury, and to draw checks against such account
                                in order that payments may be made from time to time for supplies
                                purchased in the United States.</p>
                            <p>The loan transaction will be a direct one between the United States
                                Government and the Russian Government, but no progress can be made
                                until the Russian Government fully empowers its representative in
                                the United States to act for and bind it. Will such power be
                                conferred and upon whom? The loan so made by the United States
                                Government will contain a provision that no supplies are to be
                                purchased in the United States without the approval of a
                                representative of the Treasury Department. This will insure the
                                purchase of supplies in the United States upon the most reasonable
                                terms and will facilitate prompt deliveries. This is as much to the
                                interest of the Russian Government as to the American Government,
                                because there is not an unlimited supply of credit in the United
                                States and the demands of all the Allied Governments are great. Our
                                credit resources must, therefore, be used to the best advantage.
                                After the loan is made the Russian representative in the United
                                States designated by the Russian Government to make purchases can
                                negotiate immediately through the Treasury Department for the
                                purchase of railroad cars and locomotives as desired by the Russian
                                Government, and everything will be done by this Government to
                                facilitate such purchases and deliveries. Please make this clear and
                                cable reply quickly as possible.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><persName corresp="#p_LR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Lansing</hi></persName></signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>