<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-09-03T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-09-03T00:00:00-05:00" n="196" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d196">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/2619½</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The British Chargé</hi> (<persName type="from"><hi rend="italic">Hohler</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#left">No. 973</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <p rend="center"><hi rend="smallcaps">Memorandum</hi></p>
                            <p>With reference to the communication made to Mr. <persName corresp="#p_PF1">Polk</persName> by His Majesty’s Ambassador on
                                July 26 and to the “memorandum of conversation” handed to His
                                Majesty’s Chargé d’Affaires by Mr. <persName>Phillips</persName> on
                                August 17 on the subject of the United States mission to
                                    Siberia,<note n="1" xml:id="d196fn1"><hi rend="italic">Ante</hi>, <ref target="#pg_134">pp. 134</ref> and <ref target="#pg_136">136</ref>.</note> His Majesty’s Chargé
                                d’Affaires has the honour to inform the Secretary of State, by
                                direction of His Majesty’s Government, that Mr. <persName>Harold
                                    Porter</persName>, Acting Consul at Harbin, has now been
                                appointed British Commercial Commissioner at Vladivostok, Mr.
                                    <persName>Sly</persName> now being unable to accept the
                                position. Mr. <persName>Porter</persName> will proceed to
                                Vladivostok at once.</p>
                            <p>No satisfactory agreement was come to out of the negotiations with
                                the representatives of merchants trading in the Far East which was
                                mentioned in Lord <persName corresp="#p_RE1">Reading</persName>’s
                                communication, but His Majesty’s Government has made arrangements
                                with Mr. <persName>Leslie</persName> Urquhart for the establishment
                                by him of a business organization which shall act as agent of His
                                Majesty’s Government and which shall be under the control and
                                supervision of the Board of Trade in the United Kingdom and of the
                                commercial commissioner in Siberia in the operations connected with
                                the supply of goods which was contemplated.</p>
                            <p>The name of the organization is The Siberian Supply Co. It will not
                                trade on private account but will act purely as the agent of His
                                Majesty’s Government by whom it will be financed and it will be <pb facs="0192" n="142" xml:id="pg_142"/> instructed to conform with
                                any directions given by His Majesty’s Commercial Commissioner on
                                behalf of the inter-Allied commission which it is hoped to establish
                                at Vladivostok as to the methods and terms of the distribution of
                                supplies. All receipts, expenditure, etc., will be accounted for to
                                His Majesty’s Government by the organization who will be remunerated
                                for its services by a commission of one half per cent on the
                                turnover, and by the reimbursement of out-of-pocket expenses.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <dateline rendition="#left">
                                    <placeName>
                                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                                    </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-09-03"><hi rend="italic">September 3, 1918</hi></date>. <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received September 5.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>