<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1917-08-21T10:29:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1917-08-21T10:29:00-05:00" n="29" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d29">
                            <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.51/191</note>
                            <head><hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Russia</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_FDR1" type="from"><hi rend="italic">Francis</hi></persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of State</gloss></hi></head>
                            <opener>
                                <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                            </opener>
                            <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName><hi rend="smallcaps">Petrograd</hi></placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1917-08-21T19:00:00+03:31"><hi rend="italic">August
                                            21, 1917, 7 p.m.</hi></date>
                                    <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received August 24, 3.15
                                    a.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                            </opener>
                            <p>1645. Am still without reply to several cables concerning Russian
                                credits which I understand limited to $100,000,000 and special
                                credit $75,000,000. Former about consumed. On latter $10,000,000
                                paid National City [Bank] and additional $10,000,000 requested by
                                Russia indorsed by myself. No [report] concerning additional
                                $60,000,000 for August maturities.</p>
                            <p>Have endeavored since arriving Petrograd April, last year, to
                                encourage and facilitate Russian exports, which very potent in
                                preserving exchange value ruble. Imperial Government denied all my
                                requests for export of skins but have secured consent Provisional
                                Government for export 5,000 tons thereof in exchange for sole
                                leather and shoes. Russian Government proposed requisition said
                                skins and to purchase leather and shoes at prices already agreed
                                upon but it is necessary to ship shoes, leather promptly before
                                navigation closes and before skins can be shipped, consequently shoe
                                leather manufacturers compelled to credit Russian Government until
                                arrival of and disposition of skins for about $5,000,000 which
                                vendors of shoes, leather decline to do. Hutchins, vice president,
                                Bank of Commerce, New York, here, has devoted much time and thought
                                to the transaction, sending cables amounting to over Rs. 2,000. His
                                bank willing to make advance for shoes, leather, charging 6 per
                                cent, and arrange for purchase same and sale of skins for Government
                                at minimum prices, charging 2½ per cent commission, no other profit.
                                Government desirous to consummate transaction. Leather, shoes
                                greatly needed. Commerce however desirous that cost shoes, leather
                                    <pb facs="0072" n="22" xml:id="pg_22"/> be guaranteed by our
                                Government until arrival of in America where demand for skins great.
                                Tonnage to America readily obtainable, tonnage from America arranged
                                by Minister Supplies from allotment made his Department. Can you
                                make such guaranty? <persName>Preston</persName> of Keith Co. also
                                been attempting this exchange. Possible <persName>Preston</persName>
                                and <persName>Hutchins</persName> would work jointly. Think greatly
                                desirable because moral effect [$]5,000,000 exports more helpful in
                                sustaining ruble exchange than [$]25,000,000 applied thereto. I
                                recommend because think moral effect very beneficial and important.
                                We should do everything to encourage and strengthen situation here.
                                Suggest you confer with Department of Commerce whose commercial
                                attaché familiar with situation.</p>
                            <closer>
                                <signed><persName corresp="#p_FDR1"><hi rend="smallcaps">Francis</hi></persName></signed>
                            </closer>
                        </div>
                        </body></text></TEI>