<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Ambassador in Japan ( (Morris) ) to the Secretary of State</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Russiav03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d457</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">457</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-12-31T05:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-12-31T05:00:00-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="receE6vUiHBgFwfTW" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">Tariffs</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recABbz1g69I03cEK" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh98006777"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Grant</term>
                    <term ref="rec7ZKvPwsbdUPpj2" type="topic" category="bilateral-relations"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85061212"
                        lcsh-match="exact">History</term>
                    <term ref="recQFXxgVrAcalIps" type="topic" category="uncategorized"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85031319"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Amendments</term>
                    <term ref="rec3ed041a56810f4c" type="topic" category="warfare" subcategory="general" subject="war">War</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-12-31T05:00:00-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-12-31T05:00:00-05:00" n="457"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d457">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.77/597</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Ambassador in Japan</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_MRS1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Morris</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the <gloss type="to">Secretary of
                            State</gloss>
                    </hi>
                </head>
                <opener>
                    <seg rendition="#center">[Telegram]</seg>
                </opener>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Tokyo</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-12-31T19:00:00+09:00">
                            <hi rend="italic">December 31, 1918, 7 p.m.</hi>
                        </date>
                        <lb/> [<hi rend="italic">Received January 1, 1919, 7.30
                        p.m.</hi>]</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>In reference to the recent railway agreement, I have received from <persName
                        corresp="#p_SJF1">Stevens</persName> the following telegrams: <quote
                        rend="blockquote">
                        <p>December 29, 7 p.m. Your cable December 27, 11 [10] p.m. I am giving
                            amended plan consideration; would like further information. Have you
                            agreement, secret or otherwise, [as to] who would be president technical
                            board? … Without committing myself would say section 3, president’s
                            powers, should include economic as well as technical operation. Section
                            3 says president may issue instructions Russian officials but gives him
                            no power whatever to enforce such instructions. He should at least have
                            power dismissal Russian officials and all his powers should be entirely
                            independent of technical board. He should have power to distribute his
                            experts not only at important stations but wherever he deems
                            necessary.</p>
                        <p>Section 1 says technical board shall be under control of the Allied
                            committee. This would take all control of operation away from technical
                            board or its president and would neutralize all succeeding paragraphs. I
                            could not agree to this. I see no reason why, if good faith is intended,
                            matter can not be put in plain takers [terms]. I think your [supposition
                            wrong?] that president is given full power by the wording of the
                            proposed agreement. I fail to see that president is independent in the
                            last analysis of technical board.</p>
                        <p>Of course there can be no objection to the 5th section. If an agreement
                            can be reached, absolutely necessary that War Department distributes
                            American troops sufficient numbers along the line as far as Japanese are
                            quartered. I would like to hear from you as to above points. I can not
                            see the way to express views to the Department without further
                            consideration.</p>
                        <p>December 30, 2 p.m. Further. Your [my] cable December 29, 7 p.m. (1)
                            Technical board, in all matters operation and railway economics, must be
                            independent of Allied committee; (2) president technical board must not
                            be under control of board in matters of operation; he must be free to
                            exercise his judgment in such matters, regardless of views of the
                            majority of board; (3) president must have absolute power to enforce and
                            make effective his orders to any and all Russian railway officials; (4)
                            protection of railway by Allied troops must mean that American soldiers
                            shall be distributed in sufficient numbers as far west as are Japanese
                            soldiers.</p>
                        <p>Above in addition and elaboration of my cable yesterday. Careful study of
                            the amended proposition forces me to the conclusion <pb facs="0354"
                                n="304" xml:id="pg_304"/> that it can be construed as making no
                            essential change from the original. I agree with you that we should
                            effect change of policy but feel that ambiguous wording of plan should
                            be eliminated. Why not have takers [terms] put in language that can not
                            be mistaken?</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>I have replied to-day as follows: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>December 31, 7 p.m. Your telegram of December 29, 7 p.m. Answering your
                            questions and comments: <list>
                                <label>1.</label>
                                <item>I have a definite understanding with the Japanese Foreign
                                    Office that if the plan now submitted is approved, you are to be
                                    named as president, and this understanding will be confirmed in
                                    writing to our Government before formal assent is given.</item>
                                <label>2.</label>
                                <item>Personally I think it would be a mistake to require authority
                                    in economic questions such as freight and passenger tariffs.
                                    Such questions, it seems to me, should be determined by the
                                    technical board subject to the control of the inter-Allied
                                    committee as provided in the agreement. Otherwise there would be
                                    continued criticism and suspicion both by Russians and by
                                    competing nationalities, particularly if trade conditions in
                                    Siberia improve.</item>
                                <label>3.</label>
                                <item>I submit that you have not given to sections 2 and 3 (which
                                    should be read together) the full import of their wording.
                                    Delegating of power to the president is contained in the words,
                                    “To whom shall be intrusted the technical operation of the
                                    railways.” That is a grant so broad that to enumerate any
                                    specific powers would only limit rather than enlarge it. As it
                                    stands it is only limited by the requirement in section 2 that
                                    “at the head of each railway shall remain a Russian manager or
                                    director,” not the present managers or directors necessarily but
                                    Russian managers or directors, and to them you are authorized to
                                    issue instructions and if anyone should not obey I assume you
                                    would discharge him and appoint some other Russian. One specific
                                    power is given, which by its very nature does enlarge the
                                    general power, and that is the authority to employ other
                                    nationalities as assistants, experts, and inspectors. This is a
                                    power specified because it would not be of necessity implied
                                    with their general power to operate Russian railways.</item>
                                <label/>
                                <item>As to the phrase “More important stations,” you would be the
                                    judge.</item>
                                <label>4.</label>
                                <item>You are right that the administrative acts of the technical
                                    board are subject to the control, of the inter-Allied committee,
                                    and one of these administrative acts is to elect a president, to
                                    whom, by the terms of the agreement itself, is intrusted the
                                    technical operation of the railways. While the technical board,
                                    with the approval of the inter-Allied committee, elects the
                                    president and thus fulfills its first purpose of administrating
                                    the technical management on many railways, neither it nor the
                                    Allied committee can interfere with or modify the authority of
                                    the president, so elected because the authority was conferred
                                    directly by the agreement of the associated nations and not by
                                    the action of the committee or the board. I can not therefore
                                    agree with your conclusion that the authority of the president
                                    could be neutralized. After electing the president, the
                                    inter-Allied committee and the technical committee have no
                                    further control over technical operation and are limited to
                                    economic questions.</item>
                                <pb facs="0355" n="305" xml:id="pg_305"/>
                                <label>5.</label>
                                <item>I agree with you that the wording could be more simple and
                                    direct, but the issues involved were not simple and the methods
                                    of meeting them have not always been direct. You know the
                                    history of this agreement from your first outline and <persName
                                        corresp="#p_HGL1">Horvat</persName>’s draft and <persName
                                        corresp="#p_ULA1">Ustrugov</persName>’s<note n="1"
                                        xml:id="d457fn1">Assistant Minister of Ways of Communication
                                        under <persName corresp="#p_KAF1">Kerensky</persName>; later
                                        Minister of Ways of Communication in the successive Siberian
                                        governments.</note> objections and amendments to the present
                                    time and you know how much sensitiveness on our [their?] side
                                    had to be overcome. In my judgment this agreement proves that
                                    they have in large measure been overcome and while I appreciate
                                    the practical difficulties ahead, I have absolute confidence
                                    with their [in our?] ability to solve them with the authority
                                    that this agreement gives us.</item>
                            </list>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Many rumors are in circulation at the close of recent developments in Omsk. I
                    received the following from <persName corresp="#p_SJF1">Stevens</persName> this
                    morning: <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <p>December 30, 3 p.m. Have report from Omsk, which so far can not verify as
                            telegraphic communication cut off, that <persName corresp="#p_KAV1"
                                >Kolchak</persName> killed and <persName corresp="#p_MG1">Grand Duke
                                Michael</persName> now the head of the government. If it is true,
                            undoubtedly effort to restore monarchy. I have not advised
                            Department.</p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>… correspondent of the …, arrived here on way home. Has been through Siberia as
                    far as Ural Mountains and had unusual opportunities to observe conditions. His
                    knowledge of Russian language greatly aided him in many conferences with leading
                    men. He was in Omsk both before and after the proclamation of <persName
                        corresp="#p_KAV1">Kolchak</persName>’s dictatorship. He reports that the
                        <persName corresp="#p_KAV1">Kolchak</persName> movement was engineered by
                    former officials of old regime and in the interest of a monarchy; that it has
                    been most unfavorably received in those parts of Siberia through which he passed
                    and that he is convinced that <persName corresp="#p_KMF1">General
                        Knox</persName> was involved in it. It is most unfortunate that <persName
                        corresp="#p_KMF1">General Knox</persName> continues to interfere in these
                    internal controversies. He seems to have been a disturbing factor from the day
                    of his arrival. I fear that his activities may be interpreted by many Russians
                    as expressing the views of the Associated Governments.</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_MRS1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Morris</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
