<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Russian Ambassador ( (Bakhmeteff) ) to the Assistant Secretary of State (
                    (Phillips))</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl type="frus-volume-id">frus1918Russiav03</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-id">d82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-document-number">82</bibl>
                <bibl type="frus-div-subtype">historical-document</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <settingDesc>
                <setting>
                    <date notBefore="1918-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" notAfter="1918-08-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                    />
                </setting>
            </settingDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="frus-subject-taxonomy">
                    <term ref="recZIIkaX5BdN1W86" type="topic" category="information-programs"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2017003397"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Media</term>
                    <term ref="recWi6s40GIVeUYOI" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2011002449"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Foreign currency</term>
                    <term ref="recfSAitjFhAAVL67" type="topic" category="global-issues"
                        subcategory="population-demographics"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00006969"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Population</term>
                    <term ref="recVanxJ0yM3HzUcM" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85037333"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Devaluation</term>
                    <term ref="recIL1ArZYwpyyv4I" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007503"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Production</term>
                    <term ref="rec4cw0OuBxVfLnY3" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85050531"
                        lcsh-match="bad_close">Import</term>
                    <term ref="recvwnsJn9wKOKl53" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85000411"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Commercial</term>
                    <term ref="recPQgfVTW98s8cOn" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85033856"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Credit</term>
                    <term ref="recHoFOsQcM4e5M4k" type="compound-subject"
                        category="arms-control-and-disarmament" subcategory="nuclear-weapons"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85112143"
                        lcsh-match="good_close">Reduction</term>
                    <term ref="recsoROKqAphh6ocP" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2001008994"
                        lcsh-match="exact">Transportation</term>
                    <term ref="recVH8jxIJVyDqTxX" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="general"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh00007584"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Reform</term>
                    <term ref="recfrEx67p5WM8nD5" type="topic" category="foreign-economic-policy"
                        subcategory="financial-and-monetary-policy"
                        lcsh-uri="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85008784"
                        lcsh-match="lcsh_rejected">Assets</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1918-08-21T23:59:59-05:00"
                frus:doc-dateTime-min="1918-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="82"
                subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d82">
                <note rend="inline" type="source">File No. 861.00/2543</note>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Russian Ambassador</hi> (<persName corresp="#p_BBA1"
                        type="from">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bakhmeteff</hi>
                    </persName>) <hi rend="italic">to the Assistant Secretary of State</hi>
                        (<persName type="to">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phillips</hi>
                    </persName>)</head>
                <opener>
                    <dateline rendition="#right">
                        <placeName>
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">Washington</hi>
                        </placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1918-08-21">
                            <hi rend="italic">August 21, 1918</hi>
                        </date>.</dateline>
                </opener>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">My Dear Mr. <persName>Phillips</persName>
                    </hi>: Enclosed two copies of the memorandum on questions of currency to be used
                    in connection with the proposed assistance to Russia. I will appreciate if you
                    will forward one of these copies to the Secretary of Treasury.</p>
                <p>Believe me [etc.]</p>
                <closer>
                    <signed>
                        <persName corresp="#p_BBA1">
                            <hi rend="smallcaps">B. Bakhmeteff</hi>
                        </persName>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
                <frus:attachment>
                    <opener>
                        <seg rendition="#center">[Enclosure]</seg>
                    </opener>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="italic">Memorandum on Currency in Russia</hi>
                    </head>
                    <p>One of the most important problems, which presents itself in connection with
                        the recent decisions of the United States to render active assistance to
                        Russia, is that of currency to be used. It is, first of all, the question of
                        the kind of money with which the American-Allied troops will make payments
                        in Russia. Further, and far more important, is the question of currency to
                        be <pb facs="0110" n="60" xml:id="pg_60"/> employed in connection with the
                        manifold transactions arising from the proposed economic assistance to
                        Russia. Thus, the problem of deciding upon the proper exchange media is a
                        vital practical necessity.</p>
                    <p>In determining the line of action, following considerations must be taken
                        into account: <list>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>)</label>
                            <item>No procedure should be adopted which would eventually cause
                                embarrassment to the future national government of Russia in the
                                coming task of consolidating and stabilizing the monetary system of
                                the country.</item>
                            <label>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>)</label>
                            <item>All possibilities of benefiting the Germans should be avoided,
                                especially bearing in mind Germany’s extensive operations with the
                                Russian ruble.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The three following ways of procedure present themselves: <list>
                            <label>1.</label>
                            <item>Using present Russian currency;</item>
                            <label>2.</label>
                            <item>Foreign currency (United States dollars or Japanese yens);</item>
                            <label>3.</label>
                            <item>Issuing special bank notes (certificates).</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <list>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">1.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Using present Russian currency</hi>.—Simple as it
                            appears, this method must be emphatically rejected. The unrestricted
                            issuance of paper money during the last year has rendered the ruble
                            entirely unstable and deprived of any character of standard value to be
                            used in orderly exchange. Due to the lack of confidence as to the
                            purchasing power of the present paper money, the Allied troops would be
                            confronted with the greatest difficulty when endeavoring to procure
                            commodities by means of notes, considered by the population as
                            practically valueless. Violent speculation would necessarily arise and
                            besides it is inconceivable for the Allies to use a medium of exchange,
                            the very source of which in fact lies in the sphere of German control.
                            The Allies could not contribute to strengthen and consolidate rubles now
                            in the possession of the enemy and could not indulge in offering the
                            Germans further opportunities.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">2.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Foreign currency</hi>,—To introduce any foreign
                            currency would be embarrassing at present on account of the illiteracy
                            of the population and its unfamiliarity with foreign specie and
                            denominations. In the future, such course would be bound to cause
                            difficulties to the Government of Russia. Besides consolidating the
                            value of the old paper ruble relatively to a new national unit, the
                            future government in this case would have to extract from circulation
                            certain foreign specie, which, at that time, might become a familiar
                            instrument of purchase and exchange and the value of which besides is
                            totally independent and is beyond authority on the part of any
                            institutions in Russia. Further, under present chaotic conditions,
                            foreign specie of general value introduced into the country may be
                            diverted into German channels.</item>
                        <label>
                            <hi rend="italic">3.</hi>
                        </label>
                        <item>
                            <hi rend="italic">Issuing special certificates.</hi>—Under such
                            circumstances it appears that special certificates should be issued to
                            be used in connection with Allied action in Russia. If issued in ruble
                            values and in proper denominations, such certificates would have the
                            advantage of being entirely familiar to the population. Their relative
                            value and purchasing power can easily be rendered stable. Further, most
                            simple measures would practically exclude any possibilities of
                            benefiting German activities.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">General Considerations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Certain considerations of general character are appropriate, which would
                        render clear the nature and the purpose of the proposed financial
                        enterprise.</p>
                    <p>It is to be conceived in the first place that no financial problems of
                        general character may be set as the aim of the proposed action. Questions
                        such as that of devaluation of the present paper currency, its extraction
                        from circulation <pb facs="0111" n="61" xml:id="pg_61"/> and other problems
                        of stabilization of existing ruble currency can be legally solved only by a
                        future national government of Russia, whose authority is well established
                        and recognized and which is entirely in control both of the means of issuing
                        currency as of its circulation and foreign exchange.</p>
                    <p>The purpose of introducing a new exchange medium is entirely practical, the
                        aim being to establish a standard of exchange with a stable purchasing power
                        which would enable economic assistance on the part of the Allies and render
                        possible the resumption of normal economic activities.</p>
                    <p>In the eyes of the population the value of the new currency will be connected
                        with the possibility of purchasing goods imported by the Allies, it being
                        this real purchasing power which psychologically will attribute validity to
                        the new notes.</p>
                    <p>In connection with this the amount of new notes to be issued is to be
                        determined exclusively with regard to the practical needs of economic
                        activities, developing in connection with Allied economic assistance and
                        corresponding to the actual demand of exchange media.</p>
                    <p>In defining the general outline of the proposed financial institution and in
                        considering the nature of the measures contemplated, it is supposed that the
                        economic assistance brought into Russia by the United States and the Allies
                        will be directed by a certain governing body, which will regulate and
                        coordinate the activities of different institutions and insure unity in
                        policy and action. The proposed financial institution will consequently act
                        under the auspices and direction of this main economic commission and
                        actually constitute its financial department concentrating and effecting all
                        financial transactions connected with the Allied enterprise.</p>
                    <p>It is further understood that, free from selfish aim and acting on strictly
                        business lines, the economic commission will endeavor to extend assistance
                        to the population by giving it an opportunity of purchasing goods on a fair
                        cost basis and besides, through extending proper credits and other
                        appropriate measures, will contribute to the restitution of production in
                        Russia. In these activities, the intermediary of such institutions as
                        cooperative societies, Zemstvos, and municipalities will be largely sought,
                        avoiding possibly avenues where profiteering and speculation might be
                        expected.</p>
                    <p>For these purposes, as well as for payments by the Allied troops in Russia,
                        proper stable exchange media have to be provided and a mechanism, whereby
                        this media could be properly utilized by the population, instituted and
                        brought into operation. While in the future it may be expected that the
                        importation of goods will be, to a certain extent, balanced by eventual
                        exports, it should be nevertheless realized that in the initial phase import
                        operations will necessarily dominate. This will necessitate extension of
                        credits to purchasing bodies in Russia as well as to importing corporations,
                        acting under the supervision of the economic commission, in dollars and
                        other foreign currency.</p>
                    <p>The proposed financial institution should be, therefore, established with a
                        capacity of issuing exchange media for use in Siberia and parts of Russia,
                        covered by organized Allied assistance, as well as should be authorized to
                        extend necessary credits for supply operations of all kinds.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Constituency of the Financial Institution</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>An Allied or American bank to operate in Russia should be created through
                        special decree and international agreement, the stock of the bank to be
                        formed mainly through subscription by the Allied Governments or the United
                        States; the balance eventually, but not necessarily, to be subscribed by
                        private <pb facs="0112" n="62" xml:id="pg_62"/> interests, cooperating with
                        the economic commission; the board to be nominated by the participating
                        governments and supplemented eventually by representatives of private
                        stockholders.</p>
                    <p>The bank to have two main departments: an issue department and a commercial
                        department.</p>
                    <p>The issue department to be authorized to issue bank notes (certificates),
                        secured by a respective part of the capital stock held in trust by the
                        participating governments. Besides issuing bank notes directly against
                        stock, the issue department should be allowed to issue supplementary media
                        against government notes, bank acceptances, properly secured obligations of
                        institutions and other commercial paper of undisputable value.</p>
                    <p>The commercial department will operate with the part of the capital stock in
                        foreign values, assigned to such department. It will further use for
                        operations the bank notes issued by the issue department. The commercial
                        department will establish the necessary credit in foreign currency or in
                        bank notes to different institutions and organizations in Russia as well as
                        to importing concerns. It is through the commercial department that the
                        Allied Governments could obtain necessary moneys for the current expenses of
                        their contingents in Russia against notes or similar documents.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nature of Bank Notes</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">their status in regard to interior circulation and to
                            foreign exchange</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The bank notes should be issued in rubles, adopting the regular Russian
                        denominations. The value of the bank notes should be determined by
                        ascertaining their equivalent with foreign currency. In adopting the
                        exchange equivalent it appears appropriate to accept as the relative value
                        of the ruble its former original pre-war valuation, thus establishing the
                        value of the new ruble notes on the basis of the original standard.</p>
                    <p>The new bank notes could in no case be regarded as legal tender. To issue and
                        enforce lawful money is the privilege and authority of a national government
                        only. The bank notes should be considered as certificates, issued for a
                        specific purpose and used in connection with certain economic transactions,
                        arising from the fact of Allied assistance. The nature of the bank note will
                        consequently be that of a certificate to be used for the purchase of goods
                        imported through Allied channels as well as for all transactions with Allied
                        institutions in Russia. The inscription on the face of the notes could
                        tentatively be of following character: <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <p>The __________ Bank accepts these ruble notes for all payments to the
                                Bank and to all institutions connected with it. The value of this
                                note is secured by deposits in trust with Governments of __________.
                                In exchange this note will be equivalent to __________ in the
                                currency of __________.</p>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although the value of the new ruble note will be thus established in
                        equivalence to foreign currency, this would not mean that free and
                        unrestricted exchange to foreign values would be effected. On the contrary,
                        the necessity of preventing use of these bank notes by German affiliations
                        would demand excluding entirely these bank notes from free exchange in
                        foreign markets and would oblige limiting of such operations to the
                        institutions of the bank only. Furthermore, following the actual practice of
                        Allied countries such exchange would be subject to regulations which would
                        permit the purchase of foreign currency only after proper consideration of
                        each particular case.</p>
                    <pb facs="0113" n="63" xml:id="pg_63"/>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">relation to actual russian currency</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>As heretofore stated the new bank notes should be issued without prejudice to
                        the present currency of Russia. Theoretically, the new bank notes, being
                        issued for a certain specific purpose, are not to interfere with the
                        circulation and use of the present currency. No regular exchange of the new
                        bank notes with the present ruble should be established and no fixed
                        exchange equivalent adopted. As a matter of general policy the reduction of
                        transactions with the present actual ruble to the lowest possible minimum is
                        suggested.</p>
                    <p>However, transactions of this kind can not be entirely avoided. In many cases
                        peasants and other purchasers of imported commodities, often cities,
                        Zemstvos, and Cooperatives, will possess paper rubles as an asset which they
                        may offer as the only security in the initial phase of their transactions
                        with Allied institutions. In such cases, rubles might be accepted as
                        security for credits granted, regarding them strictly as collateral without
                        specifying their actual value and leaving the final settlement to a later
                        epoch, when the future national government would consolidate the currency
                        and determine the relative value of the present ruble paper.</p>
                    <p>It should, however, be anticipated that the new bank notes, although not
                        representing a legal tender of general character, will certainly be favored
                        by the population due to their actual purchasing power and will assume,
                        after a certain period, the character of a <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi>
                        generally recognized exchange media. It is further to be expected that such
                        process may extend beyond the sphere of individual intercourse and that
                        certain municipalities and Zemstvos, besides railways, banks, etc., might,
                        on their own behalf, recognize the bank notes as tender to be accepted in
                        transactions within their sphere of action.</p>
                    <p>In this case the new bank notes would, be eventually accepted, parallel to
                        present currency, in payment of taxes, transportation fees, postal telegraph
                        service, etc. However, such procedure would be adopted and decreed by the
                        local governments and institutions themselves and certain parallel rates,
                        announced from time to time, should be regarded more as a comparative price
                        list in different currency.</p>
                    <p rend="center">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">relation to the future national government of
                            russia</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Such recognition on the part of the population of the new exchange media as
                        tender of general character should not be considered with disfavor. To a
                        certain extent this would facilitate the task of the future national
                        government in the monetary reform. At the moment when the value of the
                        inflated revolutionary ruble will have to be definitely established with
                        regard to the new consolidated national unit, bank notes of the Allied bank,
                        then in circulation, with their firm equivalent in foreign exchange will
                        happily constitute a well-established standard.</p>
                    <p>It would be only necessary for the future government, through proper
                        agreement with the Allies, to assume control of the Allied bank. Such
                        privilege for the future Russian Government to take possession of bank with
                        all its assets and liabilities should be properly stipulated in the
                        constituent charter. The charter should further enable the Russian
                        Government to determine a certain term, during which the bank notes could be
                        recalled to be exchanged for new consolidated national currency or redeemed
                        in foreign exchange at face value. The guaranty for such redemption would be
                        constituted by the stock of the bank.</p>
                    <pb facs="0114" n="64" xml:id="pg_64"/>
                    <p>This provision which would enter into effect at an epoch when the process of
                        national consolidation of Russia has been sufficiently advanced, would serve
                        as a link between the temporary conditions, created by Allied action, and
                        the future financial system established and consolidated by national
                        effort.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">August 1918.</hi>
                    </p>
                </frus:attachment>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
