<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-01-08T18:52:00-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-01-08T18:52:00-05:00" n="127" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d127">
                    <head>127. Telegram From the Department of State to the Embassy in the Soviet
                            Union<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d127fn1">Source: Department of
                            State, Central Foreign Policy File, N820001–0208. Secret; Immediate;
                                <gloss target="#t_Nodis_1">Nodis</gloss>. Sent Immediate for
                            information to Warsaw and to the U.S. Interests Section in Havana.
                            Drafted by <persName corresp="#p_VA_1">Vershbow</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_NL_1">Napper</persName>, and Glassman; cleared by
                                <persName corresp="#p_SWJ_1">Stoessel</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SJD_1">Scanlan</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ELS_1">Eagleburger</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_SS_1">Sestanovich</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_AJ_1">Azrael</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_ETO_1">Enders</persName>,
                                <persName corresp="#p_VNA_1">Veliotes</persName>, <persName corresp="#p_STW_1">Simons</persName>, and <persName corresp="#p_BLP_1">Bremer</persName>; approved by <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-01-08T23:52:00+00:00">January 8, 1982, 2352Z</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p>5511. Subject: Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_HAA_1">Hartman</persName>’s
                        Luncheon with <persName corresp="#p_KG_3">Korniyenko</persName>. Ref: State
                            004570.<note n="2" xml:id="d127fn2">In telegram 4570 to Moscow, January
                            8, the Department reported that <persName corresp="#p_SWJ_1">Stoessel</persName> called in <persName corresp="#p_DA_2">Dobrynin</persName> on January 7 to deliver a démarche on Soviet
                            jamming of Voice of America broadcasts in Polish. (Department of State,
                            Central Foreign Policy File, D820088–0360)</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>1. (S—Entire text).</p>
                    <p>2. During upcoming luncheon with <persName corresp="#p_KG_3">Korniyenko</persName>, Ambassador should discuss Poland, reiterating
                        general approach set forth in the President’s statements, his letter to
                            <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName>, and the Secretary’s
                        letter to <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> and double-tracking
                        Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWJ_1">Stoessel</persName>’s protest
                        of Soviet jamming of <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> broadcasts to
                        Poland <gloss target="#t_reftel_1">reftel</gloss>. In order to underline our
                        continuing concern over Soviet support for Cuban interventionism in Latin
                        America and Africa, you should also raise this issue with <persName corresp="#p_KG_3">Korniyenko</persName>. Talking points on both subjects
                        follow.</p>
                    <pb facs="0439" n="408" xml:id="pg_408"/>
                    <p>3. Poland:</p>
                    <p>—I want to reiterate the concerns expressed in the letters of President
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName> and Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> about the situation in Poland.</p>
                    <p>—I could go on at length about the Soviet role in the present repression in
                        that country, but I don’t want to engage in that debate today.</p>
                    <p>—Your country’s influence over events in Poland is well known, and that is
                        why my government has called on you to help bring about an end to martial
                        law and the restoration of internationally recognized rights. This can be
                        the basis for resumption of a process of national reconciliation in
                        Poland.</p>
                    <p>—The U.S. actions announced on December 29<note n="3" xml:id="d127fn3">See
                                <ref target="#d125fn2">footnote 2, Document 125</ref>.</note>
                        represent a measured response to what has transpired thus far, and to
                        President <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s unhelpful reply
                        to President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>’s letter of
                        December 24.<note n="4" xml:id="d127fn4">See attachment, <ref target="#d123">Document 123</ref>, and <ref target="#d122">Document
                            122</ref>.</note> We hope that these are the only steps we will have to
                        take.</p>
                    <p>—As was affirmed in the White House statement of December 29, the U.S.
                        remains committed to a high-level dialogue with your country, and we still
                        hope to be able to make progress on the agenda of regional and arms control
                        issues established by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName>
                        and Foreign Minister <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> in their
                        September meetings.</p>
                    <p>—Your actions with respect to Poland in the coming weeks will be taken by us
                        as an indication of whether your country is sincerely committed to moving
                        the US-Soviet relationship forward.</p>
                    <p>—In this regard, I would like to reiterate what Under Secretary <persName corresp="#p_SWJ_1">Stoessel</persName> told Ambassador <persName corresp="#p_DA_2">Dobrynin</persName> about the jamming of Voice of
                        America broadcasts in Polish which has been taking place in the past several
                        weeks from facilities within the Soviet Union, specifically from Kharkov,
                        Kaliningrad, and a location near Moscow. This activity is totally
                        unacceptable.</p>
                    <p>—Such jamming (for that matter, all jamming) is a flagrant violation of the
                            <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>’s commitments under the Helsinki
                        Final Act, Article 35 of the International Telecommunication Convention, and
                        Article 19 of the U.N. Human Rights Declaration.</p>
                    <p>—<gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss> broadcasts do not subversive [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] activity as has been repeatedly alleged in crude
                        propaganda attacks by the Soviet media. <gloss target="#t_VOA_1">VOA</gloss>
                        carries objective news and information now denied Polish people by their own
                        government-controlled press.</p>
                    <p>—We demand that these illegal jamming activities cease immediately. As we
                        have stated in the past, we reserve the right to take <pb facs="0440" n="409" xml:id="pg_409"/> necessary and appropriate actions to protect
                        our broadcasting interests, should the jamming continue.</p>
                    <p>4. Cuba/Central America:</p>
                    <p>—We have carefully reviewed President <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s October 16 [<hi rend="italic">15</hi>] letter to
                        President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName><note n="5" xml:id="d127fn5">See <ref target="#d93">Document 93</ref>.</note>
                        calling on us to leave Cuba alone and normalize relations with it and
                        asserting that Cuba represents no threat to the vital interests of the
                        United States. We note further that President <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName> made the same points in his December 1 letter to
                        President <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1">Reagan</persName>.<note n="6" xml:id="d127fn6">See <ref target="#d108">Document 108</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>—In response to this and other denials of hostile Cuban activity, we must
                        affirm that Cuba’s actions do represent a threat, not only to the United
                        States, but to the vital interest that all nations have in maintaining peace
                        and reducing tensions. I want—in response to President <persName corresp="#p_BL_1">Brezhnev</persName>’s letters—to outline to you the
                        areas in which Cuba’s actions cause us serious concern. I do this in the
                        context of looking for means to reduce tensions.</p>
                    <p>—Because Cuban activities would collapse without Soviet support, the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> bears a special responsibility for
                        Cuba’s continuing threat to peace. Cuba’s aggressive interventions in Africa
                        and the Caribbean are not acceptable to us. The purpose of any talks with
                        Cuba can only be to end this unacceptable behavior. In that context the U.S.
                        would be ready to address Cuba’s interests. At the same time, U.S.-Soviet
                        relations will continue to be damaged unless Cuba and its friends begin to
                        act responsibly.</p>
                    <p>The following Cuban activities are of primary concern to us:</p>
                    <p>. . continued Cuban troop presence in Angola and Cuban refusal to withdraw
                        troops in parallel with South African withdrawal from Namibia. Given recent
                        forward movement toward an internationally acceptable settlement, attention
                        must focus on this obstacle. The chance to remove it is a real opportunity
                        for statesmanship;</p>
                    <p>. . maintenance of Cuban forces in Ethiopia and South Yemen;</p>
                    <p>. . the build-up of military forces in Cuba capable of projecting power
                        beyond the environs of the island;</p>
                    <p>. . Cuban interference in the internal affairs of El Salvador, Guatemala,
                        Honduras, and Colombia through support of guerrilla groups;</p>
                    <p>. . Cuban dispatch of larger numbers of military and security personnel to
                        Nicaragua, its assistance in the Nicaraguan Armed Forces’ build-up to levels
                        endangering regional security, and its cooperation <pb facs="0441" n="410" xml:id="pg_410"/> with guerrilla groups which use Nicaragua as a
                        headquarters and supply center.</p>
                    <p>—I hope to discuss each in detail in coming weeks. Today I would like to talk
                        in more detail about Nicaragua:</p>
                    <p>. . Of the 5500–6000 Cuban advisors now in Nicaragua, some 1800 are military
                        and security personnel. This stands in sharp contrast to our 35 military
                        instructors in El Salvador.</p>
                    <p>. . The continued flow of arms and ammunition into Nicaragua has facilitated
                        a build-up of Nicaragua’s Armed Forces to regionally unprecedented
                        levels—three times the size of Somoza’s Armed Forces (24,000 active duty
                        personnel, 50,000 reserve forces/militia; southern neighbor Costa Rica has
                        no Armed Forces, Northern neighbor Honduras has 11,000). Realization of
                        plans to have 50,000 active duty personnel and 200,000 reservists/militia
                        would be profoundly destabilizing to the region.</p>
                    <p>. . Nicaraguan Foreign Minister D’Escoto has told Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> that Soviet Combat Aircraft will not
                        be delivered. This is good news. A moratorium on delivery of additional
                        weapons and ammunition in general would be a sign of good faith that there
                        is no intention to disrupt the regional military balance. An understanding
                        not to provide additional heavy offensive weapons would also be useful.</p>
                    <p>. . But this, in itself, is not enough. Other elements of the problem are
                        equally important. At present, the more than 1,500 Cuban military and
                        internal-security advisors in Nicaragua contribute to regional concern over
                        excessive Nicaraguan military expansion, Sandinista persecution of
                        independent elements of the population, and support for foreign guerrillas.
                        The number of these advisors should be immediately reduced to minimal
                        levels.</p>
                    <p>. . A further threat to the region is created by the Salvadoran and other
                        guerrilla groups which maintain their headquarters and communications
                        facilities in and receive their arms from Nicaragua. These foreign guerrilla
                        activities in Nicaragua, which are supported by Cuba and which aim at
                        interfering in the internal affairs of other states, should cease.</p>
                    <p>—Unless the situation in Central America is altered in some of the ways I
                        have suggested, the tension characterizing the region will continue and will
                        build. The prospect of a wider and more serious confrontation is real. It is
                        not a prospect we seek; it is not a prospect we welcome. We wish to see
                        early significant changes in the pattern of activities I have described. I
                        welcome your thoughts.</p>
                    <p>5. Afghanistan: Should <persName corresp="#p_KG_3">Korniyenko</persName>
                        raise subject of Afghanistan, you should underline our concern over recent
                        Soviet troop reinforcements and continued Soviet pressure on Pakistan and
                        indicate that any <pb facs="0442" n="411" xml:id="pg_411"/> Soviet
                        escalation of the Afghanistan conflict will provoke a response. You should
                        not, however, be drawn into discussion of <persName corresp="#p_DA_2">Dobrynin</persName>’s October 31 demarche to the Secretary<note n="7" xml:id="d127fn7">See <ref target="#d109">Document 109</ref>.</note> or
                        the reference in the President’s letter of November 18 [<hi rend="italic">17</hi>]<note n="8" xml:id="d127fn8">See the attachment to Tab A, <ref target="#d103">Document 103</ref>.</note> to our intention to
                        discuss Afghanistan further with the Soviets. If pressed by <persName corresp="#p_KG_3">Korniyenko</persName>, you should reply that
                        Afghanistan will undoubtedly be discussed by Secretary <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1">Haig</persName> and <persName corresp="#p_GA_1">Gromyko</persName> at Geneva.</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_HAM_1"><hi rend="strong">Haig</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>