<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:frus="http://history.state.gov/frus/ns/1.0"><text><body><div frus:doc-dateTime-max="1982-08-21T23:59:59-05:00" frus:doc-dateTime-min="1982-08-21T00:00:00-05:00" n="204" subtype="historical-document" type="document" xml:id="d204">
                    <head>204. National Security Study Directive 11–82<note n="1" type="source" xml:id="d204fn1">Source: Reagan Library, Executive Secretariat, <gloss target="#t_NSC_1">NSC</gloss>: National Security Study Directives
                                (<gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss>): Records, 1981–1987, <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> 11–82. Secret.</note>
                    </head>
                    <opener>
                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                            <placeName>Washington</placeName>, <date calendar="gregorian" when="1982-08-21">August 21, 1982</date>
                        </dateline>
                    </opener>
                    <p rend="center">U.S. POLICY TOWARD THE SOVIET UNION</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Introduction</p>
                    <p>A Review will be conducted of U.S. Policy Toward the Soviet Union. This
                        National Security Study Directive establishes the Terms of Reference for the
                        Review. (S)</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Objectives of the Review</p>
                    <p>The Review will assess the nature of the Soviet threat to U.S. national
                        security interests in the short and long terms, with emphasis on its
                        non-military aspects, and recommend appropriate U.S. policy responses,
                        by:</p>
                    <p>—Analyzing the determinants of Soviet foreign policy and domestic policies of
                        concern to the U.S. and other outside powers;</p>
                    <p>—Assessing Soviet strengths and weaknesses;</p>
                    <p>—Identifying key elements of likely continuity and change in the Soviet
                        system and Soviet policies; and</p>
                    <p>—Determining the political, economic, military and ideological means at our
                        disposal for achieving favorable changes in Soviet interna<pb facs="0702" n="671" xml:id="pg_671"/>tional behavior, including assessment of the
                        costs and obstacles involved in using them. (S)</p>
                    <p>The Review will proceed on the premise that Soviet international behavior is
                        determined not only by the external environment but also by political,
                        economic, social and ideological features of the Soviet system itself. It
                        will produce a paper for consideration by the National Security Council, and
                        subsequently, for decision by the President. (S)</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Scope of the Review</p>
                    <p>The Review will deal with the following subjects:</p>
                    <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The likelihood of changes in the Soviet system:</hi> to
                        ascertain what realistic expectation one can have of significant changes in
                        the Soviet system and in Soviet international behavior, and in which areas;
                        whether such changes are likely to make the country more or less
                        threatening, and in which areas. The question of non-evolutionary (violent)
                        collapse of the system from within and its implications for U.S. security
                        will also be considered. (S)</p>
                    <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Soviet vulnerabilities and strengths:</hi> the sources
                        of strains and tensions within the Soviet system and the bases for
                        continuity:</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                        <hi rend="roman">A.</hi> Internal</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Economic</hi> (resources and structures by sector,
                        strengths and weaknesses of central planning, other constraints on Soviet
                        economic growth, trends in industrial and agricultural productivity, degree
                        of dependence on foreign trade, the financial outlook, the burden of
                        military expenditures, consumer passivity and dissatisfaction).</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Political</hi> (party, police and society; social malaise
                        and revolutionary consciousness; the self-assertion of the working class;
                        dissident movements among Russians and ethnic minorities; the succession
                        problem).</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Social</hi> (demographic trends; urban and rural society;
                        youth; deviance; the religious factor).</p>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">
                        <hi rend="roman">B.</hi> External</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Imperial challenges:</hi> increasing burdens of projecting
                        a global presence; allies and proxies; strains in Eastern Europe, including
                        economic relations with <gloss target="#t_CEMA_1">CEMA</gloss>.</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Communist movements:</hi> centrifugal tendencies in the
                        international Communist movement; heresies and deviations.</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">International challenges:</hi> the United States, Western
                        Europe, Japan, China, the Third World. (S)</p>
                    <p>3. <hi rend="italic">The Balance of Internal Forces Making for Continuity or
                            Change:</hi> to analyze the Soviet ruling elite in terms of elements
                        favoring the status quo and those favoring change in either a more liberal
                        or a more <pb facs="0703" n="672" xml:id="pg_672"/> conservative direction,
                        and to determine what actions by foreign powers assist each of these
                        competing groups. (S)</p>
                    <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Meeting the Soviet Challenge in the Short and Long
                            Terms:</hi> to define the Soviet challenge to our interests over the
                        next three-five years and ten years, and to ascertain the means at the
                        disposal of the United States, its Allies and other mobilizable forces to
                        influence the evolution of Soviet policies and the Soviet regime in
                        directions favorable to our interests:</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Political</hi> (key regional crises; the role of U.S. and
                        multi-lateral diplomacy in inhibiting Soviet interventionism; political
                        assistance and support to democratic elements in the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss> and other countries; neutralization of
                        Soviet “active measures”); the role of covert action should also be
                        assessed.</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Economic</hi> (altering the mix of available Soviet policy
                        options; technology transfer; energy policy and competition for raw
                        materials; management of East/West trade, including grain sales; sectors of
                        the economy susceptible to influence through Western trade policies; policy
                        on extension of Western credits to the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>).</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Ideological</hi> (the nature and thrust of U.S.
                        informational efforts directed at the Soviet Union; the role of U.S.-Soviet
                        cultural, scientific and other exchanges; scope and intensity of U.S.
                        efforts to counter Soviet disinformation activities; presenting a democratic
                        alternative).</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">High-level dialogue</hi> (advantages and disadvantages in
                        relation to frequency and scope; the historical record of summitry). (S)</p>
                    <p>5. Shaping the Soviet <hi rend="italic">environment:</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">The military balance</hi> (the importance of U.S. and
                        Allied rearmament; the U.S. military strategy most likely to neutralize
                        Soviet strategic and regional objectives; the role of arms control in
                        advancing U.S. national security interests; security assistance to Allies
                        and assistance to anti-Communist forces; regional commitments of U.S.
                        forces). (This section should draw on NSSD–1.)<note n="2" xml:id="d204fn2">NSSD–1 is scheduled for publication in <ref target="frus1981-88v43">
                                <hi rend="italic">Foreign Relations</hi>, 1981–1988, vol. XLIII,
                                National Security Policy, 1981–1984</ref>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Allied cooperation</hi> (how best to secure and support
                        the cooperation of our Allies in pursuit of our policies toward the <gloss target="#t_USSR_1">USSR</gloss>).</p>
                    <p>—<hi rend="italic">Third World cooperation</hi> (actual and potential;
                        bilateral and multilateral; the place of diplomacy). (S)</p>
                    <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Recommended Policies for the U.S.</hi> (how U.S.,
                        Western and Third-World leverage can be applied against Soviet
                        vulnerabilities to induce Soviet restraint in the short and long term).
                        (S)</p>
                    <pb facs="0704" n="673" xml:id="pg_673"/>
                    <p rend="sectiontitleital">Administration</p>
                    <p>Management of the <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> 11–82 Review will be
                        the responsibility of an interagency group that will report its findings in
                        a paper of no more than 25 pages, single-spaced, no later than October 1,
                        1982. The group will be chaired by the Department of State and will include
                        Assistant Secretary-level representation from the Department of Defense, the
                        Central Intelligence Agency, the Joint Chiefs of Staff, the Treasury
                        Department, the Department of Commerce, the International Communication
                        Agency, the Department of Agriculture and the National Security Council
                        staff. (S)</p>
                    <p>All matters relating to this <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> will be
                        classified SECRET. Dissemination of this <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss>, the subsequent study material, and the resulting draft
                            <gloss target="#t_NSSD_1">NSSD</gloss> will be handled on a strict
                        need-to-know basis. (C)</p>
                    <closer>
                        <signed>
                            <persName corresp="#p_RRW_1"><hi rend="strong">Ronald
                                Reagan</hi></persName>
                        </signed>
                    </closer>
                </div>
                </body></text></TEI>